<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<head>-----------------------------------------------------------------------			<lb/>
		</head>


	<head>O R D E R<lb/>
 Bhaskar Raj Pradhan, J.<lb/>
</head>

<p>1.<lb/>
 The applicant seeks to prefer Writ Appeal No. 2 of<lb/>
 2019 challenging orders dated 22.07.2019, 06.09.2019 and<lb/>
 18.10.2019, passed by the learned Single Judge of this<lb/>
 court in W.P.(C) No 60 of 2016 (the writ petition) as well as<lb/>
 an order dated 03.09.2019 passed in Review Petition (C)<lb/>
 No. 1 of 2019 (the review petition). Writ Appeals are<lb/>
 preferred under Rule 148 of the Sikkim High Court<lb/>
 (Practice &amp; Procedure) Rules, 2011 which prescribes a<lb/>
 period of 30 days from the date of the judgment, decree or<lb/>
 final order as the period of limitation for an appeal.<lb/>
 According to the applicant there is a delay of 103 days. The<lb/>
 applicant explains that against the order dated 22.07.2019<lb/>
 they had preferred the review petition before this court<lb/>
 which was rejected on 03.09.2019. Aggrieved thereby, the<lb/>
 applicant preferred Special Leave Petition (C) No.22416-<lb/>
22418/2019 (the Special Leave Petition) against the orders<lb/>
 dated 22.07.2019, 06.09.2019 and 03.09.2019 passed in<lb/>
 the writ petition and the review petition. The Special Leave<lb/>
 Petition was, however, withdrawn by the applicant with<lb/>
 liberty to approach this court granted by the Hon&apos;ble<lb/>
 Supreme Court vide order dated 30.09.2019. The applicant,<lb/>
 thereafter, filed I.A. No. 9 of 2019 in the writ petition before<lb/>
 this court praying for reconsideration of order dated<lb/>
 22.07.2019. This application was rejected by the learned<lb/>
 Single Judge on 18.10.2019. The applicant preferred Writ<lb/>
 Appeal No. 1 of 2019 against the order dated 18.10.2019<lb/>
 passed by the learned Single Judge. Writ Appeal No. 1 of<lb/>
 2019 was, however, withdrawn on 22.11.2019 on the<lb/>
 ground that they had inadvertently not challenged the<lb/>
 order dated 22.07.2019 and 06.09.2019 passed in the writ<lb/>
 petition and the order dated 03.09.2019 passed in the<lb/>
 review petition. The prayer to withdraw with liberty as<lb/>
 prayed for was granted and Writ Appeal No. 1 of 2019 was<lb/>
 disposed as withdrawn with liberty as prayed for by order<lb/>
 dated 22.11.2019.<lb/>
</p>

<p>2.<lb/>
 In the application, besides narrating these facts,<lb/>
 the applicant further explains that the learned counsel for<lb/>
 the applicant started drafting the fresh writ appeal which<lb/>
 took two-three days. The same was submitted to the<lb/>
 learned Senior Counsel for vetting the draft who also took<lb/>
 two-three days to settle it. Certain clarification was sought<lb/>
 for from the applicant and on receipt thereof, the learned<lb/>
 counsel for the applicant redrafted the memo of appeal and<lb/>
 resubmitted the draft to the learned Senior Counsel who<lb/>
 then settled it. The process took few more days. Writ<lb/>
 Appeal No. 2 of 2019 along with the present application for<lb/>
 condonation of delay was finally ready on 02.12.2019 and<lb/>
 filed on the same date.<lb/>
</p>

<p>3.<lb/>
 The applicant contends that although the<lb/>
 applicant ought to have filed a writ appeal against the order<lb/>
 dated 22.07.2019, on a wrong advice, the applicant moved<lb/>
 the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court by preferring Special Leave<lb/>
 Petition and consequently, a delay of 103 days occurred in<lb/>
 moving the writ appeal because of approaching wrong<lb/>
 forums. The applicant pleads that the delay is<lb/>
 unintentional and bona fide and it was for the aforesaid<lb/>
 reasons that the applicant was prevented by sufficient<lb/>
 cause for not preferring the writ appeal within the statutory<lb/>
 period of limitation of 30 days. The applicant further<lb/>
 submits that they have a genuine case on merits and if the<lb/>
 delay is not condoned, the applicant would suffer<lb/>
 irreparable loss.<lb/>
</p>

<p>4.<lb/>
 The respondents no. 1 to 3 opposes the application<lb/>
 for condonation of delay. In their affidavit dated<lb/>
 19.06.2020, they contend that the applicant has utterly<lb/>
 failed to show sufficient cause and the lone reason<lb/>
 tendered is frivolous. It is contended that the period of<lb/>
 limitation having expired, the respondents have obtained<lb/>
 the benefit under the law of limitation to treat the<lb/>
 impugned order dated 22.07.2019 as beyond challenge,<lb/>
 and this legal right accrued to the respondents by lapse of<lb/>
 time should not be ignored and lightly disturbed. The<lb/>
 respondents no. 1 to 3 contends that the reasons given by<lb/>
 the applicant are also vague and no clear picture emerges<lb/>
 as to why the Special Leave Petition was withdrawn. They<lb/>
 further contend that the conduct of the applicant reflects a<lb/>
 casual and lackadaisical attitude in preferring Writ Appeal<lb/>
 No. 2 of 2019. It is also the case of the respondents no.1, 2<lb/>
 and 3 that the applicant has no case on merits in the Writ<lb/>
 Appeal No. 2 of 2019.<lb/>
</p>

<p>5.<lb/>
 Heard Mr. A. K. Upadhyaya, learned Senior<lb/>
 Counsel along with Mr. Sonam Rinchen Lepcha, learned<lb/>
 counsel for the applicant; Mr. Gulshan Lama, learned<lb/>
 counsel for respondents no. 1, 2 and 3; Mr. Sujan Sunwar,<lb/>
 learned Assistant Government Advocate for respondents<lb/>
 no. 4, 5 and 8; Mr. Karma Thinlay Namgyal, learned<lb/>
 Central Government Counsel for respondents no. 6 and 11<lb/>
 and as Senior Counsel for respondent no. 10 and<lb/>
 Mr. Leonard Gurung, learned counsel for respondent no. 9.<lb/>
 None appeared for respondent no. 7.<lb/>
</p>

<p>6.<lb/>
 During the course of hearing, Mr. A.K. Upadhyaya<lb/>
 referred to the judgment of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in<lb/>
 Esha Bhattacharjee v. Managing Committee of Raghunathpur<lb/>
 Nafar Academy &amp; Ors. 1 . Paragraph 21 thereof, which<lb/>
 enumerates the principles in deciding an application for<lb/>
 condonation of delay, is quoted herein below:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;21. From the aforesaid authorities the principles that<lb/>
 can broadly be culled out are:<lb/>
</item>

<item>21.1. (i) There should be a liberal, pragmatic, justice-<lb/>
oriented, non-pedantic approach while dealing with an<lb/>
 application for condonation of delay, for the courts are<lb/>
 not supposed to legalise injustice but are obliged to<lb/>
 remove injustice.<lb/>
</item>

 <item>
 21.2. (ii) The terms &quot;sufficient cause&quot; should be<lb/>
 understood in their proper spirit, philosophy and<lb/>
 purpose regard being had to the fact that these terms<lb/>
 are basically elastic and are to be applied in proper<lb/>
 perspective to the obtaining fact-situation.<lb/>
 </item>

<item>21.3. (iii) Substantial justice being paramount and<lb/>
 pivotal the technical considerations should not be given<lb/>
 undue and uncalled for emphasis.<lb/>
</item>

<item>21.4. (iv) No presumption can be attached to deliberate<lb/>
 causation of delay but, gross negligence on the part of<lb/>
 the counsel or litigant is to be taken note of.<lb/>
</item>

<item>21.5. (v) Lack of bona fides imputable to a party<lb/>
 seeking condonation of delay is a significant and<lb/>
 relevant fact.<lb/>
</item>

<item>21.6. (vi) It is to be kept in mind that adherence to<lb/>
 strict proof should not affect public justice and cause<lb/>
 public mischief because the courts are required to be<lb/>
 vigilant so that in the ultimate eventuate there is no<lb/>
 real failure of justice.<lb/>
</item>

<item>21.7. (vii) The concept of liberal approach has to<lb/>
 encapsulate the conception of reasonableness and it<lb/>
 cannot be allowed a totally unfettered free play.<lb/>
</item>

<item>21.8. (viii) There is a distinction between inordinate<lb/>
 delay and a delay of short duration or few days, for to<lb/>
 the former doctrine of prejudice is attracted whereas to<lb/>
 the latter it may not be attracted. That apart, the first<lb/>
 one warrants strict approach whereas the second calls<lb/>
 for a liberal delineation.<lb/>
</item>

<item>21.9. (ix) The conduct, behaviour and attitude of a<lb/>
 party relating to its inaction or negligence are relevant<lb/>
 factors to be taken into consideration. It is so as the<lb/>
 fundamental principle is that the courts are required to<lb/>
 weigh the scale of balance of justice in respect of both<lb/>
 parties and the said principle cannot be given a total go<lb/>
 by in the name of liberal approach.<lb/>
</item>

<item>21.10. (x) If the explanation offered is concocted or the<lb/>
 grounds urged in the application are fanciful, the courts<lb/>
 should be vigilant not to expose the other side<lb/>
 unnecessarily to face such a litigation.<lb/>
</item>

<item>21.11. (xi) It is to be borne in mind that no one gets<lb/>
 away with fraud, misrepresentation or interpolation by<lb/>
 taking recourse to the technicalities of law of limitation.<lb/>
</item>

 <item>
 21.12. (xii) The entire gamut of facts are to be carefully<lb/>
 scrutinised and the approach should be based on the<lb/>
 paradigm of judicial discretion which is founded on<lb/>
 objective reasoning and not on individual perception.<lb/>
</item>

<item>21.13. (xiii) The State or a public body or an entity<lb/>
 representing a collective cause should be given some<lb/>
 acceptable latitude.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>7.<lb/>
 Mr. A. K. Upadhyaya also referred to the judgment of<lb/>
 the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in J. Kumaradasan Nair &amp; Anr. v.<lb/>
 Iric Sohan &amp; Ors. 2 , to seek benefit of Section 14 of the<lb/>
 Limitation Act, 1963. The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court held:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;15. The question which arises for consideration is<lb/>
 as to whether only because a mistake has been<lb/>
 committed by or on behalf of the appellants in<lb/>
 approaching the appropriate forum for ventilating their<lb/>
 grievances, the same would mean that the provision of<lb/>
 sub-section (2) of Section 14 of the Limitation Act, which<lb/>
 is otherwise available, should not be taken into<lb/>
 consideration at all. The answer to the said question<lb/>
 must be rendered in the negative.<lb/>
</item>

<item>16. The provisions contained in Sections 5 and 14<lb/>
 of the Limitation Act are meant for grant of relief where<lb/>
 a person has committed some mistake. The provisions<lb/>
 of Sections 5 and 14 of the Limitation Act alike should,<lb/>
 thus, be applied in a broadbased manner. When sub-<lb/>
section (2) of Section 14 of the Limitation Act per se is<lb/>
 not applicable, the same would not mean that the<lb/>
 principles akin thereto would not be applied.<lb/>
 Otherwise, the provisions of Section 5 of the Limitation<lb/>
 Act would apply. There cannot be any doubt<lb/>
 whatsoever that the same would be applicable to a<lb/>
 case of this nature.&quot;<lb/>
</item>
<p>
 8.<lb/>
 While reiterating the pleadings in the affidavit<lb/>
 dated 19.06.2020 filed by the respondents no. 1, 2 and 3,<lb/>
 Mr. Gulshan Lama relied upon the judgment of the Hon&apos;ble<lb/>
 Supreme Court and Calcutta High Court in Balwant Singh<lb/>
 (Dead) v. Jagdish Singh &amp; Ors. 3 and Bhakti Bh. Mondal v.<lb/>
 Khagendra K. Bandopadhya &amp; Ors. 4 , respectively. He<lb/>
 submitted that once a valuable right has accrued in favour<lb/>
 of one party as a result of the failure of the other party to<lb/>
 explain the delay by showing sufficient cause and its own<lb/>
 conduct, it will be unreasonable to take away the right on<lb/>
 the mere asking of the applicant, particularly when the<lb/>
 delay is directly a result of negligence, default or inaction of<lb/>
 that party. Mr. Lama relied on the Calcutta High Court<lb/>
 judgment to submit that it was incumbent upon the<lb/>
 applicant to have filed an affidavit of the lawyer who had<lb/>
 rendered wrong advice to it. He submits that failure to do<lb/>
 so results in the failure to establish sufficient cause.<lb/>
</p>

<p>9.<lb/>
 In Balwant Singh (supra), the Hon&apos;ble Supreme<lb/>
 Court held that liberal construction of the expression<lb/>
 &quot;sufficient cause&quot; is intended to advance substantial justice<lb/>
 which itself presupposes no negligence or inaction on the<lb/>
 part of the applicant, to whom want of bona fide is<lb/>
 imputable. There could be instances where the court<lb/>
 should condone delay; equally there would be cases where<lb/>
 the court must exercise its discretion against the applicant<lb/>
 for want of any of these ingredients or where it does not<lb/>
 reflect &quot;sufficient cause&quot; as understood in law. Reasonable<lb/>
 time and proper conduct of the party concerned are<lb/>
 important considerations. The law of limitation is a<lb/>
 substantive law and has definite consequences on the right<lb/>
 and obligation of a party. Once a valuable right has<lb/>
 accrued in favour of one party as a result of a failure of the<lb/>
 other party to explain the delay by showing sufficient<lb/>
 cause, it will be unreasonable to take away that right on<lb/>
 the mere asking of the applicant, particularly when the<lb/>
 delay is directly a result of negligence, default or inaction of<lb/>
 that party.<lb/>
</p>

<p>10.<lb/>
 The High Court of Calcutta in Bhakti Bh. Mondal<lb/>
 (supra) had taken the view that the Limitation Act applied<lb/>
 to election petitions. The judgment cited by Mr. Lama has<lb/>
 been overruled by the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Anwari<lb/>
 Basavaraj Patil &amp; Ors. v. Siddaramaiah &amp; Ors. 5 which, inter<lb/>
 alia, held that Section 5 of the Limitation Act, 1963 was not<lb/>
 applicable to election petition.<lb/>
</p>

<p>11.<lb/>
 Mr. Karma Thinlay Namgyal submits that wrong<lb/>
 advice of a lawyer as pleaded by the applicant cannot be<lb/>
 sufficient cause. To buttress his arguments, the learned<lb/>
 Central Government Counsel, relied upon the judgment of<lb/>
 Delhi High Court in Haro Singh v. Ajay Kumar Chawla &amp;<lb/>
 Ors. 6 . Mr. Karma Thinlay Namgyal also sought to rely upon<lb/>
 the judgment of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Esha<lb/>
 Bhattacharjee (supra) to submit that no presumption can be<lb/>
 attached to deliberate causation of delay but, gross<lb/>
 negligence on the part of the counsel or litigant is to be<lb/>
 taken note of.<lb/>
</p>

<p>12.<lb/>
 In Haro Singh (supra), the Delhi High Court<lb/>
 preferred to follow the view taken in Babu Ram v. Devinder<lb/>
 Mohan Kaura &amp; Ors. 7 and not the contrary view taken by the<lb/>
 Delhi High Court in Krishan Lal v. Hanuman 8 . The Delhi<lb/>
 High Court was of the view that some High Courts as well<lb/>
 as the Delhi High Court in Babu Ram (supra) had taken the<lb/>
 view that the counsel must disclose the circumstances in<lb/>
 which incorrect advice was given and it is not sufficient to<lb/>
 make a perfunctory and general statement that the wrong<lb/>
 advice was given bona fide. Thus, the Delhi High Court on<lb/>
 the facts of Haro Singh (supra) held that no &quot;sufficient<lb/>
 cause&quot; had been shown for condoning the delay.<lb/>
</p>

<p>13.<lb/>
 In Babu Ram (supra), the Delhi High Court held<lb/>
 that:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;22. There is no universal rule that every mistaken<lb/>
 advice given by the counsel constitutes sufficient cause<lb/>
 or constitutes &quot;good faith&quot;. Every case depends on its<lb/>
 own facts. In some cases a bona fide opinion given by<lb/>
 a counsel can constitute sufficient cause. It all depends<lb/>
 how the opinion is given. If the opinion is given after<lb/>
 taking due care and attention then it will amount to<lb/>
 &quot;good faith&quot; as well as &quot;sufficient cause&quot;. If the opinion<lb/>
 is given off-hand without taking trouble of knowing the<lb/>
 law on the point it may not constitute sufficient cause<lb/>
 and/or &quot;good faith&quot;. Unfortunately, in the present case,<lb/>
 the learned counsel who gave the affidavit does not<lb/>
 mention how he honestly believed that a revision<lb/>
 petition was to be filed. There is no magic in the senior<lb/>
 counsel saying that he &quot;honestly gave the opinion.&quot; The<lb/>
 senior counsel or for that matter any other counsel<lb/>
 ought to further tell the court why he honestly gave that<lb/>
 opinion. What was it that led him to give the mistaken<lb/>
 advice? Was it something in the impugned judgment<lb/>
 which led him to give such an advice or was there<lb/>
 something in the law which made him give the<lb/>
 mistaken advice, it is not sufficient in such cases to<lb/>
 merely state that &apos;I am a senior counsel&apos; or &apos;I am a very<lb/>
 experienced counsel and I gave the opinion&apos;. Which is<lb/>
 of no use. The Court naturally expects that the counsel<lb/>
 concerned while choosing to file an affidavit for giving<lb/>
 mistaken advice would also state what led him to give<lb/>
 such an advice. If this much is not expected from a<lb/>
 counsel, it may lead to arbitrary decisions by Courts.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>14.<lb/>
 The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in the State of West<lb/>
 Bengal v. The Administrator, Howrah Municipality 9 , relying<lb/>
 upon the judgment rendered by the Privy Council in<lb/>
 Kunwar Rajendra Singh v. Rai Rajeshwar Bali 10 had held that<lb/>
 mistaken advice given by a legal practitioner may in the<lb/>
 circumstances of a particular case give rise to sufficient<lb/>
 cause within the section though there is no general<lb/>
 doctrine which saves parties from the results of wrong<lb/>
 advice.<lb/>
</p>

<p>15.<lb/>
 We have examined the application as well as the<lb/>
 reply filed by the respondents no. 1, 2 and 3. We have also<lb/>
 heard the learned counsel for the respective parties and<lb/>
 perused the judgments cited at the bar. The Hon&apos;ble<lb/>
 Supreme Court in Esha Bhattacharjee (supra) has<lb/>
 categorically held that there should be a liberal, pragmatic,<lb/>
 justice-oriented, non-pedantic approach while dealing with<lb/>
 an application for condonation of delay. The terms<lb/>
 &quot;sufficient cause&quot; should be understood in their proper<lb/>
 spirit, philosophy and purpose, regard being had to the fact<lb/>
 that these terms are basically elastic and are to be applied<lb/>
 in proper perspective to the obtaining fact-situation.<lb/>
 Substantial justice being paramount and pivotal, the<lb/>
 technical considerations should not be given undue and<lb/>
 uncalled for emphasis.<lb/>
</p>

<p>16.<lb/>
 The facts evidently reveal that the applicant had<lb/>
 approached this court as well as the Hon&apos;ble Supreme<lb/>
 Court against the orders sought to be challenged in Writ<lb/>
 Appeal No. 2 of 2019 by preferring application for review,<lb/>
 application for reconsideration and Special Leave Petition.<lb/>
 According to the applicant, they had approached the wrong<lb/>
 forums on wrong advice.<lb/>
</p>

<p>17.<lb/>
 It is, as argued by both Mr. Karma Thinlay<lb/>
 Namgyal and Mr. Lama, not too clear as to on whose wrong<lb/>
 advice the applicant did so. It is true that no affidavit of<lb/>
 any lawyer has been filed to support the applicant&apos;s<lb/>
 contention but there is no reason to disbelieve the<lb/>
 statement of the applicant. The statement of the applicant<lb/>
 is also supported by the narration of facts of what<lb/>
 transpired during this period of 103 days. The application,<lb/>
 read as a whole, cannot be termed perfunctory. It is evident<lb/>
 that the applicant did approach different forums to<lb/>
 ventilate its grievance before finally approaching this court<lb/>
 by way of Writ Appeal No. 2 of 2019. The sequence of<lb/>
 events which can be drawn from the orders passed in those<lb/>
 proceedings does reflect that the applicant had, in fact,<lb/>
 pursued remedy on wrong advice. It was because of the<lb/>
 filing of the applications in the writ petition, the Special<lb/>
 Leave Petition and Writ Appeal No. 1 of 2019, that<lb/>
 substantial part of the total delay of 103 days had<lb/>
 occasioned. The time taken for drafting the Writ Appeal<lb/>
 No.2 of 2019 and settling the same, as explained in the<lb/>
 application, was for a period of around a fortnight.<lb/>
</p>

<p>18.<lb/>
 The applicant filed the review petition against the<lb/>
 order dated 22.07.2019 passed by the learned Single Judge<lb/>
 in the writ petition which was rejected on 03.09.2019<lb/>
 before the expiry of the period of 30 days provided for filing<lb/>
 a writ appeal. When an order dated 06.09.2019 was passed<lb/>
 in the writ petition, the applicant approached the Hon&apos;ble<lb/>
 Supreme Court and filed the Special Leave Petition against<lb/>
 order dated and 06.09.2019 in the writ petition<lb/>
 and order dated 03.09.2019 in the review petition. The<lb/>
 applicant after withdrawing the Special Leave Petition, took<lb/>
 liberty from the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court to approach this<lb/>
 court and thereafter, filed an application i.e. I.A. No. 9 of<lb/>
 2019 in the writ petition for reconsideration of order dated<lb/>
 22.07.2019. This application was rejected by the learned<lb/>
 Single Judge on 18.10.2019. It seems that only after the<lb/>
 rejection of the application, it dawned upon it that it ought<lb/>
 to have preferred a writ appeal. The applicant did so by<lb/>
 filing Writ Appeal No. 1 of 2019 on 13.11.2019 but it soon<lb/>
 realized that it had not challenged two other orders passed<lb/>
 and accordingly withdrew the same on 22.11.2019 with<lb/>
 liberty to file afresh. The Writ Appeal No. 2 of 2019 was<lb/>
 thus filed on 02.12.2019 incurring a total delay of 103<lb/>
 days. The facts reflect that the legal advice received by the<lb/>
 applicant to file the review petition, Special Leave Petition<lb/>
 and application for reconsideration was not sound.<lb/>
 However, merely because the applicant followed the wrong<lb/>
 advice, which was evidently received, it cannot be said that<lb/>
 the applicant&apos;s conduct was casual and lackadaisical. The<lb/>
 reason to withdraw the Special Leave Petition is to our<lb/>
 mind not as important as the fact that the applicant had<lb/>
 preferred it and later chose to withdraw it. No negligence or<lb/>
 inaction can be imputed upon the applicant for pursuing<lb/>
 diligently remedies before wrong forums on advice received.<lb/>
 The limitation for filing Writ Appeal No. 2 of 2019 seems to<lb/>
 have expired due to the fact that the applicant followed the<lb/>
 advice received and filed the review petition, Special Leave<lb/>
 Petition and the application for reconsideration. It,<lb/>
 however, does reflect that the applicant was aggrieved and<lb/>
 was trying to ventilate its grievance but before wrong<lb/>
 forums. It cannot be said that there was deliberate<lb/>
 causation of delay on the part of the applicant. Section 5 of<lb/>
 the Limitation Act, 1963 provides that any appeal may be<lb/>
 admitted after the prescribed period, if the applicant<lb/>
 satisfies the court that it had sufficient cause for not doing<lb/>
 so. Section 14 of the Limitation Act, 1963 provides that in<lb/>
 computing the period of limitation the time during which<lb/>
 the applicant had been pursuing with due diligence<lb/>
 another proceeding shall be excluded. We are of the view<lb/>
 that the applicant is entitled to the benefit of Section 14 of<lb/>
 the Limitation Act, 1963 as well. We are also of the view,<lb/>
 that when we weigh the scale of balance of justice in<lb/>
 respect of the contesting parties, justice would be better<lb/>
 served if Writ Appeal No. 2 of 2019 is decided on merits<lb/>
 instead of throwing it out on the ground of delay alone.<lb/>
</p>

<p>19. In the circumstances, sufficient cause having been<lb/>
 shown by the applicant, the delay of 103 days in preferring<lb/>
 the Writ Appeal No. 2 of 2019, is condoned.<lb/>
</p>

<p>20.<lb/>
 The application is thus allowed.<lb/>
</p>

<p>21.<lb/>
 I.A. No. 1 of 2019 stands disposed.<lb/>
</p>

<p>( Bhaskar Raj Pradhan )<lb/>
 ( Arup Kumar Goswami )<lb/>
 Judge<lb/>
 Chief Justice<lb/>
 bp/to<lb/>
 Approved for reporting: Yes/No<lb/>
 Internet: Yes/No<lb/>
 BHASKAR<lb/>
 RAJ<lb/>
 PRADHAN<lb/>
 Digitally signed by<lb/>
 BHASKAR RAJ<lb/>
 PRADHAN<lb/>
 Date: 2020.10.07<lb/>
 14:53:50 +05&apos;30&apos;<lb/>
 ARUP<lb/>
 KUMAR<lb/>
 GOSWAMI<lb/>
 Digitally signed by<lb/>
 ARUP KUMAR<lb/>
 GOSWAMI<lb/>
 Date: 2020.10.07<lb/>
 15:52:41 +05&apos;30&apos;</p>


</text>
</tei>
