<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<head>
			O R D E R
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			This revision petition is directed against the
			<lb />
			judgment dated 14.02.2006 passed in Crl.Appeal
			<lb />
			No.845 of 2005 on the file of the Sessions
			<lb />
			Court, Ernakulam, which was preferred by the
			<lb />
			revision petitioners against the judgment of
			<lb />
			conviction and sentence dated 05.10.2005 in CC
			<lb />
			No.592 of 1999 on the file of the Judicial
			<lb />
			First Class Magistrate Court-I, Ernakulam.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			2. The revision petitioners were the accused in
			<lb />
			CC No.592 of 1999 on the file of the Judicial
			<lb />
			First Class Magistrate Court-I, Ernakulam
			<lb />
			consequent to a private complaint instituted
			<lb />
			by the 1 st respondent (complainant) against the
			<lb />
			revision petitioners/accused 1 and 2 alleging
			<lb />
			commission of the offence punishable under
			<lb />
			Section 138 of the Negotiable Instruments Act,
			<lb />
			1881 (hereinafter referred to as &apos;the NI
			<lb />
			Act&apos;). Parties are hereinafter referred to as
			<lb />
			&apos;the complainant&apos; and &apos;the accused&apos; according
			<lb />
			to their status in the trial court unless it
			<lb />
			is otherwise stated.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			3. The case of the complainant, in brief, is as
			<lb />
			hereunder:-
			<lb />
			The complainant, M/s Shipping Corporation of
			<lb />
			India, is represented by its local agent, M/s
			<lb />
			Jairam &amp; Sons. The 1 st accused, who is an
			<lb />
			exporting firm, and the 2 nd accused, who is its
			<lb />
			partner,
			<lb />
			had
			<lb />
			approached
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			complainant
			<lb />
			through its local agent and requested them to
			<lb />
			ship their cargo from Kochi to Hamburg. All
			<lb />
			the details of shipments were discussed in
			<lb />
			detail including the payment of freight
			<lb />
			charges etc. Accordingly, the accused shipped
			<lb />
			400
			<lb />
			bags
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			black
			<lb />
			pepper
			<lb />
			through
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			complainant as per vessel &quot;ACACIA-VOY.399&quot;
			<lb />
			from Kochi to Hamburg. Towards the freight
			<lb />
			amount, the accused issued cheque No.509028
			<lb />
			dated 26.05.1999 for Rs.79,160/-drawn on the
			<lb />
			Karur Vysya Bank, Ernakulam Branch, Cochin-16.
			<lb />
			When the complainant presented the above
			<lb />
			cheque for collection through their banker,
			<lb />
			State Bank of India, Willington Island,
			<lb />
			Cochin, the same was dishonoured with an
			<lb />
			endorsement &apos;Exceed Arrangement&apos; as per memo
			<lb />
			dated 18.05.1999 issued by the Karoor Vysya
			<lb />
			Bank, Ernakulam. Thereafter, the complainant
			<lb />
			sent a registered notice on 11.06.1999,
			<lb />
			demanding the amount covered under the cheque.
			<lb />
			The accused acknowledged the above notice on
			<lb />
			14.06.1999. Even after receipt of the demand
			<lb />
			notice, the accused failed to pay the amount
			<lb />
			covered
			<lb />
			under
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			cheque.
			<lb />
			Hence,
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			complaint.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			4. On service of summons, the accused appeared
			<lb />
			before the trial court. Particulars of the
			<lb />
			offence were read over and explained to the
			<lb />
			accused, to which the accused pleaded not
			<lb />
			guilty.
			<lb />
			Thereafter,
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			officer
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			complainant was examined as PW1 and marked
			<lb />
			Exts.P1 to P10. After PW1 was examined, the
			<lb />
			accused was questioned under Section 313(1)(b)
			<lb />
			of the Cr.P.C. for the purpose of enabling him
			<lb />
			to explain any circumstance appearing in the
			<lb />
			evidence against him. DW1 was examined on the
			<lb />
			side of the accused.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			5. On appreciation of the evidence, the learned
			<lb />
			magistrate held that the execution of the
			<lb />
			cheque was admitted by the accused and that
			<lb />
			the cheque was proved by the complainant that
			<lb />
			the cheque was dishonoured for the reason
			<lb />
			&apos;Exceed
			<lb />
			Arrangement&apos;.
			<lb />
			Hence,
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			learned
			<lb />
			magistrate concluded that the cheque was
			<lb />
			issued by the accused for the discharge of a
			<lb />
			debt or liability.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			6. Heard Sri.Ashik A. Mohamed Ali, the learned
			<lb />
			senior counsel for the revision petitioners;
			<lb />
			Sri.Vipin P. Varghese, the learned counsel for
			<lb />
			the 1 st respondent; and Sri.M.S.Breez, the
			<lb />
			learned Senior Public Prosecutor for the 2 nd
			<lb />
			respondent-State.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			7. Sri.Ashik A. Mohamed Ali, the learned counsel
			<lb />
			appearing for and on behalf of the revision
			<lb />
			petitioners, contended that the evidence in
			<lb />
			the above case, even if given face value and
			<lb />
			taken to be correct, do not constitute an
			<lb />
			offence alleged against the accused in terms
			<lb />
			of Section 138 read with Section 141 of the NI
			<lb />
			Act. It was further submitted that, in any
			<lb />
			event, the bill of lading as well as the
			<lb />
			averments in the complaint clearly spells out
			<lb />
			that the complainant is a public sector
			<lb />
			company owned by the Government of India and
			<lb />
			the company cannot issue a letter authorizing
			<lb />
			somebody to represent in a legal proceeding.
			<lb />
			It was further contended that the person, who
			<lb />
			received power from M/s Shipping Corporation
			<lb />
			of India, is a complete stranger and no
			<lb />
			contract of agency subsists between the
			<lb />
			complainant and the so called representative.
			<lb />
			It was further contended that legal notice was
			<lb />
			not issued within time.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			8. The learned counsel appearing on behalf of the
			<lb />
			1 st respondent, on the other hand, would submit
			<lb />
			that the accused issued the cheque in favour
			<lb />
			of the complainant pursuant to a transaction
			<lb />
			between them and the cheque, on presentation,
			<lb />
			was
			<lb />
			dishonoured
			<lb />
			for
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			reason
			<lb />
			&apos;Exceed
			<lb />
			Arrangement&apos;. It is contended that the privity
			<lb />
			of contract is between the complainant and the
			<lb />
			accused and the technical contention under
			<lb />
			Section 230 of the Contract Act is taken to
			<lb />
			avoid payment due to the complainant.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			9. In order to determine the question whether an
			<lb />
			offence punishable under Section 138 of the NI
			<lb />
			Act is made out against the accused, it is
			<lb />
			necessary to examine the penal provision of
			<lb />
			Section 138 of the NI Act and the presumptions
			<lb />
			to be raised as envisaged by the provisions of
			<lb />
			Sections 118 and 139 of the NI Act. Section
			<lb />
			118
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			NI
			<lb />
			Act
			<lb />
			provides
			<lb />
			certain
			<lb />
			presumptions to be raised laying down some
			<lb />
			special
			<lb />
			rules
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			evidence
			<lb />
			relating
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			presumptions. The presumption, therefore, is a
			<lb />
			matter of principle to infuse credibility to
			<lb />
			negotiable instruments including cheques and
			<lb />
			to encourage and promote the use of negotiable
			<lb />
			instruments in financial transactions. Section
			<lb />
			118 of the NI Act provides presumptions to be
			<lb />
			raised until the contrary is proved, (i) as to
			<lb />
			consideration, (ii) as to date of instrument,
			<lb />
			(iii) as to time of acceptance, (iv) as to
			<lb />
			time of transfer, (v) as to order of
			<lb />
			indorsements, (vi) as to appropriate stamp and
			<lb />
			(vii) as to holder being a holder in due
			<lb />
			course. That apart, Section 139 of the NI Act
			<lb />
			provides that it shall be presumed, unless the
			<lb />
			contrary is proved, that the holder of a
			<lb />
			cheque received the cheque of the nature
			<lb />
			referred to in Section 138 of the NI Act for
			<lb />
			the discharge, in whole or in part, of any
			<lb />
			debt
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			other
			<lb />
			liability.
			<lb />
			Applying
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			definition of the word &apos;proved&apos; in Section 3
			<lb />
			of the Evidence Act to the provisions of
			<lb />
			Sections 118 and 139 of the NI Act, it becomes
			<lb />
			evident that in a trial under Section 138 of
			<lb />
			the NI Act, a presumption will have to be made
			<lb />
			that every negotiable instrument was made or
			<lb />
			drawn for consideration and that it was
			<lb />
			executed for discharge of debt or liability
			<lb />
			once the execution of negotiable instrument is
			<lb />
			either proved or admitted. Needless to say
			<lb />
			that, as and when the complainant discharges
			<lb />
			the burden to prove that the cheque was
			<lb />
			executed
			<lb />
			by
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			accused,
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			rules
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			presumptions under Sections 118 and 139 of the
			<lb />
			NI Act are very much available to the
			<lb />
			complainant and the burden shifts on the
			<lb />
			accused.
			<lb />
			However,
			<lb />
			this
			<lb />
			presumption
			<lb />
			is
			<lb />
			rebuttable. Under the circumstances, it is the
			<lb />
			duty of the accused before the court by
			<lb />
			adducing evidence to show that the cheque was
			<lb />
			not supported by consideration and that there
			<lb />
			was no debt or liability to be discharged as
			<lb />
			alleged. It is necessary on the part of the
			<lb />
			accused to set up a probable defence for
			<lb />
			getting the burden of proof shifted to the
			<lb />
			complainant. Once such rebuttable evidence is
			<lb />
			adduced and accepted by the court, the burden
			<lb />
			shifts back to the complainant.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			10.PW1 is the Manager of M/s Jairam &amp; Sons. The
			<lb />
			firm has issued Ext.P1 power of attorney in
			<lb />
			favour of PW1. When examined before the court,
			<lb />
			he stated that he is the Manager of the firm.
			<lb />
			The complainant is M/s Shipping Corporation of
			<lb />
			India. It is represented by M/s Jairam &amp; Sons,
			<lb />
			one of the local steamer agents of the
			<lb />
			Shipping Corporation of India. The complaint
			<lb />
			is signed by the power of attorney holder of
			<lb />
			the firm, M/s Jairam &amp; Sons. The person, who
			<lb />
			signed in the complaint, is the Manager of the
			<lb />
			firm, M/s Jairam &amp; Sons.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			11.During
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			trial,
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			accused
			<lb />
			entered
			<lb />
			appearance before the court and denied the
			<lb />
			accusation levelled against him. Another case
			<lb />
			of the same nature between the same parties
			<lb />
			was pending before the very same court as CC
			<lb />
			No. 593 of 1999. Hence, joint trial was
			<lb />
			ordered and the evidence was taken in CC No.
			<lb />
			592 of 1999. Against the judgment dated
			<lb />
			05.10.2005,
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			accused
			<lb />
			preferred
			<lb />
			this
			<lb />
			Crl.R.P. It is seen from the records that the
			<lb />
			accused in CC No. 593 of 1999 preferred Crl.
			<lb />
			Appeal No. 846 of 2005 before the Sessions
			<lb />
			Court and the same was dismissed. However, no
			<lb />
			revision
			<lb />
			is
			<lb />
			seen
			<lb />
			filed
			<lb />
			challenging
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			judgment in Crl. Appeal No. 846 of 2005.
			<lb />
			Hence,
			<lb />
			it
			<lb />
			appears
			<lb />
			from
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			facts
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			circumstances that the judgment in Crl. Appeal
			<lb />
			No. 846 of 2005 has become final between the
			<lb />
			parties on identical matters.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			12.The
			<lb />
			learned
			<lb />
			counsel
			<lb />
			for
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			revision
			<lb />
			petitioners/accused
			<lb />
			contended
			<lb />
			that
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			complainant is only an agent for the principal
			<lb />
			and an agent cannot personally enforce a
			<lb />
			contract under Section 230 of the Contract
			<lb />
			Act. It is contended that the transaction
			<lb />
			covered is not enforceable through court by
			<lb />
			the complainant.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			13.The complainant, M/s Shipping Corporation of
			<lb />
			India, is doing business through its agent. In
			<lb />
			connection with the shipment, they are issuing
			<lb />
			bill of lading. It is the duty of its agent to
			<lb />
			collect the freight charges and deposit the
			<lb />
			same to the account of the Corporation. They
			<lb />
			are collecting freight charges as part of
			<lb />
			their business as steamer agents. Collecting
			<lb />
			freight charges for and on behalf of the M/s
			<lb />
			Shipping Corporation of India is not a case of
			<lb />
			delegation. Ext.P3 would show that shipment of
			<lb />
			the cargo of the accused was conducted through
			<lb />
			the vessel of M/s Shipping Corporation of
			<lb />
			India. According to the accused, the cheque
			<lb />
			was not issued to M/s Jairam &amp; Sons, but it
			<lb />
			was issued to M/s Leap Forwarders Pvt. Ltd.
			<lb />
			Ext.P3 series, on the other hand, would show
			<lb />
			that shipment was made through M/s Jairam &amp;
			<lb />
			Sons. The cheque was issued for shipment of
			<lb />
			the cargo of the accused also. Even if the
			<lb />
			shipment was through M/s Leap Forwarders Pvt.
			<lb />
			Ltd., it would be payment to the shipping
			<lb />
			company or the agents, through whom the
			<lb />
			shipment was made. In this case, no evidence
			<lb />
			was adduced to show that it was given through
			<lb />
			M/s Leap Forwarders Pvt. Ltd. The evidence
			<lb />
			adduced would show that the freight charge of
			<lb />
			the shipment was made after issuing Ext.P3
			<lb />
			series of bills of lading for a legally
			<lb />
			enforceable debt. In this case, the cheque was
			<lb />
			drawn in the name of M/s Shipping Corporation
			<lb />
			of India and notice was issued in the name of
			<lb />
			M/s Jairam &amp; Sons, their local agent.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			14.Apart from the 1 st accused partnership firm,
			<lb />
			the partner of the 1 st accused was also made as
			<lb />
			an accused in the case. Admittedly, they
			<lb />
			issued the cheque, which, on presentation, was
			<lb />
			dishonoured
			<lb />
			for
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			reason
			<lb />
			&apos;Exceed
			<lb />
			Arrangement&apos;. A person would be vicariously
			<lb />
			liable for commission of offence on the part
			<lb />
			of the partnership firm only in the event the
			<lb />
			conditions and stipulations prescribed under
			<lb />
			Section 138 read with Section 141 of the NI
			<lb />
			Act are satisfied with. The above principle
			<lb />
			has been dealt with in detail by the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court in M/s Kusum Ingots &amp; Alloys Ltd. v. M/s
			<lb />
			Pennar Peterson Securities Ltd. and others
			<lb />
			[(2000)2 SCC 745] as follows:-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;10. On a reading of the provisions of Section
			<lb />
			138 of the NI Act it is clear that the
			<lb />
			ingredients which are to be satisfied for
			<lb />
			making out a case under the provision are:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(i) a person must have drawn a cheque on an
			<lb />
			account maintained by him in a bank for payment
			<lb />
			of a certain amount of money to another person
			<lb />
			from out of that account for the discharge of
			<lb />
			any debt or other liability;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii) that cheque has been presented to the bank
			<lb />
			within a period of six months from the date on
			<lb />
			which it is drawn or within the period of its
			<lb />
			validity, whichever is earlier;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) that cheque is returned by the bank
			<lb />
			unpaid, either because the amount of money
			<lb />
			standing to the credit of the account is
			<lb />
			insufficient to honour the cheque or that it
			<lb />
			exceeds the amount arranged to be paid from
			<lb />
			that account by an agreement made with the
			<lb />
			bank;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iv) the payee or the holder in due course of
			<lb />
			the cheque makes a demand for the payment of
			<lb />
			the said amount of money by giving a notice in
			<lb />
			writing, to the drawer of the cheque, within 15
			<lb />
			days of the receipt of information by him from
			<lb />
			the bank regarding the return of the cheque as
			<lb />
			unpaid;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(v) the drawer of such cheque fails to make
			<lb />
			payment of the said amount of money to the
			<lb />
			payee or the holder in due course of the cheque
			<lb />
			within 15 days of the receipt of the said
			<lb />
			notice.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			15.For creating criminal liabilities in terms of
			<lb />
			Section 138 of the NI Act, the complainant is
			<lb />
			obliged to show that a cheque was issued; the
			<lb />
			same was presented; but, it was dishonoured; a
			<lb />
			notice in terms of the said provision was
			<lb />
			served on the person sought to be made liable;
			<lb />
			and despite service of notice, neither any
			<lb />
			payment was made nor other obligations, if
			<lb />
			any, were complied with within fifteen days
			<lb />
			from the date of receipt of the statutory
			<lb />
			notice.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			16.Section
			<lb />
			141
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			NI
			<lb />
			Act
			<lb />
			provides
			<lb />
			constructive liability on the part of the
			<lb />
			Directors of the company or other persons
			<lb />
			responsible for the conduct of the business of
			<lb />
			the company. Though the heading of Section 141
			<lb />
			of the NI Act reads &quot;Offences by companies&quot;,
			<lb />
			as per the Explanation to that Section
			<lb />
			&quot;company&quot; means &quot;any body corporate and
			<lb />
			includes a firm or other association of
			<lb />
			individuals&quot;; and &quot;director&quot; in relation to a
			<lb />
			firm, means a &quot;partner&quot; in the firm. Their
			<lb />
			liability is joint and several. Consequently,
			<lb />
			therefore, when an offence is alleged to have
			<lb />
			been committed by the partnership firm, every
			<lb />
			person who, at the time the offence was
			<lb />
			committed,
			<lb />
			was
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			charge
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			was
			<lb />
			responsible to the firm for the conduct of its
			<lb />
			business as well as the firm shall be deemed
			<lb />
			to be guilty of the offence and shall be
			<lb />
			liable to be proceeded under Section 138 of
			<lb />
			the NI Act. In S.M.S Pharmaceuticals Ltd. v.
			<lb />
			Neeta Bhalla &amp; another [(2005) 8 SCC 89], it
			<lb />
			was held that a signatory to the cheque can be
			<lb />
			held to be a person liable under Section 141
			<lb />
			of the NI Act. It has come out in evidence
			<lb />
			that the 2 nd accused issued the cheque in
			<lb />
			favour of the complainant for a legally
			<lb />
			enforceable debt. The cheque in question was
			<lb />
			drawn for consideration and the holder of the
			<lb />
			cheque received the same in discharge of an
			<lb />
			existing debt. Ex.P3 bill of lading is not
			<lb />
			sufficient to indicate that the amount was due
			<lb />
			to M/s Shipping Corporation of India and the
			<lb />
			complainant was actually the steamer agent of
			<lb />
			M/s Shipping Corporation of India. It has come
			<lb />
			out in evidence that the accused issued cheque
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			complainant
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			complainant
			<lb />
			received the same. Although the complainant
			<lb />
			issued legal notice to the accused, no reply
			<lb />
			was issued denying the liability. Ext.P5
			<lb />
			cheque dated 26.05.1999 is for an amount of
			<lb />
			Rs.79,160/-. The said cheque was presented
			<lb />
			before the State Bank of India, Willington
			<lb />
			Island, Kochi on 04.06.1999. Ext.P6 cheque is
			<lb />
			dated 18.05.1999 and is for an amount of
			<lb />
			Rs.79,325/-. Ext.P8 notice was issued on
			<lb />
			11.06.1999. Hence, statutory notice was issued
			<lb />
			right in time. When the cheque was issued in
			<lb />
			the name of the complainant, it is illogical
			<lb />
			to contend that the amounts due on account of
			<lb />
			the shipping were made through M/s Shipping
			<lb />
			Corporation of India, for whom M/s Jairam &amp;
			<lb />
			Sons stood as an agent. The accused had not
			<lb />
			offered any explanation as to why they had
			<lb />
			issued
			<lb />
			Ext.P5
			<lb />
			cheque
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			M/s
			<lb />
			Shipping
			<lb />
			Corporation of India.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			17.The conclusions drawn by the trial court and
			<lb />
			the appellate court to convict the accused 1
			<lb />
			and 2 are perfectly legal. The cheque in
			<lb />
			question was drawn for consideration and the
			<lb />
			holder of the cheque received the same in
			<lb />
			discharge of an existing debt. Thereafter, the
			<lb />
			onus shifts on the accused to establish a
			<lb />
			probable
			<lb />
			defence
			<lb />
			so
			<lb />
			as
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			rebut
			<lb />
			such
			<lb />
			presumption,
			<lb />
			which
			<lb />
			onus
			<lb />
			has
			<lb />
			not
			<lb />
			been
			<lb />
			discharged by the accused. Once the cheque is
			<lb />
			proved to be issued, it carries statutory
			<lb />
			presumption of consideration under Sections
			<lb />
			118 and 139 of the NI Act. Then, the onus is
			<lb />
			on the accused to disprove the presumption at
			<lb />
			which they have not succeeded.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			18.It is well settled law that when concurrent
			<lb />
			findings of facts rendered by the trial court
			<lb />
			and appellate court are sought to be aside in
			<lb />
			revision, the High Court does not, in the
			<lb />
			absence of perversity, upset factual findings
			<lb />
			arrived at by the two courts below. It is not
			<lb />
			for the revisional court to re-analyse and
			<lb />
			reinterpret the evidence on record in a case,
			<lb />
			where the trial court has come to a probable
			<lb />
			conclusion. Unless the contrary is proved, it
			<lb />
			is presumed that the holder of a cheque
			<lb />
			received the cheque of the nature referred to
			<lb />
			in Section 138 of the NI Act for the
			<lb />
			discharge, in whole or in part, of any debt or
			<lb />
			other liability. In the case at hand, the
			<lb />
			accused has no case that he has not signed the
			<lb />
			cheque or parted with under any threat or
			<lb />
			coercion. That apart, the accused has no case
			<lb />
			that
			<lb />
			unfilled
			<lb />
			cheque
			<lb />
			had
			<lb />
			been
			<lb />
			lost
			<lb />
			irrecoverably or stolen. The accused failed to
			<lb />
			prove in the trial by leading cogent evidence
			<lb />
			that there was no debt or liability. In Bir
			<lb />
			Singh v. Mukesh Kumar [(2019) 4 SCC 197], the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court held that in view of Section 139
			<lb />
			of the NI Act read with Section 118 of the NI
			<lb />
			Act thereof, the Court has to presume that the
			<lb />
			cheque has been issued for discharging a debt
			<lb />
			or liability. Paragraphs 39 and 40 of the
			<lb />
			above case are relevant in this context and
			<lb />
			the same are extracted below for convenience
			<lb />
			of reference:-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;39. It is not the case of the respondent-
			<lb />
			accused that he either signed the cheque or
			<lb />
			parted with it under any threat or coercion.
			<lb />
			Nor is it the case of the respondent-accused
			<lb />
			that the unfilled signed cheque had been
			<lb />
			stolen.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			existence
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			a
			<lb />
			fiduciary
			<lb />
			relationship between the payee of a cheque and
			<lb />
			its drawer, would not disentitle the payee to
			<lb />
			the benefit of the presumption under Section
			<lb />
			139 of the Negotiable Instruments Act, in the
			<lb />
			absence of evidence of exercise of undue
			<lb />
			influence or coercion. The second question is
			<lb />
			also answered in the negative.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			40. Even a blank cheque leaf, voluntarily
			<lb />
			signed and handed over by the accused, which is
			<lb />
			towards some payment, would attract presumption
			<lb />
			under Section 139 of the Negotiable Instruments
			<lb />
			Act, in the absence of any cogent evidence to
			<lb />
			show that the cheque was not issued in
			<lb />
			discharge of a debt.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			19.In view of the above, both the trial court and
			<lb />
			the appellate court rightly held that the
			<lb />
			burden was on the accused to disprove the
			<lb />
			initial presumption under Sections 118 and 139
			<lb />
			of the NI Act. The accused was examined as DW1
			<lb />
			in this case. He stated that the cheque was
			<lb />
			entrusted to M/s Leap Forwarders as a blank
			<lb />
			signed one. No evidence was let in to prove
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			alleged
			<lb />
			entrustment
			<lb />
			with
			<lb />
			M/s
			<lb />
			Leap
			<lb />
			Forwarders as contended. The burden is not
			<lb />
			discharged rightly. Hence, the conviction of
			<lb />
			the accused for the offence under Section 138
			<lb />
			of the NI Act is only to be upheld.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			20.Coming to the question of sentence, the trial
			<lb />
			court convicted and sentenced the 1 st accused
			<lb />
			to pay a fine of Rs.5,000/-each and 2 nd
			<lb />
			accused to undergo simple imprisonment for
			<lb />
			three months each in CC Nos. 592 and 593 of
			<lb />
			1999 on the file of the Judicial First Class
			<lb />
			Magistrae Court-I, Ernakulam. Further, it was
			<lb />
			ordered to pay a sum of Rs.1,19,000/-in CC
			<lb />
			No.592 of 1999 and Rs.1,18,000/-in CC No. 593
			<lb />
			of 1999 to the complainant under Section
			<lb />
			357(3) of Cr.P.C. and default of payment of
			<lb />
			fine to undergo simple imprisonment for three
			<lb />
			months each more. The amount involved in CC
			<lb />
			No. 592 of 1999 is Rs.79,160/-as per cheque
			<lb />
			bearing No. 509028 dated 26.05.1999. This
			<lb />
			revision
			<lb />
			is
			<lb />
			confined
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			an
			<lb />
			amount
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			Rs.79,160/-only. So far as CC No. 593 of 1999
			<lb />
			is concerned, the accused preferred Crl.
			<lb />
			Appeal No. 846 of 2005 before the Sessions
			<lb />
			Court, Ernakulam. Crl. Appeal 845 of 2005
			<lb />
			arising out of CC No. 592 of 1999 and Crl.
			<lb />
			Appeal 846 of 2005 arising out of CC No. 593
			<lb />
			of 1999 were heard together by the learned
			<lb />
			Sessions
			<lb />
			Judge
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			pronounced
			<lb />
			a
			<lb />
			common
			<lb />
			judgment on 14.02.2006. The accused challenged
			<lb />
			the judgment in Crl. Appeal 845 of 2005 before
			<lb />
			this Court. Regarding the other case, no
			<lb />
			submission was advanced by the learned counsel
			<lb />
			for the revision petitioner. The only logical
			<lb />
			inference is that on identical facts, Crl.
			<lb />
			Appeal No. 846 of 2005 has become final
			<lb />
			between the parties.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			21.In view of the discussion made herein above,
			<lb />
			the concurrent conviction under Section 138 of
			<lb />
			the NI Act is sustained. Section 138 of the NI
			<lb />
			Act provides sentence of imprisonment or with
			<lb />
			fine or with both. Sentence of imprisonment is
			<lb />
			not compulsory. The object is to pay the
			<lb />
			amount covered under the cheque. Hence, the
			<lb />
			mandatory term of imprisonment awarded by the
			<lb />
			trial court, which was confirmed in appeal, is
			<lb />
			liable to be set aside. The conviction and
			<lb />
			sentence as against the 1 st accused stand
			<lb />
			confirmed. While confirming the conviction of
			<lb />
			the 2 nd accused, in modification of the
			<lb />
			sentence, the 2 nd accused is sentenced to pay a
			<lb />
			fine of Rs.79,160/-and in default of payment
			<lb />
			of fine to undergo simple imprisonment for a
			<lb />
			period of three months. If the amount is paid
			<lb />
			as compensation, the same shall be given to the
			<lb />
			complainant
			<lb />
			as
			<lb />
			compensation
			<lb />
			under
			<lb />
			Section
			<lb />
			357(3) of Cr.P.C.
			<lb />
			With the above modification, the Crl.R.P. is
			<lb />
			allowed in part. In view of the situation
			<lb />
			prevailing in the country due to the outbreak
			<lb />
			of Covid-19 pandemic, this Court is inclined to
			<lb />
			grant six months time from today to the
			<lb />
			revision petitioners/accused 1 and 2 to deposit
			<lb />
			the compensation and the fine amount before the
			<lb />
			trial
			<lb />
			court,
			<lb />
			failing
			<lb />
			which
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			learned
			<lb />
			Magistrate
			<lb />
			shall
			<lb />
			take
			<lb />
			necessary
			<lb />
			steps
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			execute the sentence against the revision
			<lb />
			petitioners/accused 1 and 2 in accordance with
			<lb />
			law.
			<lb />
			The Registry is directed to forward the entire
			<lb />
			records to the trial court forthwith.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			Sd/-
			<lb />
			N.ANIL KUMAR
			<lb />
			JUDGE
			<lb />
			Bka/-
		</p>


	</text>
</tei>