<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<head>
			ORDER
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			The
			<lb />
			revision
			<lb />
			petitioner
			<lb />
			is
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			accused
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			CC.No.156/1994 on the file of the Judicial First Class
			<lb />
			Magistrate Court-V, Kozhikode and the appellant in
			<lb />
			Crl.Appeal No.580/2001 on the file of the second
			<lb />
			Additional Sessions Court, Kozhikode. The offences alleged
			<lb />
			against the accused are punishable under Sections 279,
			<lb />
			337, 338 and 304A of the IPC.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			The prosecution case in brief is that on
			<lb />
			19.1.1993 at about 3 pm., the revision petitioner drove a
			<lb />
			stage carriage bus bearing registration No.KLM-7408 in a
			<lb />
			rash and negligent manner through the Ramanattukara
			<lb />
			National High Way and when it reached in front of the
			<lb />
			Poovannur mosque at Velipram, the driver took it to the
			<lb />
			wrong side of the road and the bus hit against a mini bus
			<lb />
			bearing registration No.KL-11/7711 and due to the impact
			<lb />
			of the accident, the passengers of both vehicles sustained
			<lb />
			simple and grievous injuries and the driver of the mini bus
			<lb />
			and one of the passengers therein succumbed to the
			<lb />
			injuries.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			When the accused entered appearance before
			<lb />
			the trial court, he was furnished with copies of the police
			<lb />
			report and other documents. Upon pleading not guilty to
			<lb />
			the charge, the entire evidence was taken. By judgment
			<lb />
			dated 29.4.95, the accused was convicted and sentenced
			<lb />
			to undergo imprisonment for various counts stated supra.
			<lb />
			The accused preferred Crl.Appeal No.161/1995 before the
			<lb />
			Court of Session, Kozhikode. The appeal was allowed and
			<lb />
			consequently the conviction and sentence passed by the
			<lb />
			trial court was set aside and the case was remanded back
			<lb />
			for fresh disposal in accordance with the law. As directed
			<lb />
			by the Sessions Court, the prosecution examined PW15
			<lb />
			and marked Exts.P29 and P30. Further, PWs.1, 2, 5 and
			<lb />
			11 were recalled for cross-examination and they were
			<lb />
			cross-examined. After their examination, the learned
			<lb />
			counsel for the accused filed a witness list to examine
			<lb />
			witnesses on his side. It was allowed and summons was
			<lb />
			ordered. However, no batta was deposited by the accused
			<lb />
			and hence the defence evidence was closed.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			The total number of witnesses examined from
			<lb />
			the side of prosecution was PWs.1 to 15 and Exts.P1 to
			<lb />
			P30 and MO1 series. On appreciation of the evidence, the
			<lb />
			learned Magistrate found the accused guilty of the
			<lb />
			offences punishable under Sections 279, 337, 338 and
			<lb />
			304A of the IPC. Accordingly, he was sentenced to
			<lb />
			undergo simple imprisonment for a period of two years for
			<lb />
			the offence punishable under Section 304A of the IPC,
			<lb />
			simple imprisonment for six months for the offence
			<lb />
			punishable under Section 279 of the IPC and simple
			<lb />
			imprisonment for a period of six months for the offence
			<lb />
			punishable under Section 338 of the IPC. No separate
			<lb />
			sentence was awarded under Section 337 of the IPC. It
			<lb />
			was further directed that the sentences should run
			<lb />
			concurrently. The revision petitioner filed Crl.Appeal
			<lb />
			No.580/2001 before the Sessions Court, Kozhikode
			<lb />
			division. The appellate court dismissed the appeal
			<lb />
			confirming the conviction and sentence imposed by the
			<lb />
			trial court.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			Heard Sri.Firoz.K.M., the learned counsel for the
			<lb />
			revision petitioner and Sri.M.S.Breez, the learned Senior
			<lb />
			Public Prosecutor for the respondent-State.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			The learned counsel for the revision petitioner
			<lb />
			Sri.Firoz.K.M. contended that the two courts below failed
			<lb />
			to consider the relevant facts while passing the conviction
			<lb />
			and sentence. It was further contended that the accused
			<lb />
			had not caused hurt to any person by doing acts so rashly
			<lb />
			or negligently so as to endanger human life or personal
			<lb />
			safety of others. According to the learned counsel for the
			<lb />
			revision petitioner, the persons who had sustained injuries
			<lb />
			in the accident moved claim petitions before the Motor
			<lb />
			Accidents Claims Tribunal alleging contributory negligence.
			<lb />
			When the witnesses pleaded contributory negligence to
			<lb />
			get appropriate compensation from the Tribunal, the
			<lb />
			prosecution was obliged to produce sufficient materials
			<lb />
			before the court to prove that the accused drove the
			<lb />
			offending vehicle in a rash and negligent manner. When
			<lb />
			contributory negligence is alleged, according to the
			<lb />
			learned counsel for the revision petitioner, it was
			<lb />
			obligatory on the part of the prosecution to prove gross
			<lb />
			negligence before the trial court beyond doubt. Further it
			<lb />
			was contended that the trial court wrongly appreciated the
			<lb />
			evidence of PW3 in support of the prosecution case.
			<lb />
			Further, the courts below failed to consider the aspects
			<lb />
			relating to tyre marks of both the vehicles in the right
			<lb />
			perspective.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			Per contra, the learned Senior Public Prosecutor
			<lb />
			contended that the two courts below concurrently held
			<lb />
			that the accused committed the offences punishable under
			<lb />
			Sections 279, 337, 338 and 304A of the IPC and
			<lb />
			accordingly he was convicted thereunder. Concurrent
			<lb />
			findings of facts and law are sought to be set aside in
			<lb />
			revision. The trial court as well as the appellate court
			<lb />
			convicted the accused for the aforesaid offences by a
			<lb />
			process of well-reasoned findings and according to the
			<lb />
			learned Senior Public Prosecutor, it would not be just and
			<lb />
			proper to interfere in exercise of powers under Section
			<lb />
			401 of the Cr.P.C.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			PWs.1 and 2 were passengers of the mini bus.
			<lb />
			They had sustained injuries in the accident. PW1 lodged
			<lb />
			Ext.P1 FIS before the police. According to PWs.1 and 2 the
			<lb />
			bus which came in the opposite direction overtook another
			<lb />
			vehicle and dashed against the mini bus. PWs.1 and 2
			<lb />
			stated that the mini bus was driven at minimum speed
			<lb />
			while the other bus was coming in high speed. PWs.1 and
			<lb />
			2 identified the accused before the trial court. PW5 was
			<lb />
			travelling in the bus driven by the accused. PW5 also
			<lb />
			sustained injuries. PW5 stated that the accused drove the
			<lb />
			offending vehicle in a rash and negligent manner so as to
			<lb />
			endanger human life. According to PW5, over speed of the
			<lb />
			mini bus was one of the reasons for the accident. PW3
			<lb />
			was also a passenger in the bus bearing registration
			<lb />
			No.KLM 7408. PW3 stated that the said bus hit against the
			<lb />
			mini bus while overtaking another bus. He maintained that
			<lb />
			the accused drove the bus in a rash and negligent manner
			<lb />
			so as to endanger human life. PW3 was not cross-
			<lb />
			examined. After remand, summons was issued to PW3. It
			<lb />
			was returned unserved as he was no more.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			Ext.P22 mahazar was relied on by the two
			<lb />
			courts below to prove that the bus driven by the accused
			<lb />
			was on the wrong side at the accident site. Evidence of
			<lb />
			the Motor Vehicle Inspector as PW9, and Exts.P15 and P16
			<lb />
			reports ruled out brake failure or mechanical defect for
			<lb />
			any of the vehicles. Relying on the evidence of PWs.1 to 3
			<lb />
			and PW9, it was held that the accused was guilty of the
			<lb />
			offences punishable under Sections 279, 337, 338 and
			<lb />
			304A of the IPC.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			10. The learned counsel for the revision petitioner
			<lb />
			mainly contended that PWs.1 and 2 preferred claim
			<lb />
			petitions before the MACT for getting compensation on
			<lb />
			account of the injuries sustained in the accident. During
			<lb />
			cross-examination copies of the claim petitions were
			<lb />
			confronted to PWs.1 and 2 and marked Exts.D1 and D2.
			<lb />
			As per Exts.D1 and D2, it is seen that the allegation made
			<lb />
			therein is that both the drivers of the vehicles were
			<lb />
			negligent in driving the vehicles at the time of the
			<lb />
			accident. However, they turned round and deposed before
			<lb />
			the trial court that the accident had happened due to the
			<lb />
			negligent driving of the driver of the bus bearing
			<lb />
			registration No.KLM 7408. Going by Exts.D1 and D2, it is
			<lb />
			clear that PWs.1 and 2 pleaded contributory negligence.
			<lb />
			In Easo Mathew v. State of Kerala [ILR 1967 (1)
			<lb />
			Kerala 352] it was held that contributory negligence of
			<lb />
			the victim is no defence against a charge under Section
			<lb />
			279 or 304A of the IPC. A driver must anticipate
			<lb />
			reasonably foreseeable negligent act of odd users as
			<lb />
			doctrine of contributory negligence has no application in
			<lb />
			criminal law. Thus, the doctrine of contributory negligence
			<lb />
			does not apply to a criminal liability, where the death of a
			<lb />
			person is caused partly by the negligence of the accused
			<lb />
			and partly by his own negligence. Essential ingredients of
			<lb />
			Section 304A of the IPC are the following:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			i)
			<lb />
			Death of a person
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			ii) Death was caused by the accused
			<lb />
			during any rash or negligent act.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			iii) Act does not amount to culpable
			<lb />
			homicide.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			11. In order to prove negligence as defined under
			<lb />
			Section 304A of the IPC, the prosecution is obliged to
			<lb />
			prove,
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>>
			i)
			<lb />
			The existence of duty
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			ii)
			<lb />
			A breach of the duty causing death
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			iii)
			<lb />
			The breach of the duty must be
			<lb />
			characterized as gross negligence.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			12. PW1 testified before the court that on 19.1.93
			<lb />
			at 3 pm. near to the Poovannur Masjid at Ramanattukara
			<lb />
			while he was travelling on the mini bus bearing
			<lb />
			registration
			<lb />
			No.KL-11/7711,
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			offending
			<lb />
			vehicle
			<lb />
			overtook another vehicle negligently and hit against the
			<lb />
			mini bus and thereby he along with others sustained
			<lb />
			injuries. PW2 supported his version. Two of the injured
			<lb />
			died. During cross-examination PWs.1 and 2 stated that
			<lb />
			there was no negligence on the part of the driver of the
			<lb />
			mini bus. However, Exts.D1 and D2 would show that both
			<lb />
			the drivers were negligent in driving the vehicles.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			13. Driving at a high speed is not in itself a
			<lb />
			negligent act. In the case of Ravi Kapur v. State of
			<lb />
			Rajasthan [AIR 2012 SC 2986], the Apex Court held
			<lb />
			that a person who drives a vehicle is liable to be held
			<lb />
			responsible for the act as well as for the result and that it
			<lb />
			may not be always possible to determine with reference to
			<lb />
			the speed of a vehicle whether a person was driving rashly
			<lb />
			and negligently and even when one is driving a vehicle at
			<lb />
			a slow speed, but, recklessly and negligently, it would
			<lb />
			amount to &apos;rash and negligent driving&apos; within the meaning
			<lb />
			of the language of Section 279 of the IPC. Mere driving of
			<lb />
			a vehicle at a high speed or slow speed does not lead to
			<lb />
			an inference that negligent or rash driving had caused the
			<lb />
			accident resulting in injuries to the complainant. Thus, the
			<lb />
			speed is not a criterion to establish the fact of rash and
			<lb />
			negligent driving of a vehicle. When it is alleged that
			<lb />
			driving of the offending vehicle leads to an accident, the
			<lb />
			main question arising for consideration is as to whether
			<lb />
			the driver of the offending vehicle drove the vehicle in a
			<lb />
			rash and negligent manner. The speed is not the only
			<lb />
			criterion. The width of the road, density of traffic, tyre
			<lb />
			marks, etc. are also criteria to decide negligence. It is
			<lb />
			necessary to appreciate the evidence in unbiased manner
			<lb />
			especially when two vehicles are involved and the accident
			<lb />
			is head-on-collision. Although contributory negligence is
			<lb />
			not a defence in a criminal case, when contributory
			<lb />
			negligence is set up as a ground by the injured in a case
			<lb />
			relating to the very same accident before the Motor
			<lb />
			Accident Claims Tribunal, it is necessary on the part of the
			<lb />
			prosecution to adduce convincing evidence before the
			<lb />
			court to prove gross negligence. It is necessary to prove
			<lb />
			that the death was due to the rash or negligent act of the
			<lb />
			accused and the act must be sufficient cause without
			<lb />
			intervention of another&apos;s negligence. In other words, it
			<lb />
			must be, causa causans; it is not enough that it may have
			<lb />
			been the causa sine qua non. There must, therefore, be
			<lb />
			direct nexus between the death of a person and the rash
			<lb />
			or negligent act of the accused.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			14. The important document with regard to the
			<lb />
			offence is Ext.P22 scene mahazar. Ext.P22 would show
			<lb />
			that the road lies on North-South direction and the road is
			<lb />
			straight upto 80 metres towards North and 65 metres
			<lb />
			towards South. The width of the road at the place of
			<lb />
			occurrence is 9.30 metres which part of the road has a
			<lb />
			road margin of 4.50 metres on the western and 3 metres
			<lb />
			on the Eastern side. The place of occurrence is at 1.5
			<lb />
			metres on the western tarred end. Relying on Ext.P22
			<lb />
			mahazar as a piece of evidence, the trial court held that
			<lb />
			no explanation was offered by the accused as to how he
			<lb />
			came to the Western side where the width of the road is
			<lb />
			9.30 metres and the road is straight.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			15. In Ext.P22 mahazar PW11 stated that he
			<lb />
			identified the place of occurrence as pointed out by one
			<lb />
			Raimkutty Mohammed Kutty on 20.1.1993 at 3 pm.
			<lb />
			However the said Raimkutty was not examined as witness
			<lb />
			during trial. The trial court mainly accepted the contents
			<lb />
			of scene mahazar as evidence without the evidence to
			<lb />
			prove its contents. The contents of scene mahazar cannot
			<lb />
			be treated as &apos;evidence&apos; to prove any of the facts referred
			<lb />
			to therein unless and until the witness, who pointed out
			<lb />
			the place of occurrence, was examined before the court. A
			<lb />
			learned Single Judge of this Court had an occasion to
			<lb />
			consider this aspect in detail in Mohanan v. State of
			<lb />
			Kerala [2011 (3) KHC 680]. It is clear from Ext.P22
			<lb />
			that the investigating officer identified the place of
			<lb />
			occurrence based on the information furnished by one
			<lb />
			Raimkutty. However, he was not examined to prove the
			<lb />
			facts stated. Hence Ext.P22 cannot be acted upon to enter
			<lb />
			a finding that what are all stated in Ext.P22 are proved
			<lb />
			beyond doubt.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			16. PW3 one of the eye witnesses to the occurrence
			<lb />
			was initially chief-examined before the trial court. He was
			<lb />
			not cross-examined. After remand when summons was
			<lb />
			issued to him, the summons was returned with an
			<lb />
			endorsement that he was no more. Section 33 of the
			<lb />
			Evidence Act deals with statements of persons who cannot
			<lb />
			be called as witnesses. A reading of Section 33 of the
			<lb />
			Evidence Act shows that the evidence in earlier
			<lb />
			proceedings would be relevant in subsequent proceedings
			<lb />
			if the ingredients of the proviso were complied with. Those
			<lb />
			ingredients are:-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			(i) that the earlier proceedings were between
			<lb />
			the same parties or their predecessor-in-
			<lb />
			interest.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii) that the averse party in the first
			<lb />
			proceeding had the right and opportunity
			<lb />
			to cross-examine, and
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) that the question in issue was substantially
			<lb />
			the same in the first as in the second
			<lb />
			proceeding.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			17. One of the requirements for application of
			<lb />
			Section 33 of the Evidence Act is that the adverse party in
			<lb />
			a proceeding should have the right and opportunity to
			<lb />
			cross-examine. In the case on hand, the evidence was
			<lb />
			recorded in chief. However, the witness was not cross-
			<lb />
			examined. If opportunity for cross-examination was
			<lb />
			offered, but the party did not avail himself of the right and
			<lb />
			opportunity, the deposition would be clearly admissible. In
			<lb />
			the case on hand, such an opportunity was not given.
			<lb />
			Evidence given by a witness in a previous judicial
			<lb />
			proceeding or in a later stage of the same judicial
			<lb />
			proceeding, when the witness is dead, is relevant for the
			<lb />
			purpose of proving the matter, provided the witness
			<lb />
			examined by the prosecution was subjected to cross-
			<lb />
			examination. Hence, the evidence adduced by PW3 cannot
			<lb />
			be relied on to enter a finding that the accused drove the
			<lb />
			offending vehicle in a rash and negligent manner.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			18. On going through the oral evidence of PWs.1
			<lb />
			and 2, there is nothing to indicate that the accused was
			<lb />
			driving the vehicle at a speed which would justify holding
			<lb />
			that he was driving the vehicle rashly and negligently. No
			<lb />
			tyre mark was noticed in Ext.P22 mahazar to prove that,
			<lb />
			the offending vehicle, hit against the vehicle involved in
			<lb />
			the accident, had deviated from its path as alleged by the
			<lb />
			prosecution. There is no evidence in this case to hold that
			<lb />
			the death of the two persons was direct result of the rash
			<lb />
			or negligent act of the accused. When driving leads to an
			<lb />
			accident, the main question is whether it was rash and
			<lb />
			negligent. But in deciding this, the speed alone is not the
			<lb />
			only criteria. The width of the road, density of traffic, an
			<lb />
			attempt to overtake, tyre marks are also criterion. In this
			<lb />
			case, as stated earlier, Ext.P22 is inadmissible in evidence.
			<lb />
			PWs.1 and 2 have not adduced any evidence to locate the
			<lb />
			place of occurrence specifically. The width of the road is
			<lb />
			not proved. Tyre marks are not proved. The mere
			<lb />
			allegation that the vehicle was driven in a high speed is
			<lb />
			not enough to prove criminal rashness or criminal
			<lb />
			negligence to prove the occurrence.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			19. When there is glaring defect in the procedure
			<lb />
			and manifest error on a point of law, the findings are
			<lb />
			liable to be revised in revision. Hence the conviction and
			<lb />
			sentence imposed by the two courts below are liable to be
			<lb />
			set aside.
			<lb />
			Resultantly, the criminal revision petition is allowed.
			<lb />
			The revision petitioner/accused is found not guilty of the
			<lb />
			offences under Sections 279, 337, 338 and 304A of the
			<lb />
			IPC and he is acquitted thereunder. Cancelling his bail
			<lb />
			bond, this Court directs that he be set at liberty. If any
			<lb />
			fine amount is deposited by the revision petitioner/
			<lb />
			accused during the pendency of this revision, pursuant to
			<lb />
			an interim order passed by this Court, the same shall be
			<lb />
			refunded to the revision petitioner/accused in accordance
			<lb />
			with rules. Pending applications, if any, stand disposed of.
			<lb />
			Sd/-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			N.ANIL KUMAR,
			<lb />
			JUDGE
			<lb />
			skj
		</p>


	</text>
</tei>