<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<head>
			J U D G M E N T
			<lb />
			T.S. THAKUR, CJI.
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			1. &quot;Change&quot; it is famously said is all that is
			<lb />
			constant in the world.
			<lb />
			And yet the world hates
			<lb />
			change, no matter, it is only change that has
			<lb />
			brought progress for mankind.
			<lb />
			Statesmen, Scholars
			<lb />
			and Scientists have spoken for change and eulogised
			<lb />
			its significance. For instance Charles Darwin has
			<lb />
			spoken of &apos;change&apos; in the context of his theory of
			<lb />
			evolution and declared &quot;It is not the strongest of
			<lb />
			the species that survive, not the most intelligent,
			<lb />
			but the one most responsive to change.&quot; Benjamin
			<lb />
			Franklin, put it more pithily when he said &quot;When
			<lb />
			you&apos;re finished changing, you&apos;re finished&quot;.
			<lb />
			Albert
			<lb />
			Einstein spoke of change when he said &quot;The world as
			<lb />
			we have created is a process of our thinking.
			<lb />
			It
			<lb />
			cannot be changed without changing our thinking.&quot;
			<lb />
			The truth is that resistance to change stems partly
			<lb />
			from people getting used to status quo and partly
			<lb />
			because any change is perceived to affect their
			<lb />
			vested interest in terms of loss of ego, status,
			<lb />
			power or resources. This is true particularly when
			<lb />
			the suggested change is structural or organizational
			<lb />
			which involves some threat, real or perceived, of
			<lb />
			personal loss to those involved.
			<lb />
			No wonder,
			<lb />
			therefore, that the portents of change which the
			<lb />
			recommendations made by the Committee appointed by
			<lb />
			this
			<lb />
			Court
			<lb />
			symbolizes
			<lb />
			are
			<lb />
			encountering
			<lb />
			stiff
			<lb />
			resistance from several quarters interested in
			<lb />
			continuance of the status quo. The fact that the
			<lb />
			recommendations for change come from a body whose
			<lb />
			objectivity, fairness, sense of justice, equity and
			<lb />
			understanding of the problems that are crying for a
			<lb />
			solution are beyond any doubt or suspicion has made
			<lb />
			little or no difference to those opposing the
			<lb />
			recommendation.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			2. These proceedings are a sequel to our order
			<lb />
			dated
			<lb />
			22 nd
			<lb />
			January,
			<lb />
			2015
			<lb />
			[BCCI
			<lb />
			vs.
			<lb />
			Cricket
			<lb />
			Association of Bihar and Ors., (2015) 3 SCC 251]. We
			<lb />
			had by that order answered seven distinct questions
			<lb />
			formulated in para 20 thereof.
			<lb />
			Six out of those
			<lb />
			questions related to allegations of sporting fraud,
			<lb />
			conflict of interest leveled against functionaries
			<lb />
			of the BCCI and the jurisdiction of a writ court to
			<lb />
			intervene
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			issue
			<lb />
			directions
			<lb />
			considered
			<lb />
			appropriate in the circumstances. This Court held
			<lb />
			that even when the Board of Control for Cricket in
			<lb />
			India was not &quot;State&quot; within the meaning of Article
			<lb />
			12, it was amenable to the writ jurisdiction of the
			<lb />
			Court under Article 226 of the Constitution of India
			<lb />
			as it was discharging important public functions.
			<lb />
			Building further on that finding, this Court had
			<lb />
			while dealing with Question No.7 set up a Committee
			<lb />
			comprising Justice R.M. Lodha, former Chief Justice
			<lb />
			of India as Chairman with Justice Ashok Bhan and
			<lb />
			Justice R.V. Raveendran, former Judges of this Court
			<lb />
			as members to determine and award punishment
			<lb />
			considered appropriate on those found guilty by
			<lb />
			Justice Mudgal&apos;s Committee and to examine for any
			<lb />
			disciplinary or punitive action, the role played by
			<lb />
			Mr. Sundar Raman with the help of the investigating
			<lb />
			team constituted for that purpose. More importantly
			<lb />
			we had requested the Committee to examine and make
			<lb />
			suitable recommendations on the following aspects:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			119.1. Amendments considered necessary to the
			<lb />
			memorandum of association of BCCI and the
			<lb />
			prevalent
			<lb />
			rules
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			regulations
			<lb />
			for
			<lb />
			streamlining the conduct of elections to
			<lb />
			different posts/officers in BCCI including
			<lb />
			conditions
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			eligibility
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			disqualifications, if any, for candidates
			<lb />
			wanting to contest the election for such posts
			<lb />
			including the office of the President of BCCI.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			119.2.
			<lb />
			Amendments
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			memorandum
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			association,
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			rules
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			regulations
			<lb />
			considered necessary to provide a mechanism
			<lb />
			for resolving conflict of
			<lb />
			interest should
			<lb />
			such a conflict
			<lb />
			arise despite Rule 6.2.4
			<lb />
			prohibiting
			<lb />
			creation
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			holding
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			any
			<lb />
			commercial interest by the administrators,
			<lb />
			with particular reference to persons, who by
			<lb />
			virtue of their proficiency in the game of
			<lb />
			cricket, were to necessarily play some roles
			<lb />
			as coaches, managers, commentators, etc.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			119.3. Amendment, if any, to the memorandum of
			<lb />
			association and the rules and regulations of
			<lb />
			BCCI to carry out the recommendations of the
			<lb />
			Probe Committee headed by Justice Mudgal,
			<lb />
			subject to such recommendations being found
			<lb />
			acceptable by the newly appointed committee.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			119.4.
			<lb />
			Any
			<lb />
			other
			<lb />
			recommendation
			<lb />
			with
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			without suitable amendment of the relevant
			<lb />
			rules and regulations, which the committee may
			<lb />
			consider necessary to make with a view to
			<lb />
			preventing
			<lb />
			sporting
			<lb />
			frauds,
			<lb />
			conflict
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			interests, streamlining the working of BCCI to
			<lb />
			make it more responsive to the expectations of
			<lb />
			the public at large and to bring transparency
			<lb />
			in practices and procedures followed by BCCI.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			3. The Committee accordingly heard the individuals
			<lb />
			and the Franchisees found guilty by Mudgal Committee
			<lb />
			and by an order dated 14 th July, 2015 awarded
			<lb />
			punishments considered just and proper.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			Committee also by a separate report dated 18 th
			<lb />
			December, 2015 examined the role of Mr. Sundar Raman
			<lb />
			and exonerated him of the charges levelled against
			<lb />
			him. By a separate report dated 18 th December, 2015,
			<lb />
			the Committee has recommended several steps and
			<lb />
			measures that would in its opinion streamline the
			<lb />
			working of the BCCI and possibly prevent any
			<lb />
			aberrations or controversies in which it has been
			<lb />
			embroiled in the past. We shall presently refer to
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			findings
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			recommendations
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Committee in greater detail, but before we do so, we
			<lb />
			must mention that on receipt of the Committee&apos;s
			<lb />
			report and the recommendations, we had issued notice
			<lb />
			to the parties to give them an opportunity to
			<lb />
			respond to the same.
			<lb />
			The BCCI has, accordingly,
			<lb />
			submitted its reply to the reports and the
			<lb />
			recommendations made therein. In addition, several
			<lb />
			other organizations and individuals have intervened
			<lb />
			to file their responses and objections to the
			<lb />
			reports and the recommendations and raised several
			<lb />
			issues.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			4. At the same time certain other intervenors have
			<lb />
			stoutly supported the report of the Committee and
			<lb />
			the recommendations made therein. For instance,
			<lb />
			intervening applications made by Mr. B.S. Bedi and
			<lb />
			Mr. Kirti Azad, Cricket Association of Pondicherry
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			several
			<lb />
			others
			<lb />
			have
			<lb />
			supported
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			recommendations made by Justice Lodha Committee. The
			<lb />
			recommendations are also supported by the respondent
			<lb />
			Cricket Association of Bihar, who has prayed for
			<lb />
			acceptance of the recommendations and issue of
			<lb />
			directions for appropriate follow up action in
			<lb />
			implementation of the same.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			5 We have heard at considerable length learned
			<lb />
			counsel for the parties and those appearing for the
			<lb />
			intervenors.
			<lb />
			As noticed earlier the task assigned
			<lb />
			to the Committee was to recommend such changes in
			<lb />
			the rules and regulations of BCCI as would in the
			<lb />
			opinion of the Committee safeguard the interest of
			<lb />
			public at large in the sport of cricket, improve the
			<lb />
			ethical standards and discipline in the game,
			<lb />
			streamline and promote efficiency in the management
			<lb />
			of BCCI, provide accessibility and transparency,
			<lb />
			prevent
			<lb />
			conflict
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			interest
			<lb />
			situations
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			eradicate political and commercial interference and
			<lb />
			abuse and create mechanisms for resolution of
			<lb />
			disputes within the BCCI.
			<lb />
			The direction issued by
			<lb />
			this Court for all round reform in the working of
			<lb />
			the BCCI and the conduct of its affairs proceeded
			<lb />
			fundamentally on the juristic foundation that BCCI
			<lb />
			was discharging public functions and is, therefore,
			<lb />
			subject to the rigours of &apos;Public Law&apos; making it
			<lb />
			mandatory for the BCCI to adhere to the principles
			<lb />
			of reasonableness, fairness, accountability and
			<lb />
			transparency.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			6 The
			<lb />
			Committee
			<lb />
			had
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			right
			<lb />
			earnest
			<lb />
			circulated a detailed questionnaire to various
			<lb />
			stakeholders, aficionados and patrons of the game.
			<lb />
			The questionnaire was based on the view taken by
			<lb />
			this Court in the main judgment, the existing rules
			<lb />
			and regulations of the BCCI and various articles and
			<lb />
			news reports which pointed out the flaws and
			<lb />
			loopholes in the cricket administration in this
			<lb />
			country. The questionnaire contained 135 questions
			<lb />
			grouped under 8 distinct heads of areas of concern
			<lb />
			for cricket administration namely (a) Organization,
			<lb />
			structure and relationship (b) Source and extent of
			<lb />
			jurisdiction (c) Offices, committees and elections
			<lb />
			(d) Commercial engagements, contracts and services
			<lb />
			(e) Audit, accounts and finances (f) Player welfare
			<lb />
			and dispute resolution (g) Conflict of interest (h)
			<lb />
			Oversight and transparency.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			7. The Committee conducted over 35 days of sittings
			<lb />
			at Mumbai, Bangalore, Chennai, Kolkata, Hyderabad
			<lb />
			and New Delhi in the process providing ease of
			<lb />
			access to respective representatives from various
			<lb />
			zones and primary Test Centres. The Committee also
			<lb />
			interacted with 75 persons in India including Former
			<lb />
			Captains, International and First Class Players,
			<lb />
			Coaches,
			<lb />
			Managers,
			<lb />
			Administrators,
			<lb />
			Journalists,
			<lb />
			Talent scouts, Authors, Lawyers, Club Owners,
			<lb />
			Selectors and a Former Chief Justice of a High
			<lb />
			Court.
			<lb />
			Suggestions made by those who responded to
			<lb />
			the questionnaire and those who interacted with the
			<lb />
			Committee were summarized.
			<lb />
			The Committee also
			<lb />
			researched media reports, documentaries, published
			<lb />
			material, draft legislations, books and articles,
			<lb />
			apart from several unsolicited missives from Cricket
			<lb />
			fans, local experts and administrators about how
			<lb />
			maladministration was rife in cricket all over the
			<lb />
			country.
			<lb />
			The Committee appears to have received
			<lb />
			complaints of defalcation and siphoning of funds,
			<lb />
			opaqueness in administration, blatant favouritism
			<lb />
			and political interference in almost all State
			<lb />
			Associations, varying only in degree from place to
			<lb />
			place. The Committee prepared a comparative analysis
			<lb />
			of international sports policy and how the same were
			<lb />
			structured in their constitution, electoral process
			<lb />
			and overall management and how measures exist to
			<lb />
			check conflict of interest and enforce ethics.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			8. Based on the interactions held and the responses
			<lb />
			received from various quarters, the Committee
			<lb />
			identified the problem areas in the functioning of
			<lb />
			the BCCI, and upon an in-depth appraisal of the
			<lb />
			material and the interactive sessions held by the
			<lb />
			Committee came to the definite conclusion that BCCI
			<lb />
			has been suffering from many ills that had become
			<lb />
			endemic due to the apathy and involvement of those
			<lb />
			at the helm of the Board&apos;s administration.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			Committee recorded a specific finding that the
			<lb />
			problems faced by the BCCI have been compounded by
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			involvement/association
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			many
			<lb />
			high
			<lb />
			functionaries in the Central and State Governments
			<lb />
			some of whom had remained in charge of the
			<lb />
			administration of the BCCI for several decades. It
			<lb />
			also came to the conclusion that many officials of
			<lb />
			the State Associations were holding power without
			<lb />
			any accountability and transparency by converting
			<lb />
			the Associations into personal fiefdoms.
			<lb />
			It found
			<lb />
			inequities writ large at the high table with some
			<lb />
			States
			<lb />
			over-represented
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			votes,
			<lb />
			tournament
			<lb />
			participation and central funding while others were
			<lb />
			made to wait endlessly in the wings for indefinite
			<lb />
			period until favoured.
			<lb />
			The Committee found that
			<lb />
			policies had been formulated and altered to suit the
			<lb />
			needs of a few powerful individuals and that
			<lb />
			coteries had been formed around them which had
			<lb />
			polarized and compromised independent leadership.
			<lb />
			The Committee regretfully found that those who had
			<lb />
			no such agendas had remained quiet, their silence
			<lb />
			emboldening further malfeasance.
			<lb />
			It found that
			<lb />
			cricket players, who are sport&apos;s biggest drivers,
			<lb />
			had also not been spared from the apathy of the BCCI
			<lb />
			as they were treated less like assets and more like
			<lb />
			employees and subordinates of those governing the
			<lb />
			game.
			<lb />
			The Committee found that the Indian Premier
			<lb />
			League
			<lb />
			(IPL)
			<lb />
			which
			<lb />
			was
			<lb />
			a
			<lb />
			remunerative
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			glamourized
			<lb />
			component
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			India
			<lb />
			had
			<lb />
			unsavoury
			<lb />
			interference at the highest echelons of cricket and
			<lb />
			the overlapping and conflicting interests were not
			<lb />
			only condoned, but those in the management of the
			<lb />
			Board
			<lb />
			had
			<lb />
			made
			<lb />
			ex-post
			<lb />
			facto
			<lb />
			amendments
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			facilitate the same. Having said that the Committee
			<lb />
			did not hesitate to recognise the hardwork of BCCI
			<lb />
			staff members and match officials who had ensured
			<lb />
			that hundreds of matches are organized annually at
			<lb />
			all levels and that updates are provided to keep the
			<lb />
			BCCI fully informed. Charity matches for national
			<lb />
			causes and humanitarian assistance is another area
			<lb />
			in which BCCI has been applauded by the Committee
			<lb />
			while stating that the Committee has consciously
			<lb />
			ensured that no measures are recommended that would
			<lb />
			limit or interfere with the good work being done on
			<lb />
			behalf of the BCCI.
			<lb />
			The report submitted by the
			<lb />
			Committee further indicates that while the Committee
			<lb />
			was still in the process of hearing the concerned,
			<lb />
			the newly elected President of the BCCI had even
			<lb />
			without waiting for the Committee&apos;s report adopted
			<lb />
			and projected the Committee&apos;s views as his roadmap
			<lb />
			for improving the functioning of the BCCI. Some of
			<lb />
			those measures like uploading of the Constitution
			<lb />
			and Bye Laws on the BCCI website, creating a policy
			<lb />
			for
			<lb />
			avoidance
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			Conflict
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			interest
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			appointment of Ombudsman had also been taken.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			Committee, however, found that although these steps
			<lb />
			were in the right direction, the same were neither
			<lb />
			comprehensive nor substantive.
			<lb />
			The need of the
			<lb />
			hour observed the Committee was not of making
			<lb />
			cosmetic changes but those that are fundamental for
			<lb />
			laying proper foundations on which the BCCI could
			<lb />
			function in a professional and transparent manner
			<lb />
			bringing cricket back to its pristine form and
			<lb />
			restoring the confidence of the cricketers and
			<lb />
			lovers of the game alike. The Committee said:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;At a time when the nation&apos;s highest court has
			<lb />
			been compelled to find that the game has
			<lb />
			fallen into disrepute, only extraordinary
			<lb />
			steps will bring it back from this chasm. We
			<lb />
			are conscious that some of our proposals may
			<lb />
			evoke varied responses, but the collective
			<lb />
			conscience of this Committee is clear that
			<lb />
			tough measures are called for to restore
			<lb />
			Indian cricket to its pinnacle of glory.
			<lb />
			Individual interest will have to be sacrificed
			<lb />
			for the sake of the institution, and no
			<lb />
			exigency of convenience or convention shall
			<lb />
			stand in the way of a whole scale structural
			<lb />
			overhaul. The current governance structure of
			<lb />
			the BCCI and its Member Associations is far
			<lb />
			from satisfactory and it needs to be suitably
			<lb />
			restructured.
			<lb />
			Strict terms and tenures have
			<lb />
			to be imposed on administrators, oversight and
			<lb />
			audit of member associations need to be
			<lb />
			carried out, professional management deserves
			<lb />
			to be introduced in the administration of the
			<lb />
			game, all States require an equal say in the
			<lb />
			affairs of the BCCI, financial prudence has to
			<lb />
			be exercised, independent views in Governance
			<lb />
			are imperative and cricketers have to be
			<lb />
			14
			<lb />
			protected and given a free hand in cricketing
			<lb />
			affairs. There also ought to be an Ombudsman,
			<lb />
			an Ethics Officer and an Electoral Officer who
			<lb />
			can provide institutional resolution while
			<lb />
			principles of transparency and conflict of
			<lb />
			interest need to be infused without further
			<lb />
			delay.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The report that follows is the Committee&apos;s
			<lb />
			effort to restore Indian to its deserved
			<lb />
			status by putting in place good governance
			<lb />
			structures and best practices.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			9. In &apos;Chapter One&apos; of its report, the Committee
			<lb />
			dealt with the Structure and Constitution of BCCI,
			<lb />
			identified the problems that arise from their
			<lb />
			current status and the need for reform in the same.
			<lb />
			For
			<lb />
			clarity
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			better
			<lb />
			understanding
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			solutions proposed by the Committee we may gainfully
			<lb />
			extract Chapter One of the Report submitted by it.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;Chapter One: The Structure and Constitution
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			It was nearly 200 years after the British
			<lb />
			first brought cricket to India that its
			<lb />
			governing body was created.
			<lb />
			At a time of
			<lb />
			communal Gymkhanas and the occasional touring
			<lb />
			team from England, the princely families and
			<lb />
			other cricket patrons came together to create
			<lb />
			the Board of Control for Cricket in India,
			<lb />
			which was registered as a not-for-profit
			<lb />
			society in Madras (now Chennai). The BCCI has
			<lb />
			grown from its original composition of less
			<lb />
			than half a dozen provincial members to have
			<lb />
			>
 five times that number representing various
			<lb />
			groups and territorial divisions.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The Structure
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The BCCI at the moment consists of 30
			<lb />
			Full Members some of whom do not field teams,
			<lb />
			while others do not represent any territory.
			<lb />
			Twenty States and one Union Territory are
			<lb />
			included and ten States and six Union
			<lb />
			Territories
			<lb />
			remain
			<lb />
			either
			<lb />
			excluded
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			disenfranchised.
			<lb />
			In addition, officially
			<lb />
			there are Associate and Affiliate Members as
			<lb />
			well as so-called Future Members.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The Services Sports Control Board,
			<lb />
			the Railways Sport Promotion Board and All
			<lb />
			India
			<lb />
			Universities
			<lb />
			represent
			<lb />
			particular
			<lb />
			national service groups, who traditionally
			<lb />
			constituted the largest employers of Indian
			<lb />
			sportsmen before the advent of liberal private
			<lb />
			enterprise. Apart from these, two Clubs -the
			<lb />
			Cricket Club of India at Mumbai and the
			<lb />
			National Cricket Club at Kolkata also enjoy
			<lb />
			full membership of the BCCI.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Problems
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			An
			<lb />
			examination
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			existing
			<lb />
			structure revealed the following anomalies:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			a.
			<lb />
			Not all States are represented on the
			<lb />
			BCCI
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			One old State (Bihar) and two new states
			<lb />
			(Chhattisgarh
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			Uttarakhand)
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			six
			<lb />
			North-Eastern
			<lb />
			States
			<lb />
			(Sikkim,
			<lb />
			Manipur,
			<lb />
			Meghalaya, Nagaland, Arunachal Pradesh and
			<lb />
			Mizoram) are unrepresented on the Board.
			<lb />
			Of
			<lb />
			course, the most significant omission was
			<lb />
			Bihar, which, being the third most populous
			<lb />
			State in the nation required the cricket
			<lb />
			representatives of its 100 million populace to
			<lb />
			migrate to other States to ply their trade.
			<lb />
			Apart
			<lb />
			from
			<lb />
			Tripura,
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			other
			<lb />
			six
			<lb />
			sister-States of the north-east had been
			<lb />
			relegated to various categories of membership
			<lb />
			(Associate, Affiliate and Future) which really
			<lb />
			have no voice on the Board.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			b.
			<lb />
			Some States are over-represented
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Mainly attributable to their historic legacy,
			<lb />
			both Maharashtra and Gujarat have 3 Full
			<lb />
			Members, each representing parts of their
			<lb />
			respective States.
			<lb />
			Maharashtra therefore
			<lb />
			exercises votes through the Associations of
			<lb />
			Mumbai, Vidarbha and Maharashtra while Gujarat
			<lb />
			fields the Associations of Baroda, Gujarat and
			<lb />
			Saurashtra.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			c.
			<lb />
			Some members do not represent territories
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			The
			<lb />
			Services
			<lb />
			Sports
			<lb />
			Control
			<lb />
			Board,
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Railways Sport Promotion Board and All India
			<lb />
			Universities show that territorial divisions
			<lb />
			were not the consistent criteria to determine
			<lb />
			membership of the BCCI.
			<lb />
			However, these
			<lb />
			members were represented by teams that played
			<lb />
			competitive cricket.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			d.
			<lb />
			Some members neither play matches nor
			<lb />
			represent territories
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Both the National Cricket Club (NCC) at
			<lb />
			Kolkata and the Cricket Club of India (CCI) at
			<lb />
			Mumbai were more in the nature of recreation
			<lb />
			clubs
			<lb />
			which
			<lb />
			neither
			<lb />
			fielded
			<lb />
			teams
			<lb />
			for
			<lb />
			tournaments nor had a geographical basis for
			<lb />
			being Full Members of the BCCI. In fact, by
			<lb />
			virtue of CCI being granted full membership,
			<lb />
			Maharashtra has garnered as many as four out
			<lb />
			of the total 30 votes on the Board.
			<lb />
		</item>


		<item>
			e.
			<lb />
			Union Territories are unrepresented on
			<lb />
			the Board
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Except for Delhi which enjoys a special
			<lb />
			position under the Constitution as well, none
			<lb />
			of the other six Union Territories are Full
			<lb />
			Members of the BCCI. In fact, there have been
			<lb />
			repeated
			<lb />
			representations
			<lb />
			by
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Cricket
			<lb />
			Association of Pondicherry that just as Delhi,
			<lb />
			it is also a Union Territory with a Chief
			<lb />
			Minister and ought to be made a Full Member.
			<lb />
			This issue is sub judice before the Madras
			<lb />
			High Court but nonetheless, there seems that
			<lb />
			some artificial distinction exists in the
			<lb />
			extant rules between Delhi and Puducherry.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			f.
			<lb />
			Ad-hoc creation of Membership categories
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The Regulations of the BCCI only speak of
			<lb />
			three categories of members -Full, Associate
			<lb />
			and Affiliate. However, we find that there is
			<lb />
			a list of six &quot;Future Members&quot;, a category
			<lb />
			that does not have a legal basis.
			<lb />
			This
			<lb />
			consists of Uttarakhand, Mizoram, Telangana,
			<lb />
			Chandigarh, Puducherry and Andaman &amp; Nicobar.
			<lb />
			Such a classification seems a half-way house
			<lb />
			with no real purpose except to give the
			<lb />
			association an illusion that it will be
			<lb />
			promoted at some vague point in the future.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			g.
			<lb />
			Arbitrary
			<lb />
			addition
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			removal
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			associations
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			For reasons best known to the BCCI, despite
			<lb />
			being a Full Member, the Rajasthan Cricket
			<lb />
			Association
			<lb />
			has
			<lb />
			been
			<lb />
			treated
			<lb />
			as
			<lb />
			disenfranchised, resulting in the players of
			<lb />
			the State being forced to move elsewhere to
			<lb />
			compete. The non-addition of the Bihar Cricket
			<lb />
			Association or an equivalent has also led to
			<lb />
			such a denial to the players from Bihar.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Solutions
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Almost universally, apart from those who
			<lb />
			represented the associations in Gujarat and
			<lb />
			Maharashtra, the prevalent view was that that
			<lb />
			the State is a fair unit of representation on
			<lb />
			the BCCI.
			<lb />
			On a consideration of the entire
			<lb />
			issue, the Committee is of the view that it is
			<lb />
			not proper for only one or two States to have
			<lb />
			multiple members when all other States have
			<lb />
			single memberships (in fact, while many States
			<lb />
			have no representation).
			<lb />
			Democratic norms
			<lb />
			require
			<lb />
			each
			<lb />
			State
			<lb />
			should
			<lb />
			have
			<lb />
			equal
			<lb />
			representation, and therefore the Committee
			<lb />
			proposes the policy of &apos;One State -One Member
			<lb />
			-One Vote&apos;.
			<lb />
			In fact, this is the policy
			<lb />
			followed by other national sports associations
			<lb />
			(IHF &amp; AIFF), each of whose members have an
			<lb />
			equal vote regardless of size or population.
			<lb />
			Even at the international level (IOC &amp; FIFA),
			<lb />
			this is the position. Cricket ought to be no
			<lb />
			different.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			It was however also stated that as far as
			<lb />
			disbursement of funds by BCCI for cricket
			<lb />
			development, it need not be uniform, but can
			<lb />
			depend on the need, infrastructure and other
			<lb />
			relevant criteria, formalized as a clear and
			<lb />
			equitable policy to incentivize Members to
			<lb />
			develop the sport.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			In keeping with the above principle, and
			<lb />
			notwithstanding any sense of sentiment, there
			<lb />
			would
			<lb />
			also
			<lb />
			be
			<lb />
			no
			<lb />
			place
			<lb />
			for
			<lb />
			multiple
			<lb />
			associations from a single State.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			Committee is of the view that it be left to
			<lb />
			the BCCI to decide which of the 3 associations
			<lb />
			from Gujarat and Maharashtra would be taken to
			<lb />
			represent the entire State, and the remaining
			<lb />
			2 associations from each State would become
			<lb />
			Associate Members, who would however continue
			<lb />
			to field teams for competitions as they have
			<lb />
			done in the past.
			<lb />
			Equally, in States where
			<lb />
			there are disputes concerning the appropriate
			<lb />
			governing body [Jammu &amp; Kashmir, Bihar,
			<lb />
			Rajasthan, etc.], it is best left to the BCCI
			<lb />
			or the Court (as may be the case), to decide
			<lb />
			which association would represent the State.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			As
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Services,
			<lb />
			Railways
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			Universities have hitherto enjoyed Full Member
			<lb />
			rights although they do not represent a
			<lb />
			particular State, the Committee recommends
			<lb />
			that they be accorded the Status of Associate
			<lb />
			Member so that their views may still be
			<lb />
			considered while they will not have voting
			<lb />
			rights. The same principle would apply to the
			<lb />
			Clubs (CCI and NCC), which do not field
			<lb />
			cricket teams and have no cause to be treated
			<lb />
			as Full Members.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Those existing Members who are affected
			<lb />
			by the changes suggested by the Committee must
			<lb />
			appreciate
			<lb />
			that
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			changes
			<lb />
			are
			<lb />
			being
			<lb />
			suggested in the interest of the game as a
			<lb />
			whole and also having regard to BCCI&apos;s role as
			<lb />
			a national body to promote and control cricket
			<lb />
			in India.
			<lb />
			Governance of cricket being the
			<lb />
			central theme, the changes in membership in
			<lb />
			the BCCI are inevitable and must be seen by
			<lb />
			all concerned in the right spirit of fair
			<lb />
			representation and for the betterment of
			<lb />
			cricket administration.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			While there are seven Union Territories,
			<lb />
			it was found that only Delhi and Puducherry
			<lb />
			have a Chief Minister and are treated as
			<lb />
			substantially independent governing entities.
			<lb />
			At first glance, there seems no rationale for
			<lb />
			a distinction between the two, but what cannot
			<lb />
			be denied is the fact that Delhi, apart from
			<lb />
			being the national capital, is also a major
			<lb />
			Test Centre with an international stadium and
			<lb />
			has nearly 20 times the population of
			<lb />
			Puducherry. There may thus be some merit for
			<lb />
			Puducherry not immediately being included as a
			<lb />
			Full Member, especially when the issue is sub
			<lb />
			judice. Among the Union Territories, it would
			<lb />
			however be appropriate for Puducherry to be
			<lb />
			now inducted by the BCCI as an Associate
			<lb />
			Member which will retain rights to field a
			<lb />
			team and compete.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The consequence of the above realignments
			<lb />
			would also have an effect on how the Zones are
			<lb />
			constituted.
			<lb />
			The Zones would consist of
			<lb />
			Members in such a manner that each of them
			<lb />
			would be reasonably balanced as far as
			<lb />
			competition for the various zonal tournaments
			<lb />
			is concerned. However, this reconstitution is
			<lb />
			best left to the BCCI for the purposes of
			<lb />
			convenience and competition. It is also left
			<lb />
			to the discretion of the BCCI whether the
			<lb />
			Union Territories would field individual or
			<lb />
			combined teams for tournaments and whether,
			<lb />
			for
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			purposes
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			expediency
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			convenience, the teams representing the States
			<lb />
			of the North-East be combined as well.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The categories of Affiliate and Future
			<lb />
			Members are therefore to be removed, and only
			<lb />
			Full Members and Associate Members will
			<lb />
			remain, the former with voting rights and the
			<lb />
			latter without.
			<lb />
			The 4 associations from the
			<lb />
			States of Maharashtra and Gujarat which would
			<lb />
			be relegated to the category of Associate
			<lb />
			Members shall, however, continue to receive
			<lb />
			grants for cricket development, as may be
			<lb />
			assessed
			<lb />
			by
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			BCCI
			<lb />
			depending
			<lb />
			on
			<lb />
			infrastructure and relevant criteria.
			<lb />
			They
			<lb />
			will also field teams in the domestic
			<lb />
			tournaments and host international matches.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			It is imperative that all players across
			<lb />
			the country have opportunities to represent
			<lb />
			their States and Zones and then the national
			<lb />
			team.
			<lb />
			To punish the innocent residents and
			<lb />
			players of a State for the real or perceived
			<lb />
			shortcoming of the Member Association is
			<lb />
			illogical and unacceptable.
			<lb />
			Even if an
			<lb />
			alternate
			<lb />
			Association
			<lb />
			is
			<lb />
			not
			<lb />
			readily
			<lb />
			available, BCCI should function as the parens
			<lb />
			patriae of Indian cricket and continue to
			<lb />
			provide equal and alternate avenues for that
			<lb />
			particular State. The Model Memorandum of
			<lb />
			Association and Rules &amp; Regulations of BCCI
			<lb />
			are at ANNEXURE-A&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			10. In Annexure-A to the report, the Committee has
			<lb />
			proposed Model Memorandum of Association and Rules &amp;
			<lb />
			Regulations of the BCCI which not only sets out the
			<lb />
			objects and purposes of the BCCI with commendable
			<lb />
			clarity but also the Rules and Regulations governing
			<lb />
			its affairs. It is noteworthy that neither the BCCI
			<lb />
			nor the interveners have found fault with the
			<lb />
			revised Memorandum of Association as proposed by the
			<lb />
			Committee. What has come under attack both from the
			<lb />
			BCCI
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			intervenors,
			<lb />
			aggrieved
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			recommendations are the Rules and Regulations
			<lb />
			proposed by the Committee.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			11. Rule 3 of the proposed Rules and Regulations
			<lb />
			which deals with Membership and Jurisdiction of
			<lb />
			Members, inter alia, provides that Membership of the
			<lb />
			Board shall be confined to Full Members and
			<lb />
			Associate Members.
			<lb />
			It further provides that each
			<lb />
			State shall be represented by a State Cricket
			<lb />
			Association duly recognized by the BCCI and that
			<lb />
			such associations shall be Full Members.
			<lb />
			No State
			<lb />
			shall have more than one Full Member according to
			<lb />
			Rule 3 of the proposed Rules.
			<lb />
			Rule 3-B enumerates
			<lb />
			30 States in the country including Delhi and Goa as
			<lb />
			Full Members of the BCCI.
			<lb />
			Rule 3-C provides for
			<lb />
			recognition of only one Member out of multiple
			<lb />
			Existing Members for a State while proposing to
			<lb />
			convert the remaining as Associate Members.
			<lb />
			Rule
			<lb />
			3-C reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;3-C.
			<lb />
			In
			<lb />
			states
			<lb />
			with
			<lb />
			multiple
			<lb />
			Existing
			<lb />
			Members, the BCCI shall recognize one of them
			<lb />
			to represent the State, while the remaining
			<lb />
			shall become Associate Members.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			12. Equally important is the Rule 3(b)(1) which
			<lb />
			enumerates grounds for sanction and de-recognition
			<lb />
			of a Full Member and reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;3 (b) Grounds for sanction and derecognition
			<lb />
			of a Full Member
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(1)
			<lb />
			No Member shall be entitled to any grant
			<lb />
			from the BCCI if its Constitution fails to
			<lb />
			provide for, or comply with the following
			<lb />
			within One year after the Effective Date:
			<lb />
		</item>


		<item>
			(i) The Association shall not have any
			<lb />
			provision for any post to be held for more
			<lb />
			than 9 years.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii) The governing body of the Association
			<lb />
			shall include representatives of players and
			<lb />
			women, and a nominee of the Accountant General
			<lb />
			of the State.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) The Association shall grant automatic
			<lb />
			membership to former international players
			<lb />
			hailing from the State.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iv) The Association shall not have proxy
			<lb />
			voting.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(v) There shall be a provision whereby the
			<lb />
			Office Bearers of the Association stand
			<lb />
			disqualified under any of the grounds laid
			<lb />
			down in Rule 14(3) below.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(vi)
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			Association
			<lb />
			shall
			<lb />
			appoint
			<lb />
			an
			<lb />
			Electoral Officer, an Ethics Officer and an
			<lb />
			Ombudsman.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(vii) The Association shall abide by the
			<lb />
			principles of Transparency laid down in
			<lb />
			Chapter 8 of these Rules.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			13. Rule 4 stipulates that each Full Member shall
			<lb />
			have one vote to be exercised through its authorized
			<lb />
			representative and that an Associate Member shall be
			<lb />
			entitled to participate in the General Body Meetings
			<lb />
			but shall not be entitled either to vote or have its
			<lb />
			representative elected to the Apex Council.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			14. In terms of Rule 3(b)(1)(v) (supra), a person
			<lb />
			shall be disqualified to be an Office Bearer of any
			<lb />
			association on the grounds set out under Rule 14(3)
			<lb />
			which reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;14. THE APEX COUNCIL
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(3)
			<lb />
			A person shall be disqualified from
			<lb />
			being a Councillor if he or she:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a) Is not a citizen of India;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b) Has attained the age of 70 years;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(c) Is declared to be insolvent, or of
			<lb />
			unsound mind;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(d) Is a Minister or a government servant
			<lb />
			[except for the nominee under Rule 14(2)
			<lb />
			(c)];
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(e) Holds any office or post in a sports
			<lb />
			or athletic association or federation
			<lb />
			apart from cricket;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(f) Has been an Office Bearer of the BCCI
			<lb />
			for a cumulative period of 9 years;&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			15. In Chapter Two of the Report the Committee has
			<lb />
			examined the composition of the office bearers of
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			25
			<lb />
			the BCCI and held that those at the helm of the
			<lb />
			game come from a mixed milieu -some are patrons
			<lb />
			seeking to promote the sport, while others seek to
			<lb />
			promote themselves, with no particular attention
			<lb />
			being paid to cricket itself.
			<lb />
			The Committee takes
			<lb />
			the view that cricket, with its popularity and its
			<lb />
			finances ought to be run professionally.
			<lb />
			Towards
			<lb />
			that end, the Committee considers it imperative
			<lb />
			that a strong governance structure is put in place,
			<lb />
			which will be at arm&apos;s length from the actual
			<lb />
			day-to-day management of the Associations and the
			<lb />
			game.
			<lb />
			The Committee has recorded a finding that
			<lb />
			with an individual-centric constitution the reins
			<lb />
			of cricket&apos;s richest and arguably most powerful
			<lb />
			national body remains mired in controversy and
			<lb />
			seems to have strayed from its chosen path.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			16. The Committee takes the view that BCCI finds it
			<lb />
			difficult to control and manage the IPL and its
			<lb />
			most successful venture threatens its existence in
			<lb />
			its present form. There seems to be no collective
			<lb />
			26
			<lb />
			Page 27
			<lb />
			interest in the game being promoted and cricket
			<lb />
			stands without a custodian for its protection and
			<lb />
			propagation in its most passionately followed
			<lb />
			nation.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			17. The Committee then identifies the problems
			<lb />
			under different headings and suggests solutions for
			<lb />
			the same in the following words:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			a. Concentration of power
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			From overall superintendence of the Board
			<lb />
			and its affairs to taking action against
			<lb />
			players and even approving the composition
			<lb />
			of the team chosen by the Selectors, the
			<lb />
			President is all-powerful. In practice,
			<lb />
			this power was even abused with the
			<lb />
			exercise of veto over the changes in
			<lb />
			captaincy
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			selection
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			ICC
			<lb />
			representatives.
			<lb />
			Incumbents
			<lb />
			were
			<lb />
			also
			<lb />
			known to turn a blind eye when issues of
			<lb />
			corruption and mismanagement were brought
			<lb />
			to their notice, even going as far as
			<lb />
			permitting retrospective amendments to the
			<lb />
			bye-laws to favour particular interests.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			b. Lack of competence
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The running of an organisation like the
			<lb />
			BCCI
			<lb />
			requires
			<lb />
			a
			<lb />
			clear
			<lb />
			functioning
			<lb />
			structure with well defined ideas to be
			<lb />
			executed. The present Working Committee of
			<lb />
			the BCCI consisting of the various office
			<lb />
			bearers elected by the BCCI and other
			<lb />
			representatives of the Members do not have
			<lb />
			any managerial expertise and requisite
			<lb />
			experience to run BCCI in a professional
			<lb />
			manner. Specialists and professionals are
			<lb />
			usually
			<lb />
			engaged
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			an
			<lb />
			ad-hoc
			<lb />
			manner
			<lb />
			without any terms and tenures as would be
			<lb />
			expected with any billion dollar entity.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			c. Overlap of diverse functions
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			To
			<lb />
			borrow
			<lb />
			an
			<lb />
			analogy
			<lb />
			from
			<lb />
			political
			<lb />
			governance, it is necessary that the
			<lb />
			making
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			laws
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			regulations
			<lb />
			(legislative functions) are divorced from
			<lb />
			implementation
			<lb />
			thereof
			<lb />
			(executive
			<lb />
			functions) and those that review their
			<lb />
			validity
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			implementation
			<lb />
			(judicial
			<lb />
			functions).
			<lb />
			As
			<lb />
			far
			<lb />
			as
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			BCCI
			<lb />
			is
			<lb />
			concerned, the Working Committee not only
			<lb />
			lays down the relevant rules, regulations
			<lb />
			and bye-laws that govern the BCCI, but
			<lb />
			also oversee their implementation and
			<lb />
			takes final decisions when a Member or
			<lb />
			third party challenges either the rule or
			<lb />
			the manner of its implementation. These
			<lb />
			overlaps provide for extremely complicated
			<lb />
			and messy functioning.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			d. Zonal considerations
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			There seems to be no rational basis for
			<lb />
			the Presidency to be rotated as per Zones,
			<lb />
			which has the effect of forsaking merit. A
			<lb />
			person who has the support of as few as
			<lb />
			two or three members in his Zone may end
			<lb />
			up as the President, if it is the turn of
			<lb />
			that Zone for election of President.
			<lb />
			Recent
			<lb />
			amendments
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			rules
			<lb />
			have
			<lb />
			permitted individuals who are not even
			<lb />
			from the zone in question to be nominated
			<lb />
			to the post. For the same reason, the
			<lb />
			Vice-Presidents who are elected from each
			<lb />
			of the five zones seem to be merely
			<lb />
			ornamental without any specific functions.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			e. No representation to players
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			It is only by accident that players are
			<lb />
			elected to the Working Committee of the
			<lb />
			BCCI. Their views are, more often than
			<lb />
			not, ignored, and the lack of an assured
			<lb />
			position at the governance table leaves
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			players
			<lb />
			gravely
			<lb />
			hamstrung.
			<lb />
			With
			<lb />
			arbitrary contracts and salaries that are
			<lb />
			dwarfed by those playing for franchises,
			<lb />
			it is full credit to the national players
			<lb />
			that they continue with enthusiasm and
			<lb />
			patriotic fervour to do their best for the
			<lb />
			country when they have no say in the
			<lb />
			affairs of the very body towards which
			<lb />
			they are the primary contributors.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			f. No representation to women
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The BCCI has never seen a woman in the
			<lb />
			Working Committee, and for a body that
			<lb />
			runs the sport in the country, the BCCI
			<lb />
			ought to have bestowed greater attention
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			women&apos;s
			<lb />
			game.
			<lb />
			Australia,
			<lb />
			New
			<lb />
			Zealand, England and even Pakistan are
			<lb />
			seen to regularly play the women&apos;s game
			<lb />
			with only governance apathy responsible
			<lb />
			for the Indian women&apos;s team playing few
			<lb />
			and far between in all forms of the game.
			<lb />
			Greater support and promotion is required
			<lb />
			so that youngsters may also be attracted
			<lb />
			to it.
			<lb />
		</item>


		<item>
			g. No independent voice
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The BCCI has not embraced the modern
			<lb />
			principles of open governance, which is
			<lb />
			all the more necessary when discharging
			<lb />
			such far reaching public functions. The
			<lb />
			Working Committee consists entirely of
			<lb />
			representatives
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Full
			<lb />
			Members,
			<lb />
			thereby
			<lb />
			making
			<lb />
			it&apos;s
			<lb />
			functioning
			<lb />
			a
			<lb />
			closed-door affair with no representation
			<lb />
			of players or audit experts to act as
			<lb />
			checks on governance.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			h. Unlimited terms and tenures
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Many individuals occupy various posts in
			<lb />
			the BCCI for multiple terms and on
			<lb />
			multiple occasions, without any ceiling
			<lb />
			limit. There has even been an instance of
			<lb />
			a former President later becoming the
			<lb />
			Treasurer.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			i. No disqualifications
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			There appears to be no ground on which an
			<lb />
			office bearer has to demit office. No
			<lb />
			principles of conflict of interest, of
			<lb />
			age, of conviction by a criminal court or
			<lb />
			of holding an office under the Government
			<lb />
			has been laid down to disqualify an office
			<lb />
			bearer.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Solutions
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The governance of the BCCI must be
			<lb />
			decentralised.
			<lb />
			No individual is more
			<lb />
			important than the institution, and so all
			<lb />
			crucial powers and functions hitherto
			<lb />
			bestowed exclusively on the President will
			<lb />
			have to be divided across the governing
			<lb />
			body, which is to be known as the Apex
			<lb />
			Council (with a special and separate
			<lb />
			governing body for IPL, known as IPL
			<lb />
			Governing Council).
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The issue of competence regarding
			<lb />
			those
			<lb />
			managing
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			game
			<lb />
			has
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			be
			<lb />
			addressed by bringing in professional
			<lb />
			managers and area experts, a theme which
			<lb />
			is discussed in detail in Chapter three.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			As the zonal rotation policy is
			<lb />
			without any rational basis, and as it has
			<lb />
			been decided to keep the State as the unit
			<lb />
			to become a Full Member, it is consistent
			<lb />
			to have a president who is elected from
			<lb />
			among the Full Members, so that the best
			<lb />
			and most competent person is selected. The
			<lb />
			provision for five Vice-Presidents is
			<lb />
			detrimental to efficiency and efficacy and
			<lb />
			so
			<lb />
			only
			<lb />
			one
			<lb />
			Vice-President
			<lb />
			shall
			<lb />
			be
			<lb />
			elected to the Apex Council in the same
			<lb />
			manner as the Secretary, Joint Secretary
			<lb />
			and Treasurer.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The Apex Council should have a fair
			<lb />
			mix
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			elected
			<lb />
			representatives
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			independent members.
			<lb />
			It is recommended
			<lb />
			that it shall be a nine-member body. The
			<lb />
			five
			<lb />
			elected
			<lb />
			Office
			<lb />
			Bearers
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			BCCI
			<lb />
			(President,
			<lb />
			Vice-President,
			<lb />
			Secretary,
			<lb />
			Joint Secretary and Treasurer) shall be
			<lb />
			the members of the Apex Council. In
			<lb />
			addition, the Apex Council shall have four
			<lb />
			other &apos;Councillors&apos; -two (one male, one
			<lb />
			female) to be nominated by the Players&apos;
			<lb />
			Association which is to be formed, one to
			<lb />
			be elected by the Full Members of BCCI
			<lb />
			from amongst themselves and one to be
			<lb />
			nominated by the Comptroller &amp; Auditor
			<lb />
			General of India. These measures address
			<lb />
			the following concerns:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			a.
			<lb />
			Transparency
			<lb />
			is
			<lb />
			brought
			<lb />
			in,
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			independent
			<lb />
			voices
			<lb />
			are
			<lb />
			heard
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			governance of the BCCI for the first time;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			b The
			<lb />
			public
			<lb />
			are
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			primary
			<lb />
			stakeholders in the game while its players
			<lb />
			form its very core. Their involvement
			<lb />
			through these representatives is most
			<lb />
			deserving and long awaited.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			c.
			<lb />
			As
			<lb />
			women
			<lb />
			are
			<lb />
			nearly
			<lb />
			half
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			population of the country, the anomalous
			<lb />
			fact that they do not have a voice in the
			<lb />
			governance of the sport that has a
			<lb />
			&apos;billion hearts&apos; beating for it is now
			<lb />
			rectified.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			d.
			<lb />
			The nominee of the C&amp;AG also brings
			<lb />
			financial and audit experience which would
			<lb />
			bring in much required oversight into
			<lb />
			monitoring the finances of the BCCI.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			e.
			<lb />
			It continues to ensure a strong say
			<lb />
			for the Full Members, as it provides that
			<lb />
			two-thirds&apos; strength on the Council is
			<lb />
			made up of their representatives.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			In order to ensure that the posts are
			<lb />
			not treated as permanent positions of
			<lb />
			power, each term should be for three
			<lb />
			years.
			<lb />
			The total period for which a
			<lb />
			person can be a member of the Apex Council
			<lb />
			shall be nine years regardless of the
			<lb />
			capacity in which such position was or is
			<lb />
			occupied. However, in order to ensure that
			<lb />
			there
			<lb />
			is
			<lb />
			an
			<lb />
			appropriate
			<lb />
			cooling-off
			<lb />
			period, no person shall be a member of the
			<lb />
			Apex Council for two consecutive terms.
			<lb />
			Any
			<lb />
			elected
			<lb />
			Councillor
			<lb />
			shall
			<lb />
			stand
			<lb />
			automatically
			<lb />
			disqualified
			<lb />
			after
			<lb />
			nine
			<lb />
			ce bearer, and shall also
			<lb />
			be disqualified from contesting or holding
			<lb />
			the post if he has completed the age of 70
			<lb />
			years, is charged under the penal law, is
			<lb />
			declared to be of unsound mind, is a
			<lb />
			Minister or government servant or holds
			<lb />
			any post of another sports body in the
			<lb />
			country. Any nominated Councillor however,
			<lb />
			would not have more than one term in
			<lb />
			office. The endeavour in this regard is to
			<lb />
			filter those who are able and enthusiastic
			<lb />
			to govern the game that is the national
			<lb />
			passion.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			18. In Chapter three of its report the Committee
			<lb />
			has examined BCCI&apos;s need for reform in its
			<lb />
			cricketing and non cricketing management with the
			<lb />
			help of full time professionals with established
			<lb />
			skill-sets
			<lb />
			reporting
			<lb />
			systems,
			<lb />
			high-level
			<lb />
			IT
			<lb />
			solutions etc. The Committee has recommended that
			<lb />
			non-cricketing management ought to be handled by
			<lb />
			professional managers headed by a Chief Executive
			<lb />
			Officer at the top.
			<lb />
			Pure cricketing matters like
			<lb />
			selection, coaching and performance evaluation
			<lb />
			could however be left exclusively to ex players who
			<lb />
			have greater domain knowledge.
			<lb />
			In so far as
			<lb />
			umpiring is concerned the same could be handled
			<lb />
			exclusively by umpires.
			<lb />
			The Committee has with
			<lb />
			that objective recommended the following structure
			<lb />
			in place of the current management which is ill
			<lb />
			equipped to deal with issues of cricketing and
			<lb />
			non-cricketing
			<lb />
			management,
			<lb />
			thereby,
			<lb />
			adversely
			<lb />
			affecting its performance.
			<lb />
			The flow chart of the
			<lb />
			Management structure recommended by the Committee
			<lb />
			is as under:
			<lb />
		</p>


		<p>
			19. The
			<lb />
			Committee
			<lb />
			has
			<lb />
			out
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			existing
			<lb />
			Committees recommended the continuance of two
			<lb />
			standing Committees namely; (1) Senior Tournaments
			<lb />
			Committee and the (2) Tours, Fixtures and Technical
			<lb />
			Committee for the purpose of providing guidance and
			<lb />
			advice to the CEO and his Managers.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			20. In Chapter four of the report the Committee has
			<lb />
			discussed matters relating to Indian Premier League
			<lb />
			and recommended that the franchisee companies who
			<lb />
			are responsible for fostering competition and making
			<lb />
			revenues deserve to be given a role in the
			<lb />
			governance of the IPL.
			<lb />
			The Committee has opined
			<lb />
			that the IPL Governing Council needs to be
			<lb />
			reconstituted with more autonomy, comprising not
			<lb />
			only representatives of the Full Members, but also
			<lb />
			of Franchisees, Players and an independent auditor.
			<lb />
			In addition the Committee has recommended that the
			<lb />
			Committee/ Commission to be appointed under the IPL
			<lb />
			Regulations (Anti Corruption Code, Code of Conduct,
			<lb />
			Operational Rules, etc.) ought to consist of members
			<lb />
			selected by a panel of the Ombudsman, the Ethics
			<lb />
			Officer and the CEO which shall be presided over by
			<lb />
			the Ombudsman thereby ensuring independence from the
			<lb />
			BCCI.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			21. Chapter five of the report recommends two
			<lb />
			initiatives viz. (i) An Association of Players and
			<lb />
			(ii) a strict set of procedures to govern players&apos;
			<lb />
			Agents.
			<lb />
			The Committee notes that while almost all
			<lb />
			Test playing nations have a Players&apos; Association,
			<lb />
			there has been some reluctance on the part of the
			<lb />
			BCCI to initiate such a move, ostensibly due to the
			<lb />
			apprehension
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			unionisation.
			<lb />
			Similarly,
			<lb />
			both
			<lb />
			England and Australia have agents&apos; accreditation
			<lb />
			systems in place to ensure that only those
			<lb />
			professionals
			<lb />
			who
			<lb />
			qualify
			<lb />
			through
			<lb />
			a
			<lb />
			rigorous
			<lb />
			knowledge
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			ethics
			<lb />
			selection
			<lb />
			process
			<lb />
			alone
			<lb />
			represent
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			players.
			<lb />
			These
			<lb />
			systems
			<lb />
			are
			<lb />
			administered by the National Board in conjunction
			<lb />
			with the respective Players&apos; Associations.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			Committee accordingly recommends setting up of a
			<lb />
			Players&apos; Association with a Steering Committee
			<lb />
			comprising four persons named in the Report. It has
			<lb />
			also proposed norms for agent&apos;s registration to be
			<lb />
			administered by BCCI in consultation with the
			<lb />
			Cricket Players&apos; Association.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			22. In Chapter six the Committee deals with Conflict
			<lb />
			of Interest and Issues Central to the Regulation of
			<lb />
			Ethical Conduct in sport.
			<lb />
			The Committee has spelt
			<lb />
			out specific types of Conflict of Interest, and
			<lb />
			applied them to individuals employed with, or
			<lb />
			connected to the BCCI with the recommendation that
			<lb />
			every Office Bearer, Player, Councillor, Employee,
			<lb />
			Administrator, Team Official, Umpire or other person
			<lb />
			connected to the BCCI, its Members or the IPL and
			<lb />
			its Franchisees is mandated to avoid any act or
			<lb />
			omission which is, or is perceived to be, likely to
			<lb />
			bring the interest of the individual in conflict
			<lb />
			with the interest of the game of cricket.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			23. In Chapter Seven, the Committee has dealt with
			<lb />
			need for Ombudsman, Ethics and Electoral Officer.
			<lb />
			The Committee notes that several disputes that exist
			<lb />
			within the BCCI are born out of years of apathy in
			<lb />
			governance and gross mismanagement.
			<lb />
			The Committee
			<lb />
			has
			<lb />
			found
			<lb />
			that
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			relationship
			<lb />
			between
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Associations, on the one hand, and the BCCI, on the
			<lb />
			other, has rarely been equitable and balanced, with
			<lb />
			the latter exercising its hegemony over the former.
			<lb />
			The Committee has therefore recommended moderation
			<lb />
			of such relationship in an objective manner. The
			<lb />
			Committee
			<lb />
			has
			<lb />
			referred
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			problems
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			disgruntlement and litigation in the States of
			<lb />
			Bihar, Rajasthan, Delhi and Jammu and Kashmir. The
			<lb />
			Committee has found that absence of suitable dispute
			<lb />
			resolution mechanism has compounded the situation.
			<lb />
			Even the arbitration system that has hitherto
			<lb />
			existed has been found to be insufficient and
			<lb />
			palpably inappropriate when two unequals are pitted
			<lb />
			against each other, especially with the State
			<lb />
			associations remaining beholden to the Board for
			<lb />
			>
 matches, grants and revenues.
			<lb />
			In order to reduce
			<lb />
			the judicial role and the burdening of the courts
			<lb />
			and to expedite dispute resolution, the Committee
			<lb />
			has recommended the appointment of a retired Judge
			<lb />
			of the Supreme Court or a former Chief Justice of a
			<lb />
			High Court as the Ombudsman of the BCCI, to be
			<lb />
			appointed once a year at the Annual General Meeting
			<lb />
			to investigate any complaint received by him/her or
			<lb />
			suo motu
			<lb />
			and to resolve any dispute between the
			<lb />
			Board and any of the above entities or among
			<lb />
			themselves by following the principles of natural
			<lb />
			justice, production of evidence and fair hearing.
			<lb />
			So also the Committee has recommended an Ethics
			<lb />
			Officer for monitoring adherence to the principles
			<lb />
			governing avoidance of Conflict of Interest.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			Committee has recommended that Ethics Officer shall
			<lb />
			have powers inter alia of laying down of additional
			<lb />
			guidelines or bye-laws on ethics, initiation of
			<lb />
			investigation or adjudicatory proceedings and the
			<lb />
			award of warnings, fines, reprimands, suspensions or
			<lb />
			other action as may be recommended to the BCCI.
			<lb />
			According to the recommendation all non-IPL ethics
			<lb />
			issues shall be administered and adjudicated by the
			<lb />
			Ethics Officer who shall be a former Judge of the
			<lb />
			High
			<lb />
			Court
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			be
			<lb />
			appointed
			<lb />
			by
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Board.
			<lb />
			Recommendation for appointment of an Electoral
			<lb />
			Officer for conducting elections of the Committee
			<lb />
			under the Rules has also been made by the Committee.
			<lb />
			The Committee has recommended that in order to
			<lb />
			ensure competence and to distance the entity from
			<lb />
			any
			<lb />
			suspicion
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			bias,
			<lb />
			a
			<lb />
			former
			<lb />
			Election
			<lb />
			Commissioner for India could be appointed as the
			<lb />
			Electoral Officer for the BCCI, whose decision on
			<lb />
			any subject relating to elections shall be final and
			<lb />
			conclusive.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			24. In Chapter eight of the report, the Committee
			<lb />
			has dealt with issues touching transparency and
			<lb />
			oversight and has noted that BCCI in its website did
			<lb />
			not carry the existing constitution or the bye-laws
			<lb />
			of BCCI.
			<lb />
			The Committee has taken cognizance of
			<lb />
			complaints of many stakeholders that very little of
			<lb />
			the functioning of the BCCI is done in a fair and
			<lb />
			transparent manner and that those who seek greater
			<lb />
			information are either rebuffed by the Board or won
			<lb />
			over by enticements.
			<lb />
			The Committee has observed
			<lb />
			that those whose professional livelihood depends on
			<lb />
			cricket acknowledge the BCCI&apos;s total sway over the
			<lb />
			sport, and choose to remain silent rather than upset
			<lb />
			the apple cart. The Committee, therefore, recommends
			<lb />
			that players and the public, ought to have access to
			<lb />
			all rules and regulations, codes and instructions of
			<lb />
			the BCCI in English and Hindi and that the same
			<lb />
			should be uploaded on the official website of the
			<lb />
			BCCI.
			<lb />
			The Committee further notices that the
			<lb />
			commercial angle has overtaken the enjoyment of the
			<lb />
			sport, with advertisements continuing many a times
			<lb />
			even after the first ball and again commencing even
			<lb />
			after the last ball is played thereby interrupting
			<lb />
			the full and proper broadcast of the game.
			<lb />
			Regardless of the wicket that has fallen, century
			<lb />
			having been hit or other momentous event, full
			<lb />
			liberty is given by BCCI to the broadcasters to
			<lb />
			maximize their income by cutting away to commercial,
			<lb />
			thereby robbing the sport of its most attractive
			<lb />
			attribute -emotion.
			<lb />
			The Committee, therefore,
			<lb />
			recommends
			<lb />
			that
			<lb />
			all
			<lb />
			existing
			<lb />
			contracts
			<lb />
			for
			<lb />
			international test and one-day matches be revised
			<lb />
			and new ones to ensure that only breaks taken by
			<lb />
			both teams for drinks, lunch and tea will permit the
			<lb />
			broadcast to be interrupted with advertisements as
			<lb />
			is the practice internationally. The Committee has,
			<lb />
			further, recommended that the entire space of the
			<lb />
			screen during the broadcast will be dedicated to the
			<lb />
			display of the game, save for a small sponsor logo
			<lb />
			or sign.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			25. The Committee has further found that there is
			<lb />
			need for better financial management and expenses or
			<lb />
			professional services. Keeping in mind that BCCI is
			<lb />
			not for profit, the Committee recommends that
			<lb />
			resources must be used for the development of the
			<lb />
			game and financial prudence must be exercised to
			<lb />
			avoid any unnecessary expenditure.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			26. The Committee also records a finding that there
			<lb />
			are no standard norms, objectives and criteria for
			<lb />
			selection and empanelment of professionals in the
			<lb />
			field of law, audit, etc. Similarly infrastructure
			<lb />
			contracts, media engagements, television rights and
			<lb />
			supply of equipments are not regulated by any norms
			<lb />
			or procedures to ensure a fair and transparent
			<lb />
			selection and engagement of the contractors and
			<lb />
			service providers.
			<lb />
			The Committee, therefore,
			<lb />
			recommends that clear principles of transparency
			<lb />
			need to be laid down and that all rules, regulations
			<lb />
			and office orders of the BCCI, the Constitution of
			<lb />
			the various committees, their resolutions, their
			<lb />
			expenditures on the various heads, the reports of
			<lb />
			the Ombudsman, Auditor, Electoral Officer, Ethics
			<lb />
			Officer and the annual reports and balance sheet be
			<lb />
			uploaded on the BCCI Website.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			27. The Committee further recommends that norms and
			<lb />
			procedures ought to be laid down for the engagement
			<lb />
			43
			<lb />
			Page 44
			<lb />
			of service professionals and contractors, and full
			<lb />
			transparency of all tenders floated and bid invited
			<lb />
			by or on behalf of the BCCI will also be maintained.
			<lb />
			The Website shall also have links to the various
			<lb />
			stadia with seating capacities and transparent
			<lb />
			direct ticketing facilities.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			28. The Committee has opined that people of the
			<lb />
			country have a right to know the details about the
			<lb />
			functions of the BCCI and its activities and
			<lb />
			recommends to the legislature to bring BCCI within
			<lb />
			the purview of the RTI Act as a public authority.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			29. More importantly, the Committee has recommended
			<lb />
			that the auditors engaged by the BCCI should be
			<lb />
			tasked to not only undertake a financial analysis
			<lb />
			but also a performance audit (Compliance Report) to
			<lb />
			determine whether State associations have actually
			<lb />
			expended their grants towards the development of the
			<lb />
			game and mark them on a report card which may be
			<lb />
			utilized to determine the financial support they
			<lb />
			deserve the following year. This oversight also
			<lb />
			needs to be considered in the opinion of the
			<lb />
			Committee because of the high and unreasonable
			<lb />
			expenditure incurred by the Board under various
			<lb />
			heads which deserves to be limited and streamlined.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			30. In Chapter Nine of the Report, the Committee has
			<lb />
			dealt with the menace of match fixing and betting.
			<lb />
			The Committee has noted that there is a fundamental
			<lb />
			difference between betting and match/ spot fixing.
			<lb />
			While the latter interferes with the integrity of
			<lb />
			the game and attempts to change the course of the
			<lb />
			match, the former is a general malaise indulged by
			<lb />
			different sections of the society not only with
			<lb />
			reference to cricket but other games also. The
			<lb />
			Committee considers the match/ spot-fixing as
			<lb />
			unpardonable and opines that the only way to deal
			<lb />
			with the same effectively is to make it punishable
			<lb />
			by law. The Committee in that regard recommends
			<lb />
			appropriate amendment by the legislature.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			31. As regards betting, the Committee has on the
			<lb />
			basis of responses and opinions tendered before it,
			<lb />
			recommended to the legislature to make the same
			<lb />
			legal with certain safeguards enlisted in the
			<lb />
			report.
			<lb />
			While saying so, the Committee has taken
			<lb />
			the view that betting by Administrators, Players,
			<lb />
			Match Officials, Team Officials, Owners, etc.,
			<lb />
			should continue to be an offence under the BCCI and
			<lb />
			IPL Rules and Regulations. The Committee has made
			<lb />
			certain recommendations to fulfill the need to
			<lb />
			educate and sensitize young players and debutants
			<lb />
			about the game ethics and the need to inculcate
			<lb />
			discipline and integrity among players.
			<lb />
			It has
			<lb />
			additionally
			<lb />
			suggested
			<lb />
			certain
			<lb />
			measures
			<lb />
			like
			<lb />
			preparing Cricketers Handbook for young players,
			<lb />
			arranging lectures and interactions with cricket
			<lb />
			players and sport persons of unimpeachable integrity
			<lb />
			with regard to game ethics and also setting up of
			<lb />
			Integrity Unit consisting of former cricket players
			<lb />
			of repute, committed to the cause of cricket, to act
			<lb />
			as mentors for the young players.
			<lb />
		</p>


		<p>
			32. The Committee has in addition recommended
			<lb />
			preparation of a database of undesirable elements
			<lb />
			(bookies, fixers, etc.,) to be shared with the
			<lb />
			players and team officials. It has also emphasized
			<lb />
			the need for verifying and ascertaining whether the
			<lb />
			person controlling the prospective franchisee has
			<lb />
			any criminal antecedents.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			33. In Chapter Ten of the Report the Committee
			<lb />
			identifies several other problem areas that call for
			<lb />
			reform.
			<lb />
			These problems have been identified and
			<lb />
			elaborated under the headings &apos;Membership and
			<lb />
			Privileges, Posts and Tenures, Voting, Compliance,
			<lb />
			Expenditure
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			Infrastructure,
			<lb />
			Lack
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			Professionalism,
			<lb />
			Dual
			<lb />
			Posts,
			<lb />
			Interference
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			Selection and Transparency.
			<lb />
			The Committee has,
			<lb />
			after an elaborate discussion under each one of the
			<lb />
			above headings, proposed solutions to the same in
			<lb />
			the following words:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;Solutions
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			There
			<lb />
			was
			<lb />
			a
			<lb />
			consistent
			<lb />
			view
			<lb />
			among
			<lb />
			respondents to the queries that many of
			<lb />
			the ills befalling Indian cricket find
			<lb />
			their roots in the State Associations and
			<lb />
			their lack of administration. The root
			<lb />
			cause for the problem is that the BCCI is
			<lb />
			making substantial annual grants regarding
			<lb />
			which there is no oversight, and so the
			<lb />
			status quo remained as it was, with little
			<lb />
			effort by the provincial administrators.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Therefore, it is necessary that there is
			<lb />
			uniformity
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			constitution
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			functioning of the various associations
			<lb />
			(without any office being created for
			<lb />
			life), that membership of social clubs be
			<lb />
			divorced
			<lb />
			from
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			administration
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			cricket which is a sombre task, that
			<lb />
			cricketers be made members and have a say
			<lb />
			in governance and that management be made
			<lb />
			professional. The State Associations must
			<lb />
			also create avenues to generate revenue,
			<lb />
			improve infrastructure and develop the
			<lb />
			sport, all of which will be marked through
			<lb />
			a detailed report card. There also has to
			<lb />
			be an audit and independent oversight of
			<lb />
			how resources are allocated and spent. It
			<lb />
			is necessary that all State Associations
			<lb />
			immediately transition to the use of
			<lb />
			tamper-proof
			<lb />
			accounting
			<lb />
			software
			<lb />
			which
			<lb />
			either does not permit alterations or
			<lb />
			which records all alterations made.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The conflicts that arise by holding office
			<lb />
			both at the BCCI and in the State
			<lb />
			Associations ought to be brought to an end
			<lb />
			by automatic vacation of post at the local
			<lb />
			level when elected to the BCCI. Also,
			<lb />
			certain disqualifications have to be laid
			<lb />
			down that apply to those who seek office
			<lb />
			in the State Associations, along with
			<lb />
			limits
			<lb />
			on
			<lb />
			their
			<lb />
			tenures
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			terms.
			<lb />
			Corrective measures are to be brought into
			<lb />
			place so that professional managers will
			<lb />
			interface with the State Governments and
			<lb />
			attempt
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			rectify
			<lb />
			any
			<lb />
			prevailing
			<lb />
			shortfalls
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			drawbacks
			<lb />
			as
			<lb />
			far
			<lb />
			as
			<lb />
			infrastructure
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			permissions
			<lb />
			are
			<lb />
			concerned.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The electoral process will have to be
			<lb />
			transparent and independent, for which an
			<lb />
			Electoral Officer (a retired Central or
			<lb />
			respective State Election Commissioner)
			<lb />
			will have be appointed. In the event that
			<lb />
			no such person is available, any other
			<lb />
			former
			<lb />
			State
			<lb />
			Election
			<lb />
			Commissioner,
			<lb />
			preferably from a neighbouring State may
			<lb />
			be appointed. This officer would conduct
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			supervise
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			entire
			<lb />
			process
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			elections from the filing of nominations
			<lb />
			to the declaration of results and the
			<lb />
			resolution of any disputes and objections
			<lb />
			during the election.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			It
			<lb />
			is
			<lb />
			also
			<lb />
			necessary
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			have
			<lb />
			an
			<lb />
			independent selection committee in which
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Governing
			<lb />
			body
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			State
			<lb />
			Association will have no say, and also for
			<lb />
			the cricket committees manned only by
			<lb />
			former players to have an independent say
			<lb />
			on
			<lb />
			coaching
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			evaluation
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			team
			<lb />
			performance, apart from the selection of
			<lb />
			players.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The policies of BCCI regarding dispute
			<lb />
			resolution and Conflict of Interest, as
			<lb />
			well as the norms for Agents&apos; Registration
			<lb />
			will
			<lb />
			have
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			apply
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			State
			<lb />
			Associations
			<lb />
			as
			<lb />
			well.
			<lb />
			In
			<lb />
			order
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			administer this, the associations may also
			<lb />
			appoint an Ombudsman-cum-Ethics Officer.
			<lb />
			It would be open to multiple States to
			<lb />
			have a single Ombudsman / Ethics Officer
			<lb />
			so as to reduce expenditure. The person so
			<lb />
			appointed shall be an eminent person well
			<lb />
			versed in adjudicatory processes and it
			<lb />
			will be his/her task to decide all
			<lb />
			disputes between the Association and any
			<lb />
			of its constituents (Districts, Clubs,
			<lb />
			etc.), or between the constituents, or
			<lb />
			complaints of any player or member of the
			<lb />
			public, by following the principles of
			<lb />
			natural
			<lb />
			justice
			<lb />
			before
			<lb />
			rendering
			<lb />
			a
			<lb />
			decision.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			As Ethics Officer, it shall be his duty to
			<lb />
			administer the principles of Conflict of
			<lb />
			Interest and recommend such action as may
			<lb />
			be deemed fit as far as an Office Bearer,
			<lb />
			Employee, Player, Team Official or other
			<lb />
			individual
			<lb />
			connected
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			State
			<lb />
			Association is concerned. Needless to say,
			<lb />
			if it is an issue that concerns the BCCI
			<lb />
			as well, the Ethics Officer of the BCCI
			<lb />
			shall proceed to decide the issue. The
			<lb />
			Ethics Officer shall also decide all
			<lb />
			issues concerning the violation of the
			<lb />
			Agents&apos; Registration norms as far as
			<lb />
			players of the State are concerned.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Each State Association will necessarily
			<lb />
			have a website that carries the following
			<lb />
			minimum details:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			a. The
			<lb />
			Constitution,
			<lb />
			Memorandum
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			Association
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			Rules
			<lb />
			&amp;
			<lb />
			Regulations,
			<lb />
			Bye-Laws and Office Orders and directions
			<lb />
			that
			<lb />
			govern
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			functioning
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Association, its Committees, the Ombudsman
			<lb />
			and the Ethics Officer.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			b. The list of Members of the Association
			<lb />
			as well as those who are defaulters.
			<lb />
		</item>


		<item>
			c. The annual accounts &amp; audited balance
			<lb />
			sheets
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			head-wise
			<lb />
			income
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			expenditure details.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			d. Details
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			male,
			<lb />
			female
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			differently abled players representing the
			<lb />
			State at all age groups with their names,
			<lb />
			ages and detailed playing statistics.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			e. Advertisements and invitations for
			<lb />
			tenders when the Association is seeking
			<lb />
			supply of any goods or services (exceeding
			<lb />
			a minimum prescribed value), or notices
			<lb />
			regarding
			<lb />
			recruitment,
			<lb />
			as
			<lb />
			also
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			detailed
			<lb />
			process
			<lb />
			for
			<lb />
			awarding
			<lb />
			such
			<lb />
			contracts or making such recruitments.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			f. Details of all goals and milestones
			<lb />
			for developing cricket in the State along
			<lb />
			with timelines and the measures undertaken
			<lb />
			to achieve each of them.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			g. Details of all office bearers and
			<lb />
			other managerial staff (including CEO,
			<lb />
			COO, CFO, etc.)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			h. Details of directives from the BCCI
			<lb />
			and their compliances.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			These websites will have to be maintained
			<lb />
			and updated at least on a quarterly basis.
			<lb />
			All the above information will have to be
			<lb />
			maintained at the registered office of the
			<lb />
			State Association and when sought, the
			<lb />
			same shall be shared with the applicant on
			<lb />
			the payment of a reasonable fee, as may be
			<lb />
			prescribed by the Association.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The cost of construction of a stadium runs
			<lb />
			into hundreds of crores. On the other
			<lb />
			hand, formation of a cricket playing
			<lb />
			ground costs a small fraction of the cost
			<lb />
			of a stadium. It makes more sense to have
			<lb />
			cricket playing grounds in each District,
			<lb />
			rather than having one or two stadia in a
			<lb />
			State. In fact, the Committee learns that
			<lb />
			some members are merely collecting the
			<lb />
			grants from BCCI and depositing them in a
			<lb />
			Bank so as to accumulate sufficient funds
			<lb />
			necessary for taking up construction of a
			<lb />
			stadium. The result is some smaller States
			<lb />
			have neither a stadium nor well developed
			<lb />
			cricket
			<lb />
			playing
			<lb />
			grounds.
			<lb />
			BCCI
			<lb />
			should
			<lb />
			therefore encourage the State Associations
			<lb />
			to:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			a. Have as many cricket playing grounds
			<lb />
			and fields instead of multiple stadia,
			<lb />
			which will enable greater usage and access
			<lb />
			to greater number of players.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			b. Convert existing grounds and fields
			<lb />
			into turf wickets so that international
			<lb />
			standard facilities are made available
			<lb />
			even from a young age.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			c. To make the existing stadia amenable
			<lb />
			to other sports by providing for alternate
			<lb />
			surfaces to be laid (Astroturf for hockey,
			<lb />
			Carpet for tennis, etc.) so that income
			<lb />
			may be generated and there would be all
			<lb />
			round development of sport, care being
			<lb />
			taken not to damage the pitch.
			<lb />
			But they
			<lb />
			should not be used for public functions
			<lb />
			where thousands will stomp on the ground.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The above recommendations relating to
			<lb />
			State Associations (Full Members) will
			<lb />
			also be applicable to the 4 associations
			<lb />
			relegated to the category of Associate
			<lb />
			Members
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			who
			<lb />
			are
			<lb />
			entitled
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			disbursement of the grant from the BCCI.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>


		<p>
			34. The reforms recommended by the Committee have
			<lb />
			been finally summed up under the heading &quot;End of the
			<lb />
			Innings&quot; in the following words:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;END OF THE INNINGS
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			If there has been one unifying factor in
			<lb />
			India,
			<lb />
			it
			<lb />
			has
			<lb />
			been
			<lb />
			cricket.
			<lb />
			From
			<lb />
			C.K.Nayudu to Virat Kohli, the 32 captains
			<lb />
			of India and the men they have led have
			<lb />
			been equally deified and vilified by the
			<lb />
			masses, for such is the ability of the
			<lb />
			game to inflame passions. It is on behalf
			<lb />
			of these devotees of willow and leather
			<lb />
			that this Committee submits this effort to
			<lb />
			edify the BCCI.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			In
			<lb />
			an
			<lb />
			effort
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			present
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			recommendations made by the Committee in
			<lb />
			brief, the following synopsis of our
			<lb />
			proposals are set out:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			1. Membership
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&apos;One State, One Vote&apos;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Only cricket Associations representing the
			<lb />
			States would have voting rights as Full
			<lb />
			Members of the Board, thereby ensuring
			<lb />
			equality among the territorial divisions.
			<lb />
			Any
			<lb />
			other
			<lb />
			existing
			<lb />
			members
			<lb />
			would
			<lb />
			be
			<lb />
			Associate Members.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			2. Zones
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&apos;Zones for Tournaments alone&apos;
			<lb />
			The Zones would be relevant only for the
			<lb />
			purpose
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			tournaments
			<lb />
			conducted
			<lb />
			amongst themselves, but not for nomination
			<lb />
			to the governance of the Board or to the
			<lb />
			various Standing Committees.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			3. State Associations
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&apos;State
			<lb />
			Associations
			<lb />
			-
			<lb />
			Uniformity
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			Structure&apos;
			<lb />
		</item>

		
		The Associations that are the Members
		<lb />
		would necessarily have to restrict the
		<lb />
		tenures of office bearers and prescribe
		<lb />
		disqualifications, do away with proxy
		<lb />
		voting,
		<lb />
		provide
		<lb />
		transparency
		<lb />
		in
		<lb />
		functioning, be open to scrutiny and audit
		<lb />
		by the BCCI and include players in
		<lb />
		membership and management. They would also
		<lb />
		have to abide by the conflict of interest
		<lb />
		policy
		<lb />
		prescribed
		<lb />
		by
		<lb />
		the
		<lb />
		Board,
		<lb />
		and
		<lb />
		divorce the Association from the social
		<lb />
		club, if any.
		<lb />
		

		<item>
			4. Office Bearer
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&apos;Limited Tenures &amp; Cooling Off&apos;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			While all the existing office bearers
			<lb />
			(President,
			<lb />
			Vice-President,
			<lb />
			Secretary,
			<lb />
			Treasurer
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			Joint
			<lb />
			Secretary)
			<lb />
			are
			<lb />
			retained in honorary positions, the number
			<lb />
			of Vice Presidents is pruned from five to
			<lb />
			one. Their duties have been realigned. The
			<lb />
			President
			<lb />
			is
			<lb />
			shorn
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			his
			<lb />
			say
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			selections. The additional vote for the
			<lb />
			President at meetings is deleted. The
			<lb />
			terms of these Office Bearers continue to
			<lb />
			be of 3 years, but with a maximum of 3
			<lb />
			such terms regardless of the post held,
			<lb />
			with a cooling off period after each such
			<lb />
			term.
			<lb />
		</item>


		<item>
			5. Governance
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&apos;Governance separated from management&apos;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The
			<lb />
			14
			<lb />
			member
			<lb />
			Working
			<lb />
			Committee
			<lb />
			is
			<lb />
			replaced by a 9 member Apex Council (with
			<lb />
			one-third independent members) consisting
			<lb />
			of the Office Bearers of the BCCI, an
			<lb />
			elected representative of the General
			<lb />
			Body, two representatives of the Players
			<lb />
			Association (one man and one woman) and
			<lb />
			one nominee from the C&amp;AG&apos;s office. Terms
			<lb />
			of eligibility and disqualification are
			<lb />
			specified with a bar on Ministers and
			<lb />
			government servants.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			6. Management
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&apos;Professionalism in management&apos;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Professionalism
			<lb />
			is
			<lb />
			brought
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			by
			<lb />
			introducing a CEO with strong credentials
			<lb />
			assisted by a team of managers to handle
			<lb />
			non-cricketing affairs. The large number
			<lb />
			of Standing Committees and Sub-Committees
			<lb />
			created by the BCCI has been reduced to
			<lb />
			two essential ones that would advice the
			<lb />
			CEO with reference to tours, technical
			<lb />
			aspects and tournaments.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The
			<lb />
			selection,
			<lb />
			coaching,
			<lb />
			performance
			<lb />
			evaluation and umpiring are to be handled
			<lb />
			by Cricket Committees manned only by
			<lb />
			former professionals. Specific provisions
			<lb />
			have been made to encourage cricket for
			<lb />
			women and the differently-abled.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			7. The IPL
			<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				&apos;Limited Autonomy for IPL&apos;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				The Governing Council of the IPL is
				<lb />
				reduced
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				9,
				<lb />
				but
				<lb />
				includes
				<lb />
				2
				<lb />
				representatives of the Franchisees and
				<lb />
				nominees of the Players&apos; Association and
				<lb />
				the C&amp;AG&apos;s office.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				8. Players
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				&apos;A voice for Players&apos;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				There
				<lb />
				shall
				<lb />
				be
				<lb />
				a
				<lb />
				Cricket
				<lb />
				Players&apos;
				<lb />
				Association affording membership to all
				<lb />
				international and most first class men and
				<lb />
				women retired cricketers. This Association
				<lb />
				shall discharge assigned functions with
				<lb />
				the financial support of the BCCI. It
				<lb />
				shall be brought into existence by an
				<lb />
				independent steering committee.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				9. Agents
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				&apos;Arms length for agents&apos;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				Players&apos;
				<lb />
				interests
				<lb />
				are
				<lb />
				protected
				<lb />
				by
				<lb />
				ensuring that their Agents are registered
				<lb />
				under the prescribed norms administered by
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				BCCI
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				Players&apos;
				<lb />
				Cricket
				<lb />
				Association.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				10. Conflict of Interest
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				&apos;Avoidance of conflicts&apos;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				Detailed norms have been laid down to
				<lb />
				ensure there is no direct or indirect,
				<lb />
				pecuniary or other conflict or appearance
				<lb />
				thereof in the discharge of the functions
				<lb />
				of those persons associated or employed by
				<lb />
				the BCCI, its Committees, its Members or
				<lb />
				the IPL Franchisees. These norms shall be
				<lb />
				administered by an Ethics Officer.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				11. The
				<lb />
				Ombudsman
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				Electoral
				<lb />
				Officer
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				&apos;Independent monitors&apos;
				<lb />
			</item>


			<item>
				Provision has been made to have an
				<lb />
				independent
				<lb />
				ombudsman
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				resolve
				<lb />
				grievances
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				Members,
				<lb />
				Administrators,
				<lb />
				Players and even members of the public as
				<lb />
				per the procedures laid down. Similarly,
				<lb />
				an
				<lb />
				independent
				<lb />
				Electoral
				<lb />
				Officer
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				oversee the entire electoral process is
				<lb />
				also mandated.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				12. Functioning
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				&apos;Transparency&apos;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				The
				<lb />
				BCCI
				<lb />
				must
				<lb />
				provide
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				relevant
				<lb />
				information in discharge of its public
				<lb />
				functions. All rules and regulations,
				<lb />
				norms, details of meetings, expenditures,
				<lb />
				balance sheets, reports and orders of
				<lb />
				authorities are to be uploaded on the
				<lb />
				website as well.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				13. Oversight
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				&apos;Accountability&apos;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				An independent auditor to verify how the
				<lb />
				Full Members have expended the grants
				<lb />
				given to them by the BCCI, to record their
				<lb />
				targets and milestones, and to submit a
				<lb />
				separate compliance report in this regard.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				14. Betting &amp; Match-fixing
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				&apos;Legalization
				<lb />
				for
				<lb />
				betting
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				Criminalization for match-fixing&apos;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				A recommendation is made to legalize
				<lb />
				betting (with strong safeguards), except
				<lb />
				for those covered by the BCCI and IPL
				<lb />
				regulations. Also a recommendation for
				<lb />
				match/spot-fixing to be made a criminal
				<lb />
				offence.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				15. Ethics for Players
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				&apos;Awareness and sensitization&apos;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				Provisions
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				be
				<lb />
				made
				<lb />
				for
				<lb />
				lectures,
				<lb />
				classes, handbooks and mentoring of young
				<lb />
				players.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				The Committee fervently hopes that this
				<lb />
				report will bring cricket fans back to the
				<lb />
				fold and put an end to regional excesses
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				imbalances,
				<lb />
				reign
				<lb />
				by
				<lb />
				cliques,
				<lb />
				corruption and red tape, all of which have
				<lb />
				harmed the game and the youngsters looking
				<lb />
				for nothing more than to take the field in
				<lb />
				flannels.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				35. In order to give the recommendations made by the
				<lb />
				Committee a practical shape, suitable amendments to
				<lb />
				the Memorandum of Association of BCCI and the Rules
				<lb />
				and Regulations have been suggested as Annexure &apos;A&apos;
				<lb />
				to the Report. The Committee has, at the same time,
				<lb />
				proposed a code for the Cricket Players&apos; Association
				<lb />
				which forms Annexure &apos;B&apos; to the Report, while
				<lb />
				Regulations for Registration of Players&apos; Agents have
				<lb />
				been set out at Annexure &apos;C&apos; to the Report.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				36. In response to the notice issued by this Court,
				<lb />
				the BCCI has filed an affidavit sworn by Shri Anurag
				<lb />
				Singh Thakur, Honorary Secretary of the BCCI and
				<lb />
				currently President of BCCI in which the BCCI claims
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				have
				<lb />
				accepted
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				implemented
				<lb />
				several
				<lb />
				recommendations made by the Committee. In Para 6 of
				<lb />
				the Affidavit the deponent has identified the
				<lb />
				recommendations accepted by BCCI and the steps
				<lb />
				already taken by it or those being taken for
				<lb />
				implementation, in the following words:
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;6.Of the recommendations contained in the
				<lb />
				Report, BCCI has accepted and has either
				<lb />
				implemented or is implementing the following
				<lb />
				recommendations:
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				(a) Appointment of an Ombudsman:
				<lb />
				The BCCI
				<lb />
				has amended its Rules and Regulations to
				<lb />
				provide for the appointment of an Ombudsman at
				<lb />
				every Annual General Meeting to deal with
				<lb />
				complaints of conflicts of interest and any
				<lb />
				act of indiscipline or misconduct or violation
				<lb />
				of any rules and regulations of the BCCI by an
				<lb />
				administrator.
				<lb />
				Thus, the Ombudsman now
				<lb />
				contemplated
				<lb />
				by
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				amended
				<lb />
				Rules
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				Regulations of the BCCI effectively combine
				<lb />
				the functions of the Ethics Officer and the
				<lb />
				Ombudsman within the scope of the Ombudsman&apos;s
				<lb />
				functions whilst omitting disputes between the
				<lb />
				BCCI and IPL franchisees, which are covered by
				<lb />
				existing arbitration agreements. The Hon&apos;ble
				<lb />
				Mr. Justice A.P. Shah, Former Chief Justice of
				<lb />
				the Delhi High Court, has been appointed as
				<lb />
				the Ombudsman and has taken cognizance of and
				<lb />
				disposed of several complaints already.
				<lb />
			</item>


			<item>
				(b) Avoidance of Conflict of Interest:
				<lb />
				The
				<lb />
				BCCI has formulated Rules on Conflict of
				<lb />
				Interest, pursuant to which several persons
				<lb />
				have resigned from positions on account of
				<lb />
				conflict of interest. Any person can make a
				<lb />
				complaint to the Ombudsman regarding conflict
				<lb />
				of interest.
				<lb />
				The Rules on Conflict of
				<lb />
				Interest provide that every complaint shall be
				<lb />
				decided within a period of 30 (Thirty) days
				<lb />
				from the receipt of the complaint and the
				<lb />
				decision of the Ombudsman shall be final and
				<lb />
				binding. A copy of the Rules on Conflict of
				<lb />
				Interest is annexed hereto and marked as
				<lb />
				ANNEXURE-A (pg.61 to 63)
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				(c) Availability of Rules and Regulations on
				<lb />
				BCCI Website: All Rules and Regulations of the
				<lb />
				BCCI, Annual Reports along with the financial
				<lb />
				reports as well as details of all expenses
				<lb />
				above Rs.25 lakhs have been made available on
				<lb />
				the BCCI website.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				(d) Introduction of Professional Management:
				<lb />
				BCCI has accepted the recommendation to
				<lb />
				professionalise its management and introduce a
				<lb />
				two-tier structure.
				<lb />
				The BCCI presently has
				<lb />
				four General Managers viz. (1) Professor
				<lb />
				Ratnakar
				<lb />
				Shetty
				<lb />
				(General
				<lb />
				Manager
				<lb />
				-
				<lb />
				Administration), who has been associated with
				<lb />
				the administration of BCCI since 2003, first
				<lb />
				as the Executive Secretary and later as Chief
				<lb />
				Administrative Officer; (2) Dr. M.V. Sridhar
				<lb />
				(General Manager -Cricket Operations), who is
				<lb />
				a former Indian Cricketer and has served as
				<lb />
				the Hon. Secretary of the Hyderabad Cricket
				<lb />
				Association; (3) Mr. Amrit Mathur (General
				<lb />
				Manager -Communication and Coordination), who
				<lb />
				is in charge of media and coordination with
				<lb />
				Government of India (Sports Ministry, Home
				<lb />
				Ministry and External Affairs Ministry) and
				<lb />
				has been involved with the BCCI for over two
				<lb />
				decades inter alia as media manager on a
				<lb />
				number of overseas tours; and (4) Mr. Dhiraj
				<lb />
				Malhotra
				<lb />
				(General
				<lb />
				Manager
				<lb />
				-
				<lb />
				Events
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				Leagues), who has worked in organizing ICC
				<lb />
				60
				<lb />
				Page 61
				<lb />
				World events for over a decade and was also
				<lb />
				associated with organizing a number of sports
				<lb />
				leagues including Indian Premier League, etc.
				<lb />
				A
				<lb />
				head-hunting
				<lb />
				agency
				<lb />
				has
				<lb />
				already
				<lb />
				been
				<lb />
				appointed for the purpose of identifying
				<lb />
				candidates for appointment as a CEO and a CFO.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				(e) Limited Due Diligence of audited accounts
				<lb />
				of State Associations for finding out how
				<lb />
				associations have utilized the funds made
				<lb />
				available by Board to State Associations: BCCI
				<lb />
				Rules and Regulations have been amended to
				<lb />
				empower BCCI to appoint an independent auditor
				<lb />
				to scrutinize the statements of accounts of
				<lb />
				members with regard to payments made by BCCI
				<lb />
				to such member and all further payments due to
				<lb />
				such member shall be released after the
				<lb />
				receipt of diligence reports by the BCCI.
				<lb />
				BCCI
				<lb />
				immediately
				<lb />
				engaged
				<lb />
				agencies
				<lb />
				like
				<lb />
				PricewaterhouseCoopers, Deloitte and Grant
				<lb />
				Thorton to carry out due diligence of State
				<lb />
				Associations.
				<lb />
				As part of this process, a
				<lb />
				financial due diligence exercise is currently
				<lb />
				underway in respect of financial years ending
				<lb />
				31 st March 2014 and 31 st March 2015.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				(f) Measures to prevent match-fixing/ spot
				<lb />
				fixing:
				<lb />
				Although BCCI has implemented the
				<lb />
				Anti Corruption Code since 2012, the biggest
				<lb />
				obstacle that has been faced by BCCI in its
				<lb />
				endeavour to prevent match-fixing/ spot-fixing
				<lb />
				has been the absence powers to gather
				<lb />
				intelligence on the subject and/ or policing
				<lb />
				powers with the BCCI&apos;s Anti Corruption Unit.
				<lb />
				For this reason, the BCCI has requested the
				<lb />
				Government of Maharashtra to establish a
				<lb />
				sports integrity intelligence gathering unit
				<lb />
				under the joint aegis of the BCCI and
				<lb />
				Maharashtra Police whilst offering to fund the
				<lb />
				costs of doing so, if required. A copy of the
				<lb />
				letter dated 18 th November 2015 addressed by
				<lb />
				the BCCI to the Hon&apos;ble Chief Minister of
				<lb />
				Maharashtra is annexed hereto and marked as
				<lb />
				ANNEXURE -B (pg.64 to 65)
				<lb />
			</item>


			<item>
				(g) Decentralisation
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				powers
				<lb />
				with
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				President: By virtue of being the Chairman of
				<lb />
				the Annual General Meetings and Special
				<lb />
				General Meetings of the BCCI, the President
				<lb />
				earlier had an independent vote (in addition
				<lb />
				to a casting vote) at General Meetings.
				<lb />
				Further, any dispute as to admission or
				<lb />
				rejection of a vote at General Meetings was
				<lb />
				earlier decided by the President. BCCI Rules
				<lb />
				and Regulations have been amended to do away
				<lb />
				with the independent vote of the President at
				<lb />
				General Meetings.
				<lb />
				Similarly, any dispute as
				<lb />
				to admission or rejection of a vote at General
				<lb />
				Meetings will now be decided by a simple
				<lb />
				majority.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				37. Having said that, the affidavit questions the
				<lb />
				wisdom behind the one State one Vote principle
				<lb />
				evolved by the Committee and claims that the
				<lb />
				membership structure of the BCCI is based on level
				<lb />
				of cricketing activity, which according to it has a
				<lb />
				more rational nexus with the objects of BCCI than
				<lb />
				geographical limits of the States settled on
				<lb />
				linguistic basis much after the BCCI was formed.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				38. The BCCI asserts equal representation/ voting
				<lb />
				rights to each State irrespective of the level of
				<lb />
				cricketing activity therein is likely to result in a
				<lb />
				situation where States with little or no cricketing
				<lb />
				activity will abuse their representation/voting
				<lb />
				rights.
				<lb />
				BCCI also pleads legal impediments in
				<lb />
				disenfranchising
				<lb />
				and/or
				<lb />
				demoting
				<lb />
				existing
				<lb />
				Full
				<lb />
				Members or depriving them of their vested rights
				<lb />
				while assuming that it will not induct any new
				<lb />
				member from the State which already has a member and
				<lb />
				will induct only one full Member provided the
				<lb />
				requisite
				<lb />
				criteria
				<lb />
				is
				<lb />
				satisfied.
				<lb />
				BCCI
				<lb />
				also
				<lb />
				expresses difficulties in recognizing one of the
				<lb />
				three existing members in the States of Gujarat and
				<lb />
				Maharashtra as representing the said States while
				<lb />
				converting the Membership of the other two as
				<lb />
				associate members.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				39. BCCI argues that there is no criteria on the
				<lb />
				basis of which it can decide as to which of the
				<lb />
				existing three members should be retained as a full
				<lb />
				member. It is submitted that even assuming that the
				<lb />
				BCCI decides to retain one of the three existing
				<lb />
				full members as a full member, jurisdiction of any
				<lb />
				such retained member will extend to the entire State
				<lb />
				63
				<lb />
				Page 64
				<lb />
				including the area over which the jurisdiction of
				<lb />
				the other two member from that State extends. This
				<lb />
				would in-turn imply that apart from being relegated
				<lb />
				as an associate member, the remaining full members
				<lb />
				from that State will no longer be in-charge of
				<lb />
				cricketing activities, cricket teams, stadia and
				<lb />
				players
				<lb />
				within
				<lb />
				their
				<lb />
				respective
				<lb />
				erstwhile
				<lb />
				jurisdictions.
				<lb />
				It would thereby disable them to
				<lb />
				field teams to participate in BCCI tournaments.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				40. BCCI
				<lb />
				also
				<lb />
				apprehends
				<lb />
				that
				<lb />
				infrastructure
				<lb />
				available with the three full members each from
				<lb />
				Maharashtra and Gujarat will be wasted if the
				<lb />
				recommendation of the Committee is accepted. It is
				<lb />
				contended that Regulations 6(A) and 6(B) of BCCI&apos;s
				<lb />
				existing
				<lb />
				Rules
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				Regulations
				<lb />
				lay
				<lb />
				down
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				procedures and criteria for admitting any new
				<lb />
				members based on levels of cricketing activity in
				<lb />
				their respective territories apart from provisions
				<lb />
				that provide for promotion of an Affiliate Member to
				<lb />
				an Associate Member as well as for promotion of an
				<lb />
				Associate Member to a Full Member to take care of
				<lb />
				the interests of all concerned.
				<lb />
				This method is in
				<lb />
				tune with the method followed by International
				<lb />
				Cricket Council (for short, &quot;the ICC&quot;) where a
				<lb />
				member has to reach a certain level in performance
				<lb />
				and infrastructure before it may be promoted to the
				<lb />
				next level.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				41. BCCI has also faulted the proposed reduction in
				<lb />
				advertisement as the same will according to it have
				<lb />
				a crippling effect on the financial health of the
				<lb />
				Board and adversely impact its ability to carry out
				<lb />
				its various programmes. Restricting advertisements
				<lb />
				only
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				drinks,
				<lb />
				lunch
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				tea
				<lb />
				breaks
				<lb />
				will
				<lb />
				substantially de-value the broadcast rights and
				<lb />
				reduce the income of the BCCI as broadcasters will
				<lb />
				in that case pay a only fraction of the amount that
				<lb />
				they are now paying for the broadcast rights.
				<lb />
				The
				<lb />
				affidavit traces the history of the growth of the
				<lb />
				activities of the BCCI and corresponding growth in
				<lb />
				its finances.
				<lb />
				Induction of a nominee of the
				<lb />
				65
				<lb />
				Page 66
				<lb />
				Comptroller and Auditor General of India (for short,
				<lb />
				&quot;the CAG&quot;) on the Management Committee/Apex Council
				<lb />
				has also been stoutly opposed by the BCCI. Relying
				<lb />
				upon Article 2.9 (B) of the Memorandum and Articles
				<lb />
				of Association of the ICC it is urged that inclusion
				<lb />
				of nominee of the CAG would tantamount to Government
				<lb />
				interference in the administration of Cricket and
				<lb />
				would call for adverse action by the ICC against the
				<lb />
				BCCI.
				<lb />
				Objections are also taken to the proposed
				<lb />
				induction of franchisee&apos;s representatives in IPL
				<lb />
				Governing Council. The BCCI contend that there is a
				<lb />
				conflict of interest between representatives of IPL
				<lb />
				Franchisees and the Governing Council as the later
				<lb />
				decides matters such as player retention policy,
				<lb />
				posting of umpires for IPL matches, etc. So also a
				<lb />
				prohibition on re-appointment of Members of the
				<lb />
				Managing Committee recommended by the Committee has
				<lb />
				been opposed by the BCCI on the ground that there is
				<lb />
				no rationale for prohibiting any individual from
				<lb />
				being associated with the management of the BCCI
				<lb />
				beyond nine years particularly when there is an age
				<lb />
				66
				<lb />
				Page 67
				<lb />
				cap of 70 years in the Report that is simultaneously
				<lb />
				sought to be imposed.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				42. Prohibition
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				Association
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				Ministers/
				<lb />
				Government Servants/ Persons holding posts in
				<lb />
				another
				<lb />
				Sports
				<lb />
				Body
				<lb />
				in
				<lb />
				honorary
				<lb />
				capacity
				<lb />
				as
				<lb />
				recommended by the Committee has also been opposed
				<lb />
				by the BCCI.
				<lb />
				It is contended that the association
				<lb />
				of Government Servants and Ministers has benefitted
				<lb />
				the BCCI immensely and that all such persons work in
				<lb />
				purely honorary capacity.
				<lb />
				Travel, boarding and
				<lb />
				lodging costs of such office bearers only are taken
				<lb />
				care of by the BCCI. BCCI has also urged that the
				<lb />
				restriction on simultaneous holding of an office in
				<lb />
				a State association and the BCCI is unreasonable as
				<lb />
				senior citizens also make substantial contribution
				<lb />
				in sports as their counterparts in law, judiciary,
				<lb />
				public life, Parliament etc. As regards Players
				<lb />
				Association and Board representation, the BCCI has
				<lb />
				welcomed the suggestion of formation of a Players&apos;
				<lb />
				Association but opposed any funding by the BCCI as
				<lb />
				recommended by the Committee.
				<lb />
				It has also not
				<lb />
				favored players&apos; representation in the Board on the
				<lb />
				ground that several players have in the past served
				<lb />
				as Office Bearers in the BCCI and State Association
				<lb />
				on their own merit.
				<lb />
				Dissolution of existing
				<lb />
				Committees too has been opposed by the BCCI.
				<lb />
				In
				<lb />
				conclusion, the affidavit filed on behalf of the
				<lb />
				BCCI submits that while the report seems to have
				<lb />
				achieved a very laudable objective the same is only
				<lb />
				recommendatory and ought not to be imposed on a
				<lb />
				society formed by private individuals who enjoy
				<lb />
				constitutional protection under Article 19 of the
				<lb />
				Constitution of India. It has also raised an issue
				<lb />
				that the Committee did not give a hearing to BCCI
				<lb />
				regarding the proposed recommendations. Although a
				<lb />
				questionnaire was sent to the office bearers of the
				<lb />
				BCCI including the honorary President, honorary
				<lb />
				Secretary and the honorary Treasurer and even when
				<lb />
				the office bearers of the BCCI had appeared before
				<lb />
				the Committee to explain their view points, the
				<lb />
				failure of the Committee to put the proposed
				<lb />
				68
				<lb />
				Page 69
				<lb />
				recommendations to the BCCI has, according to the
				<lb />
				BCCI, denied to them an opportunity to represent
				<lb />
				against
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				same.
				<lb />
				The
				<lb />
				affidavit
				<lb />
				finally
				<lb />
				acknowledges that BCCI has benefitted greatly from
				<lb />
				the report of the Lodha Committee and that it is
				<lb />
				committed to implementing the same to ensure greater
				<lb />
				professionalism, transparency and accountability
				<lb />
				keeping
				<lb />
				in
				<lb />
				mind
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				underlying
				<lb />
				objective
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				betterment of cricket in India.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				43. Appearing for BCCI Mr. K.K. Venugopal, learned
				<lb />
				senior counsel, argued that although BCCI had
				<lb />
				received a questionnaire and although the office
				<lb />
				bearers of the BCCI also had extensive interaction
				<lb />
				with the Committee on several aspects concerning the
				<lb />
				subject matter of the proceedings, yet, justice and
				<lb />
				fairness
				<lb />
				demanded
				<lb />
				that
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				Committee,
				<lb />
				before
				<lb />
				submitting its final recommendations to this Court,
				<lb />
				gave an opportunity to the BCCI to respond to the
				<lb />
				same.
				<lb />
				The recommendations, according to Mr.
				<lb />
				Venugopal, came as a surprise to the BCCI and hence
				<lb />
				need to be turned down and the matter remitted back
				<lb />
				to the Committee for considering the response of
				<lb />
				BCCI on each one of the issues covered by the same.
				<lb />
				It was contended that principles of natural justice
				<lb />
				demand that since BCCI was likely to be affected by
				<lb />
				the acceptance of the recommendations a fair and
				<lb />
				reasonable opportunity to oppose such of them as
				<lb />
				were not acceptable to was provided.
				<lb />
				Inasmuch as
				<lb />
				the Committee had failed to follow that procedure
				<lb />
				and had made its recommendations unilaterally, the
				<lb />
				report and the recommendations deserved to be
				<lb />
				rejected.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				44. There is, in our opinion, no merit in the
				<lb />
				submission of Mr.Venugopal. The reasons are not far
				<lb />
				to seek.
				<lb />
				The task assigned to the Committee in
				<lb />
				terms of the order passed by this Court was to
				<lb />
				examine the issues set out in the order and make
				<lb />
				suitable recommendations in that regard.
				<lb />
				The task
				<lb />
				assigned was, in its very nature inquisitorial in
				<lb />
				which the Committee was supposed to hear the
				<lb />
				concerned stakeholders including the BCCI and
				<lb />
				formulate its views on various aspects concerning
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				subject
				<lb />
				matter
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				make
				<lb />
				recommendations
				<lb />
				considered necessary for a more efficient, objective
				<lb />
				and transparent working of the BCCI. The Committee
				<lb />
				comprising some of the finest legal minds fully
				<lb />
				aware of the requirements of law and the need for
				<lb />
				adopting a fair and reasonable procedure, decided in
				<lb />
				its wisdom to serve a questionnaire upon the
				<lb />
				stakeholders soliciting information, apart from
				<lb />
				holding several interactive sessions with them and
				<lb />
				all those who wished to be heard in the matter
				<lb />
				including
				<lb />
				representatives
				<lb />
				from
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				State
				<lb />
				Associations, Journalists, Academicians, Jurists,
				<lb />
				Public Figures etc.
				<lb />
				The Committee has on the basis
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				said
				<lb />
				interactions
				<lb />
				arrived
				<lb />
				at
				<lb />
				certain
				<lb />
				conclusions to which we have made reference at great
				<lb />
				length in the earlier part of this judgment. Based
				<lb />
				on the said findings the Committee has recommended
				<lb />
				certain steps which, in its opinion, are necessary
				<lb />
				to usher in structural and other reforms in the
				<lb />
				working of the BCCI.
				<lb />
				What is significant is that
				<lb />
				the Committee was not called upon nor has it
				<lb />
				adjudicated upon any right of the applicant finally.
				<lb />
				It has simply enquired into the working of the BCCI,
				<lb />
				identified its fault, its weaknesses, failures and
				<lb />
				shortcomings and suggested ways and means by which
				<lb />
				the same can be rectified. The report submitted by
				<lb />
				the Committee is recommendatory in nature and does
				<lb />
				not ipso facto oblige BCCI to accept the changes
				<lb />
				suggested therein unless so directed by the Court.
				<lb />
				That being so, any grievance based on the alleged
				<lb />
				violation of the principles of natural justice and
				<lb />
				failure of the Committee to put the recommendations
				<lb />
				proposed to be made before the BCCI for its response
				<lb />
				did not, in our opinion, constitute any substantive
				<lb />
				or procedural infirmity that could vitiate the
				<lb />
				report or the recommendations or call for a remand
				<lb />
				to the Committee. Principles of natural justice, it
				<lb />
				is well settled, are not codified rules of
				<lb />
				procedure.
				<lb />
				Courts have repeatedly declined to lay
				<lb />
				down in a strait jacket, their scope and extent. The
				<lb />
				extent, the manner and the application of these
				<lb />
				principles depends so much on the nature of
				<lb />
				jurisdiction exercised by the Court or the Tribunal,
				<lb />
				the nature of the inquiry undertaken and the effect
				<lb />
				of any such inquiry on the rights and obligations of
				<lb />
				those before it.
				<lb />
				The extent of the application of
				<lb />
				the principles also depends upon the fact situation
				<lb />
				of a given case.
				<lb />
				The legal position is so well
				<lb />
				settled that we do not consider it necessary to
				<lb />
				burden this judgment by elaborating on the subject.
				<lb />
				Reference to the decisions of this Court in Viveka
				<lb />
				Nand Sethi v. Chairman, J &amp; K Bank Ltd. (2005) 5
				<lb />
				SCC, 337, S.L. Kapoor v. Jagmohan (1980) 4 SCC 379,
				<lb />
				State of Punjab v. Jagir Singh (2004) 8 SCC 129,
				<lb />
				Karnataka SRTC v. S.G. Kotturappa (2005) 3 SCC 409,
				<lb />
				Ravi S Naik v. Union of India (1994) supp. (2) SCC
				<lb />
				641 and K.L. Tripathi v. SBI (1984) 1 SCC 43 should
				<lb />
				suffice.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				45. The fact that the Committee was appointed by
				<lb />
				this Court, for a specific purpose, the fact that
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				Committee
				<lb />
				comprised
				<lb />
				distinguished
				<lb />
				jurists
				<lb />
				familiar with the requirements of fairness and
				<lb />
				objectivity and the need for providing a hearing to
				<lb />
				any one likely to be affected, the fact that the
				<lb />
				Committee not only served questionnaire and heard
				<lb />
				all those who wished to be heard and the fact that
				<lb />
				the report of the Committee was not ipso facto
				<lb />
				binding but was only recommendatory, completely
				<lb />
				excludes any chance of any prejudice to BCCI nor has
				<lb />
				any prejudice otherwise been demonstrated. The fact
				<lb />
				that we have heard BCCI on the recommendations made
				<lb />
				by the Committee also eliminates the possibility of
				<lb />
				any prejudice. At any rate there was in the facts
				<lb />
				and circumstances no legal or procedural requirement
				<lb />
				for the Committee to draw up its recommendations on
				<lb />
				a provisional basis and then finalise the report
				<lb />
				after considering the response of the BCCI.
				<lb />
				The
				<lb />
				changes proposed by the Committee remain in the
				<lb />
				realm of recommendations so long as they are not
				<lb />
				accepted by this Court and before we accept the same
				<lb />
				with or without modification, we have heard not only
				<lb />
				the BCCI but everyone who has come forward to be
				<lb />
				heard.
				<lb />
				We, therefore, see no reason to remand the
				<lb />
				matter nor do we see any legal flaw in the procedure
				<lb />
				adopted by the Committee.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				46. It was then argued by Mr. Venugopal that
				<lb />
				although several of the recommendations made by the
				<lb />
				Committee were sound and useful for improving the
				<lb />
				working of the BCCI and bringing greater efficiency
				<lb />
				and transparency, yet, several others were either
				<lb />
				legally impermissible or unnecessary apart from
				<lb />
				being impracticable keeping in view the ground
				<lb />
				realities and the historical perspective in which
				<lb />
				the BCCI was founded. Mr. Venugopal, in particular,
				<lb />
				assailed the recommendations made by the Committee
				<lb />
				that each State in the country must be represented
				<lb />
				in the BCCI by an association as a full member. It
				<lb />
				was urged that while the BCCI was not averse to
				<lb />
				conceding full membership to an association duly
				<lb />
				recognized from each State in the country to give to
				<lb />
				the BCCI a truly national character, the Committee&apos;s
				<lb />
				recommendations that multiple full members from the
				<lb />
				States
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				Gujarat
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				Maharashtra
				<lb />
				should
				<lb />
				be
				<lb />
				discontinued and two members each from both the
				<lb />
				States reduced to associate membership of BCCI was
				<lb />
				neither just nor legally permissible.
				<lb />
				It was
				<lb />
				submitted that both Maharashtra and Gujarat have
				<lb />
				three full members in the BCCI, not only because the
				<lb />
				said members were founding members of the BCCI but
				<lb />
				also because they had, since their inception
				<lb />
				promoted cricketing activity in their respective
				<lb />
				regions and fielded teams to compete in tournaments.
				<lb />
				Denying to any one of the said six members the
				<lb />
				privilege of full membership of the BCCI would,
				<lb />
				according to Mr. Venugopal, violate Article 19(1)(c)
				<lb />
				of the Constitution.
				<lb />
				So also, the termination of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				membership
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				other
				<lb />
				full
				<lb />
				members
				<lb />
				namely
				<lb />
				Association of Indian Universities, Railways Sports
				<lb />
				Promotion Board, Services Sports Control Board was
				<lb />
				also not justified having regard to the fact that
				<lb />
				these members had contributed to the development of
				<lb />
				cricketing activities in the country, although some
				<lb />
				of them did not have any territory nor did they
				<lb />
				field teams. In support of his submission that the
				<lb />
				recommended change in the composition of BCCI would
				<lb />
				violate Article 19(1)(c),
				<lb />
				Mr. Venugopal placed
				<lb />
				heavy reliance upon the judgment of this Court in
				<lb />
				Damyanti Naranga v. The Union of India And Others,
				<lb />
				1971 (3) SCR 840.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				47. Mr. Kapil Sibal followed by Mr. Shyam Divan, Mr.
				<lb />
				Arvind
				<lb />
				Datar,
				<lb />
				Mr.
				<lb />
				Maninder
				<lb />
				Singh,
				<lb />
				Mr.
				<lb />
				B.H.
				<lb />
				Marlapalle, counsel appearing for the intervening
				<lb />
				full members mentioned above, adopted the submission
				<lb />
				of Mr.Venugopal and strenuously argued that the
				<lb />
				proposed change in the composition of BCCI would
				<lb />
				adversely affect the interest of those who had been
				<lb />
				members of the BCCI since the beginning, no matter
				<lb />
				some of them did not have a territory or a team to
				<lb />
				field, while some of them did not receive any
				<lb />
				monetary grant from BCCI and some others had club
				<lb />
				facilities other than cricketing activities. It was
				<lb />
				urged that grant of membership or a vote in the BCCI
				<lb />
				to each State of the country may be a laudable
				<lb />
				objective to ensure promotion of cricketing activity
				<lb />
				even in the States where the same has not, during
				<lb />
				the past 60 years or so, taken off, yet removal of
				<lb />
				those who have contributed to such activities in a
				<lb />
				big way apart from founding the BCCI itself cannot
				<lb />
				be justified.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				48. Mr.
				<lb />
				Vikas
				<lb />
				Mehta
				<lb />
				appearing
				<lb />
				for
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				respondent-Cricket Association of Bihar and Mr.
				<lb />
				Manish Tiwari appearing for Mr. Bishan Singh Bedi
				<lb />
				and Mr.Kirti Azad and Mr. Rajesh Mahale appearing
				<lb />
				for U.T Cricket Association, Chandigarh contended
				<lb />
				that the recommendations made by the Committee are
				<lb />
				well meaning and could go a long way in reforming
				<lb />
				the BCCI structurally as well as professionally. It
				<lb />
				was urged that findings of the Committee regarding
				<lb />
				the ills affecting the BCCI have not been questioned
				<lb />
				by the BCCI or by any intervenor. If those findings
				<lb />
				were correct as they indeed are, the proposed
				<lb />
				reforms become inevitable and ought to be introduced
				<lb />
				to save the game from losing its popularity in the
				<lb />
				Indian sub continent. It was argued by Mr. Mehta
				<lb />
				that Article 19(1)(c), is in no way violated in case
				<lb />
				the recommendations made by the Committee in regard
				<lb />
				to the reform and the composition of the BCCI are
				<lb />
				accepted and directed to be implemented.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				49. We have given our anxious consideration to the
				<lb />
				submissions made at the Bar.
				<lb />
				We may, before
				<lb />
				adverting to the rival submissions urged before us,
				<lb />
				point out two distinct aspects that need to be kept
				<lb />
				in mind while addressing the issues raised before
				<lb />
				us. The first is that the proceedings that led to
				<lb />
				the setting-up of the Committee arose out of a
				<lb />
				public interest petition. The directions issued by
				<lb />
				this Court proceeded on a clear finding recorded by
				<lb />
				this Court that even when BCCI is not a state within
				<lb />
				the meaning of Article 12 of the Constitution of
				<lb />
				India, it is amenable to the jurisdiction of the
				<lb />
				High Court since it discharges public functions.
				<lb />
				That part of the controversy stands concluded by
				<lb />
				judgment of this Court in the earlier round and
				<lb />
				cannot be reopened no matter Mr. Venugopal made a
				<lb />
				feeble attempt to do so by making a reference to the
				<lb />
				Constitution Bench judgment of this Court in Zee
				<lb />
				Telefilms Ltd. v. Union of India (2005) 4 SCC 649.
				<lb />
				All that we need mention is that while holding BCCI
				<lb />
				to be amenable to the writ jurisdiction of the
				<lb />
				Courts, we have taken note of the pronouncement of
				<lb />
				this Court in Zee Telefilms case (supra).
				<lb />
				This is
				<lb />
				evident from the following passages:
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;29. It was then argued that the Board
				<lb />
				discharges public duties which are in the
				<lb />
				nature of State functions. Elaborating on this
				<lb />
				argument it was pointed out that the Board
				<lb />
				selects
				<lb />
				a
				<lb />
				team
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				represent
				<lb />
				India
				<lb />
				in
				<lb />
				international matches. The Board makes rules
				<lb />
				that govern the activities of the cricket
				<lb />
				players, umpires and other persons involved in
				<lb />
				the activities of cricket. These, according to
				<lb />
				the petitioner, are all in the nature of State
				<lb />
				functions and an entity which discharges such
				<lb />
				functions can only be an instrumentality of
				<lb />
				State, therefore, the Board falls within the
				<lb />
				definition of State for the purpose of Article
				<lb />
				12. Assuming that the abovementioned functions
				<lb />
				of the Board do amount to public duties or
				<lb />
				State
				<lb />
				functions,
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				question
				<lb />
				for
				<lb />
				our
				<lb />
				consideration is: would this be sufficient to
				<lb />
				hold the Board to be a State for the purpose
				<lb />
				of Article 12. While considering this aspect
				<lb />
				of the argument of the petitioner, it should
				<lb />
				be borne in mind that the State/Union has not
				<lb />
				chosen the Board to perform these duties nor
				<lb />
				has it legally authorised the Board to carry
				<lb />
				out
				<lb />
				these
				<lb />
				functions
				<lb />
				under
				<lb />
				any
				<lb />
				law
				<lb />
				or
				<lb />
				agreement. It has chosen to leave the
				<lb />
				activities of cricket to be controlled by
				<lb />
				private bodies out of such bodies&apos; own
				<lb />
				volition
				<lb />
				(self-
				<lb />
				arrogated).
				<lb />
				In
				<lb />
				such
				<lb />
				circumstances when the actions of the Board
				<lb />
				are
				<lb />
				not
				<lb />
				actions
				<lb />
				as
				<lb />
				an
				<lb />
				authorised
				<lb />
				representative of the State, can it be said
				<lb />
				that the Board is discharging State functions?
				<lb />
				The answer should be no. In the absence of any
				<lb />
				authorisation, if a private body chooses to
				<lb />
				discharge any such function which is not
				<lb />
				prohibited by law then it would be incorrect
				<lb />
				to hold that such action of the body would
				<lb />
				make it an instrumentality of the State. The
				<lb />
				Union of India has tried to make out a case
				<lb />
				that the Board discharges these functions
				<lb />
				because of the de facto recognition granted by
				<lb />
				it to the Board under the guidelines framed by
				<lb />
				it but the Board has denied the same. In this
				<lb />
				regard we must hold that the Union of India
				<lb />
				has failed to prove that there is any
				<lb />
				recognition by the Union of India under the
				<lb />
				guidelines framed by it and that the Board is
				<lb />
				discharging these functions on its own as an
				<lb />
				autonomous body.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				xxx
				<lb />
				xxx
				<lb />
				xxx
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				31. Be that as it may, it cannot be denied
				<lb />
				that the Board does discharge some duties like
				<lb />
				the selection of an Indian cricket team,
				<lb />
				controlling the activities of the players and
				<lb />
				others involved in the game of cricket. These
				<lb />
				activities can be said to be akin to public
				<lb />
				duties or State functions and if there is any
				<lb />
				violation of any constitutional or statutory
				<lb />
				obligation or rights of other citizens, the
				<lb />
				aggrieved party may not have a relief by way
				<lb />
				of a petition under Article 32. But that does
				<lb />
				not mean that the violator of such right would
				<lb />
				go scot-free merely because it or he is not a
				<lb />
				State. Under the Indian jurisprudence there is
				<lb />
				always a just remedy for violation of a right
				<lb />
				of a citizen. Though the remedy under Article
				<lb />
				32 is not available, an aggrieved party can
				<lb />
				always seek a remedy under the ordinary course
				<lb />
				of law or by way of a writ petition
				<lb />
				under Article 226 of the Constitution which is
				<lb />
				much wider than Article 32.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				50. The second aspect that needs to be borne in mind
				<lb />
				is that neither BCCI nor anyone else has assailed
				<lb />
				the findings recorded by the Committee insofar as
				<lb />
				the deep rooted malaise that pervades in the working
				<lb />
				of the BCCI is concerned. We have referred at great
				<lb />
				length to the findings of the Committee in this
				<lb />
				regard which findings have not been assailed before
				<lb />
				us either in the affidavits filed or in the course
				<lb />
				of arguments at the bar.
				<lb />
				That being so, the
				<lb />
				question is whether reforms which the Committee has
				<lb />
				recommended
				<lb />
				after
				<lb />
				elaborate
				<lb />
				deliberations
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				consideration of all relevant factors can be stalled
				<lb />
				on the ground that the same violate Article 19(1)(c)
				<lb />
				of the Constitution or on the ground that such
				<lb />
				reforms will cause any injustice either to the cause
				<lb />
				of the game or to those who have been associated in
				<lb />
				promoting the same.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				51. With the above two aspects in mind, let us now
				<lb />
				examine whether the recommendations of the Committee
				<lb />
				have the tendency to violate Article 19(1)(c) or any
				<lb />
				other provision of the Constitution.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				52. Article 19(1)(c) of the Constitution of India
				<lb />
				guarantees to the citizens of this country the right
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				form
				<lb />
				associations,
				<lb />
				unions
				<lb />
				or
				<lb />
				cooperative
				<lb />
				societies. It reads:
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;19. Protection of certain rights regarding
				<lb />
				freedom of speech, etc. -(1) All citizens
				<lb />
				shall have the right -
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				(a) xxx xxx xxx
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				(b) xxx xxx xxx
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				(c) to form associations or unions or
				<lb />
				cooperative societies
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				(d) xxx xxx xxx
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				(e) xxx xxx xxx
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				(f) xxx xxx xxx
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				(g) xxx xxx xxx&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				53. The right, it is evident from the above, is
				<lb />
				guaranteed in favour of citizens and citizens alone.
				<lb />
				Recourse to Article 19(1)(C) is not, therefore, open
				<lb />
				to juristic or other persons and entities who are
				<lb />
				non-citizens. Confronted with this position, it was
				<lb />
				argued on behalf of the BCCI and intervening
				<lb />
				associations that even when the provisions of
				<lb />
				Article 19(1)(c) may not be available to the State
				<lb />
				Cricket Associations who are members of BCCI , yet
				<lb />
				the recommendations made by the Committee, if
				<lb />
				accepted, would prejudicially affect the citizens
				<lb />
				who
				<lb />
				have
				<lb />
				come
				<lb />
				together
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				form
				<lb />
				such
				<lb />
				State
				<lb />
				associations. It was contended that this Court could
				<lb />
				in its discretion lift the veil to determine whether
				<lb />
				the right of any citizen/citizens was affected and
				<lb />
				grant suitable relief if the answer was in the
				<lb />
				affirmative. It was contended that once this Court
				<lb />
				decides to do so it will find that citizens
				<lb />
				comprising the State Cricket Associations are the
				<lb />
				ones actually affected by the recommendations in
				<lb />
				question.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				54. We regret our inability to accept the submission
				<lb />
				so vehemently urged before us by learned Counsel for
				<lb />
				the BCCI and the State Cricket Associations. We say
				<lb />
				so, firstly because no citizen has come forward in
				<lb />
				the present proceedings or in the earlier round to
				<lb />
				complain of the violation of any fundamental right
				<lb />
				guaranteed
				<lb />
				under
				<lb />
				Article
				<lb />
				19(1)(c)
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				Constitution. Secondly and more importantly because
				<lb />
				the recommendations do not, in our opinion, affect
				<lb />
				the composition of the State Cricket Associations in
				<lb />
				any manner. Citizens who have come together to form
				<lb />
				the State Associations continue to associate as
				<lb />
				before with no change in their internal composition.
				<lb />
				If that be so as it indeed is the right guaranteed
				<lb />
				under Article 19(1)(c) stands exercised, which
				<lb />
				exercise would continue to enjoy the protection of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				constitutional
				<lb />
				guarantee
				<lb />
				till
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				Association/Union or co-operative Society, as the
				<lb />
				case may be, continues to exist. What is, however,
				<lb />
				important is that the right under Article 19(1)(c)
				<lb />
				does not extend to guaranting to the citizens the
				<lb />
				concomitant right to pursue their goals and objects
				<lb />
				uninhibited by any regulatory or other control. The
				<lb />
				legal position in this regard is settled by several
				<lb />
				decisions of this Court to which we may gainfully
				<lb />
				refer at this stage.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				55. In All India Bank Employees Association v. The
				<lb />
				National Industrial Tribunal (Bank Disputes), Bombay
				<lb />
				and Ors., AIR 1962 SC 171 a Constitution Bench of
				<lb />
				this Court while explaining the scope of Article
				<lb />
				19(1)(c) drew a distinction between the right to
				<lb />
				form an association/union and the right to carry on
				<lb />
				any such business or other activity chosen by such
				<lb />
				union or Association.
				<lb />
				This Court declared that
				<lb />
				while the right to form a union/Association is
				<lb />
				guaranteed under Article 19(1)(c), the concomitant
				<lb />
				right of the members of the Association/Union would
				<lb />
				be governed by other provisions of Article 19. This
				<lb />
				Court held:
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;If an association were formed for the purpose
				<lb />
				of carrying on business, the right to form it
				<lb />
				86
				<lb />
				would be guaranteed by sub-clause (c) of
				<lb />
				clause (1) of Article 19 subject to any law
				<lb />
				restricting that right conforming to clause
				<lb />
				(4) of Article 19.
				<lb />
				As regards its business
				<lb />
				activities, however, and the achievement of
				<lb />
				the objects for which it was brought into
				<lb />
				existence,
				<lb />
				its
				<lb />
				rights
				<lb />
				would
				<lb />
				be
				<lb />
				those
				<lb />
				guaranteed by sub-clause (g) of clause (1) of
				<lb />
				Article 19 subject to any relevant law on the
				<lb />
				matter conforming to clause (6) of Article 19;
				<lb />
				while the property which the association
				<lb />
				acquires or possesses would be protected by
				<lb />
				sub-clause (f) of clause (1) of Article 19
				<lb />
				subject to legislation within the limits laid
				<lb />
				down by clause (5) of Article 19.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				While the right to form a union is
				<lb />
				guaranteed by sub-clause (c), the right of the
				<lb />
				members of the association to meet would be
				<lb />
				guaranteed by sub-clause (b), their right to
				<lb />
				move from place to place within India by
				<lb />
				sub-clause (d), their right to discuss their
				<lb />
				problems and to propagate their views by
				<lb />
				sub-clause (a), their right to hold property
				<lb />
				would be that guaranteed by sub-clause (f) and
				<lb />
				so on -each of these freedoms being subject
				<lb />
				to such restrictions as might properly be
				<lb />
				imposed by clauses (2) to (6) of Article 19 as
				<lb />
				might be appropriate in the context.
				<lb />
				It is
				<lb />
				one thing to interpret each of the freedoms
				<lb />
				guaranteed by the several articles in Part III
				<lb />
				in a fair and liberal sense, it is quite
				<lb />
				another to read each guaranteed right as
				<lb />
				involving or including concomitant rights
				<lb />
				necessary to achieve the object which might be
				<lb />
				supposed to underlie the grant of each of
				<lb />
				those rights.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				56. In Tata Engineering and Locomotive Company Ltd.
				<lb />
				v. State of Bihar, AIR 1965 SC 40 this Court
				<lb />
				reiterated that Article 19 applies to citizens and
				<lb />
				not persons as was the position with Article 14 of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				Constitution.
				<lb />
				The
				<lb />
				effect
				<lb />
				is
				<lb />
				that
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				provisions of Article 19 can be claimed by citizens
				<lb />
				only and not by corporations. This Court held that
				<lb />
				the fundamental right to form an association or
				<lb />
				Union cannot be coupled with the fundamental right
				<lb />
				to carry on any trade or business. As soon as
				<lb />
				citizens formed a company, the right guaranteed to
				<lb />
				them by Article 19(1)(c) stood exercised.
				<lb />
				After
				<lb />
				the incorporation of the company the business
				<lb />
				carried on by it is the business of the corporation
				<lb />
				and not the business of the citizen.
				<lb />
				The Court
				<lb />
				held:
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;28. That being the position with regard to
				<lb />
				the doctrine of the veil of a corporation and
				<lb />
				the principle that the said veil can be lifted
				<lb />
				in some cases, the question which arises for
				<lb />
				our decision is; can we lift the veil of the
				<lb />
				petitioner and say that it is the shareholders
				<lb />
				who are really moving the Court under Article
				<lb />
				32, and so, the existence of the legal and
				<lb />
				juristic separate entity of the petitioners as
				<lb />
				a corporation or as a company should not make
				<lb />
				the petitions filed by them under Article 32
				<lb />
				incompetent. We do not think we can answer
				<lb />
				this question in the affirmative. No doubt,
				<lb />
				the complaint made by the petitioners is that
				<lb />
				their fundamental rights are infringed and it
				<lb />
				is a truism to say that this Court as the
				<lb />
				guardian of the fundamental rights of the
				<lb />
				citizens will always attempt to safeguard the
				<lb />
				said fundamental rights; but having regard to
				<lb />
				the decision of this Court in State Trading
				<lb />
				Corporation of India Ltd. 1 , we do not see how
				<lb />
				we can legitimately entertain the petitioners&apos;
				<lb />
				plea in the present petitions, because if
				<lb />
				their plea was upheld, it would really mean
				<lb />
				that what the corporations or the companies
				<lb />
				cannot achieve directly, can be achieved by
				<lb />
				them indirectly by relying upon the doctrine
				<lb />
				of lifting the veil. If the corporations and
				<lb />
				companies are not citizens, it means that the
				<lb />
				Constitution intended that they should not get
				<lb />
				the benefit of Article 19. It is no doubt
				<lb />
				suggested by the petitioners that though
				<lb />
				Article 19 is confined to citizens, the
				<lb />
				Constitution-makers may have thought that in
				<lb />
				dealing with the claims of corporations to
				<lb />
				invoke the provisions of Article 19, courts
				<lb />
				would act upon the doctrine of lifting the
				<lb />
				veil and would not treat the attempts of the
				<lb />
				corporations in that behalf as falling outside
				<lb />
				Article 19. We do not think this argument is
				<lb />
				well founded. The effect of confining Article
				<lb />
				19 to citizens as distinguished from persons
				<lb />
				to whom other Articles like 14 apply, clearly
				<lb />
				must be that it is only citizens to whom the
				<lb />
				rights under Article 19 are guaranteed. If the
				<lb />
				legislature intends that the benefit of
				<lb />
				Article 19 should be made available to the
				<lb />
				corporations, it would not be difficult for it
				<lb />
				to adopt a proper measure in that behalf by
				<lb />
				enlarging
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				definition
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				prescribed by the Citizenship Act passed by
				<lb />
				Parliament by virtue of the powers conferred
				<lb />
				on it by Articles 10 and 11. On the other
				<lb />
				hand, the fact that the Parliament has not
				<lb />
				chosen to make any such provision indicates
				<lb />
				that it was not the intention of Parliament to
				<lb />
				treat corporations as citizens. Therefore, it
				<lb />
				seems to us that in view of the decision of
				<lb />
				this Court in the case of State Trading
				<lb />
				Corporation of India Ltd. 1 , the petitioners
				<lb />
				cannot be heard to any that their shareholders
				<lb />
				should be allowed to file the present
				<lb />
				petitions on the ground that, in substance,
				<lb />
				the corporations and companies are nothing
				<lb />
				more than associations of shareholders and
				<lb />
				members thereof. In our opinion, therefore,
				<lb />
				the argument that in the present petition we
				<lb />
				would be justified in lifting the veil cannot
				<lb />
				be sustained.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				29. Mr Palkhivala sought to draw a distinction
				<lb />
				between the right of a citizen to carry on
				<lb />
				trade or business which is contemplated by
				<lb />
				Article l9(1)(g) from his right to form
				<lb />
				associations or unions contemplated by Article
				<lb />
				l9(1)(c). He argued that Article 19(1)(c)
				<lb />
				enables
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				citizens
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				choose
				<lb />
				their
				<lb />
				instruments or agents for carrying on the
				<lb />
				business which it is their fundamental right
				<lb />
				to carry on. If citizens decide to set up a
				<lb />
				corporation or a company as their agent for
				<lb />
				the purpose of carrying on trade or business,
				<lb />
				that is a right which is guaranteed to them
				<lb />
				under Article 19(1)(c). Basing himself on this
				<lb />
				distinction between the two rights guaranteed
				<lb />
				by Article l9(1)(g) and (c) respectively, Mr
				<lb />
				Palkhivala somewhat ingeniously contended that
				<lb />
				we should not hesitate to lift the veil,
				<lb />
				because by looking at the substance of the
				<lb />
				matter, we would really be giving effect to
				<lb />
				the two fundamental rights guaranteed by
				<lb />
				Article l9(l). We are not impressed by this
				<lb />
				argument either. The fundamental right to form
				<lb />
				an association cannot in this manner be
				<lb />
				coupled with the fundamental right to carry on
				<lb />
				any trade or business. As has been held by
				<lb />
				this Court in all-India Bank Employees&apos;
				<lb />
				Association v. National Industrial Tribunal,
				<lb />
				the argument which is thus attractively
				<lb />
				presented before us overlooks the fact that
				<lb />
				Article 19, as contrasted with certain other
				<lb />
				articles
				<lb />
				like
				<lb />
				Articles
				<lb />
				26,
				<lb />
				29
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				30
				<lb />
				guarantees rights to the citizens as such, and
				<lb />
				associations
				<lb />
				cannot
				<lb />
				lay
				<lb />
				claim
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				fundamental rights guaranteed by that article
				<lb />
				solely on the basis of their being an
				<lb />
				aggregation of citizens, that is to say, the
				<lb />
				right of the citizens composing the body. The
				<lb />
				respective rights guaranteed by Article 19(1)
				<lb />
				cannot be combined as suggested by Mr
				<lb />
				Palkhivala, but must be asserted each in its
				<lb />
				own way and within its own limits; the sweep
				<lb />
				of the several rights is no doubt wide, but
				<lb />
				the combination of any of those two rights
				<lb />
				would not justify a claim such as is made by
				<lb />
				Mr Palkhivala in the present petitions. As
				<lb />
				soon as citizens form a company the right
				<lb />
				guaranteed to them by Article l9(l)( c ) has
				<lb />
				been exercised and no restraint has been
				<lb />
				placed on that right and no infringement of
				<lb />
				that right is made. Once a company or a
				<lb />
				corporation is formed, the business which is
				<lb />
				carried on by the said company or corporation
				<lb />
				is the business of the company or corporation
				<lb />
				and is not the business of the citizens who
				<lb />
				get the company or corporation formed or
				<lb />
				incorporated,
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				rights
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				incorporated body must be judged on that
				<lb />
				footing and cannot be judged on the assumption
				<lb />
				that they are the rights attributable to the
				<lb />
				business of individual citizens. Therefore, we
				<lb />
				are satisfied that the argument based on the
				<lb />
				distinction between the two rights guaranteed
				<lb />
				by Article l9(l)(c) and (g) and the effect of
				<lb />
				their combination cannot take the petitioners&apos;
				<lb />
				case very far when they seek to invoke the
				<lb />
				doctrine that the veil of the corporation
				<lb />
				should be lifted. That is why we have come to
				<lb />
				the conclusion that the petitions filed by the
				<lb />
				petitioners are incompetent under Article 32,
				<lb />
				even though in each of these petitions one or
				<lb />
				two of the shareholders of the petitioning
				<lb />
				companies or corporation have joined.&quot;
				<lb />
				(emphasis supplied)
				<lb />
			</item>


			<p>
				57. In D.A.V. College v. State of Punjab, 1971 (2)
				<lb />
				SCC 269 this Court was examining the validity of a
				<lb />
				legislation
				<lb />
				that
				<lb />
				provided
				<lb />
				for
				<lb />
				compulsory
				<lb />
				affiliation of religious or linguistic minority
				<lb />
				institutions to the University.
				<lb />
				It was contended
				<lb />
				that the requirement of compulsory affiliation was
				<lb />
				in
				<lb />
				violation
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				their
				<lb />
				right
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				freedom
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				association guaranteed under Article 19(1)(c).
				<lb />
				This court, however, rejected that contention and
				<lb />
				held that the notification providing for compulsory
				<lb />
				affiliation with the University did not in any
				<lb />
				manner interfere or attempt to interfere with the
				<lb />
				petitioners&apos; right to form an association under
				<lb />
				Article 19(1)(c).
				<lb />
				This Court said :
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;29. It is contended that the compulsory
				<lb />
				affiliation
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				petitioners
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				University affects their fundamental right of
				<lb />
				freedom of association as guaranteed under
				<lb />
				Article 19(1)(c), therefore the notification
				<lb />
				under Section 5(3) affiliating them to the
				<lb />
				University is bad. It is also urged that since
				<lb />
				the words &quot;associated with and admitted to any
				<lb />
				privileges&quot; are used in Section 5 of the Act,
				<lb />
				it
				<lb />
				would
				<lb />
				mean
				<lb />
				that
				<lb />
				petitioners
				<lb />
				are
				<lb />
				92
				<lb />
				compulsorily formed into an Association with
				<lb />
				the University. This contention however is
				<lb />
				countered by the respondents who point out
				<lb />
				that the freedom of association under Article
				<lb />
				19(1)(c) implies association between citizens
				<lb />
				while in the case of the petitioners what is
				<lb />
				sought to be affected is an affiliation with
				<lb />
				the University which is a corporate body.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				30. The right to form an association implies
				<lb />
				that several individuals get together and form
				<lb />
				voluntarily an association with a common aim,
				<lb />
				legitimate purpose and having a community of
				<lb />
				interests. It was sought to be suggested that
				<lb />
				the compulsory affiliation with the University
				<lb />
				affects
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				aims
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				objects
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				association, as such its freedom is infringed.
				<lb />
				There is in our view a fallacy in this
				<lb />
				argument which on earlier occasions had also
				<lb />
				been repelled. In All India Bank Employees
				<lb />
				Association v. National Industrial Tribunal,
				<lb />
				it was observed that the right guaranteed
				<lb />
				under Article 19(1)(c) does not carry with it
				<lb />
				a concomitant right that the Associations
				<lb />
				shall achieve their object such that any
				<lb />
				interference in such achievement by any law
				<lb />
				would be unconstitutional unless it could be
				<lb />
				justified under Article 19(4) as being in the
				<lb />
				interests of public order or morality. The
				<lb />
				right under Article 19(1)(c) extends inter
				<lb />
				alia to the formation of an Association or
				<lb />
				Union.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				58. In Smt. Damyanti Naranga v. the Union of India
				<lb />
				Ors., 1971 (1) SCC 678 heavy reliance whereupon was
				<lb />
				placed by Mr. Venugopal, also a Constitution Bench
				<lb />
				of this Court clearly held that the right to form
				<lb />
				an association implied that the person forming the
				<lb />
				association/Union had the right to continue to be
				<lb />
				associated with only those whom they voluntarily
				<lb />
				admit in the Association. This Court declared that
				<lb />
				the right under Article 19(1)(c) was not confined
				<lb />
				to the initial stage of forming of an association
				<lb />
				for any such restricted interpretation of that
				<lb />
				provision would render the right meaningless in a
				<lb />
				situation where no sooner the association is
				<lb />
				formed, a law is passed interfering with its
				<lb />
				composition so that the association formed may not
				<lb />
				be able to function at all.
				<lb />
				This Court, in that
				<lb />
				view, held that the right will be rendered
				<lb />
				ineffective until it is held to include the right
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				continue
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				association/union
				<lb />
				with
				<lb />
				its
				<lb />
				composition as voluntarily agreed upon by the
				<lb />
				persons forming the association.
				<lb />
				This Court
				<lb />
				affirmed the view taken in its earlier decision in
				<lb />
				O.K. Ghosh and another v. E.X. Joseph, AIR 1963 SC
				<lb />
				812, and observed:
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;6. It was argued that the right guaranteed by
				<lb />
				Article
				<lb />
				19(1)(c)
				<lb />
				is
				<lb />
				only
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				form
				<lb />
				an
				<lb />
				94
				<lb />
				Page 95
				<lb />
				association and, consequently, any regulation
				<lb />
				of the affairs of the Association, after it
				<lb />
				has been formed, will not amount to a breach
				<lb />
				of that right. It is true that it has been
				<lb />
				held by this Court that, after an Association
				<lb />
				has been formed and the right under Article
				<lb />
				19(1)(c) has been exercised by the members
				<lb />
				forming it, they have no right to claim that
				<lb />
				its activities must also be permitted to be
				<lb />
				carried on in the manner they desire. Those
				<lb />
				cases are, however, inapplicable to the
				<lb />
				present case. The Act does not merely regulate
				<lb />
				the administration of the affairs of the
				<lb />
				Society; what it does is to alter the
				<lb />
				composition of the Society itself as we have
				<lb />
				indicated above. The result of this change in
				<lb />
				composition
				<lb />
				is
				<lb />
				that
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				members,
				<lb />
				who
				<lb />
				voluntarily formed the Association, are now
				<lb />
				compelled to act in that Association with
				<lb />
				other members who have been imposed as members
				<lb />
				by the Act and in whose admission to
				<lb />
				membership they had no say. Such alteration in
				<lb />
				the composition of the Association itself
				<lb />
				clearly interferes with the right to continue
				<lb />
				to function as members of the Association
				<lb />
				which was voluntarily formed by the original
				<lb />
				founders. The right to form an association, in
				<lb />
				our opinion, necessarily implies that the
				<lb />
				persons forming the Association have also the
				<lb />
				right to continue to be associated with only
				<lb />
				those whom they voluntarily admit in the
				<lb />
				Association. Any law, by which members are
				<lb />
				introduced
				<lb />
				in
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				voluntary
				<lb />
				Association
				<lb />
				without any option being given to the members
				<lb />
				to keep them out, or any law which takes away
				<lb />
				the membership of those who have voluntarily
				<lb />
				joined it, will be a law violating the right
				<lb />
				to form an association. If we were to accept
				<lb />
				the submission that the right guaranteed by
				<lb />
				Article 19(1)(c) is confined to the initial
				<lb />
				stage of forming an Association and does not
				<lb />
				protect the right to continue the Association
				<lb />
				with the membership either chosen by the
				<lb />
				founders or regulated by rules made by the
				<lb />
				Association
				<lb />
				itself,
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				right
				<lb />
				would
				<lb />
				be
				<lb />
				meaningless because, as soon as an Association
				<lb />
				is formed, a law may be passed interfering
				<lb />
				with its composition, so that the Association
				<lb />
				formed may not be able to function at all. The
				<lb />
				right can be effective only if it is held to
				<lb />
				include within it the right to continue the
				<lb />
				Association
				<lb />
				with
				<lb />
				its
				<lb />
				composition
				<lb />
				as
				<lb />
				voluntarily agreed upon by the persons forming
				<lb />
				the Association.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				59. Reference may also be made to a very recent
				<lb />
				decision of this Court in Dharam Dutt and Ors. v.
				<lb />
				Union of India &amp; Ors., (2004) 1 SCC 712. That was a
				<lb />
				case where the constitutional validity of the
				<lb />
				Indian Council of World Affairs Ordinance, 2001 was
				<lb />
				under challenge in a petition filed under Article
				<lb />
				32 of the Constitution. One of the issues that came
				<lb />
				up for consideration was whether the legislation
				<lb />
				violated the right guaranteed under Article 19(1)
				<lb />
				(c).
				<lb />
				Relying upon the decisions in Maneka Gandhi
				<lb />
				v. Union of India, (1978) 1 SCC 248; All India Bank
				<lb />
				Employees&apos;
				<lb />
				Association
				<lb />
				v.
				<lb />
				National
				<lb />
				Industrial
				<lb />
				Tribunal, AIR 1962 SC 171 and; Damyanti Naranga v.
				<lb />
				Union of India, 1971 (1) SCC 678 this Court held
				<lb />
				that the right under Article 19(1)(c) does not
				<lb />
				include the right of the association or union so
				<lb />
				formed to achieve its objective whether of running
				<lb />
				an institution or otherwise. The Court said:
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;From a reading of the two decisions, namely,
				<lb />
				Smt.
				<lb />
				Maneka
				<lb />
				Gandhi&apos;s
				<lb />
				case
				<lb />
				(supra),
				<lb />
				(seven-Judges Bench) and All India Bank
				<lb />
				Employees
				<lb />
				Association&apos;s
				<lb />
				case
				<lb />
				(supra),
				<lb />
				(five-Judges Bench), the following principles
				<lb />
				emerge : (i) a right to form associations or
				<lb />
				unions does not include within its ken as a
				<lb />
				fundamental right a right to form associations
				<lb />
				or unions for achieving a particular object or
				<lb />
				running a particular institution, the same
				<lb />
				being a concomitant or concomitant to a
				<lb />
				concomitant of a fundamental right, but not
				<lb />
				the fundamental right itself. The associations
				<lb />
				or unions of citizens cannot further claim as
				<lb />
				a fundamental right that it must also be able
				<lb />
				to achieve the purpose for which it has come
				<lb />
				into existence so that any interference with
				<lb />
				such
				<lb />
				achievement
				<lb />
				by
				<lb />
				law
				<lb />
				shall
				<lb />
				be
				<lb />
				unconstitutional, unless the same could be
				<lb />
				justified under Article 19(4) as being a
				<lb />
				restriction imposed in the interest of public
				<lb />
				order or morality; (ii) A right to form
				<lb />
				associations guaranteed under Article 19 (1)
				<lb />
				(c) does not imply the fulfillment of every
				<lb />
				object of an association as it would be
				<lb />
				contradictory to the scheme underlying the
				<lb />
				text and the frame of the several fundamental
				<lb />
				rights guaranteed by Part III and particularly
				<lb />
				by the scheme of the guarantees conferred by
				<lb />
				sub-clauses (a) to (g) of clause (1) of
				<lb />
				Article 19; (iii) While right to form an
				<lb />
				association is to be tested by reference to
				<lb />
				Article
				<lb />
				19(1)(c)
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				validity
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				restriction thereon by reference to Article
				<lb />
				19(4), once the individual citizens have
				<lb />
				formed an association and carry on some
				<lb />
				activity,
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				validity
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				legislation
				<lb />
				restricting the activities of the association
				<lb />
				shall have to be judged by reference to
				<lb />
				Article
				<lb />
				19(1)(g)
				<lb />
				read
				<lb />
				with
				<lb />
				19(6).
				<lb />
				A
				<lb />
				restriction
				<lb />
				on
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				activities
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				association is not a restriction on the
				<lb />
				activities of the individual citizens forming
				<lb />
				membership of the association; and (iv) A
				<lb />
				perusal of Article 19 with certain other
				<lb />
				Articles like 26, 29 and 30 shows that while
				<lb />
				Article 19 grants rights to the citizens as
				<lb />
				such, the associations can lay claim to the
				<lb />
				fundamental rights guaranteed by Article 19
				<lb />
				solely on the basis of there being an
				<lb />
				aggregation of citizens, i.e., the rights of
				<lb />
				the citizens composing the body. As the stream
				<lb />
				can
				<lb />
				rise
				<lb />
				no
				<lb />
				higher
				<lb />
				than
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				source,
				<lb />
				associations of citizens cannot lay claim to
				<lb />
				rights not open to citizens or claim freedom
				<lb />
				from restrictions to which the citizens
				<lb />
				composing it are subject.&quot;
				<lb />
				(emphasis supplied)
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				60. There
				<lb />
				is,
				<lb />
				in
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				light
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				above
				<lb />
				authoritative pronouncements, no room for any doubt
				<lb />
				that the right guaranteed under Article 19(1)(c)
				<lb />
				cannot be claimed by an association or union or a
				<lb />
				co-operative Society as is sought to be done in the
				<lb />
				case at hand, even when the right to form an
				<lb />
				association or union or cooperative society extends
				<lb />
				to the continued existence of such association or
				<lb />
				union or cooperative society with its original
				<lb />
				98
				<lb />
				Page 99
				<lb />
				voluntary composition.
				<lb />
				But the right does not
				<lb />
				extend so far as to include the right of any such
				<lb />
				association or union or cooperative society to
				<lb />
				achieve its objects or to conduct its business
				<lb />
				unhindered by any regulatory or other control.
				<lb />
				Anything beyond the protection of the original
				<lb />
				composition
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				association
				<lb />
				or
				<lb />
				union
				<lb />
				or
				<lb />
				cooperative society would fall outside Article 19(1)
				<lb />
				(C) and shall be governed by other clauses of
				<lb />
				Article 19 of the Constitution. For instance, the
				<lb />
				right of the association or union or cooperative
				<lb />
				society to conduct its business or pursue its
				<lb />
				objects shall be regulated under Article 19(1)(g)
				<lb />
				read with sub-Article (6) of the Constitution.
				<lb />
				So
				<lb />
				also, the right to move freely throughout the
				<lb />
				territory of India shall be governed by Article
				<lb />
				19(1)(d)
				<lb />
				read
				<lb />
				with
				<lb />
				sub-Article
				<lb />
				5
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				Constitution. Suffice it to say that so long as the
				<lb />
				initial voluntary composition of the State Cricket
				<lb />
				Associations who are complaining of the breach of
				<lb />
				their
				<lb />
				right
				<lb />
				under
				<lb />
				Article
				<lb />
				19(1)(c)
				<lb />
				remains
				<lb />
				unaffected, there is no violation of what is
				<lb />
				guaranteed by Article 19(1)(c).
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				61. Seen in the backdrop of the above, the
				<lb />
				recommendations made by the Committee in the instant
				<lb />
				do not interfere with or alter the composition of
				<lb />
				the State Associations.
				<lb />
				Individual citizens who
				<lb />
				came together to form the State Associations have
				<lb />
				not been asked to discontinue their association nor
				<lb />
				do the recommendations impose upon their members an
				<lb />
				obligation to associate with others with whom they
				<lb />
				do not wish to associate. Composition of the State
				<lb />
				Cricket Associations remain unaffected, and so does
				<lb />
				the right of those forming such Associations under
				<lb />
				Article 19(1)(c). That being so, the grievance
				<lb />
				sought to be made on behalf of citizens who have
				<lb />
				formed the State Associations does not stand
				<lb />
				scrutiny no matter none of those on whose behalf the
				<lb />
				argument is advanced is before this Court to make
				<lb />
				any such grievance.
				<lb />
				We have, in the light of the
				<lb />
				above, no difficulty in rejecting the first limb of
				<lb />
				the submissions made by learned counsel opposing the
				<lb />
				recommendation of the committee that BCCI shall have
				<lb />
				the Cricket Association from each State as a full
				<lb />
				member.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				62. That brings us to the question whether &quot;One
				<lb />
				State One vote&quot; recommended by the Committee suffers
				<lb />
				from any legal or other infirmity sufficient for
				<lb />
				this Court to reject the same. The recommendation
				<lb />
				made by the Committee has a two-fold impact on the
				<lb />
				current state of affairs in BCCI. The first is the
				<lb />
				reduction of some of the Associations and Clubs from
				<lb />
				the full membership of BCCI to the status of
				<lb />
				Associate
				<lb />
				Members.
				<lb />
				The
				<lb />
				other
				<lb />
				aspect
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				recommendation
				<lb />
				is
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				reduction
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				full
				<lb />
				membership of at least four existing full members to
				<lb />
				the status of associate members from the states of
				<lb />
				Maharashtra and Gujarat.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				63. In the first category, fall five full members
				<lb />
				whose membership should as per the recommendation
				<lb />
				get converted to associate membership. In this
				<lb />
				category fall Railways Sports Promotion Board,
				<lb />
				Association of Indian Universities, Services Sports
				<lb />
				Control Board, National Cricket Club (Kolkata) and
				<lb />
				Cricket Club of India (Bombay). The Committee has
				<lb />
				recommended that these clubs and associations need
				<lb />
				not be continued as full members as they do not
				<lb />
				represent any geographical territory. Two of the
				<lb />
				clubs namely Cricket Club of India and National
				<lb />
				Cricket Club do not even field teams in competitive
				<lb />
				cricket. These two clubs also happen to be
				<lb />
				recreational clubs. The other three clubs mentioned
				<lb />
				above however field teams but do not receive any
				<lb />
				monetary assistance from BCCI. It was contended by
				<lb />
				learned counsel appearing for these clubs that the
				<lb />
				recommendation made by the Committee based entirely
				<lb />
				on the fact that they do not represent a territory
				<lb />
				does not do full justice to them while recommending
				<lb />
				deletion of their full membership from BCCI. It was
				<lb />
				submitted that even when these clubs do not
				<lb />
				represent any geographical area and some of them
				<lb />
				even do not field teams, they should be continued as
				<lb />
				full
				<lb />
				members
				<lb />
				keeping
				<lb />
				in
				<lb />
				view
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				historical
				<lb />
				background leading to the formation of BCCI. We see
				<lb />
				no merit in that contention nor do we see any reason
				<lb />
				to disagree with the recommendation made by the
				<lb />
				committee, who has upon a thorough consideration of
				<lb />
				all facts and circumstances relevant to the working
				<lb />
				of the BCCI, recommended the conversion of the clubs
				<lb />
				and associations without a territory from full
				<lb />
				members to associate members. This is a measure
				<lb />
				which
				<lb />
				has
				<lb />
				been
				<lb />
				recommended
				<lb />
				with
				<lb />
				a
				<lb />
				view
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				structurally streamlining the BCCI to make it more
				<lb />
				responsive and accountable having regard to the
				<lb />
				aspiration of different regions for an equal
				<lb />
				opportunity to participate in the growth and
				<lb />
				promotion of the game in the country. The fact that
				<lb />
				clubs including the Railways Sports Promotion Board,
				<lb />
				Association of Indian Universities and Services
				<lb />
				Sports Control Board do not represent any region nor
				<lb />
				103
				<lb />
				Page 104
				<lb />
				do they receive any monetary benefit is, in our
				<lb />
				view, a good enough reason for converting their full
				<lb />
				membership to associate membership. The conversion
				<lb />
				notwithstanding they shall continue to be associated
				<lb />
				with the growth and promotion of the game, the right
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				vote
				<lb />
				remaining
				<lb />
				confined
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				full
				<lb />
				members,
				<lb />
				representing
				<lb />
				definite
				<lb />
				geographical
				<lb />
				regions
				<lb />
				or
				<lb />
				territories.
				<lb />
				The
				<lb />
				recommendation
				<lb />
				made
				<lb />
				by
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				committee regarding the conversion of the status of
				<lb />
				the above mentioned clubs and associations are,
				<lb />
				therefore, sound and are hereby accepted.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				64. Coming to the second aspect of &quot;One State One
				<lb />
				Vote&quot;, it was argued by learned counsel appearing
				<lb />
				for the intervening clubs from the States of
				<lb />
				Maharashtra
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				Gujarat
				<lb />
				that
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				six
				<lb />
				clubs/associations three each from the two States
				<lb />
				viz. Mumbai Cricket Association, Maharashtra Cricket
				<lb />
				Association, Vidarbha Cricket Association, Gujarat
				<lb />
				Cricket Association, Baroda cricket Association and
				<lb />
				Saurashtra Cricket Association not only represent a
				<lb />
				definite territory and participate in competitive
				<lb />
				cricket by fielding teams but have contributed to
				<lb />
				the development of the game in their regions. It was
				<lb />
				submitted that the recommendations made by the
				<lb />
				committee that BCCI should choose one of the clubs
				<lb />
				to represent the entire state was fraught with
				<lb />
				difficulty and ignored the historical perspective
				<lb />
				and the fact that the these clubs had made
				<lb />
				substantial contribution to the development and
				<lb />
				promotion of cricket in this country. It was,
				<lb />
				therefore, urged that reducing the role of four out
				<lb />
				of the six clubs from full membership to associate
				<lb />
				membership was not a sound proposition and deserved
				<lb />
				to be turned down and the associations allowed to
				<lb />
				continue their position as full members.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				65. The argument advanced by the intervenor clubs
				<lb />
				cannot be lightly brushed aside. It is not disputed
				<lb />
				that three different regions are represented by
				<lb />
				three distinct Associations both in the States of
				<lb />
				Gujarat and Maharashtra. This position has continued
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				exist
				<lb />
				from
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				inception.
				<lb />
				Some
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				clubs/associations, if not all are the founding
				<lb />
				members of BCCI. That being so, a balance has to be
				<lb />
				struck with historical reality and the need for
				<lb />
				adopting
				<lb />
				a
				<lb />
				pragmatic,
				<lb />
				uniform
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				principled
				<lb />
				approach aimed at reforming and rationalizing BCCI&apos;s
				<lb />
				structural edifice. The recommendation made by the
				<lb />
				Committee to the extent it provides for one vote for
				<lb />
				each state is unexceptionable nor should there be
				<lb />
				any
				<lb />
				compromise
				<lb />
				with
				<lb />
				what
				<lb />
				is
				<lb />
				proposed
				<lb />
				as
				<lb />
				a
				<lb />
				reformative measure. Even so the question is whether
				<lb />
				BCCI, in the peculiar situation prevalent in these
				<lb />
				two states, is in a position to recognize one of the
				<lb />
				three
				<lb />
				Associations
				<lb />
				representing
				<lb />
				different
				<lb />
				territories in those two States as the one that
				<lb />
				would represent the entire State. Learned Counsel
				<lb />
				for the intervenors and so also Mr. Venugopal
				<lb />
				counsel for BCCI are, in our opinion, justified in
				<lb />
				contending that the process of recognizing one out
				<lb />
				of three associations representing three different
				<lb />
				regions in those two states is fraught with several
				<lb />
				106
				<lb />
				Page 107
				<lb />
				difficulties
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				would
				<lb />
				result
				<lb />
				in
				<lb />
				long
				<lb />
				drawn
				<lb />
				litigation and frustration for the players in
				<lb />
				particular and cricket lovers in general. What then
				<lb />
				is the way out of this conundrum. We had in the
				<lb />
				course of the hearing asked learned counsel for the
				<lb />
				parties, if it would be possible for the three
				<lb />
				associations to sync and unify their associations
				<lb />
				into
				<lb />
				a
				<lb />
				single
				<lb />
				entity.
				<lb />
				There
				<lb />
				were
				<lb />
				serious
				<lb />
				reservations expressed on that front and rightly so
				<lb />
				as each association is entitled today to field a
				<lb />
				team and receive monetary assistance. In the process
				<lb />
				of unification, the prospects of budding cricketers
				<lb />
				of these regions would go down substantially. That
				<lb />
				being so, the only reasonable and rational answer to
				<lb />
				the problem within the broad principle of One State
				<lb />
				One Vote would be to allow the full membership of
				<lb />
				BCCI to rotate among the three clubs on an annual
				<lb />
				basis.
				<lb />
				During the period one of the associations
				<lb />
				would exercise rights and privileges of a full
				<lb />
				member, the other two associations would act as
				<lb />
				associate
				<lb />
				members
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				BCCI.
				<lb />
				This
				<lb />
				rotational
				<lb />
				arrangement would give each member a right to vote
				<lb />
				at its turn without violating the broader principle
				<lb />
				of one State one vote recommended by the Committee.
				<lb />
				This would also respect the historical aspect in
				<lb />
				which these associations grew to promote the game
				<lb />
				and form BCCI as a national body. Needless to say
				<lb />
				that the right of the association to field teams as
				<lb />
				before will remain unaffected subject to any changes
				<lb />
				that BCCI may make in its wisdom over a period of
				<lb />
				time. BCCI shall, however, decide the order in which
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				membership
				<lb />
				will
				<lb />
				rotate
				<lb />
				among
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				three
				<lb />
				associations in these two states. We make it clear
				<lb />
				that this arrangement of rotational membership shall
				<lb />
				continue till such time the clubs/Associations come
				<lb />
				together to form a single entity, if such a
				<lb />
				unification was to ever become a reality.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				66. It was next argued by Mr. Venugopal and counsel
				<lb />
				appearing for some of the interveners including Mr.
				<lb />
				Sampath, counsel for the Karnataka State Cricket
				<lb />
				Association that the recommendation made by the
				<lb />
				108
				<lb />
				Page 109
				<lb />
				Lodha Committee as to the upper age limit of any
				<lb />
				office bearer is neither reasonable nor conducive to
				<lb />
				the development and promotion of the game in this
				<lb />
				country. It was submitted that some of the office
				<lb />
				bearers continue to contribute immensely to the
				<lb />
				development and promotion of cricket even though
				<lb />
				they have crossed the recommended upper age limit of
				<lb />
				70 years.
				<lb />
				For instance, Shri Niranjan Shah,
				<lb />
				applicant in Interlocutory Application No.24 is more
				<lb />
				than 70 years old but has held the office of
				<lb />
				Secretary of Saurashtra Cricket Association for more
				<lb />
				than four decades.
				<lb />
				This, according to the learned
				<lb />
				counsel, shows that age had nothing to do with the
				<lb />
				capacity of the person to contribute to the
				<lb />
				promotion of the game.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				67. Learned counsel appearing for the interveners
				<lb />
				who support the recommendations of the Committee, on
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				other
				<lb />
				hand,
				<lb />
				argued
				<lb />
				that
				<lb />
				those
				<lb />
				playing
				<lb />
				competitive cricket are in the age group of 18 to 35
				<lb />
				years which means that anyone who has played the
				<lb />
				109
				<lb />
				Page 110
				<lb />
				game or who is actively connected with the game gets
				<lb />
				nearly 35 years to continue his active association
				<lb />
				with the game even after he has retired from
				<lb />
				competitive cricket which is a long enough period
				<lb />
				for anyone to contribute to the game and its
				<lb />
				promotion. It was also contended that the Government
				<lb />
				of India, have, in their wisdom prescribed the upper
				<lb />
				age limit of 70 years for office bearers of the
				<lb />
				National Sports Federations in terms of the National
				<lb />
				Sports Development Code of India, 2011. The Sporting
				<lb />
				fraternity has accepted the same as a reasonable
				<lb />
				upper age limit for anyone to hold office in any
				<lb />
				Sporting Federation. There is, in that view, nothing
				<lb />
				wrong with the recommendations of the Committee that
				<lb />
				those aspiring to hold any office in the BCCI or in
				<lb />
				the State Associations ought to be less than 70
				<lb />
				years old.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				68. There is no denying the fact that Cricketers who
				<lb />
				play competitive cricket generally fall in the age
				<lb />
				group of 18 to 35 years. This implies that even
				<lb />
				110
				<lb />
				Page 111
				<lb />
				after retirement from active cricket anyone who has
				<lb />
				the potential to contribute to the game can do so
				<lb />
				for over three decades till he attains the age of 70
				<lb />
				years. The upper age limit recommended by the Lodha
				<lb />
				Committee
				<lb />
				is
				<lb />
				not,
				<lb />
				therefore,
				<lb />
				unreasonable
				<lb />
				or
				<lb />
				irrational by any standard. That apart, as rightly
				<lb />
				pointed
				<lb />
				out
				<lb />
				by
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				counsel
				<lb />
				supporting
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				recommendation, the Government of India have in the
				<lb />
				National Sports Development Code of India, 2011,
				<lb />
				inter alia, stipulated that the President, Secretary
				<lb />
				and the Treasurer of any recognized National Sports
				<lb />
				Federation including the Indian Olympic Association
				<lb />
				(IOA) shall cease to hold that post on attaining the
				<lb />
				age of 70 years. The upper age limit of 70 years is
				<lb />
				not, therefore, an unusual or unacceptable norm so
				<lb />
				as to warrant our interference with the same. The
				<lb />
				recommendation made by the Lodha Committee regarding
				<lb />
				upper age limit for office bearers is accordingly
				<lb />
				accepted.
				<lb />
			</p>


			<p>
				69. Mr.Venugopal, learned counsel appearing for BCCI
				<lb />
				and counsel for some of the interveners opposing the
				<lb />
				recommendations of the Committee also assailed the
				<lb />
				Committee&apos;s
				<lb />
				recommendation
				<lb />
				that
				<lb />
				Ministers
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				Government Officials should be ineligible for any
				<lb />
				post in State Associations or in the BCCI. It was
				<lb />
				contended that the restrictions sought to be placed
				<lb />
				on the Ministers and Government Servants are
				<lb />
				unreasonable. It was contended that past experience
				<lb />
				of the BCCI has shown that Government Servants and
				<lb />
				Ministers are able Administrators whose association
				<lb />
				with BCCI and the Associations has resulted in
				<lb />
				substantial benefit to BCCI in the management of its
				<lb />
				affairs. It was contended that office bearers in
				<lb />
				BCCI serve in an honorary capacity and without any
				<lb />
				remuneration for their services, except that travel,
				<lb />
				lodging and boarding arrangements are taken care of
				<lb />
				by the BCCI.
				<lb />
				It was also contended that the
				<lb />
				Government of India has been, as a matter of policy,
				<lb />
				encouraging formation of Sporting Associations so
				<lb />
				that its employees are attracted towards sporting
				<lb />
				112
				<lb />
				Page 113
				<lb />
				activities and promotion of sports and development
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				sports
				<lb />
				related
				<lb />
				infrastructure.
				<lb />
				Also
				<lb />
				under
				<lb />
				challenge
				<lb />
				is
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				recommendation
				<lb />
				made
				<lb />
				by
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				Committee that those holding office in the State
				<lb />
				Associations shall not be eligible for holding any
				<lb />
				office in BCCI and vice versa. It was contended that
				<lb />
				administrative experience acquired by anyone in the
				<lb />
				State Associations is useful to the BCCI which need
				<lb />
				not be lost by stipulating a disqualification
				<lb />
				recommended by the Committee.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				70. Learned counsel for the interveners supporting
				<lb />
				the recommendations, on the other hand, argued that
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				recommendations
				<lb />
				were
				<lb />
				well
				<lb />
				considered
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				meaningful and in the interest of the game of
				<lb />
				cricket in this country.
				<lb />
				It was contended that
				<lb />
				political bigwigs need to be kept away from the
				<lb />
				sporting arena not only because the presence of
				<lb />
				Ministers
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				Civil
				<lb />
				Servants
				<lb />
				brings
				<lb />
				several
				<lb />
				considerations not conducive to the promotion of the
				<lb />
				game, but, at times, results in creation of vested
				<lb />
				113
				<lb />
				Page 114
				<lb />
				interests, groupism and rivalries that harm the game
				<lb />
				far more than helping it. The fact that the
				<lb />
				Ministers and Civil Servants have been helpful in
				<lb />
				promoting the game in the past does not mean that
				<lb />
				the game would cease to get their patronage if they
				<lb />
				are disqualified from holding any office in the
				<lb />
				State Associations or the BCCI. Whatever the
				<lb />
				legitimate sporting patronage is required for the
				<lb />
				game would certainly come from the concerned
				<lb />
				supporters regardless whether they are Ministers,
				<lb />
				Civil Servants or office bearers.
				<lb />
				The contention
				<lb />
				urged on behalf of the BCCI that the restriction
				<lb />
				placed on the Ministers and Public Servants holding
				<lb />
				office would, in any manner, damage the cause of the
				<lb />
				game is, therefore, without any basis.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				71. The Lodha Committee has, in its meetings, held
				<lb />
				extensive interactive sessions and deliberations
				<lb />
				with
				<lb />
				a
				<lb />
				cross
				<lb />
				section
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				stakeholders.
				<lb />
				The
				<lb />
				recommendations made by the Committee are based on
				<lb />
				the impressions which the Committee has gathered
				<lb />
				from such interactions and deliberations. In the
				<lb />
				ordinary course and in the absence of any patent
				<lb />
				perversity in what has been recommended by the
				<lb />
				Committee, this Court would be slow in interfering,
				<lb />
				especially when the Committee has recommended
				<lb />
				comprehensive restructuring of the management at
				<lb />
				different levels by proposing modification of the
				<lb />
				relevant rules and regulations.
				<lb />
				The Committee has
				<lb />
				in its wisdom found that the holding of office by
				<lb />
				the Ministers and Civil Servants in the State
				<lb />
				Associations or in the BCCI is not conducive to the
				<lb />
				health and promotion of the game. The Committee has
				<lb />
				taken the view that the game would be better
				<lb />
				managed, promoted and developed if politicians and
				<lb />
				civil servants who otherwise occupy positions of
				<lb />
				responsibility in the Government that call for their
				<lb />
				complete and unstinted attention and commitment are
				<lb />
				made ineligible from holding any post in the State
				<lb />
				associations or the BCCI. The Committee has while
				<lb />
				making that recommendation observed:
				<lb />
			</p>


			<item>
				&quot;   Any elected Councillor shall stand
				<lb />
				automatically disqualified after nine years as
				<lb />
				an
				<lb />
				office
				<lb />
				bearer,
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				shall
				<lb />
				also
				<lb />
				be
				<lb />
				disqualified from contesting or holding the
				<lb />
				post if he has completed the age of 70 years,
				<lb />
				is charged under the penal law, is declared to
				<lb />
				be of unsound mind, is a Minister or
				<lb />
				government servant or holds any post of
				<lb />
				another sports body in the country.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				xxx xxx
				<lb />
				xxx xxx
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				xxx xxx
				<lb />
				xxx xxx
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				b. Posts &amp; Tenures
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				  The lack of any qualifications or
				<lb />
				disqualifications also ensures that those with
				<lb />
				full time occupations superficially involve
				<lb />
				themselves,
				<lb />
				thereby
				<lb />
				compromising
				<lb />
				their
				<lb />
				commitment to the association and the game of
				<lb />
				cricket. Several public servants hold lead
				<lb />
				positions in State Associations which take a
				<lb />
				substantial toll on both sets of their
				<lb />
				respective obligations to the public.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				72. In light of the above we see no compelling
				<lb />
				reason for us to reject the recommendation which
				<lb />
				disqualifies Ministers and Public Servants from
				<lb />
				holding offices in the State Associations or BCCI.
				<lb />
				The argument that since ministerial and bureaucratic
				<lb />
				support and patronage has helped the BCCI in running
				<lb />
				its affairs in the past they should be allowed to
				<lb />
				continue, lest the game suffers, has not impressed
				<lb />
				116
				<lb />
				Page 117
				<lb />
				us. We do not think that the game flourishes in this
				<lb />
				country because any minister or civil servant holds
				<lb />
				office in the State Associations or BCCI.
				<lb />
				We also
				<lb />
				do not find any basis for the argument that unless
				<lb />
				the ministers and civil servants are allowed to hold
				<lb />
				office in the State Association or in the BCCI they
				<lb />
				will refuse to do what is legitimately due to the
				<lb />
				game for its development and promotion.
				<lb />
				Nothing
				<lb />
				which is not due to the game or is not legitimate
				<lb />
				need be done by any Minister or Civil Servant. But
				<lb />
				we have no manner of doubt that what is legitimately
				<lb />
				due to the game will not be denied to the game
				<lb />
				merely because Ministers or Civil Servants do not
				<lb />
				happen to be office bearers for ought we know that
				<lb />
				there may be an overwhelming number of Ministers and
				<lb />
				Bureaucrats who are passionate about the game and
				<lb />
				would like to do everything that is legally
				<lb />
				permissible and reasonably possible within the four
				<lb />
				corners of the law even without holding any office
				<lb />
				in the BCCI or the State Associations. The
				<lb />
				contention that favours which the BCCI receives will
				<lb />
				disappear just because a Minister or Civil Servant
				<lb />
				is not an office bearer in the State Association or
				<lb />
				BCCI has no real basis to commend itself to us. So
				<lb />
				also, the contention that it should be permissible
				<lb />
				to hold office simultaneously in BCCI and the State
				<lb />
				Association has not commended itself to us. The
				<lb />
				Committee has while recommending abolition of dual
				<lb />
				posts observed:
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				g. Dual posts
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				Strangely, while conflict of interest issues
				<lb />
				have
				<lb />
				been
				<lb />
				at
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				heart
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				recent
				<lb />
				controversies, virtually all office bearers of
				<lb />
				the BCCI continue to be office bearers in
				<lb />
				their respective State Associations at the
				<lb />
				same time. Presidents and Secretaries of State
				<lb />
				Associations are to discharge functions with
				<lb />
				the primary interest of the State in mind, but
				<lb />
				as BCCI office bearers, these interests would
				<lb />
				have to be subordinated to that of national
				<lb />
				interest. Often, with powers centred on an
				<lb />
				office bearer, that individual has been found
				<lb />
				to appoint his State associates to critical
				<lb />
				posts in the BCCI, thereby creating an
				<lb />
				imbalance.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				73. There is nothing irrational about the view taken
				<lb />
				by the Committee.
				<lb />
				The argument that individuals
				<lb />
				should be eligible to hold two posts one each in the
				<lb />
				118
				<lb />
				Page 119
				<lb />
				State Association and the BCCI does not stand
				<lb />
				scrutiny in the light of the reasons given by the
				<lb />
				Committee which do not, in our opinion, suffer from
				<lb />
				any perversity to call for our interference.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				74. It was next contended on behalf of the BCCI that
				<lb />
				the recommendations made by the Committee for
				<lb />
				inclusion of a nominee of the Accountant General of
				<lb />
				the State in the Governing Body of the State
				<lb />
				Associations and a nominee of the Comptroller &amp;
				<lb />
				Auditor General of India (C&amp;AG) as Member of the
				<lb />
				Apex Council in BCCI were both unacceptable to BCCI
				<lb />
				being unnecessary inflictions that were likely to
				<lb />
				result in the derecognition of the BCCI by the ICC.
				<lb />
				It was submitted that in terms of Article 2.9(b) of
				<lb />
				the Memorandum of Association and Articles of
				<lb />
				Association of the ICC any interference by the
				<lb />
				Government in the administration of the Cricket by a
				<lb />
				member would render the latter liable to be
				<lb />
				suspended and derecognized.
				<lb />
				Induction of the
				<lb />
				nominee of the Accountant General in the State
				<lb />
				119
				<lb />
				Page 120
				<lb />
				Association and nominee of a C&amp;AG in the Apex
				<lb />
				Council of the BCCI brings in an element of
				<lb />
				interference by the Government which would according
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				counsel
				<lb />
				for
				<lb />
				BCCI
				<lb />
				lead
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				suspension/derecognition of the BCCI.
				<lb />
				Any such
				<lb />
				induction was, therefore, not in the interest of the
				<lb />
				game of cricket or otherwise desirable keeping in
				<lb />
				view the fact that the BCCI cannot afford to run the
				<lb />
				risk of being derecognized or suspended by the ICC.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				75. The Lodha Committee has, while dealing with the
				<lb />
				need for transparency and oversight, referred to the
				<lb />
				grievance made by the stakeholders that the BCCI was
				<lb />
				neither fair nor transparent and those who seek
				<lb />
				greater information are either rebuffed by the Board
				<lb />
				or won over by enticements. The Committee has
				<lb />
				noticed that the state of affairs prevailing in BCCI
				<lb />
				and the expenses incurred by it call for better
				<lb />
				financial management and financial prudence.
				<lb />
				The
				<lb />
				Committee has observed:
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;In the light of all this, the Committee
				<lb />
				proposes that clear principles of transparency
				<lb />
				120
				<lb />
				be laid down, and the BCCI website and office
				<lb />
				will carry all rules, regulations and office
				<lb />
				orders of the BCCI, the constitution of the
				<lb />
				various committees, their resolutions, the
				<lb />
				expenditures under various heads, the reports
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				Ombudsman/Auditor/Electoral
				<lb />
				Officer/Ethics Officer and the annual reports
				<lb />
				and balance sheets. In addition, norms and
				<lb />
				procedures shall be laid down for the
				<lb />
				engagement
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				service
				<lb />
				professionals
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				contractors,
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				there
				<lb />
				shall
				<lb />
				be
				<lb />
				full
				<lb />
				transparency of all tenders floated and bids
				<lb />
				invited by or on behalf of the BCCI. The
				<lb />
				website shall also have links to the various
				<lb />
				stadia with seating capacities and transparent
				<lb />
				direct ticketing facilities.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				xxx xxx xxx
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				xxx xxx xxx
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				The Committee also believes that the
				<lb />
				Auditor be tasked not only with a financial
				<lb />
				analysis, but also specifically carry out a
				<lb />
				performance audit (Compliance Report) to
				<lb />
				determine whether the State associations have
				<lb />
				actually expended their grants towards the
				<lb />
				development of the game and mark them on a
				<lb />
				report card which will be utilized to
				<lb />
				determine the due they deserve the following
				<lb />
				year. This oversight also needs to consider
				<lb />
				the high and unreasonable expenditures by the
				<lb />
				Board on various heads, which would have to be
				<lb />
				limited and streamlined.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				76. While dealing with the question of governance in
				<lb />
				Chapter Two of the Report the Committee has
				<lb />
				recommended a Nine-Member Body as the Apex Council
				<lb />
				out of whom five shall be elected office bearers of
				<lb />
				the BCCI while four shall be Councillors one of them
				<lb />
				to be nominated by the C&amp;AG. The nominee of C&amp;AG,
				<lb />
				shall, in the opinion of the Committee bring
				<lb />
				transparency
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				oversight
				<lb />
				in
				<lb />
				monitoring
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				finances of the BCCI. It is in that background that
				<lb />
				the Committee has recommended in the draft Rules and
				<lb />
				Regulations/Memorandum
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				Association
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				composition of the State Associations and the BCCI
				<lb />
				to include a nominee of the Accountant General of
				<lb />
				the State in the case of State Associations and
				<lb />
				nominee of C&amp;AG as Member of the Apex Council in the
				<lb />
				case of the BCCI.
				<lb />
				It is evident from a careful
				<lb />
				reading of the Report that the object underlying the
				<lb />
				induction of the nominees of the Accountant General
				<lb />
				of the State and the C&amp;AG is to bring transparency
				<lb />
				and financial oversight into the affairs of the
				<lb />
				State Associations and the BCCI. No one can possibly
				<lb />
				argue that the object sought to be achieved by the
				<lb />
				proposed nominations is not laudable or at least
				<lb />
				desirable. Transparency and financial discipline and
				<lb />
				accountability are fundamental values to which any
				<lb />
				authority discharging public functions must be
				<lb />
				committed to.
				<lb />
				To that extent the BCCI has not
				<lb />
				faulted the report made by the Committee.
				<lb />
				What is
				<lb />
				all the same contended is that the recommendation if
				<lb />
				accepted may result in the suspension of the
				<lb />
				recognition of the BCCI as it will be seen by the
				<lb />
				ICC as Government interference contrary to Article
				<lb />
				2.9(B) of the ICC Rules, which reads as under:
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;Where
				<lb />
				a
				<lb />
				government
				<lb />
				interferes
				<lb />
				in
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				administration
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				cricket
				<lb />
				by
				<lb />
				a
				<lb />
				Member,
				<lb />
				including but not limited to interference in
				<lb />
				operational
				<lb />
				matters,
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				selection
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				management of teams, the appointment of
				<lb />
				coaches or support personnel or the activities
				<lb />
				of a Member, the Executive Board shall have
				<lb />
				the power to suspend or refuse to recognize
				<lb />
				that Member, subject to the provisions of
				<lb />
				Article 2.7.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				77. There is, in our view, no basis for the argument
				<lb />
				that any measure taken by the BCCI on its own or
				<lb />
				under the direction of a competent court specially
				<lb />
				when aimed at streamlining its working and ensuring
				<lb />
				financial
				<lb />
				discipline,
				<lb />
				transparency
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				accountability
				<lb />
				expected
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				an
				<lb />
				organization
				<lb />
				discharging public functions such as BCCI may be
				<lb />
				seen as governmental interference calling for
				<lb />
				suspension/derecognition of the BCCI. Far from
				<lb />
				finding fault with presence of a nominee of the
				<lb />
				Accountant General of the State and C&amp;AG, the ICC
				<lb />
				would in our opinion appreciate any such step for
				<lb />
				the same would prevent misgivings about the working
				<lb />
				of the BCCI especially in relation to management of
				<lb />
				its funds and bring transparency and objectivity
				<lb />
				necessary to inspire public confidence in the
				<lb />
				fairness and the effective management of the affairs
				<lb />
				of the BCCI and the State Associations. The nominees
				<lb />
				recommended by the Committee would act as conscience
				<lb />
				keepers of the State Association and BCCI in
				<lb />
				financial matters and matters related or incidental
				<lb />
				thereto which will in no way adversely impact the
				<lb />
				performance or working of the BCCI for the promotion
				<lb />
				and development of the game of cricket.
				<lb />
				The
				<lb />
				criticism leveled against the recommendations of the
				<lb />
				Committee is, therefore, unfounded and accordingly
				<lb />
				rejected.
				<lb />
			</p>


			<p>
				78. That brings us to the recommendation made by the
				<lb />
				Committee regarding the formation of a Players&apos;
				<lb />
				Association.
				<lb />
				To the extent the recommendation
				<lb />
				provides for establishment of a Players&apos; Association
				<lb />
				neither the BCCI nor any other association who has
				<lb />
				intervened has found fault with the view taken by
				<lb />
				the Committee. What has come under criticism by the
				<lb />
				BCCI
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				its
				<lb />
				supporting
				<lb />
				associations
				<lb />
				is
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				financial assistance which the BCCI is required to
				<lb />
				give to such an association. On behalf of the BCCI
				<lb />
				it was contended that cricket players can indeed
				<lb />
				form an association which they are in any case
				<lb />
				entitled to form, but that exercise need not be at
				<lb />
				the expense of the BCCI.
				<lb />
				The recommendation for
				<lb />
				financial support to the association is thus all
				<lb />
				that has been faulted by the BCCI. It was also
				<lb />
				contended that there was no need for providing any
				<lb />
				representation for the Association in the Apex
				<lb />
				Council of the BCCI having regard to the fact that
				<lb />
				some of the cricketers had in the past held offices
				<lb />
				in the State Associations and in the BCCI by
				<lb />
				recourse to the democratic process, without any such
				<lb />
				reservation.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				79. There
				<lb />
				are
				<lb />
				three
				<lb />
				distinct
				<lb />
				aspects
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				recommendation in question. One relates to formation
				<lb />
				of the Association itself; the second touches the
				<lb />
				financial support which the BCCI must provide to the
				<lb />
				Association
				<lb />
				and;
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				third
				<lb />
				deals
				<lb />
				with
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				representation given to the Association in the Apex
				<lb />
				Council.
				<lb />
				Formation of the Association, as noticed
				<lb />
				earlier, is not under challenge and rightly so for
				<lb />
				cricket players have a fundamental right to form an
				<lb />
				association even independent of the recommendation.
				<lb />
				The question is whether the association needs to be
				<lb />
				financially supported by the BCCI.
				<lb />
				The Committee
				<lb />
				has recommended such financial support but has
				<lb />
				stopped short of specifying the extent of such
				<lb />
				support.
				<lb />
				It would, therefore, be reasonable to
				<lb />
				presume that the extent of financial support which
				<lb />
				the association may be given is left to the
				<lb />
				discretion of the BCCI.
				<lb />
				If that be so, we do not
				<lb />
				126
				<lb />
				Page 127
				<lb />
				see any merit in the objection raised by the BCCI
				<lb />
				that such support need not be given or would unduly
				<lb />
				burden the BCCI. An association of cricket players
				<lb />
				would doubtless give to the cricketing community not
				<lb />
				only an opportunity to contribute to the promotion
				<lb />
				of the game but a sense of participation also so
				<lb />
				very important for the promotion of a game that
				<lb />
				brings so much joy and feelings of nationalism among
				<lb />
				our countrymen.
				<lb />
				Financial support, to the extent
				<lb />
				possible, having regard to the resources available
				<lb />
				with the BCCI and its financial commitments in other
				<lb />
				areas relevant to the game is not therefore an
				<lb />
				unacceptable idea.
				<lb />
				The recommendation requiring
				<lb />
				financial support to the players association cannot
				<lb />
				therefore be rejected especially when the extent of
				<lb />
				such support is left to the BCCI to be decided on a
				<lb />
				fair and objective view of its financial resources
				<lb />
				and commitments.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				80. The third dimension of the recommendation
				<lb />
				touching the representation given to the association
				<lb />
				also does not call for any interference. Players&apos;
				<lb />
				Association, it is obvious, would represent a very
				<lb />
				significant
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				important
				<lb />
				segment
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				stakeholders in the game. Those who have played the
				<lb />
				game
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				are,
				<lb />
				therefore,
				<lb />
				better
				<lb />
				equipped
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				understand its nuances, its challenges and concerns
				<lb />
				relevant to its development and promotion cannot be
				<lb />
				left out from the management. The Committee has
				<lb />
				recommended two positions in the Apex Council as
				<lb />
				Councillors one of whom must be a female.
				<lb />
				Keeping
				<lb />
				in view the numerical strength of the Apex Council,
				<lb />
				two nominees representing the Players&apos; Association
				<lb />
				will not unfavorably tilt the power balance within
				<lb />
				the Apex Council nor bring in any undesirable or
				<lb />
				extraneous element into the management of the BCCI.
				<lb />
				We have, therefore, no hesitation in rejecting the
				<lb />
				argument against the recommendation.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				81. That leaves us with three other recommendations
				<lb />
				of the Committee to which we may advert at this
				<lb />
				stage.
				<lb />
				Of these, two recommendations are in the
				<lb />
				128
				<lb />
				Page 129
				<lb />
				nature of an appeal to the Parliament to enact
				<lb />
				suitable statutory provisions which the Committee
				<lb />
				considers essential in public interest.
				<lb />
				The first
				<lb />
				of these recommendations relates to the BCCI being
				<lb />
				under the purview of Right to Information Act and to
				<lb />
				carry out a suitable amendment to this effect.
				<lb />
				While the second recommendation is to the effect
				<lb />
				that the Parliament ought to legalize betting in
				<lb />
				cricket. Dealing with the first recommendation the
				<lb />
				Committee has observed:
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;The Right to Information Act, 2005 (&apos;RTI
				<lb />
				Act&apos;) enacts that public authorities shall
				<lb />
				make
				<lb />
				known
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				particulars
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				facilities available to citizens.
				<lb />
				While
				<lb />
				the issue of the BCCI being amenable to
				<lb />
				the RTI Act is sub judice before the High
				<lb />
				Court of Madras in W.P.No.20229/2013, many
				<lb />
				respondents who appeared and interacted
				<lb />
				with the Committee were of the view that
				<lb />
				BCCI&apos;s activities must come under the RTI
				<lb />
				Act.
				<lb />
				Having regard to the emphasis laid
				<lb />
				by the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court that BCCI
				<lb />
				discharges public functions and also the
				<lb />
				Court&apos;s reference to indirect approval of
				<lb />
				the Central and State Governments in
				<lb />
				activities which has created a monopoly in
				<lb />
				the hands of the BCCI over cricket, the
				<lb />
				Committee feels that the people of the
				<lb />
				country have a right to know the details
				<lb />
				about the BCCI&apos;s functions and activities.
				<lb />
				It is therefore recommended that the
				<lb />
				legislature
				<lb />
				must
				<lb />
				seriously
				<lb />
				consider
				<lb />
				129
				<lb />
				bringing BCCI within the purview of the
				<lb />
				RTI Act.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				82. We are not called upon in these proceedings to
				<lb />
				issue any direction in so far as the above aspect is
				<lb />
				concerned. All that we need say is that since BCCI
				<lb />
				discharges
				<lb />
				public
				<lb />
				functions
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				since
				<lb />
				those
				<lb />
				functions are in the nature of a monopoly in the
				<lb />
				hands of the BCCI with tacit State Government and
				<lb />
				Central Government approvals, the public at large
				<lb />
				has a right to know and demand information as to the
				<lb />
				activities and functions of the BCCI especially when
				<lb />
				it deals with funds collected in relation to those
				<lb />
				activities as a trustee of wherein the beneficiary
				<lb />
				happens to be the people of this country.
				<lb />
				As a
				<lb />
				possible first step in the direction in bringing
				<lb />
				BCCI under purview of Right to Information Act, we
				<lb />
				expect the Law Commission of India to examine the
				<lb />
				issue and make a suitable recommendation to the
				<lb />
				Government.
				<lb />
				Beyond that we do not consider it
				<lb />
				necessary to say anything at this stage.
				<lb />
			</p>


			<p>
				83. So also the recommendation made by the Committee
				<lb />
				that betting should be legalized by law, involves
				<lb />
				the enactment of a Law which is a matter that may be
				<lb />
				examined by the Law Commission and the Government
				<lb />
				for such action as it may consider necessary in the
				<lb />
				facts and circumstances of the case.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				84. The third recommendation which has given rise to
				<lb />
				some debate at the bar touches the broadcast/
				<lb />
				telecasting of sporting events hosted by the BCCI.
				<lb />
				The Committee appears to have taken the view that
				<lb />
				commercial expediency has overtaken the need for a
				<lb />
				neat telecast of the events for the benefit of the
				<lb />
				viewers. The Committee has observed :
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;Commerce has also overtaken the enjoyment
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				sport,
				<lb />
				with
				<lb />
				advertisement
				<lb />
				continuing many a time, even after the
				<lb />
				first ball and again commencing even
				<lb />
				before the last ball of the over is
				<lb />
				played, thereby interrupting the full and
				<lb />
				proper broadcast of the game.
				<lb />
				Regardless
				<lb />
				of the wicket that has fallen, century
				<lb />
				having been hit or other momentous event,
				<lb />
				full liberty is granted to maximize the
				<lb />
				broadcaster&apos;s income by cutting away to a
				<lb />
				commercial, thereby robbing sport of its
				<lb />
				131
				<lb />
				most attractive attribute -emotion.
				<lb />
				It
				<lb />
				is recommended that all existing contracts
				<lb />
				for international Test &amp; One-Day matches
				<lb />
				be revised and new ones ensure that only
				<lb />
				breaks taken by both teams for drinks,
				<lb />
				lunch and tea will permit the broadcast to
				<lb />
				be interrupted with advertisements, as is
				<lb />
				the practice internationally.
				<lb />
				Also, the
				<lb />
				entire space of the screen during the
				<lb />
				broadcast will be dedicated to the display
				<lb />
				of the game, same for a small sponsor logo
				<lb />
				or sign.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				85. BCCI has filed objections in so far as the above
				<lb />
				recommendations are concerned.
				<lb />
				Firstly, it is
				<lb />
				stated that the telecast/broadcast of the game
				<lb />
				covers the entire over, namely, from the first ball
				<lb />
				to the last ball of the over and no part of the
				<lb />
				game&apos;s
				<lb />
				telecast
				<lb />
				is
				<lb />
				hampered
				<lb />
				by
				<lb />
				commercial
				<lb />
				exploitation of the event. The second contention
				<lb />
				urged is that the revision of contracts already
				<lb />
				fixed is likely to result in serious financial
				<lb />
				difficulties and other implication which will not be
				<lb />
				in the interest of the game. It is also contended
				<lb />
				that any modification of the contractual terms and
				<lb />
				conditions at this stage is likely to result in a
				<lb />
				heavy financial loss to the BCCI.
				<lb />
				To the same
				<lb />
				effect was the submission which Mr. Venugopal,
				<lb />
				Counsel appearing for the BCCI who argued that
				<lb />
				commercial aspect of the game could be best left to
				<lb />
				be considered by the BCCI and any change if at all
				<lb />
				called for could be introduced after the expiry of
				<lb />
				the existing contracts. This was without prejudice
				<lb />
				to Mr. Venugopal&apos;s submission that the pleasure of
				<lb />
				watching the game on television sets or on radios
				<lb />
				was
				<lb />
				in
				<lb />
				no
				<lb />
				way
				<lb />
				affected
				<lb />
				by
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				commercial
				<lb />
				exploitation of the event.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				86. The Committee&apos;s concern, it is evident from the
				<lb />
				passage extracted above is about the excessive
				<lb />
				exploitation of the commercial space granted to the
				<lb />
				broadcaster and in the process affecting the
				<lb />
				viewers&apos; ability to view the game in the best
				<lb />
				possible way.
				<lb />
				The Committee&apos;s recommendation is
				<lb />
				obviously based on the premise that even the viewers
				<lb />
				have a right to view the game uninterrupted by any
				<lb />
				commercials and that the BCCI&apos;s ability to encash
				<lb />
				the popularity of the game may be affected if the
				<lb />
				interest of the viewers and resultantly their
				<lb />
				numbers was reduced by excessive exploitation of the
				<lb />
				commercial space. It is, however, difficult for us
				<lb />
				in these proceedings to authoritatively pronounce
				<lb />
				upon the impact that the current contracts have on
				<lb />
				the viewers ability to enjoy the game without
				<lb />
				interruption or the financial implication that may
				<lb />
				arise in case the contracts are modified as
				<lb />
				recommended by the Committee. The proper course, in
				<lb />
				our opinion, is to leave the recommendation as it is
				<lb />
				for the consideration of the BCCI with the
				<lb />
				observation that BCCI may keeping in mind the
				<lb />
				sentiments expressed by the Committee ensure that
				<lb />
				the viewers get to see an uninterrupted broadcast of
				<lb />
				the match from the first till the last ball of the
				<lb />
				over and limiting the commercial advertisement in
				<lb />
				terms of time and space to an extent that will not
				<lb />
				deprive the viewers of the pleasure of watching the
				<lb />
				game in full.
				<lb />
				We make it clear that we have not
				<lb />
				expressed any opinion in this regard and leave it
				<lb />
				for the BCCI to examine the matter from all possible
				<lb />
				angles and take a considered decision having regard
				<lb />
				to the recommendations made by the Committee and the
				<lb />
				feasibility of any modification in the existing
				<lb />
				contracts.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				87. Last but not the least is the recommendation
				<lb />
				made by the Committee that the Governing Council of
				<lb />
				the IPL ought to be reconstituted so as to comprise
				<lb />
				three ex-officio members of the BCCI namely; the
				<lb />
				Secretary, the Treasurer and the CEO.
				<lb />
				Two
				<lb />
				representatives of the Members of BCCI to be elected
				<lb />
				by the General Body, two nominees of the IPL
				<lb />
				franchisees and nominee each to be nominated by
				<lb />
				the C&amp;AG and from the Players&apos; Association.
				<lb />
				The
				<lb />
				BCCI has objected to the recommendation in so far as
				<lb />
				same pertains to induction of two nominees of the
				<lb />
				franchisees.
				<lb />
				The BCCI contends that the induction
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				nominees
				<lb />
				from
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				franchisees
				<lb />
				is
				<lb />
				impermissible because important matters like players
				<lb />
				retention policy, posting of umpires for IPL
				<lb />
				matches, etc. are deliberated upon and decided by
				<lb />
				the Governing Council itself. There is therefore an
				<lb />
				evident conflict of interest between the nominees of
				<lb />
				the IPL franchisees on the one hand and their role
				<lb />
				as members of the Governing Council on the other.
				<lb />
				The BCCI contends that this Court has set aside an
				<lb />
				amendment by which the BCCI had permitted persons
				<lb />
				affiliated with the franchisees to take part in the
				<lb />
				management of the IPL on the ground that the same
				<lb />
				violates the principle of institutional integrity.
				<lb />
				The
				<lb />
				induction
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				representatives
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				franchisee would however, bring about a conflict of
				<lb />
				interest which is neither permissible nor desirable.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				88. The recommendation made by the Committee does
				<lb />
				not elaborately deal with the need for induction of
				<lb />
				the nominees of the IPL franchisees in the Governing
				<lb />
				Council. All that is said is that the Governing
				<lb />
				Council has denied any role to the franchisee
				<lb />
				companies and that there is no independent voice in
				<lb />
				the Governing Council which is dominated by the full
				<lb />
				members of the BCCI and two former cricketers. The
				<lb />
				136
				<lb />
				Page 137
				<lb />
				Committee does not appear to have addressed the
				<lb />
				question of conflict of interest in the event IPL
				<lb />
				franchisees place two nominees in the Governing
				<lb />
				Council keeping in view the fact that the Governing
				<lb />
				Council takes important decisions like players
				<lb />
				retention policy and in posting of umpires for IPL
				<lb />
				matches etc. There is prima facie a possibility of
				<lb />
				conflict of interest arising out of the franchisees
				<lb />
				representation in the Governing Council. Be that as
				<lb />
				it may we do not consider it necessary to finally
				<lb />
				pronounce on this aspect which can be better left to
				<lb />
				the Committee to re-examine in the light of what has
				<lb />
				been observed earlier.
				<lb />
				We make it clear that if
				<lb />
				upon reconsideration of the matter the Committee
				<lb />
				takes a view that the induction of the nominees of
				<lb />
				the franchisees will not result in any conflict of
				<lb />
				interest, it shall be free to stick to its
				<lb />
				recommendations in which event the recommendations
				<lb />
				shall be deemed to have been accepted by this Court
				<lb />
				to be formalized and carried out in such manner as
				<lb />
				the Committee may decide.
				<lb />
			</p>


			<p>
				89. We may, in conclusion, deal with two other
				<lb />
				recommendations which have also come under criticism
				<lb />
				by the BCCI and the intervening associations.
				<lb />
				The
				<lb />
				first of these recommendations proposes a cap on the
				<lb />
				number of terms for which an officer bearer can
				<lb />
				serve and the optimum period for which one can be a
				<lb />
				member of the apex council. The recommendation also
				<lb />
				provides for cooling off period between two terms.
				<lb />
				It also prescribes grounds for disqualification of
				<lb />
				office bearer which were otherwise absent in the
				<lb />
				existing rules and regulations of the BCCI. These
				<lb />
				recommendations come in the wake of a finding by the
				<lb />
				Committee that under the present dispensation office
				<lb />
				bearers could continue for any number of terms. It
				<lb />
				was also noticed that no grounds for disqualifying
				<lb />
				an office bearers were prescribed. The Committee
				<lb />
				found both of these to be unacceptable and, in our
				<lb />
				opinion, rightly so. Given the problems that often
				<lb />
				arise on account of individuals holding office for
				<lb />
				any number of consecutive terms, the Committee was,
				<lb />
				in our opinion, justified in recommending the length
				<lb />
				of a term in office. A three year term recommended
				<lb />
				by the Committee is, in our opinion, reasonable. So
				<lb />
				also, the prescription of cooling off period between
				<lb />
				two terms cannot be faulted. Similarly, an optimum
				<lb />
				period of 9 years as a member of the apex council
				<lb />
				cannot also be termed as unreasonable. Grounds for
				<lb />
				disqualification like unsoundness of mind, the
				<lb />
				member becoming a minister or holding a membership
				<lb />
				in any sporting body also meet the requirement of
				<lb />
				reasonableness and do not call for interference from
				<lb />
				the court. The contention that the recommendations
				<lb />
				have no rationale or that the same are contrary to
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				provisions
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				Tamil
				<lb />
				Nadu
				<lb />
				Societies
				<lb />
				Registration Act deserve notice only to be rejected.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				90. The other recommendation which we may deal with
				<lb />
				is the overhaul of the existing Committees of the
				<lb />
				BCCI on the ground that they do not have clearly
				<lb />
				defined terms of reference. The Committee has on the
				<lb />
				basis of a thorough consideration and deliberation
				<lb />
				with all concerned recommended that the BCCI ought
				<lb />
				to adopt an approach that would institutionalize the
				<lb />
				management of its administrative affairs rather than
				<lb />
				such affairs being run on an ad-hoc basis. The
				<lb />
				Committee has, on that premise, recommended an
				<lb />
				administrative set up which it has evolved on the
				<lb />
				basis of its interactions with people who have the
				<lb />
				necessary expertise and insight into the needs of
				<lb />
				the BCCI and its associations. We, therefore, see no
				<lb />
				compelling
				<lb />
				reason
				<lb />
				for
				<lb />
				us
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				reject
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				recommendation made by the Committee, especially
				<lb />
				when
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				objective
				<lb />
				underlying
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				said
				<lb />
				recommendation is not only laudable but achievable
				<lb />
				through the medium of the change recommended by the
				<lb />
				Committee.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				91. In the result, we accept the report submitted by
				<lb />
				the Committee and the recommendations made therein
				<lb />
				with such modifications and clarifications as have
				<lb />
				been set out by us in the body of this judgment.
				<lb />
				Having said that we must hasten to add that the
				<lb />
				140
				<lb />
				Page 141
				<lb />
				implementation of the recommendations is equally
				<lb />
				important and ought to be achieved within a
				<lb />
				reasonable period. The transition from the old to
				<lb />
				the new system recommended by the Committee shall
				<lb />
				have to be under the watchful supervision of this
				<lb />
				Court.
				<lb />
				Constrains
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				time
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				multiple
				<lb />
				dimensions of the recommendations made however make
				<lb />
				it difficult for us to take that supervisory role
				<lb />
				upon ourselves. The supervision of the transition
				<lb />
				can, in our opinion, be left to be undertaken by the
				<lb />
				Committee not only because it has a complete
				<lb />
				understanding of and insight into the nature of the
				<lb />
				problems sought to be remedied but also the ability
				<lb />
				to draw timelines for taking of steps necessary for
				<lb />
				the implementation of the proposed reforms. We are
				<lb />
				conscious of fact that the process may be time
				<lb />
				consuming but we hope that the same should be
				<lb />
				completed within a period of four months or at best
				<lb />
				six months from today. We, therefore, request the
				<lb />
				committee
				<lb />
				headed
				<lb />
				by
				<lb />
				Justice
				<lb />
				Lodha
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				draw
				<lb />
				appropriate timelines for implementation of the
				<lb />
				141
				<lb />
				Page 142
				<lb />
				recommendations and supervise the implementation
				<lb />
				thereof.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				92. Needless to say that the BCCI and all concerned
				<lb />
				shall cooperate and act in aid of the Committee and
				<lb />
				its directives. Should any impediments arise, the
				<lb />
				Committee
				<lb />
				shall
				<lb />
				be
				<lb />
				free
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				seek
				<lb />
				appropriate
				<lb />
				directions from this Court by filing a status report
				<lb />
				in that regard.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				93. The Committee shall be free to determine and
				<lb />
				direct payment of its fee for the time it devotes
				<lb />
				pursuant to this order.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				94. With these observations we dispose of the matter
				<lb />
				finally placing on record our deep appreciation for
				<lb />
				the commendable work which the Committee has done in
				<lb />
				a short period. We also place on record our
				<lb />
				appreciation and gratitude to Mr. Gopal Subramanium,
				<lb />
				senior advocate, for lending valuable assistance to
				<lb />
				us as Amicus Curiae. No costs.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				.....................CJI.
				<lb />
				(T.S. THAKUR)
				<lb />
				.......................J.
				<lb />
				(FAKKIR MOHAMED IBRAHIM KALIFULLA)
				<lb />
				NEW DELHI.
				<lb />
				JULY 18, 2016
				<lb />
				143
			</p>


	</text>
</tei>