<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<p>operative Societies Act, 1983, from the Deputy Registrar of Co-operative<lb/> Societies, Tirupattur Circle, Vellore District, 1 st respondent herein,<lb/> alleging that the petitioner was jointly responsible, along with her<lb/> husband, in the Arbitral proceedings, for the loss of Rs.29,99,823/-, with<lb/> interest, in the matter of waiver of interest, during the period 2002-03.<lb/> Pending arbitration proceedings, the 1 st respondent, has issued a notice,<lb/> dated 27.07.2007, ordering a conditional attachment of immovable<lb/> properties of the petitioner, under Section 167 of the Tamil Nadu Co-<lb/>operative Societies Act, r/w. Rule 140(1) of the Rules framed<lb/> thereunder.<lb/></p>

			<p>3.<lb/> Being aggrieved by the conditional attachment, the<lb/> petitioner has preferred W.P.Nos.29521 and 29663 of 2007 and that the<lb/> same were dismissed on 25.10.2007, on the ground that the petitioners<lb/> could avail an appeal remedy, after the passing of the final award.<lb/> Review petitions filed were also dismissed on 10.04.2008, with some<lb/> modifications to the earlier order, dated 25.10.2007. Subsequently,<lb/> summons were issued to the petitioner, by the 1 st respondent, to appear<lb/> for an enquiry. But the petitioner ignored the same. The last enquiry<lb/> was held on 29.12.2008. The petitioner did not appear on that date, so<lb/> as to defend herself or authorised anybody to appear on her behalf, in<lb/> the arbitration proceedings. She remained ex parte.<lb/></p>

			<p>4.<lb/> The petitioner has further submitted that since 29.12.2008,<lb/> there was no information or notice to her. While so, she came to know<lb/> that the 1 st respondent has passed an award in Arbitration Dispute<lb/> No.1844/2007-08, on 05.07.2012, holding that the 3 rd respondent, viz.,<lb/> her husband alone was responsible and liable for the alleged loss caused<lb/> to the society and no finding was recorded against the petitioner. In the<lb/> award, dated 05.07.2012 in Arbitration Dispute No.1844/2007-08, the 1 st<lb/> respondent has directed that a sum of Rs.29,99,823/-, should be<lb/> recovered, with 21% interest, from the 3 rd respondent alone. Thus,<lb/> according to the petitioner, in the said award, dated 05.07.2012, the<lb/> petitioners have been exonerated from their liability.<lb/></p>

			<p>5.<lb/> Inasmuch as the immovable properties in the name of the<lb/> petitioners, came to be conditionally attached under Section 167 of the<lb/> Tamil Nadu Co-operative Societies Act, 1983 read with Rule 140(1) of the<lb/> Tamil Nadu Co-operative Societies Rules, 1988, pending Arbitration Claim<lb/> of the 2 nd respondent-Society and by virtue of their exoneration from<lb/> liability, it is incumbent on the part of the Deputy Registrar of Co-<lb/>operative Societies, Thirupattur Circle, Vellore District, 1 st respondent<lb/> herein, to withdraw the attachment. Having regard to the discharge of<lb/> the petitioner from the arbitration claim, Dispute No.1844/2007-08<lb/> Sa.Pa., dated 05.07.2012, of the 1 st respondent, the petitioners have<lb/> filed W.P.No.25772 of 2012, for a Mandamus, directing the 1 st<lb/> respondent, to withdraw the conditional attachment of the petitioner&apos;s<lb/> immovable properties, made in CEP.No.223 of 2006-07, dated<lb/> 27.07.2007, exercising the power under Rule 140(3)(c) of the Tamil Nadu<lb/> Co-operative Societies Rules, 1988. In both the present writ petitions,<lb/> Mrs.R.Indrani, wife of the 3 rd respondent and her daughter,<lb/> Ms.R.Preetha, have prayed for a Mandamus, directing the 1 st respondent<lb/> to withdraw the conditional attachment of the fixed deposits, dated<lb/> 20.11.2004, 11.03.2005 and 31.03.2006 respectively, for Rs.11 Lakhs,<lb/> standing in the name of the petitioners, made in CEP.No.223 of 2006-07,<lb/> dated 27.07.2007, under Section 167 of the Tamil Nadu Co-operative<lb/> Societies Act, 1983, consequent upon the discharge of the petitioners,<lb/> from the arbitration claim in Dispute No.1844/2007-08 Sa.Pa., dated<lb/> 05.07.2012 of the 1 st respondent, with a further direction to the 2 nd<lb/> respondent Society, to repay the fixed deposits, with interest upto date.<lb/></p>

			<p>6.<lb/> The petitioners have two deposits, one in the name of the 2 nd<lb/> petitioner for Rs.8,00,000/-and another, in the name of the 1 st<lb/> petitioner, for Rs.3,00,000/-. According to the petitioners, they have<lb/> their own sources, from which, deposits were made, in the 2 nd<lb/> respondent-Society. Since the husband of the 1 st petitioner was employed<lb/> in the 2 nd respondent-Society, the amounts were deposited in the<lb/> Society. The petitioners have further submitted that if the said amount<lb/> was ill-gotten, they would not have deposited in the same, in the 2 nd<lb/> respondent-Society, where the 3 rd respondent was employed. According<lb/> to them, the deposits were made on 20.11.2004, 11.03.2005 and<lb/> 31.03.2006 respectively, with their own source of income.<lb/></p>

			<p>7.<lb/> Initially, the Deputy Registrar of Co-operative Societies,<lb/> Tirupattur, Vellore District, has filed a counter affidavit, dated<lb/> 31.01.2013, contending inter aliat that the third respondent, the then<lb/> Secretary of C-1514, Girisamudhram Primary Agricultural Co-operative<lb/> Credit Society, husband of the petitioner, had misappropriated<lb/> Rs.29,99,823/-from the society and after enquiry, under Section 81 of<lb/> the Tamil Nadu Co-operative Societies Act, disciplinary action was taken<lb/> against him and that he was dismissed from service on 08.01.2008. While<lb/> taking steps to recover the loss caused to the Society, the third<lb/> respondent has made attempts to sell the assets, which stood in the<lb/> name of the petitioners, to evade attachment. Therefore, a conditional<lb/> attachment was made under section 167 of Act, to safeguard the interest<lb/> of the society. Writ Petitions preferred by the petitioners, in<lb/> W.P.No.27141, 27142 and 29663 of 2007, were already dismissed. Review<lb/> Petitions preferred by them were also dismissed. According to the<lb/> Deputy Registrar of Co-operative Societies, Thirupattur, Vellore District,<lb/> the amount lying in the fixed deposits, in the name of the 1 st petitioner<lb/> and her minor child, were deposited by 3 rd respondent, out of the<lb/> misappropriated funds of the Society and therefore, the society has filed<lb/> Arbitration claim on 14.03.2007, before the Deputy Registrar, Tirupattur.<lb/> After giving proper opportunities to the 3 rd respondent, the Deputy<lb/> Registrar, Tirupattur, 1 st respondent herein, has passed orders in ARC<lb/> No.1844/2007-08, Sa.Pa., dated 05.07.2012.<lb/></p>

			<p>8.<lb/> According to the 1 st respondent, the petitioner and her minor<lb/> child, were not the earning members, nor inherited any property form<lb/> the 1 st petitioner&apos;s parents and therefore, the properties and deposits in<lb/> the name of petitioners, are nothing but the amounts, diverted from the<lb/> funds of the society, by misusing the powers of the third respondent. In<lb/> the arbitration claim in ARC.No.1844/2007-08, the third respondent was<lb/> given sufficient opportunities on 14.09.2007, 02.12.2008, 16.12.2008 and<lb/> 29.12.2008 respectively and upon perusal of the relevant records and<lb/> taking note of the admission of the third respondent, orders were passed<lb/> in ARC No.1844/2007-2008 on 05.07.2012 to recover the suffered loss of<lb/> Rs.29,99,823/-together with interest.<lb/></p>

			<p>9.<lb/> The 1 st respondent has further submitted that as the deposits<lb/> available in the bank, in the names of the petitioner and her minor child,<lb/> to an extent of Rs.11,00,000/-, were insufficient to satisfy the decreed<lb/> amount, further attachment of the properties, is also necessiated.<lb/> According to the 1 st respondent, the claim of the petitioners that the<lb/> properties attached are self acquired properties, has no substance, as<lb/> the petitioners have no source of income to purchase ay property or to<lb/> deposit the amounts, in the 2 nd respondent-Bank.<lb/></p>

			<p>10. Thereafter, on 28.03.2013, another counter affidavit has<lb/> been filed by the 1 st respondent, contending inter alia that, on the<lb/> earlier occasion, as it was specifically contended by the learned counsel<lb/> for the petitioners that no orders have been passed by the 1 st<lb/> respondent, insofar as the proceedings initiated by the 2 nd respondent, is<lb/> concerned, by invoking Section 90 of the Tamil Nadu Co-operative<lb/> Societies Act, r/w. Rule 107 of the Rules, against the petitioners in Thava<lb/> No.1844-A/2007-08 Sa.Pa.<lb/></p>

			<p>11. The 1 st respondent has further submitted that the<lb/> proceedings No.1844-A/2007-08, summons were served on the<lb/> petitioners, as well as, on the third respondent, husband of the 1 st<lb/> petitioner and father of the 2 nd petitioner respectively, on several<lb/> occasions, viz., 21.08.2007, 21.11.2008, 01.12.2008 and finally on<lb/> 08.12.2008 and they were directed to appear for enquiry on 16.12.2008.<lb/> Based on which, the 3 rd respondent appeared on 16.12.2008 and<lb/> 17.12.2008 and made a statement that he was representing, on behalf of<lb/> his wife and daughter also, i.e., the petitioners. Thereafter, the 3 rd<lb/> respondent, after taking note of all the documents, filed by the 2 nd<lb/> respondent-Society, before the 1 st respondent, sought for an<lb/> adjournment, for the purpose of submitting his explanation/written<lb/> submission, on behalf of the petitioners also. Thereafter on 29.12.2008,<lb/> the 3 rd respondent appeared before the Arbitrator, 1 st respondent and<lb/> gave a statement that he had perused all the documents in the abovesaid<lb/> proceedings, for the purpose of defending the case, against himself and<lb/> as well as the petitioners herein, in the capacity of their representative,<lb/> and requested to adopt the statements/explanation filed by him, in<lb/> another proceedings in Thava No.1844/2007-08, before the 1 st<lb/> respondent, as his defence and also as the defence of the petitioners<lb/> herein, in proceedings No.1844-A/2007-08.<lb/></p>

			<p>12. The 1 st respondent has further submitted that after giving<lb/> ample opportunities to both the sides and considering the above<lb/> statements in proceedings No.1844-A/2007-08, by order, dated<lb/> 03.01.2013, he has passed orders in surcharge proceedings in Thava<lb/></p>

			<item>No.1844-A/2007-08, confirming the liability of the petitioners, as well as<lb/> the 3 rd respondent and further directed the 2 nd respondent-Society<lb/> herein, to recover the misappropriated amount, from and out of the<lb/> movables as well as immovable properties of the petitioners and also the<lb/> 3 rd respondent herein. Moreover, when the abovesaid order, dated<lb/> 03.01.2013 in Arbitration Dispute No.1844-A/2007-08, of the 1 st<lb/> respondent was communicated, to the petitioners, as well as to the 3 rd<lb/> respondent, they have refused to receive the same, and therefore, the<lb/> same was affixed in the premises of the petitioners, as well as the 3 rd<lb/> respondent, as early as on 04.01.2013 itself.<lb/></item>

			<item>13. According to the 1 st respondent, the present writ petitions<lb/> are not maintainable, as there is an alternative remedy, under Section<lb/> 152 of the Tamil Nadu Co-operative Societies Act, 1983 and therefore, by<lb/> invoking the said provision, the petitioners ought to have filed an appeal,<lb/> as against the order, dated 03.01.2013 in Arbitration Proceedings<lb/> No.1844-A/2007-08, before the Co-operative Tribunal. According to 1 st<lb/> respondent, as the 3 rd respondent is the sole breadwinner of the family<lb/> and all the immovable properties and fixed deposits in the 2 nd<lb/> respondent-Society, stood in the name of the petitioners, have been<lb/> earned only by the 3 rd respondent and that the same has been confirmed<lb/> after analysing the encumbrance certificate of the properties, as well as<lb/> the period of deposits and therefore, there is no illegality or infirmity in<lb/> attaching the deposits of the petitioners.<lb/></item>

			<p>14. The Special Officer, Girisamudhram Primary Agricultural Co-<lb/>operative Bank, Girisamudhram Post, Vaniyambadi Taluk, Vellore, 2 nd<lb/> respondent has also filed a counter affidavit on the same lines, as that of<lb/> the 1 st respondent.<lb/></p>

			<p>15. On the above pleadings and referring to the records of<lb/> proceedings, Mr.S.Venkataraman, learned counsel for the petitioners<lb/> submitted that the writ petitions came up for admission on 14.09.2012.<lb/> On that day, the 1 st respondent has filed a counter affidavit in the open<lb/> Court on 31.01.2013. The matter was called on 27.02.2013, it was<lb/> posted for orders on 01.03.2013. On the said date, Mr.T.K.Prabhakaran,<lb/> Deputy Registrar of Co-operative Societies, Tirupattur Circle, Vellore<lb/> District, has filed another counter affidavit on 28.03.2013, stating that<lb/> an award has been passed on 03.01.2013, vide proceedings in Thava<lb/> No.1844-A/2007-08, in which, liability has been fixed on the petitioners,<lb/> as well as on the 3 rd respondent and in the said award, the Deputy<lb/> Registrar of the Co-operative Societies, Thirupattur Circle, Thirupattur,<lb/> Vellore District, 1 st respondent, has also directed the 2 nd respondent-<lb/>Society, to recover the misappropriated amount, from and out of the<lb/> movable, as well as immovable properties of the petitioners and the 3 rd<lb/> respondent. He further submitted that earlier, in the counter affidavit<lb/> filed by the very same person on 31.01.2013, nothing was mentioned<lb/> about the award, dated 03.01.2013, in Thava No.1844-A/2007-08.<lb/></p>

			<p>16. According to the learned counsel for the petitioners, the<lb/> subsequent award, dated 03.01.2013, in Arbitration Dispute No.1844-<lb/>A/2007-08 is manipulated, behind the back of the petitioners and it is<lb/> nothing but a cooked up award by the 1 st respondent. He also submitted<lb/> that the petitioners were not issued with any notices, nor they were<lb/> made aware of the award, dated 03.01.2013, in Arbitration Dispute<lb/> No.1844-A/2007-08. According to him, the reason assigned in the<lb/> counter affidavit filed on 28.03.2013, by Mr.T.K.Prabakaran, Deputy<lb/> Registrar of Co-operative Societies, Tirupattur Circle, Tirupattur, Vellore<lb/> District, that by inadvertence, the subsequent award, dated 03.01.2013,<lb/> was not mentioned in the counter affidavit, filed on 31.01.2013, should<lb/> not be accepted, as the subsequent award is only a manipulated award.<lb/></p>

			<p>17. Learned counsel for the petitioners further submitted that<lb/> both the petitioners have not received any notice or summons, in the<lb/> subsequent arbitral proceedings in Thava No.1844-A/2007-08, dated<lb/> 03.01.2013, nor they have authorised anybody to appear, on their behalf.<lb/> As the 2 nd respondent has manipulated the award in Thava No.1844-<lb/>A/2007-08, dated 03.01.2013, after filing of the writ petitions, according<lb/> to the petitioners, there is no need to challenge the same. On the<lb/> contrary, no sooner the petitioners were absolved of their liability in<lb/> Thava No.1844/2007-08 Sa.Pa., dated 05.07.2012, the conditional<lb/> attachment of their properties, made under Section 167 of the Tamil<lb/> Nadu Co-operative Societies Act, r/w. Rule 140(1) of the Rules framed<lb/> thereunder, ought to have been raised by the respondents 1 and 2, and in<lb/> the abovesaid circumstances, the petitioners are entitled to the relief<lb/> sought for, in both the writ petitions.<lb/></p>

			<p>18. As regards the allegation of manipulation, non-service of<lb/> summons in the subsequent proceedings and ignorance of the award<lb/> made in Thava No.1844-A/2007-08, dated 03.01.2013, this Court<lb/> directed the learned Additional Government Pleader to produce the<lb/> relevant files. Pursuant to the directions, records were produced.<lb/></p>

			<p>19. Perusal of the record shows that an award has been passed in<lb/> Thava No.1844/2007-08 Sa.Pa., dated 05.07.2012, discharging the<lb/> petitioners. Files disclose that for the very same amount of<lb/> Rs.29,99,823/-with interest, under various items, an arbitration claim in<lb/> Dispute No.1844-A/2007-08, has been raised before the Deputy Registrar,<lb/> Thiruvannamalai and notice, dated 21.08.2007, has been sent to the 3 rd<lb/> respondent and the petitioners. Along with the said notice, a copy of the<lb/> Arbitration Claim, dated 14.03.2007, has been sent. The same has been<lb/> received on 16.02.2008 by the 3 rd respondent, for himself and on behalf<lb/> of the petitioners also. Photocopy of the abovesaid notice and claim are<lb/> extracted hereunder:<lb/> 20. One Mr.Savarimani, Office Office, has made an endorsement<lb/> that the notice has been served on all the three respondents, in the<lb/> claim petition. But on the backside of the notice, it is found that the<lb/> arbitration number is given as 1844/06-07 Sa.Pa. Perusal of the records<lb/> further disclose that Smt.G.R.Indrani and R.Pritha-Minor, the petitioners<lb/> herein, have filed W.P.Nos.27141, 27142, 27148, 29521 and 29663 of<lb/> 2007, for the following reliefs,<lb/> (i) Prayer in W.P.No.27141 of 2007: Writ of<lb/> Certiorari, calling for the records, relating to the notice<lb/> C.E.P.No.223 of 2006-07, dated 27.07.2007 of the 1 st<lb/> respondent herein and to quash the same, insofar as it<lb/> attaches the immovable properties of the petitioner<lb/> (Mrs.G.R.Indrani).<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii) Prayer in W.P.No.27142 of 2007: Writ of<lb/> Certiorarified Mandamus, calling for the records, relating to<lb/> the notice C.E.P.No.223 of 2006-07, dated 27.07.2007 of the<lb/> 1 st respondent herein and to quash the same and to<lb/> consequently direct the 2 nd respondent to repay the fixed<lb/> deposit of Rs.5 Lacs standing in the name of the petitioner<lb/> (Mrs.G.R.Indrani) which matured on 30.03.2007 for<lb/> repayment in fixed deposit receipt No.024564.<lb/> (iii) Prayer in W.P.No.27148 of 2007: Writ of<lb/> Certiorarified Mandamus, calling for the records, relating to<lb/> the notice C.E.P.No.223 of 2006-07, dated 27.07.2007 of the<lb/> 1 st respondent herein and to quash the same and to<lb/> consequently direct the 2 nd respondent to repay the fixed<lb/> deposit of Rs.3 Lacs standing in the name of the petitioner<lb/> (Minor Pritha) which matured on 10.03.2007 for repayment<lb/> in fixed deposit receipt No.024501.<lb/></p>

			<p>(iv) Prayer in W.P.No.29521 of 2007: Writ of<lb/> Certiorari, calling for the records, relating to the<lb/> claim/dispute No.1844 A of 2007-2008, dated Nil filed by<lb/> the 2 nd respondent society pending on the file of the 1 st<lb/> respondent; to quash the same, insofar as the petitioner<lb/> (minor Pritha) is concerned.<lb/></p>

			<p>(v) Prayer in W.P.No.29663 of 2007: Writ of<lb/> Certiorari, calling for the records, relating to the<lb/> claim/dispute No.1844 A of 2007-2008, dated Nil filed by<lb/> the 2 nd respondent society pending on the file of the 1 st<lb/> respondent; to quash the same, insofar as the petitioner<lb/> (Mrs.G.R.Indrani) is concerned.<lb/></p>

			<p>21. Like in the present writ petitions, the Deputy Registrar of<lb/> Co-operative Societies, Tirupattur Circle, Tirupattur, Vellore District and<lb/> the Special Officer, C-1514 Girisamudhram Primary Agricultural Co-<lb/>operative Bank Ltd., Girisamudhram Post, Vaniyambadi Taluk, Vellore<lb/> District, were respondents 1 and 2 in the abovesaid writ petitions. After<lb/> considering the rival submissions, a learned Single Judge, by order, dated<lb/> 25.10.2007, has dismissed the writ petitions, as hereunder:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;</p>

			<p>3. As per the Tamil Nadu Co-operative Societies Act,<lb/> against all arbitration proceedings, a regular appeal will lie<lb/> both in law and facts, that too, before a Judicial forum and<lb/> it cannot be brushed aside as an effective forum. Further,<lb/> for moving the Tribunal, there is no pre-condition of any<lb/> deposit will arise. The Tribunal has powers to grant an<lb/> interim order also. When there is an effective alternate<lb/> remedy is available to the petitioners, the question of<lb/> entertaining these writ petitions, does not arise. Further,<lb/> the claim is made by the Co-operative Society in respect of<lb/> attachment of the property, the transactions are only<lb/> contractual in nature. This Court, by the exercise of its<lb/> power under Article 226 of the Constitution of India, cannot<lb/> invoke the writ jurisdiction and interfere with every<lb/> transaction that the petitioners have entered into with a Co-<lb/>operative Society or the Arbitration awards made pursuant to<lb/> the claim made by the Society.<lb/></p>

			<p>4. Under these circumstances, these writ petitions are<lb/> dismissed. If the petitioners institute any appeal in terms of<lb/> Section 152 of the Tamil Nadu Co-operative Societies Act,<lb/> 1983, against final Award made under Section 90, within a<lb/> period of three weeks from the date of receipt of a copy of<lb/> this order, the Co-operative Tribunal will entertain the same<lb/> on merits, without reference to the limitation.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>22. Review Application Nos.20 to 24 of 2008 have been filed to<lb/> review the orders passed in the abovesaid writ petitions and perusal of<lb/> the orders passed therein, shows that learned counsel for the petitioners<lb/> had pointed out that, in Paragraph 1 of the orders made in the writ<lb/> petitions, this Court had mistakenly observed that the petitioners were<lb/> wife and minor daughter of one late K.Rajendran. It has been pleaded<lb/> that Mr.K.Rajendran, is alive and therefore, the word &quot;late&quot; prefixed,<lb/> before the name of Mr.K.Rajendran, has to be deleted. Learned counsel<lb/> had also submitted that there is no award under Section 90 of the Tamil<lb/> Nadu Co-operative Societies Act, 1983, so as to enable the petitioners<lb/> therein to file an appeal, in terms of Section 152 of the Act. The said<lb/> position was also not disputed by the learned counsel for the<lb/> respondents therein. In these circumstances, the learned Judge, while<lb/> dismissing the review petitions, has clarified the orders made in the<lb/> writ petitions, to the effect that as and when an award is passed in<lb/> terms of Section 90 of the Act, the petitioners therein can avail such<lb/> remedies are open to them under law. From the above, it could be<lb/> deduced that there was another proceedings in Arbitration Dispute<lb/> No.1844-A/2007-08, in respect of the same amount, and that the<lb/> petitioners have prayed to quash the proceedings in Arbitration Dispute<lb/> No.1844A/2007-08, dated Nil, of the Society.<lb/></p>

			<p>23. Perusal of the files, at Page 89, shows that the Deputy<lb/> Registrar of Co-operative Societies, Tirupattur Circle, Tirupattur, Vellore<lb/> District, is stated to have sent a notice, dated 21.11.2008, in arbitration<lb/> claim, Dispute No.1844-A/2007-08, to the petitioners herein and the 3 rd<lb/> respondent, directing them to submit their reply on 02.12.2008, by 11.45<lb/> A.M., in the Office of the Deputy Registrar of Co-operative Societies. It<lb/> is also stated that in the event of any failure to appear and submit their<lb/> reply, a decision would be rendered, on the basis of the available<lb/> materials on record.<lb/> Photocopy of the said notice is extracted<lb/> hereunder:<lb/></p>

			<p>24. Thereafter, another notice, dated 01.12.2008 seemed to<lb/> have been sent in Thava No.1844/A/2007-08 Sa.Pa., to the petitioners<lb/> and the third respondent, directing them to appear before the 1 st<lb/> respondent on 08.12.2008 at 12.30 P.M. The said notice is said to have<lb/> been served by one Mr.R.Ekambaram and acknowledged by the 3 rd<lb/> respondent, for himself and on behalf of the petitioners. Photocopy of<lb/> the said notice, is extracted hereunder:<lb/></p>

			<p>25. Yet another notice in Thava No.1844/A/2006-07 Sa.Pa., has<lb/> been sent on 08.12.2008 to the 3 rd respondent and the petitioners, to<lb/> appear, in the Office of the 1 st respondent, on 16.12.2008 at 12.30 P.M.<lb/> The said notice has also been acknowledged by the 3 rd respondent for<lb/> himself and on behalf of the petitioners. Photocopy of the said notice, is<lb/> extracted hereunder:<lb/></p>

			<p>26. Files at Page No.101, further disclose that on 05.12.2008,<lb/> the 1 st petitioner has sent a letter to the Deputy Registrar of Co-op.<lb/> Societies, Tirupattur Circle, Vellore District, 1 st respondent herein,<lb/> stating that she could not appear for the enquiry, due to the marriage of<lb/> her daughter. On the same day, the 2 nd petitioner (Minor Preetha) has<lb/> also sent a letter, giving reason for non-appearance, which is found at<lb/> Page No.103 in the Files. Further, in both the letters, it has been stated<lb/> that the petitioners were aware of the summons, through the 3 rd<lb/> respondent.<lb/> In the reference column in both the letters, the<lb/> proceedings, that has been referred, is &quot;1844/07-08 Sa.Pa., dated<lb/> 01.12.2008&quot;.<lb/></p>

			<p>27. However, files at Page No.109, show that the 1 st petitioner<lb/> has written a letter, dated 11.12.2008, to the 1 st respondent, stating that<lb/> when there is no connection between her and the Bank, summons served<lb/> on her, caused mental agony. She has prayed for dismissal of the<lb/> arbitration proceedings. In the same manner, the 2 nd petitioner, Minor<lb/> Preetha, has also sent a letter, on the same day. In both the letters,<lb/> both the petitioners have noted the proceedings as, &quot;Thava No.1844-<lb/>A/2006-07, dated 08.12.2008.<lb/></p>

			<p>28. Files further disclose that in respect of the arbitration claim,<lb/> the 3 rd respondent seemed to have appeared before the 1 st respondent on<lb/> 16.12.2008 and given statements. On 17.12.2008, he has perused certain<lb/> records. The statements and records perused, are as follows:<lb/></p>

			<p>16/12/2008<lb/> 1. 1/3/2004 Kjy; 27/5/06 tiu vGjg;gl;Ls;s jPu;khd<lb/> g[j;jfj;jpy; 26/10/2004 njjp jPu;khdk; 3. ghu;f;fg;gl;lJ/<lb/> gf;f vz;/78 bjhif U:/88.125-?/<lb/></p>

			<p>2. 30/3/02 Kjy; 31/3/2002 tiu vGjg;gl;l jpdg;ngnul;oy;<lb/> (31/3/05)?y;<lb/> Blocked<lb/> loan<lb/> KfL<lb/> bra;ag;gl;Ls;sij<lb/> ghu;f;fg;gl;lJ/ gf;f vz;/111 bjhif :6/95<lb/></p>

			<p>3. jpdg;ngnuL 1/4/04 Kjy; 21/6/04 tiu cs;s g[j;jfj;jpy;<lb/> 21/6/04 njjp ghu;f;fg;gl;lJ/ gf;f vz;/198. 199 KCC<lb/> buhf;f tN:y;/<lb/></p>

			<item>4. jpdg;ngnuL 21/6/04 Kjy; 3/9/04 tiu cs;s ngnul;oy; gf;f<lb/> vz;/19.20.23.24.25 ghu;f;fg;gl;lJ/ buhf;f tN:y; xt;bthU<lb/> egu;fspd; tut[ jdpj;jdpahf vLf;fg;gl;lJ/ buhf;f tN:y;/<lb/></item>

			<item>5. 21/6/04 Kjy; 3/9/04 tiu vGjg;gl;l jpdg;ngnul;oy; gf;f<lb/> vz;/2.3 ghu;f;fg;gl;lJ/ interest tN:y;(KfL)<lb/></item>

			<item>6. 1/3/2004 Kjy; 27/5/2006 tiu cs;s jPu;khd g[j;jfj;jpy; ?<lb/></item>

			<item>CUNMT jPu;khdk; 1. gf;f vz;/6. 22/3/04 njjp<lb/> ghu;f;fg;gl;lJ/ jPu;khdk; 2. gf;f vz;/7. 22/3/04 njjp<lb/> ghu;f;fg;gl;lJ/<lb/> nkw;fz;l gjpntLfis ghu;j;njd;<lb/> vd;W rhu;g[ bra;fpnwd;<lb/> --ifbahg;gk;--16/12/2008<lb/> vd; Kd;dpiyapy; ghu;itaplg;gl;lJ -<lb/>--ifbahg;gk;--16/12/2008<lb/></item>

			<p>17/12/2008<lb/> 1. 130/3/02 Kjy; 31/3/02 tiu cs;s jpdg;ngnul;oy; gf;f<lb/> vz;/111?y; cs;s VCNMT m&apos;; fld; tptuk; vLf;fg;gl;lJ/<lb/></p>

			<p>2. bghJ ngnul;oy; 2004?2005?y; gf;f vz;/340.160<lb/> ghu;f;fg;gl;lJ/<lb/></p>

			<p>3. jpdg;ngnuL 23/11/04 Kjy; 31/1/05 tiu cs;sjpy;<lb/> g/vz;/193 Kjy; 200k;. bghJ ngnul;oy; gf;f vz;/341k;<lb/> ghu;f;fg;gl;lJ/<lb/></p>

			<p>4. jpdg;ngnuL 3/2/04 Kjy; 31/3/04 tiu cs;sjpy; 29/2/04-<lb/>16/3/04 njjpapy; gf;f vz;/120 Kjy; 124 &amp; 185<lb/> ghu;f;fg;gl;lJ/<lb/></p>

			<item>5. bghJ ngnuL 29/3/05f;F gf;f vz;/334k;. jpdg;ngnuL gf;f<lb/> vz;/197. 198 ghu;f;fg;gl;lJ/<lb/></item>

			<item>6. jpdg;ngnuL 31/3/05y; gf;f vz;/28k;. bghJngul;oy; gf;f<lb/> vz;/334 ghu;f;fg;gl;lJ/<lb/></item>

			<item>7. 29/3/05y;<lb/> jpdg;ngnul;oy;<lb/> gf;f<lb/> vz;/196?k;.<lb/></item>

			<item>bghJngnul;oy; gf;f vz;/334 ghu;f;fg;gl;lJ/<lb/> nkw;fz;l midj;J gjpntLfis ghu;j;njd; vd;W gzpt[ld;<lb/> bjhptpj;Jf;bfhs;fpnwd;/<lb/> --ifbahg;gk;--17/12/2008<lb/> nfhhpa Mtz&apos;;fis ghu;itapl;nld;<lb/> --ifbahg;gk;--17/12/2008<lb/> Jizgjpthsu; mtu;fspd; Mizapd;go gpujpthjp nfhhpa midj;J<lb/> Mtd&apos;;fSk; mtUf;F 16/12/08. 17/12/08 Mfpa njjpfspy;<lb/> fhz;gpf;fg;gl;lJ/ mtw;iw ghu;itapl;L gpujpthjp Fwpg;g[<lb/> vLj;Jf;bfhz;lhu;<lb/> --ifbahg;gk;--17/12/2008 (brayhsu;)<lb/></item>

			<item>vd; Kd;dpiyapy; ghu;itaplg;gl;lJ<lb/> --ifbahg;gk;--17/12/2008<lb/></item>

			<item>29. Page 123 of the Files, is a letter, issued by Mr.V.Elango,<lb/> Secretary (Incharge) of the 2 nd respondent-Bank, to the 1 st respondent,<lb/> requesting for postponement of the enquiry in Arbitration Claim<lb/> No.1844/2007-08 Sa.Pa., which reads as follows:<lb/> mk;gY}u; bjhlf;f ntshz;ik Tl;Lwt[ t&apos;;fp ypl;/.<lb/> mk;gY}u; ? 635 801/ (nt/kh/)<lb/> njjp 18/12/2008<lb/> tpLeu;<lb/> V.,s&apos;;nfh<lb/> brayhsu; (bghWg;g[)<lb/> C/1514 fphprKj;jpuk; bjh/nt/T/t&apos;;fp<lb/> fphprKj;jpuk;<lb/> bgWeu;<lb/> Jizg;gjpthsu; mtu;fs;.<lb/> Tl;Lwt[ r&apos;;f&apos;;fspd; Jizg;gjpthsu; mYtyfk;.<lb/> jpUg;gj;J}u;/<lb/> ma;ah.<lb/> bghUs;:jhth vz;/1844-2007?08 r/g/<lb/> miHg;ghiz njjp 29/12/2008y;<lb/> vd Fwpg;gpl;lij khw;wp kWnjjp tH&apos;;f<lb/> nfhWjy; rk;ge;jkhf/<lb/> ehd; bjhlu;e;J VG Mz;Lfshf mk;gY}hpypUe;J (tpujk;<lb/> ,Ue;J) eilgazkhf jpUg;gjp nfhtpYf;F brd;W tUfpd;nwd;/ ,e;j<lb/> Mz;Lk; nfhtpYf;F brd;W 30/12/08 md;W ,ut[ Cu; te;J<lb/> nrUfpd;nwhk;/ mjdhy; 29/12/08 md;W miHg;ghidapd;go tu<lb/> ,ayhj fhuzj;jhy; jat[Tu;e;J miHg;ghizapd; kWnjjp tH&apos;;FkhW<lb/> kpft[k; gzpt[lDk; jhH;ika[lDk; nfl;Lf;bfhs;fpd;nwd;/<lb/></item>

			<item>rku;g;gpj;jy;<lb/> --ifbahg;gk;--<lb/>brayhsu;(bghWg;g[)<lb/></item>

			<p>C.1514 fphprKj;jpuk; bjh/nt/T/t&apos;;fp<lb/></p>

			<p>30. But in the next page, the Office of the 1 st respondent has<lb/> recorded that the 3 rd respondent has appeared on 29.12.2008 for himself<lb/> and on behalf of the petitioners, in respect of Arbitration Claim No.1844-<lb/>A/2007-08 Sa.Pa., and given statement, which is as follows:<lb/></p>

			<p>be/<lb/> 2008k; Mz;L ork;gu; khjk; 16k; njjp<lb/> jhth be/ 1844 A -2007?2008<lb/></p>

			<item>1983k; Mz;oy; jkpH;ehL Tl;Lwt[r; rl;lg;gphpt[ 90<lb/> kw;Wk; 1988k; Mz;oy; jkpH;ehL Tl;Lwt[r; r&apos;;f&apos;;fspd;<lb/> tpjpfspy; tpjp 107d; fPH; nf/uhn$e;jpud; Mfpa ehd;<lb/> fPH;fz;l thf;FKyj;jpid cWjpahf rj;jpakhf brhy;fpnwd;:<lb/></item>

			<item>bgau;<lb/> / / nf/uhn$e;jpud;<lb/> jfg;gdhu; bgau;<lb/> / / M.fpUc&amp;;zrhkp<lb/> taJ<lb/> / / 42<lb/> kjk;<lb/> / /<lb/> bjhHpy;<lb/> / / Kd;dhs; brayhsu;<lb/> ,Ug;gplk;<lb/> / / 3-184 tisahk;gl;L.<lb/> thzpak;gho<lb/></item>

			<item>thf;FK:yk;<lb/> ehd; brhy;tbjy;yhk; cz;ik/ cz;ikiaj;jtpu ntbwhd;Wkpy;iy/<lb/> ehd; ,e;jj; jhthtpy; Kjyhk; gpujpthjp. ,uz;lhk; gpujpthjp<lb/> vdJ kfs; Mu;/gphpjh. K:d;whk; gpujpthjp vdJ kidtp<lb/> Mu;/,e;jpuhzp vd; rhu;ghft[k;. ,uz;lhk; kw;Wk; K:d;whk;<lb/> gpujpthjpfs; rhu;ghft[k; ,d;W eilbgw;w tprhuizapy; ,d;W<lb/></item>

			<item>j&apos;;fs; Kd;g[ M$uhfp cs;nsd;/ ,uz;lhk; kw;Wk; K:d;whk;<lb/> gpujpthjpfs;<lb/> ,izj;Js;s<lb/> fojj;jpida[k;.<lb/></item>

			<item>,d;W<lb/> j&apos;;fsplk;<lb/> tprhuizapd;nghJ jhf;fy; bra;Js;nsd;/ 1844-07?08 vz;zpl;l<lb/> jhthtpy;<lb/> ghu;itaplntz;oa<lb/> Mtz&apos;;fns<lb/> ,e;jj;<lb/> jhthtpy;<lb/> bjhlu;g[ilajhf cs;sjhy;. mtw;iw 19-12-08 njjpf;Fs;<lb/> ghu;itapl;L<lb/> mLj;j<lb/> tprhuizapy;<lb/> vdJ<lb/> thf;FK:yj;ijg;<lb/> gjpt[bra;fpnwd;/<lb/></item>

			<item>goj;J ghu;j;njd;/ rhp/ --ifbahg;gk;--16/12/2008<lb/> thf;FK:yk; vd;dhy; gjpt[ bra;ag;gl;L thf;FK:yk; mspj;jtuhy;<lb/> goj;Jg;ghu;j;J rhp vd xg;gp vd; Kd;dpiyapy; ifbahg;gkplg;gl;lJ/<lb/> --ifbahg;gk;--16/12/2008<lb/> be/<lb/> 2008k; Mz;L<lb/> jhth be/ 1844 A -2007?2008<lb/> 1983k; Mz;oy; jkpH;ehL Tl;Lwt[r; rl;lg;gphpt[ 90<lb/> kw;Wk; 1988k; Mz;oy; jkpH;ehL Tl;Lwt[r; r&apos;;f&apos;;fspd;<lb/> tpjpfspy; tpjp 107d; fPH; nf/uhn$e;jpud; Mfpa ehd;<lb/> fPH;fz;l thf;FKyj;jpid cWjpahf rj;jpakhf brhy;fpnwd;:<lb/></item>

			<item>bgau;<lb/> / / nf/uhn$e;jpud;<lb/> jfg;gdhu; bgau;<lb/> / / M.fpUc&amp;;zrhkp<lb/> taJ<lb/> / / 42<lb/> kjk;<lb/> / /<lb/> bjhHpy;<lb/> / / Kd;dhs; brayhsu;<lb/> ,Ug;gplk;<lb/> / / 3-184 tisahk;gl;L.<lb/> thzpak;gho<lb/> thf;FK:yk;<lb/> ehd; brhy;tbjy;yhk; cz;ik/ cz;ikiaj;jtpu ntbwhd;Wkpy;iy/<lb/> 16/12/08 md;W eilbgw;w tprhuizapd;nghJ bjhptpf;fg;gl;lthW<lb/> ehd; fphprKj;jpuk; bjhlf;f ntshz;ikf; Tl;Lwt[ t&apos;;fpapd; mtz&apos;;fisg;<lb/> ghu;itapl;nld;/ ,d;W eilbgw;w tprhuizapd;nghJ vd;<lb/> rhu;ghft[k;. Vida gpujpthjpfs; rhu;ghft[k; j&apos;;fs; Kd;<lb/> M$uhndd;/ 1844-07?08 vz;zpl;l jhth tprhuid bjhlu;ghf<lb/> thf;FK:yk; totpapyhd tpsf;f&apos;;fis ,d;W mspj;Js;nsd;/<lb/> mjidna ,e;j jhth kD bjhlu;ghd thf;FK:ykhft[k;. Vida<lb/> gpujpthjpfs; rhu;ghd thf;FK:ykhft[k; vLj;Jf;bfhs;Sk;go<lb/> ntz;Lfpnwd;/ ,e;jj; jhth bjhlu;ghd midj;J Mtz&apos;;fis[ak;<lb/> vd;rhu;ghft[k;. Vida gpujpthjpfs; rhu;ghft[k; ghu;itapl<lb/> nghjpa<lb/> mtfhrk;<lb/> mspf;fg;gl;Ls;sJ<lb/> vdt[k;<lb/> bjhptpj;Jf;bfhs;fpnwd;/<lb/></item>

			<item>goj;J ghu;j;njd;/ rhp/ --ifbahg;gk;--29/12/2008<lb/> thf;FK:yk;<lb/> vd;dhy;<lb/> gjpag;gl;L<lb/> thf;FK:yk;<lb/> mspj;jtuhy;<lb/> goj;Jg;ghu;j;J rhp vd xg;gp vd; Kd;dpiyapy; ifbahg;gkplg;gl;lJ/<lb/> --ifbahg;gk;--29/12/2008<lb/> be/<lb/> 2008k; Mz;L<lb/> jhth be/ 1844A-2007?2008<lb/> 1983k; Mz;oy; jkpH;ehL Tl;Lwt[r; rl;lg;gphpt[ 90<lb/> kw;Wk; 1988k; Mz;oy; jkpH;ehL Tl;Lwt[r; r&apos;;f&apos;;fspd;<lb/> tpjpfspy; tpjp 107d; fPH; _/Mu;/knfe;jpud;; Mfpa ehd;<lb/> fPH;fz;l thf;FKyj;jpid cWjpahf rj;jpakhf brhy;fpnwd;:<lb/></item>

			<item>bgau;<lb/> / / _/Mu;/knfe;jpud;<lb/> jfg;gdhu; bgau;<lb/> / / _/uh$hke;jphp<lb/> taJ<lb/> / / 44<lb/> kjk;<lb/> / /<lb/> bjhHpy;<lb/> / / vGj;;ju; fphprKj;jpuk;<lb/> ,Ug;gplk;<lb/> / /<lb/> thf;FK:yk;<lb/> ehd; brhy;tbjy;yhk; cz;ik/ cz;ikiaj;jtpu ntbwhd;Wkpy;iy/<lb/> ehd; thjp t&apos;;fp rhu;ghf m&apos;;fPfhuf; fojk; bgw;W ,d;W eilbgw;w<lb/> tprhuizapy; j&apos;;fs; Kd; M$uhfpndd;/ gpujpthjpahdtu;. mtu;<lb/> rhu;ghft[k;. Vida gpujpthjpfs; rhu;ghft[k; thjp t&apos;;fpapd;<lb/> Mtz&apos;;fis<lb/> jpUg;gj;J}u;<lb/> ruff;<lb/> Tl;Lwt[r;<lb/> r&apos;;f&apos;;fspd;<lb/> Jizg;gjpthsu;<lb/> mYtyfj;jpy;<lb/> ghu;itapl;lhu;<lb/> vdj;<lb/> bjhptpj;Jf;bfhs;fpnwd;/<lb/></item>

			<item>goj;j ghu;j;njd;/ rhp/ --ifbahg;gk;--29/12/2008<lb/> thf;FK:yk;<lb/> vd;dhy;<lb/> gjpag;gl;L<lb/> thf;FK:yk;<lb/> mspj;jtuhy;<lb/> goj;Jg;ghu;j;J rhp vd xg;gp vd; Kd;dpiyapy; ifbahg;gkplg;gl;lJ/<lb/> --ifbahg;gk;--29/12/2008<lb/></item>

			<p>31. Nearly after four years, an award has been passed in<lb/> Arbitration Dispute No.1844-A/2007-08, dated 03.01.2013, by<lb/> Mr.T.K.Prabhakaran, Deputy Registrar of Co-op. Societies, Tirupattur<lb/> Circle, Vellore District, fixing liability on the petitioners. Files disclose<lb/> that when an attempt was made by Mr.S.Rajaguru, Office Assistant,<lb/> Office of the Deputy Registrar, to serve a copy of the abovesaid award,<lb/> the 3 rd respondent and the petitioners have refused to receive the award<lb/> and therefore, the said Office Assistant is stated to have pasted the<lb/> award in Door No.3/184, in the presence of witnesses.<lb/></p>

			<p>32. It is the case of the petitioners that though they have<lb/> received the summons in Arbitration Dispute No.1844/2007-08, they<lb/> remained ex parte. Perusal of the files shows that notices have been<lb/> issued for an enquiry, mentioning the claim as Arbitration Dispute<lb/> No.1844-A/2007-08, dated 21.11.2008. Though the learned counsel for<lb/> the petitioners submitted that they are not aware of any proceedings in<lb/> 1884-A/2007-08, this Court is not inclined to accept the said contention<lb/> for the reason that, earlier writ petitions have been filed, challenging<lb/> the proceedings in Arbitration Dispute No.1844-A/2007-08 and after<lb/> dismissal, review petitions have also been filed.<lb/></p>

			<p>33. Files disclose that two proceedings numbers have been<lb/> given, ie., 1844/2007-08 and 1844-A/2007-08. It is not known as to how,<lb/> two proceedings could be initiated against the same parties, viz., the<lb/> petitioners and 3 rd respondent, for the very same amounts, under the<lb/> same items of the alleged irregularities. However, the contention of the<lb/> learned counsel for the petitioners that the Deputy Registrar of Co-<lb/>operative Societies, Tirupattur Circle, has absolved the liability of the<lb/> petitioners in Arbitration Dispute No.1844/2007-08, on 05.07.2012,<lb/> holding that the 3 rd respondent alone was responsible for the alleged loss<lb/> caused to the society, cannot be disputed.<lb/></p>

			<p>34. When the petitioners were already absolved of their liability<lb/> to pay any alleged loss caused by the 3 rd respondent, in Arbitration<lb/> Dispute No.1844/2007-08 Sa.Pa., dated 05.07.2012, it is also not known,<lb/> as to how, the 1 st respondent could pass another award in Dispute<lb/> No.1844-A/2007-08, Sa.Pa., dated 03.01.2013, fixing responsibility and<lb/> liability on the petitioners also. It is the case of the petitioners that they<lb/> did not authorise the 3 rd respondent, to represent them, in the<lb/> Arbitration Dispute No.1844/2007-08 Sa.Pa. Though the 3 rd respondent is<lb/> stated to have appeared before the 1 st respondent, in Dispute No.1844-<lb/>A/2007-08, Sa.Pa., dated 03.01.2013, on behalf of the petitioners also,<lb/> files do not disclose any authorisation letter, given by the 1 st petitioner.<lb/> As the 2 nd petitioner was a minor, at the time of dispute, the 3 rd<lb/> respondent could have represented her. But the fact remains that the 1 st<lb/> petitioner has not appeared in the enquiry.<lb/></p>

			<p>35. In Arbitration Dispute No.1844/2007-08 Sa.Pa., dated<lb/> 05.07.2012, there is a total exoneration of the petitioners from their<lb/> liability and quite contrary to the same, in Dispute No.1844-A/2007-08,<lb/> Sa.Pa., dated 03.01.2013, Mr.T.K.Prabhakaran, Deputy Registrar of Co-<lb/>operative Societies, Tirupattur Circle, Vellore District, has fixed liability<lb/> on the petitioners also.<lb/></p>

			<p>36. As stated supra, when the petitioners have filed<lb/> W.P.Nos.27141, 27142, 27148, 29521 and 29663 of 2007, for the<lb/> abovesaid relief, vide order, dated 25.10.2007, this Court has dismissed<lb/> the writ petitions and subsequently, in the review petitions, this Court<lb/> has directed the petitioners to prefer an appeal under Section 152 of the<lb/> Tamil Nadu Co-operative Societies Act, before the Co-operative Tribunal,<lb/> presided over by a District Judge. When this Court had already passed<lb/> orders, directing the petitioners to challenge the award, a further review<lb/> of the orders made in the above batch of the writ petitions, would not be<lb/> appropriate.<lb/></p>

			<p>37. Therefore, in the light of the orders made in W.P.Nos.27141,<lb/> 27142, 27148, 29521 and 29663 of 2007, dated 25.10.2007 and Review<lb/> Application Nos.20 to 24 of 2008, dated 10.04.2008, the petitioners are<lb/> permitted to challenge the award, stated to have been passed in, vide<lb/> Thava No.1844-A/2007-08, dated 03.01.2013, under Section 152 of the<lb/> Tamil Nadu Co-operative Societies Act, before the Co-operative Tribunal,<lb/> presided over by a District Judge, within a period of 15 days from the<lb/> date of receipt of a copy of this order. It is made clear that the<lb/> observations made by this Court, after a cursory look of the files, does<lb/> not foreclose the right of the respondents to defend the Award in<lb/> Arbitration Dispute No.1844-A/2007-08, dated 03.01.2013, on its merits,<lb/> nor it should be construed as a finding, in favour of the petitioners, in<lb/> the challenge to the award.<lb/></p>

			<p>38<lb/> In the result, the Writ Petitions are dismissed. No costs.<lb/></p>

			<p>04.11.2013<lb/> skm<lb/> S. MANIKUMAR, J.<lb/> On 04.11.2013, this Court dismissed the writ petitions, granting<lb/> liberty to the writ petitioners, to prefer an appeal, under Section 152 of<lb/> the Tamil Nadu Co-operative Societies Act.<lb/> On this day,<lb/> Mr.S.Venkataraman, learned counsel for the petitioners submitted that<lb/> when the petitioners have been permitted to prefer an appeal, as stated<lb/> supra, without waiting for the same, steps have been taken to bring the<lb/> property for public auction. Hence, Registry has been directed to list the<lb/> matters, at 2.15 P.M.<lb/></p>

			<p>2.<lb/> On the basis of the instructions from the Deputy Registrar of<lb/> Co-operative Societies, Tirupattur Circle, Tripattur, learned Special<lb/> Government Pleader (Co-operative Societies), submitted that no steps<lb/> have been taken, to bring the subject property for public auction, which<lb/> the learned counsel for the petitioner disputes.<lb/></p>

			<p>3.<lb/> Since this Court had already granted liberty to the<lb/> petitioners to prefer an appeal, to the Competent Authority, under<lb/> Section 152 of the Tamil Nadu Co-operative Societies Act, 1983, it is<lb/> appropriate that the respondents should wait atleast, till the expiry of<lb/> the time granted by this Court to the petitioners, to file necessary<lb/> appeal, before the Co-operative Tribunal. Hence, the respondents are<lb/> directed not to enforce the award in Thava No.1844-A/2007-08, dated<lb/> 03.01.2013, for a period of 15 days from the date of receipt of a copy of<lb/> this order. It is also open to the petitioner to file an application, for<lb/> staying the execution of the decree, along with the appeal petition and if<lb/> any such application is filed, the Tribunal is directed to consider the<lb/> same and pass orders, on merits.<lb/></p>

			<p>08.11.2013<lb/> skm<lb/> To<lb/> 1. The Deputy Registrar of Co-op. Societies,<lb/> Tirupattur Circle, Vellore District.<lb/></p>

			<p>2. The Special Officer,<lb/> Girisamudhram Primary Agricultural<lb/> Co-operative Bank,<lb/> Girisamudhram Post, Vaniyambadi Taluk,<lb/> Vellore District.<lb/></p>

			<p>S. MANIKUMAR, J.<lb/> Skm<lb/> Writ Petition Nos.25059 and 25772 of 2012<lb/> 04.11.2013</p>


	</text>
</tei>
