<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			Sureshwar Thakur, Judge.
		</p>
		<p>
			Since all the writ petitions involve common questions
			<lb />
			of law, hence all become amenable, for, a common verdict
			<lb />
			becoming rendered thereon. However, only Annexures borne in
			<lb />
			CWP No. 2363 of 2020 are being alluded in this verdict, as, on the
			<lb />
			file of other writ petitions, common thereto though specially
			<lb />
			assigned Annexure numbers exist.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			Application(s) being CMP No. 7704 of 2020 in CWP
			<lb />
			No. 2644 of 2020 and CMP No. 7703 of 2020 in CWP No. 2363 of
			<lb />
			2020, are, allowed and the applicant(s) therein, are, ordered to be
			<lb />
			impleaded as intervener(s)/respondent(s).
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			The writ petitioners, belong to the BPL category (non-
			<lb />
			SC/ST/OBC). The State of Himachal Pradesh, through, an
			<lb />
			advertisement embodied in Annexure P-7, advertised, for, the
			<lb />
			relevant purpose, the enumerated therein posts, of, TGT (Arts),
			<lb />
			TGT (Non-Medical), and, TGT (Medical). In all the afore
			<lb />
			advertised posts, vis-a-vis, the category appertaining, to,
			<lb />
			Economically Weaker Section (for short &quot;EWS&quot;), 39 posts became
			<lb />
			reserved, against advertised post(s) qua TGT (Arts), 18 posts
			<lb />
			became reserved against the advertised post(s) qua TGT (Non-
			<lb />
			Medical), and, 13 post(s) became reserved against, the, advertised
			<lb />
			post(s) qua TGT (Medical). However, in the note written, in the
			<lb />
			afore Annexure, an echoing is borne, vis-a-vis, those candidates,
			<lb />
			
			belonging to unreserved BPL category, being not required to submit
			<lb />
			any Income, and, Asset certificate, rather theirs becoming eligible
			<lb />
			for being considered, for, selection, in, the afore category
			<lb />
			appertaining, to, the afore unreserved posts, vis-a-vis, EWS
			<lb />
			category (non-SC/ST/OBC), merely, on production, of, a BPL
			<lb />
			Certificate duly countersigned, by the Block Development Officer,
			<lb />
			besides upon a non-SC/ST/OBC certificate, becoming issued by the
			<lb />
			competent authority concerned.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			The learned counsel, appearing for the petitioners, has
			<lb />
			expressed his resistance, to, the afore merger of BPL
			<lb />
			(non-SC/ST/OBC category), into, the larger nowat contemplated
			<lb />
			category, of, EWS, and, has strived, to, restore the hitherto
			<lb />
			reservation, as, exclusively made qua BPL category, hence,
			<lb />
			belonging to non-SC/ST/OBC category, as, the earlier hereto
			<lb />
			reservation, as, was in operation, prior to the issuance of afore
			<lb />
			Annexure P-7, hence, validly made BPL family(ies) aspirant(s)
			<lb />
			rather, to, exclusively fall within the domain, of, EWS.
			<lb />
			
			The afore reservation, as, is meted to the
			<lb />
			non-SC/ST/OBC category, of, EWS hence in Annexure P-7, is, in
			<lb />
			pursuance to Annexure P-5 (notification of 11.6.2019).
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			The afore resistance, as is, with utmost vehemence
			<lb />
			expressed before this Court, by the learned counsel, for the
			<lb />
			petitioners, is, anvilled upon the trite ground (i) qua the
			<lb />
			enlargement of EWS category(ies) rather by the State of Himachal
			<lb />
			Pradesh, through its making Annexures P-5, and, P-7, for, theirs
			<lb />
			becoming entitled, to, the benefits of reserved posts qua them, (ii)
			<lb />
			moreso, on fixing, of, a higher per annum income borne in a sum of
			<lb />
			Rs. 4.00 lacs, than, the one previously in prevalence, in as much, as,
			<lb />
			the hitherto per annum qualifying income, of, the apposite BPL
			<lb />
			family (EWS category) being pegged, at, Rs.35000/-, (iii) perse
			<lb />
			whereupon(s), earlier, upon, evident per annum income, of,
			<lb />
			Rs.35,000/-becoming sourced, from, all resources, hence entitled
			<lb />
			any aspirant, to, fall within, the, EWS category, and, also his/her
			<lb />
			became entitled, to, exclusivity of benefits, of reservation made qua
			<lb />
			therewith, (iv) whereas, with the afore ceiling appertaining, to, per
			<lb />
			annum income upon, becoming nowat increased, to, a per annum
			<lb />
			
			sum up to Rs. 4 lacs, as, is embodied in Annexure P-5, hence
			<lb />
			makes, visible bespeakings, vis-a-vis, the apposite escalation(s) in
			<lb />
			income criteria, happening in a shift short manner (v) and the afore
			<lb />
			escalation, in, the apposite income criteria, being both arbitrary and
			<lb />
			discriminatory, in as much, as, the special category, of, BPL
			<lb />
			families, alone merited inclusion, within the ambit, of, the
			<lb />
			constitutionally valid category of EWS, (vi) besides the extant
			<lb />
			subsuming therewithin(s) of persons, with, a higher income, with
			<lb />
			aspirants&apos; hence earlier holding the afore pegged income, rather
			<lb />
			there-through creating or constituting a constitutionally invalid
			<lb />
			class, within, the insegregable class of EWS, nor the earlier made
			<lb />
			rather exclusive reservation qua BPL families, not meriting
			<lb />
			assignments, of, constitutional merit, as, the, afore holds no nexus,
			<lb />
			with, the constitutional objective, of valid reservation(s), in public
			<lb />
			employment, being meted to, no family, other than a BPL family
			<lb />
			category aspirant.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			The writ petitioners, on, anvil of rules, existing prior to
			<lb />
			the issuance, of, Annexure P-5, in as much, as, thereat non-SC/ST/
			<lb />
			OBC and BPL certificate holders, alone became entitled to the
			<lb />
			
			prescribed per-centum, of, reservation, in public employment, make
			<lb />
			espousal(s), vis-a-vis, the constitutionally sacrosanct hitherto rule,
			<lb />
			not warranting any dilution, as has occurred, through issuance of
			<lb />
			Annexure P-5. In nutshell the learned counsel for the petitioners,
			<lb />
			espouses for setting aside, of, Annexures P-5, and, of P-7, rather,
			<lb />
			conspicuously on the ground, of, their legitimate expectation(s) in
			<lb />
			public employment, on, anvil, of, Annexure P-5 becoming
			<lb />
			jeopardized.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			The State of Himachal Pradesh, filed a detailed reply, to
			<lb />
			the writ petition, and, has there-through strived to validate the
			<lb />
			issuance of Annexure P-5, and, also the tandem therewith, issued
			<lb />
			advertised notice, as, becomes embodied in Annexure P-7. The
			<lb />
			essence of the reply meted to the writ petition is encapsulated, in,
			<lb />
			the afore Annexure(s) being constitutionally valid, and, theirs
			<lb />
			becoming rested, upon, valid exercising(s), of, constitutional
			<lb />
			discretion by the State of Himachal Pradesh. A specific contention,
			<lb />
			is, also embodied therein qua the broadening, of, the category, of,
			<lb />
			BPL certificate holder(s), into, a large category, of, EWS
			<lb />
			(non-SC/ST/OBC), through, the apposite income criteria being
			<lb />
			enhanced, up to Rs.4 lacs per annum, not undoing, the benefit, of,
			<lb />
			reservation earlier meted even to BPL certificate holders, rather, a,
			<lb />
			mere expansive swathe of population, also, hence with minimal
			<lb />
			incomes&apos;, being validly created, for, hence the benefits of
			<lb />
			reservation(s), on, the constitutionally sacrosanct pedestal, of, sub
			<lb />
			Article 6, of, Article 16, of, the Constitution of India, becoming
			<lb />
			meted, to all, hence, falling, in, the apposite category, of, EWS.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			Moreover, it is also contended that since, from the
			<lb />
			hitherto 8% reservation, as, contemplated, for, BPL certificate
			<lb />
			holder(s), rather extantly, a, 10% reservation, to, EWS becomes
			<lb />
			contemplated through Annexure P-5, hence, for direct recruitment
			<lb />
			to class I, II, III and IV posts, necessarily hence in obvious
			<lb />
			expansion, of, category(ies) of posts, where-against reservation(s)
			<lb />
			became earlier contemplated, exclusively for BPL certificate
			<lb />
			holders (non-SC/ST/OBC), in as much, as, only qua class IV posts,
			<lb />
			reiteratedly there-through, the, apposite beneficial category
			<lb />
			becoming enlarged, in, both expanse and size (i) thereupon, the
			<lb />
			extant increase(s) in the per centum of reservation(s), and, also
			<lb />
			increases in number of reserved posts, hence would ensure accruing
			<lb />
			of proportionally increased size(s), of, the constitutionally
			<lb />
			sacrosanct reservation(s) hence becoming meted to EWS, than,
			<lb />
			occurring earlier, (ii) whereupon, also the proportional increase(s)
			<lb />
			or inclusion(s) of, other persons, than, BPL aspirants, merit
			<lb />
			condonation. Significantly, hence it has become pointedly averred,
			<lb />
			in, the reply, that, the afore merger or inclusion, is, constitutionally
			<lb />
			valid, and, also has a keen and deep nexus, with the constitutional
			<lb />
			objective, in as much, as, there-through(s) the benefit(s) of
			<lb />
			reservation percolating into the largest swathe of population, hence,
			<lb />
			aspiring to become recipient(s) thereof, on, anvil of minimum or
			<lb />
			minimal income, (i) thereupon, the added category, of, persons
			<lb />
			hence befittingly becoming qualified, as, EWS, to, hence compete
			<lb />
			alongwith BPL certificate holders, for, all being considered for
			<lb />
			selection and appointment, vis-a-vis, the advertised posts.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			10.
			<lb />
			Before proceeding to analyze the vigor, of, the afore
			<lb />
			strived contention, addressed before this Court, by the learned
			<lb />
			counsel for the petitioners, and, by the learned Advocate General, it
			<lb />
			is deemed imperative, to, go through, the relevant parameters, as
			<lb />
			become contemplated, in clause 3, of, Annexure P-5, (i) a reading
			<lb />
			whereof unearths or unveils, vis-a-vis, an echoing being loudly
			<lb />
			voiced therein, vis-a-vis, a person holding, an annual income upto
			<lb />
			Rs. 4.00 lacs, hence becoming eligible for being entitled, to, avail,
			<lb />
			the, benefit, of, reservation made, vis-a-vis, EWS category, and
			<lb />
			afore income being construable alongwith all income(s) sourced
			<lb />
			from salary, agriculture, business, profession etc. Further more,
			<lb />
			dehors, the afore nowat contemplated, apposite EWS qualifying
			<lb />
			criteria, vis-a-vis, the afore per annum income, up to Rs.4.00 lacs,
			<lb />
			rather upon the aspirant concerned, holding more than one hectare,
			<lb />
			of, agricultural land in rural areas, and, 500 M 2 land in urban areas;
			<lb />
			or residential flat/house of more than 2500 square feet in
			<lb />
			rural/urban areas, rather rendering him self ineligible, besides upon
			<lb />
			his belonging, to, a family of income tax payee(s), or, upon, any, of,
			<lb />
			his family member(s) being, in, regular/contractual employment, of,
			<lb />
			the Central Government, State Government, Board, Corporations
			<lb />
			and autonomous bodies and public Sector undertakings etc, (i)
			<lb />
			thereupon, also his/her acquiring ineligibility, for, being construable
			<lb />
			to be fall, in, the EWS category. Moreover it has also become
			<lb />
			qualified, that, the property held by the family of the aspirant in
			<lb />
			…33…
			<lb />
			being clubbed, for, determining EWS category, besides, the aspirant
			<lb />
			concerned, his/her parents, and, siblings below the age of 18 years,
			<lb />
			as also his/her spouse and children, below the age of 18 years
			<lb />
			becoming declared to be the family, of, the aspirant.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			11.
			<lb />
			Further more, along therewith, a, comparative study, of,
			<lb />
			the parameters/indicators, appertaining to entitlements qua BPL
			<lb />
			certificate(s) holders (non-SC/ST/OBC), is, also imperative, and,
			<lb />
			the requisite averments become embodied, in, a notification issued
			<lb />
			in July, 2018, and, notification whereof, has come to be placed on
			<lb />
			record, by the learned Advocate General, relevant paragraph
			<lb />
			whereof, is, extracted hereinafter.
			<lb />
		</p>


		<p>
			12.
			<lb />
			A perusal thereof, discloses qua though there occurs
			<lb />
			therein a prescription, vis-a-vis, necessity of any BPL aspirant
			<lb />
			concerned (a) holding an income, upto, Rs.2500/-per month (b) the
			<lb />
			land holding of his or her family, vis-a-vis, un-irrigated land being
			<lb />
			up to 2 hectares, and, irrigated land up to 1 hectares (c) his or her
			<lb />
			family not residing in urban area like pakka house, (d) any member
			<lb />
			of his or her family being not an income tax payee (e) any member
			<lb />
			of his or her family not holding public employment either in
			<lb />
			permanent or in a contractual capacity. A further reading thereof
			<lb />
			unveils, vis-a-vis, alike the apposite income criteria contemplated in
			<lb />
			Clause 3, of Annexure 5, an apposite income criteria, becoming also
			<lb />
			contemplated, in, the notification, of, July, 2018, excepting limits
			<lb />
			thereof, and, in both, the apposite income criteria, becoming
			<lb />
			prescribed, to, assume no relevance, upon, the aspirant&apos;s family
			<lb />
			holding, prohibited sizes of landed or immovable assets, as, become
			<lb />
			respectively embodied in Annexure A-5, and, in the notification, of,
			<lb />
			July, 2018.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			13.
			<lb />
			Moreover, another similarity which occurs, inter-se,
			<lb />
			both the notification of July, 2018, and, clause 3 of Annexure P-5,
			<lb />
			is, vis-a-vis, an aspirant concerned, or, the family of the aspirant
			<lb />
			concerned, not, being an income tax payee.
			<lb />
			The afore
			<lb />
			similarity(ies) inter-se the notification of July 2018, wherethrough,
			<lb />
			the category of BPL became created, and, clause 3 of Annexure P-5,
			<lb />
			does prima-facie, ensure, vis-a-vis, the happening(s), of,
			<lb />
			enlargement(s), or, broadening(s), of, EWS category, hence
			<lb />
			enshrined, in, Sub Article 6 of Article 16, of, the Constitution of
			<lb />
			India, as, a constitutionally valid category, acquiring constitutional
			<lb />
			
			executive discretion becomes not amenable to judicial review, (i)
			<lb />
			significantly, and, amplifyingly, the, exercising of valid executive
			<lb />
			discretion, appears to ensue, from its meteing deference, vis-a-vis,
			<lb />
			the monetisable value(s), of, the immovable assets/land holdings, of
			<lb />
			an aspirant concerned, than any stricto sensu pegging(s), of, income
			<lb />
			upto Rs. 2500/-per month, (ii) perse whereupon(s) earlier an
			<lb />
			aspirant staked claim, for, his being both a befitting BPL family
			<lb />
			member, and, also claimed exclusivity, of, her/his hence falling
			<lb />
			within the category of EWS, (iii) as, thereupon(s), prima-facie the
			<lb />
			mandate of sub Article 6 of Article 16 of the Constitution of India,
			<lb />
			becomes meted valid deference, rather than suffer inapt
			<lb />
			nullification (iv) emphasisingly, the, leading valid factor in the
			<lb />
			making of the impugned notification, is grooved, in the consequent
			<lb />
			therewith economic necessity(ies), arising from passage, of, time
			<lb />
			since then upto now, hence bringing inflationary pressure upon an
			<lb />
			income higher than Rs.35,000/-per annum, with the apt corollary,
			<lb />
			vis-a-vis, the earlier economically empowered section(s) of society,
			<lb />
			becoming alike BPL certificate holders, rather marginalized, in,
			<lb />
			terms of monetisable resources, thereupon theirs also becoming
			<lb />
			eligible through economic necessity, for staking claim, for,
			<lb />
			reservation, as, nowat made qua EWS category.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			14.
			<lb />
			Even otherwise, the apposite constitutional mechanism,
			<lb />
			is enjoined to assume or enjoin the virtue, of, dynamism becoming
			<lb />
			imparted thereto, than any unwanted staticity, hence, upon,
			<lb />
			imparting(s), of, constitutional dynamism, to, the apposite norms,
			<lb />
			does validate, the inclusion of all afore nowat included persons,
			<lb />
			within the category of EWS, (i) as all fall within, the,
			<lb />
			constitutionally valid area/zone thereof, (ii) given there-through(s)
			<lb />
			not only economic necessity, arising from efflux of time, since the
			<lb />
			making, of, the earlier notification, vis-a-vis, the issuance, of, nowat
			<lb />
			notification, has become meted deference, (iii) but also the
			<lb />
			Executive has struck the apposite balance inter-se all competing
			<lb />
			interest(s) appertaining, to, constitutional norms/considerations, vis-
			<lb />
			a-vis, all marginalized or economically weaker sections of the
			<lb />
			society, deserving inclusions within the constitutional ambit of
			<lb />
			EWS.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			15.
			<lb />
			Further thereonwards, there are, stringent prohibitive
			<lb />
			restrictions, cast in Annexure P-5, upon, an aspirant, whose family
			<lb />
			income though from all sources, is, Rs. 4.00 lacs per annum, for,
			<lb />
			hence, his though perse there-through deserving inclusion, in, EWS
			<lb />
			category, (i) in as much, as, upon the family of the aspirant, upon,
			<lb />
			evidently owning or possessing, more, than 1 hectare of agricultural
			<lb />
			land, in rural areas, and, 500 M 2 land in urban area, or, residential
			<lb />
			flat/house of more than 2500 square feet in rural/urban areas, (ii)
			<lb />
			whereupon, upon the afore exclusionary prohibitive clause(s)
			<lb />
			becoming proven, thereupon, the, aspirant becoming estopped to,
			<lb />
			anchor, his, claim, for, inclusion, within, EWS category, (iii) despite
			<lb />
			the apposite per annum income, being in consonance with, the,
			<lb />
			prior thereto opening(s) of clause 3. The afore prohibited sizes, of,
			<lb />
			landed assets, or, of, immovable assets, if held, by any aspirant,
			<lb />
			hence renders the relevant income criteria, to, become irrelevant. In
			<lb />
			aftermath, in the valid exercising(s) of discretion, by, the State of
			<lb />
			Himachal Pradesh, it appears it becoming well guided, by, the
			<lb />
			monetisable quantum, of, the afore holdings in as much, as, upon
			<lb />
			the monetisable landed assets or immovable assets, of the aspirant
			<lb />
			being beyond Rs. 4.00 lacs, hence his becoming constitutionally
			<lb />
			disqualified, for, becoming reckoned, as, an EWS aspirant.
			<lb />
			Necessarily hence the afore necessity, of, size, of, per annum
			<lb />
			income, is, a well calibrated mechanism, for, making an apt
			<lb />
			determination, of, economic weakness or economic dis-
			<lb />
			empowerment, of, any aspirant, thereupon, the exercise, of,
			<lb />
			executive discretion becomes bereft, of, any vires, of, malafides or
			<lb />
			impropriety, and, even of constitutional illegality.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			16.
			<lb />
			Be that as it may, even qua BPL certificate holders
			<lb />
			(non-SC/ST/OBC), upon, the size of the land holdings, in, as much,
			<lb />
			as, the size of the irrigable land, being beyond 1 hectare, and, vis-a-
			<lb />
			vis non-irrigable land being beyond 2 hectare, are cast, as fetter(s),
			<lb />
			against, an aspirant seeking BPL status, (i) dehors, the income
			<lb />
			criteria with the apposite ceiling limit becoming accomplished. In
			<lb />
			the face, of, the afore evidently proven exclusion(s), hence
			<lb />
			emanating from the afore respective prohibited size(s), of, land
			<lb />
			holdings, as, held by any BPL aspirant, though, would render the
			<lb />
			latter to be not a member, of, a BPL family, (ii) however, thereafter,
			<lb />
			upon, monetisable values, of, his apposite prohibited size(s), of,
			<lb />
			income prescribed, vis-a-vis, the nowat created EWS category,
			<lb />
			would rather eligiblise the apposite BPL family aspirant, to, avail
			<lb />
			the benefit of reservation meted, in, the impugned notification, qua,
			<lb />
			EWS category, (iii) wherefrom, obviously, there is neither any
			<lb />
			absolute exclusion, of, any BPL family member nor
			<lb />
			any inference, of any invalid discretion, being exercised is
			<lb />
			drawable, nor any exclusivity of reservation accruing, upon, an
			<lb />
			aspirant holding per mensem income, of, Rs. 2500/-, can beget
			<lb />
			constitutional condonation, nor, can become the valid touchstone,
			<lb />
			for, invalidating the impugned notification, (iii) preponderantly,
			<lb />
			also when through(s) the size, of, reservation, as, also the
			<lb />
			categories, of, posts, where-to-which, it becomes applicable, does
			<lb />
			give leverage, even, to, a BPL family aspirant rather holding an
			<lb />
			income, of, only upto Rs.35,000/-per annum, to, compete
			<lb />
			alongwith other categories nowat included within, the, EWS
			<lb />
			category.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			17.
			<lb />
			In other words, the, prohibited monetisable value, of,
			<lb />
			land holdings, of any BPL aspirant, though when may exclude any
			<lb />
			reservation, (i) whereas, upon the apposite monetisable value
			<lb />
			thereof, arriving upto Rs.4.00 lacs, as, is the per annum, limit of
			<lb />
			income hence enhanced, from, the hitherto per annum limit of
			<lb />
			income, of, Rs. 35000/-rather would qualify the apposite excluded
			<lb />
			BPL family aspirant, to, avail the benefits, of, reservation, vis-a-vis,
			<lb />
			EWS category, (i) and, when the afore per annum income, is, the
			<lb />
			main criteria, vis-a-vis, the financial year prior to the year of
			<lb />
			application, (ii) thereupon, on the afore parameter(s), a palpable
			<lb />
			uniformity, and, equalization occurs, inter-se persons falling within,
			<lb />
			the, domain of clause 3 of Annexure P-5, with those aspirants who
			<lb />
			stand excluded from the category, of, BPL, and, who become nowat
			<lb />
			included within EWS category (iii) whereupon, obviously the afore
			<lb />
			brought equalizations, hence, bolsters an inference qua it becoming
			<lb />
			founded, upon, valid exercising(s) of discretion, by the executive.
			<lb />
			Moreover, therethrough hence the largest swathe of economically
			<lb />
			marginalized befitting population, also deserving, to, fall within the
			<lb />
			constitutional category, of, EWS, becoming validly benefited, (i)
			<lb />
			besides there-through an assimilation(s) therewithins, of, the afore
			<lb />
			also happening (ii) besides, the afore assimilation, does not, render
			<lb />
			the broadened category of EWS, to become invalidly segregated,
			<lb />
			from, the hitherto BPL category, merely, on, income criteria.
			<lb />
			Moreover, the afore merger through the afore mode, of, BPL family
			<lb />
			aspirant hence also nowat concomitantly ensures subsumings
			<lb />
			therewith, hence, conspicuously within the larger category, of,
			<lb />
			economically marginalized families contemplated in clause 3 of
			<lb />
			Annexure P-5, thereupon, the afore merger hence becomes
			<lb />
			constitutionally meritworthy, (a) as, any BPL aspirant also becomes
			<lb />
			facilitated, to, avail the benefits, of, the extant reservation.
			<lb />
			Significantly with the mode of merger/inclusion of BPL family
			<lb />
			aspirant, into the larger category, of, economically marginalized
			<lb />
			families, becoming well founded, upon, the legitimate mode,
			<lb />
			contemplated in clause 3 of Annexure P-5, (a) in as much, as, both
			<lb />
			on the parameter(s) of size, of, income and also, on, the
			<lb />
			parameter(s) of monetisable values, of, immovable assets, (b)
			<lb />
			whereupon, the afore adopted mode, of, apposite merger, becomes a
			<lb />
			merger, as, the case may be.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			18.
			<lb />
			Be that as it may, for the afore inference or conclusion,
			<lb />
			being firmly rested, on valid constitutional touchstone(s) hence
			<lb />
			permitting judicial review, of, Annexures P-5, and, of P-7, it
			<lb />
			becomes, incumbent, for this Court, to extract the relevant and
			<lb />
			permissible domains within ambits&apos; whereof, the exercise of
			<lb />
			judicial review, of, executive action, becomes impermissible or
			<lb />
			permissible, as the case may be, (i) and, domains whereof became
			<lb />
			expressed in a judgment rendered, by the Hon&apos;ble Apex Court in
			<lb />
			case titled as Chairman All India Railway Recruitment Board
			<lb />
			and another versus K Shyam Kumar and others (2010) 6 SCC
			<lb />
			614, relevant paragraphs whereof, stand extracted hereinafter (ii)
			<lb />
			wherein trite underlining(s) are echoed, vis-a-vis, the apposite
			<lb />
			constitutional fetters, operating hence against or carrying leanings,
			<lb />
			vis-a-vis, affirmative exercise of judicial review, in as much, as,
			<lb />
			the exercising, of, apposite judicial review, upon, the decision
			<lb />
			making process or the making of executive discretion or the
			<lb />
			exercise of discretion, being illegal, (iii) and, the foundation of
			<lb />
			
			illegality, as, a source, of, striking down executive action, is, ultra
			<lb />
			vires, errors of law and, onerous conditions, improper purpose,
			<lb />
			relevant and irrelevant factors, acting in bad faith, unauthorized
			<lb />
			delegation, failure to act etc. (iii) procedural impropriety, breach of
			<lb />
			natural justice, and, vice of caprice, malafides, ingraining the
			<lb />
			exercise, of,
			<lb />
			executive action, and, also upon, legitimate
			<lb />
			expectation(s) becoming eroded. Further thereonwards. it also
			<lb />
			becomes encapsulated therein, vis-a-vis, the afore &quot;wednesbury&quot;
			<lb />
			test, hence empowering the making, of, judicial review, of,
			<lb />
			executive decision(s), rather nowat also inching towards, the more
			<lb />
			omnibus doctrine of necessity, and, proportionality, (i) and, the
			<lb />
			imperative bench marks thereof being encapsulated in paragraphs
			<lb />
			22 to 28 thereof, (ii) and, obviously a reading of the hereinafter
			<lb />
			extracted paragraphs, makes vivid echoings, vis-a-vis, both the
			<lb />
			proportionality test, as well, as, the &quot;wednesbury&quot; principle,
			<lb />
			continuing to co-exist, and, finest difference, inter-se both being
			<lb />
			comprised, in, proportionality test, becoming applicable, upon,
			<lb />
			violation of human right, (iii) and, or upon breach, of, fundamental
			<lb />
			rights rather evidently surfacing, (iv) whereas, &quot;wednesbury&quot;
			<lb />
			principle, becoming attracted more on domestic law, and,
			<lb />
			obviously, when there is violation of citizens ordinary rights.
			<lb />
			Consequently, hence, the proportionality principle has not yet
			<lb />
			replaced wednesbury principle, rather both the afore principles
			<lb />
			coexist, hence in the afore factual touchstone(s). Thereupon, upon
			<lb />
			applying the afore tests hereat, the executive, has reasonably
			<lb />
			balanced the economic necessity, of, inclusion of a larger swathe,
			<lb />
			of, economically marginalized section of population, in, the EWS
			<lb />
			category (non-SC/ST/OBC category) than existing earlier (i) and,
			<lb />
			thereupon, the afore striking of balance, inter-se, the respective
			<lb />
			competing claims, vis-a-vis reservation within EWS category, of,
			<lb />
			persons, hence, in, both the notification of July, 2018, where-
			<lb />
			through the category of BPL families became created, and, of,
			<lb />
			persons, borne in the extant notification, who validly benefit,
			<lb />
			from, the hitherto upper limit of income criteria hence becoming
			<lb />
			enhanced, does find, its befitting constitutional bedrock.
			<lb />
			Necessarily also hence, thereupon, the necessity of inclusion(s)
			<lb />
			thereof(s), within EWS category, becomes well conceived, hence
			<lb />
			for the requisite purpose. Since the holistic constitutional virtue
			<lb />
			behind sub Article 6, of, Article 16 of the Constitution of India, is
			<lb />
			fully achieved, thereupon, hence the impugned notification, cannot
			<lb />
			be deprecated. Moreover reiteratedly also when through the afore
			<lb />
			notification, the executive has meted deference, vis-a-vis, the
			<lb />
			doctrine of necessity, in as much, as, through the afore escalation
			<lb />
			of per annum income, from, the hitherto per annum income of Rs.
			<lb />
			35000/-, it has definitely, validly merged therewithin, a large, and,
			<lb />
			expansive swathe, of, population, within, the EWS category (Non-
			<lb />
			SC/ST/OBC), (i) and, thereupon reiteratedly, also the apposite
			<lb />
			striking, of, balance has become meted the most befitting
			<lb />
			deference, (ii) whereupon both the afore apposite tests become
			<lb />
			satiated, conspicuously, when no material, vis-a-vis, vices, of,
			<lb />
			malafides or illegalities, rather seeking into the decision making
			<lb />
			processes, hence has made any appearance. Consequently, this
			<lb />
			Court refrains to exercise its power of judicial review, for, setting
			<lb />
			aside the impugned Annexures.
			<lb />
			&quot;
		</p>

		<item>
			22.
			<lb />
			Judicial review conventionally is concerned with the question
			<lb />
			of jurisdiction and natural justice and the Court is not much concerned
			<lb />
			with the merits of the decision but how the decision was reached. In
			<lb />
			Council of Civil Service Unions Vs. Minister of State for Civil Service
			<lb />
			(1984) 3 All ER 935 the (GCHQ Case) the House of Lords rationalized
			<lb />
			the grounds of judicial review and ruled that the basis of judicial review
			<lb />
			…33…
			<lb />
			procedural impropriety and irrationality. Illegality as a ground of judicial
			<lb />
			review means that the decision maker must understand correctly the law
			<lb />
			that regulates his decision making powers and must give effect to it.
			<lb />
			Grounds such as acting ultra vires, errors of law and/or fact, onerous
			<lb />
			conditions, improper purpose, relevant and irrelevant factors, acting in
			<lb />
			bad faith, fettering discretion, unauthorized delegation, failure to act
			<lb />
			etc., fall under the heading &quot;illegality&quot;. Procedural impropriety may be
			<lb />
			due to the failure to comply with the mandatory procedures such as
			<lb />
			breach of natural justice, such as audi alteram partem, absence of bias,
			<lb />
			the duty to act fairly, legitimate expectations, failure to give reasons etc.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			23.
			<lb />
			The ground of irrationality takes in Wednesbury
			<lb />
			unreasonableness propounded in Associated Provincial Picture Houses
			<lb />
			Limited v. Wednesbury Corporation (1947)2 All ER 680, Lord Greene
			<lb />
			MR alluded to the grounds of attack which could be made against the
			<lb />
			decision, citing unreasonableness as an `umbrella concept&apos; which covers
			<lb />
			the major heads of review and pointed out that the court can interfere
			<lb />
			with a decision if it is so absurd that no reasonable decision maker
			<lb />
			would in law come to it. In GCHQ Case (supra) Lord Diplock fashioned
			<lb />
			the principle of unreasonableness and preferred to use the term
			<lb />
			irrationality as follows:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;By `irrationality&apos; I mean what can now be succinctly referred to as
			<lb />
			&quot;Wednesbury&apos;s unreasonableness&quot;, ....... It applies to a decision which is
			<lb />
			so outrageous in its defiance of logic or of accepted moral standards that
			<lb />
			no sensible person who had applied his mind to the question to be
			<lb />
			decided could have arrived at it.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			24.
			<lb />
			In R. v. Secretary of State for the Home Department ex parte
			<lb />
			Brind (1991) 1 All ER 720, the House of Lords re-examined the
			<lb />
			reasonableness of the exercise of the Home Secretary&apos;s discretion to issue
			<lb />
			a notice banning the transmission of speech by representatives of the Irish
			<lb />
			Republican Army and its political party, Sinn Fein. Court ruled that the
			<lb />
			exercise of the Home Secretary&apos;s power did not amount to an
			<lb />
			unreasonable exercise of discretion despite the issue involving a denial of
			<lb />
			freedom of expression. House of Lords however, stressed that in all cases
			<lb />
			raising a human rights issue proportionality is the appropriate standard of
			<lb />
			review.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			25.
			<lb />
			The House of Lords in R (Daly) v. Secretary of State for the
			<lb />
			Home Department (2001) 2 AC 532 demonstrated how the traditional test
			<lb />
			of Wednesbury unreasonableness has moved towards the doctrine of
			<lb />
			necessity and proportionality. Lord Steyn noted that the criteria of
			<lb />
			proportionality are more precise and more sophisticated than traditional
			<lb />
			grounds of review and went on to outline three concrete differences
			<lb />
			between the two:-
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(1) Proportionality may require the reviewing Court to assess the
			<lb />
			balance which the decision maker has struck, not merely whether it is
			<lb />
			within the range of rational or reasonable decisions.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(2) Proportionality test may go further than the traditional grounds of
			<lb />
			review in as much as it may require attention to be directed to the
			<lb />
			relative weight accorded to interests and considerations.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(3) Even the heightened scrutiny test is not necessarily appropriate to the
			<lb />
			protection of human rights.
			<lb />
			Lord Steyn also felt most cases would be decided in the same way
			<lb />
			whatever approach is adopted, though conceded for human right cases
			<lb />
			proportionality is the appropriate test.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			26.
			<lb />
			The question arose as to whether doctrine of proportionality
			<lb />
			applies only where fundamental human rights are in issue or whether it
			<lb />
			will come to provide all aspects of judicial review. Lord Steyn in R.
			<lb />
			(Alconbury Development Limited) v. Secretary of State for the
			<lb />
			Environment, Transport and the Regions (2001) 2 All ER 929 stated as
			<lb />
			follows:-
			<lb />
			</item>
		<item>
			&quot;I consider that even without reference to the Human Rights Act, 1998
			<lb />
			the time has come to recognize that this principle (proportionality) is
			<lb />
			part of English administrative law not only when Judges are dealing
			<lb />
			with Community acts but also when they are dealing with acts subject to
			<lb />
			domestic law. Trying to keep the Wednesbury principle and
			<lb />
			proportionality in separate compartments seems to me to be unnecessary
			<lb />
			and confusing&quot;.
			
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Lord Steyn was of the opinion that the difference between both the
			<lb />
			principles was in practice much less than it was sometimes suggested
			<lb />
			and whatever principle was applied the result in the case was the same.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			27.
			<lb />
			Whether the proportionality will ultimately supersede the
			<lb />
			concept of reasonableness or rationality was also considered by Dyson
			<lb />
			Lord Justice in R. (Association of British Civilian Internees: Far East
			<lb />
			Region) v. Secretary of State for Defence [2003] QB 1397 and stated as
			<lb />
			follows:-
			<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
			&quot;We have difficulty in seeing what justification there now is for
			<lb />
			retaining Wednesbury test ..... but we consider that it is not for this Court
			<lb />
			to perform burial rights. The continuing existence of the Wednesbury
			<lb />
			test has been acknowledged by House of Lords on more than one
			<lb />
			occasion. A survey of the various judgments of House of Lords, Court of
			<lb />
			Appeals, etc. would reveal for the time being both the tests continued to
			<lb />
			co-exist.&quot;
			<lb />
			</item>

		<item>
			28.
			<lb />
			The position in English Administrative Law is that both the
			<lb />
			tests that is. Wednesbury and proportionality continue to co-exist and the
			<lb />
			proportionality test is more and more applied, when there is violation of
			<lb />
			human rights, and fundamental freedom and the Wednesbury finds its
			<lb />
			presence more on the domestic law when there is violations of citizens
			<lb />
			ordinary rights. Proportionality principle has not so far replaced the
			<lb />
			Wednesbury principle and the time has not reached to say good bye to
			<lb />
			Wednesbury much less its burial.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			19.
			<lb />
			Moreover, the, Hon&apos;ble Apex Court, in, a judgment
			<lb />
			rendered in a case titled as Basic Education Board UP versus
			<lb />
			Upendra Rai (2008) 3 SCC 432, has made an expostulation of law,
			<lb />
			vis-a-vis, Courts being prohibited, to, interfere with the policy
			<lb />
			decision of the Government, unless, it is in violation of some
			<lb />
			statutory or constitutional provision, (i) whereupon(s) there is no
			<lb />
			necessity hereat, for this Court, to, exercise its power of judicial
			<lb />
			review, as, for all the afore reasons, the, decision making processes
			<lb />
			involved in the making of Annexures P-5 and P-7, are, hence
			<lb />
			constitutionally sacrosanct, and, also constitutionally inviolable.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			Significantly vis-a-vis the merger, which has happened
			<lb />
			and occurred hereat, the Hon&apos;ble Apex Court in a judgment
			<lb />
			rendered in a case titled, as, Indian Airlines Officers&apos; Assn. Versus
			<lb />
			Indian Airlines Ltd and others alongwith connected matters,
			<lb />
			(2007) 10 SCC 684, has in paragraph 46 thereof, paragraph whereof
			<lb />
			stands extracted hereinafter, hence cast an expostulation of law,
			<lb />
			rather making it impermissible for Courts of law, to, in the exercise
			<lb />
			of their constitutional power, of judicial review, to, rip apart or
			<lb />
			disintegrate the apposite merger, upon, the apposite merger became
			<lb />
			founded, upon, any constitutional valid policy besides therein, it
			<lb />
			has, become mandated, that, any arguments of inequality or vis-a-
			<lb />
			vis unreasonable classification, being a meritless ground, to, strike
			<lb />
			down, any, policy decision.
			<lb />
			&quot;
		</p>

		<item>
			46.
			<lb />
			. In S.P. Shivprasad Pipal vs. Union of India &amp;
			<lb />
			Ors. [(1998) 4 SCC 598] Mrs. Sujata Manohar, J. took into
			<lb />
			consideration that prior to the merger of the three cadres, the
			<lb />
			Cadre Review Committee recommended the merger of three
			<lb />
			cadres/services which Committee was headed by Cabinet
			<lb />
			Secretary and had members of various other Ministries such as
			<lb />
			Secretary Labour, Finance, Department of Personnel, Law and
			<lb />
			Defence. These recommendations were approved by the Cabinet
			<lb />
			and it is thereafter that the Rules were framed which Rules were
			<lb />
			approved by the Department of Personnel and Law Ministry as
			<lb />
			also the Union Public Service Commission. The learned Judge
			<lb />
			noted that a detailed exercise was done to ensure that no
			<lb />
			injustice takes place to any of the merging cadres. The learned
			<lb />
			Judge then went on to note that the salary structure was similar
			<lb />
			in three cadres by 1987. The qualifications were also almost the
			<lb />
			same in all the three merging cadres. The learned Judge also
			<lb />
			further noted that the constitution of a unified cadre was in
			<lb />
			public interest and hence the merger could take place. The
			<lb />
			learned Judge went on to say:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;Hence the merger took place. Since this is essentially a matter
			<lb />
			of policy, the scope of review by the Court is limited. We can,
			<lb />
			however, examine the grievance of the appellant relating to
			<lb />
			unequals being treated as equals and the grievance relating to
			<lb />
			losing promotional avenues.&quot;
		</item>
		<item>
			<lb />
			Learned Judge found no fault with the policy decision and in
			<lb />
			fact went on to hold in para 19 of the judgment as under:
			<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
			&quot;However, it is possible that by reason of such a merger, the
			<lb />
			chance of promotion of some of the employees may be
			<lb />
			adversely affected, or some others may benefit in consequence.
			<lb />
			But this cannot be a ground for setting aside the merger which is
			<lb />
			essentially a policy decision. This Court in Union of India v.
			<lb />
			S.L. Dutta examined this contention. In SL Dutta a change in
			<lb />
			the promotional policy was challenged on the ground that as a
			<lb />
			result, service conditions of the respondent were adversely
			<lb />
			affected since his chances of promotion were reduced. Relying
			<lb />
			upon the decision in the State of Maharashtra vs. Chandrakant
			<lb />
			Anant Kulkarni this Court held that a mere chance of promotion
			<lb />
			was not a condition of service and the fact that there was a
			<lb />
			reduction in the chance of promotion would not amount to a
			<lb />
			change in the conditions of service.&quot;
			<lb />
			</item>

		<item>
			
			We do not think anything more is required to be said as regards
			<lb />
			the three decisions relied upon by the learned counsel.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			21.
			<lb />
			The afore trite underlining, as, becomes borne therein,
			<lb />
			is, rather with aplomb applicable hereat, vis-a-vis, merger of the
			<lb />
			hitherto BPL category, into the larger category of EWS, especially
			<lb />
			when the afore merger also does validly assimilate therewithin,
			<lb />
			even, the, hitherto category of BPL, through, the income limit,
			<lb />
			being enhanced from hitherto income of Rs.35000/-to Rs. 4.00 lacs
			<lb />
			hence drawn from all sources.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			22.
			<lb />
			This Court, for, all the afore stated reasons, deems it not
			<lb />
			fit, to exercise its power to judicial review, to, invalidate the
			<lb />
			impugned Annexures, yet, the further reason(s) for this Court, not
			<lb />
			approbating, the arguments addressed by the learned counsel for the
			<lb />
			petitioners, is, founded upon (a) the exercise of executive discretion
			<lb />
			by the Government of H.P, through, the valid enshrinement(s),
			<lb />
			occurring in sub Article 6 of Article 16, of, the constitution of India,
			<lb />
			though yet not becoming rested, upon, the firmest, hence accurate
			<lb />
			statistical data. However, the afore infirmity, if any, is condonable,
			<lb />
			as, in clause 3, of, Annexure P-5, and, for all the aforestated
			<lb />
			reasons, the, inclusion(s) therewithin, even of BPL certificate
			<lb />
			
			holders, is, an exercise rather may not requiring, any marshaling(s)
			<lb />
			qua therewith any precise scientific data, (i) especially only, vis-a-
			<lb />
			vis, any BPL family aspirant concerned, with an income up to
			<lb />
			Rs.35000/-per annum, as, any insistence, for, garnering(s), of, any
			<lb />
			firm scientific or precise data, vis-a-vis, the afore class, of, BPL
			<lb />
			family, is, rather not required to be undergone, by the executive
			<lb />
			hence prior to its, making the impugned Annexures, importantly
			<lb />
			given, the increase(s), in, sizes of reservation nowat meted to EWS
			<lb />
			category, and, also given the increase(s) in the number of posts,
			<lb />
			where-to-which, it has obviously become applicable than hitherto,
			<lb />
			(ii) and prominently, when the afore nowat contemplated
			<lb />
			economically marginalized section(s), of, society, than any aspirant
			<lb />
			holding a meager income of Rs.35000/-rather befittingly deserve,
			<lb />
			to, become valid recipient(s), of, the constitutional reservation, vis-
			<lb />
			a-vis, EWS, (iii) whereas, upon making them outside the afore
			<lb />
			realm merely, upon, firm statical data qua the number(s) of the
			<lb />
			afore remaining un-garnered, would bring breach becoming
			<lb />
			encumbered upon, the apposite constitutional norms, moreso, when
			<lb />
			even the afore hitherto category(ies) also remain within realm and
			<lb />
			
			infirmity, the impugned Annexures, cannot be invalidated, as for all
			<lb />
			the afore stated reasons, they do strike, the requisite balance, and,
			<lb />
			also ensure the apposite proportionality becoming meted adherence,
			<lb />
			and, especially heightened reverence becoming meted, vis-a-vis, the
			<lb />
			test of economic necessity, of, inclusion, of, a larger economically
			<lb />
			marginalized section(s), of, society, than, the category of EWS,
			<lb />
			significantly when it has occurred without disturbing the inclusion
			<lb />
			therewithin(s), of, even the BPL certificate holders. Consequently,
			<lb />
			merely upon the purported rights, of, purported exclusivity, of,
			<lb />
			reservation, of, BPL certificate holder, becoming purportedly
			<lb />
			truncated upon persons falling within clause 3 of Annexure P-5,
			<lb />
			hence being permitted to enter into, the area, of, competition, is, a
			<lb />
			constitutionally invalid argument, as, it fails, both the wednesbury
			<lb />
			test, and, also fails the test of proportionality, and, necessity.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			23.
			<lb />
			Moreover, since the learned counsel, for, the petitioner,
			<lb />
			has failed to convince this Court, that there, is any malafides or
			<lb />
			gross impropriety, in, the exercise of discretion, by the State of
			<lb />
			Himachal Pradesh, in, the making of Annexures P-5 and P-7,
			<lb />
			thereupon also this Court rejects, all his submissions, inclusive of,
			<lb />
			the, one appertaining, to, the legitimate expectation, of the writ
			<lb />
			petitioners, who hitherto became vested, with, an exclusive right to
			<lb />
			stake claim, for, selection and appointment under EWS category, as,
			<lb />
			the afore argument also fails the test of proportionality, and, of
			<lb />
			necessity. Since advertised posts are made by the Government of
			<lb />
			Himachal Pradesh, thereupon the challenge to the apposite
			<lb />
			Annexures, as, made by the Central Government are deemed
			<lb />
			unnecessary, for, being meted any adjudication.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			In view of the above, present petitions stand dismissed,
			<lb />
			alongwith all pending applications.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			( Sureshwar Thakur),
			<lb />
			Judge.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			21.9. 2020
			<lb />
			( Chander Bhusan Barowalia ),
			<lb />
			(priti)
			<lb />
			Judge.
			<lb />
		</p>


	</text>
</tei>