<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<head>ORDER<lb/></head>

			<p>(Order of this Court was made by S.MANIKUMAR, J.)<lb/> A resident of Kaduvetti Village, Thottiyam Taluk, Trichy District,<lb/> and claiming himself to a Public Interest Litigant, has sought for a Writ of<lb/> Mandamus, directing the respondents from constructing the community<lb/> hall in the vacant land, adjacent to Middle School in Kaduvetti Village.<lb/></p>

			<p>2. In the supporting affidavit, the petitioner has contended that in<lb/> the said Village, there is a Panchayat Union School, Kaduvetti Village,<lb/> Thottiyam Taluk.<lb/> The total extent of the School is 50 cents. School<lb/> building is in a dilapidated condition. According to him, instead of<lb/> renovating / repairing the school, the President, Kaduvetti Village<lb/> Panchayat, Thottiyam Taluk, Trichy, has attempted to construct a<lb/> Community Hall in the vacant land adjacent to the School and also laid<lb/> foundation for his personal gain. He has further added that in future, there<lb/> is a likelihood of the school being upgraded. Therefore, if the vacant space<lb/> is used for construction of a Community Hall, it would be against the<lb/> welfare of the school children and village. On the above pleadings, he has<lb/> sought for a Writ of Mandamus, as stated supra.<lb/></p>

			<p>3. At two places in the supporting affidavit, the petitioner has<lb/> specifically contended that an attempt is being made to construct a<lb/> Community Hall, which is contrary to the news item published on<lb/> 24.11.2015, which indicates that the construction is only a Community<lb/> Service Centre. From the news item, it appears that the construction of a<lb/> Community Centre in the said place has been opposed and Police have<lb/> apprehended two persons, which includes the petitioner herein, for<lb/> preventing the public servants from discharging their duties.<lb/></p>

			<p>4. When the matter came up for admission, on instruction,<lb/> Mr.A.K.Bhaskarapandian, learned Special Government Pleader has<lb/> submitted that the District Collector and the Chairman of the District Rural<lb/> Development Agency, Tiruchirappalli, has accorded administrative sanction<lb/> in Se.Mu.A8/1201/2015, dated 22.04.2015, for construction of a Community<lb/> Service Centre in Village Panchayats in Trichy District, for the year<lb/> 2015-2016. He further submitted that the Panchayat Office in Kaduvetti<lb/> Village, Thottiyam Taluk, Trichy District was in a dilapidated condition.<lb/> Therefore, the Village Panchayat passed a resolution on 29.04.2015, to pull<lb/> down the dilapidated building from the said place and proposed to construct<lb/> a Community Service Centre.<lb/></p>

			<p>5.<lb/> Accordingly,<lb/> Thottiyam<lb/> Block<lb/> Development<lb/> Officer<lb/> (Panchayats), has issued orders in R.C.No.B5/2055/2015, dated 14.09.2014,<lb/> to carryout work for construction of a Community Service Centre in<lb/> Kaduvetti Village,<lb/> Thottiyam Taluk, Tiruchirappalli at a cost of Rs.<lb/> 17,00,000/-and subject to the conditions contained in the proceedings,<lb/> dated 14.09.2014.<lb/></p>

			<p>6.Learned Special Government Pleader has further submitted that<lb/> the entire Village supported the construction of the Community Service<lb/> Centre, except two persons viz., one Mr.Palanivelu and Mr.K.R.Rengasamy,<lb/> the petitioner herein. When the construction activities were going on, the<lb/> above said persons prevented the same and therefore, the President of<lb/> Kaduvetti Panchayat has submitted a letter, dated 28.12.2015, to the Block<lb/> Development Officer, (Village Panchayats), Panchayat Union, Thottiyam, to<lb/> take appropriate action against the above said persons. Similar letter has<lb/> also been given to the Tahsildar.<lb/> Responding to the request of the<lb/> President of Kaduvetti Panchayat, Thottiyam Taluk, the Block Development<lb/> Officer (Village Panchayats), Panchayat Union, Thottiyam vide proceedings<lb/> in R.C.B5./2055/2015, dated 28.12.2015, has requested the Deputy<lb/> Superintendent of Police, Musiri, to take appropriate action. Village people<lb/> has also given a complaint to the Inspector of Police, Thottium.<lb/></p>

			<p>7. Order, dated 14.09.2014 of the Thottiyam Block Development<lb/> Officer (Panchayats), reads as follows:-<lb/></p>

			<p>8. The letter dated 28.12.2015 of the Block Development Officer,<lb/> (Village Panchayats), Panchayat Union, Thottiyam to the Superintendent of<lb/> Police, Musiri, reads as follows:-<lb/></p>

			<p>9. The letter dated 05.01.2016, of the Block Development Officer,<lb/> Thottiyam Panchayat Union, Trichy, reads as follows:-<lb/></p>

			<p>9. The letter dated 28.12.2015 of the Panchayat President,<lb/> Kaduvetti, Thottiak Taluk, reads as follows:-<lb/></p>

			<p>10. From the materials placed before us and extracted supra, we<lb/> find that the petitioner has not only mislead this Court by describing the<lb/> construction as Community Hall, but alleged to have attempted to prevent<lb/> the construction. Construction of Community Service Centre is a welfare<lb/> measure, for the benefit of the Villages.<lb/></p>

			<p>11. From the materials on record it could be deduced that huge<lb/> amount has been allotted for construction of the Village Community Service<lb/> Centres, at a total cost of Rs.28,368.170 Lakhs. There is no public interest<lb/> involved in this case.<lb/></p>

			<p>12. It is also the submission of learned Special Government<lb/> Pleader, the Panchayat Union Office building has been demolished and<lb/> only in that place, the Community Service Centre has been constructed.<lb/> Thus the contention of the petitioner that the construction is in a new place,<lb/> adjacent to the Panchayat Union School, is also not factually correct.<lb/></p>

			<p>13. Though the petitioner has contended that the Writ Petition is a<lb/> Public Interest Litigation, from the materials on record considered by this<lb/> Court extensively, we find that the Writ Petition is against Public Interest.<lb/> Considering the conduct of the petitioner in attempting to stall a public<lb/> welfare measure, and for misleading this Court by describing the<lb/> construction as Community Hall, while dismissing the writ petition, we<lb/> deem it fit to impose cost to the petitioner, which he as already undertaken<lb/> to pay, if the Court comes to a conclusion that it is a vexatious or frivolous<lb/> litigation.<lb/> Accordingly, we impose a cost of Rs.10,000/-to the petitioner,<lb/> to be paid to the District Collector, Tiruchirappalli, within a period of 10<lb/> days from the date of receipt of a copy of this Order. If the above said<lb/> amount is not paid by the petitioner, within the stipulated time, The District<lb/> Collector, Trichirappalli, is directed to take action against the petitioner,<lb/> under the Revenue Recovery Act, for recovering the amount, as ordered by<lb/> this Court. Consequently, connected miscellaneous petition is also<lb/> dismissed.<lb/></p>

			<p>(S.M.K, J.) (C.T.S, J.)<lb/></p>

			<item>15.02.2016<lb/></item>

			<item>Index<lb/> : Yes / No<lb/> Internet : Yes / no<lb/> mpk<lb/> To<lb/></item>

			<item>1.The District Collector,<lb/> Tiruchirappalli.<lb/></item>

			<item>2.The Block Development Officer,<lb/> Thottiyam Panchayat Union,<lb/> Trichy.<lb/></item>

			<item>3.The President,<lb/> Kaduvetti Village Panchayat,<lb/> Kaduvetti, Thottiyam Taluk,<lb/> Trichy.<lb/></item>

			<p>S.MANIKUMAR, J.<lb/> and<lb/> C.T. SELVAM, J.<lb/> MPK<lb/> W.P.(MD)No.3174 of 2016<lb/></p>

			<p>15.02.2016</p>


	</text>
</tei>
