<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<head>
			CORAM:
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE S. RAVINDRA BHAT
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE SANJEEV SACHDEVA
			<lb />
		</head>

		<p>
			MR. JUSTICE S. RAVINDRA BHAT
			<lb />
			%
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			1.
			<lb />
			This judgment will decide two appeals: one from the decision of the
			<lb />
			learned single judge in a writ petition, W.P.(C) No.1971/2014 [&quot;the writ
			<lb />
			petition&quot;], filed by the appellant [hereafter called &quot;Bayer&quot;] against the
			<lb />
			respondent (hereafter &quot;Natco&quot;) in LPA No. 359/2017 and the other, in a suit
			<lb />
			decided in CS (OS) (Comm) 1592/2016 filed by Bayer against the
			<lb />
			respondent in RFA(OS)(Comm) 6/2017 (Alembic Chemicals Ltd, the
			<lb />
			defendant in the suit, hereafter called &quot;Alembic&quot;). Both judgments deal with
			<lb />
			an identical issue, concerning the correct interpretation of Section 107A of
			<lb />
			the Patents Act, 1970 (&quot;the Act&quot;) which is commonly known as the -Bolar
			<lb />
			provision‖.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			Facts in the appeal arising out of the judgment in the writ petition (i.e.
			<lb />
			in LPA No359/2107) are that Bayer filed a suit [CS(OS) No.1090/2011] for
			<lb />
			injunction against Natco from making, importing, selling, offering for sale
			<lb />
			&quot;Sorafenib&quot;, ‗Sorafenib Tosylate&apos; (&quot;Bayer drugs&quot;) or any generic version or
			<lb />
			any other drug or product thereof which was a subject matter of Bayer&quot;s
			<lb />
			Patent No.215758. When the suit was pending, Natco applied to the Patent
			<lb />
			Office for grant of compulsory licence against that patent. This application
			<lb />
			was granted, on 09.03.2012, by the Patent Controller, under Section 84 of
			<lb />
			the Patents Act 1970 (hereafter &quot;the Act&quot;). The compulsory licence granted
			<lb />
			was solely for the purposes of making, using, offering to sell and selling the
			<lb />
			drug covered by the patent within the territory of India. However, inter alia,
			<lb />
			apart from producing the drug for the Indian market, Natco manufactured the
			<lb />
			product covered by the compulsory licence for export outside India. Bayer
			<lb />
			filed a writ petition seeking a direction to the Customs Authorities to seize
			<lb />
			the consignments for export containing products covered by compulsory
			<lb />
			Licence including ‗Sorafenat&apos; (&quot;Natco&quot; drugs hereafter) manufactured by
			<lb />
			Natco. Notice of writ petition was issued by a learned single judge of this
			<lb />
			court; the customs authorities were directed to ensure that no consignment
			<lb />
			from India containing ‗Sorafenat&apos; covered by compulsory licence was
			<lb />
			exported. At the same time, Natco was given the liberty to apply to the court
			<lb />
			for permission to export the drug. Later, on 23.05.2014, Natco pointed out
			<lb />
			that in fact it has already been granted a drug license and it was permitted to
			<lb />
			export the drug Sorafenib Tosylate not exceeding 15 gm for development/
			<lb />
			clinical studies and trials.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			3. Natco next applied for permission to export 1 Kg of Active
			<lb />
			Pharmaceutical Ingredient (hereafter &quot;API&quot;) Sorafenib to China to conduct
			<lb />
			clinical studies and trials for development of drug for regulatory purposes.
			<lb />
			That application was rejected by Bayer, which argued in its writ petition, that
			<lb />
			if permission were granted to Natco, it would be contrary to Section 107A
			<lb />
			and that such a transaction would be a commercial sale and hence, a patent
			<lb />
			infringement. According to Bayer, Section 107A was not applicable, because
			<lb />
			Natco was not conducting research. The sale of API, therefore, amounted to
			<lb />
			infringement of its patent. Bayer&quot;s interpretation of Section107A was that
			<lb />
			the provision mentions the word &quot;sale&quot; and also &quot;import&quot;, but the legislature
			<lb />
			consciously excluded the term &quot;export&quot;. Bayer relied on a German
			<lb />
			decision Polpharma as well as the US history of the Bolar Exemption (that
			<lb />
			allows sale only within the United States) and canvassed a restricted -as
			<lb />
			opposed to a liberal interpretation-of Section107A.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			Natco&quot;s counter affidavit in the writ petition among others urged that
			<lb />
			it did not export the finished product Sorafenat to any party outside India for
			<lb />
			commercial purpose. It further argued that the words &quot;sale&quot; for the purpose
			<lb />
			of drug development i.e. -solely for uses reasonably related to the
			<lb />
			development and submission of information required under any law for the
			<lb />
			time being in force, in India, or in a country other than India, that regulates
			<lb />
			the manufacture, construction, use, sale or import of any product‖ clearly
			<lb />
			pointed to the legislative intention that exports, for the purpose of drug
			<lb />
			development, in compliance of regulatory law of a country outside India was
			<lb />
			permissible.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			The suit, CS(COMM) No. 1592/2016 was filed by Bayer to injunct
			<lb />
			Alembic from making, selling, distributing, advertising, exporting, offering
			<lb />
			for sale and in any manner directly or indirectly dealing in Rivaroxaban and
			<lb />
			any product that infringed its (Bayer&quot;s) patent IN 211300 and for ancillary
			<lb />
			reliefs pleading: (i) that the subject patent is registered in the name of Bayer
			<lb />
			and is titled -Oxazolidinones and their Use; ii) that Alembic is
			<lb />
			manufacturing and exporting Rivaroxaban to the European Union; and that
			<lb />
			Alembic has made multiple Drug Master File submissions to the United
			<lb />
			States Food and Drug Administration in the United States of America for the
			<lb />
			drug Rivaroxaban; iv) that a drug Master File is a submission to the United
			<lb />
			States Food and Drug Administration that is used to provide confidential
			<lb />
			detailed information about the facilities, processes and articles used in the
			<lb />
			manufacturing, processing, packaging and storing of one or more human
			<lb />
			drugs; v) that Alembic has also filed a patent application for grant of a
			<lb />
			process patent for Rivaroxaban which specifically referred to Bayer&quot;s patent
			<lb />
			and said that Rivaroxaban is disclosed by Bayer&quot;s patent; thus, clearly
			<lb />
			showing that Alembic infringed Bayer&quot;s patent.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			During the hearing, Alembic stated that the exports being effected by
			<lb />
			it are covered by Section 107A. Thereafter, on 15.12.2016, Alembic
			<lb />
			categorically stated that till then it had not commercially launched
			<lb />
			Rivaroxaban and had only exported it within the meaning of Section 107A;
			<lb />
			further, that in the event Alembic, in the future, intended to launch
			<lb />
			Rivaroxaban, it would give one month&quot;s notice to Bayer to enable the latter
			<lb />
			to avail of its remedies. Bayer argued on that date that Alembic exported at
			<lb />
			least 90 Kg. Rivaroxaban worth ` 3 crores and export of such quantity could
			<lb />
			not be within the meaning of Section 107A.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			Parties in the Alembic suit were informed during the hearing, on
			<lb />
			15.12.2016, that the Natco&quot;s writ petition had been heard, (involving an
			<lb />
			identical issue of law) in which judgment had been reserved; in the
			<lb />
			circumstances, since only the legal question of interpretation of Section
			<lb />
			107A of the Act was to be decided, there was no need for pleadings; the
			<lb />
			court bound Alembic to its statement aforesaid and with the direction that
			<lb />
			Alembic thereafter will not effect any export without giving 15 days&quot; notice
			<lb />
			to Bayer. Arguments in addition to those already addressed in the writ
			<lb />
			petition, were permitted. Alembic later applied stating that it was effecting
			<lb />
			exports to Brazil and Palestine; that application was adjourned. Arguments
			<lb />
			were concluded on 14.02.2017 and judgment reserved.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			After a detailed analysis of the contentions and the facts, the impugned
			<lb />
			judgment rejected Bayer&quot;s arguments. The court found that firstly, the
			<lb />
			quantity sought to be exported by Natco was just enough for 1000-2000
			<lb />
			tablets, and, therefore, cannot be termed a commercial activity. The court
			<lb />
			then said that the intention of the legislature in interpreting Section 107 must
			<lb />
			be gathered from the plain meaning, which clearly does not exclude sale
			<lb />
			outside India. Further, there was nothing in Section 107A that implies that
			<lb />
			only the manufacturers themselves can avail of the exemption and cannot
			<lb />
			sell it to a third party. The only requirement is that the sale must be
			<lb />
			&quot;reasonably related to&quot; the submission of information under the law (in this
			<lb />
			case, Chinese law). The court also pointed that the WTO Panel had expressly
			<lb />
			upheld such a wide interpretation of the similarly-worded Canadian Bolar
			<lb />
			Exemption to be TRIPs compliant and, therefore, not unfairly prejudicial to
			<lb />
			the patent holder.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			On the text of Section 107A, the learned single judge noticed the
			<lb />
			difference between the wordings of that provision and Section 48, noting that
			<lb />
			the terms &quot;constructing&quot; in Section 107A and &quot;offering for sale&quot; in Section
			<lb />
			48 were not important. The learned single judge then held that:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-It is thus the purpose for which the said acts are done‗ which
			<lb />
			distinguishes, whether the acts constitute infringement of patent
			<lb />
			or not. If the said purpose is within the confines of Section
			<lb />
			107A, the acts so done would not constitute infringement and
			<lb />
			the patentee cannot prevent a non-patentee from doing them.
			<lb />
			However, if the purpose of doing the acts of making, using,
			<lb />
			selling or importing a patented invention is not solely for the
			<lb />
			purposes prescribed in Section 107A, the said acts would
			<lb />
			constitute infringement of patent and patentee can prevent non-
			<lb />
			patentee from doing them.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			10.
			<lb />
			The learned single judge then held:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-27. The point of difference between Bayer and Natco /
			<lb />
			Alembic is qua selling outside India. While Bayer contends that
			<lb />
			the word -selling‖ in Section 107A is confined to within the
			<lb />
			territory of India and selling of patented invention outside India
			<lb />
			even if for purposes specified in Section 107A would constitute
			<lb />
			infringement which can be prevented by patentee, the
			<lb />
			contention of the senior counsels for Natco / Alembic is that use
			<lb />
			of the word -selling‖ under Section 107A is without any such
			<lb />
			restriction of being within India only and would include selling
			<lb />
			outside India also, so long as solely for the purposes prescribed
			<lb />
			in Section 107A.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			28. The counsels for Bayer, to explain why Section 107A
			<lb />
			refers to the purpose of development and submission of
			<lb />
			information required under law in a country other than India
			<lb />
			that regulates manufacture, construction, use and sale of
			<lb />
			pharmaceutical products, if selling referred to in Section 107A
			<lb />
			was to be within the confines of India contend that the
			<lb />
			information generated in India and required under law of a
			<lb />
			country other than India to be submitted for obtaining approval
			<lb />
			for manufacture and marketing of any pharmaceutical product
			<lb />
			in that country can be submitted without the sale of patented
			<lb />
			invention outside the country. According to them, transfer from
			<lb />
			India to any other country can be only of information gathered /
			<lb />
			collected in India and required to be submitted under the laws
			<lb />
			of any other country for obtaining approvals for manufacture
			<lb />
			and sale of pharmaceutical products in that country.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			29. According to me, to uphold what Bayer contends, would be
			<lb />
			contrary to the natural / literal / textual interpretation of
			<lb />
			Section 107A of the Patents Act. To ascribe natural / literal /
			<lb />
			textual meaning to the language of Section 107A of the Patents
			<lb />
			Act, I proceed to dissect clause (a) thereof as under:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(i) Any act of making, constructing, using, selling or importing
			<lb />
			a
			<lb />
			patented
			<lb />
			invention
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(ii) solely for uses reasonably related to development and
			<lb />
			submission of information required under any law for the time
			<lb />
			being in force, in India, or in a country other than India, that
			<lb />
			regulates the manufacture, construction, use, sale or import of
			<lb />
			any product
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) shall not be considered as infringement of patent rights. It
			<lb />
			becomes immediately evident that ‗selling&apos; permitted by Section
			<lb />
			107A is of a patented invention‗i.e. a ̳
			<lb />
			product‗ and not of
			<lb />
			‗information&apos;. The word ‗information&apos; is in the context of
			<lb />
			‗required to be submitted to any authority under any law of
			<lb />
			India or of a country other than India regulating the
			<lb />
			manufacture and marketing of any product&apos;. Section 107A, as
			<lb />
			per its natural / literal / textual meaning requires selling of a
			<lb />
			patented invention solely for submission of information
			<lb />
			required under any law for the time being in force in a country
			<lb />
			other than India that regulates the manufacture, construction,
			<lb />
			use and sale of any product, to be not considered as
			<lb />
			infringement of patent right. The counsels for Bayer are unable
			<lb />
			to dispute that Section 107A envisages development and
			<lb />
			submission of information required under any law of a country
			<lb />
			other than India for obtaining approvals for manufacture and
			<lb />
			marketing of pharmaceutical products in that country. However
			<lb />
			contend that development of the information, required to be
			<lb />
			submitted in a country other than India, by making, using and
			<lb />
			constructing and selling of patented invention in India only.
			<lb />
			Significantly, the counsels for Bayer, qua ‗selling&apos; within India,
			<lb />
			admit can be of patented invention i.e. of the product, by Fine
			<lb />
			Chemical Producers of India to manufacture or producers of
			<lb />
			pharmaceutical products in India and do not insist, should be of
			<lb />
			information only. However when it comes to ‗selling&apos; outside
			<lb />
			India, they insist cannot be of patented invention or product
			<lb />
			and can be of information only. I am unable to read such
			<lb />
			dichotomy in the language of Section 107A. It is not found to
			<lb />
			distinguish between making, constructing, using, selling for
			<lb />
			submission of information required under law in India and
			<lb />
			under the law of a country other than India.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			31. I am also unable to accept the contention of Bayer that,
			<lb />
			use of the word -selling‖ refers to selling‗ within India&apos; only.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			32
			<lb />
			‗Sale&apos;, in Black‗s Law Dictionary, 10 th Edition, is
			<lb />
			defined as transfer of property or title having the elements of i)
			<lb />
			parties competent to contract; ii) mutual assent; iii) a thing
			<lb />
			capable of being transacted; and, iv) a price in money paid or
			<lb />
			promised to be paid. Thus, use of the word ‗sale&apos;/ ‗selling&apos;
			<lb />
			entails transfer of property or title in a thing and does not
			<lb />
			contain any territorial limitations viz. of being within the
			<lb />
			country or State.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			XXXXXX
			<lb />
			XXXXXX
			<lb />
			XXXXXX
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			35. The words ‗sale&apos;/ ‗selling&apos; thus, as per their literal / natural
			<lb />
			/ textual meaning are without any geographical limitations and
			<lb />
			in Section 107A are not to be understood as ‗within India&apos; only
			<lb />
			and if such sale / selling were to involve transfer of the patented
			<lb />
			invention / product to a country other than India though would
			<lb />
			also qualify as export / exporting but would not cease to be sale
			<lb />
			/ selling.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			XXXXXX
			<lb />
			XXXXXX
			<lb />
			XXXXXX
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			37. As far as Section 107A is concerned, use therein of the
			<lb />
			words -law for the time being ‗in a country other than India&apos; is
			<lb />
			evidence of, obtaining regulatory approvals in countries other
			<lb />
			than India being contemplated by the legislature. With such
			<lb />
			contemplation, the legislature provided that certain acts
			<lb />
			mentioned in Section 107A, required to be done for the purpose
			<lb />
			of obtaining such approval, would not be considered as
			<lb />
			infringement of patent rights. One of such acts is of selling of
			<lb />
			patented invention. The plain meaning of Section 107A is that
			<lb />
			selling of patented invention for obtaining regulatory approval
			<lb />
			in country other than India would entail transfer of patented
			<lb />
			invention i.e. product from India to that country. There is
			<lb />
			nothing in the language of Section 107A to suggest that only the
			<lb />
			information generated / collected in India could be transported
			<lb />
			out of India and not the patented invention. Information
			<lb />
			generated in India, unless accepted under the law of any other
			<lb />
			country for granting regulatory approvals for manufacture,
			<lb />
			sale and import in that country, would be of no use. There is
			<lb />
			nothing in the language of Section 107A to indicate that the
			<lb />
			legislature applied itself that the regulatory laws of countries
			<lb />
			other than India would accept the information generated and
			<lb />
			collected in India. The counsels for Bayer during the hearing
			<lb />
			also could not demonstrate that information collected /
			<lb />
			generated in India would be acceptable for grant of regulatory
			<lb />
			approvals for manufacture and sale of drugs in other countries.
			<lb />
			Even otherwise, the interpretation of laws of India cannot be
			<lb />
			dependent on foreign laws. I have not found any provision
			<lb />
			elsewhere in the Patents Act requiring the word ‗selling&apos; in
			<lb />
			Section 107A to be restricted to ‗within India&apos; only.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Contentions of parties: Bayer
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			11.
			<lb />
			Mr. Sudhir Chandra, Senior Advocate (for Bayer) argues that Section
			<lb />
			48 of the Act implicitly defines infringement by listing the exclusive rights
			<lb />
			of the patentee. Section 107A of the Act describes a particular set of
			<lb />
			circumstances in which acts that are largely those named in Section 48
			<lb />
			would &quot;not constitute infringement&quot;. Thus, Section 107A of the Act clearly
			<lb />
			provides for circumstances/actions which, but for its existence, would be
			<lb />
			covered as an infringement under Section 48. Therefore, it is clearly a
			<lb />
			proviso/exception. But for Section 48, Section 107 has no purpose.
			<lb />
			Therefore, the latter constitutes an exception to Section 48 and does not
			<lb />
			confer a right. He relies on the Supreme Court decision in S. Sundaram
			<lb />
			Pillai v. V.R. Pattabiraman AIR1985 SC 582 that the nature of a proviso is
			<lb />
			such that it:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-it is meant to be an exception to something within the main
			<lb />
			enactment or to qualify something enacted therein which but for
			<lb />
			the proviso would be within the purview of the enactment.‖
			<lb />
			[Emphasis supplied]
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			12.
			<lb />
			Furthermore, the nature of Section 107A of the Act as a
			<lb />
			proviso/exception can be seen from its placement in the statute by the
			<lb />
			legislature. It finds mention in Chapter XVIII which is titled &quot;suits
			<lb />
			concerning infringement.&quot; This means that Section 107A of the Act is
			<lb />
			intended to be used as a defence that may be claimed in the course of a suit
			<lb />
			for infringement rather than form the basis for an independent right or
			<lb />
			separate actionable claim. Moreover, Section 107A of the Act is placed just
			<lb />
			after, and along with, Section 107 which is titled &quot;Defences etc. in suits for
			<lb />
			infringement&quot;. This gives yet another indication of the legislative intent
			<lb />
			behind the manner in which Section 107A of the Act was envisioned to be
			<lb />
			applied. The learned single judge&quot;s finding that the provision is not an
			<lb />
			exception and that it confers an independent right, is impugned as erroneous.
			<lb />
			It is also stated that the observations in the impugned judgment that the
			<lb />
			interpretation furthers the right of the exporter, under Article 19(1)(g) of the
			<lb />
			Constitution of India does violence to the plain reading of Section 107A
			<lb />
			which neither uses such language nor envisages the commission of such acts
			<lb />
			beyond the exhaustively defined situation that it lays out. It is also argued
			<lb />
			that the existence of a right implies the creation of an actionable claim. The
			<lb />
			absence of a legislative prescription of a remedy clearly shows that it is not
			<lb />
			the legislative intent to confer an independent right to a party under section
			<lb />
			107A of the Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			13.
			<lb />
			Learned Senior Counsel relied on the rule that a proviso should be
			<lb />
			interpreted narrowly, unlike a right which warrants liberal interpretation.
			<lb />
			Specifically, a proviso must be interpreted keeping in mind the scope of the
			<lb />
			main enactment to which it forms a proviso. This was recognised by the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court in The Commissioner of Income Tax v the Indo-Mercentile
			<lb />
			Bank Ltd. [AIR 1959 SC 713].
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			14.
			<lb />
			Mr. Chandra argued that the legislative intent behind Section 107A
			<lb />
			of the Act is only to ensure the availability of a competitor&apos;s product
			<lb />
			immediately after the expiry of patent in the Indian market without having to
			<lb />
			wait for regulatory approval post patent expiry. However, this intent does
			<lb />
			not extend to ensuring the availability of the same in other countries. He
			<lb />
			relies on the Notes on Clauses of the Patents (Amendment) Act 2002 as well
			<lb />
			as the Joint Parliamentary Committee Report pertaining to the insertion of
			<lb />
			Section 107A of the Act. Learned Senior Counsel stated that the phrase &quot;in a
			<lb />
			country other than India‖ refers to the submission of information in
			<lb />
			countries other than India so that the data generated in India may be
			<lb />
			submitted around the world, as is an accepted practice in the pharmaceutical
			<lb />
			industry. In fact, India is becoming a favoured global destination for
			<lb />
			conducting clinical trials and the data generated in this process is often used
			<lb />
			before regulatory regimes around the world. The expression in Section 107A
			<lb />
			(i.e. sale, construct etc.) is qualified by the word &quot;law&quot; with the phrase &quot;in a
			<lb />
			place other than India&apos;. The latter phrase has clearly not been used to
			<lb />
			describe the acts of &quot;making, selling using&quot;, etc., i.e. it cannot possibly
			<lb />
			intend to authorise the commission of acts outside the territory of India. The
			<lb />
			phrase has merely been included so that companies in India may avail the
			<lb />
			Bolar exemption not only to obtain approvals in India but around the world,
			<lb />
			without having to conduct separate clinical trials for every instance of
			<lb />
			submission of data. It is argued that Section 107 has three important
			<lb />
			elements, i.e. the activities (selling, making, constructing) the purpose,
			<lb />
			which can only be &quot;development and submission of information&quot;; and the
			<lb />
			law i.e. that such development (and submission of information) should be
			<lb />
			&quot;required by any law in India or in a country other than India&quot;. Learned
			<lb />
			Senior Counsel argued therefore, that the phrase in &quot;a country other than
			<lb />
			India&quot; refers to the law that requires development and submission of
			<lb />
			information and the law that -regulates the manufacture, construction, use,
			<lb />
			sale or import of any product‖. The policy of the provision is, therefore, met
			<lb />
			if activities are permitted in India for the purpose of generating data which
			<lb />
			may then be submitted before the regulatory authority in India or a country
			<lb />
			other than India. It is argued that this construction only would be consistent
			<lb />
			with the legal requirement of not placing any fetters on the patentee&apos;s
			<lb />
			exclusive rights beyond the fulfillment of the legislative purpose or intent.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			15.
			<lb />
			Mr. Chandra highlighted that the expression &quot;exports&quot; occurs in
			<lb />
			various other provisions of the Act: reference is made to Sections 84, 90(1)
			<lb />
			and 92A in this regard. They prescribe restrictions and export of a patented
			<lb />
			product may be allowed only within the ambit of such restrictions. All these
			<lb />
			show that the legislature has consciously used the expression &quot;export&quot;
			<lb />
			whenever it was necessary. However, no such explicit mention of export or
			<lb />
			corresponding restriction as found in these provisions can be seen in Section
			<lb />
			107A of the Act. It is urged that this is significant, given the background of
			<lb />
			the fact that the term &quot;importing&quot; was specifically included in Section 107A
			<lb />
			of the Act by the Patents (Amendment) Act, 2005, without any mention of
			<lb />
			the word export&quot; or &quot;offering for sale&quot;. This clearly indicates that the
			<lb />
			legislature did not intend to include these activities within the ambit of the
			<lb />
			said Section. The inclusion of &quot;importing&quot; in Section 107A of the Act also
			<lb />
			reinforces the legislative intent which is to ensure the availability of the drug
			<lb />
			in the Indian market. Learned Senior Counsel also relied on the Joint
			<lb />
			Parliamentary Report which clearly states that the purpose of Section 107A
			<lb />
			of the Act is to bring India&apos;s Bolar exemption in line with the global
			<lb />
			requirements.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			16.
			<lb />
			It is next submitted that the word &quot;selling&quot; does not include exports,
			<lb />
			because firstly the Act is territorial in nature and explicitly states in Section
			<lb />
			1 that it &quot;extends to the whole of India&quot;. Clearly, the Act only seeks to
			<lb />
			regulate activities which take place in India and hence, does not deal
			<lb />
			with/permit sale outside India. Moreover, as was held in the judgment of the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court in GvkInds Ltd. &amp; Anr. v The Income Tax Officer &amp;
			<lb />
			Anr.(2011) 4 SCC 36 only those extra-territorial aspects which have an
			<lb />
			impact or nexus with India and are enacted with the intent of creating some
			<lb />
			benefit for India would fall within the constitutionally sanctioned idea of
			<lb />
			legislative competence. Next, the nature and purpose of the Act is primarily
			<lb />
			to safeguard the interests of the patentee and the nature and purpose of
			<lb />
			Section 107A of the Act is an exception to the patentee&apos;s rights so that the
			<lb />
			generic versions of the drug may be made available immediately upon
			<lb />
			expiry of the patent in the Indian market. Inclusion of &quot;export&quot; within this
			<lb />
			provision would not serve the Indian market as envisioned by the Legislature
			<lb />
			and therefore, the same would be impermissible as per the law on extra-
			<lb />
			territorial legislative action. Thus, making, constructing and using of the
			<lb />
			product are permitted in India alone and export for that purpose is not
			<lb />
			contemplated.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			17.
			<lb />
			Moreover, since the act of selling in Section 48 refers to sale &quot;in
			<lb />
			India&quot; only (as can be seen from the provision), it cannot be said that Section
			<lb />
			107A of the Act, can enlarge the scope of this term and grant an additional
			<lb />
			right to the defendant. Counsel derives support from the judgment in Indo-
			<lb />
			Mercantile Bank Ltd (supra). It is argued, moreover, as untenable that the
			<lb />
			legislature would use the word &quot;selling &quot;in one sense as part of Section 48
			<lb />
			but accord to it a different meaning in an exception to the same Section
			<lb />
			within the same Act i.e. Section 107A of the Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			18.
			<lb />
			It is argued that the expression &quot;exports&quot; has a clear meaning in the
			<lb />
			general sense, and statutorily. &quot;Export&quot; as defined in Black&apos;s Law Dictionary
			<lb />
			means:&quot;To send or carry abroad, to send, take or carry (a good or
			<lb />
			commodity) out of the country; to transport (merchandise) from one country
			<lb />
			to another in the course of trade; to carry out or convey goods by sea&quot;.
			<lb />
			Thus, the act of sale which may occur in the course of an export can be
			<lb />
			concluded upon transfer of title in the goods which may happen outside
			<lb />
			India, however, the word &quot;selling&quot; referred to in both Section 48 and Section
			<lb />
			107A of the Act is clearly territorial in nature whereas the term &quot;export&quot; is,
			<lb />
			by definition, extra-territorial in nature. Thus, the learned Single Judge has
			<lb />
			grievously erred in conflating the two terms.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			19.
			<lb />
			It is argued that &quot;sale&quot; by &quot;export&quot; is mentioned in the Central Sales
			<lb />
			Tax Act, 1956 (&quot;CST Act&quot;) which deals with a -sale said to take place in
			<lb />
			the course of export&quot;. While considering the import of this phrase in Article
			<lb />
			286, the Supreme Court held in The Stale of Travancore-Cochin and Ors. v.
			<lb />
			The Bombay Company Ltd. AIR 1952 SC 366and The State of Travancore-
			<lb />
			Cochin v. The Shanmugha Vilas Cashew Nut Factory &amp; Ors AIR 1953 SC
			<lb />
			333that two types of sales or purchases would fall within this category: (a) a
			<lb />
			sale or purchase which itself occasions the export and (b) a sale or purchase
			<lb />
			affected by a transfer of documents of title to the goods after the goods are
			<lb />
			put in the export stream (i.e. after they have crossed the customs frontiers of
			<lb />
			India). Such an interpretation suggests that &quot;sale&quot; per se does not
			<lb />
			comprehend in itself export, which is a distinct activity, and that sale which
			<lb />
			occurs in the course of exports is extra-territorial in nature.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			20.
			<lb />
			It is argued that the impugned judgment erroneously found that a
			<lb />
			plain reading of section 107A of the Act would include the word &quot;exports&quot;
			<lb />
			as the same would fall within the meaning of the word &quot;selling&quot;. The
			<lb />
			construction placed by the learned Single Judge to the provision really
			<lb />
			amounts to supplying casus omissus. This is contrary to the settled principles
			<lb />
			of statutory interpretation.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			21.
			<lb />
			It is argued that the Section must be read in accord with global
			<lb />
			standards applicable to the Bolar Exemption. Reference is made to the Joint
			<lb />
			Parliamentary Committee Report which clarifies that Section 107A of the
			<lb />
			Act was meant to be in line with the global standards in respect of the Bolar
			<lb />
			exemption. Furthermore, allowing export under Section 107A of the Act
			<lb />
			would be in violation of Article 30 of the TRIPS (Annexure14) which allows
			<lb />
			for exceptions to patent rights so long as the exception is (a) limited ; (b)
			<lb />
			does not unreasonably conflict with the normal exploitation of the patent ;
			<lb />
			and (c) does not unreasonably prejudice the legitimate interests of the
			<lb />
			patentee. It is pertinent to note that these were the very issues that were
			<lb />
			considered in the case of Canada-Patent Protection of Pharmaceutical
			<lb />
			Products [DS 114, hereafter &quot;Canada Dispute&quot; or &quot;Canada Patent Dispute]
			<lb />
			decided by the WTO Dispute Settlement Panel (&quot;DSP&quot; hereafter) when
			<lb />
			adjudicated the legality of Canada&apos;s Bolar provision. Notably, both sides
			<lb />
			in this dispute readily acknowledged that such a provision was in the nature
			<lb />
			of an exception to the patentee&apos;s rights. While the WTO upheld the validity
			<lb />
			of the Bolar exemption, it did not consider whether an export would be
			<lb />
			permissible within the ambit of this exception. In fact, Canada&apos;s contentions
			<lb />
			with respect to the issue of submission of information before foreign
			<lb />
			regulatory regimes clearly indicates that the Canadian provision envisioned
			<lb />
			the testing itself to be carried out domestically while the information
			<lb />
			generated therefrom could be used for submission abroad. This case
			<lb />
			therefore, underscores the approach which the appellant is canvassing for the
			<lb />
			consideration. Furthermore, allowing exports under Section 107A of the Act
			<lb />
			would also be in disregard of Article 31 of the TRIPS which states in clause
			<lb />
			(f) that the any use of a non-patentee should be predominantly for the supply
			<lb />
			of the domestic market of the member country authorizing such use.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			22.
			<lb />
			Bayer argues that reading exports into Section 107A of the Act
			<lb />
			would be contrary to the general interpretation of &quot;Bolar Provisions&quot; around
			<lb />
			the world. Those countries which do permit export explicitly provide for the
			<lb />
			same in their statute and do so with a specific purpose. For instance,
			<lb />
			Australia permits exports explicitly for patents which have received an
			<lb />
			extension in their term. Several jurisdictions have also recognised the blatant
			<lb />
			prejudice this would cause to the rights of the patentee such as the Polish
			<lb />
			Supreme Court in A.P. Inc. v. SFP SA [IV CSK 92/13] and the German
			<lb />
			Appellate Court in Astellas v. Polpharma [12-U 68/12]. Therefore, the
			<lb />
			learned Single Judge returned findings which are not in line with the
			<lb />
			legislative intent and also in the teeth of the global standards with respect to
			<lb />
			the Bolar exemption.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			23.
			<lb />
			It is submitted that arguendo if Section 107A of the Act permits
			<lb />
			exports, the burden of proof must fall on the non-patentee. In this regard, it
			<lb />
			is stated that it is an established position under the law of evidence that the
			<lb />
			burden of proof must lie on the party who relies on a fact. This can be seen
			<lb />
			from Section 106 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 [Annexure 19], which
			<lb />
			provides that any fact(s) must be proved by the party which seeks to rely on
			<lb />
			the same. This also follows naturally from the fact that Section 107 of the
			<lb />
			Act is a defence/exception, as shown above. The burden of proof must
			<lb />
			clearly lie on the party who relies on the exception to justify their acts.
			<lb />
			Consequently, the non-patentee who relies on the fact that their export is for
			<lb />
			the purposes allowed by Section 107A of the Act must be the one who is
			<lb />
			required to prove the same, because it is the exporter/non-patentee who is
			<lb />
			privy to all the details relevant to proving the applicability of Section 107A
			<lb />
			of the Act such as manner of export, quantities, identity of the importing
			<lb />
			party etc. Learned Senior Counsel faults the impugned judgment which held
			<lb />
			that
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-this court cannot proceed to interpret the laws of the countries
			<lb />
			of intended export to determine whether the export intended in
			<lb />
			a given case is for the purposes prescribed in Section 107A of
			<lb />
			the Act. All exports by a non-patentee of a patented invention
			<lb />
			are deemed to be for the said purpose and only if proved to be
			<lb />
			otherwise, can make the exporter liable for consequences
			<lb />
			thereof in an appropriate legal proceeding.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			24.
			<lb />
			It was submitted that this approach effectively shifts the burden of
			<lb />
			proof on the patentee to show that the non-patentee&apos;s acts are not covered by
			<lb />
			Section 107A of the Act. This, in substance and effect, results in placing a
			<lb />
			reverse burden which is legally impermissible. Further, this results in the
			<lb />
			plaintiff not only having to establish that the defendants&apos; acts overlap with
			<lb />
			the exclusive rights of the patentee but that Section 107A of the Act is
			<lb />
			inapplicable. Moreover, a consistent application of this approach would also
			<lb />
			mean that the burden of proof stands reversed in respect of all activities
			<lb />
			contemplated by Section 107A. By extension, it could also be argued that
			<lb />
			the plaintiff must prove non-applicability of every section which sets out
			<lb />
			situations of non-infringement such as Section 47, 49, etc.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			25.
			<lb />
			It is argued further that even if Section 107A is interpreted to permit
			<lb />
			exports, the safeguards implicit in Section 107A of the Act cannot be
			<lb />
			ignored. Here Bayer urges that the phrase &quot;reasonably related...&quot; in Section
			<lb />
			107A of the Act clearly implies that compliance with the foreign regulatory
			<lb />
			regime must be proven and adjudicated upon by the court. It is clear that the
			<lb />
			court, in order to ensure the non-patentee&apos;s compliance with this phrase,
			<lb />
			would be required to undertake an analysis of the foreign regulatory
			<lb />
			requirements which the non-patentee uses as a justification for their acts.
			<lb />
			Counsel stated that this position is augmented by the prior judicial
			<lb />
			interpretations of Section 107A of the Act such as in Teva API India Pvt.
			<lb />
			Ltd, v Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp. [FAO (OS) (COMM) 34/2 016 before
			<lb />
			DHC (DB)] where the defendants&apos; undertaking in respect of compliance with
			<lb />
			the foreign regulatory regime as well as the export quantities were taken into
			<lb />
			consideration. It was submitted that the learned Single Judge, by finding that
			<lb />
			the court cannot get into an analysis of foreign regulatory regimes, has
			<lb />
			rendered the phrase -reasonably related to the development and submission
			<lb />
			of information‖ otiose. Furthermore, the various safeguards which were
			<lb />
			pointed out by Bayer before the learned single judge were not taken into
			<lb />
			consideration and in fact, it has been held by the latter in paragraph 56 of the
			<lb />
			impugned judgment that:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;.... Even if it were to be believed that the patented invention
			<lb />
			once exported from this Country for the purposes prescribed in
			<lb />
			Section 107A of the Act may be used for other purposes, it is for
			<lb />
			the patentee to enforce its rights if any in that country. The laws
			<lb />
			of this country are only concerned with the sale by way of
			<lb />
			export from this country being for the purposes prescribed,&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			26.
			<lb />
			Bayer stated that this completely prejudices the interests of the
			<lb />
			patentee, which cannot be in congruence with the object of the Act. The
			<lb />
			patentee&apos;s interests are prejudiced because:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(i) The patentee may not have a patent in the country of export which would
			<lb />
			leave the patentee completely remedy-less.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(ii) Even if the activities undertaken in the destination country post-export
			<lb />
			may not be actionable in India, the original act of intention to export or offer
			<lb />
			for sale itself certainly falls within the judicial scrutiny of the courts in India.
			<lb />
			By deigning to scrutinise and thus permitting, an unqualified entitlement to
			<lb />
			export, the potential for future abuse increases manifold. This would surely
			<lb />
			prejudice the rights of the patentee.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(iii)The patentee will have to undertake a global surveillance, tracking the
			<lb />
			products exported to establish what purpose they are being used for and then
			<lb />
			enforce their patents (if any) in multiple countries. This will give the
			<lb />
			defendants a free reign to export patented products without fear of
			<lb />
			prosecution. This could not have been the purport and intent of Section
			<lb />
			107A of the Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			27.
			<lb />
			It is argued lastly that in any event, the learned single judge failed to
			<lb />
			even consider the quantities sought to be exported by the respondent. They
			<lb />
			have to be compared with the quantities that are required by the regulatory
			<lb />
			regime to which information is to be submitted. This is crucial in confirming
			<lb />
			the purpose for which the non-patentee is undertaking the export. For
			<lb />
			instance, in the present case, more than 90 kgs of the patented product has
			<lb />
			been exported by the respondent. Non-consideration of the same runs
			<lb />
			contrary to the requirements of Section 107A of the Act as held in the
			<lb />
			pronouncement of Teva (supra).
			<lb />
			Contentions of Natco
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			28.
			<lb />
			The learned senior counsel, Mr. Anand Grover submitted that Natco
			<lb />
			disputed Bayer&quot;s factual assertion and contends that it had nothing to do
			<lb />
			with the alleged exports of the formulations. It is urged that anybody can
			<lb />
			buy the formulated drug in the market and send it out of the country. It is
			<lb />
			submitted that Bayer proposes selling the API (bulk drug) of Sorafenib
			<lb />
			Tosylate to M/s Hisun Pharmaceutical Co. Ltd (&quot;Hisun&quot; hereafter) in China,
			<lb />
			solely for generating data in China through Hisun to submit it to Chinese
			<lb />
			drug regulatory authorities. In any event, the issue of export under Section
			<lb />
			107A applies both to API and formulations. Pertinently, on 13.05.2011, i.e.
			<lb />
			before the issuance of the compulsory license, the Drugs Control
			<lb />
			Administration of Govt. of Andhra Pradesh granted a license to Natco to
			<lb />
			manufacture Sorafenib Tosylate API for domestic and export purposes. This
			<lb />
			raw material/bulk form is not covered by the compulsory license issued to
			<lb />
			Bayer. It is urged that Chinese law does not permit any non-Chinese entity to
			<lb />
			submit regulatory dossiers based on data and information generated in a
			<lb />
			country other than China. Similar laws exist in other countries. The studies
			<lb />
			are required to be conducted in China by a Chinese entity to the satisfaction
			<lb />
			of Chinese regulatory authorities. Reference is made to the SFDA Order No.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			28-Provisions for Drug Registration-Article 10-Provisions of Drug
			<lb />
			Registration.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			29.
			<lb />
			Mr. Grover submits that Bayer&quot;s patent expires on 12.01.2020;
			<lb />
			Article 19 of the Chinese drug registration law enables an entity other than
			<lb />
			the patentee to apply for patent registration two years prior to the expiry of
			<lb />
			its term. Natco denies Bayer&quot;s allegation that, under the guise of the grant of
			<lb />
			compulsory license, it is exporting the formulation to diverse countries, as
			<lb />
			baseless. It is argued that Bayer concedes that a generic manufacturer in
			<lb />
			India can carry on activities of making, constructing, using, selling or
			<lb />
			importing the patented invention for the development and generation of data
			<lb />
			to Indian authorities or foreign authorities, but however, contends that the
			<lb />
			patented article cannot be exported for development and generation of data
			<lb />
			abroad for submission to the foreign regulatory authorities. Natco submits
			<lb />
			that i) The TRIPS Agreement took note of the global nature of the
			<lb />
			pharmaceutical industry, the global need of access to affordable medicines.
			<lb />
			(ii) TRIPS also took note of extant practice under the US Bolar provision of
			<lb />
			exporting a patented article abroad for, developing and generating data
			<lb />
			abroad for submission to the US regulatory authorities, as exemplified by the
			<lb />
			US Supreme Court in Intermedics Inc. v Ventrilex, 775 F. Supp. 1269 (N. D.
			<lb />
			Cal. 1991). Mr Grover argued that Section 107A is enacted pursuant to
			<lb />
			Article 30 of the TRIPS Agreement (Providing for limited exceptions to
			<lb />
			exclusive rights conferred by the grant of a patent) and after the decision of
			<lb />
			the WTO Dispute Panel decision in Canada-Patent Protection of
			<lb />
			Pharmaceutical Products dispute (WTO/DS114/R) (hereinafter, the &quot;Canada
			<lb />
			Dispute&quot;). It is submitted, furthermore, that Section 107A takes into account
			<lb />
			the unique position of the Indian generic pharmaceutical industry in the
			<lb />
			international market and its role as the key supplier of affordable generic
			<lb />
			medicines. Therefore, Section 107A goes beyond the Canadian provision in
			<lb />
			this behalf.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			30.
			<lb />
			Natco urges that rights under Section 48 are subject to the acts
			<lb />
			exempted under Section 107A. Section 107A read with Section 48 do not
			<lb />
			prohibit export if the person concerned otherwise satisfies the conditions of
			<lb />
			Section 107A. Natco argues that sale under Section 107A includes export
			<lb />
			out of India. It therefore says that export of API for purposes -reasonably
			<lb />
			related to development and submission of information‖ to Chinese
			<lb />
			authorities is legitimate. It is furthermore argued that the rights under
			<lb />
			Section 107A and under Section 84 are independent but can be exercised by
			<lb />
			the same person.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			31.
			<lb />
			Explaining the drug innovation and patent life cycle, when a product
			<lb />
			with beneficial effect is developed, its patent is sought by the inventor. But,
			<lb />
			a pharmaceutical drug can be introduced in the market only after conducting
			<lb />
			animal toxicity studies which are Phase I, II, and III human clinical trials
			<lb />
			generating information and data which is submitted to the satisfaction of
			<lb />
			drug regulatory authorities. To avoid repeated clinical trials on patients,
			<lb />
			regulatory authorities over world permit generic companies to carry on
			<lb />
			studies such as bioequivalence, bioavailability and stability studies to
			<lb />
			establishing chemical and functional equivalence of their product with the
			<lb />
			originator product. This is done on a partial scale commercial production
			<lb />
			run. Based on such studies, a drug has to satisfy requirements of
			<lb />
			bioequivalence, bioavailability and stability studies. The precise needs, in
			<lb />
			terms of quantity of production, is specified by regulatory authorities in
			<lb />
			various countries; they differ from each other.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			32.
			<lb />
			Mr. Grover emphasizes that patent regimes do not countenance
			<lb />
			continuation of monopoly even a single day more than the permitted patent
			<lb />
			term. Thus, generic companies need to only conduct development studies,
			<lb />
			generation of information and data before the expiry of the patent, i.e. during
			<lb />
			a patent&quot;s term, to launch the product in the market immediately on expiry or
			<lb />
			invalidation of the patent. It is submitted that the global nature of the
			<lb />
			pharmaceutical industry is so structured that such generic producers are in a
			<lb />
			few countries; in some countries there are no generic producers at all. At
			<lb />
			times, even developed countries procure fine chemicals from other countries.
			<lb />
			Countries without generic industries do not necessarily have domestic
			<lb />
			markets that support operation of the industry on an economic scale. In such
			<lb />
			situations, the economies of scale for the generic manufacturers would be
			<lb />
			achieved if the product is also exported. Learned Senior Counsel also
			<lb />
			highlighted the leadership role played by Indian generic pharmaceutical
			<lb />
			entities in the global pharmaceutical market and flagged the support given to
			<lb />
			developing nations in Africa, South America, Central Asia and Eastern
			<lb />
			Europe stating that they supply over 90% of Anti Retro Viral Drugs to the
			<lb />
			developing countries. He also quoted a leading author, Brenda Waning,
			<lb />
			(Journal of AIDS Studies, 2010, 1335, A lifeline of treatment: the role of
			<lb />
			Indian generic maufacturers in supplying Antiretroviral medicines)
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			33.
			<lb />
			It was contended that the TRIPS Agreement carves out an exception
			<lb />
			under Article 30, permitting regulatory exception activities prior to the
			<lb />
			expiry of patent. In this regard, it is stated that several countries including
			<lb />
			India, Canada and the US have fashioned their patent laws to carve out such
			<lb />
			exception. It is submitted that the Canadian provision, Section 55. 2(1),
			<lb />
			enabling use of a patented product for generation of data and information to
			<lb />
			be submitted to regulatory authorities, was the subject matter of a complaint
			<lb />
			lodged by the US and Europe at the Dispute Settlement Body (hereafter
			<lb />
			&quot;DP&quot;) of the WTO (in the Canada Dispute). It was contended that Section
			<lb />
			55.2(1) violated TRIPS. The other challenge was to Section 55.2(2), the
			<lb />
			stock-piling exception of the Canadian law. Mr Grover submitted that the
			<lb />
			TRIPS dispute panel in the Canada dispute upheld the Canadian provisions.
			<lb />
			He contrasted the language of Section 55.2(1) of the Canada Patent law with
			<lb />
			Section 107A of the Act, highlighting that the former only contemplates
			<lb />
			&quot;development and submission of information required under any law of
			<lb />
			Canada, a province or a country other than Canada that regulates the
			<lb />
			manufacture, construction, use or sale of any product&apos;. However, Section
			<lb />
			107A of the Act of India, contemplates -... Development and submission of
			<lb />
			information required under any law for the time being in force... In a
			<lb />
			country other than India, that regulates the manufacture, construction, use,
			<lb />
			sale or import of any product.‖It is submitted that hence, Section 107A
			<lb />
			recognizes that export (of a patented product) to another country for
			<lb />
			development and submission of information (in that country), is not
			<lb />
			infringement. In the Canada Dispute, the DSP recognized that the general
			<lb />
			language of Article 30 was agreed to by the US on the understanding that it
			<lb />
			would help the US secure the Bolar exemption which was already in place
			<lb />
			there. The DSP also noted that foreign pre-expiry testing is accepted by the
			<lb />
			FDA and noted by the US Supreme Court in Intermedix Inc. (Supra). The
			<lb />
			DP found that such a provision was a &quot;limited exception&quot; within the
			<lb />
			meaning of Article 30 of TRIPS (Ref. Paras 7.2 to 7.6 DP order). Therefore,
			<lb />
			the key is not the quantity but the purpose for which production is carried.
			<lb />
			The DP also noted that the Canadian provision was a &quot;limited exception&quot;,
			<lb />
			irrespective of the quantity involved, because of the narrow scope of its
			<lb />
			curtailment of Article 28.1 choices (under TRIPS).So long as the exception
			<lb />
			is confined to conduct necessary to comply with the requirements of the
			<lb />
			regulatory approval process, the extent of the acts unauthorized by the right
			<lb />
			holder that are permitted by it are small and narrowly bounded. Though
			<lb />
			regulatory approval processes may require substantial amounts of test
			<lb />
			production to demonstrate reliable manufacturing, the patentee&apos;s rights are
			<lb />
			unimpaired, by the size of such production runs, so long as they are solely
			<lb />
			for regulatory purposes and no commercial use is made. (Ref para 7.45 at of
			<lb />
			the Canada Dispute). Hence, the DSP clarified that there would be no
			<lb />
			infringement of Patent, regardless of the amount so used or exported,
			<lb />
			provided the use or export is solely for regulatory purposes and not
			<lb />
			commercial use of final product.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			34.
			<lb />
			Mr. Grover next dwelt on the legislative history of Section 107A,
			<lb />
			stating that it was introduced after the DSP decision in Canada Dispute. In
			<lb />
			1999, the Patents Act (Second Amendment) Bill, 1999 (&quot;1999 Bill&quot;) was
			<lb />
			introduced in the Rajya Sabha to meet India&apos;s obligations under the TRIPS
			<lb />
			Agreement (required to be met by 01.01.2000). The Bill proposed the
			<lb />
			introduction of a new section i.e. Section 107A. Section 107A was sought to
			<lb />
			be amended in 2002 and 2003; but was finally amended in 2005, taking into
			<lb />
			account the decision in the Canada Dispute. However, it went beyond that
			<lb />
			decision. The changes brought about by the 2005 amendment are: a)
			<lb />
			abolition of the three year period prior to patent expiry; b) addition that the
			<lb />
			act of selling had to be &quot;solely related to the development and submission of
			<lb />
			data‖ in law; and c) addition that the law referred in the section could be of
			<lb />
			India &quot;or any country other than India‖; d) going beyond the Canadian law
			<lb />
			in that the expression &quot;importing&quot; and &quot;import&quot; were added in Section
			<lb />
			107A. Learned Senior Counsel also referred to the Joint Committee on
			<lb />
			Patents&quot; note of December, 2001, and said that it clarifies that the object of
			<lb />
			Section 107A is ensuring that regulatory approvals are not limited to only 3
			<lb />
			years before the patent term expiry and allow prompt availability.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			35.
			<lb />
			It is urged that Section 107A and Section 84 operate in different
			<lb />
			fields; the former operates on the submission of data generated in
			<lb />
			development of the drug to Regulatory authorities for marketing approval,
			<lb />
			that is the patented product is not sold in the market, Section 84 operates on
			<lb />
			marketing of the patented product for commercial purposes. Referring to
			<lb />
			Intermedics, counsel urged that the Federal Circuit court considered the
			<lb />
			scope of the Bolar provision. The case involved the sale of stents to a party
			<lb />
			outside the US for development purposes and held that sales to foreign
			<lb />
			distributors for development studies reasonably related to developing
			<lb />
			information could be submitted to the FDA and that such development of
			<lb />
			information need not be restricted to the period just before patent expiry.
			<lb />
			Thus, export of the patented article to another country was very much part of
			<lb />
			the patent law in the US at the time of coming into force of the TRIPS
			<lb />
			Agreement. Likewise, this position was noted in Canada Dispute case,
			<lb />
			which ruled on Section 55.2 of the Canadian Act. (Ref para 4.38(a) of the
			<lb />
			decision).
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			36.
			<lb />
			Learned Senior Counsel urged that Section 107A should be
			<lb />
			interpreted in accordance with TRIPS and the interpretation placed on that
			<lb />
			by the DSP. Furthermore, considering that the Indian law, uses the phrase
			<lb />
			&quot;in a country other than India,&quot; which is absent in the US law, a fortiori
			<lb />
			India permits export to other countries in accordance with their law for
			<lb />
			submission of data of development studies. As a result, Section 48 does not
			<lb />
			prohibit, but allows export. Indian law would apply to the territory to which
			<lb />
			the medicines are imported by the expression &quot;importing&quot; which needs to be
			<lb />
			in every patent law by virtue of the minimum standards of TRIPS compliant
			<lb />
			intellectual property regime. Therefore, the expression &quot;import&quot; for another
			<lb />
			country, in so far as Section 107A is concerned, would mean an export from
			<lb />
			India. Therefore, export is actually contemplated under Section 107A.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			37.
			<lb />
			Mr. Grover states that it is an established position in law that any
			<lb />
			term in a provision should be given plain meaning. Bayer&quot;s reading into
			<lb />
			Section 107A, limitations is therefore impermissible. Non-existent
			<lb />
			limitations in a statute cannot be read into it. Reference is made to GP
			<lb />
			Singh&quot;s Principles of Statutory Interpretation 12th Edition and State of
			<lb />
			Orissa v Joginder Pattjoshi (2004) 9 SCC 278. Also, &quot;sale&quot; is a
			<lb />
			compendious term that includes &quot;export&quot;; in any event, importantly, patent
			<lb />
			law is territorial in nature and does not control any high seas transaction.
			<lb />
			Export is actually embraced in and controlled through a sale. The learned
			<lb />
			single judge too noted that &quot;sale&quot; is not to be understood as being within
			<lb />
			India.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			38.
			<lb />
			It is contended that entities such as Bayer are not prejudiced because
			<lb />
			if a drug is imported into a territory in which in respect of that drug, a patent
			<lb />
			is granted, then the patentee would be able to interdict any unauthorized use
			<lb />
			of the patented article, barring the import for regulatory exception. This is
			<lb />
			the accepted position in TRIPS. (Ref para 7.46 Canada Dispute). It is stated
			<lb />
			that the Parliament was conscious of the role the Indian generic companies
			<lb />
			play in access to affordable medicines around the world and in particular in
			<lb />
			developing countries. Mr. Grover urges that Bayer incorrectly claims that
			<lb />
			the learned single judge did not appreciate the difference between API and
			<lb />
			the finished product. It is stated that after differentiating between API and
			<lb />
			the finished formulation, the learned single judge detailed the difference
			<lb />
			between Fine Chemical Producers and other manufacturers/producers of
			<lb />
			medicines, and concluded that the term &quot;selling&quot; used in Section 107A is to
			<lb />
			facilitate selling of API/formulations to the manufacturers of medicines.
			<lb />
			Further, the learned single judge noted that even after the 2002 Amendment,
			<lb />
			Section 107A was not added as a proviso to Section 48, rather it was
			<lb />
			included under the Chapter titled &quot;suits concerning infringement of patents&quot;
			<lb />
			under Section 107 titled &quot;Defences, etc., in suits for infringement&quot;. He
			<lb />
			concluded correctly that Section 48 does not confer a right to prevent
			<lb />
			making and selling patented product for purposes solely prescribed in
			<lb />
			Section 107A.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			39.
			<lb />
			It is urged that Section 48 of the Patents Act is subject to the
			<lb />
			provisions of Section 84 and 107A of the Patents Act. Section 107A is not
			<lb />
			subject to the operation of Section 84 or of Chapter XVI of the Act. Thus,
			<lb />
			Section 84 does not control Section 107A. Section 48 would yield to other
			<lb />
			provisions of the Patents Act, including Section 107A and, its operation
			<lb />
			cannot be curtailed by Section 84. In this regard, it is submitted that the
			<lb />
			effect to both the provisions, Section 107A and 84, has to be given in
			<lb />
			appropriate circumstances. Both operate in different fields. Section 107A
			<lb />
			operates on the submission of data generated in the development of the drug
			<lb />
			to regulatory authorities for marketing approval, that is the patented product
			<lb />
			is not sold in the market, whereas Section 84 operates on marketing of the
			<lb />
			patented product for commercial purposes. Stressing on the need to
			<lb />
			harmoniously interpret all parts of the statute, it is stated that such consistent
			<lb />
			reading excludes the idea that one provision can trump the other and render
			<lb />
			it otiose, unless specifically provided. Counsel referred to Padma Ben
			<lb />
			Banushali &amp; Another v Yogendra Rathore and Others, (2006) 12 SCC 138.
			<lb />
			Reference is also made to High Court of Gujarat v Gujarat Kishan Mazdoor
			<lb />
			Panchayat (2003) 4 SCC 712. It is urged that the argument with respect to
			<lb />
			the relationship between Section 107A and Section 84 is flawed. The learned
			<lb />
			single judge noted that the purpose of Section 107A is different from Section
			<lb />
			84, which is only for obtaining the regulatory approvals under the laws of
			<lb />
			India or in a country other than India.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			40.
			<lb />
			Without prejudice, it is submitted that the compulsory license under
			<lb />
			Section 84 operates as a deed or contract between the Controller and Natco,
			<lb />
			the grantee of compulsory licence (Section 93). Such a deed being a
			<lb />
			contract, cannot override a provision of law. Hence, the condition imposed
			<lb />
			by learned Controller must be read down to give way to Section 107A.
			<lb />
			Learned Senior Counsel also highlighted that pursuant to the impugned
			<lb />
			judgment, Natco filed an affidavit that during the life of the patent, it would
			<lb />
			not export the patented product for purposes other than spelt out by Section
			<lb />
			107A. It is urged that the undertaking allows Bayer to revoke an order in
			<lb />
			case of breach of undertaking by Natco. This is apart from the remedy that
			<lb />
			Bayer has in the form of an infringement suit in the country, where the
			<lb />
			patented article is sent to for the purposes of development studies,
			<lb />
			generating data on a semi production run for submission to the regulatory
			<lb />
			authorities.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			41.
			<lb />
			On behalf of Alembic, Ms. Saya Chaudhary highlighted that Bayer
			<lb />
			filed the suit despite knowledge and admission that the defendant (i.e
			<lb />
			Alembic) had not launched any commercial product in the Indian market,
			<lb />
			and in the absence of any pleadings indicating that the patent was
			<lb />
			commercially exploited by Alembic, or any party procuring Rivaroxaban
			<lb />
			through Alembic outside India. A suit for infringement was filed solely on
			<lb />
			the basis that:(i) a process patent application being PCT/1B2013/055062
			<lb />
			pertaining to process of manufacturing Rivaroxaban was filed by Alembic,
			<lb />
			which according to Bayer, indicated its (Alembic&apos;s) intent to launch a
			<lb />
			commercial product in India (ii) a Drug Master File (DMF) was applied by
			<lb />
			Alembic, before the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA); (iii) a no-
			<lb />
			Objection Certificate was obtained by Alembic for exporting Rivaroxaban to
			<lb />
			Europe. Bayer, however could not prove or establish even prima facie that
			<lb />
			the acts complained of, fell within the purview of section 48 of the Act, i.e.
			<lb />
			commercial exploitation of the patented product as opposed to regulatory
			<lb />
			use. Initially, in the suit, Alembic made a categorical statement that it had
			<lb />
			neither launched nor commercialized the suit patent in India and that all acts
			<lb />
			conducted by it pertaining to Rivaroxaban were solely for regulatory
			<lb />
			purposes in India, and abroad as enumerated under section 107A of the Act.
			<lb />
			As a result, Alembic committed no act contemplated under section 48. No
			<lb />
			allegation of diversion of exports too was alleged in the pleadings or
			<lb />
			documents. Accordingly, the first question arising for consideration is
			<lb />
			whether based on acts covered under Section 107A, can a party be regarded
			<lb />
			as an infringer, who is then required to plead Section 107A as a defense to
			<lb />
			Section 48 of the Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			42.
			<lb />
			It is urged that the placement of Section 107A in the Act, as a
			<lb />
			separate and distinct section, different from Section 107 which deals with
			<lb />
			defences, etc., in suits for infringement is evidence of the intent of the
			<lb />
			Legislature that Section 107A ought not to be treated as a defence to Section
			<lb />
			48, but is required to be treated as an independent section which specifically
			<lb />
			provides for certain acts not to be considered as infringement.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			43.
			<lb />
			Ms. Chaudhary said that the shift in Indian Patent law is evident
			<lb />
			upon a plain reading of Sections 107A and Section 48 of the Act, both of
			<lb />
			which were inserted/substituted simultaneously by Act 38 of the 2002 so as
			<lb />
			to make India TRIPS compliant. Section 48 of the Act, in comparison to
			<lb />
			other legislative provisions pertaining to protection of IP Rights in India
			<lb />
			such as trade mark, copyright etc., is peculiar in nature inasmuch as it is a
			<lb />
			negative right, whereby a patentee is legally entitled under the Act &apos;to
			<lb />
			prevent third parties, who do not have his consent, from the act of making,
			<lb />
			using, offering for sale, selling or importing for those purposes that product
			<lb />
			in India&apos;. This aspect coupled with the fact that the said provision by clear
			<lb />
			and express language has been made &apos;subject to the other provisions
			<lb />
			contained in this Act and the conditions specified in Section
			<lb />
			47......&apos;establishes that it is the rights of a patentee enumerated under Section
			<lb />
			48 which yield to the rights of third parties under Section 107A of the Act.
			<lb />
			Thus, no fetters or restrictions can be placed on the acts enumerated under
			<lb />
			section 107A, especially by making parties liable to infringement action. In
			<lb />
			other words, patentee cannot prevent third parties from dealing with patented
			<lb />
			invention for regulatory use and no infringement action can be
			<lb />
			maintainedagainst such regulatory use. This legislative intent is evident upon
			<lb />
			a bare perusal of Section 107 of the Act, to which no amendments were
			<lb />
			made in 2002, or thereafter so as to label the rights of third parties to use
			<lb />
			patented inventions for acts detailed in Section 107A as a &apos;defence to a suit
			<lb />
			for patent infringement&apos;. In fact, in Section 107(2), acts detailed in Section
			<lb />
			47 are specifically regarded as a ground for defence as opposed to Section
			<lb />
			107A. This intent, not to make Section 107A subservient to Section 48,
			<lb />
			cannot be overlooked and nullified by a patentee to label it as nothing but a
			<lb />
			defense and a &quot;proviso&quot; to Section 48.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			44.
			<lb />
			It was urged that a known principle of law is that any party who
			<lb />
			asserts a specific claim is required under law to establish/prove it. Even
			<lb />
			under Section 107A of the Act, save cases which deal with process patents,
			<lb />
			the onus to establish infringement, both at the prima facie stage and at the
			<lb />
			final stage, with clear and cogent evidence is on a patentee, and not on the
			<lb />
			defendant or for that matter a duty of the court, especially as patents rights
			<lb />
			are private rights. This is reaffirmed upon perusal of Section 106 of Act,
			<lb />
			which deals with power of courts to grant relief in cases of groundless
			<lb />
			threats of infringement proceedings wherein again it is for the patentee to
			<lb />
			prove that &quot;…..the acts in respect of which the proceedings were threatened
			<lb />
			constitute or, if done, would constitute, an infringement of a patent.&apos; If,
			<lb />
			therefore, a third party claims that on the basis of its regulatory use, a
			<lb />
			patentee is groundlessly threatening to sue such party, then, the patentee has
			<lb />
			establish that the acts of the third party constitute commercial exploitation
			<lb />
			and is outside the purview of section 107A i.e. regulatory use. If, and only if
			<lb />
			a patentee can succeed in proving that a complained act results in
			<lb />
			commercial use or exploitation, can a regulatory use defence fail. The mere
			<lb />
			fact that a pharmaceutical product/drug is developed into a finished
			<lb />
			formulation form and is sold in India or abroad for the purpose of procuring
			<lb />
			regulatory approval is however, insufficient to establish infringement; a
			<lb />
			plaintiff patentee has to establish how the act complained of falls within the
			<lb />
			purview of Section 48 due to which a suit for infringement is maintainable.
			<lb />
			This is especially important because Section 107A permits third parties to
			<lb />
			carry out trade by way of -any act of making, constructing, using, selling or
			<lb />
			importing a patented invention‖ thereby allowing such parties to profit with
			<lb />
			the only limitation being that such trade is be solely for uses reasonably
			<lb />
			related to the development and submission of information required under
			<lb />
			any law for the time being in force, in India, or in a country other than
			<lb />
			India, that regulates the manufacture, construction, use, sole or import of
			<lb />
			any product.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			45.
			<lb />
			Ms. Chaudhary supported and reiterated the submissions made by
			<lb />
			Mr. Grover that interpretation of Section 107A cannot be cut down by
			<lb />
			Section 48. It was submitted that to establish infringement, the threshold is
			<lb />
			nothing short of proving that the use is commercial. Furthermore, it was
			<lb />
			argued that exports are not per se infringement and submitted that a bare
			<lb />
			perusal of Section 107A reveals that its application and operation travels
			<lb />
			beyond India especially in view of the fact that it seeks to allow certain acts
			<lb />
			for -uses reasonably related to the development and submission of
			<lb />
			information required under any law for the time being in force, in India, or
			<lb />
			in a country other than India...‖. The plain words of the statute itself
			<lb />
			provides for acts to be conducted outside India. It is a well settled principle
			<lb />
			of law that words of a statute must be given their plain literal meaning.
			<lb />
			Bayer&quot;s interpretation, however, would result in a dichotomy whereby the
			<lb />
			term &apos;selling&apos; would be interpreted as the selling of the &apos;product&apos; itself in
			<lb />
			India, but for the purposes of seeking regulatory approvals outside India, it
			<lb />
			would be interpreted as selling of &apos;information&apos;. Such dichotomy was never
			<lb />
			the intention of the legislature, as is evident from a plain literal interpretation
			<lb />
			of Section 107A, and it is not open to Bayer to bring in such a dichotomy by
			<lb />
			way of judicial interpretation. It was urged that therefore, no territorial
			<lb />
			restriction ought to be imposed upon the term &quot;sale&quot; contained in Section
			<lb />
			107A as it is being sought to be done by Bayer by way of judicial
			<lb />
			interpretation, which in effect amounts to seeking legislative enactment.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			46.
			<lb />
			It was argued that if one applies a purposive interpretation to the
			<lb />
			present case, the fact that other nations/countries have expressly or
			<lb />
			specifically provided for a bar to export for seeking regulatory approvals in
			<lb />
			other countries as is the case in the USA and Australia, supports Alembic&apos;s
			<lb />
			contention that it was never the intention of the Act to prevent export of
			<lb />
			patented invention for regulatory purposes under section 107A of the Act.
			<lb />
			Further, even though the application of the Bolar Provision in the USA
			<lb />
			under Section 35 U. S. C. § 271 (e) (1) is limited only to the US, yet, in
			<lb />
			Intermedics Inc (supra), export of patented product was allowed and held to
			<lb />
			be non-infringing in nature as it was for the purpose of conducting tests and
			<lb />
			procuring requisite data which was exclusively used to seek regulatory
			<lb />
			approval in the USA. Accordingly, in view of the fact that Section 107A
			<lb />
			specifically provides for uses reasonably related to seeking regulatory
			<lb />
			approval in countries other than India, it cannot be argued that Section 107A
			<lb />
			prohibits exports.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			47.
			<lb />
			Bayer&quot;s reliance on the &apos;Notes on Clause&apos; of the Patents (Second
			<lb />
			amendment) Bill, 1999 which first sought to introduce section 107A, was
			<lb />
			contested and it was submitted that the Joint Parliamentary Committee made
			<lb />
			numerous changes to the provision, which is evident from a bare perusal of
			<lb />
			the final provision which was enacted as also the Notes on Clauses detailed
			<lb />
			in the Joint Parliamentary Committee Report of the 1999 Bill. Therefore, it
			<lb />
			is evident that the scope of the said Section was expanded beyond India and
			<lb />
			the limitation of only the Indian market were specifically removed.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			48.
			<lb />
			Ms. Chaudhary urged that a look at Section 107A reveals that it does
			<lb />
			not impose any restriction on the quantity which can be made, constructed,
			<lb />
			used, sold or imported as long as all such quantity is utilized solely for uses
			<lb />
			reasonably related to development and submission of information required
			<lb />
			under any law for the time being in force in India or in a country other than
			<lb />
			India that regulates the manufacture, construction, use, sale or import of any
			<lb />
			product. Different countries have different regulatory regimes and
			<lb />
			requirements whereby the data required to be submitted at the time of
			<lb />
			seeking any regulatory approval varies from region to region based on local
			<lb />
			testing required which may vary anywhere from redoing complete clinical
			<lb />
			trials or certain phases of it. For example, in India, Phase III clinical trials
			<lb />
			have to be undertaken in India under the Drugs and Cosmetics Act, 1940,
			<lb />
			bioavailability/bio equivalent studies, stability data which covers both
			<lb />
			accelerated and real time data are to be performed in India. Such testing
			<lb />
			requires different quantities depending on the drug, the dosage, the mode of
			<lb />
			delivery (tablets, capsules, injection, Intravenous Therapy etc.) and may vary
			<lb />
			from, for example, one pilot scale batch of 100,000 tablets to 3 pilot scale
			<lb />
			batches of 100,000 tablets. These, coupled with the fact that an entity may
			<lb />
			have multiple clients in a country, who would want to procure the patented
			<lb />
			product for testing, establishes that placing any restriction on the quantity to
			<lb />
			be used under Section 107A of the Act would result in impinging upon the
			<lb />
			fundamental rights of drug makers/manufacturers in complete contravention
			<lb />
			of the legislative intent behind incorporating Section 107A of the Act. It is
			<lb />
			urged that it is a well settled principle of law that it is not open for a party to
			<lb />
			seek legislative enactments from a court of law under the guise of judicial
			<lb />
			interpretation. Accordingly, it is not open for the court to put in multiple
			<lb />
			restrictions while interpreting Section 107A as is sought by Bayer inasmuch
			<lb />
			as the entire exercise under the present litigation is: (a) to impose
			<lb />
			unreasonable restrictions on export under Section 107A to the effect of
			<lb />
			completely excluding it from the purview of the said provision (b) to create
			<lb />
			an automatic presumption of infringement immediately upon any use, sale or
			<lb />
			export of patented product even though the same is declared to be for
			<lb />
			regulatory purposes and there is nothing to prove otherwise, so as to
			<lb />
			completely shift the onus of infringement from the plaintiff to the defendant.
			<lb />
			Relevant provisions of the Patents Act:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			49.
			<lb />
			Sections 48, 84, 92A, 107 and 107A of the Act read as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-48. Rights of patentees
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Subject to the other provisions contained in this Act and the
			<lb />
			conditions specified in section 47, a patent granted under this
			<lb />
			Act shall confer upon the patentee-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a) where the subject matter of the patent is a product, the
			<lb />
			exclusive right to prevent third parties, who do not have his
			<lb />
			consent, from the act of making, using, offering for sale, selling
			<lb />
			or importing for those purposes that product in India:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b) where the subject matter of the patent is a process the
			<lb />
			exclusive right to prevent third parties, who do not have his
			<lb />
			consent, from the act of using that process, and from the act of
			<lb />
			using, offering for sale, selling or importing for those purposes
			<lb />
			the product obtained directly by that process in India:‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			XXXXXX
			<lb />
			XXXXXX
			<lb />
			XXXXXX
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			84. Compulsory licences
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(1) At any time after the expiration of three years from the date
			<lb />
			of the 1 [grant] of a patent, any person interested may make an
			<lb />
			application to the Controller for grant of compulsory licence on
			<lb />
			patent on any of the following grounds, namely:-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a) that the reasonable requirements of the public with
			<lb />
			respect to the patented invention have not been satisfied,
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b) that the patented invention is not available to the
			<lb />
			public at a reasonably affordable price, or
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(c) that the patented invention is not worked in the
			<lb />
			territory of India.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(2) An application under this section may be made by any
			<lb />
			person notwithstanding that he is already the holder of a
			<lb />
			licence under the patent and no person shall be estopped from
			<lb />
			alleging that the reasonable requirements of the public with
			<lb />
			respect to the patented invention are not satisfied or that the
			<lb />
			patented invention is not worked in the territory of India or that
			<lb />
			the patented invention is not available to the public at a
			<lb />
			reasonably affordable price by reason of any admission made
			<lb />
			by him, whether in such a licence or otherwise or by reason of
			<lb />
			his
			<lb />
			having
			<lb />
			accepted
			<lb />
			such
			<lb />
			a
			<lb />
			licence.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(3) Every application under sub-section (1) shall contain a
			<lb />
			statement setting out the nature of the applicant&apos;s interest
			<lb />
			together with such particulars as may be prescribed and the
			<lb />
			facts upon which the application is based.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(4) The Controller, if satisfied that the reasonable requirements
			<lb />
			of the public with respect to the patented invention have not
			<lb />
			been satisfied or that the patented invention is not worked in the
			<lb />
			territory of India or that the patented invention is not available
			<lb />
			to the public at a reasonably price, may grant a licence upon
			<lb />
			such terms as he may deem fit.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(5) Where the Controller directs the patentee to grant a licence
			<lb />
			he may, as incidental thereto, exercise the powers set out in
			<lb />
			section 88.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(6) In considering the application filed under this section, the
			<lb />
			Controller shall take into account,-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(i) the nature of the invention, the time which has elapsed since
			<lb />
			the sealing of the patent and the measures already taken by the
			<lb />
			patentee or any licensee to make full use of the invention;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(jj) the ability of the applicant to work the invention to the
			<lb />
			public advantage;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) the capacity of the applicant to undertake the risk in
			<lb />
			providing capital and working the invention, if the application
			<lb />
			were granted;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iv) as to whether the applicant has made efforts to obtain a
			<lb />
			licence from the patentee on reasonable terms and conditions
			<lb />
			and such efforts have not been successful within a reasonable
			<lb />
			period as the Controller may deem fit: PROVIDED that this
			<lb />
			clause shall not be applicable in case of national emergency or
			<lb />
			other circumstances of extreme urgency or in case of public
			<lb />
			non-commercial use or on establishment of a ground of anti-
			<lb />
			competitive practices adopted by the patentee, but shall not be
			<lb />
			required to take into account matters subsequent to the making
			<lb />
			of the application.
			<lb />
			[Explanation : For the purposes of clause (iv), &quot;reasonable
			<lb />
			period&quot; shall be construed as a period not ordinarily exceeding
			<lb />
			a period of six months.]
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(7) For the purposes of this Chapter, the reasonable
			<lb />
			requirements of the public shall be deemed not to have been
			<lb />
			satisfied-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a) if, by reason of the refusal of the patentee to grant a licence
			<lb />
			or licences on reasonable terms,-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(i) an existing trade or industry or the development thereof or
			<lb />
			the establishment of any new trade or industry in India or the
			<lb />
			trade or industry in India or the trade or industry of any person
			<lb />
			or class of persons trading or manufacturing in India is
			<lb />
			prejudiced; or (ii) the demand for the patented article has not
			<lb />
			been met to an adequate extent or on reasonable terms; or
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) a market for export of the patented article manufactured in
			<lb />
			India is not being supplied or developed; or
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iv) the establishment or development of commercial activities
			<lb />
			in India is prejudiced; or
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b) if, by reason of conditions imposed by the patentee upon the
			<lb />
			grant of licences under the patent or upon the purchase, hire or
			<lb />
			use of the patented article or process, the manufacture, use or
			<lb />
			sale of materials not protected by the patent, or the
			<lb />
			establishment or development of any trade or industry in India,
			<lb />
			is prejudiced; or
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(c) if the patentee imposes a condition upon the grant of
			<lb />
			licences under the patent to provide exclusive grant back,
			<lb />
			prevention to challenges to the validity of patent or coercive
			<lb />
			package licensing; or
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(d) if the patented invention is not being worked in the territory
			<lb />
			of India on a commercial scale to an adequate extent or is not
			<lb />
			being so worked to the fullest extent that is reasonably
			<lb />
			practicable; or
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(e) if the working of the patented invention in the territory of
			<lb />
			India on a commercial scale is being prevented or hindered by
			<lb />
			the importation from abroad of the patented article by-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(i) the patentee or persons claiming under him; or
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii) persons directly or indirectly purchasing from him;
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) other persons against whom the patentee is not
			<lb />
			taking or has not taken proceedingsfor infringement.
			<lb />
			XXXXXX
			<lb />
			XXXXXX
			<lb />
			XXXXXX
			<lb />
			90
			<lb />
			Terms and conditions of compulsory licences. -
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(1) In settling the terms and conditions of a licence under
			<lb />
			section 84, the Controller shall endeavour to secure-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(i) that the royalty and other remuneration, if any, reserved to
			<lb />
			the patentee or other person beneficially entitled to the patent,
			<lb />
			is reasonable, having regard to the nature of the invention, the
			<lb />
			expenditure incurred by the patentee in making the invention or
			<lb />
			in developing it and obtaining a patent and keeping it in force
			<lb />
			and other relevant factors;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii) that the patented invention is worked to the fullest extent by
			<lb />
			the person to whom the licence is granted and with reasonable
			<lb />
			profit to him;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) that the patented articles are made available to the public
			<lb />
			at reasonably affordable prices;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iv) that the licence granted is a non-exclusive licence;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(v) that the right of the licensee is non-assignable;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(vi) that the licence is for the balance term of the patent unless
			<lb />
			a shorter term is consistent with public interest;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			179 [(vii) that the licence is granted with a predominant purpose
			<lb />
			of supply in the Indian market and that the licensee may also
			<lb />
			export the patented product, if need be in accordance with the
			<lb />
			provisions of sub-clause (iii) of clause (a) of sub-section (7) of
			<lb />
			section 84;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(viii) that in the case of semi-conductor technology, the licence
			<lb />
			granted is to work the invention for public non-commercial use;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ix) that in case the licence is granted to remedy a practice
			<lb />
			determined after judicial or administrative process to be anti-
			<lb />
			competitive, the licensee shall be permitted to export the
			<lb />
			patented product, if need be.]
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(2) No licence granted by the Controller shall authorise the
			<lb />
			licensee to import the patented article or an article or
			<lb />
			substance made by a patented process from abroad where such
			<lb />
			importation would, but for such authorisation, constitute an
			<lb />
			infringement of the rights of the patentee.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(3) Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (2), the
			<lb />
			Central Government may, if in its opinion it is necessary so to
			<lb />
			do, in the public interest, direct the Controller at any time to
			<lb />
			authorise any licensee in respect of a patent to import the
			<lb />
			patented article or an article or substance made by a patented
			<lb />
			process from abroad (subject to such conditions as it considers
			<lb />
			necessary to impose relating among other matters to the royalty
			<lb />
			and other remuneration, if any, payable to the patentee, the
			<lb />
			quantum of import, the sale price of the imported article and
			<lb />
			the period of importation), and thereupon the Controller shall
			<lb />
			give effect to the directions.
			<lb />
			XXXXXX
			<lb />
			XXXXXX
			<lb />
			XXXXXX
			<lb />
			92A Compulsory licence for export of patented pharmaceutical
			<lb />
			products
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			certain
			<lb />
			exceptional
			<lb />
			circumstances.
			<lb />
			-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(1) Compulsory licence shall be available for manufacture and
			<lb />
			export of patented pharmaceutical products to any country
			<lb />
			having insufficient or no manufacturing capacity in the
			<lb />
			pharmaceutical sector for the concerned product to address
			<lb />
			public health problems, provided compulsory licence has been
			<lb />
			granted by such country or such country has, by notification or
			<lb />
			otherwise, allowed importation of the patented pharmaceutical
			<lb />
			products from India.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(2) The Controller shall, on receipt of an application in the
			<lb />
			prescribed manner, grant a compulsory licence solely for
			<lb />
			manufacture and export of the concerned pharmaceutical
			<lb />
			product to such country under such terms and conditions as
			<lb />
			may be specified and published by him.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(3) The provisions of sub-sections (1) and (2) shall be without
			<lb />
			prejudice to the extent to which pharmaceutical products
			<lb />
			produced under a compulsory license can be exported under
			<lb />
			any other provision of this Act. Explanation. -For the purposes
			<lb />
			of this section, &apos;pharmaceutical products&apos; means any patented
			<lb />
			product, or product manufactured through a patented process,
			<lb />
			of the pharmaceutical sector needed to address public health
			<lb />
			problems and shall be inclusive of ingredients necessary for
			<lb />
			their manufacture and diagnostic kits required for their use.
			<lb />
			XXXXXX
			<lb />
			XXXXXX
			<lb />
			XXXXXX
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			107. Defences, etc ., in suits for infringement. -
			<lb />
			(1) In any suit for infringement of a patent every ground on
			<lb />
			which it may be revoked under section 64 shall be available as
			<lb />
			a ground for defence.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(2) In any suit for infringement of a patent by the making, using
			<lb />
			or importation of any machine, apparatus or other article or by
			<lb />
			the using of any process or by the importation, use or
			<lb />
			distribution or any medicine or drug, it shall be a ground for
			<lb />
			defence that such making, using, importation or distribution is
			<lb />
			in accordance with any one or more of the conditions specified
			<lb />
			in section 47.
			<lb />
			107A Certain acts not to be considered as infringement. -For
			<lb />
			the purposes of this Act,-
			<lb />
			(a) any act of making, constructing, 197 [using, selling or
			<lb />
			importing] a patented invention solely for uses reasonably
			<lb />
			related to the development and submission of information
			<lb />
			required under any law for the time being in force, in India, or
			<lb />
			in a country other than India, that regulates the manufacture,
			<lb />
			construction, 198 [use, sale or import] of any product;
			<lb />
			(b) importation of patented products by any person from a
			<lb />
			person 199 [who is duly authorised under the law to produce and
			<lb />
			sell or distribute the product], shall not be considered as a
			<lb />
			infringement of patent rights.‖
			<lb />
			TRIPS-Relevant provisions
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			50. The relevant TRIPS provisions are extracted below:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;Article 30
			<lb />
			Exceptions to Rights Conferred
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Members may provide limited exceptions to the exclusive
			<lb />
			rights conferred by a patent, provided that such exceptions do
			<lb />
			not unreasonably conflict with a normal exploitation of the
			<lb />
			patent and do not unreasonably prejudice the legitimate
			<lb />
			interests of the patent owner, taking account of the legitimate
			<lb />
			interests of third parties.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Emergence of the research exception
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			51. Much before the evolution of the Bolar doctrine (through the decision
			<lb />
			in Roche) non-commercial, academic research of the art underlying a patent,
			<lb />
			or the determination of the use of the patent, was recognized. Thus, for
			<lb />
			instance in Whittemore v Cutter, 29 F. Cas. 1120, 1121 (No. 17,600) (C.C.D.
			<lb />
			Mass. 1813) Justice Joseph Story articulated the principle as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;[i]t could never have been the intention of the legislature to
			<lb />
			punish a man who constructed such a machine merely for
			<lb />
			philosophical experiments, or for the purpose of ascertaining
			<lb />
			the sufficiency of the machine to produce its described effects.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			52. The next phase in the development of this branch was in Roche where
			<lb />
			the patentee plaintiff Roche Products, Inc. (Roche), a large research-oriented
			<lb />
			pharmaceutical company, wanted the United States district court to enjoin
			<lb />
			Bolar Pharmaceutical Co., Inc. (Bolar), a manufacturer of generic drugs,
			<lb />
			from taking, during the life of a patent, the statutory and regulatory steps
			<lb />
			necessary to market, after the patent expired, a drug equivalent to a patented
			<lb />
			brand name drug. Roche argued that the use of a patented drug for federally
			<lb />
			mandated premarketing tests is a use in violation of the patent laws. The
			<lb />
			district court recognized that the issue in the case was narrow: did limited
			<lb />
			use of a patented drug for testing and investigation strictly related to FDA
			<lb />
			drug approval requirements during the last 6 months of a patent&quot;s term
			<lb />
			constitute a use which, unless licensed, was infringement. The district court
			<lb />
			held that it was not an infringement. The Federal Circuit Appellate court
			<lb />
			reversed the trial court&quot;s order, holding that:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-Bolar may intend to perform &quot;experiments,&quot; but unlicensed
			<lb />
			experiments conducted with a view to the adoption of the
			<lb />
			patented invention to the experimentor&apos;s business is a violation
			<lb />
			of the rights of the patentee to exclude others from using his
			<lb />
			patented invention. It is obvious here that it is a misnomer to
			<lb />
			call the intended use de minimis. It is no trifle in its economic
			<lb />
			effect on the parties even if the quantity used is small. It is no
			<lb />
			dilettante affair such as Justice Story envisioned. We cannot
			<lb />
			construe the experimental use rule so broadly as to allow a
			<lb />
			violation of the patent laws in the guise of &quot;scientific inquiry,&quot;
			<lb />
			when that inquiry has definite, cognizable, and not
			<lb />
			insubstantial commercial purposes.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			53. Soon after this judgment, the US Congress enacted a law permitting
			<lb />
			use of patented products in experiments for the purpose of obtaining Food
			<lb />
			and Drug Administration (FDA) approval [Section 271(e)(1)]. This
			<lb />
			provision, known as the research exemption, consolidated the Bolar research
			<lb />
			exception articulated by the US District Court, which was reversed in the
			<lb />
			Federal Circuit decision. The new provision (Section 271 (e)(i)) reads as
			<lb />
			follows:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-(e) (1)It shall not be an act of infringement to make, use, offer
			<lb />
			to sell , or sell within the United States or import into the
			<lb />
			United States a patented invention (other than a new animal
			<lb />
			drug or veterinary biological product (as those terms are used
			<lb />
			in the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act and the Act
			<lb />
			of March 4, 1913) which is primarily manufactured using
			<lb />
			recombinant DNA, recombinant RNA, hybridoma technology,
			<lb />
			or other processes involving site specific genetic manipulation
			<lb />
			techniques) solely for uses reasonably related to the
			<lb />
			development and submission of information under a Federal
			<lb />
			law which regulates the manufacture, use, or sale of drugs or
			<lb />
			veterinary biological products.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			54. It is noticeable that the provision does not expressly enable
			<lb />
			development and submission of information under a law other than a
			<lb />
			-Federal law which regulates the manufacture, use, or sale of drugs or
			<lb />
			veterinary biological products‖ implying that the use of the patented
			<lb />
			invention in relation to regulatory approval abroad was not authorized. Yet,
			<lb />
			in Intermedics, Ventritex used the clinical trial data obtained under the
			<lb />
			protection of Section 271(e)(1) to solicit money to fund further clinical trials
			<lb />
			after the patent term expired; Ventritex also used this data to obtain patent
			<lb />
			rights in other countries. The court noted that an otherwise infringing
			<lb />
			activity is exempt if:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-It [would] have been reasonable, objectively, for a party in
			<lb />
			defendant&apos;s situation to believe that there was a decent prospect
			<lb />
			that the &quot;use&quot; in question would contribute (relatively directly)
			<lb />
			to the generation of kinds of information that was likely to be
			<lb />
			relevant in the processes by which the FDA would decide
			<lb />
			whether to approve the product.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			55. The court, therefore, held that Ventritex&apos;s uses did not infringe the
			<lb />
			patent, and the Federal Circuit affirmed the district court&apos;s decision,
			<lb />
			suggesting that Congress intended that Section271(e)(1) be used to shelter
			<lb />
			all products seeking FDA approval, regardless of their projected
			<lb />
			commercialization date.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			56. In Merck KGaA v. Integra Lifesciences Ltd., 545 U.S. 193, 200
			<lb />
			(2005), the US Supreme Court had the occasion to consider the experimental
			<lb />
			exception. Integra owned several patents, including a &quot;short tri-peptide
			<lb />
			segment of fibronectin&quot; with the amino acid sequence Arg-Gly-Arg, known
			<lb />
			as the RGD peptide. The defendant, Merck hired one Dr. Cheresh, a scientist
			<lb />
			at a research institute, to investigate compounds with the same receptor
			<lb />
			blocking capability as the RGD peptides. Integra offered to license their
			<lb />
			patents to Merck, which declined the offer. Integra sued Merck, Scripps, and
			<lb />
			Dr. Cheresh for patent infringement. The district court rejected the
			<lb />
			defendant&quot;s research exception based argument. This ruling was affirmed by
			<lb />
			the Federal Circuit court, which held that:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;the Scripps work sponsored by Merck was not clinical testing
			<lb />
			to supply information to the FDA, but only general biomedical
			<lb />
			research to identify new pharmaceutical compounds.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			57. The US Supreme Court judgment unanimously reversed the Federal
			<lb />
			Circuit judgment and disapproved the narrow interpretation of the
			<lb />
			experimental use provision, stating that:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;as an initial matter, we think it apparent from the statutory text
			<lb />
			that §271(e)(1)&apos;s exemption from infringement extends to all
			<lb />
			uses of patented inventions that are reasonably related to the
			<lb />
			development and submission of any information under the
			<lb />
			FDCA.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			58. The Supreme Court further said
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;this [information] necessarily includes preclinical studies of
			<lb />
			patented compounds that are appropriate for submission to the
			<lb />
			FDA in the regulatory process.&quot;
			<lb />
			And that to construe § 271(e)(1) what the Federal Circuit did:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;is effectively to limit assurance of exemption to the activities
			<lb />
			necessary to seek approval of a generic drug.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			59. In Japan, acts relating to the marketing approval of pharma products
			<lb />
			were deemed by the Supreme Court covered by its Patents law&quot;s
			<lb />
			experimentation exception. In a unanimous decision, the court in Ono
			<lb />
			Pharmaceuticals Co., Ltd. v Kyoto Pharmaceutical Industries, Ltd 1999 (30)
			<lb />
			IIC 448, held that tests during the patent term for obtaining data needed for
			<lb />
			regulatory approval were not infringing acts, under section 69(1) of the
			<lb />
			Japanese Patent law.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			60. In the UK, the experimental use exception followed an unusual
			<lb />
			trajectory of development. The experimental use exemption was inserted by
			<lb />
			Section 60(5)(b) of the Patents Act 1977. This is still in force and it applies
			<lb />
			to all patent subject matter, including medicines, medical devices and
			<lb />
			agrochemicals. In Monsanto v Stauffer 1985 RPC 515, the defendants
			<lb />
			sought the modification to an injunction that had been ordered against the
			<lb />
			manufacture and sale of their Touchdown herbicide for agricultural use. The
			<lb />
			Court of Appeal permitted limited modifications to the injunction so that it
			<lb />
			did not prevent the defendants from conducting experiments on Touchdown
			<lb />
			in laboratories or glasshouses in the UK to find out more about it. But the
			<lb />
			court did not permit field trials for the purpose of commercial clearance from
			<lb />
			the Pesticides Safety Precautions Scheme and approval from the Agricultural
			<lb />
			Chemicals Approval Scheme (that existed under legislation at the time).
			<lb />
			Explaining, where the line is to be drawn between exempted and non-
			<lb />
			exempted experiments under the Original Experimental Use Exemption, the
			<lb />
			court stated:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-Trials
			<lb />
			carried
			<lb />
			out
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			order
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			discover
			<lb />
			something unknown, or to test an hypothesis, or even in
			<lb />
			order to find out whether something which is known to
			<lb />
			work in specific conditions, e.g. of soil or weather, will
			<lb />
			work in different conditions can fairly … be regarded as
			<lb />
			experiments. But trials carried out in order to demonstrate
			<lb />
			to a third party that a product works or, in order to amass
			<lb />
			information to satisfy a third party, whether a customer or
			<lb />
			a [regulatory] body such as the PSPS or ACAS, that the
			<lb />
			product works as its maker claims are not to be regarded
			<lb />
			as acts done for &apos;experimental purposes&apos;‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			61. Exempted experiments therefore, are those that generate new
			<lb />
			knowledge, but not those that verifying existing knowledge, for example for
			<lb />
			getting regulatory clearance. The later decision of the Court of Appeal in
			<lb />
			Auchinclossv Agricultural and Veterinary Supplies and Others [1999]
			<lb />
			RPC 397 is in line with this, as it holds that making and experimenting with
			<lb />
			a patented invention merely for the purposes of gaining official approval
			<lb />
			would not fall within the Original Experimental Use Exemption. The facts of
			<lb />
			the Auchincloss case again concern agrochemicals: a sample of a dry water-
			<lb />
			soluble biocidal composition sent by the defendant to MAFF, the old
			<lb />
			Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food. Here, the Court of Appeal held
			<lb />
			that supplying a sample to MAFF in order to obtain official approval rather
			<lb />
			than to discover something unknown or to test a hypothesis, was not covered
			<lb />
			by the exemption. The UK courts thus distinguish between application of the
			<lb />
			experimental use exemption to activity conducted for the purpose of
			<lb />
			discovering something new (about the subject matter of the invention), and
			<lb />
			mere verification of what is already known. If trials and tests on a substance
			<lb />
			for regulatory approval of that substance are not discovering something new,
			<lb />
			the exemption is inapplicable. It is accepted that this is the case as regards
			<lb />
			bioequivalence studies for an abridged application -they cannot be
			<lb />
			protected; there is also lack of clarity that full clinical trials would be
			<lb />
			protected.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			62. The new exemption was enacted in the wake of concerns that the UK
			<lb />
			was losing opportunities to conduct work in support of getting marketing
			<lb />
			authorizations, such as trials, because of the limited UK Bolar Exemption. It
			<lb />
			is therefore concerned specifically with medicinal products. This new
			<lb />
			Exemption came into force on 01.10.2014, by way of addition to the
			<lb />
			Original Exemption. However, as stated above, the Original Experimental
			<lb />
			Use Exemption and the Bolar Exemption, remain intact. A medicinal product
			<lb />
			assessment is defined as
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;any testing, course of testing or other activity undertaken with
			<lb />
			a view to providing data for purposes which include the
			<lb />
			following:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 obtaining or varying an authorisation to sell or supply,
			<lb />
			or offer to sell or supply, a medicinal product (whether
			<lb />
			in the United Kingdom or elsewhere);
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 complying with any regulatory requirement imposed
			<lb />
			(whether in the United Kingdom or elsewhere) in
			<lb />
			relation to such an authorisation;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 enabling a government or public authority (whether in
			<lb />
			the United Kingdom or elsewhere), or a person
			<lb />
			(whether in the United Kingdom or elsewhere) with
			<lb />
			functions of-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 providing health care on behalf of such a government
			<lb />
			or public authority,
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			63. Therefore, in addition to activities covered by the Bolar Exemption,
			<lb />
			the preparation and running of clinical trials on innovative drugs for
			<lb />
			marketing authorisation are also exempt. Furthermore, work undertaken in
			<lb />
			the UK in support of a regulatory filing in a country outside of the EU is also
			<lb />
			now covered.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			64. The statutory exemption to infringement under Canadian law is
			<lb />
			embodied in Section 55.2(1) of its Patent Act which provides that:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-It is not an infringement of a patent for any person to
			<lb />
			make, construct, use or sell the patented invention solely
			<lb />
			for uses reasonably related to the development and
			<lb />
			submission of information required under any law of
			<lb />
			Canada, a province or a country other than Canada that
			<lb />
			regulates the manufacture, construction, use or sale of any
			<lb />
			product.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			65. This provision concerns activities relating to the development and
			<lb />
			submission of information required by a regulatory body. The Canadian
			<lb />
			provision is agnostic and sector neutral, in that it concerns with regulatory
			<lb />
			approval for inventions in all areas of technology and is not restricted to
			<lb />
			pharmaceuticals. The disputes before the Canadian courts are primarily in
			<lb />
			the pharmaceutical area, most often in the context of generic manufacturers
			<lb />
			performing tests in respect of a patented drug. Also, this provision relates to
			<lb />
			information that may be required by a regulatory body anywhere (and not
			<lb />
			just in Canada).
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			66. A leading Canadian decision, Merck et al. v. Apotex (2006) FCA
			<lb />
			323, (Federal Court of Appeal), was in the context of a generic drug
			<lb />
			development. The court held that the defendant prepared and tested the
			<lb />
			patented Lisinopril drug for the purposes of filing abbreviated new drug
			<lb />
			submissions necessary to sell Lisinopril in Canada and the USA. Some of
			<lb />
			the data was referenced in Apotex&apos;s submissions, directed to that purpose.
			<lb />
			Apotex also had stored samples in the event that they were required for
			<lb />
			future reference by the government. The court held that Section 55.2(1) was
			<lb />
			broad enough to exempt such generic drug development activities from
			<lb />
			infringement. The safe-harbour provision can protect activities reasonably
			<lb />
			related to development and submission of information required by law,
			<lb />
			either before or after market approval. The court also found that Apotex&apos;s
			<lb />
			use of Lisinopril in ongoing research and development of alternate
			<lb />
			formulations and alternate techniques for tablet-making fell within
			<lb />
			the common law exemption to infringement. This was because they did not
			<lb />
			proceed beyond an experimental (testing) phase and did not take steps to
			<lb />
			manufacture, promote and sell the product.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			67. In the opinion of the court, the course of the experimental exception-
			<lb />
			both before and after the TRIPS has shown the adoption, generally of a
			<lb />
			broad approach, to permit use of all kinds. Broadly, the courts&quot; approach has
			<lb />
			been not to enjoin or prohibit purely experimental or scientific activity, as
			<lb />
			long as it does not have any primary commercial undertones.
			<lb />
			Legislative history of Section 107A
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			68. Curiously, predating Section 107A the Indian Parliament had enacted
			<lb />
			a research exception, Section 47 which stated, inter alia,[by Section 47 (3)]
			<lb />
			that:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;47. Grant of patents to be subject to certain conditions.-The
			<lb />
			grant of a patent under this Act shall be subject to the condition
			<lb />
			that-
			<lb />
			*****
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(3) any machine, apparatus or other article in respect of which
			<lb />
			the patent is granted or any article made by the use of the
			<lb />
			process in respect of which the patent is granted, may be made
			<lb />
			or used, and any process in respect of which the patent is
			<lb />
			granted may be used, by any person, or the purpose merely of
			<lb />
			experiment or research including the imparting of instructions
			<lb />
			to pupils…‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			69. This provision has been retained in the statute book. This was
			<lb />
			suggested by the committee, constituted in 1957, under the chairmanship of
			<lb />
			Justice N. Rajagopala Ayyangar to take a fresh look at patent law to suggest
			<lb />
			the best way to best sub-serve the contemporary needs of India. Justice
			<lb />
			Ayyangar&quot;s Report on Patent Law Revision of September 1959 was the basis
			<lb />
			of the Patents Act, 1970. The report noticed that the right of researchers, to
			<lb />
			use the invention -whether it be an article or a process -for the purposes of
			<lb />
			carrying out experiments -in the course of research, as distinguished from
			<lb />
			use for a commercial purpose is one matter in connection with the right of
			<lb />
			patentees had to be clarified. In this connection, while taking note of the
			<lb />
			uncertainty of the law on this topic in the U.K., Justice Ayyangar took the
			<lb />
			view that:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;I consider it desirable that the law should specifically exempt
			<lb />
			use of the patented articles or processes or the use of articles or
			<lb />
			products made by the use of the patented process or patented
			<lb />
			machine or apparatus for experimental purposes from being
			<lb />
			actionable as an infringement.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			70. The amendment of 1999 to the Patents Act was pre-dated by a report
			<lb />
			of the Joint Parliamentary Committee. It recommended introduction of a
			<lb />
			Bolar exemption provision. The report explained the reason for Clause 51
			<lb />
			(which was to be the amendment):
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-Clause 51: this clause seeks to insert a new Section 107A in
			<lb />
			the principal Act, relating to certain acts which are not to be
			<lb />
			considered as infringement. This provision has been made to
			<lb />
			ensure prompt availability of products, particularly generic
			<lb />
			drugs, immediately after the expiry of the term of the patent.
			<lb />
			The amendment in this clause has been made to make a
			<lb />
			provision in consonance with the Bolar Provisions at the global
			<lb />
			level. The other amendment in this clause is correction of a
			<lb />
			typographical error.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			71. The Notes on clauses, amending the Act, through the Bill reads as
			<lb />
			follows:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;this clause seeks to insert a new section 107A in the Act,
			<lb />
			relating to certain acts which are not to be considered
			<lb />
			infringements. It is proposed that the act of making or using a
			<lb />
			patented product for the purpose of development and
			<lb />
			submission of information to a regulatory authority regulating
			<lb />
			marketing approval of the product, shall not constitute an
			<lb />
			infringement. This provision is proposed to ensure that generic
			<lb />
			drug should be available in Indian market immediately after the
			<lb />
			expiry of the term of the concerned patents.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			72. The Patents (Second Amendment) Bill, 1999 reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-After section 107 of the principal Act. the following section
			<lb />
			shall be inserted, namely:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Clause 51. After section 107 of the principal act, the following
			<lb />
			section shall be inserted, namely
			<lb />
			-107A For the purposes of this Act,-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a)
			<lb />
			Any act of making or using a patented invention within
			<lb />
			three years before the expiry of the term of the patent by any
			<lb />
			person for the purpose of development and submission of the
			<lb />
			information to any regulatory authority responsible for grant of
			<lb />
			marketing approval for the product of invention.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			73. In the Statement of Objects and Reasons (introducing the Amending
			<lb />
			Act), it was stated that:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-4. Some of the salient features of the Bill are….
			<lb />
			-(h) to make a provision enabling persons other than patent
			<lb />
			holder to obtain marketing approval from the appropriate
			<lb />
			regulatory authorities within three years before the expiration
			<lb />
			of the term of the patent‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			74. Eventually, the Patents Amendment Act of 2002 was enacted; it stated
			<lb />
			as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-44. After section 107 of the Principal Act, the following
			<lb />
			section shall be inserted namely,
			<lb />
			107A: For the purposes of this Act
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a) Any act of making, constructing, using or selling a patented
			<lb />
			invention solely for uses reasonably related to the development
			<lb />
			and submission of information required under any law for the
			<lb />
			time being in force, in India or in a country other than India,
			<lb />
			that regulates the manufacture, construction, use or sale of any
			<lb />
			product‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			75. The Patent (Amendment) Bill, 2003 proposed insertion of the
			<lb />
			expression &quot;import&quot; as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-107A: For the purposes of this Act
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a) any act of making, constructing, using selling or importing
			<lb />
			a patented invention solely for uses reasonably related to the
			<lb />
			development and submission of information required under any
			<lb />
			law for the time being in force, in India or in a country other
			<lb />
			than India, that regulates the manufacture, construction, use or
			<lb />
			sale of any product‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			76. Eventually, the Patents Amendment Act, 2005 which proposed the
			<lb />
			amendment in its present form, was enacted; it reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-107A: For the purposes of this Act
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a) any act of making, constructing, using selling or importing a
			<lb />
			patented invention solely for uses reasonably related to the
			<lb />
			development and submission of information required under any
			<lb />
			law for the time being in force, in India or in a country other
			<lb />
			than India, that regulates the manufacture, construction, use or
			<lb />
			sale or import of any product‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			77. These stages in the amendment of the Act and the introduction of
			<lb />
			India&quot;s Bolar exemption demonstrate that Parliament took a careful and
			<lb />
			nuanced view of the matter; it also had the benefit of provisions enacted in
			<lb />
			other countries, including the US and Canadian law.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			A Interpretation of &quot;sale&quot; and whether it encompasses &quot;exports&quot;
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			78. Rival arguments were addressed with respect to the expression &quot;sale&quot;
			<lb />
			and whether it comprehends &quot;export&quot;. Bayer contended that the use of &quot;sale&quot;
			<lb />
			along with &quot;import&quot; excluded the term &quot;export&quot; from the meaning of the
			<lb />
			expression &quot;sale&quot; which is otherwise wide. In aid of this, it was contended
			<lb />
			that Section 84 and Section 92A used the term &quot;export&quot; expressly and that,
			<lb />
			given this clear internal clue from the statute, the court should not accept
			<lb />
			Natco&quot;s contention that an export transaction is covered by sale. According
			<lb />
			to Bayer, the learned single judge erred in writing into the statute an
			<lb />
			expression which was omitted by resorting to an over liberal interpretation of
			<lb />
			a causus omissius. A third argument made was that only those extra-
			<lb />
			territorial aspects which have an impact or nexus with India and are enacted
			<lb />
			with the intent of creating some benefit for India would fall within the
			<lb />
			constitutionally sanctioned idea of legislative competence; since none can be
			<lb />
			said to accrue to India, the term &quot;export&quot; should not be read into the
			<lb />
			expression &quot;sell&quot;. Lastly it was argued that Section 107A is in the nature of a
			<lb />
			proviso or exception to Section 48, which defines the content and rights of a
			<lb />
			patentee and that the court should, consistent with the interpretation of any
			<lb />
			proviso, ensure that it is kept within the bounds of what is sought to be
			<lb />
			excepted. Natco disputed each of these contentions, urging that &quot;sell&quot; should
			<lb />
			not be juxtaposed with other provisions which expressly talk of export and
			<lb />
			that the court should consider the context of Section 84 and Section 92A the
			<lb />
			underlying purposes of which are entirely different from Section 107A. It
			<lb />
			was highlighted that the references to &quot;other country&quot; in Section 107A
			<lb />
			would be meaningless if export is not construed to be part of &quot;sell&quot; and that
			<lb />
			an export is but a species of sale. Also, Natco relied on the term &quot;construct&quot;
			<lb />
			occurring in Section 107A and stated that the use of &quot;sell&quot; &quot;import&quot; and
			<lb />
			&quot;construct&quot; permit all range of transactions and uses covered by the
			<lb />
			provision. It was contended that considerations of extra territorial impact of
			<lb />
			any provision do not arise. Lastly it was urged that Section 107A -in its
			<lb />
			placement and having regard to its legislative history is clearly not an
			<lb />
			exception or proviso, but a special provision which must be given full
			<lb />
			meaning and effect.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			79. Two clear strands of reasoning have prevailed in various judgments of
			<lb />
			the Supreme Court, while interpreting the meaning and purport of general
			<lb />
			words. One, that plain and natural meaning should be preferred ordinarily,
			<lb />
			and two, that the context and purpose of the provision should always be kept
			<lb />
			in mind. Thus, in Polestar Electronic (Pvt.) Ltd. v Additional Commissioner,
			<lb />
			Sales Tax and Anr. (1978) 1 SCC 636, it was held:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-11. ... If the language of a statute is clear and explicit, effect
			<lb />
			must be given to it, for in such a case the words best declare the
			<lb />
			intention of the law-giver. It would not be right to refuse to place
			<lb />
			on the language of the statute the plain and natural meaning
			<lb />
			which it must bear on the ground that it produces a consequence
			<lb />
			which could not have been intended by the legislature. It is only
			<lb />
			from the language of the statute that the intention of the
			<lb />
			Legislature must be gathered, for the legislature means no more
			<lb />
			and no less than what it says. It is not permissible to the Court to
			<lb />
			speculate as to what the Legislature must have intended and
			<lb />
			then to twist or bend the language of the statute to make it
			<lb />
			accord with the presumed intention of the legislature. ...‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			80. Central Bank of India v State of Kerala and Ors. (2009) 4 SCC 94, a
			<lb />
			three-Judge Bench judgment, quoted Professor H.A. Smith (as quoted in
			<lb />
			Justice G.P. Singh&quot;s Principles of Statutory Interpretation) to the following
			<lb />
			effect:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-&apos;No word&apos;, says Professor H.A. Smith &apos;has an absolute
			<lb />
			meaning, for no words can be defined in vacuo, or without
			<lb />
			reference to some context&apos;. According to Sutherland there is a
			<lb />
			&apos;basic fallacy&apos; in saying &apos;that words have meaning in and of
			<lb />
			themselves&apos;, and &apos;reference to the abstract meaning of words&apos;,
			<lb />
			states Craies, &apos;if there be any such thing, is of little value in
			<lb />
			interpreting statutes&apos;. ... in determining the meaning of any word
			<lb />
			or phrase in a statute the first question to be asked is -&apos;What is
			<lb />
			the natural or ordinary meaning of that word or phrase in its
			<lb />
			context in the statute? It is only when that meaning leads to
			<lb />
			some result which cannot reasonably be supposed to have been
			<lb />
			the intention of the legislature, that it is proper to look for some
			<lb />
			other possible meaning of the word or phrase.&apos; The context, as
			<lb />
			already seen, in the construction of statutes, means the statute as
			<lb />
			a whole, the previous state of the law, other statutes in pari
			<lb />
			materia, the general scope of the statute and the mischief that it
			<lb />
			was intended to remedy.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			81. Speaking of the use of an expression or term in different parts of a
			<lb />
			statute, the court held in Central Bank of India v Ravindra &amp; Ors. (2002) 1
			<lb />
			SCC 36 that:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-42. ...Ordinarily, a word or expression used at several places
			<lb />
			in one enactment should be assigned the same meaning so as to
			<lb />
			avoid &quot;a head-on clash&quot; between two meanings assigned to the
			<lb />
			same word or expression occurring at two places in the same
			<lb />
			enactment. It should not be lightly assumed that &quot;Parliament
			<lb />
			had given with one hand what it took away with the other&quot; (see
			<lb />
			Principles of Statutory Interpretation, Justice G.P. Singh, 7th
			<lb />
			Edn. 1999, p. 113). That construction is to be rejected which
			<lb />
			will introduce uncertainty, friction or confusion into the
			<lb />
			working of the system (ibid, p. 119). While embarking upon
			<lb />
			interpretation of words and expressions used in a statute it is
			<lb />
			possible to find a situation when the same word or expression
			<lb />
			may have somewhat different meaning at different places
			<lb />
			depending on the subject or context. This is however an
			<lb />
			exception which can be resorted to only in the event of
			<lb />
			repugnancy in the subject or context being spelled out. It has
			<lb />
			been the consistent view of the Supreme Court that when the
			<lb />
			legislature used same word or expression in different parts of
			<lb />
			the same section or statute, there is a presumption that the
			<lb />
			word is used in the same sense throughout (ibid, p. 263). More
			<lb />
			correct statement of the rule is, as held by the House of Lords
			<lb />
			in Farrell v. Alexander All ER at p. 736b, &quot;where the draftsman
			<lb />
			uses the same word or phrase in similar contexts, he must be
			<lb />
			presumed to intend it in each place to bear the same meaning&quot;.
			<lb />
			The court having accepted invitation to embark upon
			<lb />
			interpretative expedition shall identify on its radar the
			<lb />
			contextual use of the word or expression and then determine its
			<lb />
			direction avoiding collision with icebergs of inconsistency and
			<lb />
			repugnancy.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			82. It is, therefore, clear that whilst there is one rule generally speaking,
			<lb />
			use of a term or expression in a statute, carries upon it to be interpreted in the
			<lb />
			same manner in all provisions of that statute, the rule is neither inflexible
			<lb />
			admitting no exception nor of universal application. The object of the
			<lb />
			concerned provision is one of the important factors which weigh in while
			<lb />
			interpreting whether the same meaning has to be attributed to all parts of the
			<lb />
			statute. Given these circumstances, this Court is of the opinion that &quot;exports&quot;
			<lb />
			is used in different contexts in Sections 84, 90 and 92A. Section 84 is the
			<lb />
			provision which enables compulsory licensing of certain conditions. Section
			<lb />
			84(7) spells out what are reasonable requirements of the public. These are
			<lb />
			deemed not to have been satisfied if under Section 84(7)(a)(iii), a market for
			<lb />
			the patented article manufactured in India is not being supplied or developed.
			<lb />
			Section 90(1)(vii) is in a sense, complimentary to Section 84 and has to be
			<lb />
			read with it: it guides the Controller to ensure inter alia that the license
			<lb />
			granted under Section 84(7)(a)(c)(iii) is with the predominant purpose of
			<lb />
			supply to the Indian market and that the licensee may also export the
			<lb />
			patented product.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			83. Section 92A is a species of compulsory license. The principles in one
			<lb />
			sense are even an exception to it. The provision dealing with compulsory
			<lb />
			licensing [Section 84] is concerned only with the availability of patented
			<lb />
			market, of reasonable terms for users in India. Therefore, the question of
			<lb />
			reasonable requirements of other countries does not arise and yet the
			<lb />
			Parliament, in keeping with TRIPS, (cognizant of the broad classification of
			<lb />
			nations as developed, developing and least developed countries), envisioned
			<lb />
			Section 92A which enables licensing for export of patented pharmaceutical
			<lb />
			products in exceptional circumstances, i.e. whether the country concerned
			<lb />
			has insufficient or no manufacturing capacity in the pharmaceutical sector.
			<lb />
			Really speaking, this provision, i.e. Section 92A constitutes an exception to
			<lb />
			the general rule that compulsory licensing is only resorted primarily and
			<lb />
			predominantly to cater to the needs of the domestic market of the host
			<lb />
			country with regard also being had to export potential from that country.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			84. Having regard to all these factors, it cannot be held that the Parliament
			<lb />
			intended to per se exclude &quot;exports&quot; from the sweep and width of the term
			<lb />
			&quot;sale&quot; in Section 107A regard being had to the disparate and differing
			<lb />
			objectives of Sections 84, 90 and 92A all of which in some way or the other
			<lb />
			primarily deal with compulsory licensing and on the other hand, Section
			<lb />
			107A is the only provision that allows an exception to be used-construction
			<lb />
			and sale of a patented article only for research purposes and subject to
			<lb />
			fulfillment of the conditions specified therein. The next argument which
			<lb />
			Bayer strongly advanced with respect to exclusion of exports from the term
			<lb />
			&quot;sale&quot; is that patent rights are territorial in nature, specific allusion was made
			<lb />
			to Section 48 in this regard. Elaborating, it was contended that the grant of a
			<lb />
			patent constitutes a negative right to prevent third parties from making,
			<lb />
			using, forwarding for sale, selling or importing the patented product in India.
			<lb />
			Secondly, it was urged that the research exception, can be accepted, and
			<lb />
			needs to be carried out in India if the benefit of that provision is to be
			<lb />
			secured.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			85. It was submitted that Section 107A(a) really constitutes an exception
			<lb />
			and its effect has to be strictly confined to the extent the terms of the
			<lb />
			expression spelt out and no more. Reliance was placed upon Mohan Kumar
			<lb />
			Singhania v UOI AIR 1992 SC 1. There are a line of judgments which state
			<lb />
			that a particular provision of an enactment cannot be said to nullify or set at
			<lb />
			nought the main or substantive provision. In Dwarka Prasad v Dwarka Das
			<lb />
			Saraf 1976 (1) SCC 128, it was stated as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-18. We may mention in fairness to Counsel that the following,
			<lb />
			among other decisions, were cited at the Bar bearing on the
			<lb />
			uses of provisos in statutes: CIT v. Indo-Mercantile Bank Ltd.,
			<lb />
			AIR 1959 SC 713]; Ram Narain Sons Ltd. v. Asstt. (1955) 2
			<lb />
			SCR 483, 493:]; Thompson v. Dibdin [(1912) AC 533, 541; Rex
			<lb />
			v. Dibdin [1910 Pro Div 57, 119, 125] and Tahsildar Singh v.
			<lb />
			State of U.P. AIR 1959 Supp (2) SCR 875,]. The law is trite. A
			<lb />
			proviso must be limited to the subject-matter of the enacting
			<lb />
			clause. It is a settled Rule of construction that a proviso must
			<lb />
			prima facie be read and considered in relation to the principal
			<lb />
			matter to which it is a proviso. It is not a separate or
			<lb />
			independent enactment. &quot;Words are dependent on the principal
			<lb />
			enacting words to which they are tacked as a proviso. They
			<lb />
			cannot be read as divorced from their context&quot;
			<lb />
			(Thompson v. Dibdin, 1912 AC 533). If the Rule of construction
			<lb />
			is that prima facie a proviso should be limited in its operation
			<lb />
			to the subject-matter of the enacting clause, the stand we have
			<lb />
			taken is sound. To expand the enacting clause, inflated by the
			<lb />
			proviso, sins against the fundamental Rule of construction that
			<lb />
			a proviso must be considered in relation to the principal matter
			<lb />
			to which it stands as a proviso. A proviso ordinarily is but a
			<lb />
			proviso, although the golden Rule is to read the whole section,
			<lb />
			inclusive of the proviso, in such manner that they mutually
			<lb />
			throw light on each other and result in a harmonious
			<lb />
			construction.
			<lb />
			The proper course is to apply the broad general Rule of
			<lb />
			construction which is that a Section or enactment must be
			<lb />
			construed as a whole, each portion throwing light if need be on
			<lb />
			the rest.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The true principle undoubtedly is, that the sound interpretation
			<lb />
			and meaning of the statute, on a view of the enacting clause,
			<lb />
			saving clause, and proviso, taken and construed together is to
			<lb />
			prevail.(Maxwell on Interpretation of Statutes, 10th Edn., p.
			<lb />
			162)‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			86. In S. Sundaram Pillai v V.R. Pattabiraman1985 (1) SCC 591, it was
			<lb />
			held that:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;27. The next question that arises for consideration is as to
			<lb />
			what is the scope of a proviso and what is the ambit of an
			<lb />
			Explanation either to a proviso or to any other statutory
			<lb />
			provision. We shall first take up the question of the nature,
			<lb />
			scope and extent of a proviso. The well-established Rule of
			<lb />
			interpretation of a proviso is that a proviso may have three
			<lb />
			separate functions. Normally, a proviso is meant to be an
			<lb />
			exception to something within the main enactment or to qualify
			<lb />
			something enacted therein which but for the proviso would be
			<lb />
			within the purview of the enactment. In other words, a proviso
			<lb />
			cannot be torn apart from the main enactment nor can it be
			<lb />
			used to nullify or set at naught the real object of the main
			<lb />
			enactment.(Emphasis supplied)‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			87. Likewise, in J.K. Industries Ltd. v Chief Inspector of Factories and
			<lb />
			Boilers 1996 (6) SCC 665, it was held as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-33. A proviso to a provision in a statute has several functions
			<lb />
			and while interpreting a provision of the statute, the court is
			<lb />
			required to carefully scrutinise and find out the real object of
			<lb />
			the proviso appended to that provision. It is not a proper Rule
			<lb />
			of interpretation of a proviso that the enacting part or the main
			<lb />
			part of the Section be construed first without reference to the
			<lb />
			proviso and if the same is found to be ambiguous only then
			<lb />
			recourse may be had to examine the proviso as has been
			<lb />
			canvassed before us. On the other hand an accepted Rule of
			<lb />
			interpretation is that a Section and the proviso thereto must be
			<lb />
			construed as a whole, each portion throwing light, if need be,
			<lb />
			on the rest. A proviso is normally used to remove special cases
			<lb />
			from the general enactment and provide for them specially.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			34. A proviso qualifies the generality of the main enactment
			<lb />
			by providing an exception and taking out from the main
			<lb />
			provision, a portion, which, but for the proviso would be a part
			<lb />
			of the main provision. A proviso must, therefore, be considered
			<lb />
			in relation to the principal matter to which it stands as a
			<lb />
			proviso. A proviso should not be read as if providing something
			<lb />
			by way of addition to the main provision which is foreign to the
			<lb />
			main provision itself.
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			88. In the present case, this court notices that Section 107A is not made
			<lb />
			subject to the other provisions of the Act -on the other hand, Section 48,
			<lb />
			which talks of the rights of a patent holder is subject to other provisions of
			<lb />
			the Act that includes Section 107A. Furthermore, Bayer&quot;s argument that
			<lb />
			Section 107A constitutes an exception, cannot be accepted. It is an
			<lb />
			independent provision with a specific history behind it and was subject to
			<lb />
			intensive Parliamentary debate and scrutiny by a Joint Committee report.
			<lb />
			Furthermore, it was enacted in response to the TRIPS enabling provision to
			<lb />
			the member countries to evolve national legislation facilitating research and
			<lb />
			progress in fields covered by the patents. The judgments cited, all generally
			<lb />
			and invariably contended by Bayer deal with provisos embodied in the main
			<lb />
			provision that constituted exceptions to the general rule. However, in this
			<lb />
			case, the court is not called upon to interpret the proviso to Section 48; nor
			<lb />
			even an exception. Bayer&quot;s argument that Section 107A has to be read as
			<lb />
			subordinate to the main provision of Section 48 has to, therefore, fail. This
			<lb />
			Court is also fortified in its conclusions. In Indian Oil Corporation v the
			<lb />
			Chief Inspector of Factories and Ors. (1998) 5 SCC 738, the Supreme Court
			<lb />
			had to decide whether one of the Directors only could recognise his occupier
			<lb />
			and whether Section 2(n)(iii) of the Factories Act, 1948, applied to the IOC&quot;s
			<lb />
			factories and if it was open to the Central Government to nominate any
			<lb />
			person other than the Director or the occupier. Section 2(n) was amended to
			<lb />
			say that &quot;occupier&quot; meant the person who had ultimate control over the
			<lb />
			affairs of the factory and also that in the case of firms or associations; and as
			<lb />
			to who could be occupiers in the case of firms and association in the case of
			<lb />
			company (any of the Directors) and in the case of factory owned by the
			<lb />
			Central Government, &quot;person or persons nominated to manage the affairs of
			<lb />
			the factory by the State Government, Central Government etc.‖. Prior to the
			<lb />
			amendment, the &quot;occupier&quot; did not include the specific designated officials
			<lb />
			or employees of the company or firms. The Supreme Court held that the
			<lb />
			requirement of third proviso could really constitute a separate provision, and
			<lb />
			had to be read as such. The Supreme Court held as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			20. Apart from the main part of Section 2(n), the first proviso
			<lb />
			also indicates that the Legislature intended that the person
			<lb />
			having ultimate control over the affairs of the factory has to be
			<lb />
			regarded as occupier of the factory. The proviso to the Section
			<lb />
			is not in the nature of an exception. In order to avoid any
			<lb />
			ambiguity, to plug loopholes and to seal the escape routes a
			<lb />
			deeming provision has been made in a mandatory form. In the
			<lb />
			case of a firm obviously the partners of the firm have ultimate
			<lb />
			control over the affairs of the partnership. In case of other type
			<lb />
			of association the members thereof will have such control. In
			<lb />
			the case of a company the directors have the ultimate control,
			<lb />
			as the power to manage the affairs of the company vests in the
			<lb />
			Board of Directors. What clauses (i) and (ii) of the proviso
			<lb />
			provide is that they shall be deemed to be &apos;occupiers&apos;. Thus they
			<lb />
			merely restate the position which is obvious even otherwise.
			<lb />
			The position of the government and the local authority is quite
			<lb />
			different from that of a firm or an association or a company not
			<lb />
			only with respect to the person who can be said to be in
			<lb />
			ultimate control but also with respect to the object for which
			<lb />
			factory is set up. In a democratic set-up of Government, it may
			<lb />
			not be possible to say with certainty as to who is having the
			<lb />
			ultimate control. In a welfare state, the government does not
			<lb />
			carry on such activity for its own profit or benefit but for the
			<lb />
			benefit of the people as a whole. Moreover, it is the government
			<lb />
			which looks after the successful implementation of the
			<lb />
			provisions of the Factories Act and, therefore, it is not likely to
			<lb />
			evade implementation of the beneficial provisions of the
			<lb />
			Factories Act. That appears to be the reason why the
			<lb />
			legislature though it fit to make a separate provision for the
			<lb />
			Government and the local authorities. Ordinarily, for running
			<lb />
			the factories owned or controlled by the Central Government or
			<lb />
			any State Government, or any local authority, a person or
			<lb />
			persons would be appointed by it to manage the affairs of the
			<lb />
			factory, because the Government or the local authority as a
			<lb />
			whole would not run the factory. Therefore, the legislature
			<lb />
			appears to have provided that in case of a factory owned or
			<lb />
			controlled by the Central Government, the State Government or
			<lb />
			the local authority the person or persons appointed to manage
			<lb />
			the affairs of the factory by the Central Government, State
			<lb />
			Government or the local authority, as the case may be, shall be
			<lb />
			deemed to be the occupier. Therefore, if it is a case of a factory
			<lb />
			in fact and in reality owned or controlled by the Central
			<lb />
			Government or the State Government or any local authority
			<lb />
			then in case of such a factory the person or persons appointed
			<lb />
			to manage the affairs of the factory shall have to be deemed to
			<lb />
			be the occupier, even though for better management of such a
			<lb />
			factory or factories a corporate form is adopted by the
			<lb />
			government.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			21. Before 1987, when Section 100 was the governing
			<lb />
			provision, any one of the individual partners of a firm or any
			<lb />
			one of the members of association of individuals could be
			<lb />
			punished under Sub-section (I) thereof for any offence for
			<lb />
			which the occupier of the factory was punishable. The firm or
			<lb />
			association was given an option to nominate one of its members
			<lb />
			as the occupier of the factory and if such an option was
			<lb />
			exercised by giving a notice to the Inspector then he alone was
			<lb />
			to be deemed to be the occupier of the factory for the said
			<lb />
			purpose. Under Sub-section (2) if the occupier of the factory
			<lb />
			was a company then any one of the directors thereof could be
			<lb />
			prosecuted and punished. A similar option was available to the
			<lb />
			company, as in the case of a firm and an association of
			<lb />
			individuals. It is significant to note that it was by way of a
			<lb />
			proviso to Sub-section (2) which dealt with case of a company
			<lb />
			that the provision was made for deciding who should be
			<lb />
			deemed to be the occupier of a factory in case it belonged to the
			<lb />
			Central Government or any State Government or any local
			<lb />
			authority and a similar option is made available to them. The
			<lb />
			said proviso though enacted as an exception to the main part of
			<lb />
			Sub-section (2) is truly by way of a separate provision made in
			<lb />
			the case of a factory belonging to the Central Government or
			<lb />
			any State Government or any local Authority. While making the
			<lb />
			amendment in 1987 in Section 2(n) and deleting Section 100 at
			<lb />
			the same time the Legislature made the proviso to subsection
			<lb />
			(2) of Section 100 an independent proviso to Section 2(n). That
			<lb />
			also clearly indicates the intention of the Legislature that it
			<lb />
			wanted to make a separate provision for deeming who should
			<lb />
			be the occupier of a government factory.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			89. In the light of the above discussion, the court is of the opinion that
			<lb />
			there is no question of treating Section 107A(a) as an exception to Section
			<lb />
			48. Its history of interpretation by TRIPS, the discussion in the
			<lb />
			Parliamentary Joint Committee Report, all clearly point to its being a special
			<lb />
			provision that deals with the rights of the patented invention for research
			<lb />
			purposes.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			90. As far as the question of territoriality is concerned, Bayer&quot;s argument
			<lb />
			is twofold: that the reference to regulatory requirements of other countries
			<lb />
			and its reference to reasonable regulations or laws of other countries, for the
			<lb />
			purpose of development of the product and its making, construction, use or
			<lb />
			sale, is to be understood as meaning that the overseas requirements are to be
			<lb />
			met with through experimental use in India. Explaining further, it is
			<lb />
			contended that the reference to overseas or other nations&quot; laws or regulations
			<lb />
			with respect to research requirements is to be understood in such a way that
			<lb />
			information development in India can be exported.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			91. This Court is of the opinion that the interpretation canvassed by Bayer
			<lb />
			is strained and artificial. Once it is held that patented inventions can be sold
			<lb />
			for the purpose of carrying on research which fulfils the regulatory
			<lb />
			requirements of India, there cannot be any bar or an interpretation narrowing
			<lb />
			the scope of such sale. What is important is the purpose of the sale, i.e.
			<lb />
			objective of carrying on experiment, research and developing information (in
			<lb />
			the form of reports, outcomes etc.). If the purpose of the sale is to ultimately
			<lb />
			exploit the patented invention and either work upon it or &quot;work around&quot; or
			<lb />
			work it through research so as to be prepared to apply for the patent for
			<lb />
			approval to market it once the patent tenure ends, there can be no impairment
			<lb />
			of the patentee&quot;s rights. The natural consequence of that sale cannot be
			<lb />
			curtailed by a contrived interpretation to say that it is only information that
			<lb />
			can be sold or exported, not the patented invention. Likewise, the reference
			<lb />
			of another country i.e the export for reasonably complying with the laws of
			<lb />
			another country in relation to the kind of research and experimentation
			<lb />
			needed is something that cannot be dictated by interpretation of Indian law
			<lb />
			alone. It is plausible-even reasonable-that many nations may require
			<lb />
			experimentation or research to be carried on in their soil nationally so as to
			<lb />
			be able to supervise the process and then oversee the outcome. It is,
			<lb />
			therefore, not possible to dictate the behaviour and legal requirements of
			<lb />
			other nations by confining the research exception within the territory of
			<lb />
			India.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			92. The natural interpretation of the expression &quot;use&quot; is in all its senses. In
			<lb />
			this context, it would be necessary to recognize that in regard to various
			<lb />
			products, especially those concerning the pharmaceutical, medicinal
			<lb />
			preparations, surgical and diagnostic purposes and those relating to the
			<lb />
			agriculture or bio-chemical sector, it may be critical for a database of
			<lb />
			populations, drugs and co-relation, with disease and its relationship with
			<lb />
			characteristics that are predominantly local. National regimes might well
			<lb />
			insist that such research and experimentation in regard to those aspects be
			<lb />
			either entirely or at least in part be carried on in their territory. In this
			<lb />
			context, therefore, it is held that the expressions, -making, constructing,
			<lb />
			using, selling or importing patented articles solely for uses reasonably
			<lb />
			related to development and submission of information required under any
			<lb />
			law for the time being in force…… or in a country other than India that
			<lb />
			regulates the manufacturing, construction, use, sale or import of any
			<lb />
			product‖, consequently, has to be given a wide import. It is, therefore, open
			<lb />
			that the sale of the article or invention for the purpose of development of
			<lb />
			information in compliance with the reasonable requirements of developing
			<lb />
			countries, solely for purposes of research or development falls within
			<lb />
			Section 107A(a).
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			93. There is one more manner of looking at the issue. A patent owner&quot;s
			<lb />
			interests are clearly injured if the invention or the product or the method
			<lb />
			which is the subject matter of the patent is worked for purely commercial
			<lb />
			purposes and the ensuing product is offered in the market. Such products
			<lb />
			would be competitors to the patented invention and because of their copycat
			<lb />
			nature, one can reasonably expect them to be significantly lower in cost, in
			<lb />
			the marketplace. However, in the case of sale, construction or use of the
			<lb />
			patented article, either within India or outside the territory of India, the
			<lb />
			question of such injury cannot ordinarily arise if the object or purpose of that
			<lb />
			transaction is solely to experiment or research and develop information that
			<lb />
			is reasonably related to the requirements of the law (Indian or overseas). If
			<lb />
			one considers this aspect, it is clear that the fullest effect ought to be given to
			<lb />
			the research exception embodied in Section 107A(a). The objections with
			<lb />
			regard to the territoriality of patents or the strained interpretation given to the
			<lb />
			provision of construing export (i.e. the export sale) only to sale of
			<lb />
			information overseas, is unwarranted. Bayer&quot;s argument, therefore, is
			<lb />
			rejected on this aspect.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			94. This Court also finds unpersuasive, Bayer&quot;s subsidiary submission that
			<lb />
			Rule 122B of the Drugs and Cosmetics Rules, 1945 permits the licensing
			<lb />
			authority to grant permission (for a product) on the basis of data available
			<lb />
			from other countries. Thus, Bayer&quot;s argument here was that the act of
			<lb />
			importation in Section 107A refers to all such information which can be used
			<lb />
			for regulatory purposes of the research and development in India. Here
			<lb />
			again, the court is of the opinion that the broad nature of the provision -
			<lb />
			which enables development and research of the product and information
			<lb />
			related thereto, on fulfilling the regulatory or other legal requirements of
			<lb />
			India, and other countries-cannot be construed narrowly as to permit
			<lb />
			development and research of the product only in India, even though the
			<lb />
			backup research is conducted elsewhere. The object and underlying purpose
			<lb />
			of Drugs and Cosmetics Act is entirely different from those of the Patent
			<lb />
			Act. The former deals with the range of regulatory provisions necessary for
			<lb />
			various classes of drugs to receive licensing, marketing approvals etc. On the
			<lb />
			other hand, the patent regime is premised solely upon the regulation of the
			<lb />
			intellectual property right relating to patents. The court is also of the opinion
			<lb />
			that Natco&quot;s status as compulsory licensee did not place it under any
			<lb />
			additional statutory bar from exporting the product, as long as the underlying
			<lb />
			condition in Section 107A was satisfied, as held by the learned Single Judge.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			95. It is therefore, clear that the submissions with respect to
			<lb />
			impermissibility of exportation of the product cannot be accepted. Bayer&quot;s
			<lb />
			arguments are rejected.
			<lb />
			Submissions in respect of the Canada Dispute
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			96. Bayer had relied on the Canada Dispute (supra) ruling by the WTO
			<lb />
			DSP. Two important issues in that case involved questions of public policy
			<lb />
			(societal public interest v. private rights). They were permissible exceptions,
			<lb />
			under Articles 30 and 31 of TRIPS, to the use of patented products or
			<lb />
			processes, without permission of the patent-owner (a patentee&quot;s rights are
			<lb />
			detailed in Article 28.1 and 29), having regard to TRIPS principles in
			<lb />
			Articles 7 and 8. The provisions of Canadian Patent Law-i.e. the regulatory
			<lb />
			review exception and the stockpiling exception were challenged by the EU.
			<lb />
			The Regulatory Review Exception, in Section 55.2(1) of Canada&quot;s patent
			<lb />
			law, allows the generic industry without authorization, to develop the
			<lb />
			product and submit it to regulatory authorities for market approval so that
			<lb />
			they could market the product when the patent expires; no permission of the
			<lb />
			patent owner was essential. The stockpiling exception in Section 55.2(2) of
			<lb />
			Canada&quot;s law permitted generic manufacturers to produce and stockpile
			<lb />
			(store) generic products for which marketing approval has been obtained,
			<lb />
			during a six-month period before expiry of the patent, and market the generic
			<lb />
			products as soon as the patent has expired. The first exception (regulatory or
			<lb />
			research exception) to patent rights has been held legal, but the stockpiling
			<lb />
			exception was held to be illegal.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			97. Bayer&quot;s argument was that Canada&quot;s plea was that the reference to
			<lb />
			&quot;selling&quot; the invention was necessitated by the fact that a generic drug
			<lb />
			manufacturer had to usually purchase the active ingredient for its product
			<lb />
			from a &quot;fine chemical producer&quot;. Bayer relied upon footnote 49 on page 21
			<lb />
			of the award, which reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-In response to a question from the Panel, Canada explained
			<lb />
			that, if the patentee claimed that a fine chemical manufacturer
			<lb />
			was infringing the patent, i.e. was manufacturing fine chemicals
			<lb />
			for purposes which were outside the exception, the patentee
			<lb />
			would commence infringement litigation against the
			<lb />
			manufacturer under Sections 54 and 55 of the Patent Act. The
			<lb />
			manufacturer would then be obliged to prove that it would have
			<lb />
			been reasonable, objectively, for a party in its position to
			<lb />
			believe
			<lb />
			that the use made of its manufactured active
			<lb />
			ingredients related to the development and submission of
			<lb />
			information required by law. It would be common commercial
			<lb />
			practice for the supply contract with the manufacturer to
			<lb />
			specify the purposes for which the chemicals were being
			<lb />
			manufactured and to provide an appropriate indemnity against
			<lb />
			infringement liability. While the matter had not been decided in
			<lb />
			the courts, the effect of the exception of Section 55.2(2) for the
			<lb />
			fine chemical producer would appear to be that a third party
			<lb />
			could acquire intermediate products, or -inputs‖, such as the
			<lb />
			bulk fine chemical constituting the active ingredient of a
			<lb />
			generic drug, for manufacturer and storage during the last six
			<lb />
			months of the patent term. In other words, both the third party
			<lb />
			and manufacturer would appear to be covered by the
			<lb />
			exception.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			98. It was submitted that the DSP in its findings stated that &quot;selling&quot; in the
			<lb />
			provision was under challenge. Para 7.4 of the award was also relied on; it
			<lb />
			states that:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-The structure of the generic pharmaceutical industry
			<lb />
			illustrates the actual operation of the regulatory review
			<lb />
			exception. Production of generic pharmaceuticals often
			<lb />
			involves a two-tier production arrangement. The firm that
			<lb />
			assembles and markets the final generic product often does not
			<lb />
			have the technological capacity/expertise or the commercial
			<lb />
			motivation to produce the so called -active ingredient‖ -the
			<lb />
			chemical product that generates the desired medicinal effect.
			<lb />
			The active ingredient is thus often manufactured by a
			<lb />
			specialized producer of fine chemicals, and then sold to the
			<lb />
			generic producer which assembles the active ingredient with
			<lb />
			other agents to create the final product in a form that can be
			<lb />
			used by the ultimate consumer. In such cases, both producers
			<lb />
			must engage in conduct that, in the absence of a regulatory
			<lb />
			review exception, would be potentially infringing, if they are to
			<lb />
			satisfy the requirements of the regulatory review process -the
			<lb />
			fine chemical producer in developing, making and selling the
			<lb />
			necessary amounts of the active ingredient to the generic
			<lb />
			producer, and the generic producer in combining the various
			<lb />
			elements to make the final product and then demonstrating its
			<lb />
			safety, stability and effectiveness by appropriate tests. The
			<lb />
			regulatory review exception applies to these activities of both
			<lb />
			producers.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			99. In view of these submissions, Bayer argued that Parliament inserted
			<lb />
			the term &quot;selling&quot; in Section 107A(a) with intent to exempt the activities of
			<lb />
			the contract manufactures and any entity selling within the territory of India
			<lb />
			for the purposes as contemplated under the said section.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			100. Several countries, including India, Canada and the US have fashioned
			<lb />
			their patent laws to carve out such an exception. The Canadian provision,
			<lb />
			Section 55.2(1), which enabled use of a patented product for generation of
			<lb />
			information to be submitted to regulatory authorities was the subject matter
			<lb />
			of a complaint lodged by the US and Europe at the Dispute Settlement Body
			<lb />
			of the WTO. It was contended that Section 55.2(1) violated TRIPS.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			101. The DSP under TRIPS in the Canada dispute case (supra) discussed
			<lb />
			the issue; it found that such a provision (i.e. Canada&quot;s regulatory exception)
			<lb />
			was a &quot;limited exception&quot; within the meaning of Article 30 of TRIPS, and
			<lb />
			that the size of production would not violate patent rights so long as it is
			<lb />
			solely for regulatory purposes. The DSP flagged the purpose of use in its
			<lb />
			award, relevant portions of which are extracted below:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			7.3 Because of the regulatory review exception&apos;s importance to
			<lb />
			the pharmaceutical industry, the operation of the exception with
			<lb />
			regard to new pharmaceuticals was explained in some detail by the
			<lb />
			parties. Information supplied by Canada in the proceedings before
			<lb />
			the Panel on the process of regulatory approval in Canada for
			<lb />
			patented and generic drugs can be found in paragraphs 2.2 to 2.7
			<lb />
			above and Annexes 3 and 4 to this Report. The information has not
			<lb />
			been contested by the European Communities. Since patent
			<lb />
			applications are generally filed as quickly as possible after the
			<lb />
			invention has been made, actual marketing of the patented product
			<lb />
			is frequently delayed for a certain period of time because time is
			<lb />
			required for development of the product in commercial form, after
			<lb />
			which additional time is required to complete the testing required
			<lb />
			for government approval. According to the information supplied by
			<lb />
			Canada, the process of development of the drug and regulatory
			<lb />
			approval for new patented pharmaceuticals normally takes
			<lb />
			approximately eight to 12 years. The long development and
			<lb />
			approval process means that, for most patented pharmaceuticals,
			<lb />
			the 20-year patent term results in an actual period of market
			<lb />
			exclusivity of only some 12 to eight years. After a pharmaceutical
			<lb />
			patent expires, it is common for other producers to enter the
			<lb />
			market supplying copies of the patented product at lower prices.
			<lb />
			These lower-priced copies, known as &quot;generic&quot; pharmaceuticals,
			<lb />
			often constitute a large part of the supply of pharmaceuticals in
			<lb />
			national markets. Generic pharmaceuticals must also comply with
			<lb />
			the government approval process. According to Canada&apos;s
			<lb />
			information, for generic producers the process of developing their
			<lb />
			version of the drug and obtaining regulatory approval takes
			<lb />
			approximately three to six-and-a-half years, with development
			<lb />
			taking some two to four years and the regulatory process itself one
			<lb />
			to two-and-a-half years. If none of the development process could
			<lb />
			be performed during the term of the patent, generic producers
			<lb />
			could be forced to wait the full three to six-and-a-half years after
			<lb />
			the patent expires before being able to enter the market in
			<lb />
			competition with the patent owner. To the extent that some
			<lb />
			development activity might be permitted, consistently with Article
			<lb />
			30 of the TRIPS Agreement, under other exceptions such as the
			<lb />
			traditional exception for experimental use of the patented product,
			<lb />
			the delay in entering the market would be correspondingly less.
			<lb />
			The regulatory review exception in Section 55.2(1) would allow
			<lb />
			generic producers to complete both development and regulatory
			<lb />
			approval during the term of the patent, thus allowing them to enter
			<lb />
			the market as soon as the patent expires.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			7.4 The structure of the generic pharmaceutical industry
			<lb />
			illustrates the actual operation of the regulatory review exception.
			<lb />
			Production of generic pharmaceuticals often involves a two-tier
			<lb />
			production arrangement. The firm that assembles and markets the
			<lb />
			final generic product often does not have the technological
			<lb />
			capacity/expertise or the commercial motivation to produce the so-
			<lb />
			called &quot;active ingredient&quot; -the chemical product that generates the
			<lb />
			desired medicinal effect. The active ingredient is thus often
			<lb />
			manufactured by a specialized producer of fine chemicals, and
			<lb />
			then sold to the generic producer which assembles the active
			<lb />
			ingredient with other agents to create the final product in a form
			<lb />
			that can be used by the ultimate consumer. In such cases, both
			<lb />
			producers must engage in conduct that, in the absence of a
			<lb />
			regulatory review exception, would be potentially infringing, if
			<lb />
			they are to satisfy the requirements of the regulatory review
			<lb />
			process -the fine chemical producer in developing, making and
			<lb />
			selling the necessary amounts of the active ingredient to the
			<lb />
			generic producer, and the generic producer in combining the
			<lb />
			various elements to make the final product and then demonstrating
			<lb />
			its safety, stability and effectiveness by appropriate tests. The
			<lb />
			regulatory review exception applies to these activities of both
			<lb />
			producers.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			7.5 To qualify for exemption under Section 55.2(1), such
			<lb />
			activities by either fine chemical producers or generic producers
			<lb />
			must be &quot;solely for uses reasonably related to the development and
			<lb />
			submission of information required&quot; by any law, Canadian or non-
			<lb />
			Canadian, that &quot;regulates the manufacture, construction, use or
			<lb />
			sale of any product&quot;. In answer to a question from the Panel,
			<lb />
			Canada stated that, although Canadian marketing regulations for
			<lb />
			generic producers did not require production runs to demonstrate
			<lb />
			the applicant&apos;s ability to maintain quality production in
			<lb />
			commercial volumes373, the statute would allow either fine
			<lb />
			chemical manufacturers or generic producers to undertake such
			<lb />
			production runs if they were required by regulations in other
			<lb />
			countries.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			102. Later, in its decision, the DSP held as follows:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			-7.45 In the Panel&apos;s view, however, Canada&apos;s regulatory review
			<lb />
			exception is a &quot;limited exception&quot; within the meaning of TRIPS
			<lb />
			Article 30. It is &quot;limited&quot; because of the narrow scope of its
			<lb />
			curtailment of Article 28.1 rights. As long as the exception is
			<lb />
			confined to conduct needed to comply with the requirements of the
			<lb />
			regulatory approval process, the extent of the acts unauthorized by
			<lb />
			the right holder that are permitted by it will be small and narrowly
			<lb />
			bounded. Even though regulatory approval processes may require
			<lb />
			substantial amounts of test production to demonstrate reliable
			<lb />
			manufacturing, the patent owner&apos;s rights themselves are not
			<lb />
			impaired any further by the size of such production runs, as long
			<lb />
			as they are solely for regulatory purposes and no commercial use
			<lb />
			is made of resulting final products.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			7.46 The Panel found no basis for believing that activities seeking
			<lb />
			product approvals under foreign regulatory procedures would be
			<lb />
			any less subject to these limitations. There is no a priori basis to
			<lb />
			assume that the requirements of foreign regulatory procedures will
			<lb />
			require activities unrelated to legitimate objectives of product
			<lb />
			quality and safety, nor has the EC provided any evidence to that
			<lb />
			effect. Nor is there any reason to assume that Canadian law would
			<lb />
			apply the exception in cases where foreign requirements clearly
			<lb />
			had no regulatory purpose. Nor, finally, is there any reason to
			<lb />
			assume that it will be any more difficult to enforce the
			<lb />
			requirements of Canadian law when Canadian producers claim
			<lb />
			exceptions under foreign procedures. With regard to the latter
			<lb />
			point, the Panel concurred with Canada&apos;s point that the
			<lb />
			government is not normally expected to regulate the actual
			<lb />
			conduct of third parties in such cases. The enforcement of these
			<lb />
			conditions, as with other enforcement of patent rights, occurs by
			<lb />
			means of private infringement actions brought by the patent owner.
			<lb />
			The patent owner merely has to prove that the challenged conduct
			<lb />
			is inconsistent with the basic patent rights created by national law.
			<lb />
			Once that initial case is made, the burden will be on the party
			<lb />
			accused of infringement to prove its defence by establishing that its
			<lb />
			conduct with respect to foreign regulatory procedures was in
			<lb />
			compliance with the conditions of Section 55.2(1).
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			7.47 In reaching this conclusion, the Panel also considered
			<lb />
			Canada&apos;s additional arguments that both the negotiating history of
			<lb />
			Article 30 of the TRIPS Agreement and the subsequent practices of
			<lb />
			certain WTO Member governments supported the view that Article
			<lb />
			30 was understood to permit regulatory review exceptions similar
			<lb />
			to Section 55.2(1). The Panel did not accord any weight to either
			<lb />
			of those arguments, however, because there was no documented
			<lb />
			evidence of the claimed negotiating understanding, and because
			<lb />
			the subsequent acts by individual countries did not constitute
			<lb />
			&quot;practice in the application of the treaty which establishes the
			<lb />
			agreement of the parties regarding its interpretation&quot; within the
			<lb />
			meaning of Article 31.3(b) of the Vienna Convention.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			7.48 A final objection to the Panel&apos;s general conclusion remains to
			<lb />
			be addressed. Although the point was raised only briefly in the
			<lb />
			parties&apos; legal arguments, the Panel was compelled to acknowledge
			<lb />
			that the economic impact of the regulatory review exception could
			<lb />
			be considerable. According to information supplied by Canada
			<lb />
			itself, in the case of patented pharmaceutical products
			<lb />
			approximately three to six-and-a-half years are required for
			<lb />
			generic drug producers to develop and obtain regulatory approval
			<lb />
			for their products. If there were no regulatory review exception
			<lb />
			allowing competitors to apply for regulatory approval during the
			<lb />
			term of the patent, therefore, the patent owner would be able to
			<lb />
			extend its period of market exclusivity, de facto, for some part of
			<lb />
			that three to six-and-half year period, depending on how much, if
			<lb />
			any, of the development process could be performed during the
			<lb />
			term of the patent under other exceptions, such as the scientific or
			<lb />
			experimental use exception. The Panel believed it was necessary to
			<lb />
			ask whether measures having such a significant impact on the
			<lb />
			economic interests of patent owners could be called a &quot;limited&quot;
			<lb />
			exception to patent rights.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			103. This Court notices that the phraseology of the Canadian provision
			<lb />
			(Section 55.2.1) is closely similar to Section 107A(a). Given this fact, the
			<lb />
			DSP ruling assumes significance. It noticed that firms which -assemble and
			<lb />
			market the final generic product‖ oftentimes do not have technological
			<lb />
			expertise or capacity to produce the active ingredient (the chemical product
			<lb />
			that generates the desired medicinal effect or &quot;API&quot;). This API is produced
			<lb />
			by a specialized manufacturer and sold to the generic producer. The latter
			<lb />
			assembles the API with other agents and creates the final product in a form
			<lb />
			that can be used by the ultimate consumer. The DSP stated that the conduct
			<lb />
			of such generic manufacturer and the API producer&quot;s activities are covered
			<lb />
			by the regulatory or research exception.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-7.5 To qualify for exemption under Section 55.2(1), such
			<lb />
			activities by either fine chemical producers or generic producers
			<lb />
			must be &quot;solely for uses reasonably related to the development and
			<lb />
			submission of information required&quot; by any law, Canadian or non-
			<lb />
			Canadian, that &quot;regulates the manufacture, construction, use or
			<lb />
			sale of any product&quot;. In answer to a question from the Panel,
			<lb />
			Canada stated that, although Canadian marketing regulations for
			<lb />
			generic producers did not require production runs to demonstrate
			<lb />
			the applicant&apos;s ability to maintain quality production in
			<lb />
			commercial volumes373, the statute would allow either fine
			<lb />
			chemical manufacturers or generic producers to undertake such
			<lb />
			production runs if they were required by regulations in other
			<lb />
			countries.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			104. The Panel&quot;s view on this aspect is clear and unambiguous:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			-7.45 In the Panel&apos;s view, however, Canada&apos;s regulatory review
			<lb />
			exception is a &quot;limited exception&quot; within the meaning of TRIPS
			<lb />
			Article 30. It is &quot;limited&quot; because of the narrow scope of its
			<lb />
			curtailment of Article 28.1 rights. As long as the exception is
			<lb />
			confined to conduct needed to comply with the requirements of the
			<lb />
			regulatory approval process, the extent of the acts unauthorized by
			<lb />
			the right holder that are permitted by it will be small and narrowly
			<lb />
			bounded. Even though regulatory approval processes may require
			<lb />
			substantial amounts of test production to demonstrate reliable
			<lb />
			manufacturing, the patent owner&apos;s rights themselves are not
			<lb />
			impaired any further by the size of such production runs, as long
			<lb />
			as they are solely for regulatory purposes and no commercial use
			<lb />
			is made of resulting final products.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			7.46 The Panel found no basis for believing that activities seeking
			<lb />
			product approvals under foreign regulatory procedures would be
			<lb />
			any less subject to these limitations. There is no a priori basis to
			<lb />
			assume that the requirements of foreign regulatory procedures will
			<lb />
			require activities unrelated to legitimate objectives of product
			<lb />
			quality and safety, nor has the EC provided any evidence to that
			<lb />
			effect. Nor is there any reason to assume that Canadian law would
			<lb />
			apply the exception in cases where foreign requirements clearly
			<lb />
			had no regulatory purpose. Nor, finally, is there any reason to
			<lb />
			assume that it will be any more difficult to enforce the
			<lb />
			requirements of Canadian law when Canadian producers claim
			<lb />
			exceptions under foreign procedures.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			105.
			<lb />
			It is clear, therefore, that neither the quantity used nor the place of
			<lb />
			research and development or information (i.e. within the country granting
			<lb />
			patent or on foreign soil) is per se conclusive that the claim to use the Bolar
			<lb />
			or research exception has to be rejected. Instead, the conduct or action of the
			<lb />
			individual or entity making, using, constructing or selling the patented
			<lb />
			product or invention and the purpose for which it sought to be used (i.e. end
			<lb />
			use and that it should not be commercial) would be important and decisive
			<lb />
			whether the exporting or purchasing entity intends to use the patented
			<lb />
			product for commercial purposes.
			<lb />
			Tests necessary to regulate the use of the Section 107A exemption
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			106.
			<lb />
			This Court, in the previous parts of the present judgment, has
			<lb />
			rejected Bayer&quot;s argument with respect to the interpretation of Section 107A.
			<lb />
			Nevertheless, the court is also cognizant of the fact that export of patented
			<lb />
			invention can potentially be troublesome to the patent owner; an unregulated
			<lb />
			export activity can result in exploitation of the Bolar exemption beyond what
			<lb />
			can be considered &quot;reasonably&quot; related to obtaining approval under laws of
			<lb />
			India or another country. The wide nature of reliefs claimed by Bayer in the
			<lb />
			writ petition, i.e direct seizure of export consignment, direction to customs
			<lb />
			authorities to insist on labelling of products to facilitate their seizure and
			<lb />
			other such reliefs, in the opinion of the court, cannot be granted in a writ
			<lb />
			proceeding because whether the research provision has been invoked
			<lb />
			correctly can be determined by an examination of facts and also seeking
			<lb />
			expert opinion wherever needed. Equally, directing the executive to ensure
			<lb />
			labelling of the products sought to be exported, cannot be the subject matter
			<lb />
			of judicial review proceedings.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			107.
			<lb />
			That brings the question to what is use, sale, etc &quot;reasonably related&quot;
			<lb />
			for the purpose of developing information, ultimately used for in compliance
			<lb />
			with regulatory processes and laws in or outside India? Ultimately, on this
			<lb />
			aspect, there cannot be an ironclad rule or bright line as to what acts are
			<lb />
			reasonably related to the use or sale of the product, with the object of using
			<lb />
			the developed information to satisfy the regulations.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			108. The Canada dispute case (supra) is a clear authority which instructs
			<lb />
			that the volume of use, sale, construction, etc of a patented invention -or the
			<lb />
			quantum is itself inconclusive on the issue. Some guidance is, however,
			<lb />
			available in this regard by the UK Intellectual Property Office (UKIPO) and
			<lb />
			Medicines and Healthcare products Regulatory Agency (MHRA). The
			<lb />
			guidelines issued in this regard are extracted below:
			<lb />
			
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-The carrying out of chemical and biological synthetic
			<lb />
			processes suitable for the making, disposal or keeping of the
			<lb />
			active substance(s) including the manufacture or the import of
			<lb />
			batches in quantities sufficient to provide material for
			<lb />
			preparing investigative batches of the medicinal product and to
			<lb />
			validate the processes to the satisfaction of the competent
			<lb />
			authorities.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			
			<lb />
			The development, testing and use of the associated
			<lb />
			analytical techniques for the above.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			
			<lb />
			The development of the final pharmaceutical composition
			<lb />
			and manufacturing processes for the medicinal product to be
			<lb />
			marketed including the making, disposal or keeping or import
			<lb />
			of product batches in quantities sufficient to conduct the
			<lb />
			necessary pre-clinical tests, clinical and bioavailability trials
			<lb />
			and stability studies of the medicinal product and to validate
			<lb />
			the processes to the satisfaction of the competent authorities.
			<lb />
			
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The development, testing and use of the associated
			<lb />
			analytical techniques for the above.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			
			<lb />
			The manufacture and supply to the competent authorities
			<lb />
			of samples of active substances, their precursors, intermediates
			<lb />
			or impurities and of finished product samples.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			
			<lb />
			The compilation and submission of an MA or Variation
			<lb />
			application and application for an MA.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(The acronym -MA‖ refers to marketing approval of a
			<lb />
			pharmaceutical product).
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			109. During end of 2012, the UKIPO consulted stakeholders on whether
			<lb />
			the Act should be changed to include an exemption from patent infringement
			<lb />
			for activities involved in preparing or running clinical or field trials which
			<lb />
			use innovative drugs. The changes became effective from 01.12.2014. The
			<lb />
			new guidelines are extracted below:
			<lb />
			
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-obtaining or varying an authorisation to sell or supply,
			<lb />
			or offer to sell or supply, a medicinal product (whether in
			<lb />
			the United Kingdom or elsewhere);
			<lb />
			
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			complying with any regulatory requirement imposed
			<lb />
			(whether in the United Kingdom or elsewhere) in relation
			<lb />
			to such an authorisation
			<lb />
			
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			enabling a government or public authority (whether in the
			<lb />
			United Kingdom or elsewhere), or a person (whether in the
			<lb />
			United Kingdom or elsewhere) with functions of:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			
			<lb />
			providing health care on behalf of such a
			<lb />
			government or public authority, or
			<lb />
			
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			providing advice to, or on behalf of, such a
			<lb />
			government or public authority about the provision
			<lb />
			of health care, to carry out an assessment of
			<lb />
			suitability of a medicinal product for human use for
			<lb />
			the purpose of determining whether to use it, or
			<lb />
			recommend its use, in the provision of health care.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			110. Thus, the volume of the patented product and its use for research and
			<lb />
			development of information cannot be prescribed by any one norm. Each
			<lb />
			case merits an analysis of the evidence, the proof regarding the regulatory
			<lb />
			concerns is to be based on it. At the same time, this cannot be short circuited
			<lb />
			by approaching and seeking relief under Article 226 of the Constitution.
			<lb />
			Bayer&quot;s claim that the court should have directed the authorities to seize or
			<lb />
			prohibit quantities of articles which Natco, or someone else sought to export,
			<lb />
			is not based on any obligation cast upon Customs authorities, in law. Further,
			<lb />
			even for the court to issue blanket directions of the kind, sought by Bayer, in
			<lb />
			its writ petition, is not feasible, because whether such seizure or prohibition
			<lb />
			or labelling ought to be mandatory, are aspects to be worked out, at the
			<lb />
			policy level, by the executive government, and not upon the court&quot;s
			<lb />
			understanding. If Bayer&quot;s claim were to succeed on this score, not only
			<lb />
			would the court become a proactive institution in framing policy and
			<lb />
			evolving normative standards in respect of spheres that have public
			<lb />
			repercussions, but would be exposed to the criticism that it would do so at
			<lb />
			the interests of private parties; moreover the episodic nature of writ
			<lb />
			jurisdiction is such that at the behest of a patent proprietor, sometimes even
			<lb />
			on its apprehension, the court would be in effect legislating policy in the
			<lb />
			guise of interpretation of law. Equally, the direction given for permission to
			<lb />
			export, in the course of writ proceedings, (in Natco&quot;s case of howsoever
			<lb />
			miniscule an amount of API) was inappropriate.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			111. The approach of the learned single judge in permitting export, without
			<lb />
			any inquiry and holding that export of 1000 or 2000 tablets constituted
			<lb />
			reasonable use, in this case, cannot be countenanced. In such case, upon the
			<lb />
			patent proprietor alleging the infringement was to institute legal proceedings
			<lb />
			to injunct the alleged exporter or seller, it is equally possible for the seller or
			<lb />
			exporter to seek a declaration or appropriate relief (including in a suit for
			<lb />
			groundless threat, if such action lies) that its overseas sales are for research
			<lb />
			and purposes covered by Section 107A. This Court is of the opinion that the
			<lb />
			inquiry and adjudication in such cases would be in regard to the following:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(1) The patent granted;
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(2) The nature of the product or elements sought to be exported;
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(3) The details of the party or party importing the product,
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(4) The quantity sought to be exported
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(5) Other particulars with respect to the end use of the product, to
			<lb />
			establish that it is solely for research and development of information to
			<lb />
			regulatory authorities in the other country;
			<lb />
		</p>


		<p>
			(6) All particulars regarding the relevant regulations, covering the kind
			<lb />
			and scope of inquiry, including the quantities of the product (i.e the patented
			<lb />
			product or compound, API or fine chemical needed). These details must be
			<lb />
			supplied by the exporter/seller of the product to the overseas buyer. In case
			<lb />
			the defendant is not the seller, it should disclose who had purchased the
			<lb />
			product in the relevant quantities, to facilitate its impleadment in the
			<lb />
			proceedings. In the event it cannot do so, the consequences of such result
			<lb />
			ought to be considered by the court.
			<lb />
		</p>


		<p>
			(7) If the regulations are in the language of that country, an authentic
			<lb />
			English translation to facilitate a speedy resolution;
			<lb />
			(8) Appropriate interim order, including undertaking by way of affidavit
			<lb />
			to compensate the plaintiff, in the event the suit were to be decreed and the
			<lb />
			extent of such monetary compensation. The affidavit should be of an
			<lb />
			authorized personnel, and kept alive during the pendency of litigation, duly
			<lb />
			authenticated by the board of director or other controlling body of the
			<lb />
			defendant-and whenever the company or entity undergoes amalgamation or
			<lb />
			transfer, suitable undertaking from the successor organization;
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(9) If necessary, verification through the Indian mission (and its trade
			<lb />
			division) abroad regarding the authentication of the third party and/ or its
			<lb />
			facilities abroad.
			<lb />
		</p>


		<p>
			(10) If it is held by the court that the exporter is not involved in sale or
			<lb />
			export of any patented product, but a generic article, unprotected by patent
			<lb />
			law, when denying relief, suitable restitutionary relief should be awarded to
			<lb />
			the defendants in monetary terms, to preclude litigation that prevents trade or
			<lb />
			competition.
			<lb />
			The above aspects are only indicative of the matters that need
			<lb />
			examination, they are in no way exhaustive and the court may consider any
			<lb />
			other matter relevant to the subject.
			<lb />
			Postscript
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			112. The TRIPS Agreement (1994) mentions in Article 7, as an objective,
			<lb />
			the need to balance IP rights:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			-The protection and enforcement of intellectual property rights
			<lb />
			should contribute to the promotion of technological innovation
			<lb />
			and to the transfer and dissemination of technology, [...] in a
			<lb />
			manner conducive to a balance of rights and obligations.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			113. The Doha Declaration-(i.e. the Declaration on the TRIPS Agreement
			<lb />
			and Public Health, adopted on 14.11.2001) does not contain any express
			<lb />
			mention of such need to strive for balance. It, however alludes, significantly
			<lb />
			the role necessary through -balanced rules &quot;thereby recognizing the need
			<lb />
			for all people to benefit from the increased opportunities and welfare gains
			<lb />
			that intellectual property -as part of the multilateral trading system -can
			<lb />
			generate. The 2005 Decision of the General Council on the amendment of
			<lb />
			the TRIPS Agreement also impliedly flags the concern of balancing
			<lb />
			humanitarian and development goals on the one hand, and right-holder
			<lb />
			interests, on the other, in the public health field.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			114. In the context of IP rights, the concept of balance was explained
			<lb />
			eloquently in the dissenting opinion of Judge Kozinski in White v Samsung
			<lb />
			Electronics America, Inc. 989 F.2d 1512 (Ninth Circuit, 1993) where he
			<lb />
			stated:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			intellectual property law is full of careful balances between
			<lb />
			what&apos;s set aside for the owner and what&apos;s left in the public
			<lb />
			domain for the rest of us: The relatively short life of patents;
			<lb />
			the longer, but finite, life of copyrights; copyright&apos;s idea
			<lb />
			expression dichotomy; the fair use doctrine; the prohibition on
			<lb />
			copyrighting facts; the compulsory license of television
			<lb />
			broadcasts and musical compositions; federal preemption of
			<lb />
			overbroad state intellectual property laws; the nominative use
			<lb />
			doctrine in trademark law; the right to make soundalike
			<lb />
			recordings. All of these diminish an intellectual property
			<lb />
			owner&apos;s rights. All let the public use something created by
			<lb />
			someone else. But all are necessary to maintain a free
			<lb />
			environment in which creative genius can flourish.‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			115. The history of the Bolar provision highlights that the interest in
			<lb />
			creativity and progress was not to be undermined by the seemingly wide
			<lb />
			nature of patent rights; in the context of essential products such as drugs,
			<lb />
			diagnostic aids, medical devices and other articles, the teachings in the
			<lb />
			patent necessarily do not lead to its use by the public, upon their lapse to the
			<lb />
			public domain. To fulfill drug acceptability standards prescribed by
			<lb />
			regulatory authorities, further tests are to be conducted. The Roche v
			<lb />
			Bolar decision elicited immediate Congressional response and the Hutch
			<lb />
			Waxman Act was enacted, in effect, nullifying that decision. TRIPS
			<lb />
			recognised the need for Bolar like research provisions, enabling research and
			<lb />
			development in numerous ways which relieve those involved in such
			<lb />
			activities, of the charge of patent infringement. Therefore, a constricted and
			<lb />
			narrow textual interpretation of such provisions is not called for.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			116. This court notes, furthermore, that as early as in 1946, the Constitution
			<lb />
			of the World Health organization (WHO) recognized that the -the enjoyment
			<lb />
			of the highest attainable standard of health is one of the fundamental rights
			<lb />
			of every human being without distinction of race, religion, political belief,
			<lb />
			economic or social condition.‖ Later, the International Covenant on
			<lb />
			Economic, Social and Cultural Rights, by Article 12 stated that:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			1. The States Parties to the present Covenant recognize the
			<lb />
			right of everyone to the enjoyment of the highest attainable
			<lb />
			standard of physical and mental health.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			2. The steps to be taken by the States Parties to the present
			<lb />
			Covenant to achieve the full realization of this right shall
			<lb />
			include those necessary for:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a)The provision for the reduction of the still birth rate and of
			<lb />
			infant mortality and for the healthy development of the child;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b) The improvement of all aspects of environmental and
			<lb />
			industrial hygiene;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(c) The prevention, treatment and control of epidemic, endemic,
			<lb />
			occupational and other diseases;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(d) The creation of conditions which would assure to all
			<lb />
			medical service and medical attention in the event of sickness..‖
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			117. This Court is of the opinion that it is necessary for national courts to
			<lb />
			be aware and cognizant of these obligations, even while considering the
			<lb />
			assertion of property rights which it has to enforce. It is here that the
			<lb />
			concerned national courts&quot; constitutional ethos and the values embodied in it
			<lb />
			also need consideration: whether they can be given primacy or not is to be
			<lb />
			decided on a case to case, fact dependent basis. Article 47 of the Indian
			<lb />
			Constitution obliges the State to ensure that the standards of public health of
			<lb />
			all are ensured and maintained and policies are to be fashioned appropriately.
			<lb />
			Article 21, which ensures the right to life and liberty, has been interpreted by
			<lb />
			our Supreme Court as including certain guarantees to health care access.
			<lb />
			Given these paradigms, an interpretation that furthers the objectives of
			<lb />
			Section 107A (and the previous research enabling existing in the Patents Act,
			<lb />
			i.e. Section 47) and Article 30 of TRIPS is to be preferred. This court has
			<lb />
			added these as a postscript-rather than in the main body of its findings,-
			<lb />
			inasmuch as these aspects too need to be discussed appropriately, in the
			<lb />
			context of patent infringement claims, which generally tend to be confined in
			<lb />
			the &quot;silo&quot; of assertion and negation of private rights and their enforcement,
			<lb />
			despite (at times) larger implications to the general public in terms of
			<lb />
			outcomes.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			Conclusions
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;Each generation stands on the shoulders of those who have
			<lb />
			gone before them, just as I did as a young PhD student in
			<lb />
			Cambridge, inspired by the work of Isaac Newton, James Clerk
			<lb />
			Maxwell and Albert Einstein.‖
			<lb />
			Stephen Hawking
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			118. The Bolar exemption is the global community&quot;s thought out design to
			<lb />
			ensure that the enclosure of intellectual property rights, granted to
			<lb />
			inventions, does not last beyond the term assured and that the general public
			<lb />
			is afforded with the end of the bargain which every society guarantees while
			<lb />
			sealing a patent i.e. access to the technology or invention for generations to
			<lb />
			come. But for a Bolar exemption, a third party manufacturer would not be
			<lb />
			able to start experimentation and ready a product, for its availability to the
			<lb />
			general public after the expiry of the patent term.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			119. In the light of the above discussion and findings, it is held and directed
			<lb />
			as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			(a) Sale, use, construction of patented products (by individuals and
			<lb />
			entities that do not hold patents) in terms of Section 107A of the Act for
			<lb />
			purposes both within the country and abroad is authorized and legal provided
			<lb />
			the seller ensures that the end use and purpose of sale/export is reasonably
			<lb />
			related to research and development of information in compliance with
			<lb />
			regulations or laws of India (or the importing country), for its submission in
			<lb />
			accordance with such laws. The impugned judgment of the learned single
			<lb />
			judge and the findings recorded on this aspect are accordingly affirmed.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b) A dispute about the sale, i.e. whether it is legitimately related to the
			<lb />
			reasonable end use or purpose of research etc. for submission of information
			<lb />
			is properly the subject matter of a civil suit in which the full range of reliefs
			<lb />
			available in law can be granted having regard to the circumstances and the
			<lb />
			evidence led;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(c) The court trying the suit would suitably take into account the factors
			<lb />
			that need to be examined (which are elaborated in the previous part of this
			<lb />
			judgment) and other relevant factors;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(d) Such disputes are not ordinarily the subject of public law proceedings,
			<lb />
			as they involve investigation into facts and also result in reliefs to private
			<lb />
			parties for enforcement of private property entitlements. Therefore, such
			<lb />
			disputes should not be the subject matter of writ proceedings; petitions under
			<lb />
			Article 226 of the Constitution of India should not be entertained and
			<lb />
			wherever filed, the parties should be relegated to civil remedies.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(e) CS(OS) No.1090/2011-subsequently renumbered as CS(Comm)
			<lb />
			33/2017 (Bayer&quot;s suit against Natco) is pending. Issues were framed in the
			<lb />
			said suit, on 09.01.2017. In these circumstances, no separate orders are
			<lb />
			called for.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(f)
			<lb />
			CS(OS) (Comm) 1592/2016 filed by Bayer against Alembic is
			<lb />
			restored to the file of this Court. The concerned learned single judge would
			<lb />
			proceed to try it.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(g) Both the above suits shall be decided in accordance with law, keeping
			<lb />
			in mind the discussion in this judgment and the factors indicated above.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			120. For the above reasons, the letters patent appeal has to fail; LPA
			<lb />
			359/2017 is dismissed, subject to the observations in this judgment.
			<lb />
			RFA(OS)(Comm) 6/2017 is for the reasons indicated above and subject to
			<lb />
			the directions, allowed. In the peculiar circumstances of the case, there shall
			<lb />
			be no order on costs.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			S. RAVINDRA BHAT
			<lb />
			(JUDGE)
			<lb />
			SANJEEV SACHDEVA
			<lb />
			(JUDGE)
			<lb />
			APRIL 22, 2019
		</p>


	</text>
</tei>