<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			Crl.M.C. 2005/2016
			<lb />
			Page 1 of 8
			<lb />
			*
			<lb />
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF DELHI AT NEW DELHI
			<lb />
			+
			<lb />
			CRL.M.C. 2005/2016
			<lb />
			Date of Decision: August 19 th , 2016
			<lb />
			SAHEB LAL
			<lb />
			..... Petitioner
			<lb />
			Through
			<lb />
			Mr.M.K. Chaudhary, Advocate.
			<lb />
			versus
			<lb />
			THE STATE &amp; ANR
			<lb />
			..... Respondents
			<lb />
			Through
			<lb />
			Ms.Meenakshi Chauhan, APP for the
			<lb />
			State.
			<lb />
			SI Yogesh Kumar, PS Mayapuri.
			<lb />
			Respondent no.2 in person.
			<lb />
		</front>

		<body>
			CORAM:
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE P.S TEJI.
			<lb />
			P.S.TEJI, J.
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			The present petition under Section 482 Cr.P.C. has been filed by
			<lb />
			the petitioner, namely, Sh. Saheb Lal for quashing of FIR
			<lb />
			No.204/2013 dated 24.08.2013, under Sections 498-A IPC registered
			<lb />
			at Police Station Maya Puri on the basis of Mediation Report of Delhi
			<lb />
			Mediation Centre, Tis Hazari Courts, Delhi in view of the settlement
			<lb />
			arrived at between the petitioner and respondent no.2, namely, Smt.
			<lb />
			Vidyawati on 04.01.2016.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Learned Additional Public Prosecutor for respondent-State
			<lb />
			submitted that the respondent No.2, present in the Court has been
			<lb />
			identified to be the complainant/first-informant of the FIR in question
			<lb />
			by SI Yogesh Kumar.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			The factual matrix of the present case is that the marriage was
			<lb />
			solemnized between petitioner and the complainant/respondent no.2
			<lb />
			on 13.04.2004 according to Hindu rites and ceremonies and a male
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.M.C. 2005/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 2 of 8
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			child, namely, Shiv was born out of the said wedlock on 25.02.2005.
			<lb />
			The husband of the complainant used to beat her and demand money
			<lb />
			from her instead of giving her enough money to run the house.
			<lb />
			Thereafter, the complainant got lodged the complaint following
			<lb />
			which the FIR in question was registered against the petitioner. During
			<lb />
			the pendency of the proceedings, the matter was settled between the
			<lb />
			petitioner and the respondent no. 2.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Respondent No.2, present in the Court, submitted that the
			<lb />
			dispute between the parties has been amicably resolved and that the
			<lb />
			petitioner and respondent no. 2 have mutually agreed to live together
			<lb />
			peacefully in a healthy atmosphere and shall not give any chance of
			<lb />
			complaint. It is agreed that the respondent no. 2 shall withdraw the
			<lb />
			cases filed by her against the petitioner and that both the parties shall
			<lb />
			be left with no claim against each other with respect to the present
			<lb />
			matter.
			<lb />
			Respondent No.2 affirmed the contents of the aforesaid
			<lb />
			settlement and of her affidavit dated 18.05.2016 supporting this
			<lb />
			petition. In the affidavit, she has stated that she has no objection if the
			<lb />
			FIR in question is quashed. All the disputes and differences have been
			<lb />
			resolved through mutual consent. Now no dispute with petitioner
			<lb />
			survives and so, the proceedings arising out of the FIR in question be
			<lb />
			brought to an end. Statement of the respondent No.2 has been
			<lb />
			recorded in this regard in which she stated that she has entered into a
			<lb />
			compromise with the petitioner and has settled all the disputes with
			<lb />
			him. She further stated that she has no objection if the FIR in question
			<lb />
			is quashed.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.M.C. 2005/2016
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 3 of 8
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			5.
			<lb />
			In Gian Singh v. State of Punjab (2012) 10 SCC 303 Apex
			<lb />
			Court has recognized the need of amicable resolution of disputes in
			<lb />
			cases like the instant one, by observing as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;61.
			<lb />
			In other words, the High Court must consider
			<lb />
			whether it would be unfair or contrary to the interest of justice
			<lb />
			to continue with the criminal proceedings or continuation of
			<lb />
			criminal proceedings would tantamount to abuse of process of
			<lb />
			law despite settlement and compromise between the victim
			<lb />
			and the wrongdoer and whether to secure the ends of justice, it
			<lb />
			is appropriate that criminal case is put to an end and if the
			<lb />
			answer to the above question(s) is in the affirmative, the High
			<lb />
			Court shall be well within its jurisdiction to quash the criminal
			<lb />
			proceedings.&quot;
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			The aforesaid dictum stands reiterated by the Apex Court in a
			<lb />
			recent judgment in Narinder Singh v. State of Punjab (2014) 6 SCC
			<lb />
			466. The relevant observations of the Apex Court in Narinder Singh
			<lb />
			(Supra) are as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;29. In view of the aforesaid discussion, we sum up and lay
			<lb />
			down the following principles by which the High Court would
			<lb />
			be guided in giving adequate treatment to the settlement
			<lb />
			between the parties and exercising its power under Section 482
			<lb />
			of the Code while accepting the settlement and quashing the
			<lb />
			proceedings or refusing to accept the settlement with direction
			<lb />
			to continue with the criminal proceedings:
			<lb />
			29.1 Power conferred under Section 482 of the Code is to be
			<lb />
			distinguished from the power which lies in the Court to
			<lb />
			compound the offences under Section 320 of the Code. No
			<lb />
			doubt, under Section 482 of the Code, the High Court has
			<lb />
			inherent power to quash the criminal proceedings even in those
			<lb />
			cases which are not compoundable, where the parties have
			<lb />
			settled the matter between themselves. However, this power is
			<lb />
			to be exercised sparingly and with caution.
			<lb />
			29.2. When the parties have reached the settlement and on that
			<lb />
			basis petition for quashing the criminal proceedings is filed,
			<lb />
			the guiding factor in such cases would be to secure:
			<lb />
			(i) ends of justice, or
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.M.C. 2005/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 4 of 8
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			(ii) to prevent abuse of the process of any court.
			<lb />
			While exercising the power the High Court is to form an
			<lb />
			opinion on either of the aforesaid two objectives.
			<lb />
			29.3. Such a power is not to be exercised in those prosecutions
			<lb />
			which involve heinous and serious offences of mental
			<lb />
			depravity or offences like murder, rape, dacoity, etc. Such
			<lb />
			offences are not private in nature and have a serious impact on
			<lb />
			society. Similarly, for the offences alleged to have been
			<lb />
			committed under special statute like the Prevention of
			<lb />
			Corruption Act or the offences committed by public servants
			<lb />
			while working in that capacity are not to be quashed merely on
			<lb />
			the basis of compromise between the victim and the offender.
			<lb />
			29.4. On the other hand, those criminal cases having
			<lb />
			overwhelmingly and predominantly civil character,
			<lb />
			particularly those arising out of commercial transactions or
			<lb />
			arising out of matrimonial relationship or family disputes
			<lb />
			should be quashed when the parties have resolved their entire
			<lb />
			disputes among themselves.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			The inherent powers of the High Court ought to be exercised to
			<lb />
			prevent the abuse of process of law and to secure the ends of justice.
			<lb />
			The respondent no.2 agrees to the quashing of the FIR in question
			<lb />
			without any threat or coercion or undue influence and has stated that
			<lb />
			the matter has been settled out of her own free will. As the matter has
			<lb />
			been settled and compromised amicably, so, there would be an
			<lb />
			extraordinary delay in the process of law if the legal proceedings
			<lb />
			between the parties are carried on. So, this Court is of the considered
			<lb />
			opinion that this is a fit case to invoke the jurisdiction under Section
			<lb />
			482 Cr.P.C. to prevent the abuse of process of law and to secure the
			<lb />
			ends of justice.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			The incorporation of inherent power under Section 482 Cr.P.C.
			<lb />
			is meant to deal with the situation in the absence of express provision
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.M.C. 2005/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 5 of 8
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			of law to secure the ends of justice such as, where the process is
			<lb />
			abused or misused; where the ends of justice cannot be secured; where
			<lb />
			the process of law is used for unjust or unlawful object; to avoid the
			<lb />
			causing of harassment to any person by using the provision of Cr.P.C.
			<lb />
			or to avoid the delay of the legal process in the delivery of justice.
			<lb />
			Whereas, the inherent power is not to be exercised to circumvent the
			<lb />
			express provisions of law.
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			It is settled law that the inherent power of the High Court under
			<lb />
			Section 482 Cr.P.C. should be used sparingly. The Hon&apos;ble Apex
			<lb />
			Court in the case of State of Maharashtra through CBI v. Vikram
			<lb />
			Anatrai Doshi and Ors. MANU/SC/0842/2014 and in the case of
			<lb />
			Inder Singh Goswami v. State of Uttaranchal MANU/SC/0808/2009
			<lb />
			has observed that powers under Section 482 Cr.P.C. must be exercised
			<lb />
			sparingly, carefully and with great caution. Only when the Court
			<lb />
			comes to the conclusion that there would be manifest injustice or there
			<lb />
			would be abuse of the process of the Court if such power is not
			<lb />
			exercised, Court would quash the proceedings.
			<lb />
			10. It is a well settled law that where the High Court is convinced
			<lb />
			that the offences are entirely personal in nature and therefore do not
			<lb />
			affect public peace or tranquility and where it feels that quashing of
			<lb />
			such proceedings on account of compromise would bring about peace
			<lb />
			and would secure ends of justice, it should not hesitate to quash them.
			<lb />
			In such cases, pursuing prosecution would be waste of time and
			<lb />
			energy. Non-compoundable offences are basically an obstruction in
			<lb />
			entering into compromise. In certain cases, the main offence is
			<lb />
			compoundable but the connected offences are not. In the case of B.S.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.M.C. 2005/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 6 of 8
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Joshi and others v. State of Haryana and another 2003 (4) SCC 675
			<lb />
			the Hon&apos;ble Apex Court observed that even though the provisions of
			<lb />
			Section 320 Cr.P.C. would not apply to such offences which are not
			<lb />
			compoundable, it did not limit or affect the powers under Section 482
			<lb />
			Cr.P.C. The Hon&apos;ble Apex Court laid down that if for the purpose of
			<lb />
			securing the ends of justice, quashing of FIR becomes necessary,
			<lb />
			section 320 Cr.P.C. would not be a bar to the exercise of power of
			<lb />
			quashing. In the nutshell, the Hon&apos;ble Apex Court justified the
			<lb />
			exercise of powers under Section 482 Cr.P.C. to quash the
			<lb />
			proceedings to secure the ends of justice in view of the special facts
			<lb />
			and circumstances of the case, even where the offences were non-
			<lb />
			compoundable.
			<lb />
			In the light of the aforesaid, this Court is of the view that
			<lb />
			notwithstanding the fact the offence under Section 498A IPC is a non-
			<lb />
			compoundable offence, there should be no impediment in quashing the
			<lb />
			FIR under this section, if the Court is otherwise satisfied that the facts
			<lb />
			and circumstances of the case so warrant.
			<lb />
			11. The Courts in India are now normally taking the view that
			<lb />
			endeavour should be taken to promote conciliation and secure speedy
			<lb />
			settlement of disputes relating to marriage and family affairs such as,
			<lb />
			matrimonial disputes between the couple or/and between the wife and
			<lb />
			her in-laws. India being a vast country naturally has large number of
			<lb />
			married persons resulting into high numbers of matrimonial disputes
			<lb />
			due to differences in temperament, life-styles, opinions, thoughts etc.
			<lb />
			between such couples, due to which majority is coming to the Court to
			<lb />
			get redressal. In its 59 th report, the Law Commission of India had
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.M.C. 2005/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 7 of 8
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			emphasized that while dealing with disputes concerning the family, the
			<lb />
			Court ought to adopt an approach radically different from that
			<lb />
			adopted in ordinary civil proceedings and that it should make
			<lb />
			reasonable efforts at settlement before the commencement of the trial.
			<lb />
			Further it is also the constitutional mandate for speedy disposal of
			<lb />
			such disputes and to grant quick justice to the litigants. But, our
			<lb />
			Courts are already over burdened due to pendency of large number of
			<lb />
			cases because of which it becomes difficult for speedy disposal of
			<lb />
			matrimonial disputes alone. As the matrimonial disputes are mainly
			<lb />
			between the husband and the wife and personal matters are involved
			<lb />
			in such disputes, so, it requires conciliatory procedure to bring a
			<lb />
			settlement between them. Nowadays, mediation has played a very
			<lb />
			important role in settling the disputes, especially, matrimonial
			<lb />
			disputes and has yielded good results. The Court must exercise its
			<lb />
			inherent power under Section 482 Cr.P.C. to put an end to the
			<lb />
			matrimonial litigations at the earliest so that the parties can live
			<lb />
			peacefully.
			<lb />
			12. Since the subject matter of this FIR is essentially matrimonial,
			<lb />
			which now stands mutually and amicably settled between the parties,
			<lb />
			therefore, continuance of proceedings arising out of the FIR in
			<lb />
			question would be an exercise in futility and is a fit case for this Court
			<lb />
			to exercise its inherent jurisdiction.
			<lb />
			13. In the facts and circumstances of this case, in view of statement
			<lb />
			made by the respondent No.2 and the compromise arrived at between
			<lb />
			the parties, the FIR in question warrants to be put to an end and
			<lb />
			proceedings emanating thereupon need to be quashed.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.M.C. 2005/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 8 of 8
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			14. Accordingly, this petition is allowed and FIR No.204/2013
			<lb />
			dated 24.08.2013, under Sections 498-A IPC registered at Police
			<lb />
			Station Maya Puri and the proceedings emanating therefrom are
			<lb />
			quashed against the petitioner.
			<lb />
			15. This petition is accordingly disposed of.
			<lb />
			(P.S.TEJI)
			<lb />
			JUDGE
			<lb />
			AUGUST 19, 2016/dd
		</body>


	</text>
</tei>