<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<head>J U D G M E N T<lb/> Meenakshi Madan Rai, J.<lb/></head>

			<p>1.<lb/> The Appellants were the Plaintiffs before the learned<lb/> trial Court, in Title Suit No.08 of 2011 (Nil Kumar Dahal and Another<lb/> v. Indira Dahal and Others), a Suit for Declaration, Recovery of<lb/> Possession, Injunction and other Consequential Reliefs, against the<lb/> Respondents No.1 to 4 herein, who were the Defendants No.1 to 4<lb/> in the said Title Suit. The learned trial Court on consideration of the<lb/> evidence and all materials on record dismissed the Suit of the<lb/> Appellants, by the impugned Judgment, dated 26.07.2017.<lb/> Dissatisfied thereof this Appeal has arisen.<lb/></p>

			<p>2.<lb/> Parties shall hereinafter be referred to in their order of<lb/> appearance before the learned trial Court.<lb/></p>

			<p>3.<lb/> The Plaintiffs are blood brothers being the sons of one<lb/> Devi Prasad Dahal. The Defendant No.1 is their step mother and the<lb/> Defendant No.4 is their niece, being the daughter of their deceased<lb/> step brother, Bal Krishna Dahal, the son of Defendant No.1 and the<lb/> Plaintiffs&quot; father. Defendant No.4 is represented by her guardian<lb/> Devi Kala Sharma. Defendants No.2 and 3 are Government officials<lb/> inter alia concerned with registration of land. The Plaintiffs claim to<lb/> be governed by the Mitakshara School of Hindu Law. The dispute<lb/> between the parties pivots around the &quot;jiwni&quot; land described in the<lb/> Schedule to the Plaint, kept aside by their late father from the<lb/> ancestral properties, for his upkeep and sustenance during his<lb/> lifetime at Raley Block, East Sikkim, after partitioning the ancestral<lb/> properties amongst his sons. By the &quot;Banda Patra&quot; (&quot;Partition<lb/> Deed&quot;), Exhibit &quot;A,&quot; dated 17.05.1985, their father devised dual<lb/> conditions for the &quot;jiwni&quot; land to be passed on to his sons i.e.<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;father&quot;s &quot;jiwni&quot; share would go to the son who would look after and<lb/> perform death rites.&quot; On his passing on 23.09.2001, the Plaintiffs<lb/> and the father of the Defendant No.4, each laid claims to the said<lb/> &quot;jiwni&quot; land on grounds that each of them fulfilled the conditions laid<lb/> out in Exhibit &quot;A.&quot; Defendant No.1, for her part, while denying<lb/> governance by the Mitakshara School of Hindu Law, claims the<lb/> property on grounds that she has been in unencumbered physical<lb/> possession of the property since the execution of Exhibit &quot;A&quot; and<lb/> exercising all rights over it as its owner, sans interference from any<lb/> quarter.<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/></p>

			<p>4.(i)<lb/> Undisputedly, the property is ancestral having belonged<lb/> to the Plaintiffs&quot; great-grandfather, one Parmananda Bahun. He had<lb/> three sons Bishnu Lall (grandfather of the Plaintiffs), Purananda and<lb/> Lok Nath. Bishnu Lall and Lok Nath passed away before the<lb/> properties could be partitioned, Lok Nath having died issueless, as a<lb/> result, the properties came to be partitioned amongst the four<lb/> remaining sons of Bishnu Lall (out of his five sons) and Purananda<lb/> Bahun. One of the sons of Bishnu Lall was their father Devi Prasad.<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii)<lb/> According to the Plaintiffs, on 26.03.2010, the<lb/> Defendant No.1, who also allegedly maintains her Nepalese<lb/> citizenship, filed an application before the District Collector<lb/> (Defendant No.2), East Sikkim, seeking mutation of the &quot;jiwni&quot; land<lb/> to her name from that of Devi Prasad. Despite objections raised by<lb/> the Plaintiffs, by the impugned Order dated 03.11.2010, the<lb/> Defendant No.2, allowed mutation of the &quot;jiwni&quot; land in the name of<lb/> Defendant No.1 and ordered that Plots bearing No.450 and 452<lb/> measuring an area of 0.3050 hectares at Raley Khesey Block, be<lb/> mutated in the name of the Defendant No.1 although Plot No.452<lb/> was already mutated in the name of the Plaintiff No.2, as his share,<lb/> vide Exhibit &quot;A.&quot; That, the Order lacked jurisdiction as the<lb/> Defendant No.2 was not vested with powers to decide Title disputes<lb/> and exhibited lack of application of mind for ordering mutation of<lb/> Plot No.452 in the name of the Defendant No.1. That, as the<lb/> Plaintiffs have fulfilled the dual conditions laid down in Exhibit &quot;A,&quot;<lb/> they are entitled to the &quot;jiwni&quot; land to the exclusion of Defendant<lb/> No.1 and Defendant No.4, the latter allegedly having no locus to<lb/> claim a share in the testamentary disposition as her father (Bal<lb/> Krishna) was a Nepalese citizen and had passed away before the<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> issue of sharing of &quot;jiwni&quot; land came up for consideration. Besides,<lb/> the Partition Deed nowhere mentions that a daughter or grand-<lb/>daughter is entitled to the &quot;jiwni&quot; land. That, when proceedings<lb/> were taken up before the Defendant No.2, the Defendant No.1 had<lb/> stated that her son Bal Krishna had two sons therefore it is unclear<lb/> as to how Defendant No.4 has now emerged as the legal heir of Bal<lb/> Krishna. The Plaintiffs also objected to the Guardianship Certificate<lb/> issued to the guardian of Defendant No.4 alleging that she too is a<lb/> Nepalese citizen. Hence, the prayers in the Plaint which are<lb/> extracted hereinbelow;<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;In the circumstances the plaintiffs pray for a<lb/> Decree:<lb/></p>

			<item>i.<lb/> Declaring that the defendant no0(sic).2 has<lb/> no<lb/> right,<lb/> title<lb/> and<lb/> authority to pass<lb/> an Order(sic) dated 03/11/2010;<lb/></item>

			<item>(i)A<lb/> Declaring that late Bal Krishna Dahal<lb/> predeceased his father and having waived<lb/> to perform certain obligations towards<lb/> father, as such, his legal heirs has(sic) no<lb/> right, title and interest over the &quot;jiwni land&quot;;<lb/></item>

			<item>(i)B<lb/> Declaring that defendant no.4 not being son<lb/> of late Devi Prasad Dahal has no right, title<lb/> and interest over the &quot;Jiwni land&quot;;<lb/></item>

			<item>(i)C<lb/> Declaring that a portion of the &quot;jiwni land&quot;<lb/> cannot and shall not be mutated in the<lb/> name of defendant no.4;<lb/></item>

			<item>(i)D<lb/> Declaring that the Guardianship Certificate<lb/> obtained by Smt. D.K. Sharma by<lb/> misrepresentation of facts is liable to be set<lb/> aside and cancelled.<lb/></item>

			<item>(i)E<lb/> Praying for recovery of possession of Jiwni<lb/> land from defendant no.1.<lb/></item>

			<item>(i)F<lb/> Declaring that the defendnat(sic) no.1<lb/> being a Nepal subject has no right to claim<lb/> any share of the suit property.<lb/></item>

			<item>ii<lb/> Declaring that the Order dated 03/11/2010,<lb/> i.e. Annexure-15 to be null and void and<lb/> the same is nonest;<lb/></item>

			<item>iii.<lb/> Declaring that the Order dated 03/11/2010,<lb/> i.e. Annexure 15 be set aside and quashed.<lb/></item>

			<item>iv.<lb/> Declaring that the plaintiffs are only entitled<lb/> for the jiwni land that is Plot no.450;<lb/></item>

			<item>v.<lb/> Declaring that the schedule property cannot<lb/> and shall not be mutated in the name of the<lb/> defendant no.1;<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> vi.<lb/> In the mean time if<lb/> the<lb/> Schedule<lb/> property is mutated/transferred<lb/> in<lb/> the<lb/> name of the defendant no.1 then to set<lb/> aside, quash and cancel such mutation/<lb/> order of mutation;<lb/></item>

			<item>vii.<lb/> Declaring that the plaintiffs have their right,<lb/> title and interest on the Schedule Property<lb/></item>

			<item>viii.<lb/> A permanent injunction<lb/></item>

			<item>(a) restraining the defendant no.3 from<lb/> mutating/transferring the Schedule<lb/> Property in the name of Defendant<lb/> No.1;<lb/></item>

			<item>ix.<lb/> A temporary injunction in terms of Prayer<lb/> no.(X);<lb/></item>

			<item>x.<lb/> Any other relief or reliefs as this Hon&quot;ble<lb/> Court may deem fit and proper.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>5.<lb/> Contesting the claims of the Plaintiffs, the Defendant<lb/> No.1 while denying that neither she nor her son were citizens of<lb/> Nepal or that they were governed by the Mitakshara School of Hindu<lb/> Law, averred that they were governed by the &quot;Law of the land&quot;<lb/> which did not differentiate between male and female heirs. The<lb/> Plaintiff No.1 had voluntarily left the &quot;mul ghar&quot; (&quot;main house&quot;) in<lb/> 1983-84 as he did not get along with his father and the Plaintiff<lb/> No.2 left after the execution of Exhibit &quot;A.&quot; Consequent thereto, it<lb/> fell upon her son Bal Krishna to take care of the family and Devi<lb/> Prasad financially as he was ailing and bedridden for almost a<lb/> decade, with no moral or financial support from the Plaintiffs. All<lb/> medical expenses and expenses for death rites were arranged by<lb/> the Defendant No.1 and her son by borrowing money from their well<lb/> wishers. The Defendant No.1 asserts that she is entitled to fifty per<lb/> cent of her husband&quot;s property as per the &quot;Law of the land&quot; while<lb/> the Plaintiffs have no such entitlement on their failure to fulfill the<lb/> conditions in Exhibit &quot;A&quot; which, according to her, were &quot;to look after<lb/> their parents and perform death rites.&quot; She denies that the<lb/> Defendant No.2 had no jurisdiction to issue the impugned Order or<lb/> that only &quot;sons&quot; are entitled to the &quot;jiwni&quot; land. That, the entire Plot<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> No.452 does not belong to the Plaintiff No.2 as his Plot is numbered<lb/> &quot;452/1192&quot; which measures 0.325 hectares, while Plot No.452<lb/> measures 0.560 hectares. That, the cause of action arose after the<lb/> completion of the forty-five days death ritual of the deceased and<lb/> hence the Suit is barred by limitation, has no cause of action and is<lb/> undervalued and on these grounds, liable to be dismissed.<lb/></p>

			<p>6.<lb/> Defendant No.4, the minor daughter of late Bal Krishna<lb/> Dahal, was abandoned by her mother after her father&quot;s death and is<lb/> thus represented by her paternal aunt and legal guardian Devi Kala<lb/> Sharma, the sister of Bal Krishna, claiming to be a bona fide<lb/> Sikkimese. She had obtained a Guardianship Certificate from the<lb/> Family Court. In pith and substance, the Written Statement of the<lb/> Defendant No.4 is similar to and reiterates the averments made by<lb/> the Defendant No.1. According to her, the property kept as &quot;jiwni&quot; is<lb/> the land on which the main house stands and has been in the<lb/> unencumbered physical possession of the Defendant No.1 after the<lb/> death of her grandfather, without objection or interference from any<lb/> quarter including the Plaintiffs, hence, the Defendant No.1 is<lb/> entitled to fifty per cent of her late husband&quot;s property as per the<lb/> Law of the Land.<lb/></p>

			<p>7.<lb/> The Defendants No.2 and 3 had no Written Statements<lb/> to file.<lb/></p>

			<p>8.<lb/> It is essential for clarity to recapitulate here that earlier<lb/> in the same matter i.e. Title Suit No.08 of 2011, the learned trial<lb/> Court vide its Judgment dated 30.11.2013, concluded that the<lb/> Plaintiffs are entitled to one-third share each from the &quot;jiwni&quot; land<lb/> which was in the possession of the Defendant No.1. Calling in<lb/> question the said decision, the Defendant No.1 was before this<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> Court in Appeal being Regular First Appeal No.04 of 2014 (Indira<lb/> Dahal v. Nil Kumar Dahal and Another). The Appellant therein<lb/> (Defendant No.1 herein) argued that the Suit ought to have failed<lb/> on account of non-joinder of necessary parties as the son of Bal<lb/> Krishna was not made a party to the Suit. This Court vide its<lb/> Judgment, dated 22.04.2016, in the said RFA, remanded the matter<lb/> back to the learned trial Court for impleadment of the legal heirs<lb/> and successors of late Bal Krishna Dahal. The Plaintiffs filed their<lb/> Amended Plaint, impleading the daughter of late Bal Krishna as<lb/> Defendant No.4 in the instant Suit. The Defendants No.1 and 4 also<lb/> filed their amended responses and the learned trial Court resettled<lb/> the Issues for determination after the remand, as follows;<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;1.<lb/> Whether the Suit is maintainable?<lb/> Onus on Plaintiffs.<lb/></item>

			<item>2.<lb/> Whether the Plaintiffs have right, title and<lb/> interest in the suit property i.e., &quot;jiwni<lb/> land&quot; being plot No.450?<lb/> Onus on Plaintiffs.<lb/></item>

			<item>3.<lb/> Whether the Plaintiffs are entitled to<lb/> recover the suit land i.e. the &quot;jiwni land&quot;<lb/> from the possession of the Defendant<lb/> No.1?<lb/> Onus on Plaintiffs.<lb/></item>

			<item>4.<lb/> Whether the &quot;jiwni land&quot; can be mutated in<lb/> the name of the Defendant Nos.1 and 4?<lb/> Onus on Defendant Nos.1 and 4. (Issue<lb/> No.4<lb/> modified<lb/> vide<lb/> Order<lb/> dated:<lb/></item>

			<item>21.06.2016)<lb/></item>

			<item>5.<lb/> Whether the Defendant Nos.1 and 4 are<lb/> entitled to any share in the &quot;jiwni land&quot; as<lb/> per &quot;banda patra&quot; dated: 17.05.1985?<lb/> Onus on Defendant Nos.1 and 4.<lb/></item>

			<item>6.<lb/> Whether the Defendant Nos.1 and 4 have<lb/> already got their shares as per &quot;banda<lb/> patra&quot; dated 17.05.1985?<lb/> Onus on Plaintiffs. (Modified vide order<lb/> dated: 21.6.2016?<lb/></item>

			<item>7.<lb/> Whether the Plaintiffs have looked after<lb/> and performed the death rites of the late<lb/> Devi Prasad Dahal?<lb/> Onus on Plaintiffs.<lb/></item>

			<item>8.<lb/> Whether Devi Kala Sharma has right to act<lb/> as a guardian of the minor i.e. Defendant<lb/> No.4<lb/> in<lb/> force<lb/> of(sic)<lb/> Guardianship<lb/> Certificate?<lb/></item>

			<item>Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> Onus on Defendant No.4.<lb/></item>

			<item>9.<lb/> Whether Devi Kala Sharma has obtained<lb/> the guardianship certificate fraudulently?<lb/> Onus on Plaintiffs. (Issue framed vide<lb/> Order dated: 21.6.2016)<lb/></item>

			<item>10. Whether the Defendant No.1, being the<lb/> wife of Late Devi Prasad Dahal have(sic)<lb/> any right, title and interest over the<lb/> property recorded in the name of Late Devi<lb/> Prasad Dahal?<lb/> Onus on Defendant No.1.<lb/></item>

			<item>11. To what relief or reliefs, if any, are the<lb/> Plaintiffs entitled?<lb/> Onus on Plaintiffs.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>9.(i)<lb/> The Plaintiffs, in order to establish their case, before the<lb/> remand, had examined themselves as PW1 and PW2 and four other<lb/> witnesses being Kunta Maya Dahal (she was variously numbered as<lb/> &quot;PW3&quot; and &quot;PW2&quot; hence, hereinafter for convenience shall be<lb/> referred to by name), PW3 Man Bahadur Kharka, PW6 Krishna<lb/> Prasad Sapkota and PW7 Tanka Maya Adhikari. After remand, the<lb/> Plaintiffs again examined themselves as PW1 and PW2 and one<lb/> Laxuman Nepal, (son of Krishna Lall Nepal) as &quot;PW1&quot; and Ram<lb/> Chandra Koirala as &quot;PW2.&quot; Since Plaintiffs have also been numbered<lb/> as &quot;PW1&quot; and &quot;PW2,&quot; the witnesses above shall also be referred to<lb/> by their names to avoid confusion.<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii)<lb/> The Defendant No.1, before the remand, had examined<lb/> herself as DW1, Tika Devi Sharma as DW2, Madhav Prasad Adhikari<lb/> (he was variously numbered as &quot;DW1&quot; and &quot;DW3&quot; hence,<lb/> hereinafter shall be referred to by name) and Dol Nath Gautam (he<lb/> was variously numbered as &quot;DW3&quot; and &quot;DW4&quot; hence, hereinafter for<lb/> convenience shall be referred to by name). After remand, she<lb/> examined herself as DW1, Dhan Maya Adhikari as DW2, Dol Nath<lb/> Gautam as DW3, Punya Prasad Adhikari (witness not numbered)<lb/> and Ramesh Kumar Dahal as DW4.<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/></p>

			<item>(iii)<lb/> The Defendant No.4 examined one Laxuman Nepal, son<lb/> of Jai Narayan Nepal as DW1 (to be distinguished from Laxuman<lb/> Nepal, son of Krishna Lall Nepal, witness of the Plaintiffs), Madhav<lb/> Prasad Adhikari as DW2, Tika Devi Sharma as DW3, Bishnu<lb/> Khatiwada as DW4 and her legal guardian (Devi Kala Sharma)<lb/></item>

			<item>(witness not numbered).<lb/></item>

			<item>(iv)<lb/> Defendants No.2 and 3 had no witnesses to examine.<lb/></item>

			<p>(v)<lb/> It may be remarked here that the numbers allotted to<lb/> the witnesses by the learned trial Court are slipshod and rather<lb/> unhappily maintained, which should be discouraged. Due care ought<lb/> to be taken by the concerned Court while numbering witnesses to<lb/> avoid any conundrum in referring to them in the Judgment either by<lb/> the learned trial Court itself or by the Appellate Court. The learned<lb/> trial Court is expected to heed to this suggestion.<lb/></p>

			<p>10.<lb/> The learned trial Court while taking up the Issues for<lb/> consideration, took up Issue No.7 first and concluded that although<lb/> the Plaintiffs did perform the death rites of their father, however,<lb/> the evidence on record reflected that they had not taken care of him<lb/> during his lifetime including the time of his ailment and therefore<lb/> did not meet the dual conditions laid out in Exhibit &quot;A.&quot; The Issue<lb/> was decided against the Plaintiffs. Issue No.2 was next taken up for<lb/> consideration and it was concluded that while the Plaintiffs had only<lb/> performed the death rites of their father, late Bal Krishna had<lb/> performed the death rites and also taken care of their father by<lb/> incurring expenditure for their father&quot;s treatment vide loans<lb/> obtained from different persons and was, thus, entitled to the<lb/> &quot;jiwni&quot; land to the exclusion of the Plaintiffs. This Issue also went<lb/> against the Plaintiffs. Issues No.4, 5, 6 and 10 were taken up<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> together and relying on the provisions of the Sikkim Succession Act,<lb/> 2008, the learned trial Court held that the Defendant No.4 and the<lb/> Defendant No.1 would be eligible to inherit the properties left<lb/> behind by Bal Krishna, in equal portions and the said properties<lb/> should be mutated in their names. While deciding Issues No.8 and<lb/> 9, it was concluded that there was nothing to suggest that the<lb/> Guardianship Certificate was obtained by Devi Kala Sharma<lb/> fraudulently and that the learned Family Court, East Sikkim had<lb/> found Devi Kala Sharma competent to be the guardian of the minor<lb/> Defendant No.4 therefore it could not be held that she had no such<lb/> right. These Issues were also decided against the Plaintiffs. Issues<lb/> No.1, 3 and 11 were taken up together and the Court concluded<lb/> that the Plaintiffs are not entitled to the concerned &quot;jiwni&quot; land or its<lb/> recovery. That, the Suit filed by them was clearly not maintainable<lb/> and was thereby dismissed.<lb/></p>

			<p>11.(i)<lb/> Advancing his arguments for the Plaintiffs, learned<lb/> Senior Counsel walked this Court through the evidence of the<lb/> parties and their witnesses as well as the findings of the learned<lb/> trial Court and contended that a careful scrutiny of Exhibit &quot;A&quot;<lb/> reveals that vide the document, Devi Prasad made no provision for<lb/> the Defendant No.1 and he was concerned with bequeathing the<lb/> &quot;jiwni&quot; property on his sons only. That, Defendant No.1 has falsely<lb/> laid claim to it sans any intention of Devi Prasad.<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii)<lb/> That, the Defendant No.2 not being a Civil Court, has<lb/> passed the impugned Order, dated 03.11.2010, Exhibit 12, illegally<lb/> ordering mutation of the &quot;jiwni&quot; land in favour of the Defendant<lb/> No.1, in the teeth of the conditions laid down in the Partition Deed,<lb/> Exhibit &quot;A.&quot;<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> (iii)<lb/> That, the Defendant No.1, besides being ineligible for<lb/> the property, holds dual citizenship, being a Nepalese citizen also.<lb/> Hence, the claim of the Defendant No.1 seeking mutation of the<lb/> property and the Order of the Defendant No.2, dated 03.11.2010,<lb/> have no legal validity.<lb/></p>

			<p>(iv)<lb/> That, Issues No.4, 5 and 6 ought to have been decided<lb/> in favour of the Plaintiffs and &quot;jiwni&quot; land granted to them, they<lb/> having fulfilled both conditions mentioned in Exhibit &quot;A.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>(v)<lb/> That, the evidence reveals that the Plaintiffs were driven<lb/> out from the main house by an intolerant Defendant No.1 with a<lb/> &quot;khukuri&quot; (sharp edged weapon) and they thus had inimical<lb/> relations, which their father was aware of. Despite the said<lb/> circumstances, the Plaintiffs were expected to and did take care of<lb/> their father although living away from the main house. After being<lb/> driven out, the Plaintiff No.1 had to take shelter consecutively in the<lb/> house of one Kunta Maya Dahal, Krishna Lall Nepal and Rinzing<lb/> Tongden. Thereafter on passing his Class VIII, he secured<lb/> Government employment. The Plaintiff No.2 similarly was<lb/> constrained to leave the main house due to the ill-treatment of his<lb/> father and step-mother and had taken shelter in the house of his<lb/> sister, PW7 Tanka Maya Adhikari, who has substantiated this fact.<lb/> Thus, the Plaintiffs were compelled to leave the main house which<lb/> was not of their own volition. In spite of living separately from the<lb/> main house, the Plaintiff No.1 replaced its thatched roof with GCI<lb/> Sheets, this has been fortified by the evidence of PW6 Krishna<lb/> Prasad Sapkota and PW7 Tanka Maya Adhikari and was not<lb/> demolished in cross-examination.<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> (vi)<lb/> While referring to the observation of the learned trial<lb/> Court in Issue No.7, learned Senior Counsel contended that in fact<lb/> late Devi Prasad used to visit both Plaintiffs in the absence of the<lb/> Defendant No.1 and they extended financial help to him for the<lb/> purposes of his medication and clothing. They also visited him when<lb/> he was ill and this evidence has remained unimpeached. As their<lb/> father was compelled to live with Defendant No.1 and her son Bal<lb/> Krishna, the Plaintiffs could not take care of him directly but did so<lb/> whenever the occasion arose. Devi Prasad left no documentary<lb/> evidence to suggest that the Plaintiffs did not take care of him.<lb/> That, the Defendant No.1 failed to examine any Doctor to establish<lb/> that Devi Prasad was ailing for a decade while Defendant No.4, in<lb/> cross-examination, could not stand by her evidence in this context.<lb/> No Medical Certificates suggesting that Devi Prasad was ailing and<lb/> bedridden were also furnished. DW Dol Nath Gautam, in fact, was<lb/> only eleven years in 1985 when the Plaintiff No.1 was driven out but<lb/> deposed that he was aware of the entire circumstance in which the<lb/> Plaintiffs left the house therefore he cannot be said to be a truthful<lb/> witness. The four Defence witnesses are also unreliable as their<lb/> evidence were verbatim reproduction of each other&quot;s statements.<lb/></p>

			<p>(vii)<lb/> The learned trial Court while deciding Issues No.1, 2, 3,<lb/> 7 and 11 against the Plaintiffs failed to appreciate the<lb/> uncontroverted evidence of their witnesses.<lb/></p>

			<p>(viii)<lb/> PW Kunta Maya Dahal affirmed that the annual death<lb/> rites were observed by the Plaintiffs besides stating that the<lb/> Plaintiffs were present beside the body of their late father<lb/> immediately after his death and her evidence remained<lb/> uncontroverted as also the evidence of PW3 Man Bahadur Kharka<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> who deposed about Devi Prasad meeting the Plaintiffs. None of the<lb/> DWs have disputed the evidence to the effect that the Plaintiffs<lb/> performed the death rites of their father.<lb/></p>

			<p>(ix)<lb/> The learned trial Court while concluding that the<lb/> Plaintiffs had failed to prove that they maintained and looked after<lb/> their late father did not discuss the yardstick required for such<lb/> maintenance. That, the dual conditions were inserted into Exhibit<lb/> &quot;A&quot; despite their father&quot;s knowledge that the Plaintiffs lived<lb/> separately from him which goes to establish that he had<lb/> acknowledged that they had taken care of him during his lifetime.<lb/> That, Bal Krishna had an advantageous position as he continued to<lb/> live with his parents even after the partition and thereby could look<lb/> after them directly. The learned trial Court observed that the<lb/> Plaintiffs had failed to prove through documentary evidence that<lb/> they had taken care of their father. In doing so, the Court failed to<lb/> consider that children do not maintain books of accounts while<lb/> rendering financial assistance to take care of their parents. Nor did<lb/> the Court consider that the evidence of the witnesses pertaining to<lb/> the Plaintiffs visiting their father, were not controverted in cross-<lb/>examination.<lb/></p>

			<item>(x)<lb/> That, the observation of the learned trial Court<lb/> regarding Hindu Law by Raghavachariar [N.R. Raghavachariar&apos;s Hindu<lb/> Law] is totally misconceived and out of context.<lb/></item>

			<item>(xi)<lb/> That, reliance on the Sikkim Succession Act of 2008 by<lb/> the learned trial Court, is also erroneous as the Law was never<lb/> enforced in the State of Sikkim.<lb/></item>

			<item>(xii)<lb/> In view of all the facts and circumstances and the<lb/> evidence on record, the prayers in the Plaint be granted and the<lb/></item>

			<p>Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> impugned Judgment and Decree of the learned trial Court be set<lb/> aside as the Plaintiffs have proved that they complied with the<lb/> terms of Exhibit &quot;A&quot; with regard to the &quot;jiwni&quot; land.<lb/></p>

			<p>12.(i)<lb/> Learned Counsel for the Defendant No.1, repudiating<lb/> the arguments of learned Senior Counsel for the Plaintiffs,<lb/> contended that the Plaintiffs had filed the Suit only on their failure<lb/> to obtain a favourable Order from the Defendant No.2, despite<lb/> knowing fully well that the Plaintiff No.1 had failed to step into the<lb/> main house from the year 1983-84.<lb/></p>

			<item>(ii)<lb/> Learned Counsel also advanced the contention that the<lb/> Plaintiffs had voluntarily left the house and separated from their<lb/> father and the Defendant No.1.<lb/></item>

			<item>(iii)<lb/> That, when their father was ailing for almost a decade,<lb/> Bal Krishna along with the Defendant No.1 tended to him, providing<lb/> for the house financially and also for his treatment, which has been<lb/> extracted in the evidence of the Defendant No.1 duly supported by<lb/> the evidence of her witnesses and of Defendant No.4.<lb/></item>

			<item>(</item>

			<p>iv)<lb/> On his death, the Plaintiffs came reluctantly to the main<lb/> house only on the request of the village elders and lit their father&quot;s<lb/> funeral pyre but offered no financial assistance. The evidence of the<lb/> Defendant No.1 and her witnesses establishes as much. Contrarily,<lb/> both Plaintiffs have no evidence to establish that they supported<lb/> their father during his illness, took care of him in the Hospitals or<lb/> contributed financially or morally during his illness.<lb/></p>

			<p>(v)<lb/> It was contended that the Plaintiffs, by virtue of Exhibit<lb/> &quot;A,&quot; had already received sufficient landed property while the<lb/> Defendant No.1, despite her contribution to the family, has not<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> inherited any property and she is entitled to fifty per cent of her<lb/> husband&quot;s property as per the Law of the land.<lb/></p>

			<p>13.(i)<lb/> It was the next argument of the learned Counsel that<lb/> the Plaintiffs had, only in the second Amended Plaint, at Paragraph<lb/> 22 &quot;G,&quot; spun out a new story of having taken care of their father.<lb/> To support this in evidence, sans pleadings, they deposed that the<lb/> thatched roof of the main house was replaced by the Plaintiff No.1<lb/> and that he was driven out by the Defendant No.1 and his father<lb/> with a &quot;khukuri.&quot; That, it is a well settled principle of Law that<lb/> evidence adduced beyond the pleadings would not be admissible nor<lb/> can any evidence be permitted to be adduced which is at variance<lb/> with the pleadings. Such evidence is therefore to be disregarded. On<lb/> this aspect, reliance was placed on Govind Singh v. Harchand Kaur 1 , M.<lb/> Chinnasamy v. K.C. Palanisamy and Others 2 and Union of India v.<lb/> Ibrahim Uddin and Another 3 .<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii)<lb/> That, even if the roof had been replaced in 1978-79 as<lb/> contended, it is evident that the Plaintiff No.1 was living in the main<lb/> house at that time. The Plaintiff No.1 has admitted that he lived<lb/> separately from his father and visited the house only on 23.09.2001<lb/> on hearing of his father&quot;s death. His further admission was that no<lb/> custom in their family debars the females from shares in the family<lb/> property and that none of his sisters were married when Exhibit &quot;A&quot;<lb/> was executed. The Plaintiff No.2 also admitted to living separately<lb/> from his father. That, the evidence of the Plaintiffs&quot; witnesses failed<lb/> to support that of Plaintiff No.1 with regard to his replacing the<lb/> thatched roof, while the evidence of PW7 Tanka Maya Adhikari<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> proves that it was not only the sons of Devi Prasad but all the<lb/> children of the deceased, numbering fifteen, who performed his<lb/> death rites.<lb/></p>

			<p>(iii)<lb/> It was further canvassed by learned Counsel that the<lb/> Plaintiffs have to prove their case &quot;beyond a reasonable doubt&quot; and<lb/> the Plaintiffs must stand or fall on their own case. On this count,<lb/> learned Counsel sought assistance from the ratio in Kiran Limboo v.<lb/> Kussang Limboo 4 .<lb/></p>

			<p>(iv)<lb/> Reliance was also placed on the provisions of Order VII<lb/> Rules 1 and 3 and Order II Rule 2 of the Code of Civil Procedure,<lb/> 1908 (&quot;CPC&quot;) and it was urged that the Suit must include the whole<lb/> claim but the Plaintiffs have only sought for a declaration that they<lb/> are entitled to the &quot;jiwni&quot; land.<lb/></p>

			<p>14.(i)<lb/> DW Punya Prasad Adhikari, the witness for the<lb/> Defendant No.1, has deposed that Defendant No.1 did not ill-treat<lb/> the Plaintiffs. Placing reliance on the ratio of Karedla Parthasaradhi v.<lb/> Gangula Ramanamma (Dead) Through Legal Representatives and Others 5<lb/> and Sadhu Singh v. Gurdwara Sahib Narike &amp; Ors. 6 , it was contended<lb/> that the wife is the Class I heir of her husband and entitled to his<lb/> properties on his death. That, the Hindu Succession (Amendment)<lb/> Act, 2005 and Section 6 of the Act, in particular, removes<lb/> discrimination by giving equal rights to daughters/widows in the<lb/> Hindu Mitakshara coparcenary property for which strength was<lb/> drawn from Vineeta Sharma v. Rakesh Sharma 7 . That, accordingly the<lb/> Defendant No.1 and the Defendant No.4 are entitled to fifty per cent<lb/> each of the &quot;jiwni&quot; land despite the conditions laid down in Exhibit<lb/></p>

			<item>4 2020 SCC OnLine Sikk 2<lb/> 5 AIR 2015 SC 891<lb/> 6 AIR 2006 SC 3282<lb/> 7 MANU/SC/0582/2020<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/></item>

			<item>&quot;A.&quot; Reliance was placed on Anar Devi and Others v. Parmeshwari Devi<lb/> and Others 8 .<lb/></item>

			<p>(ii)<lb/> Arguments were also advanced denying that Defendant<lb/> No.1, late Bal Krishna Dahal and Devi Kala Sharma were citizens of<lb/> Nepal. In this context, learned Counsel placed reliance on State of<lb/> Andhra Pradesh v. Abdul Khader 9 .<lb/></p>

			<item>(iii)<lb/> That apart, the Plaintiffs are well settled in life being<lb/> Government employees and have received their respective shares of<lb/> the property.<lb/></item>

			<p>(iv)<lb/> That, this Court in its Judgment, dated 22.04.2016, in<lb/> &quot;RFA No.04 of 2014 (Smt. Indira Dahal v. Shri Nil Kumar Dahal and<lb/> Another)&quot; had held that &quot;…Indisputably, Bal Krishna Dahal used to live<lb/> with his parents, looked after them and had also performed the death rites<lb/> of his father along with……&quot; Hence, the observations of the learned<lb/> trial Court in the impugned Judgment requires no interference.<lb/></p>

			<p>15.<lb/> Learned Counsel Ms. Kunzang Choden Lepcha,<lb/> appearing for the Defendant No.4 made no verbal submissions but<lb/> filed her written synopsis of arguments reiterating the facts as<lb/> averred in the pleadings and in sum and substance, also reiterating<lb/> the arguments advanced by learned Counsel for the Defendant<lb/> No.1. Learned Counsel led this Court through the evidence of the<lb/> various witnesses and ultimately contended that the Defendant<lb/> No.1, besides the Defendant No.4, is also entitled to fifty per cent of<lb/> the &quot;jiwni&quot; land.<lb/></p>

			<p>16.<lb/> Learned Additional Advocate General for State-<lb/>Respondents No.2 and 3 had no submissions to make.<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> 17.<lb/> The submissions advanced by learned Counsel for the<lb/> parties were heard at length and duly considered. The pleadings, all<lb/> evidence, documents on record, the impugned Judgment and the<lb/> citations placed at the Bar have also been perused.<lb/></p>

			<p>18.(i)<lb/> Before embarking into a discussion on the merits of the<lb/> matter, it is essential to point out here that the averments made by<lb/> both Defendants No.1 and 4 in Paragraph &quot;17&quot; of their respective<lb/> written statements inter alia reflects as follows;<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;17. ……..The said two pre conditions which are<lb/> also acknowledged by the Honble High Court in its<lb/> Judgment dated 22.04.2016 passed in RFA No.04 of<lb/> 2016 between Smt. Indira Dahal versus Shri Nil<lb/> Kumar Dahal &amp; another are &quot;look after the parents<lb/> and also perform death rites&quot; which were not fulfilled<lb/> by the Plaintiffs. It is only Defendant No.1 and her<lb/> son, Bal Krishna Dahal who fulfill both this (sic<lb/> &quot;these&quot;) pre conditions and hence entitled to the<lb/> JEWNI land as per the Hon&apos;ble High Court…&quot;<lb/> (Emphasis supplied)<lb/></item>

			<item>(ii)<lb/> Learned Counsel for the Defendant No.1 in his written<lb/> arguments has inter alia contended as under;<lb/></item>

			<item>&quot;………And finally when one comes to the case of<lb/> respondent No. 4, it is not in doubt that Late Bal<lb/> Krishna Dahal (the respondent No. 4 before this<lb/> Hon&apos;ble Court) had taken care of Late Devi Prasad<lb/> Dahal during his lifetime and he had also performed<lb/> his death rites thus fulfilling the twin conditions laid<lb/> down in the Banda Patra.<lb/> This was the observation of this Hon&quot;ble Court<lb/> way back on 22.04.2016 when Late Bal Krishna Dahal<lb/> was not even impleaded as respondent No. 4 in the<lb/> instant case in Judgment dated 22.04.2016 passed in<lb/> R.F.A. No. 4 of 2014 at paragraph 15 concluded.-<lb/></item>

			<item>&quot;What stares one in the face is that the Appellant<lb/> (Respondent No. 1/Defendant No. 1) bore one son Bal<lb/> Krishna Dahal to Devi Prasad Dahal. It appears that<lb/> the said Bal Krishna Dahal died in an accident in<lb/> Nepal leaving behind his widow and a daughter.<lb/></item>

			<item>Indisputably, Bal Krishna Dahal used to live with his<lb/> parents, looked after them and had also performed<lb/> the death rites of his father along with his step<lb/> brothers, the Respondent………..&quot;.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<item>(iii)<lb/> The Defendant No.4, in her written arguments stated<lb/> that the Defendant No.1, at Paragraph &quot;3&quot; of her Additional<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> Evidence-on-Affidavit (Exhibit D1/G), has affirmed that, &quot;The Hon&quot;ble<lb/> High Court in its Judgment dated 22.04.2016 passed in RFA No. 04 of<lb/> 2016 came to the conclusion that only my son, Bal Krishna Dahal fulfill the<lb/> two conditions &quot;look after the parents and also perform death rites&quot;,<lb/> specifically laid down in the Banda Patra dated 17.05.1985 Exhibit D1/A<lb/> is the Judgment dated 22.04.2016 passed in RFA No. 04 of 2016.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<item>19.<lb/> It is imperative to clarify here that the interpretation<lb/> given to the Judgment of this Court in RFA No.04 of 2014 (supra) as<lb/> reflected in the averments of the Written Statements of the<lb/> Defendant No.1 and Defendant No.4 and their written arguments,<lb/> are misleading, erroneous and mischievous. It is necessary to refer<lb/> herein to the Judgment and extract the relevant portion thereof;<lb/></item>

			<item>&quot;15. What stares one in the face is that the<lb/> Appellant bore one son Bal Krishna Dahal to Devi<lb/> Prasad Dahal. It appears that the said Bal Krishna<lb/> Dahal died in an accident in Nepal leaving behind his<lb/> widow and a daughter. Indisputably, Bal Krishna<lb/> Dahal, used to live with his parents, looked after them<lb/> and had also performed the death rites of his father<lb/> along with his step brothers, the Respondents.<lb/> Although the Learned Trial Court in its Judgment has<lb/> alluded to the fact that Bal Krishna Dahal looked after<lb/> and maintained his late father as well as performed<lb/> the death rites, however, in paragraph 56 of the<lb/> impugned Judgment has recorded inter alia, that<lb/> &quot;…………..….It may be necessary to mention that though<lb/> the younger son of late Devi Prasad Dahal, Bal Krishna<lb/> (since deceased) also maintained/looked after and<lb/> performed the death ritual of their father, however,<lb/> neither his legal heir and successor were made parties in<lb/> the present suit nor any of them came as interested<lb/> party to claim the said Jiwni land, as such, it is not<lb/> necessary to go into the details.&quot;<lb/> ……………………………………………………………………………………...<lb/></item>

			<item>23. It is hereby ordered that the legal heirs and<lb/> successors of Bal Krishna Dahal be impleaded as<lb/> Defendants in the Title Suit which shall be readmitted<lb/> to its original number in the Register of Civil Suits of<lb/> the Learned Court of the District Judge, Special<lb/> Division-I, Sikkim at Gangtok. The Suit be determined<lb/> as per Law within six months from today in view of<lb/> the fact that the Title Suit is of the year 2010.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>(Emphasis supplied)<lb/> From a reading of the above, it is clear that this Court had observed<lb/> that Bal Krishna lived with his parents, looked after them and also<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> performed the death rites of his father &quot;along&quot; with his step<lb/> brothers i.e. the Plaintiffs. The adverb &quot;along&quot; which obtains in the<lb/> relevant sentence, has to be read in its correct perspective. It is<lb/> clear that no decision with regard to the merits of the case has been<lb/> made, as sought to be insinuated by the Defendant No.1 and<lb/> Defendant No.4. The facts and circumstances at that juncture were<lb/> duly considered and direction issued by this Court to implead the<lb/> descendants of late Bal Krishna on account of his admitted role in<lb/> his family. The Judgment, by no stretch of the imagination stated<lb/> that only Bal Krishna fulfilled both the conditions. Such an<lb/> erroneous interpretation cannot be given to the decision of this<lb/> Court in the RFA supra and parties ought to refrain from such<lb/> misrepresentation.<lb/></p>

			<p>20.<lb/> That having been said, while perusing the averments of<lb/> the parties in their pleadings, it is clear that the Plaintiffs claim to be<lb/> governed by the Mitakshara School of Hindu Law while the<lb/> Defendants No.1 and 4 deny it, asserting that they were governed<lb/> by the Law of the land. The learned trial Court ought to have settled<lb/> an issue for determination on this point in view of the provisions of<lb/> Order XIV of the CPC, which inter alia provides that Issues arise<lb/> when a material proposition of fact or Law is affirmed by the one<lb/> party and denied by the other. Nonetheless, this matter shall be<lb/> taken up for discussion herein. Accordingly, the questions that fall<lb/> for consideration before this Court are;<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> Whether the Mitakshara School of Hindu Law was<lb/> applicable to the Plaintiffs?;<lb/> (ii)<lb/> Who is entitled to succeed to the &quot;jiwni&quot; land of<lb/> deceased Devi Prasad Dahal?; and<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> (iii)<lb/> Whether the Defendant No.1 is entitled to fifty per<lb/> cent of the &quot;jiwni&quot; land despite the conditions laid<lb/> down in the testamentary disposition of the Partition<lb/> Deed, Exhibit &quot;A&quot;?<lb/></p>

			<p>21.<lb/> Taking up the first question framed hereinabove, in the<lb/> first instance, we may relevantly examine whether there are Laws of<lb/> Succession in the State protected by the provisions of Article 371-F<lb/> of the Constitution of India (&quot;Constitution&quot;). Necessary reference is<lb/> made to the provisions of Article 371-F(k), (l) and (n) of the<lb/> Constitution which provides;<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;371-F. Special provisions with respect to the<lb/> State of Sikkim.-Notwith-standing anything in this<lb/> Constitution,-<lb/>………………………………………………………………………………<lb/> (k) all laws in force immediately before the<lb/> appointed day in the territories comprised in the State<lb/> of Sikkim or any part thereof shall continue to be in<lb/> force therein until amended or repealed by a<lb/> competent Legislature or other competent authority;<lb/> ………………………………………………………………………………<lb/></item>

			<item>(l) for the purpose of facilitating the application<lb/> of any such law as is referred to in clause (k) in<lb/> relation to the administration of the State of Sikkim<lb/> and for the purpose of bringing the provisions of any<lb/> such law into accord with the provisions of this<lb/> Constitution, the President may, within two years<lb/> from the appointed day, by order, make such<lb/> adaptations and modifications of the law, whether by<lb/> way of repeal or amendment, as may be necessary or<lb/> expedient, and thereupon, every such law shall have<lb/> effect subject to the adaptations and modifications so<lb/> made, and any such adaptation or modification shall<lb/> not be questioned in any court of law;<lb/> ………………………………………………………………………………<lb/></item>

			<item>(n) the President may, by public notification,<lb/> extend with such restrictions or modifications as he<lb/> thinks fit to the State of Sikkim any enactment which<lb/> is in force in a State of India at the date of the<lb/> notification;<lb/> ………………………………&quot;<lb/> These provisions are self-explanatory and have been extracted to<lb/> elucidate the position of the old Laws in Sikkim as well as provisions<lb/> existing for extension and enforcement of the Laws of the country to<lb/> the State, consequent upon the 36 th Amendment Act to the<lb/> Constitution, whereby Sikkim became a part of the Indian Union.<lb/></item>

			<p>Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/></p>

			<p>22.<lb/> It was the vehement argument of learned Counsel for<lb/> the Defendant No.1 that the parties are bound by the Law of the<lb/> land which do not differentiate between men and women in terms of<lb/> Succession thereby entitling Defendant No.1 to fifty per cent of her<lb/> husband&quot;s property. No specific Law was brought forth for the<lb/> perusal of this Court by the Defendant No.1. It may be noticed that<lb/> lex terrae or Law of the land refers to Laws within a country or<lb/> region, but no effort was made by the Defendant No.1 to clarify<lb/> either the &quot;Law&quot; or the &quot;land&quot; referred to in view of the afore-<lb/>extracted provisions of Article 371-F of the Constitution. Before the<lb/> learned trial Court, reliance had been placed by the Defendant No.1<lb/> on the Sikkim Succession Act, 2008, therefore it can be safely<lb/> presumed that this was the Statute being referred to. The fate that<lb/> this Law has met will be discussed later.<lb/></p>

			<p>23.<lb/> The contention of the Defendant No.1 was that both<lb/> Plaintiffs in their cross-examination, admitted that they belonged to<lb/> the Brahmin community and follow their community traditions and<lb/> customs and were unaware of the words &quot;Mitakshara School&quot; or<lb/> what it stood for.<lb/></p>

			<p>24.<lb/> In the light of the statement relating to customs and<lb/> traditions extracted supra from the Plaintiffs in cross-examination, it<lb/> would be relevant to examine what &quot;Customs&quot; are and the method<lb/> of proof of such &quot;Customs&quot; for Courts to take it into consideration<lb/> for the purposes of adjudication. In Halsbury&apos;s Laws of England,<lb/> (Fourth Edition), Volume 12(1), the attributes of &quot;Custom&quot; was<lb/> enumerated as follows;<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;606. Essential attributes. To be valid, a custom<lb/> must have four essential attributes: (1) it must be<lb/> immemorial; (2) it must be reasonable; (3) it must be<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> certain in its terms, and in respect both of the locality<lb/> where it is alleged to obtain and of the persons whom<lb/> it is alleged to affect; and (4) it must have continued<lb/> as of right and without interruption since its<lb/> immemorial origin. These characteristics serve a<lb/> practical purpose as rules of evidence when the<lb/> existence of a custom is to be established or refuted.<lb/> [Page No.160]<lb/></item>

			<item>626. Nature of proof. All customs of which the<lb/> courts do not take judicial notice must be clearly<lb/> proved to exist, the onus of establishing them being<lb/> upon the parties relying upon their existence. Proof<lb/> must be made either by matter of record or by<lb/> evidence of usage since time immemorial. Evidence to<lb/> prove a custom must not only be consistent with the<lb/> custom which is alleged, but must also prove a<lb/> custom which is no wider than that alleged. If the<lb/> evidence tends to prove a custom wider than that<lb/> which is alleged, the party seeking to establish the<lb/> custom is not at liberty to adopt part only of the<lb/> evidence and to reject the rest.<lb/> [Page No.177]<lb/></item>

			<item>627. Usual method of proof. In proving an<lb/> immemorial custom, the usual course taken is to call<lb/> persons of middle or old age to state that in their<lb/> time, usually at least half a century, the custom has<lb/> always prevailed. This is considered, in the absence of<lb/> countervailing evidence, to show that the custom has<lb/> existed from all time. There are two sorts of<lb/> countervailing evidence. First, other old person may<lb/> be called to show that there was an interruption<lb/> during the period spoken of by the first set of<lb/> witnesses; secondly, evidence may be given that,<lb/> from the nature of the case, it was quite impossible<lb/> that such a right should have existed from time<lb/> immemorial, or that there is some legal difficulty or<lb/> obstacle in the way which makes the alleged assertion<lb/> of the right incompatible with the law of the country.<lb/> Whether the evidence supports the custom as alleged<lb/> or not is a question of fact for the court. A custom<lb/> possible in law, being reasonable and otherwise<lb/> fulfilling the requisites of a good custom, may be<lb/> established by very slender evidence.<lb/> [Page No.178]<lb/></item>

			<item>The extracts supra throw light on what comprises &quot;Customs&quot; and<lb/> the usual method of proof required.<lb/></item>

			<p>25.<lb/> In Ass Kaur (Smt.) (Deceased) by LRs. v. Kartar Singh<lb/> (Dead) by LRs. and Others 10 , a two Judge Bench of the Hon&quot;ble<lb/> Supreme Court observed that in the absence of any proof of<lb/> custom, indisputably the Hindu Law would apply.<lb/></p>

			<p>10 (2007) 5 SCC 561<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/></p>

			<p>26.<lb/> As far back as in 1908, in Daya Ram v. Sohel Singh 11 , the<lb/> Chief Court of Punjab while dealing with the true effect of Section 5<lb/> of the Punjab Laws Act, 1872, Robertson, J held as follows;<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;In all cases it appears to me under this Act, it<lb/> lies upon the person asserting that he is ruled in<lb/> regard to a particular matter by custom, to prove that<lb/> he is so governed, and not by personal law, and<lb/> further to prove what the particular custom is. There<lb/> is no presumption created by the clause in favour of<lb/> custom; on the contrary, it is only when the custom is<lb/> established that it is to be the rule of decision. The<lb/> Legislature did not show itself enamored of custom<lb/> rather than law nor does it show any tendency to<lb/> extend the &apos;principles&apos; of custom to any matter to<lb/> which a rule of custom is not clearly proved to apply.<lb/> It is not the spirit of Customary Law, nor any theory<lb/> of custom or deductions from other customs which is<lb/> to be a rule of decision, but only &apos;any custom<lb/> applicable to the parties concerned which is not...&apos;<lb/> and it therefore, appears to me clear that when either<lb/> party to a suit sets up &apos;custom&apos; as a rule of decision,<lb/> it lies upon him to prove the custom which he seeks<lb/> to apply; if he fails to do so Clause (b) of Section 5 of<lb/> the Laws Act applies, and the rule of decision must<lb/> be the personal law of the parties subject to the<lb/> other provisions of the clause.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<item>(Emphasis supplied)<lb/></item>

			<p>27.<lb/> In H.H. Mir Abdul Hussain Khan v. Bibi Sona Dero 12 , the<lb/> question of custom came up for consideration in view of the<lb/> difference in opinions of the Court of first instance and the Court of<lb/> Appeal. The District Court held that the custom was established and<lb/> the Court of the Judicial Commissioner of Sind decided that custom<lb/> was not established. The Appeal arose from the latter decision and<lb/> the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court inter alia observed as follows;<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;6. ……It is therefore incumbent upon the<lb/> plaintiff to allege and prove the custom on which he<lb/> relies, and it becomes important to consider the<lb/> nature and extent of the proof required. Their<lb/> Lordships have carefully considered the difficulty of<lb/> applying all the strict rules that govern the<lb/> establishment of custom in this country to<lb/> circumstances which find no analogy here. Custom<lb/> binding inheritance in a particular family has long<lb/> been recognised in India (see Soorendronath Roy v.<lb/> Mussamut Heeramonee Burmoneah (1868) 12 M.I.A.<lb/> 81, although such a custom is unknown to the law of<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> this country and is foreign to its spirit. Customs<lb/> affecting descent in certain areas or customs<lb/> affecting-rights of inhabitants of a particular district<lb/> are perhaps the nearest analogies in this country. ……<lb/> ………………………………………………………………………………………<lb/></item>

			<item>19. In every case of this kind the burden of<lb/> proof lies heavily upon the plaintiff, and though his<lb/> evidence may consist of a number of striking<lb/> instances in support of his case, it receives a severe<lb/> blow when prominent members of the families<lb/> concerned deny that the custom exists.<lb/> …………………………&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>A reading of this Judgment thus reflects that the Hon&quot;ble Judges<lb/> were aware of the myriad of castes and customs of the country and<lb/> that custom in one family may not necessarily be the custom of<lb/> another family and thereby the lack of uniformity in customs. In<lb/> other words, it is accepted in our country that every family may<lb/> have their own customs but it is for the person asserting it to<lb/> establish that such a custom exists by sufficient proof, as laid down<lb/> in Daya Ram v. Sohel Singh and H.H. Mir Abdul Hussain Khan (supra).<lb/></p>

			<p>28.<lb/> In Ujagar Singh v. Jeo 13 the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court held<lb/> inter alia as follows;<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;13. It therefore appears to us that the ordinary<lb/> rule is that all customs, general or otherwise, have to<lb/> be proved. Under s. 57 of the Evidence Act however<lb/> nothing need be proved of which courts can take<lb/> judicial notice. Therefore it is said that if there is a<lb/> custom of which the courts can take judicial notice, it<lb/> need not be proved. Now the circumstances in which<lb/> the courts can take judicial notice of a custom were<lb/> stated by Lord Dunedin in Raja Rama Rao v. Raja of<lb/> Pittapur I.L.R. (1918) IndAp 148, in the following<lb/> words, &quot;When a custom or usage, whether in regard<lb/> to a tenure or a contract or a family right, is<lb/> repeatedly brought to the notice of the Courts of a<lb/> country, the Courts may hold that custom or usage to<lb/> be introduced into the law without necessity of proof<lb/> in each individual case.&quot; When a custom has been so<lb/> recognised by the courts, it passes into the law of the<lb/> land and the proof of it then becomes unnecessary<lb/> under s. 57(1) of the Evidence Act. It appears to us<lb/> that in the courts in the Punjab the expression<lb/> &quot;general custom&quot; has really been used in this sense,<lb/> namely, that a custom has by repeated recognition by<lb/> courts, become entitled to judicial notice as was said<lb/> in Bawa Singh v. Mt. Taro A.I.R. 1951 Simla 239 and<lb/> 13 MANU/SC/0187/1959<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> Sukhwant Kaur v. Balwant Singh A.I.R. 1951 Simla<lb/> 242..<lb/> ……………………………………………………………………………………<lb/></item>

			<item>30. It was then said that in the plaint it had<lb/> been admitted by the respondent that there was a<lb/> general custom as alleged by the appellant and so no<lb/> proof of that general custom was required in this<lb/> case. We do not think this contention is justified. No<lb/> doubt in her plaint the respondent referred to a<lb/> custom entitling her to succeed and termed it a<lb/> special custom. We are unable to read the reference<lb/> to a special custom as amounting to an admission of a<lb/> general custom or its terms.<lb/> ……………………………………………………………………………………<lb/></item>

			<item>41. As we have earlier said this observation was<lb/> approved by the Judicial Committee in Abdul Hussain<lb/> Khan v. Bibi Sona Dero I.L.R.(1917) IndAp 10. In<lb/> Fatima Bibi v. Shah Nawaz I.L.R. (1920) Lah. 98., a<lb/> case to which we have earlier referred, the Court<lb/> allowed the plaintiff&apos;s sisters, who had based their<lb/> claim on custom and not on the personal law, to fall<lb/> back on Mohammedan law, the personal law of the<lb/> parties, on their failure to establish the custom, no<lb/> custom against them having been proved by the<lb/> collaterals. There are a number of other authorities,<lb/> to which it is not necessary to refer, in which<lb/> personal law was resorted to when no custom on<lb/> either side was established. We agree that is the<lb/> correct view to take. We therefore think that even if<lb/> the respondent had been unable to prove the custom<lb/> in her favour she is entitled to succeed in the suit on<lb/> the basis of the personal law of the parties, namely,<lb/> the Hindu law.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<item>(Emphasis supplied)<lb/></item>

			<item>It thus follows that where custom is not established, the personal<lb/> Law of the parties becomes applicable.<lb/></item>

			<p>29.<lb/> To be fair to the Plaintiffs, it was not their averment in<lb/> the pleadings that their family had established customs for<lb/> Succession. The statement, as already reflected above, came to be<lb/> extracted in cross-examination in which both Plaintiffs made<lb/> identical statements viz.;<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;………….It is true that I belonged(sic) to the<lb/> Brahmin community and we follow our own traditions<lb/> and customs as per the said community. It is true<lb/> that I am not aware of the word Mitakshara School<lb/> and I cannot say what it stands for. ……………&quot;<lb/> However, as seen from the text of Halsbury (supra) and the catena<lb/> of ratiocination referred to above, if a person claims governance by<lb/> custom, he is to prove it to enable the Courts to apply it, failing<lb/></item>

			<p>Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> which the personal Law of the parties will be applicable. Ironically,<lb/> from the evidence on record neither have the Plaintiffs been able to<lb/> establish by furnishing any evidence, the customs followed either in<lb/> their community or specifically in their family nor has the Defendant<lb/> No.1, for her part, been able to show any Law of the land which<lb/> confers rights on her to acquire her husband&quot;s property.<lb/></p>

			<p>30.<lb/> Assuming that the reference made by the Defendant<lb/> No.1 was to the Sikkim Succession Act, 2008, it may pertinently be<lb/> pointed out here that a Division Bench of this High Court in Basanti<lb/> Rai and Ors. v. State of Sikkim and Ors. 14 was considering the legality<lb/> and validity of the said Statute issued vide Notification<lb/> No.22/LD/P/2008, dated 24.07.2008, of the Law Department,<lb/> Government of Sikkim. In the said Writ Petition, the State<lb/> Government in its Return, clearly stated that the Act is only on<lb/> paper and has not yet been notified, as required, to bring the same<lb/> into force and contended that the Petition was premature. This<lb/> Court, on examining the reply filed by the State-Respondents, vide<lb/> its Order, dated 31.07.2017, concluded as follows;<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;4. ……that the Sikkim Succession Act, 2008 is<lb/> not yet enforced, the same having not been notified<lb/> as yet. Consequently, Orders, if any, passed by the<lb/> Authorities, in terms of the provisions of the Sikkim<lb/> Succession Act, 2008, are declared null and void ab<lb/> initio. Examination of the validity of an enactment,<lb/> which is nonexistent, is not required, as it is pre-<lb/>mature. ……&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>31.<lb/> In the absence of any established custom of the parties<lb/> pertaining to Succession, any State enactment occupying the field<lb/> and the absence of personal Law, the quandary therefore would now<lb/> be how the matter is to be adjudicated upon. At this juncture, it is<lb/> thus imperative that we refer to the ratiocination of Sonam Topgyal<lb/> 14 2017 SCC OnLine Sikk 123<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> Bhutia v. Gompu Bhutia 15 , decided on 14.06.1979, by a Division<lb/> Bench of this High Court, comprising of M.S. Gujral, C.J. and A.M.<lb/> Bhattacharjee, J. The Court was concerned with a matter relating to<lb/> Wills and whether Buddhists in Sikkim can legally make<lb/> testamentary disposition. It was also specified that though this point<lb/> was not taken up by any of the parties in their pleadings or<lb/> otherwise but had cropped up during the hearing of the Appeal. The<lb/> Court was of the opinion that the question would go to the root of<lb/> the matter and was of general public importance in Sikkim as there<lb/> was no judicial pronouncement of the Court or any other Court on<lb/> this point. It was observed therein as follows;<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;9. There is no doubt that in Sikkim, there is, as<lb/> yet, no statutory law authorising testamentary<lb/> disposition. But as will appear from the unchallenged<lb/> evidence of the witnesses appearing before us, in<lb/> practice Wills had been and have been recognised,<lb/> acted upon and given effect to in the Courts of Sikkim<lb/> as valid modes of post-mortem disposition of<lb/> properties and witnesses Sarki Bhutia, Karma Pintso<lb/> Bhutia and T.D. Densapa have also referred to several<lb/> instances of the execution of Will by Sikkimese-<lb/>Buddhists. The question before us is whether Wills in<lb/> Sikkim can be regarded to be valid and legal without<lb/> any legislative provision to that effect. The Shastric<lb/> Hindu Law did not recognise testamentary disposition<lb/> and statutory provisions had to be made by and under<lb/> the provisions of the Hindu Wills Act, 1870,<lb/> empowering the Hindus to make Wills. Buddhism also<lb/> favoured intestacy and as pointed out by the Privy<lb/> Council in Dwe Maung v. Khoo Haung Shein (AIR<lb/> 1925 PC 29 at p. 31), according to &quot;the strict<lb/> Buddhist view&quot; &quot;intestacy is compulsory&quot;. As the<lb/> personal laws of the Hindus and Buddhists did not<lb/> recognise testamentary disposition, doubts have<lb/> arisen as to whether the Hindus and Buddhists in<lb/> Sikkim can validly make Wills in the absence of<lb/> legislative provisions.<lb/> ……………………………………………………………………………………<lb/></item>

			<item>26. But though there is no legislation in Sikkim<lb/> relating to Wills, the Courts in Sikkim have followed<lb/> and applied the provisions of the Indian Succession<lb/> Act, 1925 in all matters relating to Wills including<lb/> granting of Probates and Letters of Administration.<lb/> The question, therefore, is whether the provisions<lb/> 15 AIR 1980 Sikk 33<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> relating to Wills in the Indian Succession Act, 1925,<lb/> which have never been formally adopted in or<lb/> extended to Sikkim by any formal legislative authority<lb/> are to be regarded as laws in force in Sikkim?<lb/> Salmond has defined law as a body of principles<lb/> recognised<lb/> and<lb/> applied<lb/> by<lb/> the<lb/> State<lb/> in<lb/> the administration of Justice and as to consist of &quot;of<lb/> the rules recognised and acted on by Courts of<lb/> justice&quot;. Holland has defined law as &quot;a rule of external<lb/> human action enforced by a Sovereign political<lb/> authority.&quot; Therefore, the provisions relating to Wills<lb/> in the Indian Succession Act, 1925, having so long<lb/> been &quot;recognised&quot; &quot;applied&quot; and &quot;acted on&quot; by the<lb/> Courts of justice in Sikkim in the administration of<lb/> justice in matters relating to Wills, are also to be<lb/> regarded as Laws in force in Sikkim.<lb/></item>

			<item>27. In other words the statutory laws relating to<lb/> Wills as contained in the Indian Succession Act, 1925<lb/> have, as a result of their continuous and systematic<lb/> recognition and application by the Courts in Sikkim,<lb/> become the non-statutory laws of Sikkim. Law does<lb/> not and need not always flow formally or directly from<lb/> a legislative authority. For otherwise, personal laws,<lb/> customary laws, common laws or even precedents<lb/> cannot be regarded as laws. Reference in this<lb/> connection may be made to a recent decision of<lb/> Sikkim High Court in Asharam Agarwala v. Union of<lb/> India, (reported in 1978 Sikkim LJ 18) where it has<lb/> been held that though the Arbitration Act, 1940 has<lb/> never been formally made applicable in Sikkim, yet<lb/> the provisions of the said Act, having so long been<lb/> recognised, applied and acted upon by the Courts of<lb/> Justice in Sikkim in the administration of justice in<lb/> matters relating to Arbitration, are to be regarded as<lb/> laws in force in Sikkim, though not as direct statutory<lb/> laws. In dealing with the question as to whether such<lb/> non-statutory laws could or can also create<lb/> jurisdictions for the Courts to entertain applications,<lb/> appeals and other proceedings under the said Act, it<lb/> has been observed as hereunder:-<lb/>&quot;If as already noted, Courts in Sikkim have all<lb/> along not only applied the provisions of the<lb/> Arbitration Act in between the parties to<lb/> arbitration but have also applied the provisions<lb/> relating to entertainment of all applications and<lb/> appeals as provided in the said Act, then the<lb/> latter provisions also, as a result of application<lb/> and recognition by Courts, became the laws in<lb/> force within the meaning of Article 371-F(K) of<lb/> the Constitution whereunder all laws in force in<lb/> Sikkim immediately before the commencement<lb/> of the Constitution (Thirty-Sixth Amendment)<lb/> Act, 1975, shall continue in force until amended<lb/> or repealed by a competent Legislature or other<lb/> competent authority. In other words, if by and<lb/> under the Laws of Sikkim, though not statutory,<lb/> the Courts had been exercising the jurisdiction to<lb/> entertain applications relating to arbitration<lb/> matters and also appeals therefrom, such laws<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> and jurisdiction have also continued and shall<lb/> continue in force.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<item>28. Following this decision, I would hold that not<lb/> only the provisions relating to the execution,<lb/> interpretation or effect of Wills in the Indian<lb/> Succession Act, 1925, but all the provisions therein<lb/> relating to Wills including the provisions relating to<lb/> grants of Probate and Letters of Administration and<lb/> also appeals and other proceedings therefrom have<lb/> become the laws of Sikkim. ……&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>32.<lb/> On the same lines, in Bishnu Kala Karki Dholi and Others v.<lb/> Bishnu Maya Darjeeni, Civil First Appeal No.8 of 1976, decided earlier<lb/> on, viz. 06.03.1978 by the same Bench of this High Court, the two<lb/> questions requiring determination in the Appeal were, whether a<lb/> mortgager is entitled to file a Suit and to obtain a decree for<lb/> redemption of mortgage, where a Deed of mortgage is invalid for<lb/> want of registration and, if not, whether the mortgager is entitled in<lb/> such a Suit to a decree for recovery of possession on proof of title.<lb/> Speaking for the Court, Justice A.M. Bhattacharjee while considering<lb/> and observing that the Transfer of Property Act had not been<lb/> extended and enforced in the State of Sikkim then, held as follows;<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;9. ………The observation quoted above should be<lb/> read with the observation of the Supreme Court in the<lb/> above noted decision in Namdeo v. Narmada Bai (AIR<lb/> 1953 Supreme Court 228 at p. 230) quoted<lb/> hereinbelow:-<lb/></item>

			<item>&quot;It is axiomatic that the Courts must apply<lb/> the principles of justice, equity and good<lb/> conscience to transactions which come up<lb/> before them for determination even though<lb/> the statutory provisions of the Transfer of<lb/> Property Act are not made applicable to<lb/> these transactions. It follows therefore that<lb/> the provisions of the Act which are but a<lb/> statutory recognition of the rules of justice,<lb/> equity and good conscience also governs<lb/> those transfers.&quot;<lb/> And when so read will lead to the conclusion that<lb/> even though the Transfer of Property Act does not<lb/> formally apply in Sikkim, the Courts in Sikkim, in<lb/> discharging their paramount duty to act in the<lb/> absence of statutory provisions, according to the<lb/> principles of justice, equity and good conscience<lb/> should reasonable(sic) and properly apply the<lb/> principles contained in Section 60 of the Transfer of<lb/> Property Act relating to redemption of mortgage and<lb/> unenforceability of any clog on the right of<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> redemption. This is what was also done by the<lb/> Rajasthan High Court in Dev Karan v. Murarilal (ILR<lb/> 1958 Rajasthan 811) in a case arising from the<lb/> former State of Alwar before the extension of the<lb/> Transfer of Property Act thereto and this decision has<lb/> been affirmed by the Supreme Court in Murarilal v.<lb/> Devkaran (AIR 1965 SC 225) and relying in the<lb/> observations made therein at page 231, I would hold<lb/> that it would be reasonable to assume that the Civil<lb/> Courts established in Sikkim, like Civil Courts all over<lb/> India, were and are required to administer justice<lb/> according to the principles of equity and justice where<lb/> there was or is no specific statutory provision to deal<lb/> with the question before them and, therefore, it would<lb/> be just and proper to apply the principles contained in<lb/> Section 60 of the Transfer of Property Act relating to<lb/> the right of redemption and clog on the equity of<lb/> redemption.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>33.<lb/> In Jas Bahadur Rai v. Putra Dhan Rai, 1978 (3) Sikkim Law<lb/> Journal, decided on 29.07.1978, the same Bench of this High Court,<lb/> while considering whether the provisions of the Indian Easements<lb/> Act, 1882, should be applied in Sikkim sans extension or<lb/> enforcement of the Law, in the absence of any corresponding Law<lb/> on the point, in Sikkim, held as follows;<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;3. The Indian Easements Act, 1882, was never<lb/> formally adopted in Sikkim prior to its incorporation in<lb/> the Union of India; nor the same has been extended<lb/> to Sikkim by any notification under Article 371-F (n)<lb/> of the Constitution of India or otherwise; and neither<lb/> there was nor there is any corresponding statutory<lb/> law relating to easement or licence in force in Sikkim.<lb/> But when a point for decision was not covered by the<lb/> provision of any law in force in Sikkim, the Courts in<lb/> Sikkim, from long before its incorporation in the Union<lb/> of India, have followed the principles of laws in force<lb/> in India in deciding such a point, if such principles<lb/> appeared to them to be based on or in consonance<lb/> with the principles of justice, equity and good<lb/> conscience. If this is characterized as making of laws<lb/> by Courts, it may be pointed out that the very same<lb/> thing was done by the Courts in India during the<lb/> early British period when legislative laws in India were<lb/> scanty and the Courts in India freely followed and<lb/> adopted the principles of the English law in deciding<lb/> points not covered by the provisions of the Indian<lb/> laws in force. As is well-known, India was then a<lb/> country which was almost empty of legislative laws<lb/> and the void was to a great extent filled up by Courts<lb/> through their decisions by importing the principles of<lb/> English law, both common and statutory.<lb/></item>

			<item>4. …………………………………………………………………<lb/></item>

			<item>5. The principles contained in the Section quoted<lb/> above are no doubt based on justice, equity and good<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> conscience as has been held by the Division Bench of<lb/> the Allahabad High Court in Mathuri versus Bhola<lb/> Nath (AIR 1934 Allahabad 517) and the principles of<lb/> this section have been applied in those parts of India<lb/> where this Easements Act does not expressly extend<lb/> and apply. As I have already pointed out, the Courts<lb/> in Sikkim have freely applied the provisions of Indian<lb/> Laws in cases not specifically covered by the laws in<lb/> Sikkim, if the relevant provisions of the Indian laws<lb/> appeared -to them to be consonant with the<lb/> principles of equity and justice. In my view, therefore,<lb/> the provisions of Section 60, Indian Easements Act,<lb/> 1882 can be invoked and should be applied in Sikkim<lb/> in the absence of any corresponding law in Sikkim on<lb/> the point. I would repeat that if this amounts to<lb/> making of laws by Courts, the Courts in Sikkim will<lb/> have to continue to do so until the field is occupied or<lb/> is substantially occupied by specific laws. ………&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>34.<lb/> In the decision of Durga Prasad Pradhan v. Palden Lama,<lb/> Second Appeal No.1 of 1980, decided on 03.06.1981, the Division<lb/> Bench of this High Court while considering the submissions of<lb/> Counsel for the Respondent that the Specific Relief Act of 1963 had<lb/> not been extended to Sikkim and therefore did not apply to Sikkim,<lb/> held as follows;<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;5. ………………It is true that the Specific Relief<lb/> Act, 1963, does not apply in Sikkim and there is no<lb/> statutory law in Sikkim on this subject. But it is now<lb/> beyond doubt that even if an enactment does not<lb/> extend and apply to any area ex proprio vigore, but<lb/> the enactment contains provisions which are statutory<lb/> embodiment of the rules of equity and justice, such<lb/> provisions have been, are and may be applied by the<lb/> Courts to transactions beyond such area, in the<lb/> absence of any law operating therein. ……&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>35.<lb/> It may also be recounted here that Justice A.M.<lb/> Bhattacharjee, J in his notes sent to the Law Commission of Sikkim,<lb/> reported in 1978 (3) Sikkim Law Journal, at Page 4, wrote as follows;<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;…………………………………<lb/> The provisions of the Hindu Law and the<lb/> Mahomedan Law having been so long applied,<lb/> recognised, administered, enforced and acted upon by<lb/> the State and its Judicial Organ, the Courts of Sikkim,<lb/> the provisions so applied became laws in Sikkim and<lb/> have continued as laws under the principle enunciated<lb/> in those Privy Council and Supreme Court cases and<lb/> have actually been continued as laws under the<lb/> provisions of Clause (k) of Article 371F of the<lb/> Constitution<lb/> whereunder<lb/> &quot;all<lb/> laws<lb/> in<lb/> force<lb/> immediately before the applinted(sic) day in the<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> territories comprised in the State of Sikkim or any<lb/> part thereof shall continue to be in force therein until<lb/> amended or repealed by a competent Legislature or<lb/> other competent authority.&quot; The provisions of the<lb/> Hindu Law and the Mahomedan Law, therefore, to the<lb/> extent they have been applied, recognised,<lb/> administered, enforced and acted upon by the Courts<lb/> in Sikkim before its incorporation in the Union of<lb/> India, still continue as laws in force under the<lb/> mandate of Article 371F (k). ………………………<lb/> I am, therefore, of opinion that notwithstanding<lb/> the absence of any statutory provisions making Hindu<lb/> Law and Mahomedan Law applicable to Hindus and<lb/> Mahomedans in Sikkim, the provisions of Hindu Law<lb/> and Mahomedan Law would apply to Hindus and<lb/> Mahomedans of Sikkim to the extent those have been<lb/> applied, recognised, administered, enforced and acted<lb/> upon by the Courts of Sikkim prior to its incorporation<lb/> in the Union of India. …………………………&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>36.<lb/> Relying on the various ratio referred to hereinabove and<lb/> on the bedrock of the reasoning thereon, it is evident that where<lb/> there is no existing old Law on a particular subject in Sikkim or<lb/> where the Law is scanty or inadequate, the Courts in Sikkim also<lb/> being Courts of equity, justice and good conscience, have to turn to<lb/> the Laws of the country. It is but apposite to notice that the Courts<lb/> in Sikkim, even prior to being part of the Indian Union have followed<lb/> principles of Law in force in India if the principles were based on<lb/> justice, equity and good conscience, as already reflected in the<lb/> plethora of ratio of this High Court referred to above. In Jas Bahadur<lb/> Rai (supra), it may be reiterated that it was observed as follows;<lb/> &quot;5.……In my view, therefore, the provisions of<lb/> Section 60, Indian Easements Act, 1882 can be<lb/> invoked and should be applied in Sikkim in the<lb/> absence of any corresponding law in Sikkim on the<lb/> point. I would repeat that if this amounts to making<lb/> of laws by Courts, the Courts in Sikkim will have to<lb/> continue to do so until the field is occupied or is<lb/> substantially occupied by specific laws. ……&quot;<lb/> (Emphasis supplied)<lb/> Considering that the provisions of the Hindu Succession Act, 1956,<lb/> has not been extended or enforced in the State, nor does any<lb/> corresponding Statute occupy the field in the State, it would, in the<lb/> circumstances be just and proper to look to and apply the principles<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> contained in the Hindu Succession Act, 1956, for the purposes of<lb/> considering matters relating to Succession in Sikkim, for persons to<lb/> whom it applies as personal Law.<lb/></p>

			<p>37.<lb/> The parties are Hindu Brahmins. This is not disputed.<lb/> Their father Devi Prasad divided the property amongst his three<lb/> sons contemporaneously which was consented to by all without any<lb/> objection. As under the Mitakshara Law, the father i.e. Devi Prasad<lb/> had the power to divide the family property during his lifetime and<lb/> exercised his power, as evident from Exhibit &quot;A&quot; which is admitted<lb/> to by all parties, thus, for all intents and purposes, it can be gauged<lb/> that their family was following the principles of the Mitakshara<lb/> School of Hindu Law. The above discussions soundly answers the<lb/> first question settled for determination by this Court.<lb/></p>

			<p>38.<lb/> Now to address the second question flagged, under the<lb/> Mitakshara School of Hindu Law, each son and now daughters vide<lb/> the Hindu Succession (Amendment) Act, 2005, in Section 6, are<lb/> coparceners in their own right and upon birth, take an equal interest<lb/> in the ancestral property, whether movable or immovable. Thus,<lb/> being entitled to a share, they can seek partition. If they do so, the<lb/> effect in Law is not only a separation of the father from the sons but<lb/> a separation inter se, the consent of the sons is not necessary for<lb/> the exercise of that power. However, no Hindu father joined with his<lb/> sons and governed by the Mitakshara Law although vested with the<lb/> power to partition the property can make a partition of the joint<lb/> family property by Will. In Kalyani (Dead) by Lrs. v. Narayanan and<lb/> Others 16 , the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court has propounded this principle.<lb/> Once partition is complete, the property then becomes the separate<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> property of each of the coparceners, however, in the hands of the<lb/> son, the property will be ancestral property and the natural or<lb/> adopted son of that son will take interest in it and be entitled to it<lb/> by survivorship and joint family property. [See Mullah&apos;s Hindu Law,<lb/> 22 nd Edition, Chapter XII]. The Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court in C.N.<lb/> Arunachala Mudaliar v. C.A. Muruganatha Mudaliar and Another 17<lb/> considered the question as to where a Hindu, instead of requiring<lb/> his self-acquired or separate property to go by descent, makes a<lb/> gift of it to his son, or bequeaths it to him by Will, whether such<lb/> property is the separate property of the son or whether it is<lb/> ancestral in the hands of the son as regards his male and female<lb/> issues. It was observed that if there are no clear words describing<lb/> the kind of interest intended to be given, the Court would have to<lb/> collect the intention from the language of the document, taken<lb/> along with the surrounding circumstances in accordance with the<lb/> established cannons of construction.<lb/></p>

			<p>39.<lb/> It is apparent from the records, that the parties are in<lb/> agreement that the property partitioned amongst the Plaintiffs and<lb/> the deceased Bal Krishna, were ancestral properties. Late Devi<lb/> Prasad, during his lifetime, vide Exhibit &quot;A,&quot; partitioned all movable<lb/> and immovable property amongst his three sons, the Plaintiffs being<lb/> his sons from his first wife and Bal Krishna being the son from his<lb/> second wife, the Defendant No.1. He set aside some property for<lb/> himself during the said partition, for his sustenance during his<lb/> lifetime, known in common local parlance as &quot;jiwni.&quot; Admittedly,<lb/> Exhibit &quot;A&quot; was prepared by Devi Prasad in his full consciousness<lb/> and consented to by his three sons, duly witnessed by the<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> Panchayat and the village elders, who also affixed their signatures<lb/> on the document along with the Plaintiffs. On partition, the share of<lb/> Devi Prasad became his separate property, and he was free to<lb/> dispose it off as he thought fit including bequeathing it by a Will.<lb/> Exhibit &quot;A&quot; is thus, not only a Deed of Partition but a testamentary<lb/> disposition for the &quot;jiwni&quot; property of Devi Prasad. On pain of<lb/> repetition, it may be stated that vide Exhibit &quot;A,&quot; Devi Prasad laid<lb/> down conditions viz. &quot;father&quot;s &quot;jiwni&quot; share would go to the son who<lb/> would look after and perform death rites.&quot; It needs to be clarified<lb/> here that he has not mentioned &quot;parents&quot; as claimed by the<lb/> Defendant No.1 and Devi Kala Sharma, guardian of Defendant No.4,<lb/> in their evidence. In the scheme of Exhibit &quot;A,&quot; no reference has<lb/> been made to Defendant No.1 save to the effect that when the<lb/> partition was executed, the &quot;sons&quot; were referred to as the &quot;sons of<lb/> first wife&quot; and &quot;sons of second wife&quot; and not by their own names.<lb/> On this aspect, in Reserve Bank of India v. Peerless General Finance<lb/> and Investment Co. Ltd. And Others 18 , it was inter alia observed as<lb/> under;<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;33. Interpretation must depend on the text and<lb/> the context. They are the bases of interpretation. One<lb/> may well say if the text is the texture, context is what<lb/> gives the colour. Neither can be ignored. Both are<lb/> important. That interpretation is best which makes<lb/> the textual interpretation match the contextual. A<lb/> statute is best interpreted when we know why it was<lb/> enacted. With this knowledge, the statute must be<lb/> read, first as a whole and then section by section,<lb/> clause by clause, phrase by phrase and word by word.<lb/></item>

			<item>If a statute is looked at, in the context of its<lb/> enactment, with the glasses of the statute-maker,<lb/> provided by such context, its scheme, the sections,<lb/> clauses, phrases and words may take colour and<lb/> appear different than when the statute is looked at<lb/> without the glasses provided by the context. …… No<lb/> part of a statute and no word of a statute can be<lb/> construed in isolation. Statutes have to be construed<lb/></item>

			<p>18 (1987) 1 SCC 424<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> so that every word has a place and everything is in its<lb/> place. ……&quot;<lb/> Further, in Anwar Hasan Khan v. Mohd. Shafi and Others 19 , the Hon&quot;ble<lb/> Supreme Court inter alia held thus;<lb/> &quot;8. ...... It is a cardinal principle of construction<lb/> of a statute that effort should be made in construing<lb/> its provisions by avoiding a conflict and adopting a<lb/> harmonious construction. The statute or rules made<lb/> thereunder should be read as a whole and one<lb/> provision should be construed with reference to the<lb/> other provision to make the provision consistent with<lb/> the object sought to be achieved.&quot;<lb/> The testamentary disposition of Devi Prasad of course, in no way,<lb/> can be described as a Statute, nevertheless the principles<lb/> enunciated above for interpretation, may well be adopted for the<lb/> purposes of interpreting the relevant portion of Exhibit &quot;A.&quot; Thus, on<lb/> the anvil of the said principles, a careful scrutiny of Exhibit &quot;A&quot;<lb/> indubitably establishes that Devi Prasad was referring to himself<lb/> only and none else for the purposes of the conditions laid down in<lb/> the testamentary disposition.<lb/></p>

			<p>40.<lb/> While further considering Exhibit &quot;A,&quot; it is evidently an<lb/> unregistered document. The Sikkim State General Department<lb/> Notification No.385/G, dated 11.04.1928, requires all documents<lb/> such as mortgage and Sale Deeds and &quot;other important documents&quot;<lb/> and Deeds to be registered and will not be considered valid unless<lb/> they are duly registered. Nevertheless, it is now no more res integra<lb/> that the Courts can look into unregistered documents more so, if it<lb/> is a family settlement. The Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court in Thulasidhara<lb/> and Another v. Narayanappa and Others 20 held inter alia as follows;<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;</item>

9.4……… The High Court has refused to look<lb/> into the said document and/or consider document<lb/> dated 23-4-1971 (Ext. D-4) solely on the ground that<lb/> it requires registration and therefore as it is<lb/> unregistered, the same cannot be looked into.<lb/></item>

			<item>Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> However,<lb/> as<lb/> observed<lb/> by<lb/> this<lb/> Court<lb/> in Kale [Kale v. Director of Consolidation, (1976) 3<lb/> SCC 119] that such a family settlement, though not<lb/> registered, would operate as a complete estoppel<lb/> against the parties to such a family settlement. …………<lb/></item>

			<item>9.5. As<lb/> held<lb/> by<lb/> this<lb/> Court<lb/> in Subraya<lb/> M.N. [Subraya M.N. v. Vittala M.N., (2016) 8 SCC 705<lb/> : (2016) 4 SCC (Civ) 163] even without registration a<lb/> written<lb/> document<lb/> of<lb/> family<lb/> settlement/family<lb/> arrangement can be used as corroborative evidence<lb/> as explaining the arrangement made thereunder and<lb/> conduct of the parties. In the present case, as<lb/> observed hereinabove, even the plaintiff has also<lb/> categorically admitted that the oral partition had<lb/> taken place on 23-4-1971 and he also admitted that 3<lb/> to 4 panchayat people were also present. However,<lb/> according to him, the same was not reduced in<lb/> writing. Therefore, even accepting the case of the<lb/> plaintiff that there was an oral partition on 23-4-<lb/>1971, the document, Ext. D-4 dated 23-4-1971, to<lb/> which he is also the signatory and all other family<lb/> members are signatory, can be said to be a list of<lb/> properties partitioned. Everybody got right/share as<lb/> per the oral partition/partition. Therefore, the same<lb/> even can be used as corroborative evidence as<lb/> explaining the arrangement made thereunder and<lb/> conduct of the parties. Therefore, in the facts and<lb/> circumstances of the case, the High Court has<lb/> committed a grave/manifest error in not looking into<lb/> and/or not considering the document Ext. D-4 dated<lb/> 23-4-1971.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>The Law having been thus settled, Exhibit &quot;A&quot; reveals the family<lb/> arrangement pertaining to partition of the ancestral properties as<lb/> well as bequeathment by Will.<lb/></p>

			<p>41.<lb/> It would now be relevant to consider and address the<lb/> contesting arguments of the parties regarding the care given by the<lb/> Plaintiffs to their deceased father. The averments in the Plaint at<lb/> Paragraph 22 &quot;G&quot; reveal as follows;<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;That, the Plaintiffs had taken care of their<lb/> father during his lifetime and never performed death<lb/> rites under duress. The Plaintiffs had also provided<lb/> financial, medical and all types of help those are given<lb/> by son(sic) to their father late D.P. Dahal during his<lb/> lifetime.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>The Plaintiffs&quot; contention and evidence is that the Plaintiff No.1 was<lb/> driven out of the main house in 1983-84 with a &quot;khukuri&quot; by his<lb/> father and step mother. Notwithstanding such treatment, he took<lb/> care of his father by replacing the thatched roof of the main house<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> with GCI sheets and extending all financial and other relevant help.<lb/> The Defendant No.1 asserted that the two points raised above were<lb/> never pleaded and it is settled Law that evidence cannot be adduced<lb/> beyond the pleadings. Beneficial reference on this count is made to<lb/> M. Chinnasamy (supra) relied on by Defendant No.1, wherein it was<lb/> held inter alia as follows;<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;42. With respect, we are not in a position to<lb/> endorse the views taken therein in their entirety.<lb/> Unfortunately, the decision of a larger Bench of this<lb/> Court in Jagjit Singh [AIR 1966 SC 773] had not been<lb/> noticed therein. Apart from the clear legal position as<lb/> laid down in several decisions, as noticed<lb/> hereinbefore, there cannot be any doubt or dispute<lb/> that only because a re-counting has been directed, it<lb/> would not be held to be sacrosanct to the effect that<lb/> although in a given case the court may find such<lb/> evidence to be at variance with the pleadings, the<lb/> same must be taken into consideration. It is now<lb/> well-settled principle of law that evidence adduced<lb/> beyond the pleadings would not be admissible nor<lb/> can any evidence be permitted to be adduced which<lb/> is at variance with the pleadings. The court at a later<lb/> stage of the trial as also the appellate court having<lb/> regard to the rule of pleadings would be entitled to<lb/> reject the evidence wherefor there does not exist any<lb/> pleading.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<item>(Emphasis supplied)<lb/></item>

			<p>In Union of India v. Ibrahim Uddin and Another (supra), the Hon&quot;ble<lb/> Supreme Court observed inter alia as under;<lb/> &quot;85.6. The court cannot travel beyond the<lb/> pleadings as no party can lead the evidence on an<lb/> issue/point not raised in the pleadings and in case,<lb/> such evidence has been adduced or a finding of fact<lb/> has been recorded by the court, it is just to be<lb/> ignored. Though it may be a different case where in<lb/> spite of specific pleadings, a particular issue is not<lb/> framed and the parties having full knowledge of the<lb/> issue in controversy lead the evidence and the court<lb/> records a finding on it. ………………&quot;<lb/> (Emphasis supplied)<lb/></p>

			<p>42.<lb/> In light of the established position of Law, the Plaintiffs&quot;<lb/> evidence, as well as those of their witnesses with regard to the<lb/> instance of the Plaintiff No.1 being chased out by his father and step<lb/> mother with a &quot;khukuri&quot; and replacement by him of the thatched<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> roof of his main house, being over and above the averments in his<lb/> pleadings, is rejected and disregarded in totality by this Court.<lb/></p>

			<p>43.<lb/> However, the pleadings of the Plaintiffs do also contain<lb/> the averment that they had provided financial, medical and other<lb/> assistance to their father as expected of sons. I now examine the<lb/> proof thereof.<lb/></p>

			<p>44.<lb/> Plaintiffs No.1 and 2 both deposed that during their<lb/> father&quot;s visits to their respective houses, they gave him money for<lb/> medicine and clothing, apart from which they also took him for<lb/> medical treatment to Doctors. PW Kunta Maya Dahal, relative of the<lb/> Plaintiffs, supported their evidence, her evidence found<lb/> substantiation in the evidence of PW7 Tanka Maya Adhikari, the<lb/> blood sister of the Plaintiffs. PW Laxuman Nepal and PW Ram<lb/> Chandra Koirala, both known to the Plaintiffs and their father, were<lb/> witness to the Plaintiffs visiting their father during his illness and<lb/> stated as much. A perusal of the cross-examination of Plaintiffs No.1<lb/> and 2 reveal that no questions were put to them in cross-<lb/>examination to test the veracity of their statements pertaining to<lb/> extension of financial help to their father and taking him to the<lb/> Doctor, save to the extent that they did not furnish documentary<lb/> evidence of such facts. With regard to the second condition in<lb/> Exhibit &quot;A&quot; i.e. &quot;perform death rites,&quot; both Plaintiffs deposed that<lb/> they had performed their father&quot;s death rites and rituals voluntarily.<lb/> This evidence was buttressed by the deposition of PW Kunta Maya<lb/> Dahal, PW3 Man Bahadur Kharka, PW 7 Tanka Maya Adhikari, PW<lb/> Laxuman Nepal (son of Krishna Lall Nepal), PW Ram Chandra<lb/> Koirala and PW6 Krishna Prasad Sapkota. Both PW3 Man Bahadur<lb/> Kharka and PW6 Krishna Prasad Sapkota admitted to being illiterate<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> but no questions were put to them in cross-examination to test their<lb/> knowledge or otherwise of the contents of their evidence-in-chief<lb/> nor was any effort made by Defendant No.1 and Defendant No.4 to<lb/> gauge as to whether they had each been explained the contents of<lb/> Exhibit 17 and Exhibit 18, their respective Evidence-on-Affidavit. It<lb/> was also the admission of both witnesses that the contents were in<lb/> &quot;English&quot; and they did not know what it stated but the contents of<lb/> the documents were not translated for their benefit during cross-<lb/>examination. Omnibus and vague questions put to the witnesses<lb/> from rural backgrounds, in cross-examination, is not only<lb/> unacceptable but such questions, in no way, demolish the evidence-<lb/>in-chief. In this context, apposite reference may be made to Shivaji<lb/> Sahabrao Bobade and Another v. State of Maharashtra 21 wherein the<lb/> Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court observed inter alia as follows;<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;8. Now to the facts. The scene of murder is<lb/> rural, the witnesses to the case are rustics and so<lb/> their behavioural pattern and perceptive habits have<lb/> to be judged as such. The too sophisticated<lb/> approaches familiar in courts based on unreal<lb/> assumptions about human conduct cannot obviously<lb/> be applied to those given to the lethargic ways of our<lb/> villages. When scanning the evidence of the various<lb/> witnesses we have to inform ourselves that variances<lb/> on the fringes, discrepancies in details, contradictions<lb/> in narrations and embellishments in inessential parts<lb/> cannot militate against the veracity of the core of the<lb/> testimony provided there is the impress of truth and<lb/> conformity to probability in the substantial fabric of<lb/> testimony delivered. ……&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>45.<lb/> It therefore transpires that the rustic background and<lb/> education of the witnesses viz. PW3 and PW6 were not taken into<lb/> consideration by the learned Defence Counsel when the questions<lb/> were put to them in cross-examination. Notwithstanding such a<lb/> circumstance, even if the evidence of PW3 and PW6 are to be<lb/> disregarded, the claim of the Plaintiffs that they had extended<lb/> 21 (1973) 2 SCC 793<lb/> monetary assistance to their father, spent time with him by visiting<lb/> him when he was unwell and both of them having performed the<lb/> death rites of their late father, could not be said to be untrue, the<lb/> evidence of the Plaintiffs and their two witnesses having stood<lb/> resolute under cross-examination on these two counts. In fact, even<lb/> the evidence of DW2 Tika Devi Sharma, witness for Defendant No.1,<lb/> reveals that both Plaintiffs used to visit the main house in intervals<lb/> and they behaved cordially with their father and Defendant No.1,<lb/> while Laxuman Nepal (son of Jai Narayan Nepal), witness for the<lb/> Defendant No.4, admitted that the Plaintiffs performed the death<lb/> rites of their father voluntarily. It may be observed here that taking<lb/> care of parents cannot be construed only as financial assistance<lb/> rendered, time spent with parents is also to be given the credit it<lb/> deserves.<lb/></p>

			<p>46.<lb/> Defendant No.1, for her part, denied the claims of the<lb/> Plaintiffs that they had contributed financially towards the treatment<lb/> of Devi Prasad as, according to her, only she and her son Bal<lb/> Krishna, bore all required expenses, even to the extent of having<lb/> taken loans. Exhibit D4/A, dated 16.08.2001 and Exhibit D4/B,<lb/> dated 23.09.2001, i.e. documents purportedly establishing loan<lb/> taken by her son for her husband&quot;s treatment from Bishnu<lb/> Khatiwada and Laxuman Nepal (son of Jai Narayan Nepal), were<lb/> strongly relied upon by her. No documents were furnished to<lb/> establish the decade long illness of Devi Prasad or his bedridden and<lb/> convalescent condition. No explanation ensued as to why Exhibit<lb/> D4/A and Exhibit D4/B were not furnished before the learned trial<lb/> Court before the remand of the matter. The scribe of the said<lb/> documents were also not produced as witnesses either by the<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> Defendant No.1 or the Defendant No.4 and although DW1 Laxuman<lb/> Nepal ventured to state that Bal Krishna was the scribe of Exhibit<lb/> D4/B, no handwriting of Bal Krishna was furnished for comparison.<lb/> The credibility of these documents, in my considered opinion, is<lb/> suspect. Reliance on the ratio of Kiran Limboo (supra) and on the<lb/> provisions of Section 67 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872, in fact,<lb/> goes against the Defendant No.1 as no witness has proved the<lb/> contents of Exhibit D4/A and Exhibit D4/B.<lb/></p>

			<p>47.<lb/> Although, DW2 Tika Devi Sharma made an effort to<lb/> support the evidence of the Defendant No.1, however, under cross-<lb/>examination, buckled and admitted that the Plaintiffs used to visit<lb/> the main house at intervals and behave cordially with her parents.<lb/> According to her, there was no quarrel between her father and the<lb/> Plaintiffs on the execution of Exhibit &quot;A.&quot; The evidence of DW Dol<lb/> Nath Gautam can scarcely be relied on considering that when the<lb/> partition was affected in 1985, he was eleven years old and could<lb/> have had no personal knowledge of events that took place then.<lb/></p>

			<p>DW2 Dhan Maya Adhikari, the half sister of the Plaintiffs, supported<lb/> the evidence of Defendant No.1, her evidence withstood cross-<lb/>examination. DW Punya Prasad Adhikari, known to the Plaintiffs and<lb/> their father as well as the Defendant No.1, brought a new twist to<lb/> the tale by stating in his evidence that the Plaintiffs were<lb/> disgruntled with the family partition which he had learnt from Devi<lb/> Prasad and therefore the Plaintiffs and their father did not share<lb/> cordial relations. He supported the evidence of Defendant No.1 that<lb/> only she and her son took care of Devi Prasad and performed the<lb/> death rites, however, later he admitted that no issue was raised by<lb/> any of the sons relating to the shares allotted and that the Plaintiffs<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> had performed the thirteenth day funeral rites of their father. His<lb/> evidence is therefore vacillating with regard to the conduct of the<lb/> Plaintiffs in the context of execution of Exhibit &quot;A&quot; as reflected supra<lb/> and cannot be considered reliable. DW4 Ramesh Kumar Dahal is the<lb/> son of Plaintiff No.1, born in 1982. He failed to give any substantive<lb/> evidence pertaining to the case save to the extent that his parents<lb/> are separated and that Bal Krishna had participated in the<lb/> &quot;Anthyesthi Kriya&quot; (death rites) of his grandfather.<lb/></p>

			<p>48.<lb/> For the Defendant No.4, DW1 Laxuman Nepal (son of Jai<lb/> Narayan Nepal), known to the Plaintiffs and their father and the<lb/> Defendants No.1 and 4, had no knowledge of the relations between<lb/> the Plaintiffs and their father. He, however, admitted that the<lb/> Plaintiffs performed the death rites of their father voluntarily.<lb/> According to him, vide Exhibit D4/B, dated 23.09.2001, he loaned<lb/> Rs.20,000/-(Rupees twenty thousand) only, to Bal Krishna. Exhibit<lb/> D4/B is an unregistered document. It does not mention the interest<lb/> amount nor does it mention that the interest amount would be fixed<lb/> subsequently on non-payment of the principle amount, thus the<lb/> contents are rather nebulous for a loan document. The only witness<lb/> to Exhibit D4/B is the elder sister of Bal Krishna, Devi Kala Sharma.<lb/> The entire circumstances of the document having been furnished<lb/> only after the matter was sent back on remand and produced before<lb/> the learned trial Court with Bal Krishna&quot;s sister as the sole witness,<lb/> lends suspicion to it. Considering the belated appearance of the<lb/> document and lack of proof thereof, it is reiterated that it appears to<lb/> have been manufactured for the purposes of the instant matter and<lb/> cannot be relied upon.<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/></p>

			<p>49.<lb/> Madhav Prasad Adhikari examined as witness No.2 for<lb/> Defendant No.4, was also a witness for Defendant No.1. In his<lb/> evidence as witness for Defendant No.1, he stated that he is the<lb/> maternal uncle of late Devi Prasad. Contrarily, in his evidence as<lb/> witness for Defendant No.4, he stated that Devi Prasad was his<lb/> maternal uncle. Relevantly, in Paragraph &quot;5&quot; of his evidence as<lb/> witness for Defendant No.1, he has stated that the Plaintiffs being<lb/> satisfied with the respective shares that they received, in full<lb/> consent, scribed their signature on the said Partition Deed.<lb/> Conversely, as witness for the Defendant No.4, in Paragraph &quot;3&quot; of<lb/> his evidence, he stated that he had learnt from late Devi Prasad<lb/> that both the Plaintiffs did not share good relations with him as they<lb/> were unhappy with the family partition and after the said partition,<lb/> they had discarded their father and had very sour relations with his<lb/> entire family. The witness appears to be confused with regard to<lb/> how he was related to Devi Prasad added to which, his inconsistent<lb/> and ambivalent evidence reflected hereinabove makes him an<lb/> unreliable and untrustworthy witness. His evidence thereby merits<lb/> no reliance.<lb/></p>

			<p>50.<lb/> DW3 Tika Devi Sharma, was witness for Defendant No.1<lb/> and also appeared as witness for the Defendant No.4. She sought to<lb/> establish that Bal Krishna as also her sister Devi Kala, the guardian<lb/> of Defendant No.4, were bona fide Sikkimese Indians and reiterated<lb/> that only Defendant No.1 and her brother looked after their father<lb/> but admitted that she had no documents relating to her father&quot;s<lb/> prolonged ailment and that they were not on talking terms with the<lb/> Plaintiffs. DW4 Bishnu Khatiwada, son-in-law of late Devi Prasad<lb/> being the husband of DW3, also narrated the story of the Plaintiffs<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> abandoning their parents after voluntarily leaving the main house<lb/> and identified Exhibit D4/A as the receipt for a sum of Rs.50,000/-<lb/>(Rupees fifty thousand) only, taken by Bal Krishna from him, for his<lb/> father&quot;s treatment. The cross-examination of this witness revealed<lb/> that he was a Bus conductor in the SNT Department and in 2001,<lb/> his monthly salary was around Rs.15,000/-(Rupees fifteen<lb/> thousand) only, besides which he had two School going sons and a<lb/> wife to support. He was unaware as to who had scribed Exhibit D4/A<lb/> and did not state its contents although he identified it as a &quot;Money<lb/> Receipt&quot; and his signature on it. Admittedly, he was not on speaking<lb/> terms with the Plaintiffs and did not share good relations with them.<lb/> His evidence of having loaned Rs.50,000/-(Rupees fifty thousand)<lb/> only, to Bal Krishna has to be taken with a pinch of salt as he was<lb/> earning Rs.15,000/-(Rupees fifteen thousand) only, per month as<lb/> the sole bread winner in his family comprising of his wife and two<lb/> School going sons. Mere marking and exhibiting of documents is not<lb/> proof of its contents. His evident inimical relations with the Plaintiffs<lb/> and lack of proof of Exhibit D4/A, renders his evidence unreliable.<lb/> DW Devi Kala Sharma, half sister of the Plaintiffs, is the guardian of<lb/> the Defendant No.4. She too asserted that the family of Devi Prasad<lb/> is governed by the Law of the land and not by the Mitakshara<lb/> School of Hindu Law. According to her, the Plaintiffs are signatories<lb/> to Exhibit &quot;A&quot; and they have already acted upon the Partition Deed.<lb/> She further stated that Bal Krishna and Defendant No.1 looked after<lb/> Devi Prasad and she was aware of this fact as she helped them,<lb/> being a Staff Nurse at the Central Referral Hospital, Tadong. From<lb/> there, he was taken to Siliguri for further treatment. After he<lb/> passed away, the Plaintiffs were forced to come to the main house<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> and perform the death rites. According to her, the &quot;jiwni&quot; land had<lb/> been kept by her father for her mother&quot;s welfare and he had sold a<lb/> piece of land to meet her (witness&quot;s) educational expenses. While<lb/> considering her evidence, it is clear that she is now making an<lb/> endeavour to insert a tangential angle to the case of the Defendant<lb/> No.1 by stating that the &quot;jiwni bari&quot; was kept for her mother&quot;s<lb/> welfare. Her deposition is evidently an attempt to protect her<lb/> mother (Defendant No.1) and ensure that she gets the property<lb/> although Exhibit &quot;A&quot; specifically mentions the conditions on which<lb/> the son(s) of Devi Prasad would get the &quot;jiwni&quot; property. In tandem<lb/> with the evidence of Defendant No.1, this witness has also stated<lb/> that the conditions in the Partition Deed are that the son &quot;look after<lb/> the parents and also perform their death rites.&quot; This is an erroneous<lb/> interpretation of the document as already discussed in detail above.<lb/> No mention of either &quot;mother&quot; or &quot;parents&quot; has been made in the<lb/> document neither was any witness of the Plaintiffs, Defendant No.1<lb/> or Defendant No.4, confronted with the contents of the document to<lb/> explain or expound this portion. She denied all suggestions put to<lb/> her with regard to manufacturing of the documents exhibited and<lb/> stated that the Plaintiff No.1 had not been maintaining his first wife.<lb/> This is contrary to the evidence of DW4 Ramesh Kumar Dahal, the<lb/> son of the Plaintiff No.1, who stated under cross-examination that<lb/> his father pays maintenance to his mother after she had filed a<lb/> Maintenance Case in the Court in 1998. Her evidence, therefore,<lb/> cannot be accepted in its totality in view of the exacerbations she<lb/> has made with regard to the interpretation of Exhibit &quot;A&quot; and that<lb/> the &quot;jiwni bari&quot; was for her mother&quot;s welfare.<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/></p>

			<p>51.<lb/> The foregoing evidence, thus, establishes that the<lb/> Plaintiffs did assist their father financially whenever he visited them<lb/> and they also visited him at intervals, behaved cordially with him as<lb/> also with the Defendant No.1 and were seen to be with their father<lb/> when he fell ill. The weight of the evidence furnished by the parties<lb/> tilts in favour of the Plaintiffs notwithstanding the fact that they<lb/> were living apart from him and were involved in running homes for<lb/> their own separate families as against the ambivalent and vacillating<lb/> evidence of the witnesses of the Defendant No.1 and Defendant<lb/> No.4, as already discussed. Bal Krishna had the advantage of living<lb/> with his parents and it is not contested that he took care of them by<lb/> virtue of such a circumstance. The fact that the Plaintiffs along with<lb/> Bal Krishna, performed the death rites of their father withstood all<lb/> cross-examination and, in any event, the Defendant No.1 and her<lb/> witnesses have also admitted this fact. I have to agree with the<lb/> observation of learned Senior Counsel for the Plaintiffs that no son<lb/> or daughter worth their salt would keep an account book of the<lb/> expenditure made towards maintaining or taking care of their<lb/> parents. It would indeed be an abhorrent circumstance sufficient to<lb/> arouse indignation in any person. Devi Prasad evidently made no<lb/> complaints to any witness of nonchalant or callous attitude of the<lb/> Plaintiffs towards him.<lb/></p>

			<p>52.<lb/> In this context, the learned trial Court while deciding<lb/> Issue No.7, was of the opinion that the Plaintiffs were unable to<lb/> substantiate their claims of having taken care of their father during<lb/> his lifetime by any documentary proof thereof. The evidence of PW<lb/> Laxuman Nepal and PW Ram Chandra Koirala were found to be<lb/> unreliable as according to the learned trial Court, these witnesses<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> had only made bald claims with regard to the Plaintiffs having taken<lb/> care of Devi Prasad when he was unwell. The learned trial Court<lb/> desired &quot;corroboration from worthy evidence,&quot; however, it was not<lb/> specified as to what the &quot;worthy evidence&quot; was to comprise of. The<lb/> learned trial Court had concluded that although the Plaintiffs had<lb/> performed the death rites of their father, however, they had not<lb/> taken care of their father during his lifetime. In the light of the<lb/> evidence on record and the foregoing discussions already discussed<lb/> by me, I am unable to bring myself to agree with the finding of the<lb/> learned trial Court in Issue No.7.<lb/></p>

			<p>53.<lb/> While deciding Issue No.2, the learned trial Court relied<lb/> heavily on the evidence of Defendant No.1 and DW4 Bishnu<lb/> Khatiwada, the witness for Defendant No.4, Exhibit D4/A, the<lb/> unregistered Money Receipt, the evidence of Laxuman Nepal (son of<lb/> Jai Narayan Nepal) and Exhibit D4/B. Learned trial Court was<lb/> impressed with the production of Exhibit D4/A and Exhibit D4/B<lb/> despite the fact that these documents had been filed rather<lb/> belatedly, only after the matter having been sent back on remand,<lb/> thereby raising doubts about the authenticity of the documents. The<lb/> reasoning of the learned trial Court at Paragraph &quot;43&quot; of the<lb/> impugned Judgment inter alia was that,<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;43. …………The Plaintiffs on the other hand were<lb/> already staying separately from Late Devi Prasad<lb/> Dahal and once the partition took place the severance<lb/> of joint status, even if the same were to be assumed,<lb/> would also be deemed to have taken place. Once it is<lb/> held so, even if there was no banda patra/<lb/> testamentary disposition above the &quot;jiwni land&quot; of Late<lb/> Devi Prasad Dahal (which became his separate<lb/> property after the partition) would devolve on his<lb/> undivided son (Late Bal Krishna Dahal) to the<lb/> exclusion of his divided sons (Plaintiffs)………………<lb/> …………………………Raghavachariar in his Hindu Law,<lb/> Second Edition, Page 444 states that where a father<lb/> was joint at the time of his death with some only of<lb/> his sons, the others having already separated from<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> him, those who remained joint with him, whether they<lb/> were sons born before or after the partition, succeed<lb/> to the whole property, whether ancestral or self-<lb/>acquired, to the exclusion of the divided sons. ……&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>54.<lb/> The learned trial Court concluded that this seems to be<lb/> the settled position under the Mitakshara Law which solely governed<lb/> the Hindus in the State during the year 2001 when Devi Prasad had<lb/> died. I have to disagree with this finding and the interpretation<lb/> given to the above position of Law as stated by Raghavachariar in<lb/> view of the fact that after the partition had taken place vide Exhibit<lb/> &quot;A,&quot; as already discussed supra, the father had his own share in the<lb/> property which thus, was his separate property. Bal Krishna also<lb/> received his separate share. Consequently, Devi Prasad was free to<lb/> decide how his share would be given away after his passing viz. by<lb/> the testamentary disposition, on the conditions therein being<lb/> fulfilled. The reasoning that the share of Devi Prasad would devolve<lb/> on his undivided son Bal Krishna despite him having received his<lb/> share, is an erroneous interpretation of the concerned Law. Merely<lb/> because Bal Krishna continued to live in the main house with the<lb/> father did not vest this circumstance with the legal connotation that<lb/> he was joint with the father, as Exhibit &quot;A,&quot; with clarity states that<lb/> all the sons were given properties and they had separated and the<lb/> father had kept &quot;jiwni&quot; land for himself. I am inclined to agree with<lb/> the arguments canvassed by learned Senior Counsel for the<lb/> Plaintiffs in this context wherein it was stated that the observation<lb/> of the learned trial Court regarding Hindu Law by Raghavachariar is<lb/> totally misconceived and out of context.<lb/></p>

			<p>55.<lb/> The learned trial Court, also discussed the provisions of<lb/> the Sikkim Succession Act, 2008, and held that the Act is applicable<lb/> to all Sikkimese who possess Sikkim Subject Certificate and die<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> intestate. He further opined that although the Defendant No.1 had<lb/> denied that she and the Plaintiffs were governed by the Mitakshara<lb/> School of Hindu Law, in fact, till 2008 the Hindus in Sikkim were<lb/> solely governed by the said Law.<lb/></p>

			<p>56.<lb/> The above statement leads to the conclusion that the<lb/> learned trial Court was of the opinion that in fact the Mitakshara<lb/> School of Hindu Law governed the Hindus in the State till 2008. The<lb/> Sikkim Succession Act, 2008, as already discussed, never saw the<lb/> light of day. Hence, the reliance of the learned trial Court on a non<lb/> est Statute is erroneous.<lb/></p>

			<p>57.<lb/> While deciding Issues No.4, 5, 6 and 10, the learned<lb/> trial Court, in Paragraph &quot;45&quot; of the impugned Judgment, observed<lb/> inter alia as under;<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;45. ……Strictly speaking, the Defendants No.1 &amp;<lb/> 4 cannot therefore claim any share on the basis of the<lb/> concerned &quot;banda patra&quot; and the question of their<lb/> having gotten any share vide the said &quot;banda patra&quot;<lb/> also does not arise. However, it may be mentioned<lb/> here that while Late Devi Prasad Dahal had died<lb/> during September 2001 Late Bal Krishna Dahal died in<lb/> the year 2010. On the death of Late Devi Prasad<lb/> Dahal, as discussed above, it was Late Bal Krishna<lb/> Dahal who was entitled to get, and did acquire, his<lb/> father&quot;s &quot;jiwni land&quot; and therefore he is to be regarded<lb/> as being the owner of the &quot;jiwni land&quot; till he expired in<lb/> the year 2010. When he died intestate in the year<lb/> 2010, which is seen to be the case here, the Sikkim<lb/> Succession Act, 2008, which as discussed earlier is<lb/> applicable to persons possessing Sikkim Subject<lb/> Certificate/Certificate of Identification(COI) and those<lb/> who are descendants of Sikkim Subject Certificate<lb/> holder identified through COI, had already come into<lb/> force in the State of Sikkim and was/is applicable<lb/> throughout the State(in cases where a person dies<lb/> intestate after its enactment). ……&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>The learned trial Court, invoking the provisions of Section 5 of the<lb/> Sikkim Succession Act, 2008, and Note II appended to Section 2<lb/> and the provisions of Section 6 of the said Act, concluded that the<lb/> Defendant No.1 and Defendant No.4 would be eligible to inherit the<lb/> properties left behind by Bal Krishha, including the &quot;jiwni&quot; land.<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/></p>

			<p>58.<lb/> In the first instance, I have to disagree with the finding<lb/> of the learned trial Court vide which he has divided the entire<lb/> property of Bal Krishna including the &quot;jiwni&quot; land between<lb/> Defendant No.1 and Defendant No.4, for the reason that the Issues<lb/> under discussion do not deal with the separate property of Bal<lb/> Krishna. The passing away of Bal Krishna if intestate, entitles the<lb/> Defendant No.1 to a share in his properties in view of the provisions<lb/> of the Hindu Succession Act, 1956, however, this is not the Issue in<lb/> the instant matter and discussions thereof stand truncated here.<lb/> Issues No.4 and 5 revolve around the &quot;jiwni&quot; land and Issue No.6 is<lb/> not even relevant for the disposal of the present Suit as the claim of<lb/> the Plaintiffs is confined to the &quot;jiwni&quot; land in terms of Exhibit &quot;A&quot;.<lb/> There is no ambiguity in the conditions laid down by Devi Prasad in<lb/> Exhibit &quot;A&quot;, the intention has to be collected from the language of<lb/> the document as observed in C.N. Arunachala Mudaliar supra.<lb/></p>

			<p>59.<lb/> With regard to Issues No.8 and 9, the Plaintiffs could<lb/> not have raised the Issues before the learned trial Court and ought<lb/> to have approached the correct Forum if they were of the opinion<lb/> that the Certificate of Guardianship had been obtained fraudulently.<lb/> Consequently, I am in agreement with the findings of the learned<lb/> trial Court on these Issues.<lb/></p>

			<p>60.<lb/> While disagreeing with the view of the learned trial<lb/> Court on Issues No.1, 3 and 11, it is clear from the evidence before<lb/> the Court that the Plaintiffs, having fulfilled both requisite conditions<lb/> of Exhibit &quot;A,&quot; are entitled along with Defendant No.4, the daughter<lb/> of their half brother Bal Krishna, to a share each of the &quot;jiwni&quot; land.<lb/></p>

			<p>61.<lb/> Now addressing question No.3 framed hereinabove, the<lb/> Defendant No.1 has staked a claim to fifty per cent of the properties<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> recorded in the name of her late husband by virtue of being his<lb/> second wife and having cared for him, during his lifetime. Devi<lb/> Prasad did not make any provision for the Defendant No.1 in his<lb/> separate property i.e. the &quot;jiwni&quot; land by arranging for a life estate<lb/> for her. He did not die intestate. Had Devi Prasad died intestate,<lb/> then in terms of Section 8 of the Hindu Succession Act, 1956, a<lb/> share of her husband&quot;s property would have devolved upon her, she<lb/> being a Class I heir as per the Schedule to Section 8 of the Act.<lb/></p>

			<p>62.<lb/> In Sadhu Singh (supra) relied on by the Defendant No.1,<lb/> the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court dealt with the provisions of Section 8,<lb/> Section 14(1) and Section 30 of the Hindu Succession Act, 1956.<lb/> One Ralla Singh had a wife Isher Kaur. They had no children. Ralla<lb/> Singh executed a Will on 07.10.1968 and died on 19.03.1977. His<lb/> widow Isher Kaur on 21.01.1980, purported to gift the property in<lb/> favour of a Gurdwara. The Appellant (Sadhu Singh) filed a Suit<lb/> challenging the Deed of Gift and also prayed for recovery of<lb/> possession after the death of Isher Kaur. According to the Appellant,<lb/> under the Will of Ralla Singh, Isher Kaur took only a life estate and<lb/> the properties were to vest in the Appellant and his brother. She<lb/> had no right to gift the property to the Gurdwara under the terms of<lb/> the Will under which she took the properties. She was bound by the<lb/> terms of the bequest. Isher Kaur and the Gurdwara contended that<lb/> the property received by her on the death of her husband was as his<lb/> heir and it was taken by her absolutely and she was competent to<lb/> deal with the property. It was pleaded that in any event Section<lb/> 14(1) of the Hindu Succession Act entitled her to deal with the<lb/> property as an absolute owner. The Appellant countered that Isher<lb/> Kaur, having taken the property under the disposition of her<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> husband, was bound by its terms and she had only a life estate and<lb/> no competence to donate the property. It was a case to which<lb/> Section 14(2) of the Hindu Succession Act applied and the limitation<lb/> on right imposed by the Will was binding on Isher Kaur. Her estate<lb/> could not get enlarged under Section 14(1) of the Act. The trial<lb/> Court held that the Will executed by the Appellant was not genuine<lb/> and dismissed the Suit holding that Isher Kaur had taken the<lb/> property absolutely on the death of her husband as an heir and<lb/> under the circumstances she was entitled to donate the property to<lb/> the Gurdwara. The lower Appellate Court, on Appeal by the<lb/> Appellant, held that the Will propounded by the Appellant was found<lb/> to be the last Will and Testament of Ralla Singh and was a valid<lb/> execution and upheld it. Thus, the trial Court decree was reversed<lb/> and the Suit decreed. The Gurdwara was in Second Appeal before<lb/> the High Court which reversed the decision of the first Appellate<lb/> Court. The Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court while citing various other<lb/> decisions in the matter, set aside the Judgment and Decree of the<lb/> High Court and passed a Decree in favour of the original Plaintiff for<lb/> recovery of possession of the property from the Gurdwara, the<lb/> donee from Isher Kaur, and anyone claiming under or through it, on<lb/> the strength of his title and to hold it for himself and his brother.<lb/> The Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court while considering the ratio of the<lb/> Second Appeal, held as follows;<lb/> &quot;3. ……What it has presumably held is that Isher<lb/> Kaur had pre-existing right in the property and<lb/> consequently the limitation placed on her rights in the<lb/> will, could not prevail in view of Section 14(1) of the<lb/> Hindu Succession Act. It did not bear in mind that the<lb/> property was the separate property or self-acquired<lb/> property of Ralla Singh and his widow, though she<lb/> might have succeeded to the property as an absolute<lb/> and sole heir if Ralla Singh had died intestate on 19-<lb/>3-1977, had no pre-existing right as such. The widow<lb/> had, at best, only a right to maintenance and at best<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> could have secured a charge by the process of court<lb/> for her maintenance under the Hindu Adoptions and<lb/> Maintenance Act in the separate property of her<lb/> husband. May be, in terms of Section 39 of the<lb/> Transfer of Property Act, she could have also<lb/> enforced the charge even as against an alienee from<lb/> her husband. Unlike in a case where the widow was<lb/> in possession of the property on the date of the<lb/> coming into force of the Act in which she had a pre-<lb/>existing right at least to maintenance, a situation<lb/> covered by Section 14(1) of the Hindu Succession<lb/> Act, if his separate property is disposed of by a Hindu<lb/> male by way of testamentary disposition, placing a<lb/> restriction on the right given to the widow, the<lb/> question whether Section 14(2) would not be<lb/> attracted, was not considered at all by the High<lb/> Court.<lb/></p>

			<p>It proceeded as if the ratio of V.<lb/> Tulasamma [(1977) 3 SCC 99 : (1977) 3 SCR 261]<lb/> would preclude any enquiry in that line.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>(Emphasis supplied)<lb/></p>

			<p>The Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court, while referring to the ratio of V.<lb/> Tulassama and Others v. Sesha Reddy (Dead) by L.Rs. 22 concluded that<lb/> on the wording of Section 14(1) of the Hindu Succession Act and the<lb/> context of the decision, the ratio would apply only when a female<lb/> Hindu is possessed of the property on the date of the Act under<lb/> semblance of a right, whether it be a limited or a preexisting right<lb/> to maintenance in lieu of which she was put in possession of the<lb/> property. The Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court also held therein;<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;13. An owner of property has normally the right<lb/> to deal with that property including the right to devise<lb/> or bequeath the property. He could thus dispose it of<lb/> by a testament. Section 30 of the Act, not only does<lb/> not curtail or affect this right, it actually reaffirms that<lb/> right. Thus, a Hindu male could testamentarily<lb/> dispose of his property. When he does that, a<lb/> succession under the Act stands excluded and the<lb/> property passes to the testamentary heirs. Hence,<lb/> when a male Hindu executes a will bequeathing the<lb/> properties, the legatees take it subject to the terms of<lb/> the will unless of course, any stipulation therein is<lb/> found invalid. Therefore, there is nothing in the Act<lb/> which affects the right of a male Hindu to dispose of<lb/> his property by providing only a life estate or limited<lb/> estate for his widow. The Act does not stand in the<lb/> way of his separate properties being dealt with by him<lb/> as he deems fit. His will hence could not be<lb/> challenged as being hit by the Act.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>(Emphasis supplied)<lb/></p>

			<p>22 (1977) 3 SCC 99<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> The Court went on to refer to the decision in Ramachandra Shenoy<lb/> and Another v. Mrs. Hilda Brite and Others 23 . The ratio therein<lb/> observed;<lb/> &quot;14. ……It is one of the cardinal principles of<lb/> construction of wills that to the extent that it is legally<lb/> possible effect should be given to every disposition<lb/> contained in the will unless the law prevents effect<lb/> being given to it. ……&quot;<lb/> That, the Court has to attempt a harmonious construction to give<lb/> effect to all terms of the Will if it is in any manner possible.<lb/></p>

			<p>63.<lb/> This sets to rest the rights of Defendant No.1 with<lb/> regard to the land that she is in occupation of being the &quot;jiwni&quot; land.<lb/> Defendant No.1 was not possessed of the property under the<lb/> semblance of a right, whether limited or for the purposes of<lb/> maintenance. Suffice it to state here that the &quot;jiwni&quot; land is to<lb/> descend in terms of the testamentary disposition of Exhibit &quot;A&quot; and<lb/> the Defendant No.1, as also all other parties to the Suit, are bound<lb/> by the terms of the bequest.<lb/></p>

			<p>64.<lb/> While considering the decisions of the Hon&quot;ble Supreme<lb/> Court and various High Courts relied on by the Defendant No.1, it is<lb/> worth mentioning here that the ratio in Karedla Parthasaradhi (supra)<lb/> is not relevant for the present purposes as it deals with a Hindu<lb/> male having died intestate and the Defendant therein asserting that<lb/> she was his legally married wife and thereby entitled to his house<lb/> after his death being the Class I heir of her husband. While<lb/> considering the reliance made on Ganduri Koteshwaramma and<lb/> Another v. Chakiri Yanadi and Another 24 and Vineeta Sharma (supra), it<lb/> is worth noticing that the Defendant No.1, after averring rather<lb/> vaguely that she was governed by the Law of the land, has taken a<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> U-turn and placed reliance on the ratio (supra) which are centred<lb/> around the Hindu Succession Act, 1956, and contrary to the stance<lb/> taken by her. No reasons have been extended for such reliance<lb/> which thereby requires no consideration.<lb/></p>

			<p>65.<lb/> Next, it may be clarified here that in a civil dispute the<lb/> standard of proof extends to a &quot;preponderance of probability&quot; and<lb/> not &quot;beyond a reasonable doubt,&quot; as canvassed by learned Counsel<lb/> for the Defendant No.1. The latter is the standard required for proof<lb/> in a criminal case against an accused. The argument of learned<lb/> Counsel for the Defendant No.1 contending that the Plaintiffs have<lb/> to prove their case beyond a reasonable doubt is therefore rejected.<lb/> Anar Devi and Others (supra) relied on by the Defendant No.1 being a<lb/> Suit for partition of notional share of the deceased father in a<lb/> coparcenary property, is not relevant to the issue at hand. The<lb/> argument of learned Counsel for the Defendant No.1 that the Suit is<lb/> only for declaration cannot be countenanced as the prayers in the<lb/> Plaint reveal otherwise.<lb/></p>

			<p>66.<lb/> In light of the foregoing discussions and the reasons set<lb/> forth by me, I cannot bring myself to agree with the observations<lb/> and findings of the learned trial Court on the Issues settled by it for<lb/> determination, save in Issues No.8 and 9, as already discussed.<lb/></p>

			<p>67.<lb/> In conclusion, it follows that;<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> In the absence of any statutory provision dealing with<lb/> Succession in the State and as the Hindu Succession Act, 1956, has<lb/> not been extended and enforced in the State but considering that<lb/> the Courts in Sikkim have applied the provisions of the Laws of the<lb/> country where the Laws in Sikkim are inadequate or do not cover a<lb/> specific area, it stands to reason that the provisions of the Hindu<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> Succession Act, 1956, can be invoked and applied for the purposes<lb/> of determining matters relating to Succession in Sikkim, involving<lb/> parties to whom the personal Law is applicable, till specific Laws<lb/> occupy the field.<lb/></p>

			<item>(ii)<lb/> The Sikkim Succession Act, 2008, is not a notified Act<lb/> and being non est no reliance can be placed on it.<lb/></item>

			<p>(iii)<lb/> The Plaintiffs and late Bal Krishna are entitled to an<lb/> equal share each of the &quot;jiwni&quot; land of late Devi Prasad as described<lb/> in the Schedule to the Plaint and are also entitled to take steps with<lb/> regard to their respective shares. Defendant No.4 being the<lb/> daughter of Bal Krishna would be entitled to his share of the &quot;jiwni&quot;<lb/> property.<lb/></p>

			<p>(iv)<lb/> The question of Defendant No.1 being entitled to the<lb/> &quot;jiwni&quot; property does not arise at all sans any such intention of Devi<lb/> Prasad in Exhibit &quot;A&quot; and the provisions of Law.<lb/></p>

			<p>68.<lb/> The contention of the Defendant No.1 that the Suit is<lb/> barred by limitation is not tenable as it is clear that the cause of<lb/> action arose only after the issuance of the impugned Order by the<lb/> Defendant No.2, dated 03.11.2010.<lb/></p>

			<p>69.<lb/> The prayer of the Plaintiffs seeking a declaration that<lb/> Bal Krishna predeceased his father has no legs to stand as the<lb/> evidence on record establishes that Devi Prasad passed away in<lb/> &quot;2001&quot; and Bal Krishna was witnessed performing his father&quot;s death<lb/> rites. Evidence also reveals that Bal Krishna died in &quot;2010,&quot; no<lb/> evidence to the contrary was furnished by the Plaintiffs.<lb/></p>

			<p>70.<lb/> Similarly, as no evidence was led on the averment of<lb/> the Plaintiffs that the Defendant No.1 had claimed before the<lb/> Defendant No.2 that Bal Krishna had left behind two sons and the<lb/> Nil Kumar Dahal and Another vs. Indira Dahal and Others<lb/> existence of a daughter was never pleaded, it requires no further<lb/> discussion. Besides, by filing the Amended Plaint and impleading the<lb/> Defendant No.4 as a party, they have recognized the daughter of<lb/> Bal Krishna as his legal heir.<lb/></p>

			<p>71.<lb/> The prayer that the Defendant No.4 not being a son of<lb/> Devi Prasad, had no right, title and interest over the &quot;jiwni&quot; land, is<lb/> correct to that extent as it does not fulfill the specific conditions set<lb/> out in Exhibit &quot;A,&quot; however she is the legal heir and successor of Bal<lb/> Krishna and thereby entitled to his share.<lb/></p>

			<p>72.<lb/> The prayer seeking a declaration that the Defendant<lb/> No.1 is a Nepal citizen and that the Guardianship Certificate of Devi<lb/> Kala Sharma was obtained fraudulently, deserves no consideration.<lb/> If the Plaintiffs are aggrieved by such a circumstance, they are to<lb/> approach the correct Forum.<lb/></p>

			<p>73.<lb/> The impugned Order of the Defendant No.2, dated<lb/> 03.11.2010, is hereby declared as null, void and non est and is<lb/> quashed and set aside, having been issued without jurisdiction.<lb/></p>

			<p>74.<lb/> Appeal allowed to the extent above and disposed of<lb/> accordingly. Pending applications, if any, also stand disposed of.<lb/></p>

			<p>75.<lb/> No order as to costs.<lb/></p>

			<p>76.<lb/> Copy of this Judgment be sent to the learned trial Court<lb/> for information.<lb/></p>

			<p>77.<lb/> Records of the learned trial Court be remitted forthwith.<lb/></p>

			<p>( Meenakshi Madan Rai )<lb/> Judge<lb/> 12.11.2020<lb/> ml<lb/> Approved for reporting : Yes</p>


	</text>
</tei>
