<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>H <lb/>i g h <lb/>C <lb/>o u r t o f H <lb/>. P . <lb/>IN THE HIGH COURT OF HIMACHAL PRADESH AT SHIMLA <lb/>ON THE 15 TH DAY OF SEPTEMBER 2021 <lb/>BEFORE <lb/>HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE TARLOK SINGH CHAUHAN <lb/>&amp; <lb/>HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE SATYEN VAIDYA <lb/>EXECUTION PETITION NO.304 OF 2021 <lb/>Between:-<lb/>OM PRAKASH, <lb/>SON OF SHRI DEVI CHAND (RTD H.M.) <lb/>RESIDENT OF VILL. SAMBLI, P.O. PURANI <lb/>MANDI TEHSIL SADAR, DISTRICT MANDI, <lb/>H.P. <lb/>…...PETITIONER <lb/>(BY SH. H.S. RANGRA, ADVOCATE) <lb/>AND <lb/>1. HIMACHAL ROAD TRANSPORT CORPORATION <lb/>THROUGH ITS MANAGING DIRECTOR, SHIMLA <lb/>2 REGIONAL MANAGER, HIMACHAL ROAD <lb/>TRANSPORT CORPORATION MANDI, <lb/>DISTT. MANDI H.P. <lb/>3. THE FINANCIAL ADVISOR CUM CAO, HRTC <lb/>HED OFFICE SHIMLA-3 H.P. <lb/>…..RESPONDENTS <lb/>(BY SH.VIKAS RAJPUT ADVOCATE) <lb/></front>

			<body>This <lb/>petition <lb/>coming <lb/>on <lb/>for <lb/>orders <lb/>this <lb/>day, <lb/>Hon&apos;ble Mr. Justice Tarlok Singh Chauhan, passed the following: <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 12:59:42 :::CIS <lb/></note>

			<front>H <lb/>i g h <lb/>C <lb/>o u r t o f H <lb/>. P . <lb/></front>

			<page>-2 -<lb/></page>

			<body>ORDER <lb/>Notice. Mr. Vikas Rajput, Advocate, appears and <lb/>waives service of notice on behalf of the respondents. <lb/>The execution petition is disposed of with a <lb/>direction to the respondents to comply with the judgment <lb/>passed by this Court in CWP NO.2205 of 2020, titled as <lb/>Om Parkash Versus Himachal Road Transport <lb/>Corporation and others, decided on 23.07.2020 and <lb/>file compliance affidavit within six weeks from today. <lb/>Pending miscellaneous application(s), if any, shall also <lb/>stand disposed of. <lb/>2. <lb/>List for compliance come up on 27.10.2021. <lb/>(Tarlok Singh Chauhan) <lb/>Judge <lb/>(Satyen Vaidya) <lb/>Judge <lb/>September 15, 2021 <lb/>(tarun) <lb/>::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 12:59:42 :::CIS </body>


	</text>
</tei>
