<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>H <lb/>i g h <lb/>C <lb/>o u r t o f H <lb/>. P . <lb/>IN THE HIGH COURT OF HIMACHAL PRADESH AT SHIMLA <lb/>ON THE 29 th DAY OF DECEMBER, 2021 <lb/>BEFORE <lb/>HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE MOHAMMAD RAFIQ, <lb/>CHIEF JUSTICE <lb/>&amp; <lb/>HON&apos;BLE MS. JUSTICE JYOTSNA REWAL DUA <lb/>CIVIL WRIT PETITION (ORIGINAL APPLICATION) <lb/>No.6830 of 2020 <lb/>Between:-<lb/>1. PREM LAL <lb/>S/O SHRI SURAT RAM SHARMA, <lb/>R/O VILLAGE BAG, POST OFFICE PAHAL, <lb/>DISTRICT SHIMLA, H.P. <lb/>PRESENTLY WORKING AS <lb/>LECTURER (POLITICAL SCIENCE) IN <lb/>GSSS SHOGI, SHIMLA, <lb/>DISTRICT SHIMLA, H.P. <lb/>2. NARESH KUMAR <lb/>S/O PANNA LAL, <lb/>R/O VILLAGE JAG JARELI JAGTARLI, <lb/>TEHSIL ROHROO, DISTRICT SHIMLA, <lb/>PRESENTLY WORKING AS <lb/>LECTURER (COMMERCE), <lb/>GSSS BIACHRI, DISTRICT SHIMLA, H.P. <lb/>…...PETITIONERS <lb/>(BY MR. KARAN SINGH PARMAR, ADVOCATE) <lb/>AND <lb/>1. STATE OF HIMACHAL PRADESH <lb/>THROUGH SECRETARY (EDUCATION) <lb/>TO THE GOVERNMENT OF HIMACHAL <lb/>PRADESH, SHIMLA-2 <lb/>2. DIRECTOR HIGHER EDUCATION, <lb/>HIMACHAL PRADESH, SHIMLA <lb/>…...RESPONDENTS <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:06 :::CIS <lb/></note>

			<front>H <lb/>i g h <lb/>C <lb/>o u r t o f H <lb/>. P . <lb/></front>

			<page>-2 -<lb/></page>

			<front>(BY MR. ASHOK SHARMA, ADVOCATE GENERAL <lb/>WITH MR. NAND LAL THAKUR, ADDITIONAL <lb/>ADVOCATE GENERAL) <lb/></front>

			<body>This petition coming on for admission this day, <lb/>Hon&apos;ble Ms. Justice Jyotsna Rewal Dua, passed the following: <lb/>O R D E R <lb/>The petitioners seek regularization on completion of <lb/>eight years of service. <lb/>2. <lb/>Facts:-<lb/>2(i). <lb/>The case of the petitioners is that they were engaged <lb/>as Lecturers on contract basis in the respondent-Education <lb/>Department in the year 1998. Their services were terminated w.e.f. <lb/>11.05.2000 and 19.05.2000, respectively, on joining of regular <lb/>incumbents. Petitioners were re-engaged in the year 2001 after the <lb/>decision in CWP No.415 of 2000, titled Baldev Singh &amp; others <lb/>Versus State of H.P. &amp; others. <lb/>2(ii). <lb/>Subsequently, in view of the orders passed by this <lb/>Court, the respondents regularized the services of the petitioners by <lb/>taking the dates of their initial engagement as starting point of their <lb/>service. The regularization order was issued by the respondents in <lb/>favour of the petitioners in July, 2018. <lb/>2(iii). <lb/>The grievance of the petitioners in the instant petition is <lb/>that their services have been regularized on completion of 10 years <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:06 :::CIS <lb/></note>

			<front>H <lb/>i g h <lb/>C <lb/>o u r t o f H <lb/>. P . <lb/></front>

			<page>-3 -<lb/></page>

			<body>of service, whereas, they were required to be regularized on <lb/>completion of eight years of service at par with similarly situated <lb/>persons. The substantive prayer made in the petition is as under:-<lb/>&quot;(i) <lb/>That regularization order of the applicant issued in July, 2018 <lb/>(Annexure A-2) may kindly be quashed and set aside to the <lb/>extent it regularize the services of the applicants on <lb/>completion of ten years of service with further direction to <lb/>respondents to regularize the services of the applicants on <lb/>completion of eight years of service i.e. with effect from <lb/>1.1.2006/1.1.2007 which may deem fit by this Hon&apos;ble Court.&quot; <lb/>3. <lb/>During hearing of the case, learned counsel for the <lb/>petitioners placed on record a judgment dated 10.04.2013, rendered <lb/>in CWP No.1853 of 2009, titled Arpana Bali Versus The State of <lb/>Himachal Pradesh &amp; Others. In the said case, the respondents-<lb/>State had declined to regularize petitioner&apos;s (therein) services on the <lb/>ground that there was break in her service w.e.f. 22.03.1999 till <lb/>19.05.1999. The State had asserted that the petitioner therein was <lb/>re-engaged on 20.05.1999, therefore, she had not completed eight <lb/>years of continuous service on 10.11.2006. This was the reason <lb/>given by the respondents-State for not regularizing the services of <lb/>said Arpana Bali. The petitioner therein had claimed that break in <lb/>her service w.e.f. 22.03.1999 to 19.05.1999 was on account of act, <lb/>conduct and deeds attributable to the respondents and not on <lb/>account of any fault on her part. The Court held that the period from <lb/>22.03.1999 to 19.05.1999 cannot be treated as break in service of <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:06 :::CIS <lb/></note>

			<front>H <lb/>i g h <lb/>C <lb/>o u r t o f H <lb/>. P . <lb/></front>

			<page>-4 -<lb/></page>

			<body>the petitioner-Arpana Bali. That she had completed eight years of <lb/>continuous service as on 10.11.2006. The Court held the petitioner <lb/>therein entitled to regularization of her services on completion of <lb/>eight years of service, i.e. with effect from 10.11.2006. Relevant <lb/>paras from the judgment read as under:-<lb/>&quot;15. True it is that as per the policy dated 9.6.2005, Annexure-I, the <lb/>services of those contractual appointees like the petitioner, <lb/>who had completed eight years of service on 31.12.2004 and <lb/>those likely to complete eight years of service as on <lb/>31.12.2005 had to be regularized w.e.f. 1.1.2005 and 1.1.2006 <lb/>respectively. The petitioner admittedly had completed eight <lb/>years of service after 31.12.2005 i.e. 10.11.2006. This Court, <lb/>however, is not in agreement with the submissions that the <lb/>case of the petitioner being not covered under this policy and <lb/>that only those contractual appointees having completed eight <lb/>years of service as on 31.12.2004 or 31.12.2005 have been <lb/>regularized for the reason that as per the own stand of the <lb/>respondent-department in the reply to the writ petition, the <lb/>services of those incumbents, who had completed eight years <lb/>of continuous service as on 10.11.2006 were regularized and <lb/>as the petitioner had also completed such services as on <lb/>10.11.2006, therefore, her services have also been regularized <lb/>w.e.f. 10.11.2006/31.12.2006. The non-regularization of her <lb/>services leads to the only conclusion that she has been denied <lb/>the benefit of regularization from 10.11.2006/31.12.2006 <lb/>illegally, arbitrarily and rather discriminating against similarly <lb/>situated persons on account of there being break in her <lb/>service which stand of the respondent department has not <lb/>been approved by this Court as per the findings recorded <lb/>hereinabove and rather has been held as illegal. It has further <lb/>been held that the period w.e.f. 22.3.1999 to 19.5.1999 cannot <lb/>be said to a break in her service and rather has to be counted <lb/>towards the continuity in service and seniority. The petitioner, <lb/>therefore, is entitled to regularization of her services on the <lb/>completion of eight years of service i.e. 10.11.2006. <lb/>16. This court is also not satisfied with the arguments that after <lb/>completion of eight years of service by the petitioner, she has <lb/>rightly been considered as per the policy dated 9th September, <lb/>2008, Annexure-II, for the reason that as per this policy, the <lb/>services of those incumbents, who had completed eight years <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:06 :::CIS <lb/></note>

			<front>H <lb/>i g h <lb/>C <lb/>o u r t o f H <lb/>. P . <lb/></front>

			<page>-5 -<lb/></page>

			<body>of continuous service as on 31.3.2008, were to be regularized. <lb/>The petitioner, however, had already completed eight years of <lb/>service as on 10.11.2006, therefore, was entitled to be <lb/>considered for regularization immediately thereafter having <lb/>acquired the requisite service well before 31.12.2008, and <lb/>during the currency of the policy dated 9.6.2005, Annexure-I <lb/>referred to hereinabove. <lb/>17. There is again no substance in the arguments addressed on <lb/>behalf of the respondent-State that there was no policy in <lb/>existence during the year 2006 or 2007 and that the petitioner <lb/>could have only been considered on coming into being the <lb/>new Policy viz the policy dated 9th September, 2008 for the <lb/>reason that in a bunch matter of daily wagers (CWP No.2735 <lb/>of 2010, titled Rakesh Kumar vs. State of H.P.&amp; Others and its <lb/>connected matters) decided by the Principal Bench of this <lb/>Court vide judgment dated 28.7.2010, while holding that the <lb/>Policy of 2000 was in existence till the new one was <lb/>introduced on 9th June, 2005, the daily wagers, who had <lb/>acquired the requisite number of working years in the <lb/>interregnum were also held liable to be brought on work <lb/>charge establishment as per the old policy framed in the year <lb/>2000. Therefore, applying these principles in the present case, <lb/>the services of the petitioner should have been regularized on <lb/>completion of the eight years of service. <lb/>18. The upshot of the above discussion would be that the <lb/>petitioner is entitled to be regularized as Lecturer Music <lb/>(Vocal) w.e.f. 1.1.2007 instead of 31.12.2008, however, only <lb/>on notional basis from the said date and entitled to the actual <lb/>financial benefits from the date she has joined as Lecturer <lb/>Music (Vocal) on regular basis pursuant to impugned order <lb/>Annexure P-13. The impugned order is hereby ordered to be <lb/>modified, accordingly.&quot; <lb/>Learned counsel for the petitioners also submitted that <lb/>original petitioner No.7, Sh. Mahender Kumar S/o Shri Pyare Lal, <lb/>was deleted from the array of parties in the instant case. Said <lb/>Sh. Mahender Kumar filed CWP No.3273 of 2019 seeking his <lb/>regularization on completion of eight years of services with effect <lb/>from the date of his first engagement in the year 1998. The said writ <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:06 :::CIS <lb/></note>

			<front>H <lb/>i g h <lb/>C <lb/>o u r t o f H <lb/>. P . <lb/></front>

			<page>-6 -<lb/></page>

			<body>petition was disposed of on 17.07.2020 in the following terms:-<lb/>&quot;Learned counsel for the petitioner states that the issue in <lb/>question is squarely covered by the judgment rendered in <lb/>CWP No. 1853 of 2009-D, titled as Arpana Bali vs. The State <lb/>of Himachal Pradesh and others, decided on 10 th April, 2013 <lb/>and the said judgment, in turn, stands implemented by the <lb/>respondents. This is a matter which is required to be <lb/>considered by the employer. <lb/>2. Accordingly, the present petition is disposed of with a direction <lb/>to respondent No. 2 to consider and decide the case of the <lb/>petitioner in light of the averments made in this petition and, <lb/>more particularly, the judgment rendered in Arpana Bali&apos;s case, <lb/>which stands implemented. Needful be done within four weeks <lb/>and in case the petitioner is similarly situated to Arpana Bali&apos;s <lb/>case, then consequential action be taken within two weeks.&quot; <lb/>Learned counsel further submitted that the judgment <lb/>dated 17.07.2020 has already been implemented by the <lb/>respondents. Order dated 22.01.2021 was passed in this regard, <lb/>regularizing the services of said Sh. Mahender Kumar w.e.f. <lb/>01.01.2007 on notional basis. Due and admissible monetary benefits <lb/>were restricted to him from the date he had actually joined the <lb/>duties. Office order dated 22.01.2021 has been placed on record by <lb/>the petitioners, relevant portion of which reads as under:-<lb/>&quot;Now therefore, facts and circumstances of the case Smt. <lb/>Arpana Bali was engaged in the year 1998 and petitioner <lb/>namely Sh. Mahender Kumar was also engaged in the year <lb/>1998 having completed 08 years services as on 31.12.2006. <lb/>Smt. Arpana Bali has been allowed regularization w.e.f. <lb/>01.01.2007 notionally. Hence the regularization is hereby <lb/>allowed to Sh. Mahender Kumar w.e.f. 01.01.2007 on notional <lb/>basis. However, the due and admissible monitory benefits be <lb/>restricted from the date he had joined duties pursuant office <lb/>order dated 27.07.2010. The Principal Govt. Sr. Sec. School <lb/>Behli is further directed that arrear be released as per Finance <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:06 :::CIS <lb/></note>

			<front>H <lb/>i g h <lb/>C <lb/>o u r t o f H <lb/>. P . <lb/></front>

			<page>-7 -<lb/></page>

			<body>Department instructions dated 07.01.2012 &amp; 15.12.2011 and <lb/>the entry in this regard may also be made in the service book <lb/>of the petitioner. May inform the parties accordingly.&quot; <lb/>The petitioners contend that they are similarly situated <lb/>as the said Sh. Mahender Kumar and are entitled for the same <lb/>benefits as have been released in favour of Sh. Mahender Kumar. <lb/>4. <lb/>In view of the above submissions and taking note of the <lb/>judgment passed in CWP No.1853 of 2009, titled Arpana Bali <lb/>Versus The State of Himachal Pradesh &amp; Others as well as the <lb/>judgment passed in CWP No.3273 of 2019, titled Mahender Kumar <lb/>Versus State of H.P. &amp; Ors., and the order dated 22.01.2021 passed <lb/>by the respondents, regularizing the services of said Sh. Mahender <lb/>Kumar on completion of eight years of services, we direct the <lb/>respondents to decide the cases of the petitioners for their <lb/>regularization on completion of eight years of continuous service by <lb/>passing speaking orders in accordance with law, within a period of <lb/>four weeks from today. <lb/>The petition stands disposed of in the above terms, so <lb/>also the pending miscellaneous application(s), if any. <lb/>( Mohammad Rafiq ) <lb/>Chief Justice <lb/>( Jyotsna Rewal Dua ) <lb/>December 29, 2021 <lb/>Judge <lb/>Mukesh <lb/>::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:06 :::CIS </body>


	</text>
</tei>
