<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<head>
			ORDER
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			Dated this the 28 th day of January, 2021
			<lb />
			Petitioner is the accused in Crime No.660 of
			<lb />
			2017 registered at the Varandarapilly Police
			<lb />
			Station for the offence punishable under Section
			<lb />
			27 of the NDPS Act, now pending as C.C.No.2388 of
			<lb />
			2017 on the file of the Judicial First Class
			<lb />
			Magistrate Court-I, Irinjalakuda.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			2. According
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			prosecution,
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			petitioner along with 4 others were found smoking
			<lb />
			ganja. Five partly burned beedies were seized
			<lb />
			from the spot.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			3. The petitioner is the Physical Education
			<lb />
			Teacher in an aided school and consequent to
			<lb />
			registration of the crime against him, has been
			<lb />
			placed under suspension. The petitioner therefore
			<lb />
			prays for expeditious disposal of the case.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			4. In the report called for by this Court,
			<lb />
			the learned Magistrate has stated that from
			<lb />
			18.12.2019 onwards, the case was repeatedly
			<lb />
			posted after recording plea of the accused, but
			<lb />
			in view of the lock down restrictions and the
			<lb />
			guidelines issued by the High Court, the case has
			<lb />
			to be adjourned on notification and the next
			<lb />
			posting is on 23.02.2021. That, on 18.12.2019,
			<lb />
			summons has been ordered to CW1. It is report
			<lb />
			that statements of only two witnesses have been
			<lb />
			produced with the final report filed. According
			<lb />
			to the learned Magistrate, two months time is
			<lb />
			required to dispose the case.
			<lb />
			In view of the report and the urgency
			<lb />
			expressed by the petitioner, the Crl.M.C is
			<lb />
			disposed of directing the Judicial First Class
			<lb />
			Magistrate
			<lb />
			Court-I,
			<lb />
			Irinjalakkuda,
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			take
			<lb />
			earnest efforts to dispose C.C.No.2388 of 2017
			<lb />
			within an outer limit of three months from the
			<lb />
			date of receipt of a copy of this order.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			Sd/-
			<lb />
			V.G.ARUN
			<lb />
			JUDGE
			<lb />
			Scl/28.01.2021
		</p>


	</text>
</tei>