<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF KERALA AT ERNAKULAM
			<lb />
			PRESENT
			<lb />
			THE HONOURABLE MR. JUSTICE SUNIL THOMAS
			<lb />
			THURSDAY, THE 07TH DAY OF JANUARY 2021 / 17TH POUSHA, 1942
			<lb />
			Crl.MC.No.2161 OF 2020(A)
			<lb />
			CRIME NO.3/2009 OF VACB, THIRUVANANTHAPURAM , Thiruvananthapuram
			<lb />
			PETITIONER/ACCUSED NO.7:
			<lb />
			A.DHARMAKEERTHI
			<lb />
			AGED 53 YEARS
			<lb />
			S/O. K.P.ARJUNAN,
			<lb />
			BHAVANA, NO.79,
			<lb />
			M.P.APPAN ROAD,
			<lb />
			VAZHUTHACAUD,
			<lb />
			TRIVANDRUM-695 014
			<lb />
			BY ADV. SHRI.SASTHAMANGALAM S. AJITHKUMAR
			<lb />
			RESPONDENT/COMPLAINANT:
			<lb />
			THE STATE OF KERALA
			<lb />
			REPRESENTED BY THE PUBLIC PROSECUTOR,
			<lb />
			HIGH COURT OF KERALA,
			<lb />
			ERNAKULAM-682 031
			<lb />
			OTHER PRESENT:
			<lb />
			SPL.GP SRI.A RAJESH
			<lb />
			THIS CRIMINAL MISC. CASE HAVING BEEN FINALLY HEARD ON 17-11-
			<lb />
			2020, THE COURT ON 07-01-2021 PASSED THE FOLLOWING:
			<lb />
			Crl.M.C.2161/2020
			<lb />
			2
			<lb />
		</front>

		<body>
			ORDER
			<lb />
			Petitioner herein is the 7 th accused in C.C.No.3 of 2020 arising
			<lb />
			from Crime No.3/2009/SIU-1 of VACB, SIU-I, Thiruvananthapuram for
			<lb />
			offences punishable under section 13(1)(d) r/w 13(2) and section 120B of
			<lb />
			the PC Act, 1988.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			The crux of the prosecution allegation is that, 6 th accused is
			<lb />
			the owner of an old building, T.C.No.28/1830 in survey No.709 of
			<lb />
			Vanchiyoor Village in Thiruvananthapuram district. He proposed to
			<lb />
			renovate the above building. 7 th accused, who is a registered architect,
			<lb />
			was entrusted with the duty of preparing the plan and for obtaining
			<lb />
			license from the authorities. Accordingly, the architect prepared a plan
			<lb />
			for internal renovation of the existing building. The plan was submitted
			<lb />
			for approval by 6 th accused. By order in No.TP7/BA/662/06, plan was
			<lb />
			approved and license was granted for carrying out internal renovation.
			<lb />
			Prosecution alleged that, on the pretext of renovation, 6 th accused
			<lb />
			demolished the entire structure and constructed a new four storied
			<lb />
			building in its place.
			<lb />
			On getting information about the illegal
			<lb />
			construction, stop memo was issued by corporation. This resulted in
			<lb />
			other legal proceedings. Thereafter, 6 th accused submitted a revised plan
			<lb />
			and applied for regularization of the alleged deviation on the basis of the
			<lb />
			renovation application prepared by 7 th accused. Prosecution alleged that
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.M.C.2161/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			3
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			the real intention of the 6 th accused in obtaining a plan for internal
			<lb />
			renovation and getting permission for that, was for demolishing the entire
			<lb />
			building and to construct a new building in its place under that plan, fully
			<lb />
			knowing that, new construction was not permitted in that area. It was
			<lb />
			alleged that, it was done consequent to the conspiracy hatched by 6 th and
			<lb />
			7 th accused along with the first accused who was the Assistant Planning
			<lb />
			Officer of the Corporation, 2 nd accused Town Planning Officer, 3 rd accused
			<lb />
			Building Inspector, 4 th accused UD Clerk and 5 th accused Building
			<lb />
			Inspector of the Town Planning Section who were public servants. It was
			<lb />
			alleged that, the accused, during the period 15.03.2006 to 27.11.2006
			<lb />
			committed various irregularities pursuant to the conspiracy. Further
			<lb />
			allegation was that, accused Nos.1 to 5 had misused their official position
			<lb />
			as public servants to help the 6 th accused. It was further alleged that, on
			<lb />
			the application submitted for license, 7 th accused had undertaken that, he
			<lb />
			will construct the building as per the approved plan and if there was any
			<lb />
			violation, it would be brought to the notice of the authorities. The specific
			<lb />
			allegation against the 7 th accused was that the building was newly
			<lb />
			constructed under his supervision. Further, even though he knew that the
			<lb />
			new building was constructed in complete violation of the plan and
			<lb />
			license and that he was duty bound by the undertaking to inform the
			<lb />
			Corporation, he did not inform the Corporation about the above violation.
			<lb />
			Thereafter, he even submitted an application for regularization of the
			<lb />
			alleged deviation, fully knowing that it was not a renovation or a mere
			<lb />
		</body>
			<note place="headnote">
				Crl.M.C.2161/2020
				<lb />
			</note>
			<page>
				4
				<lb />
			</page>
			<body>
			deviation from the plan and license. On the basis of the complaint
			<lb />
			received, crime was registered and investigation was carried out.
			<lb />
			Annexure-A final report was submitted before the court below.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			Contending that, 7 th accused was innocent and that, he was
			<lb />
			only entrusted with the work of preparing a plan for internal renovation
			<lb />
			and that apart from obtaining the plan and license, he was not involved in
			<lb />
			the construction work, he has approached this Court. He was neither
			<lb />
			involved in the supervision of nor in the actual work of the construction of
			<lb />
			the building. Only after the completion of the construction, he got
			<lb />
			involved with the building. He being the architect, was duty bound to
			<lb />
			submit an application for regularization as instructed by the client, which
			<lb />
			he did for the 6 th accused. He did it only as a part of professional
			<lb />
			engagement. It was further contended that, even if he was aware of the
			<lb />
			violation and that, he was duty bound to inform the Corporation about the
			<lb />
			violation in the light of the undertaking given by him, the breach of it can
			<lb />
			at the most result in a civil liability or a violation of the Code of Conduct
			<lb />
			for the Architects but, not a criminal liability. It was contended that, he
			<lb />
			had neither conspired with the 6 th accused nor committed any act
			<lb />
			independently or in combination with the remaining accused.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Learned Special Government Pleader for Vigilance opposing
			<lb />
			the application contended that, plan submitted was prepared by the
			<lb />
			petitioner herein for internal renovation only. The area where the building
			<lb />
			was situated was a heritage zone, where new constructions were not
			<lb />
			</body>
			<note place="headnote">
				Crl.M.C.2161/2020
				<lb />
			</note>
			<page>
				5
				<lb />
			</page>
			<body>
			permitted. Fully knowing it, an application for internal renovation was
			<lb />
			submitted and under the guise of it, the building was demolished lock,
			<lb />
			stock and barrel and it was newly constructed. Thereafter, claiming that it
			<lb />
			was only a deviation from the plan, application for regularization was also
			<lb />
			submitted. Petitioner was aware of the nature of construction and he was
			<lb />
			duty bound to bring it to the notice of the Corporation. It was alleged
			<lb />
			that, he along with the 6 th accused clandestinely obtained the plan
			<lb />
			approved under the guise of renovation and made the new construction.
			<lb />
			The undertaking given by him in Annexure-B to reconstruct as per the
			<lb />
			plan under his supervision was violated and he had conspired with the
			<lb />
			remaining accused.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			In the final report, 7 persons including the petitioner were
			<lb />
			arrayed as the accused. There is no dispute that the plan was prepared
			<lb />
			by the petitioner herein. He had also undertaken on the plan that the
			<lb />
			renovation work would be carried on under his supervision and in case of
			<lb />
			breach, it will be informed to the authorities. Records available disclose
			<lb />
			that the application for renewal was submitted by 6 th accused, the owner
			<lb />
			through his employees. Approved plan also shows that, it was specifically
			<lb />
			for internal renovation only, keeping the main structure intact.
			<lb />
			Investigation revealed that a bar hotel was functioning in that building
			<lb />
			and license was granted for that old building, T.C.No.37/208 and 37/208/1
			<lb />
			under the name Vrindavan Tourist Home. Thereafter, a new building
			<lb />
			number 28/1830 was constructed and bar continued under the name
			<lb />
			
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.M.C.2161/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			6
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			and style Samrat Hotel. Excise records also show that the 6 th accused had
			<lb />
			submitted applications for changing the name and address of the hotel to
			<lb />
			Hotel Samrat.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			The limited question that now arises is whether any criminal
			<lb />
			liability can be fastened on the petitioner herein who was a professional
			<lb />
			architect and whether prosecution against him is legally sustainable. The
			<lb />
			twin contentions advanced by the Special government Pleader against the
			<lb />
			petitioner herein was that, firstly, he was involved in the conspiracy and
			<lb />
			secondly that even though he was duty bound to inform the authorities
			<lb />
			about the violation, he failed to do so and had played active role in the
			<lb />
			construction of the building. It was vehemently contended by the
			<lb />
			learned counsel for the petitioner that the records do not indicate that,
			<lb />
			either he had entered into a conspiracy with the second accused or that
			<lb />
			he was involved in the construction. It was also contended that, even if
			<lb />
			the petitioner had undertaken to reconstruct under his supervision and to
			<lb />
			ensure that the renovation would be done in accordance with the
			<lb />
			approved plan and license, breach of it by the owner or employees of the
			<lb />
			owner, will not cast any criminal liability on him and he cannot be held
			<lb />
			answerable for that. According to the learned counsel, at the most,
			<lb />
			breach of an undertaking by itself can only result in a civil liability and a
			<lb />
			proceeding, if any, for breach of the Rules of Conduct applicable to
			<lb />
			architects.
			<lb />
			
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.M.C.2161/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			7
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			7.
			<lb />
			The memorandum of witnesses submitted along with the final
			<lb />
			report shows that, CWs.1 and 2 are arrayed as witnesses to establish that,
			<lb />
			they had submitted complaints against the new construction, alleging
			<lb />
			violation of the rules. CWs. 3 to 10 were arrayed as witnesses to prove
			<lb />
			the submission of application to the Corporation seeking license and
			<lb />
			sanction and that, pursuant to complaints regarding violation, stop memo
			<lb />
			was issued by the Corporation. CWs3 to 10, 12, 13, 33 to 37, 39 to 43 and
			<lb />
			45 and 54 are the official witnesses of the Corporation and that of the
			<lb />
			Excise department, who were proposed to be examined to establish the
			<lb />
			alleged illegal construction and thereafter the application for
			<lb />
			regularization.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			Prosecution casts liability on the 7 th accused on the allegation
			<lb />
			that, he had undertaken to ensure renovation in accordance with plan.
			<lb />
			The specific allegation of the prosecution was that, even the plan for
			<lb />
			renovation was sanctioned by the 7 th accused pursuant to a conspiracy
			<lb />
			with the 6 th accused, to use the permit as a cover for construction of a
			<lb />
			new building in the guise of renovation.
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			The crucial question that arises is whether, materials are
			<lb />
			available to show that 7 th accused was privy to the construction, apart
			<lb />
			from his admitted duty of preparing the plan. CW11 was the employee of
			<lb />
			6 th accused. CWs.31 and 32 were the employees of 7 th accused. CW10
			<lb />
			was the Operations Manager of 6 th accused. Essentially, the prosecution
			<lb />
			allegation that the petitioner herein was directly involved in the
			<lb />
			
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.M.C.2161/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			8
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			construction of the building, has to be evaluated on the basis of the
			<lb />
			statement of above witnesses.
			<lb />
			10. CW10, the Operations Manager of 6 th accused had stated that,
			<lb />
			roof tiles were removed for renovation of the building in accordance with
			<lb />
			the plan and license. In the meanwhile, due to heavy rain, the building
			<lb />
			collapsed. Since it could not be renovated, it was newly constructed.
			<lb />
			11. CW32 was the Supervisor of 7 th accused. It was stated by him
			<lb />
			that, roof tiles of the building were removed and due to the heavy rain,
			<lb />
			the structure collapsed.
			<lb />
			The versions of CW10 and CW32 show that,
			<lb />
			initial work for renovation of the building were done and after the tiles
			<lb />
			were removed, due to heavy rain, the building collapsed. In the light of
			<lb />
			the above version of witnesses that old building collapsed due to rain, the
			<lb />
			allegation that the very purpose of obtaining permit for renovation was to
			<lb />
			newly construct the building under the guise of renovation pursuant to
			<lb />
			the conspiracy hatched between 6 th and 7 th accused along with the other
			<lb />
			officials cannot survive. The version of above witnesses indicate that roof
			<lb />
			tiles were removed for renovation and to the unexpected fall of building,
			<lb />
			the reconstruction had to be done only in such circumstances.
			<lb />
			These
			<lb />
			Rules point out the possibility of a conspiracy to get permission for
			<lb />
			renovation and under the guise of it, to construct a new building.
			<lb />
			12. It has to be considered that, even though the prosecution
			<lb />
			alleged that the petitioner herein conspired with other accused to obtain
			<lb />
			the plan and license under the guise of renovation and that, under his
			<lb />
			
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.M.C.2161/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			supervision, a new building was constructed, there is absolutely no
			<lb />
			evidence to prima facie show that the 7 th accused had conspired with the
			<lb />
			remaining accused. The prosecution has no specific allegation as to
			<lb />
			when, where and how 7 th accused conspired with the remaining accused
			<lb />
			and how they hatched the plan. As mentioned above, in the light of the
			<lb />
			materials indicating that the building collapsed due to natural
			<lb />
			consequences, the allegation of conspiracy, atleast involving 7 th accused,
			<lb />
			for obtaining the plan and the license under the guise of renovation for
			<lb />
			achieving the real object of new construction and thereafter, under its
			<lb />
			cover, it was renovated, cannot survive.
			<lb />
			13. The next allegation of the prosecution was that, even assuming
			<lb />
			that the accused was not directly involved in any conspiracy, he was
			<lb />
			aware that the building was not renovated but was newly constructed.
			<lb />
			He had an obligation to ensure that the building was renovated in
			<lb />
			accordance with the plan and license. By virtue of his undertaking given
			<lb />
			at the time of submission of plan and license, not only that he undertook
			<lb />
			to do that, but also to inform the Corporation authorities in case of
			<lb />
			breach, to enable them to stop the violation. It is pertinent to note that, in
			<lb />
			the course of reconstruction, Corporation authorities issued stop memo,
			<lb />
			which was duly accepted on behalf of 6 th accused. This is clear from the
			<lb />
			evidence of CW10.
			<lb />
			14. CW10 in his statement admitted that, he was not only the
			<lb />
			Operations Manager of 6 th accused, but his close relative also. According
			
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.M.C.2161/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			10
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			to him, plan was prepared by the 7 th accused. After it was prepared, the
			<lb />
			plan was submitted to the Corporation and was got approved by CW11
			<lb />
			who was the Bar Manager of 6 th accused. He also admitted that the
			<lb />
			building was newly constructed. Construction work was done by one
			<lb />
			Sreedharan Nair and his employees. According to CW10, he had not seen
			<lb />
			7 th accused or his employees supervising the work.
			<lb />
			15. CW44 who was the Senior Engineer of 7 th accused. According
			<lb />
			to him, the plan was prepared by 7 th accused. He asserted that, 7 th
			<lb />
			accused had not supervised the work in the disputed building. To his
			<lb />
			knowledge, the work was done under the supervision of CW11. It was also
			<lb />
			completed under the direct supervision of CW11. CW32 who was the
			<lb />
			Supervisor of 7 th accused admitted that, 7 th accused had initially asked
			<lb />
			him to supervise the work in the disputed building. He went to the spot
			<lb />
			and supervised the work of demolishing of the building for a period of 2½
			<lb />
			months. In the meanwhile, building collapsed. Instead of renovating it,
			<lb />
			new construction started under the supervision of CW11. This was
			<lb />
			promptly conveyed to 7 th accused who directed him not to get associated
			<lb />
			with construction work thereafter and to keep away from supervising the
			<lb />
			construction.
			<lb />
			16. CW11 who is the Bar Manager of 6 th accused admitted that, on
			<lb />
			receipt of plan from 7 th accused, he had taken it to the Corporation office,
			<lb />
			submitted it there and got the plan approved. Thereafter, the work
			<lb />
			started. However, he proceeded to add that the work was done under the
			<lb />
			
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.M.C.2161/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			11
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			supervision of 7 th accused.
			<lb />
			17. In the light of statement given by CW10, CW44 and CW32 who
			<lb />
			have unanimously stated that neither the petitioner herein nor his
			<lb />
			employees supervised the new construction of work, a stray sentence of
			<lb />
			CW11 when analyzed in the background of his own admission that he was
			<lb />
			directly involved in the entire work, has no significance at all.
			<lb />
			18. However, the available materials atleast indicate that,
			<lb />
			immediately after the building collapsed and the new construction
			<lb />
			started, petitioner herein was aware that, 6 th accused had deviated from
			<lb />
			the plan and was proceeding with renovation. In the absence of any
			<lb />
			materials to show that, petitioner was actively involved in the
			<lb />
			construction of new building or that, he had conspired with the other
			<lb />
			accused, the above knowledge is insufficient to cast criminal liability on
			<lb />
			him. The contention of the learned counsel for the petitioner was that,
			<lb />
			this by itself would not cast any criminal liability on the accused. There is
			<lb />
			no case that the petitioner misused his authority to make any wrongful
			<lb />
			gain. At the most, he can be found guilty of having violated the
			<lb />
			undertaking which may amount to professional misconduct. These are
			<lb />
			materials outside the scope of a criminal prosecution, it was submitted.
			<lb />
			19. To buttress the above contention, learned counsel for the
			<lb />
			petitioner relied on the decision of this Court in Thomas A.V. v. State of
			<lb />
			Kerala and Others (2013 KHC 672). That was a case wherein
			<lb />
			prosecution was initiated against the office bearers of Kerala Cricket
			<lb />
			
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.M.C.2161/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			12
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Association regarding the purchase of land for construction of a stadium.
			<lb />
			It was alleged that, suppressing the actual price and showing higher
			<lb />
			price, office bearers caused loss to the Association and thereby misused
			<lb />
			their official position. Petitioner herein, who was a lawyer was also the
			<lb />
			Legal Advisor of the Kerala Cricket Association. He was also arrayed as
			<lb />
			an accused on the ground that, he had given legal opinion on the
			<lb />
			genuineness of the title deed and that, he had participated in the stadium
			<lb />
			committee meeting as a special invitee.
			<lb />
			20. Challenging his prosecution, it was contended by the advocate
			<lb />
			that the legal opinion given by him was only professional advise and that
			<lb />
			by itself cannot cast criminal liability on him. This was accepted by the
			<lb />
			learned Single Judge of this Court holding that the entire prosecution
			<lb />
			case against that accused was based on the allegation that the petitioner
			<lb />
			was an office bearer of the Association. In fact, he was not the office
			<lb />
			bearer of the Cricket Association and hence, not a public servant. There
			<lb />
			was no case that the petitioner misused his capacity as a Legal Advisor
			<lb />
			with a motive to commit the offence alleged against him. It was also held
			<lb />
			by the learned Judge that, there was no specific pleading in the complaint
			<lb />
			or factual imputation in the FIR regarding the ingredients of offence.
			<lb />
			Hence, for giving legal advice alone, criminal liability cannot cast on the
			<lb />
			above Legal Advisor.
			<lb />
			21. Case of the petitioner herein is slightly different from the
			<lb />
			above case. In this case, petitioner had given an additional undertaking
			<lb />
			
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.M.C.2161/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			13
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			that, he will ensure that the building will be renovated in accordance with
			<lb />
			the plan and license. Definitely, he is under an obligation to comply with
			<lb />
			his undertaking. However, that by itself is not sufficient to cast any
			<lb />
			criminal liability on the accused except that, he has violated the
			<lb />
			undertaking. Breach of it may invite civil consequence and action, if any,
			<lb />
			under the Architects Act. That is a different issue. However, I am
			<lb />
			convinced that the undertaking by itself and the failure in not promptly
			<lb />
			informing the Corporation inspite of knowledge that the 7 th accused had
			<lb />
			deviated from the plan and license cannot be a ground for a criminal
			<lb />
			action.
			<lb />
			22. Having considered these facts, I am satisfied that a successful
			<lb />
			prosecution of the petitioner on the basis of the above materials is not
			<lb />
			possible. Necessarily, proceedings against the petitioner alone is liable to
			<lb />
			be quashed.
			<lb />
			In the result, Crl.M.C is allowed. All further proceedings in
			<lb />
			C.C.No.3 of 2020 arising from Crime No.3/2009/SIU-1 of VACB, SIU-I,
			<lb />
			Thiruvananthapuram against the petitioner will stand quashed.
			<lb />
			Sd/-
			<lb />
			SUNIL THOMAS
			<lb />
			Sbna
			<lb />
			JUDGE
			<lb />
			
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.M.C.2161/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<front>
			APPENDIX
			<lb />
			PETITIONER&apos;S EXHIBITS:
			<lb />
			ANNEXURE-A
			<lb />
			CERTIFIED COPY OF FINAL REPORT IN CC 3/20
			<lb />
			PENDING BEFORE THE SPL JUDGE VIGILANCE
			<lb />
			TRIVANDRUM
			<lb />
			ANNEXURE-B
			<lb />
			TRUE COPY OF THE APPROVED RENEWAL PLAN FOR
			<lb />
			INTERNAL CHANGE OF EXISTING BUILDING WITH
			<lb />
			THE STRUCTURAL STABILITY CERTIFICATE IN
			<lb />
			EXT. B2 FILE OF THE FINAL REPORT
			<lb />
			ANNEXURE-C
			<lb />
			TRUE
			<lb />
			COPY
			<lb />
			OF
			<lb />
			LETTER
			<lb />
			DT
			<lb />
			5.3.20
			<lb />
			TCPCTP/631/2020-E3
			<lb />
			OF
			<lb />
			THE
			<lb />
			CHIEF
			<lb />
			TOWN
			<lb />
			PLANNER, GOVT. OF KERALA STATING THAT FOR
			<lb />
			REMOVING INTERMEDIATE WOODEN FLOOR AND
			<lb />
			REPLACEMENT WITH FLOOR SLAB BUILDING PERMIT
			<lb />
			IS REQUIRED
			<lb />
			ANNEXURE-D
			<lb />
			TRUE COPY OF THE LICENSE CONDITION OF
			<lb />
			ARCHITECTS ACT, 1972 ISSUED BY THE COUNCIL
			<lb />
			OF
			<lb />
			ARCHITECTURE,
			<lb />
			NEW
			<lb />
			DELHI
			<lb />
			SPECIFYING
			<lb />
			ARCHITECTS
			<lb />
			PROFESSIONAL
			<lb />
			LIABILITY
			<lb />
			ND
			<lb />
			EXCEPTS
			<lb />
			ANNEXURE E
			<lb />
			TRUE COPY OF THE ORDER OF THIS HONOURABLE
			<lb />
			COURT DATED 18.01.2017 IN WPC NO.1832/17
			<lb />
			ANNEXURE-F
			<lb />
			TRUE COPY OF THE WPC NO.31115/18 PENDING
			<lb />
			BEFORE THIS HONOURABLE COURT
			<lb />
			ANNEXURE-G
			<lb />
			THE TRUE COPY OF THE STATEMENT FILED BY THE
			<lb />
			STATE GOVERNMENT IN WPC NO.31115/18 PENDING
			<lb />
			BEFORE THIS HONOURABLE COURT
		</front>


	</text>
</tei>