<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<head>
			O R D E R
			<lb />
			DATED THIS THE 28 th DAY OF JANUARY, 2021
			<lb />
			Shaffique, J:
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			These review petitions have been filed inter alia contending
			<lb />
			that there are errors apparent on the face of record. Three
			<lb />
			specific issues had been raised by the learned counsel for the
			<lb />
			review petitioners. One is that though the petition was barred by
			<lb />
			limitation, this court did not take into consideration the fact that
			<lb />
			earlier original applications have been filed and the same had
			<lb />
			been rejected by the Tribunal. Yet another contention urged is
			<lb />
			that there was no public interest in absorbing the Nurses to ESI
			<lb />
			Hospitals. Even assuming that the hospitals were taken over in
			<lb />
			public interest, absorption of staff are not strictly in public
			<lb />
			interest. It is also contended that the Regulations which govern
			<lb />
			the field is ESIC (Recruitment) Regulations, 2010.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			In fact all these issues had been considered elaborately
			<lb />
			in the order under review. As far as limitation is concerned, we
			<lb />
			have taken note of the earlier orders passed by the Tribunal and
			<lb />
			had arrived at a decision that there is no bar of limitation and
			<lb />
			therefore there is no error apparent on the face of record as far
			<lb />
			as the said issue is concerned.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			With reference to clause 3.4.3 which indicates in cases
			<lb />
			in which absorbees are not strictly in public interest, the
			<lb />
			transferred officers will be placed below all officers appointed
			<lb />
			regularly to ESIC, we have come to the conclusion that the
			<lb />
			absorption was in public interest. The contention that it was not
			<lb />
			strictly in public interest, cannot be sustained as the entire
			<lb />
			absorption of the employees as well as hospital was only in
			<lb />
			public interest. There cannot be a different view. Therefore we
			<lb />
			don&apos;t find any error being committed by us.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			As far as 2010 Regulations are concerned, it applies
			<lb />
			only to direct recruitees and not to absorbees as contemplated in
			<lb />
			the orders issued by the competent authorities. Under such
			<lb />
			circumstances, we don&apos;t find any error apparent on the face of
			<lb />
			record warranting interference while exercising review
			<lb />
			jurisdiction.
			<lb />
			Review petitions are therefore dismissed.
			<lb />
			(Sd/-)
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			A.M. SHAFFIQUE, JUDGE.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(Sd/-)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			GOPINATH P., JUDGE.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>AMG</item>


	</text>
</tei>