<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			1
			<lb />
			BEFORE THE MADURAI BENCH OF MADRAS HIGH COURT
			<lb />
			DATED : 05.04.2016
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			CORAM :
			<lb />
			THE HONOURABLE MR.JUSTICE S.MANIKUMAR
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			THE HONOURABLE MR.JUSTICE C.T.SELVAM
			<lb />
			Writ Petition(MD)No.5898 of 2016
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			W.M.P(MD)No.5231 of 2016
			<lb />
		</body>
		<front>
			s
			<lb />
			.... Petitioner
			<lb />
			vs.
			<lb />
			1)The District Collector,
			<lb />
			Virudhunagar,
			<lb />
			Virudhunagar District.
			<lb />
			2)The Superintendent of Police,
			<lb />
			Virudhunagar,
			<lb />
			Virudhunagar District.
			<lb />
			3)The Tahsildar,
			<lb />
			Rajapalayam Taluk,
			<lb />
			Virudhunagar District.
			<lb />
			.... Respondents
			<lb />
			Petition filed under Article 226 of the Constitution of India, for issuance of
			<lb />
			a Writ of Mandamus, forbearing the respondents from undertaking any
			<lb />
		</front>
		<page>
			2
			<lb />
		</page>
		<front>
			construction activity at Survey No.50/2, Chettiyarpatti Village, Thalavaipuram,
			<lb />
			which has been earmarked as Kalam Poromboke.
			<lb />
			For Petitioner
			<lb />
			: Mr.R.Anand for Mr.L.Bhagath Singh
			<lb />
			For Respondents
			<lb />
			: Mr.M.Alagadevan,
			<lb />
			Special Government Pleader
			<lb />
		</front>

		<body>
			ORDER
			<lb />
			(Order of the Court was made by Mr.Justice S.MANIKUMAR)
			<lb />
			Mr.Senthil Kumar, resident of Thalavaipuram, Rajapalayam Taluk,
			<lb />
			Virudhunagar District, has filed this writ petition, for issuance of a Writ of
			<lb />
			Mandamus, forbearing the respondents from undertaking any construction
			<lb />
			activity in Survey No.50/2, Chettiyarpatti Village, Thalavaipuram, which has
			<lb />
			been earmarked as Kalam Poromboke.
			<lb />
			2.In the supporting affidavit, he has contended that in the village, there is
			<lb />
			a temple called, Sithi Vinayagar temple, located on the southern side of Kalam
			<lb />
			Poromboke (thrashing field). The field is surrounded by temples and all the
			<lb />
			festivals are conducted in the thrashing field, by the village people. For their
			<lb />
			village, there is a police station located near Thalavaipuram bus stand and it is
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			3
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			functioning for the past 20 years. On 12.02.2016, the Tahsildar, Rajapalayam
			<lb />
			Taluk, Virudhunagar District, performed Boomi pooja, in the said Kalam
			<lb />
			Poromboke. After enquiry, the villagers came to know that a new police station
			<lb />
			is proposed to be constructed in the said place. They objected to the same. Even
			<lb />
			in the Peace Committee Meeting convened, no settlement was arrived at. On
			<lb />
			19.03.2016, despite objections, the respondents demolished the Kalam situated in
			<lb />
			S.No.50/2, Chettiyarpatti Village, Thalavaipuram.
			<lb />
			3.According to the petitioner, there are 2500 families living in the said
			<lb />
			area. Agriculture is their main occupation. Kalam has been used for time
			<lb />
			memorial days and alteration of the same would affect the villagers. thrashing
			<lb />
			field at S.No.50/2, Chettiyarpatti Village, Thalavaipuram, is the place used by the
			<lb />
			villagers both for agricultural purposes and to conduct public festivals. In the
			<lb />
			abovesaid circumstances, Writ of Mandamus is sought for.
			<lb />
			4.Considering the prayer sought for, we directed Mr.M.Alagadevan,
			<lb />
			learned Special Government Pleader, to take notice on behalf of the respondents
			<lb />
			and get instructions.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			4
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			5.Reverting, he submitted that as early as on 06.10.2013 itself, the District
			<lb />
			Collector, vide proceedings in Na.Ka.B4/11246/2012, dated 06.10.2013, has
			<lb />
			accorded permission for transfer of lands, under Section 23-A of the Board
			<lb />
			Standing Orders, measuring an extent of 0.05.0 hectare out of 0.41.0 hectare,
			<lb />
			Kalam Poromboke in S.No.50/2, Chettiyarpatti Village, Thalavaipuram,
			<lb />
			Rajapalayam Taluk, for construction of a police station. We further directed the
			<lb />
			learned Special Government Pleader to produce the records.
			<lb />
			6.Learned Special Government Pleader by placing reliance on the
			<lb />
			documents and records enclosed in the typed set of papers, dated 31.03.2016,
			<lb />
			submitted that all the objections raised in the present writ petition, do not merit
			<lb />
			any consideration and prayed for dismissal for the writ petition.
			<lb />
			7.Per contra, learned counsel for the petitioner submitted that there was
			<lb />
			no consultation with Thalavaipuram Village Panchayat Council, nor there was
			<lb />
			any resolution passed by the Council permitting transfer of land. Based on the
			<lb />
			recent objections dated 22.03.2016, he further submitted that when 5 out of 9
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			5
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			ward members have objected to construction of a police station, the District
			<lb />
			Collector, Virudhunagar, ought to have considered the same. It is also his
			<lb />
			contention that the order of the District Collector passed without following the
			<lb />
			procedure, is null and void, and for the abovesaid reasons, prayed to issue a
			<lb />
			Writ of Mandamus.
			<lb />
			Heard the learned counsel for the parties and perused the materials
			<lb />
			available on record.
			<lb />
			8.Section 134 of the Tamil Nadu Panchayats Act, 1994, reads as follows:-
			<lb />
			&apos;&apos;134. (1) The provisions of this section shall apply only in
			<lb />
			ryotwari tracts.
			<lb />
			(2) The following porambokes, namely, grazing grounds,
			<lb />
			thrashing floors, burning and burial-grounds, cattle-stands, cart-
			<lb />
			stands and topes shall vest in the village panchayat, and the village
			<lb />
			panchayat shall have power, subject to such restrictions and control
			<lb />
			as may be prescribed to regulate the use of such prorambokes,
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			6
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			provided the porambokes are at the disposal of the Government.
			<lb />
			(3) The Collector, afler consulting the village panchayat,
			<lb />
			may, by notification, exclude from the operation of this Act, any
			<lb />
			poramboke referred to in sub-section (2), and may also modify or
			<lb />
			cancel such notification.
			<lb />
			(4) The village panchayat shall also have power, subject to
			<lb />
			such restrictions and control as may be prescribed, to regulate the
			<lb />
			use of any other poramboke which is at the disposal of the
			<lb />
			Government, if the village panchayat is authorised in that behalf by
			<lb />
			an order of the Government. (5) The village panchayat may, subject
			<lb />
			to such restrictions and control as may be prescribed, plant trees on
			<lb />
			any poramboke, the use of which is regulated by it under
			<lb />
			subsection (2) or sub-section (4). &apos;&apos;
			<lb />
			9.Government have issued orders in G.O(Ms)No.503, Revenue (Ni.Mu.
			<lb />
			4-1) Department, dated 21.9.99, empowering the District Collectors to transfer
			<lb />
			Government poromboke lands to the Government departments when requested
			<lb />
			and the same reads as follows:-
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			7
			<lb />
			</page>
			<page>
			8
			<lb />
		</page>

		<page>
			9
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			10.The Superintendent of Police, Virudhunagar District, has submitted an
			<lb />
			application requesting transfer of land for construction of a police station and
			<lb />
			sought for appropriate orders. The application and covering letter read as
			<lb />
			follows:-
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			10
			<lb />
		</page>
		<page>
			11
			<lb />
		</page>
		<page>
			12
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			11.Extract from the resolution book of the village panchayat shows that
			<lb />
			the Council has passed a resolution No.203 on 03.10.2007 permitting
			<lb />
			construction of police station in S.No.50/2.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			13
			<lb />
		</page>
		<page>
			14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<page>
			15
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			12.Spot inspection has been done on 14.02.2008 and the report of the
			<lb />
			Tahsildar, Rajapalayam Taluk reads as follows:-
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			16
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			13.Thereafter, the Tahsildar, Rajapalayam Taluk, in his letter
			<lb />
			Roc.No.B5/4815/2007 dated 15.02.2008 has sent the particulars to the District
			<lb />
			Revenue Officer, Virudhunagar District:-
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			17
			<lb />
		</page>
		<page>
			18
			<lb />
		</page>
		<page>
			19
			<lb />
		</page>
		<page>
			20
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			14.Letter of the Revenue Divisional Officer, Sivagangai, addressed to the
			<lb />
			District Revenue Officer, Virudhunagar District, reads as follows:-
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			21
			<lb />
		</page>
		<page>
			22
			<lb />
		</page>

		<page>
			23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<page>
			24
			<lb />
		</page>

		<page>
			25
			<lb />
		</page>

		<page>
			26
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			15.Copy of the District Gazette both in Tamil and English have been
			<lb />
			published excepting 0.05 H of land.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			27
			<lb />
		</page>
		<page>
			28
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			16.Vide letter dated 24.04.2011, the Director of Agriculture Department
			<lb />
			has given consent for conversion of land and it is extracted hereunder:-
			<lb />
			17.Thereafter, the District Collector, Virudhunagar District, has sent a
			<lb />
			letter dated 15.06.2011 to the Principal Secretary and Commissioner for
			<lb />
			Municipal Administration, Chennai and it reads as follows:-
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			29
			<lb />
		</page>
		<page>
			30
			<lb />
		</page>
		<page>
			31
			<lb />
		</page>
		<page>
			32
			<lb />
		</page>
		<page>
			33
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			18.Letter dated 26.07.2011 of the Principal Secretary and Commissioner of
			<lb />
			Land Administration, Chennai, to the Principal Secretary to the Government,
			<lb />
			Revenue Department, Chennai, reads thus.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			34
			<lb />
		</page>
		<page>
			35
			<lb />
		</page>
		<page>
			36
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			19.Finally orders have been passed by the District Collector,
			<lb />
			Virudhunagar District, in 2013, which reads as follows:-
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			37
			<lb />
		</page>
		<page>
			38
			<lb />
		</page>
		<page>
			39
			<lb />
		</page>
		<page>
			40
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			20.From the extract from the typed set of papers dated 31.03.2016, it is
			<lb />
			evident that the District Collector, Virudhunagar District, has followed the
			<lb />
			procedure and transfer of land has been gazetted in Virudhunagar District
			<lb />
			Gazette. Though the learned counsel for the petitioner submitted that there was
			<lb />
			no proper consultation with Thalavaipuram Village Panchayat Council, copy of
			<lb />
			the Resolution Book of Thalavaipuram Village Panchayat Council, enclosed in
			<lb />
			the typedset of papers, filed by the respondents, shows that Thalavaipuram
			<lb />
			Village Panchayat Council has passed a resolution on 03.10.2007, in Resolution
			<lb />
			No.203, agreeing for transfer of lands, for the purpose of construction of a police
			<lb />
			station.
			<lb />
			21.Thalavaipuram Village Panchayat Council has passed a resolution way
			<lb />
			back in 2007 and transfer of land has been effected by following the procedure.
			<lb />
			Therefore, it is too late in the day, to make any objection, for construction of a
			<lb />
			police station, by the present ward members. Moreover, thrashing field
			<lb />
			measures 0.41.0 hectares in S.No.50/2. The extent of land allotted to the police,
			<lb />
			for construction of a police station in the abovesaid S.No.50/2, is only 0.05.0
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			41
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			hectares, which is marginal. Contention of the petitioner that police station can
			<lb />
			be constructed in some other place, cannot be accepted, as it is not for the
			<lb />
			petitioner to say. It is for the District Administration and Police Department to
			<lb />
			decide.
			<lb />
			22.Going through the documents extracted supra, we are of the view that
			<lb />
			there is no procedural impropriety. Public purpose is per se evident. The
			<lb />
			decision taken by the district administration would not affect the livelihood of
			<lb />
			the villagers as contended.
			<lb />
			23.Writ of mandamus cannot be issued merely because a person is praying
			<lb />
			for. One must first establish a right and then he must seek for the prayer to
			<lb />
			enforce the said right. If there is failure of duty by the authorities or inaction,
			<lb />
			one can approach the Court for a mandamus.
			<lb />
			24.Though the petitioner has contended that the entire villagers would be
			<lb />
			affected, by taking away a portion of the land, used by them, as thrashing field
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			42
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			and to conduct functions and festivals, having regard to the steps taken by the
			<lb />
			departments right from the year 2007, which has culminated to an order in the
			<lb />
			year 2013, this Court is not inclined to issue any mandamus as prayed for.
			<lb />
			In the result, the writ petition is dismissed. No costs. Consequently,
			<lb />
			W.M.P(MD)No.5231 of 2016 is closed.
			<lb />
			(S.MANIKUMAR, J.) (C.T.SELVAM, J.)
			<lb />
			05 th April 2016
			<lb />
			Index
			<lb />
			: Yes / No
			<lb />
			Internet
			<lb />
			: Yes / No
			<lb />
			NBI
			<lb />
			To
			<lb />
			1)The District Collector,
			<lb />
			Virudhunagar,
			<lb />
			Virudhunagar District.
			<lb />
			2)The Superintendent of Police,
			<lb />
			Virudhunagar,
			<lb />
			Virudhunagar District.
			<lb />
			3)The Tahsildar,
			<lb />
			Rajapalayam Taluk,
			<lb />
			Virudhunagar District.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			43
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			S.MANIKUMAR, J.
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			C.T.SELVAM, J.
			<lb />
			NBI
			<lb />
			W.P(MD)No.5898 of 2016
			<lb />
			05.04.2016
		</body>


	</text>
</tei>