<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 11<lb/> mind against Baburao and his family members.<lb/> Said<lb/> Baburao had arranged dinner in his house on 09.01.2008<lb/> and had invited relatives and persons from village for<lb/> dinner. The dinner was ready and persons from the house<lb/> of Baburao with invitees were to start to take the meal.<lb/> Meanwhile, Baburao and persons in the house heard noise<lb/> from outside the house. Then Baburao and persons in the<lb/> house came out and noticed that, 30 to 40 persons had<lb/> come in the courtyard with weapons in the hands like<lb/> sticks, rods. Persons were uttering words &quot; हानी तर आपली<lb/> हातातली गराम पं चायत घालवली, िनकालाचया िदवशीच याना खलास करायला पािहजे<lb/> होते . तयावे ळे स वाचले . आता हाचं बी पण ठे वू नका.&quot; Uttering these words,<lb/> the persons from the mob started assaulting the family<lb/> members of Baburao. A person from the mob namely<lb/> Shivaji s/o. Kadaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on the chest<lb/> of Gyandeo, the son of Baburao. Other persons from the<lb/> mob were giving blows to Gyandeo, Vijaykumar the brother<lb/> of Baburao; Sanjay, Shahuraj and Sheshrao, the sons of<lb/> Baburao; Bhagwat, the son of Vijaykumar. Then Baburao<lb/> and other persons in the house intervened to separate<lb/> fighting. Meanwhile, persons from the mob rushed against<lb/> them and restrained them from interfering in the event. In<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 13<lb/> 15.01.2008, he recorded memorandum statement of Balaji<lb/> and Govind, and recovered weapons under the panchnamas<lb/> at<lb/> their<lb/> instance.<lb/> On<lb/> 18.01.2008,<lb/> he<lb/> recorded<lb/> supplementary statements of injured persons.<lb/> On<lb/> 20.01.2008, he recorded memorandum statement of<lb/> accused Namdeo s/o. Shivaji, Vilas s/o. Kadaji and Ashok<lb/> s/o. Kadaji, and recovered weapons under the panchnama<lb/> as produced by them. On 21.01.2008, he recovered weapon<lb/> that was produced by accused Ashok s/o. Vishwanath<lb/> under the panchnama. On 31.01.2008, he forwarded seized<lb/> Muddemal to C.A., Aurangabad by a letter. He, then,<lb/> handed over investigation to API Anant Kulkarni, who made<lb/> arrest of accused Nagnath s/o. Raosaheb Pawar, Komalbai<lb/> and Vimalbai. Further investigation was carried out by API<lb/> Laxman Kendre, who on 04.02.2008 recovered stick under<lb/> the panchnama that was produced by accused Waman s/o.<lb/> Dadarao. He forwarded letter to MSEB office and sought<lb/> information about supply of electricity on the date of<lb/> incident in village Jamga, more particularly in the house of<lb/> the complainant. He received letter from the concerned<lb/> office. On 05.04.2008, he submitted charge sheet against<lb/> 14 accused, showing accused No. 15 to 37 absconding. On<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 14<lb/> 20.05.2008, he recovered sticks and rods under panchnama<lb/> that were produced by accused Vishwanath Pawar, Udhav<lb/> Pawar and Vaijinath Pawar, who were on anticipatory bail.<lb/> He recorded memorandum statement of accused Pandurang<lb/> s/o. Vishwanath Pawar and recovered sword produced by<lb/> him under the panchnama. On 16.06.2008, he made arrest<lb/> of 13 accused persons and recorded memorandum of those<lb/> accused and recovered weapons under panchnama that was<lb/> produced by them. Finally, he submitted supplementary<lb/> charge sheet against subsequently arrested accused,<lb/> showing two accused absconding.<lb/></figure>

			<head>4]<lb/></head>

			<p>The Judicial Magistrate First Class, Nilanga<lb/> after noticing that, main offences alleged against accused<lb/> persons are exclusively triable by the Court of Sessions,<lb/> committed case to the Court of Sessions vide his committal<lb/> order dated 19.07.2008.<lb/></p>

			<head>5]<lb/></head>

			<p>The trial Court framed charge against the<lb/> accused at Exh.5 for the offences levelled against them. The<lb/> contents of the charge came to be read over and explained<lb/> to the accused, to which they did not plead guilty and<lb/></p>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 18<lb/> 14 to 21, 23 to 27 and 29 to 35 named above stood<lb/> cancelled due to order passed by the trial Court. Accused<lb/> No.5 Abhimanyu s/o. Raosaheb Pawar, accused No.12<lb/> Ashok s/o. Kadaji Pawar, accused No.22 Vishnu s/o.<lb/> Madhav Pawar and accused No.28 Pandurang s/o. Maroti<lb/> Bhingole were in jail. The trial Court ordered that, they be<lb/> set at liberty forthwith if not required in any other crime.<lb/> Being aggrieved by the Judgment and Order dated 30 th<lb/> June, 2011 passed by the Additional Sessions Judge,<lb/> Nilanga in Sessions Case No. 14/2008, three separate<lb/> Appeal are filed by the convicted accused, by the State and<lb/> the original complainant.<lb/></figure>

			<head>7]<lb/></head>

			<p>The learned counsel appearing for the<lb/> appellants in Criminal Appeal No.414/2011, submitted<lb/> that, the Court below has not at all properly appreciated the<lb/> evidence on record causing miscarriage of justice. It is<lb/> submitted that, the prosecution has miserably failed to<lb/> prove its case against the appellants beyond reasonable<lb/> doubt. It is submitted that, it is doubtful if the so called eye<lb/> witnesses could discern the overt acts in the darkness.<lb/></p>

			<p>There are manifold contradictions and omissions which<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/></figure>

			<head>414.11crapl<lb/> 19<lb/></head>

			<p>completely demolished the evidence of the socalled eye<lb/> witnesses. It is further submitted that, the injuries on the<lb/> deceased were not possible by the weapons allegedly used.<lb/> This is demonstrated from the evidence of the Doctor. It is<lb/> also submitted that, blood group on the clothes of accused<lb/> and weapons do not tally with the blood group of the<lb/> injured. The blood group on the sword seized from accused<lb/> -Shivaji and on the clothes is &quot;O&quot;. Shivaji did not assault<lb/> PW25 Vijaykumar, whose blood group is &quot;A&quot;. It is further<lb/> submitted that, the weapons allegedly used have not been<lb/> seized. Blood group of deceased is &quot;O&apos; but blood of group<lb/> &quot;O&quot; is not detected on the soil seized from the spot.<lb/></p>

			<head>8]<lb/></head>

			<p>The learned counsel appearing for the<lb/> appellants submits that, in fact, it was not possible for the<lb/> alleged eye witnesses to watch accused and his overt acts<lb/> since according to the prosecution case, mob of 40 accused<lb/> gathered at the alleged spot of the incident. According to<lb/> the prosecution case, 39 accused formed unlawful assembly<lb/> and villagers from the village also gathered near the spot of<lb/> incident. It is submitted that, the trial Court was not<lb/> correct in placing reliance on the version of the prosecution<lb/></p>

			<head>414.11crapl<lb/> 20<lb/></head>

			<p>witnesses since there are inherent omissions, contradictions<lb/> and exaggeration. It is submitted that, the complainant has<lb/> not attributed any overt act to accused Namdeo, and<lb/> therefore, he deserves to be given benefit of doubt. It is<lb/> submitted that, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in the case of<lb/> Masalti vs. State of Uttar Pradesh 1 held that, when the<lb/> prosecution alleges unlawful assembly of more than 5<lb/> persons, in such a case it would be unsafe to place reliance<lb/> on the evidence of one witness, but there should be more<lb/> than two witnesses for incident. It is submitted that, the<lb/> prosecution case suffers from inherent contradictions,<lb/> omissions and improvements, and therefore, the benefit of<lb/> doubt deserves to be given to the appellants. The learned<lb/> counsel invited our attention to the evidence of prosecution<lb/> witnesses, and also the medical evidence and submits that,<lb/> the evidence of prosecution witnesses if examined in the<lb/> light of the admissions given in their cross examinations,<lb/> and the portion marked in police statement, it unequivocally<lb/> indicates that, the presence of the appellants was doubtful,<lb/> and also there are no corresponding injuries traced out in<lb/> the medical evidence so as to sustain conviction of the<lb/> <ref type="biblio">1 AIR 1965 SC 202;<lb/></ref> 414.11crapl<lb/> 21<lb/> appellants. It is submitted that, if the version of the<lb/> prosecution witnesses about accused -Vilas is carefully<lb/> perused, the overt act attributed to him by his alleged<lb/> assault by stick, there are no corresponding injuries as it is<lb/> evident from the evidence of PW28 Medical Officer.<lb/></p>

			<p>Therefore, the learned counsel appearing for the appellants<lb/> relying upon the grounds taken in the appeal memo,<lb/> relevant provisions of Indian Penal Code and the Evidence<lb/> Act and also notes of evidence would submit that, the<lb/> appellants deserve to be acquitted.<lb/></p>

			<head>9]<lb/></head>

			<p>The learned counsel appearing for the appellant<lb/> submits that, it has come in the evidence of prosecution<lb/></p>

			<figure>witnesses [PW22Shahuraj] injured eye witness that, Vilas<lb/> Kadaji had assaulted Shahuraj Pawar by stick on his left<lb/> shoulder and stomach. However, the injury certificate at<lb/> Exh. 301 of said injured Shahuraj Pawar does not at all<lb/> show any injury on the left shoulder and stomach of injured<lb/> Shahuraj Pawar. Moreover, the injuries shown is &apos;incised<lb/> wound penetrating&apos; by hard and sharp weapon. Manifestly,<lb/> the stick is not hard and sharp weapon. It is also submitted<lb/> that, it has come in the evidence of prosecution witnesses<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 22<lb/> [PW25 Vijaykumar] injured eye witness that, Vilas Kadaji<lb/> had assaulted Vijaykumar by stick on his head. However,<lb/> the injury certificate [Exh.303] of said injured Vijaykumar,<lb/> does not at all show any injury by stick on the head of the<lb/> said Vijaykumar. The injuries caused to him are all &apos;Incised<lb/> penetrating wounds&apos; caused by hard and sharp weapon, and<lb/> none are on the head.<lb/> Considering above mentioned<lb/> medical certificates, the prosecution evidence of injured eye<lb/> witnesses PW22 and 25 in respect of accused No.11 -Vilas<lb/> is clearly falsified by the medical evidence i.e. Injury<lb/> certificates.<lb/> 10]<lb/> The learned counsel appearing for the<lb/> respondent -accused in Criminal Appeal No.602/2012<lb/> submits that, it has come in the evidence of prosecution<lb/> witnesses / injured eye witnesses that, Ashok Kadaji had<lb/> assaulted Sheshrao Pawar by &apos;Katti&apos; on the right leg shin of<lb/> Sheshrao Pawar. However, the injury certificate of said<lb/> injured Sheshrao Pawar, does not at all show any injury on<lb/> the leg of injured Sheshrao Pawar. It is further submitted<lb/> that, it has come in the evidence of prosecution witnesses /<lb/> injured eye witnesses that, Prakash Kadaji had assaulted<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> Shahuraj Pawar by iron rod on his back. However, the<lb/> injury certificate of said injured Shahuraj Pawar does not at<lb/> all show any injury by iron rod on the back of the said<lb/> Shahuraj Pawar. The injury caused to him is incised wound<lb/> caused by hard and sharp weapon. Considering above<lb/> mentioned medical certificates, the prosecution evidence of<lb/> injured eye witnesses in respect of accused Nos. 12 and 30<lb/> is clearly falsified by the medical evidence i.e. injury<lb/> certificates.<lb/></figure>

			<head>11]<lb/></head>

			<p>The learned counsel Mr. R.S. Shinde appearing<lb/> for the respondent -original accused <ref type="biblio">Nos.4, 12, 30 &amp; 34<lb/></ref> further submitted that, if the entire evidence on record is<lb/> considered, the presence of the accused <ref type="biblio">Nos.4, 12, 30 &amp; 34<lb/></ref> is doubtful, and therefore, they deserves to be given benefit<lb/> of doubt.<lb/></p>

			<head>12]<lb/></head>

			<p>The learned counsel Mr. T.M.Venjane appearing<lb/> for the respondent -accused Nos. 2, 5 to <ref type="biblio">10, 15, 16, 19, 21<lb/></ref> to 24, 26 to 28, 33 and 35 submits that, none of the<lb/> witnesses have named these accused in their deposition<lb/> before the Court. It is further submitted that, the presence<lb/></p>

			<head>414.11crapl<lb/></head>

			<p>of these accused persons is not established by the<lb/> prosecution at the spot of occurrence.<lb/></p>

			<p>It is further<lb/> submitted that, when the presence itself is not established,<lb/> further question of any overt act on behalf of the said<lb/> accused would not arise. Therefore, he submits that, the<lb/> order of acquittal passed by the trial Court, giving benefit of<lb/> doubt deserves no interference.<lb/></p>

			<head>13]<lb/></head>

			<p>The learned counsel Mrs. M.A. Kulkarni<lb/> appearing for the accused -respondent <ref type="biblio">Nos. 3, 14, 17, 18,<lb/> 20, 25, 29, 31</ref> and 32 submits that, the trial Court after<lb/> appreciating the entire evidence on record, reached to the<lb/> correct conclusion and acquitted the accused. The view<lb/> taken by the trial Court is possible, and therefore, this<lb/></p>

			<p>Court may not interfere in the acquittal order.<lb/> It is<lb/> submitted that, evidence of the prosecution witnesses is not<lb/> consistent with each other, and also suffers from the<lb/> inherent contradictions, omissions and improvements, and<lb/> therefore, same deserves to be discarded. It is submitted<lb/> that, the complainant has not named all the accused in the<lb/> complaint, and therefore, said aspect is also required to be<lb/> considered by this Court.<lb/></p>

			<p>It is submitted that, the<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 25<lb/> supplementary statement of the complainant was not<lb/> considered by the trial Court, and same was not read in the<lb/> evidence, and therefore, this Court may not rely upon the<lb/> said supplementary statement.<lb/></p>

			<p>Therefore, the learned<lb/> counsel submits that, the Appeal filed by the State and also<lb/> the complainant may be dismissed.<lb/></p>

			<head>14]<lb/></head>

			<p>Upon careful perusal of the findings recorded by<lb/> the trial Court, it appears that, trial Court compared<lb/> statements of the prosecution witnesses under Section 161<lb/> with their depositions before the Court. It further appears<lb/> that, trial Court instead of giving importance and due<lb/> weightage to the substantive evidence in the nature of eye<lb/> witnesses coupled with the medical evidence chose to acquit<lb/> accused Vimalbai holding that the recovery of the weapon<lb/> from her is not believable. In the present case, there is<lb/> evidence of 11 eye witnesses and out of said witnesses, as<lb/> many as 6 witnesses i.e. P.W. 22 to 26 sustained injuries.<lb/></p>

			<p>The injured witnesses Vijaykumar, Sanjay and Sheshrao,<lb/> sustained grievous injuries, and in particular Vijaykumar<lb/> sustained as many as 7 injuries, which could have caused<lb/> his death in case he would not have got timely treatment.<lb/></p>

			<head>414.11crapl<lb/> 26<lb/></head>

			<p>Upon perusal of the Judgment of the trial Court, it appears<lb/> that, trial Court totally ignored the prosecution case that,<lb/> the accused more than 5 in numbers went to the house of<lb/> the complainant Baburao with the deadly weapons. They<lb/> were aggressors. They were giving slogans. Sum and<lb/> substance of their slogans was that, they will see that, not<lb/> even a single member of the family of the complainant is left<lb/> alive. In furtherance of their common object to cause<lb/> grievous hurt to the members of complainant&apos;s family,<lb/> accused went to his house entered in the courtyard with<lb/> deadly weapons committed criminal trespass with afore<lb/> mentioned object and actually committed various offences.<lb/></p>

			<p>Therefore, it was the duty of the trial Court to address all<lb/> the issues -points arose before it, and render the findings<lb/> thereupon. However, as already observed, the trial Court<lb/> even did not make an attempt to find out that, whether the<lb/> accused persons gathered together with deadly weapons,<lb/> they were more than 5 in numbers, they were aggressors<lb/> inasmuch as they all went to the house of the complainant<lb/> in the evening, they were giving slogans that, they will<lb/> ensure that, not a single member from the family of the<lb/> complainant is left alive. The accused had knowledge that,<lb/></p>

			<head>414.11crapl<lb/> 27<lb/></head>

			<p>such deadly weapons carried by some of the accused, would<lb/> be used for commission of offence, which would result into<lb/> grievous injuries, and also death and as a matter of fact,<lb/> Gyandeo died during attack, and 6 persons were injured.<lb/></p>

			<head>15]<lb/></head>

			<p>This Court is exercising powers -jurisdiction<lb/> under Section 386 of Criminal Procedure Code, which reads<lb/> thus:<lb/></p>

			<head>386. Power of the Appellate Court.<lb/></head>

			<p>After perusing such record and hearing the<lb/> appellant or his pleader, if he appears, and<lb/> the Public Prosecutor, if he appears, and in<lb/> case of an appeal under section 377 or<lb/> section 378, the accused, if he appears, the<lb/> Appellate Court may, if it considers that<lb/> there is no sufficient ground for interfering,<lb/> dismiss the appeal, or may<lb/> <ref type="biblio">(a)<lb/></ref> in an appeal from an order of<lb/> acquittal, reverse such order and direct that<lb/> further inquiry be made, or that the<lb/> accused be retried or committed for trial,<lb/> as the case may be, or find him guilty and<lb/> pass sentence on him according to law;<lb/></p>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 28<lb/> 414<lb/> (b) in an appeal from a conviction<lb/> (i)<lb/> reverse<lb/> the<lb/> finding<lb/> and<lb/> sentence and acquit or discharge the<lb/> accused, or order him to be retried by a<lb/> Court of competent jurisdiction subordinate<lb/> to such Appellate Court or committed for<lb/> trial, or<lb/> (ii)<lb/> alter the finding, maintaining<lb/> the sentence, or<lb/> (iii)<lb/> with or without altering the<lb/> finding, alter the nature or the extent, or the<lb/> nature and extent, of the sentence, but not<lb/> so as to enhance the same;<lb/> (c)<lb/> in an appeal for enhancement<lb/> of sentence<lb/> (i) reverse<lb/> the<lb/> finding<lb/> and<lb/> sentence and acquit or discharge the<lb/> accused or order him to be retried by a<lb/> Court competent to try the offence, or<lb/> (ii)<lb/> alter the finding maintaining the<lb/> sentence, or<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 29<lb/> (iii)<lb/> with or without altering the finding,<lb/> alter the nature or the extent, or the nature<lb/> and extent, of the sentence, so as to<lb/> enhance or reduce the same;<lb/> (d)<lb/> in an appeal from any other order,<lb/> alter or reverse such order;<lb/> (e)<lb/> make any amendment or any<lb/> consequential or incidental order that may<lb/> be just or proper:<lb/> Provided that the sentence shall not<lb/> be enhanced unless the accused has had<lb/> an opportunity of showing cause against<lb/> such enhancement:<lb/> Provided further that the Appellate<lb/> Court shall not inflict greater punishment<lb/> for the offence which in its opinion the<lb/> accused has committed, than might have<lb/> been inflicted for that offence by the Court<lb/> passing the order or sentence under<lb/> appeal.<lb/> 16]<lb/> Since we are deciding three Appeals, one filed by<lb/> the convicted accused No.1 Shivaji, accused No.11 Vilas and<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 30<lb/> accused No.13 Namdeo; another Appeal is filed by the State<lb/> against the acquittal of the remaining accused and for<lb/> enhancement of the sentence of the three convicted<lb/> accused, and the original complainant has filed statutory<lb/> Appeal under Section 372 of Criminal Procedure Code, and<lb/> therefore, in view of the provisions of Section 386 of<lb/> Criminal Procedure Code it is permissible for this Court to<lb/> appreciate the entire evidence on record and pass the<lb/> appropriate order as permissible within the ambit and scope<lb/> of Section 386 of Criminal Procedure Code.<lb/> 17]<lb/> We have given careful consideration to the<lb/> submissions advanced by the learned counsel appearing for<lb/> the convicted accused, the learned Additional Public<lb/> Prosecutor appearing for the State in Criminal Appeal<lb/> No.602/2012, and the learned counsel appearing for the<lb/> complainant in Criminal Appeal No.601/2012, with the<lb/> assistance of the learned counsel, we have carefully perused<lb/> the entire evidence, relevant provisions and also Judgments<lb/> of the High Court and the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court cited<lb/> across the bar by the learned counsel appearing for the<lb/> respective parties. Since three Appeals are arising out of<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 31<lb/> the conviction of three accused and acquitted of remaining<lb/> accused by the trial Court, we propose to reappreciate the<lb/> entire evidence available on record. At the outset it would<lb/> be relevant to reproduce herein below charge framed against<lb/> the accused by the trial Court:<lb/> i]<lb/> That, you accused No.1 to 35 along with<lb/> absconding accused Dayanand S/o Maroti<lb/> Bhingole and Madhav S/o Shivaji Pawar, on<lb/> 09.01.2008 at about 7=20 p.m. at the house of<lb/> the complainant Baburao S/o Bhagwanrao<lb/> Pawar situated at village Jamaga, Tq. Nilanga,<lb/> Dist. Latur, were members of an unlawful<lb/> assembly, the common object of which was to<lb/> assault the complainant and his family<lb/> members, and thereby committed an offence<lb/> punishable under Section 143 of Indian Penal<lb/> Code and within the cognizance of Court of<lb/> Sessions.<lb/> ii]<lb/> That, you accused No. 1 to 35 along with<lb/> absconding accused Dayananad S/o Maroti<lb/> Bhingole and Madhav S/o Shivaji Pawar, on the<lb/> aforesaid date, time and place, were members of<lb/> an unlawful assembly, and in prosecution of the<lb/> common object of said assembly, viz., to assault<lb/> the complainant and his family members,<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 32<lb/> committed the offence of rioting, punishable<lb/> under Section 147 of Indian Penal Code and<lb/> within the cognizance of Court of Sessions.<lb/> iii]<lb/> That, you accused No. 1 to 35 along with<lb/> absconding accused Dayananad S/o Maroti<lb/> Bhingole and Madhav S/o Shivaji Pawar, on the<lb/> aforesaid date, time and place, were members of<lb/> an unlawful assembly, and in prosecution of the<lb/> common object of said assembly, viz., to assault<lb/> the complainant and his family members,<lb/> committed the offence of rioting, and at that<lb/> time, were armed with sword, knives, dagger,<lb/> large sickle (Katti), rods and stick, which are<lb/> sharp cutting instruments and used as weapon<lb/> of offence, was likely to cause death, and<lb/> thereby committed an offence punishable under<lb/> Section 148 of Indian Penal Code and within the<lb/> cognizance of Court of Sessions.<lb/> iv]<lb/> That, you accused No. 1 to 35 along with<lb/> absconding accused Dayananad S/o Maroti<lb/> Bhingole and Madhav S/o Shivaji Pawar, on the<lb/> aforesaid date, time and place, were members of<lb/> an unlawful assembly, and in prosecution of the<lb/> common object of said assembly, viz., to assault<lb/> the complainant and his family members,<lb/> committed house trespass by entering into the<lb/> house of the complainant Baburao Pawar,<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 33<lb/> which is used as a human dwelling and as a<lb/> place for custody of property, having made<lb/> prepared for causing hurt to them by means of<lb/> sword, knives, Katti, dagger, rods and sticks or<lb/> to put them under fear of hurt or assault or<lb/> wrongful restrain and thereby committed an<lb/> offence punishable under Section 452 read with<lb/> 149 of Indian Penal Code and within the<lb/> cognizance of Court of Sessions.<lb/> v]<lb/> That, you accused No. 1 to 35 along with<lb/> absconding accused Dayananad S/o Maroti<lb/> Bhingole and Madhav S/o Shivaji Pawar, on the<lb/> aforesaid date, time and place, were members of<lb/> an unlawful assembly, and in prosecution of the<lb/> common object of said assembly, assaulted<lb/> complainant&apos;s son Gyandeo alias Dnyanoba, by<lb/> means of sword and knives and committed his<lb/> murder intentionally or knowingly caused his<lb/> death, and you all thereby committed an offence<lb/> punishable under Section 302 read with 149 of<lb/> Indian Penal Code and within the cognizance of<lb/> the Court of Sessions.<lb/> vi]<lb/> That, you accused No. 1 to 35 along with<lb/> absconding accused Dayananad S/o Maroti<lb/> Bhingole and Madhav S/o Shivaji Pawar, on the<lb/> aforesaid date, time and place, were members of<lb/> an unlawful assembly, and in prosecution of the<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 34<lb/> common object of said assembly, assaulted the<lb/> complainant&apos;s sons Sanjay, Shahuraj and<lb/> Sheshrao, his brother Vijaykumar and nephew<lb/> Bhagwat by means of sword, knives, dagger,<lb/> Katti, rods and sticks and caused them grievous<lb/> injuries, with such intention or knowledge, and<lb/> under such circumstances that if by that act<lb/> you had caused the death of above persons or<lb/> either of them, you would have been guilty of<lb/> murder, and you all thereby committed an<lb/> offence punishable under Section 307 read with<lb/> 149 of Indian Penal Code and within the<lb/> cognizance of Court of Sessions.<lb/> vii]<lb/> That, you accused No. 1 to 35 along with<lb/> absconding accused Dayananad S/o Maroti<lb/> Bhingole and Madhav S/o Shivaji Pawar, on the<lb/> aforesaid date, time and place, were members of<lb/> an unlawful assembly, and in prosecution of the<lb/> common object of said assembly, voluntarily<lb/> caused hurt to the complainant Baburao, his<lb/> sons Sanjay, Shahuraj and Sheshrao, his<lb/> brother Vijaykumar and nephew Bhagwat by<lb/> means of sword, knives, dagger, Katti, rods and<lb/> sticks, sharp cutting instruments and which<lb/> used as weapon of offence was likely to cause<lb/> death, and you all thereby committed an offence<lb/> punishable under Section 324 read with 149 of<lb/> Indian Penal Code and within the cognizance of<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 35<lb/> Court of Sessions.<lb/> viii] That, you accused No. 1 to 35 along with<lb/> absconding accused Dayananad S/o Maroti<lb/> Bhingole and Madhav S/o Shivaji Pawar, on the<lb/> aforesaid date, time and place, were members of<lb/> an unlawful assembly, and in prosecution of the<lb/> common object of said assembly, voluntarily<lb/> caused hurt to the complainant Baburao, his<lb/> sons Sanjay, Shahuraj and Sheshrao, his<lb/> brother Vijaykumar, nephew Bhagwat and other<lb/> family members, and you all thereby committed<lb/> an offence punishable under Section 323 read<lb/> with 149 of Indian Penal Code and within the<lb/> cognizance of Court of Sessions.<lb/> ix]<lb/> That, you accused No. 1 to 35 along with<lb/> absconding accused Dayananad S/o Maroti<lb/> Bhingole and Madhav S/o Shivaji Pawar, on the<lb/> aforesaid date, time and place, were members of<lb/> an unlawful assembly, and in prosecution of the<lb/> common object of said assembly, intentionally<lb/> abused and insulted the complainant Baburao<lb/> Pawar and his family members and thereby gave<lb/> provocation with intent to or knowingly that<lb/> such provocation would cause them to break<lb/> the public peace and you all thereby committed<lb/> an offence punishable under Section 504 read<lb/> with 149 of Indian Penal Code and within the<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 36<lb/> cognizance of Court of Sessions.<lb/> x]<lb/> That, you accused No. 1 to 35 along with<lb/> absconding accused Dayananad S/o Maroti<lb/> Bhingole and Madhav S/o Shivaji Pawar, on the<lb/> aforesaid date, time and place, were members of<lb/> an unlawful assembly, and in prosecution of the<lb/> common object of said assembly, you all have<lb/> contravened the proclamation issued by the<lb/> District Magistrate, Latur under Sections 37 of<lb/> the Bombay Police Act, prohibiting formation of<lb/> an assembly and to be armed with deadly<lb/> weapons etc., and thereby committed an offence<lb/> punishable under Section 135 of the Bombay<lb/> Police Act, 1951 and within the cognizance of<lb/> Court of Sessions.<lb/> xi]<lb/> That, you accused No. 1 to 35 along with<lb/> absconding accused Dayananad S/o Maroti<lb/> Bhingole and Madhav S/o Shivaji Pawar, on the<lb/> aforesaid date, time and place, were members of<lb/> an unlawful assembly, and in prosecution of the<lb/> common object of said assembly, possessed<lb/> weapons like sword, knives, dagger, katti<lb/> without requisite licence, despite issuance of<lb/> such proclamation by competent authority in<lb/> this area, and thereby committed an offence<lb/> punishable under Section 4 read with 25 of The<lb/> Arms Act, 1959 and within the cognizance of<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 37<lb/> Court of sessions.<lb/> These Appeals raise various points for consideration<lb/> and determination firstly, what are the facts -<lb/>circumstances prior to occurrence of incident, which laid to<lb/> actual incident. Secondly, whether there was prelude to the<lb/> incident which occurred on 9 th January, 2008. Whether<lb/> each member of the assembly had knowledge that, by the<lb/> acts of members of assembly, carrying deadly weapons,<lb/> would result in grievous hurt to the persons from the<lb/> complainant&apos;s family and other persons present at the spot<lb/> of the incident. Thirdly, whether the accused persons went<lb/> to the house of the complainant i.e. place of incident, with<lb/> deadly weapons so as to cause grievous hurt to family<lb/> members of the complainant&apos;s family. Fourthly, whether the<lb/> accused formed unlawful assembly and in furtherance of<lb/> the common object to assault / cause grievous hurt to the<lb/> family members of the complainant so as to finish the<lb/> complainant&apos;s family, assaulted the deceased Gyandeo and<lb/> other persons by weapons like sword, knife, katti, sticks,<lb/> stones, iron rod and fist blows. Fifthly, as a result of the<lb/> assault -attack by the accused persons, there was death of<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/></figure>

			<head>414.11crapl<lb/> 38<lb/></head>

			<p>Gnyandeo and other 6 witnesses sustained injuries<lb/> dangerous to their life. Sixthly, whether each accused<lb/> member of the unlawful assembly present at the place of<lb/> occurrence, in furtherance of their common object to<lb/> assault / cause grievous hurt so as to finish each member<lb/> of the complainant&apos;s family, can be held responsible for the<lb/> commission of murder of Gyandeo and other injuries on<lb/> persons. Seventhly, whether the ingredients of the<lb/> provisions of <ref type="biblio">Section 302, 307, 323, 324, 452, 504, 141,<lb/> 142, 143, 148 and 149</ref> of Indian Penal Code are attracted in<lb/> the light of the evidence brought on record through eye<lb/> witnesses, medical evidence and other evidence. Eightly,<lb/> whether each accused whose presence in the unlawful<lb/> assembly is established by the prosecution, can be held<lb/> responsible for the commission of offence of murder of<lb/> Gyandeo and said accused can be punished for life under<lb/> Section 302 with the aid of Section 149 of I.P. Code.<lb/></p>

			<p>Ninethly, whether the prosecution has proved the spot of<lb/> occurrence and also there was sufficient light so as to watch<lb/> the incident by the prosecution witnesses.<lb/></p>

			<head>18]<lb/></head>

			<p>These are the afore mentioned broad points -<lb/></p>

			<head>414.11crapl<lb/> 39<lb/></head>

			<p>aspects arise for the consideration -determination of this<lb/> Court for which entire reappreciation of the evidence is<lb/> necessary.<lb/></p>

			<head>19]<lb/></head>

			<p>The prosecution has proved spot of incident and<lb/> spot panchanama through PW14 Dnyanoba Kadaji Sagare.<lb/></p>

			<p>His evidence is at Exhibit224 and also Investigating Officer.<lb/></p>

			<p>It would be apposite to reproduce herein below relevant<lb/> portion of the contents of spot panchanama duly translated<lb/> by the official Translator of the High Court Registry in<lb/> English, which reads thus:<lb/></p>

			<head>SPOT PANCHNAMA<lb/></head>

			<p>FIRST INFORMATION REPORT NO.<lb/></p>

			<head>2/2008<lb/> REGISTERED ON 10012008<lb/></head>

			<p>Offence U/<ref type="biblio">Sse. 302, 307, 452, 324, 323,<lb/> 504, 143, 147, 148, 149, of I.P.C. Sec. 4, 7,<lb/> (1)</ref></p>

 26(3) 27(3) Indian Arms Act and 135 of<lb/> Bombay Police Act.<lb/> Name of the Informant :<lb/> 1) Baburao Bhagwanrao @ Bhavan<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/></figure>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 40<lb/> Pawar,<lb/> R/o Jamga, Tal.Nilanga, Dist.Latur.<lb/> Mr.M.D.Thorat, A.P.I., Police Station,<lb/> Aurad (Sha.) called us, the panchas, to act<lb/> as panchas,<lb/> in front of the house of<lb/> Baburao Bhagwanrao @ Bhavan Pawar,<lb/> R/o Jamga, Tal.Nilanga, Dist.Latur for<lb/> preparation of a panchnama in connection<lb/> with Crime No.2/2008 for the offence u/s.<lb/> <ref type="biblio">302, 307, 452, 324, 323, 504, 143, 147,<lb/> 148, 149, of IPC u/s 4, 7, (1)</ref></p>

 26(3) 27(3)<lb/> Indian Arms Act and 135 of Bombay Police<lb/> Act. On the spot, the complainant was<lb/> present. He demonstrated the spot of<lb/> incident. He narrated facts of incident.<lb/> Accordingly, we, the panchas, accepted<lb/> the same and agreed to act as panchas.<lb/> The complainant, who was present<lb/> at the spot,<lb/> stated his name to be<lb/> Baburao Bhagwanrao @ Bhavan Pawar,<lb/> R/o Jamga, Tal. Nilanga, Dist. Latur. He<lb/> narrated the incident before the panchas.<lb/> In the year 2007, elections of Gram<lb/> panchyat were held. In that election, our<lb/> panel got majority. My daughterin law<lb/> was elected as Sarpanch of the village<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 41<lb/> Gram panchayat. Being aggrieved by the<lb/> said election, rival group, headed by viz<lb/> Shivaji Kadaji and his associates was<lb/> having grudge in their mind, from the date<lb/> of election till election of Sarpanch and<lb/> Upsarpanch.<lb/> They deliberately created<lb/> hurdles in the day to day work of Gram<lb/> Sabha. As the Sarpanch of village was<lb/> from our family, they decided to kill the<lb/> family members. The accused namely<lb/> Shivajii Kadaji Pawar and other 35 to 36<lb/> persons, by holding weapons like sword,<lb/> knife, sickle, sticks, iron bars and axe in<lb/> their hands and giving slogans, suddenly,<lb/> on 09012008 at about 7.15 p.m, came<lb/> to our house. They pelted stones. They<lb/> asked all family members to come out of<lb/> the house. They threatened that they will<lb/> not leave any body from his family to<lb/> remain alive.<lb/> They<lb/> will finish entire<lb/> family.<lb/> On the call, we, the family<lb/> members, viz, sons, daughterinlaws,<lb/> brothers, sisterinlaws, and the relatives,<lb/> who were gathered<lb/> on account of a<lb/> function known as &quot;Kanduri&quot;, came out of<lb/> the house, in the court yard. All accused<lb/> assaulted my son namely Dnyadeo with<lb/> the help of sword, knife and sickle in the<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 42<lb/> court yard and committed murder of my<lb/> son. They also assaulted my son Sanjay<lb/> Bhau Vijaykumar and nephew Shahuraj<lb/> with sword and sickle, causing serious<lb/> injuries. Myself, my family members and<lb/> relatives were also<lb/> beaten.<lb/> The<lb/> complainant also shown the spot of<lb/> incident where deceased Gyndeo, injured<lb/> Vijaykumar, Shesharao and<lb/> Shahurao<lb/> Bhagwat were lying.<lb/> While observing the said spot, it is<lb/> noticed that the said location is a new<lb/> habitat village Jamga, towards the road<lb/> leading Nilanga to Sonkhed, towards<lb/> EastWest side,<lb/> where house of<lb/> Shri.Baburao Bhagwanrao @ Bhavan<lb/> Pawar is situated. Said house is situated<lb/> in the newly occupied area having its face<lb/> on West side, adjacent to the road towards<lb/> SouthNorth corner. The house of Baburao<lb/> Pawar is situated in his own land bearing<lb/> Gut No. 48(b). The area of said residential<lb/> house is 95 X 75 feet, towards EastWest<lb/> and North South. Said spot is adjacent to<lb/> the tar road, at the distance of 22 feet and<lb/> one room, constructed with brick and<lb/> cement, consisting of 25 X 18 size,<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 43<lb/> having door of tinshutter, which is used<lb/> as front hall, wherein,<lb/> sags of grains<lb/> have been kept. The said room is also<lb/> having a door of small shutter, wherein,<lb/> an arrangement of electric light has also<lb/> been made. Adjacent to the said room, a<lb/> heap of sand has also been noticed. From<lb/> the said spot, it is said that, open space<lb/> of informant is situated at a distance of<lb/> 50 feet,<lb/> where a<lb/> stones were lying<lb/> scattered.<lb/> The room which was<lb/> constructed by cement and bricks is also<lb/> having 20 feet open space towards Eastern<lb/> side.<lb/> A roof of 18 X 15 size, made of a<lb/> sheet of dried steams or twigs,<lb/> is also<lb/> fixed. On the Eastern side, a tin shed<lb/> was fixed, as if a wall to the said house.<lb/> A wooden frame, having a latch and a lock<lb/> affixed and two folded wooden doors, has<lb/> also been affixed. While inspecting and<lb/> entering in the tin shade house, from the<lb/> door, three sides of wall made up with<lb/> tin, were noticed. One wooden almirah<lb/> was found kept adjacent to the door and<lb/> near<lb/> a partition of tin which runs<lb/> towards North side.<lb/> It was noticed that,<lb/></figure>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 44<lb/> in the kitchen room an earthen kiln was<lb/> kept. Besides this, in the said tin shed<lb/> compartment, towards Southern side, two<lb/> big<lb/> pots of grains (Kangis) were also<lb/> noticed. In the same compartment, a<lb/> cradle was affixed for the use of minor<lb/> children.<lb/> Towards the same line of<lb/> compartments, two rooms have also been<lb/> constructed towards Southern side. On<lb/> the South West side, there is a bath room<lb/> and<lb/> water tank. Out of two rooms<lb/> towards Southern side, one has six tins<lb/> on roof. It is having a cot and T.V. In the<lb/> same line of compartment, West sides two<lb/> rooms have been constructed. Out of these<lb/> two rooms, one room consists of 8 tins on<lb/> roof, wherein, an iron cot along with<lb/> household articles are kept. In the room<lb/> towards Southern side, there is an iron<lb/> cot, a row of pots, a house of deities and<lb/> other goods &amp; chattels are kept. In the<lb/> said three tin compartments, few plates &amp;<lb/> dishes containing nonveges items were<lb/> kept ready for being served at the dinner<lb/> with informant and other male members<lb/> and invitees.<lb/> This is the position of the<lb/> house as was seen.<lb/> The informant<lb/> present here has told where the deceased<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 45<lb/> Gyandev was lying injured.<lb/> Looking at<lb/> that place, it is at a distance of 10 feet, in<lb/> front of the door of<lb/> tin shed house,<lb/> towards the West and at a distance of 20<lb/> feet, behind the room built by brick and<lb/> cement. At the said place, there are many<lb/> big stains of blood.<lb/> The said place looks<lb/> like as if it has been dug into by feet of a<lb/> person. Next to the tinshed house&apos;s door<lb/> towards the North, there is a big wooden<lb/> log, used for heating water, which faces<lb/> the West. Towards the West, in the open<lb/> courtyard, at the distance of 20 feet, there<lb/> is the spot where injured Vijay Kumar<lb/> was lying. At the said spot,<lb/> at many<lb/> places, it appears that blood was spilled<lb/> and stains thereof appear in the shape of<lb/> blood being clogged there. The door of the<lb/> brick cement house faces the North and 5<lb/> feet from here, is the place where the<lb/> sand is put and spread where injured<lb/> Shahuraj Pawar was lying<lb/> and was<lb/> found in injured condition. The injured<lb/> was found lying where the sand was<lb/> spread. The dried blood can be found on<lb/> the sand. At the place of incident five<lb/> sticks, two iron rods are seen lying, as<lb/> also, small stones are seen lying in the<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 46<lb/> courtyard and in the tin shed house. An<lb/> electric wire taken from the house adjacent<lb/> to the tin shed house and a big bulb<lb/> hanging from it can also be seen. Towards<lb/> the West side of the plot of Baburao Pawar<lb/> and near the Eastern road, there is a<lb/> horizontal water tank and a vertical water<lb/> tank. Next to the vertical water tank, an<lb/> electric cement pole,<lb/> with a Gram<lb/> Panchayat bulb, can also be seen. At the<lb/> place of incident, in the courtyard and on<lb/> terrace, five sticks both long and short<lb/> two iron rods of different lengths and<lb/> samples of blood mixed with sand, from<lb/> two places,<lb/> have been taken in the<lb/> presence of the &quot;panchas&quot;. The slips of<lb/> signatures of police and panchas have<lb/> been attached thereon.<lb/> The photographs<lb/> of the place of incident have been taken by<lb/> a photographer from Aurad (Sh) city.<lb/> The four directional boundaries, as<lb/> seen; from the place where the dead /<lb/> injured was found, are :<lb/> Towards the East : Residential house<lb/> of the informant viz. Baburao Pawar and<lb/> in front of it, there is a plot owned by<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 47<lb/> Baburao Bhagwanrao Pawar.<lb/> Towards the West : Open space in<lb/> front of the informant&apos;s house as well as a<lb/> living room built by brick and cement and<lb/> in front of it, a tar road running towards<lb/> North South, from Nilanga to Sonkhed.<lb/> Towards the South :<lb/> Residential<lb/> house of Dilip Bhagwanrao Pawar and<lb/> there is an open Court yard in front of the<lb/> house. In front of it, residential house of<lb/> Vijaykumar Bhagwanrao Pawar.<lb/> Towards<lb/> the North : Open plot<lb/> belonging to the informant Baburao Pawar<lb/> upt 30 feet. Next to it, is the a agricultural<lb/> field of Ganesh Shankar Pawar. The crop<lb/> of harvested tur dal was seen lying.<lb/> In<lb/> front thereof, there is residential house<lb/> constructed in bricks and cement belonging<lb/> to Raosaheb Bhalrao Suryawanshi.<lb/> The abovesaid place of incident<lb/> seems to be in the courtyard of the<lb/> residential house of the informant Baburao<lb/> Bhagwanrao Pawar which consists of 95 X<lb/> 75 plot which is situated at village Jamga.<lb/></figure>

			<head>414.11crapl<lb/> 48<lb/></head>

			<p>The<lb/> abovesaid<lb/> panchnama<lb/> is<lb/> written, from the beginning to the end, in<lb/> the presence of the &quot;panchas&quot; and same is<lb/> read over to them, which is true and<lb/> correct.<lb/></p>

			<p>[</p>

			<figure type="table">Emphasis supplied]<lb/> 20]<lb/> The prosecution has examined Dnyanoba Kadaji<lb/> Sagare as PW14, who acted as panch. He stated in his<lb/> evidence before the Court that, he came to know about<lb/> murder of Gyandeo and then came to Jamga. Police had<lb/> called him for panchanama at the house of Baburao Pawar.<lb/> Baburao, Dilip, Chandrakant, Kamlakar Jadhav etc. were<lb/> present. Baburao showed them the spot of incident. At the<lb/> spot of incident, 5 sticks and 2 iron rods were noticed.<lb/> There were plates, smallplates and the pot having cooked<lb/> Mutton. One bulb was in the roof of courtyard. There was<lb/> also bulb in the shop which part of the house. Near the<lb/> shop by the side of road, there was bulb on electric pole. At<lb/> two places on the earth, blood was noticed. Police collected<lb/> blood mixed earth in two bags. Lables bearing signature of<lb/> PW14 and another panch were affixed on the sticks and<lb/> iron rod. Police had brought with them cameraman and he<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 49<lb/> snapped photographs of the place of incident.<lb/> Police<lb/> prepared panchnama at the spot and obtained his<lb/> signature. Panchnama now shown to him is the same. It<lb/> bears his signature. Panchnama is at Exh.225. Sticks, iron<lb/> rods shown to him are the same, which bears their<lb/> signatures lables. Those are articles 2 and 3.<lb/> This witness was cross examined on behalf of<lb/> accused Nos. 3 and 29. Through his cross examination<lb/> defence tried to bring it on record that, this witness is<lb/> relative of the complainant Baburao. It is true that, this<lb/> witness has admitted that, the complainant is his brother in<lb/> law. However, he specifically stated that, panchnama was<lb/> effected from 7.30 to 8.30 a.m. on 10 th January, 2008.<lb/> Place of incident is a plot admeasuring 95 x 75 sq. ft. The<lb/> plot is located in the land of Baburao. The construction is<lb/> at two places in that plot. Incident took place in the portion<lb/> on backside of shop and front side of the house. The said<lb/> vacant portion where incident took place admeasuring 25 x<lb/> 18 sq. ft. Pot containing cooked Mutton was inside the<lb/> house. There was only one pot. There were ten dinner<lb/> plates and 10 small plates. He has specifically denied the<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 50<lb/></figure>

			<p>suggestion that, blood lying on the earth was of crock. He<lb/> further stated that, Police collected blood mixed earth only.<lb/></p>

			<p>He also stated that, he noticed sticks, also iron rods,<lb/> however, he does not know length of such sticks and iron<lb/> rod. In his crossexamination, he reiterated his version in<lb/> examination in chief that, the spot panchanama is prepared<lb/> in his presence and he has signed the same.<lb/></p>

			<p>According to the prosecution case, the incident<lb/> had taken place after 7.00 p.m. and there was sufficient<lb/> light to witness the incident, and according to defence, there<lb/> was dark.<lb/></p>

			<p>Prosecution did examine PW8 Shailesh<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">Narayanrao Patil, who was working as Junior Engineer with<lb/> MSEDCL, Nilanga, Unit Rural 2 at the relevant time. In his<lb/> examination in chief, he stated that, he is serving since<lb/> 1999. He is attached to Nilanga Unit as Junior Engineer<lb/> since 2006.<lb/> Police had addressed one letter dated<lb/> 29.02.2008 to his office. It is the same, shown to him. It is<lb/> his signature on that letter. It is at Exhibit 156. He had<lb/> given reply to that letter. It is the same shown to him. It<lb/> bears his signature. It is at Exhibit 157. He did bring the<lb/> Daily Load Record Register. He has given reply to the letter<lb/></figure>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 51<lb/> of Police after referring the entry in DLR Register. In DLR<lb/> Register there are entries of existence of electricity on<lb/> 09.01.2008. He has brought the attested copy of entry in<lb/> DLR Register dated 09.01.2008, which is as per original,<lb/> and which is at Exhibit 160.<lb/></figure>

			<p>In his cross examination, nothing has been<lb/> brought on record by the defence so as to disbelieve his<lb/> evidence. Therefore, prosecution has proved that, there was<lb/> electric supply available on the date of incident at the<lb/> relevant time. To that effect Exhibit 157 has been proved by<lb/> the prosecution through PW8. The evidence brought on<lb/> record unequivocally indicates that, on the date of incident<lb/> there was electric supply and as a matter of fact, at the time<lb/> of incident, there was sufficient light, and therefore, the<lb/> witnesses had sufficient opportunity to watch the incident<lb/> and also to see the accused persons. As per the prosecution<lb/> case, panel supported by accused persons did loose in the<lb/> Gram Panchayat elections inasmuch as they could not get<lb/> the requisite strength of elected members to have their<lb/> control. There was an attempt on the part of the accused<lb/> even on earlier occasions to create dispute, and as a matter<lb/></p>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 52<lb/> of fact threats were extended by them that, they will not<lb/> allow to hold Gram Sabha. It has come on record through<lb/> the prosecution witnesses that, though the election of the<lb/> post of Sarpanch was scheduled to be held on 23.11.2007,<lb/> however, it was postponed on next day i.e. on 24.11.2007<lb/> due to tense situation created by the accused persons not<lb/> allowing to hold the election on scheduled date. It is also<lb/> relevant to mention that, accused persons are resident of<lb/> the same village, and therefore, the witnesses knew them.<lb/></figure>

			<p>Therefore, the question of holding identification parade for<lb/> identifying them was not necessary, when the witnesses had<lb/> sufficient opportunity to see the accused persons on the<lb/> spot.<lb/></p>

			<head>21]<lb/></head>

			<p>The prosecution examined Dattatraya Narayan<lb/> Gosavi as PW9, who was working as Gramsevak at village<lb/> Jamga at the relevant time.</p>

			<figure type="table">His evidence is at Exhibit 168.<lb/> He stated that, he was called by the Police in the Court on<lb/> 28 th March, 2008. The complaint was read over to him. The<lb/> complaint was relating to the incident occurred in the village<lb/> Jamga. Police demanded Form No. VIII regarding house of<lb/> Baburao Bhagwan Pawar. Accordingly, he issued extract to<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> the Police. He stated that, the extract shown to him is the<lb/> same, which is at Exhibit 169. He specifically denied the<lb/> suggestion in the cross examination that, he did not issue<lb/> VIIIA extract, as per the original to the Police. He further<lb/> stated that, at the relevant time daughter in law of the<lb/> complainant was Sarpanch of the village Jamga. Therefore,<lb/> the prosecution has proved that, the house where incident<lb/> had taken place is belonging to the complainant Baburao.<lb/> 22]<lb/> The inquest panchanama of dead body of<lb/> Gyandeo is at Exhibit62. The said inquest panchanama<lb/> has been proved by the prosecution by examining Rajendra<lb/> Pandu More as PW1, whose evidence is at Exhibit61. In<lb/> his evidence, he stated before the Court that, on<lb/> 10.01.2008, he had been to Nilanga. On 09.01.2008 at<lb/> 11.00 p.m. he received telephonic call that, there was an<lb/> attack on the house of his relative, and the relatives had<lb/> come to Nilanga, and so, he came to Nilanga. He came to<lb/> Nilanga on 10.01.2008 at Sub District Hospital at Nilanga.<lb/> He was called by Police at 7.30 a.m. for panchanama, as he<lb/> was relative of the complainant. The other panch Shahuraj<lb/> Patil was also called by police. They both panch witnesses<lb/></figure>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 54<lb/> went near the dead body of the deceased Gyandeo @<lb/> Dnyanoba. They saw the dead body and injuries on the<lb/> dead body.<lb/></figure>

			<head>23]<lb/></head>

			<p>He further stated that, he saw the injuries on<lb/> the head below left ear. It was cut injury admeasuring 2<lb/> inch. He saw the hair at the backside of the head were<lb/> smeared with blood. He saw that, the eyes and the mouth<lb/> of the deceased were halfopened, and there was saliva<lb/> coming from the mouth. He saw injury on the left side of<lb/> the chest, and it was 2 ½ inch in the length and 0.75 inch<lb/> deep. It was bleeding injury. He saw 2 injuries on the<lb/> stomach. Each injury was of 1 inch. He saw the back of<lb/> the deceased, and there were 2 injuries on the back, and<lb/> those injuries were 1 inch length and depth. The private<lb/> part of the deceased was intact and there was no bleeding or<lb/> semen. There was abrasion on the shoulder. There was<lb/> abrasion on right knee.<lb/></p>

			<head>24]<lb/></head>

			<p>He further stated that, the panchnama was<lb/> written in their presence. It was read over to them. The<lb/> photographs of the dead body were taken by the<lb/> photographer. Then he himself, Shahuraj Patil signed said<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 55<lb/> panchnama. The panchnama shown to him is the same.<lb/></p>

			<p>The panchnama was completed between the period 7.30<lb/> a.m. to 8.30 a.m. The contents of the panchanama are<lb/> correct, which is at Exhibit 62.<lb/></p>

			<p>Upon perusal of his cross examination, it<lb/> appears that, defence tried to bring on record that, he is<lb/> close relative of the complainant except said admission,<lb/> nothing useful to the defence has been brought on record by<lb/> the prosecution so as to disbelieve evidence of said witness.<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">The inquest panchnama is also proved by the prosecution<lb/> through Investigating Officer and Shahurao Baburao Patil.<lb/> 25]<lb/> It appears that, clothes of the deceased Gyandeo<lb/> were seized on 10.01.2010. The panchanama to that effect<lb/> has been prepared. The said is given Exhibit65. It appears<lb/> that, Tanaji Nagorao Gade and Satyanarayan Pandurang<lb/> Dapake were the panchas for the said seizure panchanama.<lb/> Rajeshwar Dhondiba Hampalle was examined as PW3. His<lb/> evidence is at Exhibit 94. He stated that, on 10.01.2008, he<lb/> was present in Sub District Hospital, Nilanga when there<lb/> was post mortem of deceased Gyandeo. He has taken the<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/></figure>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 56<lb/> clothes on the person of deceased in his custody after the<lb/> post mortem. The clothes were bunian, pant, sweater,<lb/> nicker, and one white big handkerchief. Those clothes were<lb/> in Aurad Police Station. He submitted report to that effect<lb/> to the Police Station. He identified the contents of the said<lb/> report before the Court and also his signature. He stated<lb/> that, the contents of the said report are true and correct.<lb/></figure>

			<p>Nothing useful to the defence has been brought on record so<lb/> as to disbelieve the evidence of this witness before the<lb/> Court.<lb/></p>

			<head>26]<lb/></head>

			<p>It appears that, Tanhaji Nagorao Kale who was<lb/> panch to the seizure of the clothes on the person of the<lb/> deceased Gyandeo and was examined as PW4. However, he<lb/> stated before the Court that, the clothes of Vilas Kadaji<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">Pawar, Ashok Kadaji Pawar, Shivaji Kadaji Pawar were not<lb/> seized in his presence. However, he has not stated that,<lb/> clothes on the person of Gyandeo were not seized in his<lb/> presence. It appears that, clothes of the deceased Gyandeo,<lb/> which were seized were sent to the Regional Forensic<lb/> Science Laboratory, State of Maharashtra, Old Nizam<lb/> Bungalow Cantonment, Aurangabad. The description of the<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/></figure>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 57<lb/> clothes -articles contained in parcels was Sando Banian<lb/> [cut] wrapped in cloth labelled -A1, full pant [cut] wrapped<lb/> in cloth labelled -A2, Sweater wrapped in cloth labelled -<lb/>A3 belongs to the deceased Gyandeo was sent to the<lb/> Regional Forensic Science Laboratory, State of Maharashtra.<lb/> The result of the analysis of the said article A1 to A3 is<lb/> those were soaked with blood. It further appears that, in<lb/> presence of PW2 Govind Keshavrao Birajdar the Police<lb/> seized clothes on the person of the accused. This witness in<lb/> his evidence stated that, on 10 th January, 2008, he had<lb/> been to attend funeral of the deceased son of the<lb/> complainant. The Police called him at Aurad Shahajani<lb/> Police Station so as to seize clothes on the person of<lb/> accused. He himself and Hanmant Sagre had been to the<lb/> said Police Station. They reached at the Police Station at<lb/> about 4.45 p.m. The Police seized clothes on the person of<lb/> accused in their presence. He stated the names of accused<lb/> whose clothes were seized in their presence, which are as<lb/> follows: 1]<lb/> Mahadeo Ganpati Shahapure, 2] Shivaji s/o.<lb/> Kadaji Pawar, 3] Tukaram<lb/> s/o.<lb/> Shivaji<lb/> Pawar,<lb/> 4]<lb/> Abhimanyu s/o. Ramsaheb Pawar, 5] Ashok s/o.<lb/> Vishwanath Pawar, 6] Govind s/o.Ganpati Shahapure, 7]<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 58<lb/> Satyanarayan s/o. Madhav Shahapure, 8] Pandhari s/o.<lb/> Manik Pawar, 9] Manik s/o. Ramji Pawar, and 10] Balaji<lb/> s/o. Apparao Pawar.<lb/></figure>

			<head>27]<lb/></head>

			<p>He further stated that, he had seen clothes<lb/> seized by Police. He saw blood stains on the clothes seized.<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">The Police seized clothes of those accused by preparing<lb/> separate 10 panchnamas. The panchnamas were<lb/> commenced at 5.00 to 5.15 p.m. and were completed till<lb/> 10.20 p.m.<lb/> He can identify the clothes seized in his<lb/> presence, if shown to him. He further stated that, the police<lb/> prepared 10 separate panchnamas of seizure of clothes.<lb/> Each panchanama shown to him bears his signature.<lb/> Content of each panchnamas, which are at Exhibit 77 and<lb/> 86. The panchanamas at Exh.81 to 86 was shown to this<lb/> witness before the Court and he stated that, there were<lb/> blood stains on all clothes seized under the panchnama at<lb/> Exh.77 to 86. During his cross examination, the defence<lb/> has brought on record that, he is in blood relations of the<lb/> complainant Baburao.<lb/> He has specifically denied<lb/> suggestion that, he was not able to identify accused<lb/> persons. He has denied the suggestion that, Police prepared<lb/></figure>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 59<lb/> false panchnama and obtained his signature. He further<lb/> denied suggestion that, since he being relative of the<lb/> complainant his signatures are obtained on the<lb/> panchanama. However, he stated that, accused namely<lb/> Govind Shahapure, Satyanarayan Shahapure, Pandhari<lb/> Pawar, Manik Pawar and Balaji Pawar, their clothes were<lb/> seized. It was not mentioned in panchanama at Exh.81 to<lb/> 86 that, their clothes were blood stained.<lb/></figure>

			<p>However,<lb/> according to this witness, panchanama at Exh.81 to 86 are<lb/> false, therefore, the evidence of this witness so far at Exh.77<lb/> to 80 and blood stains found on the clothes which were<lb/> seized appears to be correct.<lb/></p>

			<head>28]<lb/></head>

			<p>The prosecution did examine PW5 Subhash<lb/> Vishwanath Solanke, his evidence is at Exhibit111, to<lb/> prove memorandum statement given by the accused Balaji<lb/> Apparao Pawar and accused Govind Ganpatrao Shahapure.<lb/></p>

			<p>In his evidence, he stated that, accused Balaji Apparao<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">Pawar has given memorandum statement that, he has<lb/> concealed stick in his house and he would hand over the<lb/> same. The said memorandum was reduced into writing by<lb/> Police. It bears his signature and also signature of other<lb/></figure>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 60<lb/> panch Shahajirao. Contents of the said memorandum<lb/> panchanama are true and correct. He stated that, the<lb/> accused Govind Ganpatrao Shahapure has also given<lb/> memorandum statement stating that, he has concealed<lb/> stick in his house, and he would hand over the same. Police<lb/> reduced into writing said disclosure in his presence. He<lb/> identified the contents of the said memorandum<lb/> panchanama and also he bears signature and signature of<lb/> other panch Shahajirao.<lb/></figure>

			<p>According to this witness that, the accused<lb/> Balaji Pawar removed one stick which was under the<lb/> wooden flanks and same was handed over to the Police in<lb/> presence of the panchas. He further stated that, accused<lb/> Govind Shahapure also removed one stick from beneath the<lb/> matrix on the wooden bed and same was seized by Police in<lb/> their presence under the panchanama. He identified his<lb/> signatures and also the stick. In his cross examination, the<lb/> defence has brought on record that, this witness was<lb/> relative of the deceased Gyandeo. He has denied suggestion<lb/> that, the sticks were seized in the Police Station itself.<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 61<lb/> 29]<lb/> The prosecution did examine Ramakant Uttam<lb/> Solanke as PW6. In his evidence, he stated that, accused<lb/> Ashok Pawar gave memorandum in his presence and<lb/> showed willingness to hand over one stick from his house.<lb/> He identified the memorandum panchnama. He stated that,<lb/> Yuvraj Solunke was another panch. He stated that, the<lb/> accused entered in the house and handed over one stick to<lb/> Police. The said stick was at the corner of the room behind<lb/> row of earthen pots. Nothing useful has been brought on<lb/> record by the defence so as to disbelieve his version in the<lb/> examination in chief.<lb/> 30]<lb/> The<lb/> prosecution<lb/> examined<lb/> one<lb/> Goroba<lb/> Chanderrao Ghorpade as PW7, who was as Naik Police<lb/> Constable, B.No.1114, Police Station, Latur on 13.01.2008.<lb/> He stated that, on 13.01.2008, he had been to Civil<lb/> Hospital, Latur. Four injured persons were under medical<lb/> treatment in the said Hospital. He has taken clothes of<lb/> injured persons from the said Hospital to the Police Station,<lb/> Aurad Shahajani and he handed over those clothes to PSO,<lb/> ASI Shri Chavan. He further stated that, those clothes were<lb/> seized under the panchnama. Accordingly, he submitted<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/></figure>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 62<lb/> report to the Police Station. He identified the said report<lb/> and bears his signature, which is at Exh.127. In his cross<lb/> examination he stated that, he denied suggestion that,<lb/> report prepared by him was not true.<lb/> 31]<lb/> The prosecution examined Madhukar Bapurao<lb/> Pawar as PW11. His evidence is at Exhibit190. He stated<lb/> in his evidence that, on 20.05.2008, police had called him in<lb/> the village. He was coming to his house from the field. He<lb/> reached near the bridge and the Police called him there.<lb/> Police seized weapons there. Weapon was by the side of<lb/> stream, and the said stream was by the side of land of<lb/> Narsing. Weapon was the sword. Police seized the sword.<lb/> He signed on the panchnama. He identified the weapon at<lb/> Article No.29. This witness was declared hostile by the<lb/> learned APP. In his cross examination, he stated that, he<lb/> know Pandurang Pawar. Pandurang stated in his presence<lb/> to police that, he will produce the sword and police reduced<lb/> into writing his disclosure. It bears his signature. It is at<lb/> Exhibit 191. He went near the bridge. From there below<lb/> the bridge from the earth below the cement pipe Pandurang<lb/> removed sword and Police seized it. He signed on the said<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 63<lb/> panchanama. Panchanama shown to him is the same. It<lb/> bears his signature. It is at Exh.192. He further stated<lb/> that, the sword shown to him at Article No.2 is the same.<lb/> Therefore, he denied suggestion given by defence that, Police<lb/> called him for panchnama for being rival of Pandurang. He<lb/> denied the suggestion that, their signatures were obtained<lb/> on the Panchnama in the village. He further stated that, he<lb/> denied suggestion that, he is deposing due to political<lb/> rivalry with Pandurang.<lb/> 32]<lb/> The prosecution examined Ram Sambhaji Pawar<lb/> as PW12, whose evidence is at Exhibit209.<lb/> In his<lb/> evidence, he stated that, on 04.02.2008, he was at village<lb/> Jamga. On that day, police had called him. Waman<lb/> Dadarao Pawar was with the Police. Dayanand Pawar was<lb/> also with them. Police took him at the house of Waman.<lb/> Waman produced there a stick from his house. Police<lb/> seized stick under the panchanama.<lb/> He signed said<lb/> panchanama as witness.<lb/> He identified his thumb<lb/> impression. Panchanama is at Exhibit 210. The defence<lb/> has brought on record in cross examination that, this<lb/> witness is a relative of the complainant Baburao.<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 64<lb/> 33]<lb/> The prosecution examined one Narsing Namdeo<lb/> Hingole as PW13, whose evidence is at Exh. 211. He stated<lb/> that, on 20.05.2008, he was taken by Police to the house of<lb/> Vishwanath Pawar. Police took inspection of his house.<lb/> Vishwanath Pawar handed over one stick to Police which<lb/> was kept by the side of grain store. Police affixed chit on the<lb/> stick with his signature and seized it under the<lb/> panchanama. He identified the said panchanama and his<lb/> signature [Exh. 212]. He also identified the muddemal stick<lb/> shown to him before the Court which is at Article No.4. He<lb/> further stated that, Police took him to the house of Vaijinath<lb/> Pawar and inspected the house. Vaijinath Pawar produced<lb/> one stick kept under the cot. Police affixed chit on it with<lb/> his signature and seized stick under the panchnama. He<lb/> identified his signature and contents of the said<lb/> panchanama [213]. He further stated that, Police took him<lb/> to the house of Udhav Pawar. Udhav produced iron rod<lb/> before the Police. Police affixed chit of his signature on the<lb/> rod and seized it under the panchanama. He identified<lb/> panchanama and his signature on it at Exh.214. He<lb/> identified said article No.5 i.e. iron rod.<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 65<lb/> 34]<lb/> The prosecution examined one Maroti Baliram<lb/> Nagade as PW15, whose evidence is at Exhibit 226. In his<lb/> evidence before the Court, he stated that, on 14.01.2008<lb/> Police had called him in Police Station, Nilanga. There was<lb/> one accused. He identified the said accused before the<lb/> Court.<lb/> Accused told his name as Mahadu Ganpatrao<lb/> Shahapure. He further stated that, accused stated before<lb/> them that, he himself and other 30 to 35 persons went to<lb/> the house of Baburao Pawar at Jamga and committed<lb/> murder of son of Baburao by assaulting with sticks and he<lb/> is ready to produce the stick with which he had assaulted.<lb/> Police accordingly recorded statement of the accused and<lb/> obtained his signature on it. He identified statement of the<lb/> accused Madhav which was shown to him and also<lb/> signature of PW15, accused and other panch. He stated<lb/> that, accused put thumb impression on it.<lb/> He further stated that, this witness has also<lb/> deposed about the memorandum statement of the accused<lb/> Satyanarayan Shahapure and Manik Pawar and stated that,<lb/> Satyanarayan disclosed that, he along with other went to<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 66<lb/> the house of the complainant Baburao and committed<lb/> murder of his son. He identified his signature on the said<lb/> memorandum and also thumb impression of the accused.<lb/> The said memorandum is at Exh.228 likewise he also<lb/> identified the memorandum at Exh.230 given by accused<lb/> Manik Pawar.<lb/> It appears that, in pursuant to the<lb/> memorandum statement of Manik Pawar, he shown<lb/> willingness to produce the stick. It further appears that,<lb/> accused Abhimanyu Pawar also gave memorandum<lb/> statement and showed willingness to produce the knife used<lb/> by him. Accordingly, the statement was recorded by Police<lb/> and signature of this witness was obtained. He identified<lb/> his signature and memorandum statement. He further<lb/> stated that, accused Pandhari Pawar gave memorandum<lb/> statement before him and at his instance iron rod was<lb/> recovered. He further stated that, accused Tukaram Pawar<lb/> also gave memorandum statement and showed readiness to<lb/> produce stick and accordingly said stick was recovered at<lb/> the instance of the said accused.<lb/> He further stated that, accused Shivaji Pawar<lb/> stated before the police in his presence and showed<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 67<lb/> willingness to produce the sword used by him in the<lb/> assault. Accordingly, Police recorded his memorandum and<lb/> obtained signature of this witness on it. The memorandum<lb/> shown to him and obtained his signature. He further stated<lb/> that, accused Madhav Shahapure gave memorandum and<lb/> accordingly his memorandum was recorded by the Police.<lb/> Accused Madhav Shahapure showed his house and from a<lb/> room beneath black box removed a stick and handed over<lb/> the same to the Police. Likewise, accused Satyanarayan<lb/> gave memorandum and iron rod was recovered at his<lb/> instance. He further stated that, Abhimanyu Pawar was<lb/> also gave memorandum, same was seized under the<lb/> panchanama and in pursuant to his statement at his<lb/> instance he showed willingness to hand over knife and<lb/> accordingly knife article No.51 was handed over by the<lb/> accused Abhimanyu Pawar to Police. He further stated that,<lb/> memorandum of Tukaram Pawar was recorded, he signed<lb/> the same at his instance, police recovered a stick. Accused<lb/> Shivaji Pawar produced sword from the tin sheet roof of the<lb/> house. He also stated that, thereafter they went to the<lb/> house of Manik Pawar from the house of Madhav<lb/> Shahapure. Manik Pawar went in the house and brought<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 68<lb/> one stick. He also stated that, police seized the said stick<lb/> and drawn panchanama and obtained signature of this<lb/> witness. He identified the panchanama.<lb/> The defence<lb/> brought on record through his cross examination that,<lb/> complainant is his relative. He denied suggestion that, none<lb/> of the accused gave memorandum nor produced any<lb/> weapons in his presence.<lb/></figure>

			<head>35]<lb/></head>

			<p>The prosecution did send 27 sealed clothes<lb/> parcels to the Regional Forensic Science Laboratory, Old<lb/> Nizam Bungalow, Cantonment, Aurangabad, forwarding<lb/> letter to the Assistant Police Inspector, Police Station, Aurad<lb/> Shahajani, District Latur.<lb/> Upon perusal of result of<lb/> analysis, it appears that, on almost all articles blood was<lb/> found. Therefore, result of the analysis shows that, blood<lb/> stains were found on the articles, which were sent to the<lb/> C.A.<lb/></p>

			<head>36]<lb/></head>

			<p>It further appears that, result of the analysis is<lb/> that, exhibits <ref type="biblio">1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15,<lb/> 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 26 and 27</ref>; same blood is<lb/> human. Exhibits 1, 2, 7, 8, 9, 10, 19, 20, 21 and 24 are<lb/></p>

			<head>414.11crapl<lb/> 69<lb/></head>

			<p>stained with blood of Group &apos;O&apos;. Exhibits 5, 6, 11 and 14<lb/> are stained with blood of group &apos;A&apos;. <ref type="biblio">Exhibits 15, 16, 17, 22,<lb/> 23</ref> and 27 are stained with blood of group &apos;B&apos;. Selection of<lb/> blood stains on exhibit 26 and grouping thereof reveals that<lb/> some of the stains are of blood group &apos;A&apos; and some of blood<lb/> group &apos;O&apos;. Group of blood detected on exhibits 3, 4, 12, 13<lb/> and 18 cannot be determined as the results are<lb/> inconclusive.<lb/></p>

			<head>37]<lb/></head>

			<p>Whether the death of deceased Gyandeo was<lb/> homicidal, accidental or suicidal will have to be ascertained<lb/> from the medical evidence.<lb/></p>

			<p>Postmortem report is at<lb/></p>

			<figure>Exhibit291. The probable cause of death was due to cardio<lb/> respiratory arrest due to puncture of left ventricle of heart.<lb/> The prosecution has examined Dr. Pralhad Tulshiram<lb/> Solanke as PW27. His evidence is at Exhibit290. In his<lb/> evidence, he stated that, on 10.01.2008, he was on duty in<lb/> S.D.H. Nilanga. On that day, at 11.50 a.m. the dead body of<lb/> Gyandeo @ Dnyanoba s/o. Baburao Pawar was brought by<lb/> Police Station, Nilanga by Head Constable Hundekar for<lb/> post mortem along with inquestpanchnama. He carried<lb/> post mortem on the dead body of Gyandeo @ Dnyanoba and<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 70<lb/> found following injuries on his person:<lb/> i]<lb/> C L W at left Temporal Region Size 3 x 2 x<lb/> 1 cm<lb/> ii]<lb/> Deep incised wound at left anterior<lb/> axillary region, at 5 th and 6 th Inter costal space<lb/> with 3 x 2 x Deep dimension<lb/> iii]<lb/> Deep incised wound at epigastric region 3<lb/> x 2 x Deep.<lb/> iv]<lb/> Deep incised wound at left hypochamdric<lb/> region size 3 x 2 x Deep.<lb/> v]<lb/> Deep incised wound at left infrascapular<lb/> region. Size 3 x 2 x Deep.<lb/> vi]<lb/> Parallel wound deep of samedimension, 5<lb/> Cm on left of 5 th wound.<lb/> He also found following internal injuries on the<lb/> dead body:<lb/> i]<lb/> Fracture of 5 th and 6 th left rib.<lb/> ii]<lb/> Tear at Ventricular region.<lb/> iii]<lb/> Left Ventricle get punctured with 1.5 Cm<lb/> dimensions<lb/> iv]<lb/> Deep incised wound at left lung<lb/> paranchyme on back.<lb/> v]<lb/> Stomach get punctured of dimensions 2<lb/> Cm.<lb/> He expressed his opinion that, cause of death<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 71<lb/> was due to cardio respiratory arrest due to puncture of left<lb/> ventricle of heart, and accordingly, he issued P.M. Notes.<lb/></figure>

			<head>38]<lb/></head>

			<p>During his cross examination, he stated that, C<lb/> L W injury No.1 can be caused by hard and blunt object,<lb/> and it is not caused by sharp weapon. He further stated<lb/> that, if blow is given by weapon like sword on ribs, then<lb/> there is possibility of cutting of ribs. If sword blow is given<lb/> horizontal on chest, then ribs of both sides would be cut.<lb/></p>

			<p>In case of sword attack, there is possibility of amputation of<lb/> organs. Ventricle is one of the chamber of the heart. There<lb/> are four chambers in heart. Out of that only one chamber is<lb/> punctured. He further stated that, puncture injury to heart<lb/> was due to piercing of weapon.<lb/></p>

			<head>Upon reading the injuries mentioned in column<lb/></head>

			<p>No.17 of the post mortem, and also evidence of PW27, it is<lb/> abundantly clear that, Gyandeo died homicidal death.<lb/></p>

			<head>39]<lb/></head>

			<p>It is also necessary to find out from the<lb/> Medical evidence about injuries sustained by as many<lb/> as six eye witnesses to the incident. It appears that, Dr.<lb/></p>

			<figure>::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 72<lb/> Shivanand Shivhari Biradar was examined as PW28 by<lb/> the prosecution and his evidence is at Exhibit 299. In<lb/> his examination in chief, he sated that, on 09.01.2008,<lb/> he was attached to SubDistrict Hospital, Nilanga as<lb/> Medical officer. On that day, he examined injured<lb/> Sheshrao S/o Baburao Pawar, who approached suo<lb/> motu and found following injuries on his person:<lb/> i]<lb/> Clean Incised wound over left dorsum of forearm,<lb/> horizontal, near wrist. Size 3 x 1 x 1 Cm. deep.<lb/> ii] Clean Incised wound over left forearm near wrist<lb/> lower onethird, oblique, dorsoventrally on radial<lb/> side. Size 8 x 1.5 x 1.5 depth Cms. It was bleeding.<lb/> iii] Clean Incised wound on medical aspect of injury<lb/> No.2, left forearm.<lb/> iv] Contusion over wrist joint left. Size 3 x 4 x 1 Cm<lb/> Movements were painful and restricted.<lb/> All these injuries No.1 to 3 were caused by<lb/> hard and sharp object. Injury No.4 was caused by hard<lb/> and blunt object. All these injuries were simple in<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 73<lb/> nature and caused within 6 hours. Patient was referred<lb/> to Civil Hospital, Latur for orthopedic opinion.<lb/> Accordingly he has issued injury certificate at Exhibit<lb/> 300. This witness identified the said certificate, which<lb/> bears his signature.<lb/> 40]<lb/> This witness then examined injured<lb/> Shahuraj S/o Baburao Pawar and found Incised wound<lb/> penetrating over right renal angle over back, oblique.<lb/> Size 4 x 1 Cm penetrating depth not recorded as deep.<lb/> It was grievous in nature, caused by hard and sharp<lb/> weapon, within 6 hours. Patient was referred to Civil<lb/> Hospital, Latur for further treatment. Accordingly, he<lb/> issued injury certificate at Exhibit 301. He identified<lb/> the said certificate and stated that, same bears his<lb/> signature. He further stated that, then he examined<lb/> Sanjay S/o Baburao Pawar and found Incised<lb/> penetrating injury over right iliac fossa. Size 5 x 2.5<lb/> Cm. penetrating. It was grievous in nature, caused by<lb/> hard and sharp weapon, within 6 hours. Accordingly,<lb/> he issued injury certificate at Exhibit 302. He identified<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 74<lb/> the said certificate and stated that, it bears his<lb/> signature.<lb/> Then<lb/> he<lb/> examined<lb/> Vijaykumar<lb/> S/o<lb/> Bhagwanrao Pawar and found following injuries on his<lb/> person :<lb/> (i)<lb/> Incised penetrating wound over right back,<lb/> oblique, Size 10 x 5 Cm muscle deep.<lb/> (ii)<lb/> Incised penetrating wound over infra<lb/> scapular region, right back. Size 5 x 3 Cm. 5 Cm<lb/> below injury No.1.<lb/> (iii) Incised penetrating wound, over left scapular<lb/> region. Size 3 x 2.5 Cm x muscle deep.<lb/> (iv) Incised penetrating wound, infrascapular<lb/> region, right side. Size 3 x 1.5 Cm. X muscles cut.<lb/> (v)<lb/> Incised penetrating would, left lower back,<lb/> paraspinal region. Size 2 x 1.5 Cm. x deep<lb/> muscles cut.<lb/> (vi) Incised would, left zygomatic arch. Size 4 x 1<lb/> x ½ Cm.<lb/> (vii) Penetrating incised wound with intestinal<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 75<lb/> coils protruding out of injury, over supra umbilical<lb/> region, extending to epigastric region. Size 6 x 4<lb/> Cm. perforating.<lb/> (viii) Abrasion with C.L.W. over upper lip over nose<lb/> and upper lip. Size 1 x ½ x ½ Cm.<lb/> (ix) Abrasion over left elbow. Size 1 x 1 x ½ Cm.<lb/> Injuries No. 1 to 5 and 7 are grievous in<lb/> nature. Injury Nos. 6, 8 and 9 are simple in nature.<lb/> Injury no. 9 caused by hard and blunt object.<lb/> Accordingly, he issued injury certificate at Exhibit 303.<lb/> He identified the said certificate and stated that, it<lb/> bears his signature.<lb/> He further stated that, then he examined<lb/> patient Bhagwat S/o Vijaykumar Pawar and found<lb/> clean lacerated wound over left frontal region, Size 10 x<lb/> 2.5 Cm. It was caused by hard and blunt object, within<lb/> 6 hours. It was simple in nature. Accordingly, he issued<lb/> injury certificate at Exhibit 304. He identified the said<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 76<lb/> certificate and stated that, it bears his signature.<lb/> 41]<lb/> He was crossexamined by Advocate Mr. T.V.<lb/> Jamdar for some of the accused. In his cross examination<lb/> he stated that, he recognized injury of Shahuraj as grievous<lb/> injury, as it is penetrating injury and on vital part. It was<lb/> grievous injury because it endangers human life. He has<lb/> also further stated details about the injuries sustained by<lb/> Sanjay, Vijaykumar and Bhagwat. If his evidence is perused<lb/> in its entirety including examination in cross, his evidence<lb/> is not shattered in any manner.<lb/> 42]<lb/> The prosecution examined P.Ws.16 to 26 as eye<lb/> witnesses of the incident. The evidence of original<lb/> complainant Shri Baburao Bhagwanrao Pawar, who was<lb/> examined as PW16 by the prosecution, is at Exhibit241.<lb/> PW16 in his evidence stated that, he resides in the house<lb/> along with his four sons, four daughtersinlaw, mother,<lb/> grandchildren. His four sons are married. His house is<lb/> located in Survey No.48/B at village Jamga.<lb/> On<lb/> 07.09.2007, elections of the Grampanchayat was held. Two<lb/> panels contested the said election. One panel was headed<lb/> by him and another was led by accused Shivaji. His panel<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 77<lb/> was elected in that election. He further stated that, the<lb/> elections of the Grampanchayat were held on 07.09.2007.<lb/> Results were declared on 09.09.2007. In that election, 4<lb/> candidates out of 7 from his panel were successful. Three<lb/> candidates of accused Shivaji&apos;s panel out of 7 were elected.<lb/> Since the said elections, relations between him and group of<lb/> accused No.1 are strained.<lb/> Thereafter, there was dispute<lb/> in Gram Sabha. On 23.11.2007, Sarpanch was to be<lb/> elected. On that day, accused No.1 and his group raised<lb/> dispute saying that election of Sarpanch will not be allowed<lb/> to be held. For conducting election of Sarpanch, Naib<lb/> Tahsildar had come. For the post of Sarpanch, Varsh w/o.<lb/> Shahuraj Pawar was the candidate from his panel. Finally,<lb/> on the next day of election of Sarpanch was conducted in<lb/> Police Bandobast on 24.11.2007, and in that election his<lb/> daughterinlaw Varsha Shahuraj Pawar was elected as<lb/> Sarpanch.<lb/> He further deposed that, in the Gram<lb/> Panchayat, accused picked up quarrels with him and his<lb/> panel saying that, they will not allow to hold Gram Sambha<lb/> and they will not allow them to work as Sarpanch. They<lb/> made complaint about it to Tahsildar. He further deposed<lb/> that, incident took place on 09.01.2008 at about 7.00 to<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 78<lb/> 7.15 p.m. On that day, there was next day of Yal Amawasya<lb/> Festival, and he had arranged chickendinner. He had<lb/> invited Chandrakant Solanke, Maroti Jadhav, Waman<lb/> Pawar, Anant Pawar and Tatyarao Bhingole for dinner at his<lb/> house. These persons had arrived at his house. He had<lb/> discussion with these persons about the terror and threats<lb/> by accused on account of elections. His son Gyandeo and<lb/> female members of family prepared food for dinner. After<lb/> cooking food, he himself and above persons sat for dinner<lb/> under tinshed roof. At the time of dinner, they heard loud<lb/> noise from outside. Abusing and stone pelting started.<lb/> Then he himself, Gyandeo, Vijaykumar, Dilip, Shahuraj,<lb/> Sheshrao, Bhagwat, Sanjay, aforesaid guests, Anuradha<lb/> Pawar, Varsha Shahuraj, Santoshibai Sanjay Pawar, Babita<lb/> Sheshrao Pawar came in the courtyard. About 30 to 35<lb/> persons from outside came in his courtyard. Amongst those<lb/> persons, Shivaji Kadaji Pawar was holding sword, Namdeo<lb/> Shivaji Pawar was holding sword, Madhav Shivaji Pawar<lb/> was holding sword like Jamibya, Ashok Kadaji Pawar was<lb/> holding Katti, Vimalbai Shivaji Pawar was holding knife,<lb/> Dayanand Bhingole was holding sword. Other persons were<lb/> holding sticks and iron rods. All these persons rushed on<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 79<lb/> the person of Gyandeo. Satish Vaijinath Pawar, Tukaram<lb/> Shivaji Pawar, Udhav Shivaji Pawar caught hold to<lb/> Gyandeo. Shivaji Kadaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on the<lb/> chest of Gyandeo. Then, Madhav Shivaji Pawar inflicted<lb/> sword blow on the right side abdomen of Gyandeo. Namdeo<lb/> Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow near bemby of Gyandeo.<lb/> Dayanand Bhingole inflicted sword blow on the back side<lb/> and ribs on right of Gyandeo. Vimalbai Shivaji Pawar<lb/> inflicted knife blow on the back of Gyandeo. Other accused<lb/> assaulted Gyandeo by sticks and iron rods.<lb/> Then<lb/> Vijaykumar Bhagwanrao was assaulted by Madhav Shivaji<lb/> Pawar by sword on the face. Namdeo Shivaji Pawar inflicted<lb/> sword blow to Vijaykumar on shoulder. Udhav Shivaji<lb/> Pawar assaulted by iron rod to Vijaykumar. Vilas and<lb/> Haridas Pawar each assaulted Vijaykumar by stick and iron<lb/> rod. Accused Prakash Kadaji Pawar assaulted Shahuraj<lb/> Pawar by iron rod. Vilas Kadaji Pawar assaulted Shahuraj<lb/> Pawar by stick. Accused Shivaji Kadaji Pawar assaulted<lb/> Shahuraj on back right side by sword. Ashok Kadaji Pawar<lb/> assaulted on right shin by Katti to Sheshrao Baburao<lb/> Pawar. Shivaji Kadaji Pawar assaulted on left hand wrist of<lb/> Sheshrao Pawar by sword.<lb/> Devidas Pralhad Pawar<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 80<lb/> assaulted by stick to Bhagwat Pawar on the head. Waman<lb/> Dadarao Pawar assaulted him by stick on the back. Other<lb/> accused persons assaulted other persons in their family.<lb/> Then Gyandeo, Shahuraj, Sheshrao, Sanjay, Vijaykumar,<lb/> Bhagwat were taken to the Hospital. He himself and other<lb/> persons were accompanying them. Injured were taken to<lb/> Hospital at Nilanga. Doctor examined injured persons.<lb/> Sanjay, Baburao Pawar, Shahuraj Baburao Pawar,<lb/> Vijaykumar Bhagwanrao Pawar were referred by Doctor to<lb/> Latur for further treatment. He himself and other guests<lb/> accompanied them to Latur. Sheshrao and Bhagwat were<lb/> referred to Latur Hospital on next day for further treatment.<lb/> 43]<lb/> PW16 further deposed that, they received<lb/> phone at Latur from the Nilanga Hospital that, during<lb/> treatment Gyandeo Baburao Pawar died. He instructed<lb/> guest to file application at Aurad Police Station regarding<lb/> incident. They prepared the application. PW16 put his<lb/> signature on it, and then, they went to Police Station, Aurad<lb/> along with said application and submitted it in the Police<lb/> Station. This witness identified the said application and<lb/> also stated that it bears his signature at Exh.259. He<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 81<lb/> further deposed that, he went to Nilanga Hospital. He saw<lb/> there the dead body of Gyandeo. Then, post mortem was<lb/> conducted on the dead body of Gyandeo. Then, he went to<lb/> village Jamga for effecting spot panchnama at the call of<lb/> Police. Police prepared the spot panchnama of the place<lb/> shown by him. Again he came to Nilanga Hospital. After<lb/> conducting post mortem, Doctor handed over dead body of<lb/> Gyandeo to him.<lb/></figure>

			<head>44]<lb/></head>

			<p>This witness was cross examined by Advocate<lb/> for accused <ref type="biblio">Nos. 1, 4, 11, 12, 13, 30, 18, 20, 32, 25, 31, 17<lb/></ref> and 34. It appears that, some questions were asked to him<lb/> about who contested the Grampanchayat elections.<lb/></p>

			<p>However, nothing useful to defence was brought on record<lb/> from the said information about elections. It further appears<lb/> that, the defence did ask certain questions about<lb/> preparation of the application which was submitted to the<lb/> Police Station. It appears that, this witness has stated that,<lb/> names of the accused mentioned in the said application<lb/> were as per his say. It appears that, the defence did ask the<lb/> question about the contents of the said application, and<lb/> whether the aspects like accused did not allow to conduct<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/></figure>

			<head>414.11crapl<lb/> 82<lb/></head>

			<p>Gram Sabha were incorporated in the said application or<lb/> not. However, nothing useful to the defence has been<lb/> brought on record by asking such questions by the defence.<lb/></p>

			<p>It is pertinent to mention that, PW16 who was under<lb/> tremendous mental stress on that relevant night, was not<lb/> expected to incorporate everything in the FIR. FIR is not<lb/> encyclopedia.<lb/></p>

			<head>PW16 in his cross</head>

			<figure>examination further stated<lb/> that, at the time of complaint, he had stated before the<lb/> Police that, accused Shivaji Namdeo Pawar was holding<lb/> sword. He had not stated before the Police that, Vimalbai<lb/> was having Katti in her hand. He further stated that, while<lb/> writing the complaint that, accused Mahadeo Shivaji Pawar<lb/> had given sword blow on right side abdomen of Gyandeo.<lb/> However, he cannot assign any reason why it is not<lb/> mentioned in the complaint.<lb/> He further stated that,<lb/> accused Namdeo Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow near<lb/> navel of Gyandeo. The accused Dayanand Bhingole inflicted<lb/> sword blow on the backside near ribs on right of Gyandeo.<lb/> He further stated in the complaint that, accused Madhav<lb/> Shivaji Pawar had given sword blow on mouth of<lb/> Vijaykumar, and accused Namdeo Pawar inflicted sword<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 83<lb/> blow on the shoulder of Vijaykumar. Accused Udhav Pawar<lb/> assaulted Vijaykumar by iron rod. Accused Vilas and<lb/> Haridas each assaulted Vijaykumar by stick.<lb/> Accused<lb/> Prakash Kadaji Pawar assaulted Shahuraj Pawar by iron<lb/> rod. Accused Vilas Kadaji Pawar assaulted Shahuraj by<lb/> stick. Accused Shivaji Pawar had given blow with sword on<lb/> back to right side of Shahuraj.<lb/> Ashok Kadaji Pawar<lb/> assaulted Shesherao Pawar on right shin by Katti. Accused<lb/> Shivaji Pawar had inflicted sword blow on left hand wrist of<lb/> Sheshrao Pawar. Accused Devidas Pawar gave stick blow<lb/> on the head of Bhagwat. Accused Waman Dadarao Pawar<lb/> assaulted by stick on his back and other persons beat other<lb/> persons from his family. He further stated that, he cannot<lb/> assign any reason why above facts are not mentioned in his<lb/> complaint. He further stated that, at the time of incident<lb/> about 3040 persons had come to his house for assault. On<lb/> that day, three persons from his village and two guests had<lb/> come to his house for dinner. At that time, 5 to 6 persons<lb/> from his house were present. At the time of incident, three<lb/> persons from his village and two guests who had come to<lb/> his house for dinner, had intervened the quarrel. Assailants<lb/> assaulted aforesaid 5 persons causing them concealed<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 84<lb/> injuries. They were assaulted by sticks. There were no<lb/> visible injuries on their person. Their family members and<lb/> the persons who come for dinner were raising hue and cry.<lb/> Other persons from the village did not come at the place of<lb/> incident on hearing hue and cry. Witness volunteers that<lb/> villagers did not come at the spot of incident on seeing the<lb/> mob of assailants. He further stated that, when accused<lb/> persons went away from the spot of incident, 5 to 50<lb/> persons from the village had come there. His daughter in<lb/> law Varsha Pawar had sustained invisible injuries. They did<lb/> not resist the assailants. He further stated that, all accused<lb/> in collusion with each other assaulted them. He can tell<lb/> names of all accused. He specifically denied suggestion<lb/> that, at the time of incident, there was dark at his house<lb/> due to loadshading. He stated that, four persons amongst<lb/> assailants were holding sword, one was holding knife, one<lb/> was having katti, two were holding iron rods and 8 to 9<lb/> persons were holding sticks. However, he clearly stated that,<lb/> he does not know what other 22 persons were holding, as<lb/> the mob of assailants was large. He has specifically denied<lb/> suggestion that, no incident took place as narrated by him<lb/> and only with view to extract money from accused, he has<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 85<lb/> filed false case. He specifically denied suggestion that,<lb/> incident had not taken place at his house and that blood<lb/> was not lying in his house.<lb/> He specifically denied<lb/> suggestion that, on the day of incident, no dinner<lb/> programme was arranged at his house and that nobody<lb/> guest or friends in the village had come to his house for<lb/> dinner.<lb/> 45]<lb/> This witness was further cross examined by the<lb/> Advocate for accused Nos. 2, 5 to 10, 15, 16, 19, 21 to 24,<lb/> 26 to 28, 33 and 35. In his cross examination, he stated<lb/> that, Pandurang Vishwanath Pawar is in service in<lb/> Pharmacy College at Nilanga as Store Keeper since many<lb/> years and he resides at Nilanga along with his family.<lb/> Dhondiram Pawar is serving as Teacher since many years in<lb/> Zilla Parishad, and he resides at Nilanga along with his<lb/> family.<lb/> Ashok Vishwanath Pawar is serving in Police<lb/> Department and he resides at Latur since many years.<lb/> Govind Ganpat Shahapure is also a Teacher. Vishwanath<lb/> Vithal Pawar, Maroti Madhav Pawar, Vishnu Madhav Pawar,<lb/> Chandrahans Vishwanath Pawar, Vinayak Raosaheb Pawar,<lb/> Narayan Maroti Bhingole, Suresh Maroti Bhingole,<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 86<lb/> Pandurang Maroti Bhingole, Nagnath Raosaheb Pawar,<lb/> Madhav Ganpat Shahapure, Abhimanyu Raosaheb Pawar,<lb/> Manik Ramji Pawar, Balaji Apparao Pawar all are<lb/> agriculturists. Komal Maroti Pawar is household woman.<lb/> Satyanarayan Shahapure resides at other village. He know<lb/> all these persons as they hail from his village. Komal Maroti<lb/> Pawar has no concern with the incident in question. All<lb/> aforesaid persons are also having no concerned with the<lb/> incident.<lb/></figure>

			<head>46]<lb/></head>

			<p>This witness was further cross examined by the<lb/> Advocate for accused Nos.</p>

			<figure type="table">3, 14 and 29. In his cross<lb/> examination, he stated that, accused Pandhari and Haridas<lb/> are real brothers inter se. Both these are nephews of<lb/> Waman Limbaji Pawar, who had come to his house for<lb/> dinner.<lb/> Accused Pandhari has no concern with the<lb/> incident. He further deposed that, it is not true to say that,<lb/> he falsely implicated accused Haridas at the instance of<lb/> witness Waman Pawar. He specifically denied suggestion<lb/> that, accused Waman Pawar did not assault him by stick,<lb/> and that accused Haridas Pawar did not assault Vijaykumar<lb/> by iron rod.<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 87<lb/> 47]<lb/> PW16 was reexamined by the Special Public<lb/> Prosecutor for State. In his reexamination, he stated that,<lb/> on the next day of incident, Police had come to him and<lb/> recorded his statement. He was also cross examined by the<lb/> Advocate for accused Nos. 1, 4, 11 to 13, 17, 18, 20, 25, 30<lb/> to 32 and 34, he stated that, complaint was given on<lb/> 10.01.2008 at 4.00 a.m.<lb/> Funeral was performed on<lb/> 10.01.2008 at 2.00 p.m. Spot panchnama was conducted<lb/> on 10 th January, 2008 at 10.00 a.m. Police recorded his<lb/> statement on 10.01.2008 at 10.00 a.m. At that time,<lb/> condition of his mind was not good. While recording his<lb/> supplementary statement, he stated that, accused Satish,<lb/> Tukaram and Udhav had caught hold Gyandeo when Shivaji<lb/> assaulted him by sword. He stated that, he cannot assign<lb/> any reason why Police did not record to that effect in his<lb/> supplementary statement. He specifically denied suggestion<lb/> that, police did not record his supplementary statement. It<lb/> appears that, this witness was reexamined. In his recross<lb/> examination, he denied suggestion that, he did not state<lb/> before the Police about assault by Haridas by iron road, and<lb/> accused Waman Pawar assaulted by stick.<lb/></figure>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 88<lb/> 48]<lb/> Upon careful perusal of the evidence of PW16,<lb/> it clearly appears that, the accused persons who were<lb/> aggressors came to the house of complainant holding deadly<lb/> weapons in their hands and giving slogans that, they will<lb/> see that, no family members of the complainant is left alive,<lb/> entered the house of the complainant and by use of deadly<lb/> weapons like sword, knife, katti, sticks and iron rod<lb/> assaulted son of the complainant Gyandeo and other<lb/> persons including his family members, who were present in<lb/> his house at the relevant time. It has also come in his<lb/> evidence that, some of the accused pelted stones at his<lb/> house. It has also come on record that, because of hearing<lb/> of noise of the accused persons, villagers did not dare to<lb/> come to the house of the complainant for their rescue. It<lb/> further appears that, the accused persons were armed and<lb/> gathered at the spot of occurrence and formed unlawful<lb/> assembly, and assaulted Gyandeo and other persons who<lb/> were present at the spot of incident so as to achieve<lb/> common object of assaulting / causing grievous hurt to the<lb/> family members of the complainant.<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 89<lb/> It is abundantly clear from the reading of the<lb/> evidence of the complainant that, in his examination in<lb/> chief, he named accused Shivaji Kadaji Pawar was holding<lb/> sword, Namdeo Shivaji Pawar was holding sword, Madhav<lb/> Shivaji Pawar was holding sword like Jamibya, Ashok Kadaji<lb/> Pawar was holding Katti, Vimalbai Shivaji Pawar was<lb/> holding knife, Dayanand Bhingole was holding sword and<lb/> other persons were holding sticks and iron rods. It is<lb/> specifically stated by him that, all these persons rushed on<lb/> the person of Gyandeo. He further attributed overt act to the<lb/> Satish Vaijinath Pawar, Tukaram Shivaji Pawar, Udhav<lb/> Shivaji Pawar, who caught hold to Gyandeo. Shivaji Kadaji<lb/> Pawar inflicted sword blow on the chest of Gyandeo. Then<lb/> Madhav Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on the right side<lb/> abdomen of Gyandeo. Namdeo Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword<lb/> blow near bemby of Gyandeo. Dayanand Bhingole inflicted<lb/> sword blow on the back side and ribs on right of Gyandeo.<lb/> Vimalbai Shivaji Pawar inflicted knife blow on the back of<lb/> Gyandeo and other accused assaulted Gyandeo by sticks<lb/> and iron rods. Then Vijaykumar Bhagwanrao was assaulted<lb/> by Madhav Shivaji Pawar by sword on the face. Namdeo<lb/> Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow to Vijaykumar on<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 90<lb/> shoulder. Udhav Shivaji Pawar assaulted Vijaykumar by<lb/> iron rod.<lb/> Vilas and Haridas Pawar each assaulted<lb/> Vijaykumar by stick and iron rod. Accused Prakash Kadaji<lb/> Pawar assaulted Shahuraj Pawar by iron rod. Vilas Kadaji<lb/> Pawar assaulted Shahuraj Pawar by stick. Accused Shivaji<lb/> Kadaji Pawar assaulted Shahuraj by stick on back right side<lb/> by sword. Ashok Kadaji Pawar assaulted on right shin by<lb/> Katti to Sheshrao Baburao Pawar. Shivaji Kadaji Pawar<lb/> assaulted on left hand wrist of Sheshrao Pawar by sword.<lb/> Devidas Pralhad Pawar assaulted by stick to Bhagwat Pawar<lb/> on the head. Waman Dadarao Pawar assaulted him by stick<lb/> on the back. Other persons assaulted other persons in their<lb/> family. Therefore, upon careful perusal of the evidence<lb/> of this witness, it is abundantly clear that, he named and<lb/> attributed specific role to the accused Shivaji Kadaji Pawar,<lb/> Namdeo Shivaji Pawar, Madhav Shivaji Pawar, Ashok Kadaji<lb/> Pawar, Vimalbai Shivaji Pawar, Dayanand Bhingole, Satish<lb/> Vaijinath Pawar, Tukaram Shivaji Pawar, Udhav Shivaji<lb/> Pawar, Vilas and Haridas Pawar, Prakash Kadaji Pawar,<lb/> Waman Dadarao Pawar and other accused.<lb/> He has<lb/> specifically stated the manner in which each of the accused<lb/> assaulted Gyandeo and other persons including six injured<lb/></figure>

			<figure type="table">::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 91<lb/> eye witnesses.<lb/> 49]<lb/> Upon careful perusal of his examination in<lb/> cross, his evidence in the examination in chief has not been<lb/> shattered in slightest manner, on the contrary, he has<lb/> reiterated his assertions in the examination in chief during<lb/> his cross examination.<lb/> Nothing substantial has been<lb/> brought on record by the defence useful to accused to<lb/> disbelieve his version in the examination in chief. However,<lb/> fact remains that, though the prosecution has named as<lb/> many as 39 accused. He has not named all 39 accused in<lb/> his evidence. In his cross examination in para No.10, he<lb/> has stated that, Komal Maruti Pawar has no concerned with<lb/> the incident in question. He has specifically stated that, the<lb/> names of the accused mentioned in para No.10 of his cross<lb/> examination have no concerned with the incident.<lb/> Therefore, upon considering the evidence of PW<lb/> 16 complainant, we find that, his evidence is fully<lb/> trustworthy, reliable, truthful and not shaken in the cross<lb/> examination. His evidence on all points -aspects is truthful<lb/> and deserves acceptance.<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 92<lb/> 50]<lb/> The learned counsel Mr. Joydeep Chatterji<lb/> appearing for the accused Nos.1 Shivaji, accused No.11<lb/> Vilas and accused No.13 Namdeo, submitted that, so far<lb/> Namdeo is concerned, his name is not mentioned in the<lb/> First Information Report, and he deserves to be given benefit<lb/> of doubt, cannot be accepted. The First Information Report<lb/> is not an encyclopedia. In his evidence before the Court,<lb/> PW16 has named Namdeo and also specific overt act is<lb/> attributed to him. It appears that, he was one of the main<lb/> assailant, who inflicted blows by sword on the deceased<lb/> Gyandeo and also other injured persons.<lb/> 51]<lb/> The prosecution witness Nos.22 to 26 are<lb/> injured witnesses. Their evidence assumes significance<lb/> inasmuch as some of them have sustained grievous injuries,<lb/> which would have caused their death, if timely treatment<lb/> would not have been given to them.<lb/> 52]<lb/> There are in all eleven eye witnesses to the<lb/> incident who are examined by the prosecution. We have<lb/> already discussed in detail about the evidence. Of P.W.16 -<lb/>::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/></figure>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 93<lb/> complainant. As per the prosecution case, all the eye<lb/> witnesses sustained injuries. However, in case of some<lb/> witnesses, injuries were not visible. So far as P.W.22 to 26<lb/> are concerned, they are injured eye witnesses.<lb/></figure>

			<head>53]<lb/></head>

			<p>Vijykumar Bhagwantrao Pawar was examined<lb/> as P.W.25, whose evidence is at Exh.284. This is the<lb/> witness in whose evidence, there are no omissions,<lb/> contradictions or improvements; therefore, we propose to<lb/> discuss his evidence at this juncture.<lb/></p>

			<p>In his examinationinchief, he stated that the<lb/> complainant is his real brother. Deceased Gyandeo was son<lb/> of the complainant Baburao. The incident took place on 9 th<lb/> January, 2008 in the house of Baburao. On that day, in the<lb/> house of Baburao, he himself, Shahuraj Pawar, Sheshrao<lb/></p>

			<head>414.11crapl<lb/> 94<lb/></head>

			<p>Pawar were present. On that day, there was dinner at the<lb/> house of the complainant on the eve of &apos;Vel Amwasaya&apos; and<lb/> the above persons were present for dinner. The witness<lb/> stated that at about 7 to 7.15 p.m., they had sat for dinner<lb/> in room of tins. At that time about 30 to 40 persons all of a<lb/> sudden came in the door of the house, saying that, &quot;Marto,<lb/> Hanto, Todto&quot;. Persons from the mob were pelting stones.<lb/></p>

			<p>Then the mob came in their court yard.<lb/></p>

			<p>Mob was<lb/> comprising of 30 to 40 persons.<lb/> On hearing shouts,<lb/> Gyandeo came outside frist of all, and the witness followed<lb/></p>

			<figure>him. Other persons in their house also came in the court<lb/> yard. Satish Vaijinath Pawar, Tukaram Shivaji Pawar,<lb/> Udhav Shivaji Pawar caught hold Gyandeo; and at that<lb/> time, Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on the left chest of<lb/> Gyandeo. Vimalbai Pawar amongst mob inflicted knife blow<lb/> on the ribs of Gyandeo.<lb/> Dayanand Bhingole inflicted<lb/> sword blow on the back of Gyandeo. Madhav Shivaji Pawar<lb/> inflicted sword blow on the stomach of Gyandeo. Namdeo<lb/> Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow above the navel of<lb/> Gyandeo. Then Gyandeo fell down due to sustaining of<lb/> bleeding injuries. Satish Pawar, Vaijinath Pawar, Venkat<lb/> Vaijinath Pawar caught hold this witness P.W.25. Madhav<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 95<lb/> Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on his face, due to which<lb/> he sustained bleeding injury on his nose. Madhav then<lb/> inflicted sword blow above his navel.<lb/> Namdeo Pawar<lb/> inflicted sword blow on right thigh, Vilas Pawar inflicted<lb/> stick blow on his head. Udhav Pawar inflicted iron blow on<lb/> his left shoulder. Hari Pawar inflicted iron blow on back of<lb/> this witness. He sustained bleeding injuries, his intestines<lb/> were pierced out of his stomach.<lb/> P.W.25 Vijaykumar<lb/> pointed out persons from accused who assaulted him and<lb/> Gyandeo, those persons disclosed their names as Shivaji<lb/> Kadaji Pawar, Vilas Kadaji Pawar, Namdeo Shivaji Pawar,<lb/> Ashok Kadaji Pawar, Satish Baburao Pawar, Satish<lb/> Vaijinath Pawar, Udhav Shivaji Pawar and Vimalbai w/o<lb/> Shivaji Pawar. This witness volunteered that assailants<lb/> Dayanand Maroti Bhingole and Madhav Shivaji Pawar were<lb/> not present on that day in the court hall. He stated that he<lb/> became unconscious at the spot due to assault and<lb/> regained consciousness in the hospital at Latur after four<lb/> days. Then he came to know that injured Gyandeo died. He<lb/> stated that police recorded his statement thrice.<lb/> His<lb/> statement was also recorded by Special Executive Officer.<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 96<lb/> In the crossexamination, P.W.25 Vijaykumar<lb/> stated that accused Madhav Ganpat Shahapure was not<lb/> present on the spot of the incident on that day. So also,<lb/> accused Nos.2, 5 to 10, 15, 16, 19, 21 to 24, 26 to 28, 33<lb/> and 35 were not present at the place of incident at the time<lb/> of incident. He further stated in his crossexamination that<lb/> he knows accused Pandhari Pawar and he had no concern<lb/> with the incident.<lb/> P.W.25 Vijaykumar was further crossexamined<lb/> by Advocate Mr.T.V. Jamdar appearing for some of the<lb/> accused. PW25 specifically admitted that 18 persons who<lb/> are named as accused persons were not present at the time<lb/> of incident. He identified accused persons who participated<lb/> in commission of offence and present before the Court. He<lb/> has stated further details in his crossexamination that<lb/> before the police, he stated that Madhav Shivaji Pawar<lb/> inflicted sword blow on the stomach of Gyandeo and<lb/> Namdeo Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on navel of<lb/> Gyandeo. He further stated that he stated before the police<lb/> that Satish Pawar, Vaijinath Pawar, Venkat Pawar caught<lb/> hold him, Madhav Pawar inflicted sword blow on his face<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 97<lb/> and above his navel and Namdeo Pawar inflicted sword blow<lb/> on his right thigh and Vilas Pawar inflicted stick blow on his<lb/> head and Hari Pawar inflicted iron rod blow on his back. He<lb/> further stated that after Gyandeo, accused assaulted him.<lb/> While Gyandeo was being assaulted, he was caught hold by<lb/> the accused. Then he became unconscious and fell down.<lb/> He stated that in all 16 persons including females were<lb/> present in the house when the accused came at the spot of<lb/> the incident. They could not resist at the time of incident,<lb/> they did not raise shouts.<lb/> 54]<lb/> Upon perusal of the evidence of this witness, it<lb/> appears that he has specifically stated the manner in which<lb/> the accused entered in the house [courtyard], they were<lb/> pelting stones, they were giving slogans, they were armed<lb/> with deadly weapons and also sticks and they came<lb/> prepared so as to assault the persons who were in the house<lb/> of P.W.16 at the relevant time. He has stated the actual<lb/> incident in a specific manner that Satish Vaijinath Pawar,<lb/> Tukaram Shivaji Pawar, Udhav Shivaji Pawar caught hold<lb/> Gyandeo; and at that time, Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword<lb/> blow on the left chest of Gyandeo. Vimalbai Pawar amongst<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 98<lb/> mob inflicted knife blow on the ribs of Gyandeo. Dayanand<lb/> Bhingole inflicted<lb/> sword blow on the back of Gyandeo.<lb/> Madhav Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on the stomach<lb/> of Gyandeo. Namdeo Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow<lb/> above the navel of Gyandeo. Then Gyandeo fell down due to<lb/> sustaining of bleeding injuries. Satish Baburao Pawar,<lb/> Vaijinath Pawar, Venkat Vaijinath Pawar caught hold this<lb/> witness P.W.25. Madhav Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow<lb/> on his face, due to which he sustained bleeding injury on<lb/> his nose. Madhav then inflicted sword blow above his navel.<lb/> Namdeo Pawar inflicted sword blow on right thigh, Vilas<lb/> Pawar inflicted stick blow on his head. Udhav Pawar<lb/> inflicted iron blow on his left shoulder. Hari Pawar inflicted<lb/> iron blow on back of this witness.<lb/> 55]<lb/> It appears from his evidence that he sustained<lb/> bleeding injuries, intestines were pierced out of his<lb/> stomach. He has specifically pointed out accused persons,<lb/> who were present in the court, and identified them, who<lb/> assaulted him and Gyandeo. It appears from the medical<lb/> evidence brought on record by the prosecution and the<lb/> evidence of the Medical Officers P.W.27 Dr.Pralhad Solanke<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 99<lb/> and P.W.28 Dr. Shivanand Biradar supports the version of<lb/> this witness. The version of this witness corresponds with<lb/> the injuries stated in the injury certificate of Gyandeo and<lb/> also other six injured persons. Therefore, the evidence of<lb/> P.W.25 corresponds with the medical evidence.<lb/> His<lb/> evidence is fully trustworthy, reliable, truthful and not<lb/> shaken in any manner in his crossexamination and the<lb/> same can safely be accepted on all the points including<lb/> forming an unlawful assembly by the accused persons, who<lb/> are named in his evidence, in furtherance of their common<lb/> object to assault / cause grievous hurt to the family<lb/> members of the complainant in order to finish every member<lb/> of family of P.W.16 Baburao. The evidence of this witness<lb/> corroborates with the evidence of the complainant in all<lb/> material particulars. The evidence of the complainant and<lb/> also P.W.25 Vijaykumar corroborates each other and also<lb/> gets corroboration from medical evidence led by P.W.27<lb/> Dr.Pralhad Solanke and P.W.28 Dr. Shivanand Biradar.<lb/> 56]<lb/> The learned Counsel for the accused Shivaji<lb/> Kadaji Pawar, Namdeo Shivaji Pawar and Vilas Kadaji Pawar<lb/> was at pains to argue that, in view of the judgment of the<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 100<lb/> Supreme Court in the case of Masalti (supra), where<lb/> factions prevail in villagers and murders are committed as a<lb/> result of enmity between such factions, criminal Courts<lb/> have to deal with evidence of a partisan type. The learned<lb/> Counsel for the accused relied on the observations of the<lb/> Supreme Court in paragraph 16 of the judgment in case of<lb/> Masalti (supra) and argued that where the criminal Court<lb/> has to deal with the evidence pertaining to commission of an<lb/> offence involving a large number of offenders and a large<lb/> number of victims, it is usual to adopt the test that the<lb/> conviction could be sustained only if it is supported by two<lb/> or three or more witnesses who give a consistent account of<lb/> the incident. In a sense, the test may be described as<lb/> mechanical; but it cannot be treated as irrational or<lb/> unreasonable. Therefore, in his submission, in the present<lb/> case, though evidence of P.W.25 Vijaykumar does not suffer<lb/> from omissions, contradictions and improvements, the<lb/> evidence of other prosecution witnesses, including the<lb/> complainant, suffers from contradictions, omissions and<lb/> improvements and, therefore, the evidence of P.W.25<lb/> Vijaykumar alone is not sufficient so as to sustain the<lb/> conviction of the accused.<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 101<lb/> 57]<lb/> As<lb/> already<lb/> observed,<lb/> evidence<lb/> of<lb/> the<lb/> complainant P.W.16 Baburao and P.W.25 Vijaykumar<lb/> corroborates<lb/> with each other and lends support from<lb/> medical evidence and therefore,the evidence of the P.W.16<lb/> Baburao complainant and also the P.W.25 Vijaykumar is<lb/> fully trustworthy, reliable, truthful and has not been<lb/> shaken, in any manner, in the crossexamination. There is<lb/> also evidence of other nine eye witnesses.<lb/> 58]<lb/> The prosecution examined Shahuraj Baburao<lb/> Pawar as PW22, his evidence is at Exhibit278. In his<lb/> examination in chief, he stated that, complainant Baburao<lb/> is his father. Varsha is his wife. She is acting as Sarpanch<lb/> of the village. Election of the Gram Panchayat was held in<lb/> the Year 2007, between two panels headed by his father and<lb/> another by Shivaji Pawar. Panel of his father was elected in<lb/> the election. On the day of result of election, Shivaji Pawar<lb/> and his persons assaulted persons from rival group. They<lb/> filed application in that respect with the Police Station. One<lb/> and half month thereafter on 23.11.2007 election for<lb/> Sarpanch was scheduled. On that day, in the election of<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 102<lb/> Sarpanch, Shivaji Pawar and his persons obstructed.<lb/> Therefore, complainant&apos;s group filed application with<lb/> Tahsildar. On 24.11.2007, Tahsildar conducted election for<lb/> the post of Sarpanch in Police Bandobast, and in that<lb/> election, his wife was elected as Sarpanch. Since then there<lb/> are strained relations between complainant&apos;s group and<lb/> group of Shivaji Pawar. Persons from the side of Shivaji<lb/> Pawar used to threat to kill the complainant&apos;s persons and<lb/> they will not allow to conduct the work. He further stated<lb/> that, deceased Gyandeo was his real brother. Incident<lb/> occurred on 09.01.2008. It was next day of Vel Amawasya.<lb/> Dinner of Chicken Mutton was arranged at his house. On<lb/> that day, Chandrakant Bhagwantrao Solanke, r/o.<lb/> Chandori, Maroti s/o. Dhanaji Jadhav, r/o. Sawangira and<lb/> villagers Anant Pawar, Waman Limbaji Pawar, Tatyarao<lb/> Balaji Bhingole were invited for the dinner. Uncles and<lb/> other family members were also present. At about 7.00<lb/> p.m., they were about to sit for dinner. At that time, all of<lb/> sudden, noise was heard from outside. Mob came there<lb/> saying &apos;Babya, Vijya, Gyana come outside. They were saved<lb/> on the day of election. Now they are to be seen. Their<lb/> heritage will not be saved&apos;. About 30 to 40 persons in the<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 103<lb/> mob came at their house. Persons in the mob were holding<lb/> swords, sticks and iron rods. They all came from inside in<lb/> the courtyard. Gyandeo, Vijaykumar, PW22, Sheshrao,<lb/> Bhagwat, Dilip, Baburao, Waman Pawar, Anant Pawar,<lb/> Tatyarao Bhingole, Chandrakant Solanke, Maroti Jadhav,<lb/> Varsha Pawar, Babita, Santosi, Popatbai, Mahdeo Pawar<lb/> came in the courtyard. Gyandeo was caught hold by Satish<lb/> Vaijinath Pawar, Udhav Shivaji Pawar, Tukaram Shivaji<lb/> Pawar, Shivaji Kadaji Pawar inflicted sword blow in the left<lb/> chest of Gyandeo. He further stated that, Madhav Shivaji<lb/> inflicted on the right side stomach of Gyandeo by Jambiya.<lb/> Namdeo Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on above the<lb/> navel of Gyandeo. Vimalbai Pawar inflicted knife blow on<lb/> the left ribs of Gyandeo by katti. Dayanand Maroti Bhingole<lb/> inflicted sword blow on the back of Gyandeo. Gyandeo<lb/> sustained bleeding injuries and fell down.<lb/> Thereafter,<lb/> Shivaji Kadaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on the waist right<lb/> side of PW22. Vilas Pawar beat him by stick on left<lb/> shoulder and stomach. Prakash Kadaji Pawar gave iron rod<lb/> blow on right side waist of PW22. PW22 also sustained<lb/> bleeding injury.<lb/> Thereafter, Vijaykumar, Sheshrao,<lb/> Bhagwat, Sanjya, Baburao and female members were also<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 104<lb/> assaulted by persons from the mob with weapons in their<lb/> hands.<lb/> Vijaykumar, Sheshrao, Sanjay, Bhagwat also<lb/> sustained bleeding injuries. Then the injured were admitted<lb/> in Nilanga Hospital. Vijaykumar, Sanjay and he himself<lb/> were referred to Latur Hospital for further treatment. They<lb/> learnt at Latur that, Gyandeo is dead. Police recorded his<lb/> statement twice. [Emphasis supplied].<lb/> 59]<lb/> He was cross examined by Advocate Shri<lb/> T.V.Jamdar. He stated that, post of Sarpanch was reserved<lb/> for woman. In Gram Panchayat elections, in all 3 women<lb/> were elected. Sushilabai Gaikwad, Usha Dinkar Katekar<lb/> and his wife were elected. He has specifically denied the<lb/> suggestion that, there was no panel headed by Shivaji in the<lb/> said election. This witness stated in his examination in<lb/> cross that, he was taken to the Hospital at Nilanga for<lb/> treatment. He received first blow by stick on left shoulder<lb/> and last blow by sword on the back. Upon perusal of his<lb/> evidence in cross examination, nothing useful to the defence<lb/> have been elicited.<lb/> 60.<lb/> The learned counsel Mr. Joydeep Chatterji<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 105<lb/> appearing for the accused Shivaji, Namdeo and Vilas invited<lb/> our attention to the portion marked &apos;A&apos;, &apos;B&apos; and &apos;C&apos; from the<lb/> statement of this witness under Section 161 of I.P. Code and<lb/> submitted that, this witness in the police station has not<lb/> named Namdeo or no overt act is attributed to him, and<lb/> therefore, Namdeo is entitled for benefit of doubt. In our<lb/> opinion, he has specifically stated in his examination in<lb/> chief that, Namdeo Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on<lb/> above the navel of Gyandeo. Aforesaid version about<lb/> Namdeo gets corroboration from the evidence of other<lb/> prosecution witnesses and also from the medical evidence,<lb/> and therefore, contention of the learned Counsel Mr.<lb/></figure>

			<p>Chatterji cannot be accepted that accused Namdeo deserves<lb/> to be acquitted.<lb/></p>

			<head>61]<lb/></head>

			<p>The prosecution has examined Bhagwat<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">Vijaykumar Pawar as PW23. His evidence is at Exhibit<lb/> 279. In his examination in chief, he stated that, deceased<lb/> Gyandeo was his cousin. Incident took place on 09.01.2008<lb/> at about 7.15 p.m. at his house in the courtyard. It was<lb/> next day of Vel Amawasya. On that day, Chandrakant<lb/> Solanke, r/o. Chandori, Maroti Dhanaji Jadhav, r/o.<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/></figure>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 106<lb/> Sawangira and villagers Waman Pawar, Anant Pawar,<lb/> Tatyarao Bhingole were invited for dinner at his house. He<lb/> further stated that, while they were about to sit for dinner,<lb/> mob of 30 to 40 persons came towards his house while<lb/> abusing and saying &apos;Babya, Gyana, Vijya. Heritage from<lb/> their house will not be saved. Mob came in the courtyard<lb/> with weapons. He further stated that, first of all Gyandeo<lb/> came from out of house. They others followed Gyandeo.<lb/> Gyandeo Pawar was caught hold by Satish Vaijinath Pawar,<lb/> Tukaram Shivaji Pawar and Udhav Shivaji Pawar, and<lb/> Shivaji Pawar pierced sword on the left chest of Gyandeo.<lb/> Vimal Pawar assaulted Gyandeo by knife on ribs left side.<lb/> Dayanand Bhingole inflicted sword blow on the left side<lb/> back of Gyandeo. Mahadeo Pawar inflicted Jamibya blow<lb/> on right side stomach of Gyandeo. Namdeo Pawar inflicted<lb/> sword blow above the navel of Gyandeo. Due to assault,<lb/> Gyandeo sustained bleeding injuries and Gyandeo fell down.<lb/> He then went to rescue Gyandeo. Devidas Pawar inflicted<lb/> stick blow on his head. He sustained bleeding head injury.<lb/> He moved aside. He further stated that, thereafter, 15 to 16<lb/> persons from the mob assaulted by sword, stick, iron rod to<lb/> Vijaykumar, Shahuraj, Sanjay, Sheshrao and others from<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 107<lb/> his house, guests, Vijaykumar, Shahuraj, Sheshrao, Sanjay<lb/> also sustained bleeding injuries. He himself and other<lb/> injured were taken to Nilanga Hospital.<lb/> He himself,<lb/> Gyandeo and Sheshrao were admitted in Nilanga Hospital.<lb/> He further stated that, other injured were referred to Latur<lb/> Hospital for further treatment. On the next day morning, he<lb/> learnt at Nilanga that, Gyandeo is dead. Police recorded his<lb/> statement.<lb/> He was cross examined by Advocate Shri T.V.<lb/> Jamdar on behalf of the some of the accused. In his cross<lb/> examination nothing useful to the defence has been brought<lb/> on record by the defence.<lb/> 62]<lb/> The prosecution has examined Sheshrao<lb/> Baburao Pawar as PW24. His evidence is at Exhibit280.<lb/> In his examination in chief, he stated that, deceased<lb/> Gyandeo was his real brother. Incident took place prior to 3<lb/> years.<lb/> It was next day of Vel Amawasya. On that day,<lb/> Chandrakant Solanke, Dhanaji Jadhav, Waman Pawar,<lb/> Anant Pawar, Tatyarao Bhingole had come to his house for<lb/> dinner. Incident occurred at 7.00 to 7.15 p.m. They were<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 108<lb/> about to sit for dinner. At that time, they heard noise of<lb/> abusing of the mob. Mob came in his courtyard and<lb/> persons from the mob pelted stone. Some persons from the<lb/> mob were holding sticks, iron rods, swords, Jambiya,<lb/> Gyandeo and Vijaykumar came out of house in the<lb/> courtyard. He further stated that, others followed them in<lb/> the courtyard. Satish Vaijinath Pawar, Tukaram Pawar and<lb/> Udhav Pawar caught hold Gyandeo, and Shivaji Pawar<lb/> pierced sword in the chest of Gyandeo. Namdeo Pawar<lb/> inflicted Jambiya blow near the navel on left side of<lb/> Gyandeo. Vimalbai inflicted knife blow on the ribs of<lb/> Gyandeo. Madhav Shivaji inflicted Jamibya like sword on<lb/> the ribs of Gyandeo. Dayanand Bhingole inflicted sword<lb/> blow on the back of Gyandeo. Gyandeo sustained bleeding<lb/> injuries due to assault and Gyandeo fell down. He further<lb/> stated that, Shivaji Pawar inflicted 3 blows by sword on his<lb/> left hand wrist. Ashok Pawar inflicted katti blow on left leg.<lb/> About 16 to 17 persons in the mob assaulted Vijaykumar,<lb/> Bhagwat, Shahuraj, Baburao, Dilip, Sanjay.<lb/> Sanjay,<lb/> Shahuraj, Vijaykumar, Bhagwat also sustained bleeding<lb/> injuries. Then the injured were taken to Nilanga Hospital<lb/> for treatment. He himself, Bhagwat and Gyandeo were<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 109<lb/> retained in Nilanga Hospital. He further stated that, other<lb/> injured were referred to Latur Hospital for further<lb/> treatment. On the next day morning, Doctor informed them<lb/> that, Gyandeo is dead. Police recorded his statement.<lb/></figure>

			<p>He was cross examined by Advocate Shri<lb/> T.V.Jamdar. Relying upon his statement that, the portion<lb/> marked &apos;A&apos; read over to him, during his cross examination<lb/> was not stated before the Police. The learned counsel Mr.<lb/></p>

			<p>Chatterji submitted that, when he did not state before the<lb/> Police that, Shivaji actually assaulted by sword on chest and<lb/> when this witness further stated that, he has not named<lb/> Namdeo, both of them are entitled for benefit of doubt. As<lb/> already observed, there is overwhelming evidence led by the<lb/> prosecution in the nature of 11 eye witnesses before the<lb/> Court naming accused Shivaji, Namdeo and also Vilas and<lb/> attributing specific role to them and also there are<lb/> corresponding injuries. The evidence of PW25 remained<lb/> unshaken and gets corroboration from the evidence of other<lb/> eye witnesses, and also from the medical evidence, and<lb/> therefore, the contention of Advocate Shri Chatterji stands<lb/> rejected.<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on 18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 110<lb/> 63]<lb/> The prosecution has examined Sanjay Baburao<lb/> Pawar as PW26. His evidence is at Exhibit286. In his<lb/> examination in chief, he stated that, complainant Baburao<lb/> is his father. Deceased Gyandeo was his real brother.<lb/> Incident took place on 09.01.2008 in the courtyard. At that<lb/> time, guests Chandrakant Solanke, r/o. Chandori, Maroti<lb/> Jadhav r/o. Sawangira, villagers Anant Pawar, Tatyarao<lb/> Bhingole, Waman Pawar and he himself, Baburao,<lb/> Shahuraj, Sheshrao, Bhagwat, Dilip, Vijaykumar, Varsha,<lb/> Babita, Santoshi, Anuradha, Urmila, Popatbai were present<lb/> in his house. On that day, there was dinner arranged at his<lb/> house on account of next day of Vel Amawasya. He further<lb/> stated that, at about 7.00 to 7.15 p.m., they were about to<lb/> sit for dinner. At that time, electric light was on. From the<lb/> road in front of house, they heard shouts relating to abuses,<lb/> &apos;Babya, Vijya, Gyana, Shahuraj, Gotya, Sheshrao, Sanjya,<lb/> come out side. Mob was pelting stones on his house. Then<lb/> mob came in his courtyard. He further stated that, then<lb/> they came outside from the house. Gyandeo came out of<lb/> house first of all. Satish Vaijinath Pawar, Tukaram Shivaji<lb/> Pawar and Udhav Shivaji Pawar caught hold Gyandeo.<lb/></figure>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 111<lb/> Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on the left chest of<lb/> Gyandeo. Vimalbai inflicted knife blow on left ribs of<lb/> Gyandeo. Dayanand Maroti Bhingole inflicted sword blow<lb/> on the back of Gyandeo. Madhav Shivaji Pawar inflicted<lb/> blow on right side stomach of Gyandeo by sword. He again<lb/> say that, it was Jambiya like sword. Namdeo Shivaji Pawar<lb/> inflicted sword blow near navel of Gyandeo. He further<lb/> stated that, Gyandeo sustained bleeding injuries and<lb/> Gyandeo fell down. He went near Gyandeo. Madhav Shivaji<lb/> Pawar assaulted him Jambiya like sword on the right side<lb/> waist. His intestines were came out. He fell down on the<lb/> earth.<lb/> Other accused persons were assaulting other<lb/> persons in the house. Persons who assaulted him and<lb/> Gyandeo are the same, who are now present in the<lb/> courtyard. Witness<lb/> pointed out the accused and they<lb/> disclosed their names Satish Vaijinath Pawar, Tukaram<lb/> Shivaji Pawar, Udhav Shivaji Pawar, Shivaji Kadaji Pawar,<lb/> Vimalbai Shivaji Pawar, Namdeo Shivaji Pawar.<lb/> Other<lb/> assailants Madhav Shivaji Pawar and Dayanand Maroti<lb/> Bhingole are not present in the court hall. Injured were<lb/> then taken in Nilanga Hospital. He regained consciousness<lb/> after four days in Latur Hospital. Police recorded his<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 112<lb/> statement.<lb/> Special Executive Officer also recorded his<lb/> statement.<lb/> He was cross examined by Advocate Mr.<lb/> T.V.Jamdar on behalf of some of the accused. In his cross<lb/> examination, he stated that, he had stated before the Police<lb/> that, Satish Vaijinath Pawar, Tukaram Shivaji Pawar,<lb/> Udhav Shivaji Pawar had caught hold Gyandeo and then<lb/> Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on the stomach of<lb/> Gyandeo, he cannot assign any reason why the police has<lb/> not recorded in his statement. In his statement under<lb/> Section 161 before the Police he narrated that, Madhav<lb/> Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on the right side stomach<lb/> of Gyandeo, Namdeo Shivaji Pawar had inflicted sword blow<lb/> near navel of Gyandeo and Madhav Shivaji Pawar assaulted<lb/> him by Jambiya like sword on the right side waist. However,<lb/> he cannot assign any reason why above facts are not<lb/> recorded by police in his statement. Relying upon the<lb/> portion marked &apos;A&apos; and &apos;B&apos; from his evidence, it was tried to<lb/> be canvassed that, his evidence suffers from omissions and<lb/> contradictions. However, in our opinion, the said argument<lb/> deserves no consideration. This witness is injured witness<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 113<lb/> and sustained grievous injuries. Evidence of other eye<lb/> witness and medical evidence corroborates his version.<lb/> 64]<lb/> P.W.17 Chandrakant Bhagwantrao Solanke was<lb/> examined by the prosecution, who was an eye witness of the<lb/> incident. His evidence is at Exh.267. In his examination<lb/> inchief, he stated that the complainant Baburao Pawar is<lb/> his maternal uncle. The incident occurred on 9.1.2008. On<lb/> the date of incident, he had been to the house of his<lb/> maternal uncle Baburao for dinner. He has named the<lb/> persons who had gathered in the house of Baburao for<lb/> dinner. He has further narrated details about the elections<lb/> of Gram Panchayat, which took place in the said village. He<lb/> has stated further details about whose panel got elected and<lb/> at the time of election of Sarpanch, there was dispute<lb/> between the groups of complainant and accused Shivaji.<lb/> He further deposed that on 9 th January, 2008 in<lb/> the night in all ten persons had sat at the house of the<lb/> complainant for dinner. It was about 7 p.m. They heard<lb/> shouts from the outside to the effect that &quot;Babya, Gayna,<lb/> Vijya, Sanjya,<lb/> Yanchya<lb/> Gharanyache<lb/> purna<lb/> Beej<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 114<lb/> Budwayache Ahe.&quot;<lb/> (i.e. Everybody from the families of<lb/> Babya, Gayna, Vijya, Sanjya, has to be finished). At that<lb/> time, stone pelting started at the house of the complainant.<lb/> Then, in the courtyard of Baburao, accused Shivaji Pawar<lb/> and other came.<lb/> Then the witness himself, Gyandeo,<lb/> Vijaykumar,Sanjay,<lb/> Shahuraj,<lb/> Shesherao,<lb/> Bhagwat,<lb/> Baburao, Maroti, Waman, Anant, Dilip, Varsha, Anuradha,<lb/> Santoshi, Babita, Urmila, Popat came outside in the court<lb/> yard. Gyandeo went ahead. At that time, Satish Vaijinath<lb/> Pawar, Tukaram Shivaji Pawar and Udhav Shivaji Pawar<lb/> caught hold Gyandeo.<lb/> Accused Shivaji Pawar inflicted<lb/> sword blow on the chest of Gyandeo. Namdeo Shivaji Pawar<lb/> inflicted sword blow on the stomach of Gyandeo. Mahadeo<lb/> Shivaji Pawar inflicted blow by Jambiya like sword on the<lb/> right side stomach of Gyandeo. Dayanand Maroti Bhingole<lb/> inflicted sword blow on the back of Gyandeo. Accused<lb/> Vimalbai Shivaji Pawar inflicted knife blow on the back of<lb/> Gyandeo. Gyandeo fell down due to oozing of blood from his<lb/> injuries. P.W.17 Chandrakant Solanke further deposed<lb/> that, then Namdeo Shivaji Pawar assaulted Vijaykumar by<lb/> sword on right side stomach.<lb/> Mahadeo Shivaji Pawar<lb/> assaulted Vijaykumar on the stomach by Jambiya like<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 115<lb/> sword. Vilas Kadaji Pawar assaulted Vijaykumar by stick<lb/> on the back. Udhav Shivaji Pawar assaulted Vijaykumar by<lb/> iron rod on right shoulder. Haridas Manik Pawar assaulted<lb/> Vijaykumar by iron rod on the backside at lower portion.<lb/> Due to assault, Vijaykumar fell down and his intestine had<lb/> come out. Mahadeo Shivaji Pawar assaulted Sanjay by<lb/> Jambiya like sword on right side of abdomen. Shivaji Kadaji<lb/> Pawar assaulted Shesherao on left hand by 3 blows with<lb/> sword. Ashok Kadaji Pawar assaulted Sheshrao by Katti on<lb/> left leg shin. Shivaji Kadaji Pawar assaulted Shahuraj by<lb/> sword on the waist at right side back. Prakash Kadaji<lb/> Pawar assaulted Shahuraj by iron rod on the back. Devidas<lb/> Pralhad Pawar assaulted Bhagwat by stick on the head.<lb/> Prakash Pawar assaulted him by iron rod on the back.<lb/> Waman Dadarao Pawar assaulted complainant Baburao by<lb/> stick on the back. Remaining persons assaulted the female<lb/> members from the side of complainant.<lb/> 65]<lb/> He further stated that the injured were taken by<lb/> him and Baburao Pawar and other relatives to the Nilanga<lb/> Hospital. Doctor advised to shift Vijaykumar, Sanjay and<lb/> Shahuraj to Latur for further treatment. Accordingly, they<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 116<lb/> were taken tot he Hospital at Latur. They came to know in<lb/> the hospital at Latur that injured Gyandeo died during<lb/> treatment at Nilanga Hospital. Accordingly, his statement<lb/> was recorded on the next day of the incident.<lb/> This witness was crossexamined by the<lb/> Advocate of Accused Nos.2, 5 to 10, 15, 16, 19, 21 to 24, 26<lb/> to 28, 33 and 35. During his crossexamination by the<lb/> Advocate of aforesaid accused, he stated that accused<lb/> Komalbai Maroti Pawar has no concern with the incident.<lb/> He was further crossexamined on behalf of the accused<lb/> Nos.3, 14 and 29 wherein he stated that Haridas Manik<lb/> Pawar is known to him. There were 30 to 40 persons in the<lb/> mob. He specifically denied the suggestion that he was not<lb/> present at the time of the incident. He was further cross<lb/> examined on behalf of accused Nos.1,4,11 to 13, 17, 18, 20,<lb/> 25, 30 to 32 and 34. The defence tried to elucidate from his<lb/> crossexamination that he did not identify all the accused.<lb/> It is true that in his crossexamination, this witness stated<lb/> that out of 37 accused persons, he identified 10 to 12<lb/> persons on the day of the incident and remaining persons<lb/> were unknown to him and he could not identify those<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 117<lb/> accused who were pelting stones.<lb/> He has reiterated his<lb/> assertion in his examinationinchief about the manner in<lb/> which the accused came to the house of Baburao, giving<lb/> slogans with deadly weapons, fully prepared and formed an<lb/> unlawful assembly with an object to cause grievous hurt in<lb/> order to finish the entire family of the complainant Baburao.<lb/></figure>

			<p>His evidence in the examinationinchief is not shattered in<lb/> his crossexamination, in any manner.<lb/></p>

			<head>66]<lb/></head>

			<p>The learned Counsel Mr.Chatterji appearing for<lb/> the accused Shivaji Kadaji Pawar, Namdeo Shivaji Pawar<lb/> and Vilas Kadaji Pawar criticized the evidence of P.W.17<lb/></p>

			<p>Chandrakant Solanke on the ground that there are<lb/> contradictions in his evidence inasmuch as, the manner in<lb/> which he stated overtacts of the accused, has no<lb/> corroboration from the other evidence. He invited our<lb/> attention to the portion marked as &quot;A&quot; from his police<lb/> statement and submitted that accused Namdeo is not<lb/> named by him in his police statement.<lb/></p>

			<p>Upon appreciating the evidence of P.W.17<lb/></p>

			<p>Chandrakant in its entirety, as already observed, his<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 118<lb/> evidence remained unshaken.<lb/> It appears from his<lb/> statement that, police have narrated his version in the<lb/> police statement u/s 161 of Cr.P.C. not in the manner in<lb/> which he stated about the incident and, therefore, portion<lb/> marked in his police statement cannot be considered as an<lb/> omission. His substantive evidence before the court gets<lb/> corroboration from the evidence of complainant and also<lb/> from the evidence of P.W.25 Vijaykumar and all other eye<lb/> witnesses to the incident, coupled with medical evidence<lb/> and therefore, in our opinion, there is no substance in the<lb/> contention of the learned Counsel appearing for the accused<lb/> Namdeo that, Namdeo could have been given benefit of<lb/> doubt since this witness has not named Namdeo Shivaji<lb/> Pawar and not attributed any overtacts in his police<lb/> statement.<lb/> Therefore, evidence of P.W.17 Chandrakant<lb/> Solanke on all aspects is reliable, trustworthy and truthful.<lb/> 67]<lb/> Prosecution has examined Dilip Bhagwanrao<lb/> Pawar as PW18 who is an eye witness. His evidence is<lb/> at Exhibit -269. In his examination in chief, he stated<lb/> that, he is brother of the complainant Baburao. They all<lb/> are three brothers. Vijaykumar is their third brother.<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/></figure>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 119<lb/> They reside separately in one Wada. Their tinsheet<lb/> rooms are adjoining to each other. Incident occurred on<lb/> 09.01.2008 at about 7.15 p.m. On that day, there was<lb/> Mutton dinner arrangement on account of next day of<lb/> Vel Amawasya at the house of complainant Baburao.<lb/> For dinner, guests Chandrakant Solanke, Maroti<lb/> Dhanaji Jadhav and guest from village Tatyarao<lb/> Bhingole, Waman Pawar and Anant Pawar were invited.<lb/> He himself and Vijaykumar, Bhagwat were also invited<lb/> for dinner. Varsha Pawar is daughterinlaw of the<lb/> complainant Baburao. She was elected as Sarpanch of<lb/> the village. There was dispute between the panels<lb/> headed by complainant and accused Shivaji on account<lb/> of elections. The said election took place in the year<lb/> 2007. In the election, 4 members from the panel of<lb/> complainant Baburao were elected. He further stated<lb/> that, on 09.01.2008, they (aforementioned persons)<lb/> were taking dinner at the house of complainant<lb/> Baburao. At that time, all of sudden they heard noise of<lb/> abuses. Then stone pelting took place from outside on<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 120<lb/> the house of Baburao. Then in the court yard of<lb/> Baburao mob of 30 to 40 persons came. Then this<lb/> witness, Gyandeo, Shahuraj, Sheshrao, Sanjay,<lb/> Vijaykumar, Bhagwat, Baburao, Chandrakant, Maroti,<lb/> Tatyarao, Anant came outside in the courtyard.<lb/> Gyandeo went ahead. Satish Pawar, Tukaram Shivaji<lb/> Pawar and Udhav Shivaji Pawar caught hold Gyandeo.<lb/> Accused Shivaji Kadaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on<lb/> the chest of Gyandeo. Vimalbai Shivaji inflicted left side<lb/> ribs on Gyandeo by knife. Namdeo Shivaji Pawar<lb/> inflicted sword blow on the stomach of Gyandeo.<lb/> Dayanand Bhingole inflicted sword blow on the back<lb/> left side of Gyandeo. Mahadeo Shivaji Pawar inflicted<lb/> blow by Jambiya like sword on the right side abdomen<lb/> of Gyandeo. Gyandeo sustained bleeding injuries and<lb/> he collapsed. Madhav Shivaji Pawar assaulted<lb/> Vijaykumar by Jambiya like sword two blows on the<lb/> stomach and single blow on the face. Namdeo Pawar<lb/> inflicted sword blow on right leg. Udhav Shivaji Pawar<lb/> assaulted Vijaykumar by iron rod on right shoulder. He<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 121<lb/> further stated that, Vilas Kadaji Pawar assaulted<lb/> Vijaykumar by stick on the back. Haridas Manik Pawar<lb/> assaulted Vijaykumar by iron rod on the back. Madhav<lb/> Shivaji Pawar assaulted Sanjay by Jambiya like sword<lb/> on right side abdomen. Vilas Kadaji Pawar assaulted<lb/> Shahuraj by stick on left shoulder. Prakash Kadaji<lb/> Pawar assaulted Shahurao by sword on the right side<lb/> back. Ashok Kadaji Pawar assautled Sheshrao by Katti<lb/> on right leg shin. Shivaji Kadaji Pawar inflicted 3 blows<lb/> by sword on left hand of Sheshrao. Devidas Pralhad<lb/> Pawar assaulted Bhagwat by stick on the head.<lb/> Remaining persons assaulted female members of the<lb/> complainant. He identified the assailants Shivaji Kadaji<lb/> Pawar, Vilas Kadaji Pawar, Namdeo Shivaji Pawar,<lb/> Ashok Kadaji Pawar, Vimalbai, Udhav, Devidas,<lb/> Tukaram, Satish. Injured were admitted in Nilanga<lb/> Hospital for treatment. This witness was accompanying<lb/> them. He further stated that, in Nilanga Hospital,<lb/> Gyandeo, Sheshrao and Bhagwat were treated.<lb/> Vijaykumar, Shahuraj and Sanjay were referred by the<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 122<lb/> doctor to Latur Hospital. Accordingly, they carried them<lb/> to Latur Hospital and admitted them there. Baburao<lb/> and other guests were with him while going to Latur. At<lb/> Latur they came to know that, Gyandeo died at Nilanga<lb/> during the course of treatment. He identified the<lb/> weapons used by the accused before the Court. He<lb/> stated that, those weapons are at Article Nos. 1, 35, 39,<lb/> 37, 36, 8, 9, 7, 10, 11, 2, 48.<lb/> He was cross examined by Advocate Mr.<lb/> M.B. Jadhav on behalf of accused nos. 2, 5 to 10, 15,<lb/> 16, 19, 21 to 24, 26 to 28, 33 and 35. In his cross<lb/> examination, he stated that, accused Vishwanath<lb/> Vithal Pawar is 80 years old. He was the Chairman of<lb/> Jamga Society for 25 years and elected unopposed and<lb/> thereafter he retired from politics. Accused Pandurang<lb/> Pawar is in service since 1987 in Maharashtra<lb/> Pharmacy College, Nilanga as StoreKeeper. He resides<lb/> at Nilanga along with his family. He had a son Umesh<lb/> who is mentally retarded. Ashok S/o Vishvanath Pawar<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 123<lb/> is in Police Department service since 1980 and he was<lb/> at Solapur till 2007. Accused Satyanarayan Madhav<lb/> Shahapure is student for M.Sc. Softwear Engineering<lb/> since 5 to 7 years. Manik Ramji Pawar runs grocery<lb/> shop and also does agriculture at village Jamga. His<lb/> house is at a distance of 700 to 800 ft. from his house.<lb/> On the day of incident, Komalbai Maroti Pawar along<lb/> with her husband and brotherinlaw Vishnu Madhav<lb/> Pawar had gone to village Bhutmugali due to death of<lb/> her uncle. He stated that, accused nos.2, 5 to 10, 15,<lb/> 16, 19, 21 to 24, 26 to 28, 33 and 35 have no concern<lb/> with the incident in question. Dhondiram Raosaheb<lb/> Pawar is a Teacher since 1991 in Zilla Parishad, and<lb/> since 1999 he is serving at Lambota. He resides at<lb/> Nilanga. Govind Ganpatrao Shahapure is also Teacher<lb/> in Zilla Parishad since 1992. Bhagyashri D/o Vinayak<lb/> Pawar is married with Manoj Mule. On the day of<lb/> incident, Vinayak Raosaheb Pawar had gone to the<lb/> hospital to see his daughter in Jyoti Hospital at Latur,<lb/> whose abortion was carried there.<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 124<lb/> 68]<lb/> He was further crossexamined by Mr. V.S.<lb/> Gaikwad, the learned counsel on behalf of accused<lb/> nos. 3, 14 and 29. In his cross examination, he stated<lb/> that, complainant Baburao is his real brother. Accused<lb/> Pandhari Manik Pawar has no concern with the<lb/> incident. He did not see him at the time of incident.<lb/> Haridas Pawar assaulted Vijaykumar by iron rod. He<lb/> did not assault this witness. He has specifically denied<lb/> the suggestion that, Haridas Pawar was not present at<lb/> the time of incident and he did not assault Vijaykumar<lb/> by iron rod. He has specifically denied suggestion that,<lb/> Haridas Pawar and Waman Pawar were not present and<lb/> they did not assault anybody.<lb/> 69]<lb/> He was further crossexamined by Advocate<lb/> Mr. T.V. Jamdar on behalf of accused nos. <ref type="biblio">1, 4, 11 to<lb/> 13, 17, 18, 20, 25, 30</ref></p>

 to 32 and 34. He stated in his<lb/> cross examination that, he did not state before police<lb/> the portion marked A read over to him from his<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/></figure>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 125<lb/> statement. He further stated that, he cannot assign any<lb/> reason why police recorded so in his statement. He<lb/> further stated that, he did not state the portion mark B<lb/> read over to him before the Police. However, in para 6 of<lb/> the crossexamination, he has again reiterated his<lb/> version about the accused, who actually participated in<lb/> the commission of offence and also the manner in<lb/> which they inflicted injuries on deceased Gyandeo and<lb/> other witnesses. He has given minute details in para 6<lb/> of his examination in cross. He has specifically stated<lb/> that, Gyandeo had sustained three blows, one blow by<lb/> Jambiya like sword and one blow by knife. Chest blow<lb/> of Gyandeo and other blows by sword were also<lb/> piercing. On the back of Gyandeo on left side, there was<lb/> sword blow. Third blow was on the stomach i.e. four<lb/> fingers above the navel. Knife blow was on left side ribs<lb/> of Gyandeo. Blow by Jambiya like sword was on the<lb/> right side stomach of Gyandeo. Bhagwat had sustained<lb/> stick blow on the head. Shahuraj was beaten by sticks<lb/> and iron rod after he fell down. He was given 4 to 5<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 126<lb/> blows by stick and 4 to 5 blows by iron rod. Sheshrao<lb/> had sustained 4 blows by Katti and sword. Sword blow<lb/> was given on the left hand wrist by sharp edge. Blow by<lb/> Katti was given on the left leg shin of Sheshrao. He had<lb/> not sustained any other injury. Sanjay was assaulted<lb/> by Jambiya like sword on the right side abdomen. He<lb/> was given 4 blows by stick and 4 blows by iron rod.<lb/> Vijaykumar was given 2 sword blows on the stomach<lb/> and one blow by sword on the nose. Nose blow was by<lb/> vertical sword. Nose and lips were cut. He had received<lb/> other concealed injuries.<lb/> He has specifically stated that, afterwards<lb/> though villagers had gathered at the time of incident,<lb/> none of them came for their rescue. They did not resist<lb/> assailants. They did not attempt to flee away from the<lb/> place of incident. At the time of incident, one female<lb/> accused was there and 17 males were present. He has<lb/> also stated details about the manner in which the<lb/> incident had taken place. He has specifically denied<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 127<lb/> suggestion that, he is deposing falsely that, accused<lb/> assaulted deceased and other injured by weapons.<lb/> 70]<lb/> Mr. Joydeep Chatterji, the learned counsel<lb/> invited our attention to Portion Mark at `A&apos;, `B&apos;, `C&apos; from<lb/> his (PW18) statement under Section 161 before the<lb/> Police and tried to submit that, his evidence before the<lb/> Court is contradictory to his statement before the<lb/> Police. We have carefully perused the evidence of PW<lb/> 18, in his examinationinchief and also his cross<lb/> examination, he has deposed about incident in minute<lb/> details. His evidence is consistent and finds<lb/> corroboration from other eye witnesses and also<lb/> medical evidence. The statement before the police<lb/> officer and the statement in the evidence before the<lb/> Court are not so inconsistent or irreconcilable with<lb/> each other that both of them cannot coexist, and<lb/> therefore, submission of learned counsel deserves no<lb/> consideration. In our opinion, his evidence is not<lb/> shaken in any manner. It appears from his evidence<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/></figure>

			<p>414.11crapl<lb/> 128<lb/> that, he wanted to convey that, the manner in which he<lb/> stated before the Police about each accused and overt<lb/> act attributed to them has not been recorded properly.<lb/></p>

			<p>However, the said portion marked cannot be taken to<lb/> mean that, same are omissions. Therefore, his evidence<lb/> is reliable, trustworthy, appears to be truthful and<lb/> deserves acceptance.<lb/></p>

			<head>71]<lb/></head>

			<p>Prosecution examined Maroti Dhanaji<lb/> Jadhav as PW19, whose evidence is at Exhibit -272.<lb/></p>

			<p>In his evidence he stated that, he was invited for dinner<lb/> by complainant Baburao on the date of incident. He<lb/> went there. At about 7 to 7.15 p.m. they were about to<lb/> sit for dinner, at that time, from the outside of house of<lb/> Baburao, they heard noise of abuses and there was<lb/> stone pelting on the house of the complainant. Then<lb/> they came out of room in the court yard. Gyandeo went<lb/> ahead. Gyandeo, Vijaykumar, Sanjay, Sheshrao,<lb/> Bhagwat, Baburao, Chandrakant and this witness and<lb/> family members in the house came in the court yard.<lb/></p>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 129<lb/> All of sudden, 30 to 40 persons from outside came in<lb/> the court yard of Baburao. 2 to 3 persons caught hold<lb/> hands of Gyandeo. Shivaji Pawar then inflicted sword<lb/> blow on the chest of Gyandeo. Two other persons came<lb/> there. One person from them inflicted sword blow on<lb/> the right side of navel of Gyandeo. Another person<lb/> inflicted sword blow on the left side of navel of<lb/> Gyandeo. Then wife of Shivaji Pawar inflicted knife<lb/> blow on the above side of waist (ribs) of Gyandeo.<lb/> Gyandeo sustained bleeding injuries and he fell down.<lb/> Then Vijaykumar was assaulted by the mob. Three<lb/> persons had caught hold Vijaykumar. Sword blow was<lb/> given on the stomach of Vijaykumar. One more person<lb/> gave sword blow on the stomach of Vijaykumar. Other<lb/> persons were also beating Vijaykumar. Sanjkumar was<lb/> inflicted sword blow on the stomach and ribs. This<lb/> witness again said that, one blow was given to him by<lb/> Jambiya and another blow was given by sword. Then<lb/> some persons rushed on the person of Shahuraj. He<lb/> was given sword blow by the side of waist. Then<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 130<lb/> Sheshrao was assaulted. Three blows were given on the<lb/> hand of Sheshrao. A stick blow was given to Bhagwat.<lb/> Injured sustained bleeding injuries and they collapsed<lb/> in the courtyard. Injured were thereafter shifted to<lb/> Nilanga hospital.<lb/> 72]<lb/> This witness was crossexamined by<lb/> Advocate Mr. T.V. Jamdar on behalf of some of the<lb/> accused. It appears that, defence crossexamined him<lb/> on the aspect that, he is close relative of the<lb/> complainant -Baburao. He stated in his cross<lb/> examination that, Varsha is the daughter of his cousin<lb/> brother, who is daughterinlaw of complainant<lb/> Baburao. He stated in his crossexamination that, it is<lb/> true to say that, he was deposing for the first time<lb/> today before the Court that, Shivaji Pawar assaulted<lb/> Gyandeo by sword, however, in our opinion, it is quite<lb/> possible that, this witness, who is relative of the<lb/> complainant from some other village, did not know<lb/> about the name of all the accused, and therefore,<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 131<lb/> merely because first time he stated before the Court<lb/> that, Shivaji Pawar assaulted Gyandeo by sword would<lb/> not affect credibility of his evidence. Therefore, his<lb/> evidence also appears to be trustworthy. His evidence is<lb/> clear, cogent and does not suffer from any omissions,<lb/> contradictions or improvements and defence has not<lb/> brought anything on record so as to disbelieve his<lb/> evidence before the Court.<lb/> 73]<lb/> The prosecution examined Varsha Shahuraj<lb/> Pawar as PW20. Her evidence is at Exhibit -273. In<lb/> her examination in chief, she stated that, complainant<lb/> Baburao is her fatherinlaw. She know accused. They<lb/> are from her village. She is Sarpanch of village Jamga.<lb/> She was elected three years before. In the election,<lb/> panel of her fatherinlaw was elected. On the day of<lb/> election, Shivaji Pawar and his persons had assaulted.<lb/> Two months after the election, she was elected for the<lb/> post of Sarpanch. On the day of election for Sarpanch,<lb/> Shivaji Pawar and his persons obstructed in the Gram<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 132<lb/> Panchayat office and said that, they will not allow to<lb/> hold election. Therefore, the meeting could not be held<lb/> and they went in Tahsil office and informed Tahsildar<lb/> about it. On the next day, Tahsildar, his colleagues and<lb/> police came in the village and conducted election for<lb/> Sarpanch. On 24 th election was over and she was<lb/> elected as Sarpanch. Shivaji Pawar and his companions<lb/> were threatening them not to allow to work in the Gram<lb/> Panchayat office and they will ruin heritage of their<lb/> family.<lb/> She further stated that, incident took place<lb/> on 09.01.2008. It was next day of Vel Amawasya<lb/> festival. Incident took place at about 7.00 to 7.15 p.m.<lb/> On that day, there was nonvegetarian dinner at their<lb/> house. Maroti Jadhav, Chandrakant Solanke and<lb/> villagers Waman Pawar, Anant Pawar, Bhingole<lb/> Tatyarao were also invited for dinner at their house.<lb/> Persons from the house and guests were about to sit for<lb/> dinner, at that time, stone pelting started and abuses<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 133<lb/> started from outside of their house. Then mob and<lb/> shout raising persons about 30 to 40 came in their<lb/> court yard. Gyandeo went ahead of all. Thereafter,<lb/> Vijaykumar, Sanjay, Shahuraj, Sheshrao, Bhagwat,<lb/> Baburao, this witness and other females came in the<lb/> court yard. Guests who had came for dinner also came<lb/> in the court yard. Gyandeo was caught hold by 3<lb/> persons amongst mob. Those were Satish Pawar,<lb/> Tukaram Pawar and Udhav Pawar. Shivaji Kadaji<lb/> Pawar inflicted sword blow on the chest of Gyandeo.<lb/> Namdeo Pawar inflicted sword blow near navel of<lb/> Gyandeo. Mahadeo Shivaji Pawar inflicted Jambiya<lb/> blow on the right side stomach of Gyandeo. Accused<lb/> Vimalbai gave knife blow on the back side ribs left side<lb/> of Gyandeo. Dayanand Bhingole inflicted sword blow on<lb/> the left side back portion of Gyandeo. Gyandeo had<lb/> sustained bleeding injuries and felled down. Then<lb/> Waman Dadarao Pawar inflicted stick blow on her<lb/> back. Then she did not understand what happened<lb/> thereafter. Persons from the mob then assaulted<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 134<lb/> Vijaykumar, Sanjay, Bhagwat, Sheshrao and females.<lb/> Injured were taken to Nilanga Hospital for treatment.<lb/> Doctor advised to shift three injured to Latur for further<lb/> treatment. Gyandeo, Bhagwat and Sheshrao were<lb/> retained at Nilanga for treatment. Gyandeo died during<lb/> the course of treatment.<lb/> This witness was crossexamined by<lb/> Advocate T.V. Jamdar for some of the accused. In her<lb/> crossexamination, she reiterated her version in her<lb/> examinationinchief about the manner in which<lb/> incident had taken place and also prelude about the<lb/> incident.<lb/> 74]<lb/> Mr. Joydeep Chatterji, the learned counsel<lb/> invited our attention to portion mark `A&apos;, `B&apos; from the<lb/> evidence of this witness and tried to submit that, this<lb/> witness has not named Namdeo in the said portion<lb/> mark, and therefore, Namdeo is entitled for benefit of<lb/> doubt. Upon perusal of the evidence of this witness, in<lb/> examinationinchief and also in crossexamination,<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 135<lb/> she has named Namdeo Pawar and also overt act is<lb/> attributed to him that, he inflicted sword blow near<lb/> navel of Gyandeo, and therefore, when her evidence<lb/> finds corroboration from evidence of other prosecution<lb/> witnesses and medical evidence, there is no reason to<lb/> disbelieve her evidence.<lb/></figure>

			<head>75]<lb/></head>

			<p>One</p>

			<figure type="table">Mahadeo S/o Sheshrao Pawar was<lb/> examined as PW21. His evidence is at Exhibit -274. In<lb/> his examinationinchief, he stated that, Baburao is his<lb/> grandfather.<lb/> Vijaykumar<lb/> is<lb/> also<lb/> grandfather.<lb/> Deceased was his uncle. Sanjay, Shahuraj are also his<lb/> uncles. Sheshrao is his father. Bhagwat is his cousin<lb/> brother. He stated that, incident took place on<lb/> 09.01.2008 at about 7.15 p.m. On that day, this<lb/> witness, Baburao, Vijaykumar, Bhagwat, Sheshrao,<lb/> Sanjay, Shahuraj, Gyandeo and other females were at<lb/> the house. On that day, it was next day of Vel<lb/> Amawasya and so dinner of chicken was arranged at<lb/> their house. For the dinner, guests Chandrakant<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/></figure>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 136<lb/> Solanke, Maroti Jahdav and villagers Waman Pawar,<lb/> Anant and Tatyarao Bhingole were invited. While they<lb/> were sitting for dinner, mob came in the court yard and<lb/> were saying that, they will ruin their heritage, they will<lb/> cut them into pieces and the mob then started stone<lb/> pelting. About 30 to 40 persons were in the mob. Then<lb/> persons in the house came outside in the courtyard.<lb/> Gyandeo came ahead of all. Thereafter, Vijaykumar and<lb/> other persons came in the court yard. Satish Vaijinath<lb/> Pawar, Udhav Shivaji Pawar and Tukaram Pawar<lb/> caught hold Gyandeo. Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword<lb/> blow on the chest of Gyandeo. Mahadeo Shivaji Pawar<lb/> inflicted Jambiya blow on the right side stomach of<lb/> Gyandeo. Namdeo Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow<lb/> on the left side of navel of Gyandeo. Vimalbai Pawar<lb/> inflicted knife blow on the back of Gyandeo. Dayanand<lb/> Bhingole inflicted sword blow on the left side of<lb/> Gyandeo. Due to assault, Gyandeo sustained bleeding<lb/> injuries and he fell down. Then mob assaulted<lb/> Vijaykumar. Satish Baburao Pawar, Vaijinath Pawar,<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 137<lb/> Venkat Vaijinath Pawar caught hold Vijaykumar.<lb/> Madhav Shivaji Pawar inflicted three blows by sword on<lb/> the face of Vijaykumar. Other persons also inflicted<lb/> blows on Vijaykumar. Vijaykumar also sustained<lb/> bleeding injuries and he also felled down. Shahuraj was<lb/> also assaulted on the back by Madhav Pawar by<lb/> Jambiya. Shahuraj, Sheshrao, Bhagwat were also<lb/> assaulted. Then injured were taken to Nilanga Hospital.<lb/> Doctor told in the hospital that, Gyandeo was dead.<lb/></figure>

			<p>This witness was cross examined by<lb/> Advocate Mr. T.V. Jamdar on behalf of some of the<lb/> accused. This witness stated that, he did not state<lb/> portion mark `A&apos; read over to him from his police<lb/> statement. Portion mark `B&apos; read over to him from his<lb/> statement is not stated by him before the Police and<lb/> that, he cannot assign any reason why police recorded<lb/> the said portion in his statement. Though the<lb/> Investigating Officer has stated that, the said portion<lb/> mark `A&apos; and `B&apos; was stated by this witness, that is to<lb/> the effect that, Gyandeo was caught hold by Govind<lb/></p>

			<figure>::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 138<lb/> Shahapure, Dhondiram Raosaheb Pawar, Ashok<lb/> Vishwanath Pawar and Shivaji Kadaji Pawar assaulted<lb/> Gyandeo by sword. Another portion mark `B&apos; is PW21<lb/> does not know, who assaulted. From these portion<lb/> marks `A&apos; and `B&apos;, in our opinion, nothing useful to the<lb/> defence has been brought on record. On the contrary<lb/> this witness has reiterated his version in his<lb/> examinationinchief even in cross examination. It<lb/> appears that, the Investigating Officer stated in his<lb/> crossexamination that, this witness has not stated<lb/> before him the facts read over to him from para 3 of his<lb/> chiefexamination, lines no. 1 to 14. In fact there are no<lb/> third paragraph in his examinationinchief. In our<lb/> opinion, trial Court was not correct in allowing such<lb/> crossexamination.<lb/> 76]<lb/> At this juncture, it would be relevant to<lb/> observe that, the trial Court while marking portions<lb/> from the statements of the witnesses before Police<lb/> under section 161 of Code of Criminal Procedure, has<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 139<lb/> not adhered to the procedure. The trial Court has not<lb/> properly appreciated, keeping in view the judgment of<lb/> the Supreme Court in the case of Tahsildar Singh<lb/> and another V/s State of U.P. 2 , what amounts to<lb/> omissions, contradictions and improvements. The<lb/> Supreme Court in the case of Tahsildar Singh and<lb/> another (supra) held that, the contradiction, under the<lb/> section, should be between what a witness asserted in<lb/> the witnessbox and what he stated before the police<lb/> officer, and not between what he said he had stated<lb/> before the policeofficer and what he actually made<lb/> before him. In such a case the question could not be<lb/> put at all: only questions to contradict can be put and<lb/> the question here posed does not contradict; it leads to<lb/> an answer which is contradicted by the police<lb/> statement. Section 145 of the Evidence Act indicates<lb/> the manner in which contradiction is brought out. The<lb/> crossexamining Counsel shall put the part or parts of<lb/> the statement which affirms the contrary to what is<lb/> 2 AIR 1959 SC 1012<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 140<lb/> stated in evidence. This indicates that there is<lb/> something in writing which can be set against another<lb/> statement made in evidence. If the statement before the<lb/> policeofficer and the statement in the evidence before<lb/> the Court are so inconsistent or irreconcilable with<lb/> each other that both of them cannot coexist, it may be<lb/> said that one contradicts the other. It is further<lb/> observed by the Supreme Court in paras 26 and 27 of<lb/> the said judgment that, it is for the trial Judge to<lb/> decide in each case, after comparing the part or parts of<lb/> the statement recorded by the police with that made in<lb/> the witnessbox, to give a ruling, having regard to the<lb/> aforesaid principles, whether the recital intended to be<lb/> used for contradiction satisfies the requirements of law.<lb/> 77]<lb/> In the present case, even if the portion<lb/> marked in the police statement of the witnesses, and<lb/> cross examination on it of said witnesses is considered,<lb/> there are no material omissions, contradictions or<lb/> improvements, which would eclipse evidence of eleven<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 141<lb/> eye witnesses coupled with medical evidence and other<lb/> evidence led by the prosecution.<lb/> In our opinion, course adopted by the trial<lb/> Court to allow defence to confront the witness by<lb/> asking question about whole paragraph without<lb/> specifying particular portion, was not proper. Keeping<lb/> in view relevant procedure, provisions and the<lb/> judgment of the Supreme Court in the case of<lb/> Tahsildar Singh and anr (Supra), the Trial Court<lb/> ought to have considered omissions, contradictions or<lb/> improvements.<lb/> 78]<lb/> P.W.21 in his police statement, in portion<lb/> mark `A&apos;, `B&apos;, has stated that, he could not state about<lb/> specific names of the assailants of all injured witnesses<lb/> i.e. Vijaykumar, Sanjay, Shahuraj and Sheshrao, but<lb/> that is not helpful to the defence. The evidence of this<lb/> witness corroborates with the evidence of other<lb/> prosecution witnesses, whose evidence has already<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 142<lb/> been discussed.<lb/> 79]<lb/> After exhaustively discussing evidence of 11<lb/> eye witnesses, in foregoing paragraphs, it would be<lb/> appropriate in nutshell to state herein below the overtacts<lb/> attributed by the eye witnesses to the accused persons.<lb/> P.W.16 Baburao deposed that accused Satish<lb/> Vaijinath Pawar, Tukaram Shivaji Pawar and Udhav Shivaji<lb/> Pawar caught hold deceased Gyandeo and Shivaji Kadaji<lb/> Pawar inflicted sword blow on the chest of Gyandeo,<lb/> Madhav Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on the right side<lb/> abdomen of Gyandeo, Namdeo Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword<lb/> blow on stomach of Gyandeo, Dayanand Bhingole inflicted<lb/> sword blow on the back side and ribs on the right side of<lb/> Gyandeo, Vimalbai Shivaji Pawar inflicted knife blow on<lb/> back of Gyandeo.<lb/> P.W.16 stated that other accused<lb/> assaulted Gyandeo with stick and iron rods.<lb/> As regards assault on injured witness P.W.25<lb/> Vijaykumar, Baburao P.W.16 attributed overtacts to the<lb/> accused stating that accused Madhav Shivaji Pawar<lb/> assaulted with sword on the face of Vijaykumar, accused<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 143<lb/> Namdeo Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on the shoulder<lb/> of Vijaykumar, accused Udhav Shivaji Pawar assaulted by<lb/> iron rod to Vijaykumar.<lb/> As regards assault on injured P.W.22 Shahuraj,<lb/> Baburao P.W.16 attributed overtacts to the accused stating<lb/> that accused Prakash Kadaji Pawar assaulted Shahuraj<lb/> with iron rod, accused Vilas Kadaji Pawar assaulted<lb/> Shahuraj with stick, and accused Shivaji Kadaji Pawar<lb/> assaulted Shahuraj with sword.<lb/> As regards assault on injured P.W.24<lb/> Shesherao, Baburao P.W.16 attributed overtacts to the<lb/> accused stating that accused Ashok Kadaji Pawar assaulted<lb/> by Katti on right shin of Shesherao Pawar, accused Shivaji<lb/> Kadaji Pawar assaulted him with sword on left wrist.<lb/> As regards assault on injured P.W.23 Bhagwat<lb/> Pawar, Baburao P.W.16 attributed overtacts to the accused<lb/> stating that accused Devidas Pralhad Pawar assaulted with<lb/> stick on the head of Bhatwat.<lb/> As regards assault on himself, Baburao P.W.16<lb/> attributed overtacts to the accused stating that accused<lb/> Waman Dadarao Pawar assaulted with stick on his back.<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 144<lb/> 80]<lb/> P.W.17 Chandrakant Pawar attributed overt<lb/> acts to the accused as regards assault on Gyandeo stating<lb/> that accused Satish Vaijinath Pawar, Tukaram, Udhav<lb/> caught hold Gyandeo and Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow<lb/> on the chest of Gyandeo, Vimalbai Pawar inflicted knife blow<lb/> on the ribs of Gyandeo, Dayanand Bhingole inflicted sword<lb/> blow on the back of Gyandeo, Madhav Shivaji Pawar<lb/> inflicted blow of Jambiya like sword on the stomach of<lb/> Gyandeo and Namdeo Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on<lb/> the stomach of Gyandeo.<lb/> As regards assault on injured P.W.25<lb/> Vijaykumar, Chandrakant Pawar P.W.17 attributed overt<lb/> acts to the accused stating that accused Namdeo Shivaji<lb/> Pawar assaulted with sword on the right side stomach of<lb/> Vijaykumar, accused Madhav Shivaji Pawar inflicted<lb/> Jambiya blow on the stomach of Vijaykumar, accused Vilas<lb/> Kadaji Pawar assaulted with stick on his back, accused<lb/> Udhav Shivaji Pawar assaulted Vijaykumar with iron rod on<lb/> right shoulder, Haridas Manik Pawar assaulted Vijaykumar<lb/> with iron rod on back side of lower portion.<lb/> As regards assault on P.W.26 Sanjay,<lb/> Chandrakant Pawar P.W.17 attributed overtacts to the<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 145<lb/> accused stating that accused Madhav Shivaji Pawar<lb/> assaulted Sanjay by Jambiya like sword on right side of<lb/> abdomen.<lb/> As regards assault on P.W.24 Shesherao,<lb/> Chandrakant Pawar P.W.17 attributed overtacts to the<lb/> accused stating that accused Shivaji Kadaji Pawar assaulted<lb/> Shesherao on left hand with three blows of sword, also on<lb/> the waist at the right side back of Shesherao, accused<lb/> Ashok Kadaji Pawar assaulted Shesherao with Katti on leg<lb/> shin, accused Prakash kadaji Pawar assaulted by iron rod<lb/> on back.<lb/> As regards assault on P.W.23 Bhagwat,<lb/> Chandrakant Pawar P.W.17 attributed overtacts to the<lb/> accused stating that accused Devidas Pralhad Pawar<lb/> assaulted him with stick on his head.<lb/> As regards assault on P.W.16 Baburao,<lb/> Chandrakant Pawar P.W.17 attributed overtacts to the<lb/> accused stating that accused Waman Dadarao Pawar<lb/> assaulted Baburao with stick on back.<lb/> 81]<lb/> P.W.18 Dilip Pawar attributed overtacts to the<lb/> accused stating that accused Satish Vaijinath Pawar,<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 146<lb/> Tukaram, Udhav caught hold Gyandeo and Shivaji Kadaji<lb/> Pawar inflicted sword blow on the chest of Gyandeo,<lb/> Vimalbai inflicted knife blow on the left ribs of Gyandeo,<lb/> Namdeo Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on the stomach<lb/> of Gyandeo, Dayanand Bhingole inflicted sword blow on<lb/> back side (left side) of Gyandeo, Madhav Shivaji Pawar<lb/> inflicted blow on the right side of abdomen of Gyandeo with<lb/> Jambiya like sword.<lb/> As regards assault on P.W.25 Vijaykumar, Dilip<lb/> Pawar P.W.18 attributed overtacts to the accused stating<lb/> that accused Madhav Shivaji Pawar assaulted Vijaykumar<lb/> with Jambiya like sword on the stomach and face, Namdeo<lb/> Pawar inflicted sword blow on right leg of Vijaykumar,<lb/> Udhav Shivaji Pawar assaulted Vijaykumar with iron rod on<lb/> right shoulder, Vilas Kadaji Pawar assaulted with iron rod<lb/> on back of Vijaykumar.<lb/> As regards assault on P.W.26 Sanjay, Dilip<lb/> Pawar P.W.18 attributed overtacts to the accused stating<lb/> that accused Madhav Shivaji Pawar assaulted with Jambiya<lb/> like sword on right side abdomen of Sanjay.<lb/> As regards assault on P.W.22 Shahuraj, Dilip<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 147<lb/> Pawar P.W.18 attributed overtacts to the accused stating<lb/> that accused Vilas Kadaji Pawar assaulted with stick on the<lb/> left shoulder of Shahuraj, Prakash Kadaji Pawar assaulted<lb/> with iron rod on waist of Shahuraj, Shivaji Kadaji Pawar<lb/> assaulted with sword on right side back of Shahuraj.<lb/> As regards assault on P.W.24 Shesherao, Dilip<lb/> Pawar P.W.18 attributed overtacts to the accused stating<lb/> that accused Ashok Kadaji Pawar assaulted by Katti on<lb/> right leg shin of Sheshrao, Shivaji Kadaji Pawar inflicted<lb/> three sword blows on left hand of Sheshrao.<lb/> As regards assault on P.W.23 Bhagwat, Dilip<lb/> Pawar P.W.18 attributed overtacts to the accused stating<lb/> that accused Devidas Pralhad Pawar assaulted with stick on<lb/> head of Bhagwat.<lb/> 82]<lb/> P.W.19 Maroti attributed overtacts to the<lb/> accused stating that 2 to 3 accused caught hold Gyandeo,<lb/> Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on the chest of Gyandeo,<lb/> one person inflicted sword blow on the back of Gyandeo, two<lb/> other persons came and one of them inflicted sword blow on<lb/> the right side of navel of Gyandeo and another person<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 148<lb/> inflicted sword blow on the left side of navel of Gyandeo, and<lb/> wife of Shivaji Pawar inflicted knife blow on the back of<lb/> Gyandeo.<lb/> As regards assault on P.W.25 Vijaykumar,<lb/> Maroti P.W.19 attributed overtacts to the accused stating<lb/> that accused Vijaykumar was assaulted by the mob, three<lb/> persons caught hold Vijaykumar, sword blow was given on<lb/> the stomach of Vijaykumar, one more accused person gave<lb/> sword blow on his stomach and sword blows were inflicted<lb/> on his stomach and ribs.<lb/> As regards assault on P.W.22 Shahuraj, Maroti<lb/> P.W.19 attributed overtacts to the accused stating that<lb/> some accused persons rushed on Shahuraj and gave three<lb/> sword blows on hand of Shahuraj.<lb/> As regards assault on P.W.23 Bhagwat, Maroti<lb/> P.W.19 attributed overtacts to the accused stating that<lb/> accused gave stick blow to Bhagwat.<lb/> 83]<lb/> P.W.20 Varshabai Pawar attributed overtacts<lb/> to the accused stating that accused Satish, Tukaram,<lb/> Uddhav caught hold Gayndeo and Shivaji Pawar inflicted<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 149<lb/> sword blow on the chest of Gyandeo, Vimalbai Pawar<lb/> inflicted knife blow on the ribs of Gyandeo, Dayanand<lb/> Bhingole inflicted sword blow on back of Gyandeo, Madhav<lb/> Shivaji Pawar inflicted Jambiya like sword blow on the<lb/> stomach of Gyandeo and Namdeo Shivaji Pawar inflicted<lb/> Jambiya (sword) blow on the navel of Gyandeo.<lb/> As regards assault on herself, this witness<lb/> attributed overtacts to the accused stating that Waman<lb/> Dadarao Pawar inflicted stick blow on her back.<lb/> 84]<lb/> P.W.21 Mahadev Pawar attributed overtacts to<lb/> the accused stating that accused Satish Vaijinath,<lb/> Tukaram, Uddhav caught hold Gayndeo and Shivaji Pawar<lb/> inflicted sword blow on the chest of Gyandeo, Vimalbai<lb/> Pawar inflicted knife blow on the ribs of Gyandeo,<lb/> Dayanand Bhingole inflicted sword blow on back of<lb/> Gyandeo, Madhav Shivaji Pawar inflicted Jambiya like<lb/> sword blow on the stomach of Gyandeo and Namdeo Shivaji<lb/> Pawar inflicted Jambiya (sword) blow on the navel of<lb/> Gyandeo.<lb/> As regards assault on Vijaykumar P.W25,<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 150<lb/> P.W.21 Mahadev Pawar attributed overtacts to the accused<lb/> stating that accused Satish Baburao Pawar, Vaijinath Pawar<lb/> and Venkat Pawar caught hold Vijaykumar, Madhav Shivaji<lb/> Pawar inflicted three blows of sword on the face of<lb/> Vijaykumar.<lb/> He also attributes overtact to accused Madhav<lb/> Pawar in assaulting Shahuraj with Jambiya.<lb/> 85]<lb/> P.W.22 Shahuraj Pawar attributed overtacts to<lb/> the accused stating that accused Satish Vaijinath Pawar,<lb/> Tukaram, Udhav caught hold Gyandeo and Shivaji Pawar<lb/> inflicted sword blow on the chest of Gyandeo, Vimalbai<lb/> Pawar inflicted knife blow on the ribs of Gyandeo, Dayanand<lb/> Bhingole inflicted sword blow on the back of Gyandeo,<lb/> Mahdav Shivaji Pawar inflicted Jambiya like sword blow on<lb/> the stomach of Gyandeo, Namdeo Shivaji Pawar inflicted<lb/> Jambiya blow on the navel of Gyandeo.<lb/> As regards assault on himself, P.W.22 Shahuraj<lb/> Pawar attributed overtacts to the accused stating that Vilas<lb/> Kadaji Pawar assaulted with stick on left shoulder and<lb/> stomach of Shahuraj, Prakash Kadaji Pawar assaulted with<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 151<lb/> iron rod on right side waist of Shahuraj, Shivaji kadaji<lb/> Pawar assaulted with sword on the right side waist of<lb/> Shahuraj.<lb/> 86]<lb/> P.W.23 Bhagwat Pawar attributed overtacts to<lb/> the accused stating that Satish, Tukaram, Udhav caught<lb/> hold Gyandeo and Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on the<lb/> chest of Gyandeo, Vimalbai Pawar inflicted knife blow on the<lb/> ribs of Gyandeo, Dayanand Bhingole inflicted sword blow on<lb/> the back of Gyandeo, Mahdav Shivaji Pawar inflicted<lb/> Jambiya like sword blow on the stomach of Gyandeo,<lb/> Namdeo Shivaji Pawar inflicted Jambiya blow on the navel<lb/> of Gyandeo.<lb/> As regards assault on himself, P.W.23 Bhagwat<lb/> Pawar attributed overtacts to the accused Devidas Pralhad<lb/> Pawar stating that accused Devidas assaulted him with<lb/> stick on the head.<lb/> 87]<lb/> P.W.24 Sheshrao Pawar attributed overtacts to<lb/> the accused stating that Satish Vaijinath Pawar, Tukaram,<lb/> Udhav caught hold Gyandeo and Shivaji Pawar inflicted<lb/> sword blow on the chest of Gyandeo, Vimalbai Pawar<lb/> inflicted knife blow on the ribs of Gyandeo, Dayanand<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 152<lb/> Bhingole inflicted sword blow on the back of Gyandeo,<lb/> Mahdav Shivaji Pawar inflicted Jambiya like sword blow on<lb/> the stomach of Gyandeo, Namdeo Shivaji Pawar inflicted<lb/> Jambiya blow on the navel of Gyandeo.<lb/> As regards assault on himself, P.W.24 Sheshrao<lb/> Pawar attributed overtacts to the accused stating that<lb/> accused Shivaji Pawar inflicted three blows of sword on his<lb/> left leg, accused Ashok Pawar inflicted Katti blow on the left<lb/> leg.<lb/> 88]<lb/> P.W.25 Vijaykumar attributed overtacts to the<lb/> accused stating that Satish Pawar, Tukaram, Udhav caught<lb/> hold Gyandeo and Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on the<lb/> left chest of Gyandeo, Vimalbai Pawar inflicted knife blow on<lb/> the ribs of Gyandeo, Dayanand Bhingole inflicted sword<lb/> blow on the back of Gyandeo, Mahdav Shivaji Pawar<lb/> inflicted sword blow on the stomach of Gyandeo, Namdeo<lb/> Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on the navel of Gyandeo.<lb/> As regards assault by accused on himself,<lb/> P.W.25 Vijaykumar attributed overtacts to the accused<lb/> stating that Satish Pawar, Vaijinath Pawar and Venkat<lb/> Pawar caught hold him, Madhav Shivaji Pawar inflicted<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 153<lb/> sword blow on his face, Madhav also inflicted sword blow on<lb/> his navel, Namdeo Pawar inflicted sword blow on the right<lb/> thigh, Vilas Pawar inflicted stick blow on head, Udhav<lb/> Pawar inflicted iron blow on left shoulder, Hari Pawar<lb/> inflicted iron blow on the back. Due to the assault, his<lb/> intestines came out.<lb/> 89]<lb/> P.W.26 Sanjay Pawar attributed overtacts to<lb/> the accused stating Satish, Tukaram, Udhav caught hold<lb/> Gyandeo and Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on the<lb/> chest of Gyandeo, Vimalbai Pawar inflicted knife blow on the<lb/> ribs of Gyandeo, Dayanand Bhingole inflicted sword blow on<lb/> the back of Gyandeo, Mahdav Shivaji Pawar inflicted<lb/> Jambiya like sword blow on the stomach of Gyandeo,<lb/> Namdeo Shivaji Pawar inflicted Jambiya blow on the navel<lb/> of Gyandeo.<lb/> As regards assault on himself, P.W.26 Sanjay<lb/> Pawar attributed overtacts to the accused stating that the<lb/> accused Madhav Shivaji Pawar assaulted him by Jambiya<lb/> like sword on the right side waist due to which his<lb/> intestines came out.<lb/> 90]<lb/> Maroti Dnyanoji Thorat was working as A.P.I.<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 154<lb/> since 19.05.2007 till 2008 at Police Station Aurad<lb/> Shahajani Police Station. He was examined as PW29. His<lb/> evidence is at Exhibit 316. He stated that, he received<lb/> complaint of Baburao Bhagwanrao Pawar at 4.00 p.m.<lb/> Then, he registered crime and retained investigation with<lb/> him. On that day, he visited the spot of incident and<lb/> prepared its panchanama. He further stated that, spot of<lb/> incident was courtyard premises of house of complainant at<lb/> village Jamga. Panchnama was prepared in presence of two<lb/> panchas. Panchnama shown to him is the same. It is at<lb/> Exh. 225. He seized simple earth and blood stained earth in<lb/> separate papers, five sticks and two iron rods under the<lb/> spot panchnama. Labels bearing signatures of PW29 and<lb/> panchas were affixed on those sticks and iron rods. Sticks<lb/> and iron rods shown to him are the same. Those are at<lb/> article Nos. 2 and 3. On that day, he went to Sub District<lb/> Hospital, Nilanga and prepared inquest panchnama of dead<lb/> body of Gyandeo. Inquest panchnama Exh.62 shown to<lb/> him is the same. Then dead body was sent for post mortem<lb/> along with police Constable Songir. He further stated that,<lb/> on that day, he arrested 10 accused under arrest<lb/> panchnamas. He seized clothes from the person of arrested<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 155<lb/> accused in presence of panchas under panchnama.<lb/> Arrested accused were Balaji Apparao Pawar, Madhav<lb/> Ganpat Shahapure, Manik Ramji Pawar, Abhimanyu<lb/> Raosaheb Pawar, Satyanarayan Madhav Shahapure, Shivaji<lb/> Kadaji Pawar, Ashok Vishwanath Pawar, Govind Ganpat<lb/> Shahapure, Pandhari Manik Pawar, Tukaram Shivaji Pawar.<lb/> Panchnama of seizure clothes of these accused shown to<lb/> him are the same. It bears his signature and panchas. It is<lb/> at Exh.80 to 84, 78, 79, 85, 86, 77. He recorded statements<lb/> of three witnesses. He further stated that, on 12.01.2008,<lb/> he issued letter to Special Executive Officer for recording<lb/> statement of injured persons. He also recorded statements<lb/> of injured by going in Latur Hospital. On 13.01.2008, he<lb/> recorded statements of 2 injured persons. On 14.01.2008,<lb/> accused Shivaji Kadaji Pawar, Madhav Ganpati Shahapure,<lb/> Manik Ramji Pawar, Abhimanyu Raosaheb Pawar, Pandhari<lb/> Manik Pawar, Tukaram Shivaji Pawar, Satyanarayan<lb/> Madhav Shahapure gave memorandum of statement. He<lb/> recorded it in present of witnesses. In pursuance of their<lb/> statements, weapons produced by them from respective<lb/> places were seized under panchnama. Memorandum bears<lb/> signatures of PW29 and panchas. It is at Exh.227, 228,<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 156<lb/> 229, 230, 231, 232, 233.<lb/> Seizure panchnama are at<lb/> Exh.234, 235, 240, 236, 237, 238, 239. On 14.01.2008, he<lb/> arrested three accused namely Vikas Kadaji Pawar, Ashok<lb/> Kadaji Pawar and Dnyandeo Shivaji Pawar under arrest<lb/> panchnamas. It bears signatures of PW29 and panchas. It<lb/> is at Exh.317 to 319.<lb/> He seized clothes panchnama.<lb/> Panchnama shown to him are the same and bears<lb/> signatures of PW29 and panchas. It is at Exh.320 to 322.<lb/> He again said that, panchnamas bear signatures of<lb/> Ganganbone. He knows his signature. He further stated<lb/> that, on 15.01.2008, he recorded memorandum of Balaji<lb/> Apparao Pawar, Govind Ganpat Shahapure, in presence of<lb/> panchas. It bears signature of PW29 and panchas. It is at<lb/> Exh.112 and 113. In pursuance to these memorandums,<lb/> accused produced weapons from the places pointed out by<lb/> them and he seized those weapons under the panchnama in<lb/> presence of panchas witnesses.<lb/> Panchanamas bear<lb/> signatures of PW29 and panch witnesses. It is at Exh.114<lb/> and 115. He affixed labels bearing signature of PW29 and<lb/> panchas on the seized weapons. He further stated that, on<lb/> 18.01.2008, he recorded supplementary statement of<lb/> injured<lb/> persons.<lb/> On<lb/> 20.01.2008,<lb/> he<lb/> recorded<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 157<lb/> memorandums of accused Namdeo Shivaji, Vilas Kadaji<lb/> Pawar and Ashok Kadaji Pawar in presence of panchas.<lb/> Memorandums shown to him are the same.<lb/> It bear<lb/> signatures of PW29 and panch witnesses. It is at Exh.323<lb/> to 325.<lb/> Then, he seized weapons produced by those<lb/> accused from the places pointed by them under<lb/> panchnamas in presence of panchas. Panchnama shown to<lb/> him are the same. It bears signatures of PW29 and<lb/> panchas. It is at Exh.326 to 328.<lb/> On 21.01.2008, he<lb/> recorded memorandum of accused Ashok Vishwanath<lb/> Pawar. It is at Exh.124. He seized weapon produced by<lb/> accused from the place pointed out by him, under the<lb/> panchnama in presence of panchas. Panchnama Exh.125<lb/> shown to him is the same. It bears signature of PW29 and<lb/> panchas. Lables bearing signatures of PW29 and panchas<lb/> were affixed on the weapons seized. On 31.01.2008, he sent<lb/> seized muddemal to C.A. Along with letter. Office copy of<lb/> that letter shown to him is the same. It bears his signature.<lb/> It is at Exh. 329.<lb/> He was cross examined by Mr. T.V.Jamdar<lb/> advocate for the accused. In his cross examination, he<lb/> stated that, on the very day i.e. on 10 th January, 2008, he<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 158<lb/> recorded supplementary statement of the complainant. He<lb/> has denied suggestion that, panch witnesses on all<lb/> panchnamas were from relations of the complainant only<lb/> and that those panchas were provided by the complainant.<lb/> He also denied suggestion that, he shown false spot of<lb/> incident and that none of the accused gave memorandum<lb/> and none of the accused produced weapons in pursuance to<lb/> such memorandums and that he prepared false<lb/> memorandums and panchanamas. He further stated that,<lb/> he has recorded statement of persons referred in the<lb/> complaint. He specifically denied suggestion that, he posed<lb/> false witnesses at the instance of complainant and that<lb/> conducted improper investigation and examined only the<lb/> persons who are relatives of the complainant. He denied<lb/> suggestion that, he manipulated panchnama regarding<lb/> seizure of clothes of accused persons. Further accused have<lb/> not given memorandum statement before him nor produced<lb/> any weapon in pursuance to such memorandum. He denied<lb/> suggestion that, he prepared false panchnama about seizure<lb/> of weapons and clothes from the accused.<lb/> 91]<lb/> PW30 Laxman Dnyanoba Kendre, who<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 159<lb/> investigated the crime from 31.01.2008 to 18 th June, 2008<lb/> as API. In his evidence, he stated that, API Thorat handed<lb/> over investigation to him. On 02.02.2008, he collected<lb/> injury certificate of injured and P.M. Report. On 04.02.2008,<lb/> he inquired with accused Waman Dadarao Pawar and seized<lb/> stick produced by him under the panchnama Exh.210.<lb/> Panchnama shown to him is the same.<lb/> It bears his<lb/> signature. Lable bearing signatures of PW30 and panch<lb/> was affixed on the stick. He further stated that, he took<lb/> Waman Pawar to Police Station, arrested him and seized<lb/> clothes on his person under the panchnama. Panchnama<lb/> shown to PW30 is the same. It bears his signature. It is at<lb/> Exh.357. He further stated that, on 29.02.2008, he sent<lb/> letter to MSEB office, Nilanga whether on the day of incident<lb/> and at the time of incident there was electricity supply at<lb/> village Jamga. The office copy of said letter shown to him is<lb/> the same. It bears his signature. It is at Exh.156. Reply to<lb/> said letter is at Exh.157.<lb/> He further stated that, he<lb/> recorded statement of Gram Sevak Goswami and collected<lb/> the Gram Panchayat extract of the place of incident. On<lb/> 05.04.2008, he submitted charge sheet against accused<lb/> Nos. 1 to 14 as there was sufficient evidence against them,<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 160<lb/> showing accused No.15 to 37 absconding. He stated that,<lb/> on 20.05.2008, accused Vishwanath Pawar, Udhav Pawar<lb/> and Vaijinath Pawar were released on anticipatory bail, and<lb/> they produced sticks and iron rod before him and he seized<lb/> the same under separate panchanamas.<lb/> Panchanama<lb/> shown to him is the same. It bears signature of PW30 and<lb/> panch witnesses. It is at Exh.214, 213 and 212. Accused<lb/> Pandurang Vishwanath Pawar gave memorandum in<lb/> presence of panchas, and he seized sword produced by him<lb/> in pursuance of memorandum, under the panchnama in<lb/> presence of panch. Memorandum and panchnama shown<lb/> to him are the same. It bears signatures of PW30 and<lb/> panch witnesses. It is at Exh.191 and 192. He stated that,<lb/> on 16.06.2008 he arrested 13 accused. Accused Vishnu<lb/> Pawar, Vinayak Pawar, Maroti Pawar, Chandraharsha<lb/> Pawar, Satish Vaijinath Pawar and Pandurang Maroti<lb/> Bhingole gave memorandum before him in presence of<lb/> panchas, and each accused produced weapon from different<lb/> places in pursuance to memorandum, and he seized those<lb/> weapons under panchnamas in presence of panch<lb/> witnesses. Memorandums are at Exh<ref type="biblio">.358, 360, 362, 364,<lb/> 366 and 368. Panchnamas are at Exh.359, 361, 363, 365,<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 161<lb/> 367, 369</ref></p>

 and 371. Lables bearing signatures of PW30 and<lb/> panch were affixed on seized weapons. Then due to his<lb/> transfer, he handed over investigation to PSI Naginwad.<lb/> Nothing useful to the defence has been brought on record<lb/> from his cross examination.<lb/> 92]<lb/> One Anant Mahipatrao Kulkarni was examined<lb/> as PW31. His evidence is at Exhibit379. He stated in his<lb/> evidence that, he attached to Aurad Shahajani Police<lb/> Station from 20.06.2008 to January 2009 as API. He<lb/> received investigation in Crime No.02/2008 on 20.06.2008<lb/> from API Kendre. He had arrested accused Nagnath Pawar,<lb/> Vimalbai Pawar and Komalbai Pawar. Arrest panchnamas<lb/> shown to him bears his signature and panch. Arrest<lb/> panchanamas are at Exh.380 to 382. He stated that,<lb/> accused Komalbai had produced knife / batai before him<lb/> which recovered under panchnama in the presence of<lb/> panch. Panchnamas at at Exh.383. Accused Vimalbasi had<lb/> produced knife before him which he seized under<lb/> panchnama in the presence of panch. Panchnama shown to<lb/> him, bears signature of PW31 and panch. It is at Exh.384.<lb/> He affixed label to the knife bearing signature of panch and<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 162<lb/> PW31. Thereafter, he submitted the charge sheet against<lb/> above referred accused.<lb/></figure>

			<head>93]<lb/></head>

			<p>We have discussed the entire evidence on<lb/> record. There is overwhelming direct evidence in the nature<lb/> of eleven eye witnesses to the incident. The main criticism<lb/> by the defence qua the evidence of eye witnesses is that<lb/> they are partisan or interested witnesses inasmuch as, they<lb/> are in blood relation with the complainant. In this respect,<lb/> at this juncture, it would be apt to make reference to the<lb/> judgment of the Supreme Court in the case of Masalti<lb/> (supra). The Supreme Court in the case of Masalti (supra)<lb/> has made it clear that it is, no doubt, the quality of the<lb/> evidence that matters and not the number of witnesses who<lb/> give evidence. The Supreme Court in para 14 of the<lb/> judgment in case of Masalti (supra) observed, thus:<lb/> &quot;14. Mr. Sawhney has then argued that where<lb/> witnesses giving evidence in a murder trial like the<lb/> present are shown to belong to the faction of victims,<lb/> their evidence should not be accepted, because they<lb/> are prone to involve falsely members of the rival<lb/> faction out of enmity and partisan feeling. There is no<lb/> doubt that when a criminal Court has to appreciate<lb/> evidence given by witnesses who are partisan or<lb/> interested, it has to be very careful in weighing such<lb/> evidence. 51 S.C.IO 146 Whether or not there are<lb/> discrepancies in the evidence; whether or not the<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 163<lb/> evidence strikes the Court as genuine; whether or not<lb/> the story disclosed by the evidence is probable, are all<lb/> matters which must be taken into account. But it<lb/> would, we think, be unreasonable to contend that<lb/> evidence given by witnesses should be discarded only<lb/> on the ground that it is evidence of partisan or<lb/> interested witnesses. Often enough, where factions<lb/> prevail in villages and murders are committed as a<lb/> result of enmity between such factions, criminal<lb/> Courts have to deal with evidence of a partisan type.<lb/> The mechanical rejection of such evidence on the sole<lb/> ground that it is partisan would invariably lead to<lb/> failure of justice. No hard and fast rule can be laid<lb/> down as to how much evidence should be appreciated.<lb/> Judicial approach has to be cautious in dealing with<lb/> such evidence; but the plea that such evidence should<lb/> be rejected because it is partisan cannot be accepted<lb/> as correct.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<head>94]<lb/></head>

			<p>In the light of the observations of the Supreme<lb/> Court in paragraph 14 quoted above, we have discussed the<lb/> evidence of all eye witnesses. Therefore, in our opinion,<lb/> merely because the eye witnesses are in blood relation with<lb/> the complainant, is no ground to disbelieve their evidence.<lb/></p>

			<p>The prosecution has placed on record satisfactory evidence<lb/> showing the involvement of accused persons in commission<lb/> of offence. There is overwhelming medical evidence which<lb/> would unequivocally suggest that, the deceased Gyandeo<lb/> was brutally murdered by the accused persons by using<lb/> deadly weapons like sword, knife and also stick and iron<lb/></p>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 165<lb/> that, the prosecution has not placed on record satisfactory<lb/> evidence to prove that the accused persons did form an<lb/> unlawful assembly either prior to commission of offence or<lb/> at the time of commission of offence.<lb/> It is common<lb/> contention of the learned Counsel appearing for the accused<lb/> that the ingredients of sections 141, 142 and 149 of the IPC<lb/> are not attracted in the light of evidence brought on record<lb/> and, therefore, it cannot be held that the accused persons<lb/> formed an unlawful assembly in furtherance of their<lb/> common object to assault / cause grievous hurt in order to<lb/> kill every member of the family of the complainant as alleged<lb/> by the prosecution. In this respect, at this juncture it would<lb/> be apt once again to make reference to the exposition of the<lb/> Supreme Court in case of Masalti (supra) wherein the<lb/> Supreme Court while explaining scope of sections 141 to<lb/> 149 of IPC and also section 302 r/w 149 of IPC, in<lb/> paragraphs 16, 17 and 20 held, thus:<lb/></figure>

			<p>&quot;16. Mr. Sawhney also urged that the test applied by<lb/> the High Court in convicting the appellants is<lb/> mechanical. He argues that under the Indian<lb/> Evidence Act, trustworthy evidence given by a single<lb/> witness would be enough to convict an accused<lb/> person, whereas evidence given by half a dozen<lb/> witnesses which is not trustworthy would not be<lb/> enough to sustain the conviction. That, no doubt is<lb/> true; but where a criminal court has to deal with<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 166<lb/> evidence pertaining to the commission of an offence<lb/> involving a large number of offenders and a large<lb/> number of victims, it is usual to adopt the test that<lb/> the conviction could be sustained only if it is<lb/> supported by two or three or more witnesses who give<lb/> a consistent account of the incident. In a sense, the<lb/> test may be described as mechanical; but it is difficult<lb/> to see how it can be treated as irrational or<lb/> unreasonable. Therefore, we do not think that any<lb/> grievance can be made by the appellants against the<lb/> adoption of this test. If at all the prosecution may be<lb/> entitled to say that the seven accused persons were<lb/> acquitted because their cases did not satisfy the<lb/> mechanical test of four witnesses, and if the said test<lb/> had not been applied, they might as well have been<lb/> convicted. It is, no doubt, the quality of the evidence<lb/> that matters and not the number of witnesses who<lb/> give such evidence. But, sometimes it is useful to<lb/> adopt a test like the one which the High Court has<lb/> adopted in dealing with the present case.<lb/></p>

			<head>17.<lb/></head>

			<p>Mr. Sawhney then attempted to argue that the<lb/> High Court failed to give effect to the principles<lb/> enunciated by this Court in the case of Baladin v.<lb/> State of Uttar Pradesh (S) AIR 1956 SC 181. In that<lb/> case, it was observed by Sinha, J., who spoke for the<lb/> Court, that it is wellsettled that mere presence in an<lb/> assembly does not make a person, who is present, a<lb/> member of an unlawful assembly unless it is shown<lb/> that he had done something or omitted to do<lb/> something which would make him a member of an<lb/> unlawful assembly, or unless the case falls under<lb/> s.142, I.P.C. The argument is (1) A.I.R. 1956 S.C. 181<lb/> 148 that evidence adduced by the prosecution in the<lb/> present case does not assign any specific part to most<lb/> of the accused persons in relation to any overt act,<lb/> and so, the High Court was in error in holding that<lb/> the appellants were members of an unlawful<lb/> assembly. The observation of which Mr. Sawhney<lb/> relies, prima facie, does seem to support his<lb/> contention; but, with respect, we ought to add that<lb/> the said observation cannot be read as laying down a<lb/> general proposition of law that unless an overt act is<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 167<lb/> proved against a person who is alleged to be a<lb/> member of an unlawful assembly, it cannot be said<lb/> that he is a member of such an unlawful assembly. In<lb/> appreciating the effect of the relevant observation on<lb/> which Mr. Sawhney has built his argument, we must<lb/> bear in mind the facts which were found in that case.<lb/> It appears that in the case of Baladin (S) AIR 1956 SC<lb/> 181, the members of the family of the appellants and<lb/> other residents of the village had assembled together;<lb/> some of them shared the common object of the<lb/> unlawful assembly, while others were merely passive<lb/> witnesses. Dealing with such an assembly, this Court<lb/> observed that the presence of a person in an assembly<lb/> of that kind would not necessarily show that he was a<lb/> member of an unlawful assembly. What has to be<lb/> proved against a person who is alleged to be a<lb/> member of an unlawful assembly is that he was one of<lb/> the persons constituting the assembly ,and he<lb/> entertained along with the other members of the<lb/> assembly the common object as defined by s.141,<lb/> I.P.C. Section 142 provides that whoever, being aware<lb/> of facts which render any assembly an unlawful<lb/> assembly, intentionally joins that assembly, or<lb/> continues in it, is said to be a member of an unlawful<lb/> assembly. In other words, an assembly of five or more<lb/> persons actuated by, and entertaining one or more of<lb/> the common objects specified by the five clauses of s.<lb/> 141, is an unlawful assembly. The crucial question to<lb/> determine in such a case is whether the assembly<lb/> consisted of five or more persons and whether the said<lb/> persons entertained one or more of the common<lb/> objects as specified by S.141. While determining this<lb/> question, it becomes relevant....to consider whether<lb/> the assembly consisted of some persons.....who were<lb/> merely passive witnesses and had (1) A.I.R. 1956 S.C.<lb/> 181 I49 joined the assembly as a matter of idle<lb/> curiosity without intending to entertain the common<lb/> object of the assembly. It is in that context that the<lb/> observations made by this Court in the case of<lb/> Baladin (S) AIR 1956 SC 181 assume significance;<lb/> otherwise, in law, it would not be correct to say that<lb/> before a person is held to be a member of an unlawful<lb/> assembly, it must be shown that he had committed<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 168<lb/> some illegal overt act or had been guilty of some illegal<lb/> omission in pursuance of the common object of the<lb/> assembly. In fact, s.149 makes it clear that if an<lb/> offence is committed by any member of an unlawful<lb/> assembly in prosecution of the common object of that<lb/> assembly, or such as the members of that assembly<lb/> knew to be likely to be committed in prosecution of<lb/> that object, every person who, at the time of the<lb/> committing of that offence. is a member of the same<lb/> assembly, is guilty of that offence; and that<lb/> emphatically brings out the principle that the<lb/> punishment prescribed by s.149 is in a sense<lb/> vicarious and does not always proceed on the basis<lb/> that the offence has been actually committed by every<lb/> member of the unlawful assembly. Therefore, we are<lb/> satisfied that the observations made in the case of<lb/> Baladin(l) must be read in the context of the special<lb/> facts of that case and cannot be treated as laying<lb/> down an unqualified proposition of law such as Mr.<lb/> Sawhney suggests.<lb/></p>

			<p>20. That leaves one question still to be considered<lb/> and that has relation to the sentence of death<lb/> imposed on 10 persons. Mr. Sawhney argues that in<lb/> confirming the sentences of death imposed by the trial<lb/> Court on 10 accused persons in this case, the High<lb/> Court has adopted a mechanical rule. The High Court<lb/> has held that the 10 persons who carried fire arms<lb/> should be ordered to be hanged, whereas others who<lb/> have also been convicted under s. 302/149, should be<lb/> sentenced to imprisonment for life. It is true that<lb/> except for Laxmi Prasad, the charge under s. 302/149<lb/> rests against the other accused persons on the ground<lb/> that five murders have been committed by some<lb/> members of the unlawful assembly of which they were<lb/> members, and the argument is that unless it is shown<lb/> that a particular accused person has himself<lb/> committed the murder of one or the other of the<lb/> victims, the sentence of death should not be imposed<lb/> on him. In other words, the contention is that if a<lb/> person is found guilty of murder under s. 302/149<lb/> and it is not shown that he himself committed the<lb/> murder in question, he is not liable to be sentenced to<lb/></p>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 169<lb/> death. In support of this argument, Mr. Sawhney has<lb/> relied on certain observations made by Bose J. who<lb/> spoke for the Court in Dalip Singh v. State of Punjab<lb/> <ref type="biblio">AIR 1953 SC 64.</ref> In that case, what this Court<lb/> observed was that the power to enhance a sentence<lb/> from transportation to death should very rarely be<lb/> exercised and only for the strongest reasons; and it<lb/> was added that it is not enough for the appellate court<lb/> to say or think that if left to itself it would have<lb/> awarded the....greater penalty because the discretion<lb/> does ,not belong to the..appellate court but to the trial<lb/> Judge, and the only ground on which the appellate<lb/> court can interfere is that the discretion has been<lb/> improperly exercised. These observations have no<lb/> relevance in the present case, because we are not<lb/> dealing With a case where the High Court has<lb/> enhanced the sentence imposed by the trial Judge at<lb/> all. In fact, both the trial Court and the High Court<lb/> are agreed that the sentences of death imposed on 10<lb/> persons are justified by the circumstances of the case<lb/> and by the requirements (1) (1954] S.C.R. 145 151 of<lb/> justice. As a mere proposition of law, it should be<lb/> difficult to accept the argument that the sentence of<lb/> death can be legitimately imposed only where an<lb/> accused person is found to have committed the<lb/> murder himself. Whether or not sentences of death<lb/> should be imposed on persons who are found to be<lb/> guilty not because they themselves committed the<lb/> murder, but because they were members of an<lb/> unlawful assembly and the offence of murder was<lb/> committed by one or more of the members of such an<lb/> assembly in pursuance of the common object of that<lb/> assembly, is a matter which had to be decided on the<lb/> facts and circumstances of each case. In the present<lb/> case, it is clear that the whole group of persons<lb/> belonged to Laxmi Prasad&apos;s faction, joined together<lb/> armed with deadly weapons and they were inspired by<lb/> the common object of exterminating the male<lb/> members in the family of Gayadin, 10 of these persons<lb/> were armed with firearms and the others with several<lb/> other deadly weapons, and evidence shows that five<lb/> murders by shooting were committed by the members<lb/> of this unlawful assembly. The conduct of the<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> members of the unlawful assembly both before and<lb/> after the commission of the offence has been<lb/> considered by the courts below and it has been held<lb/> that in order to suppress such fantastic criminal<lb/> conduct on the part of villagers it is necessary to<lb/> impose the sentences of death on 10 members of the<lb/> unlawful assembly who were armed with firearms. It<lb/> cannot be said that discretion in the matter has been<lb/> improperly exercised either by the trial Court or by<lb/> the High Court. Therefore we see no reason to accept<lb/> the argument urged by Mr. Sawhney that the test<lb/> adopted by the High Court in dealing with the<lb/> question<lb/> of<lb/> sentence<lb/> is<lb/> mechanical<lb/> and<lb/> unreasonable.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<head>95]<lb/></head>

			<p>While considering various provisions of IPC and<lb/> in particular, sections 148, 149 and 302 IPC, the Supreme<lb/> Court, in case of Ranjit Singh (supra), in paragraph 22<lb/> held, thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;22. Thus, from the above, the law on the issue<lb/> remains that in a case involving an unlawful assembly<lb/> with a very large number of persons, there is no rule<lb/> of law that states that there cannot be any conviction<lb/> on the testimony of a sole eyewitness, unless that the<lb/> court is of the view that the testimony of such sole<lb/> eyewitness is not reliable. Though, generally it is a<lb/> rule of prudence followed by the courts that a<lb/> conviction may not be sustained if it is not supported<lb/> by two or more witnesses who give a consistent<lb/> account of the incident in a fit case the court may<lb/> believe a reliable sole eyewitness if in his testimony<lb/> he makes specific reference to the identity of the<lb/> individual and his specific overt acts in the incident.<lb/> The rule of requirement of more than one witness<lb/> applies only in a case where a witness deposes in a<lb/> general and vague manner, or in the case of a riot.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<head>414.11crapl<lb/> 171<lb/> 96]<lb/></head>

			<p>As already observed, we have discussed the<lb/></p>

			<figure>evidence of the eye witnesses in detail. It is true that the<lb/> trial Court has convicted the accused Shivaji Kadaji Pawar<lb/> and Namdeo Shivaji Pawar for the offence punishable under<lb/> Section 302 of IPC and the accused Shivaji Kadaji Pawar,<lb/> Vilas s/o Kadaji Pawar and Namdeo Shivaji Pawar<lb/> have<lb/> been convicted for the offence punishable under Section 452<lb/> and 324 of IPC and sentenced them as stated herein above.<lb/> In all 35 accused faced the trial; out of which, accused<lb/> Dayanand Maruti Bhingole and Mahadeo Shivaji Pawar<lb/> absconded and their trial is separated by the trial Court.<lb/> The State and also the original complainant have filed two<lb/> separate appeals against acquittal of other accused and also<lb/> for enhancement of sentence of three accused who are<lb/> convicted by the trial Court. Since we are exercising our<lb/> appellate jurisdiction under Section 386 of Cr.P.C., it was<lb/> incumbent upon us to reappreciate the entire evidence in<lb/> minute details, since there are three appeals, one against<lb/> conviction and two against acquittal of the remaining<lb/> accused. The common argument advanced on behalf of the<lb/> acquitted accused is that in view of their acquittal by the<lb/> trial Court, their innocence is reinforced and therefore, this<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 172<lb/> Court may not interfere in their acquittal order. In that<lb/> respect, it would be worthwhile to refer the observations of<lb/> the Supreme Court in case of State of U.P. vs. Babu &amp;<lb/> Ors. 4 , in paragraph 10 of the judgment which reads, thus:<lb/> &quot;10. Recently in State of Punjab v. Karnail Singh<lb/> (2003 AIR SCW 4065) it was observed that there is no<lb/> embargo on the Appellate Court reviewing the<lb/> evidence upon which an order of acquittal is based.<lb/></figure>

			<p>Generally, the order of acquittal shall not be interfered<lb/> with because the presumption of innocence of the<lb/> accused is further strengthened by acquittal. The<lb/> golden thread which runs through the web of<lb/> administration of justice in criminal cases is that if<lb/> two views are possible on the evidence adduced in the<lb/> case, one pointing to the guilt of the accused and the<lb/> other to his innocence, the view which is favourable to<lb/> the accused should be adopted. The paramount<lb/> consideration of the Court is to ensure that<lb/> miscarriage of justice is prevented. A miscarriage of<lb/> justice which may arise from acquittal of the guilty is<lb/> no less than from the conviction of an innocent. In a<lb/> case where admissible evidence is ignored, a duty is<lb/> cast upon the Appellate Court to reappreciate the<lb/> evidence even where the accused has been acquitted,<lb/> for the purpose of ascertaining as to whether any of<lb/> the accused committed any offence or not. [See<lb/> Bhagwan Singh and others v. State of Madhya<lb/> Pradesh (2002 (3) JT (SC) 387). The principle to be<lb/> followed by appellate Court considering the appeal<lb/> against the judgment of acquittal is to interfere only<lb/> when there are compelling and substantial reasons for<lb/> doing so. If the impugned judgment is clearly<lb/> unreasonable, it is a compelling reason for<lb/> interference.</p>

			<figure>These aspects were highlighted by this<lb/> Court in Shivaji Sahabrao Bobade and another v.<lb/> State of Maharashtra (1973 (2) SCC 793), Ramesh<lb/> Babulal Doshi v. State of Gujarat (1996 (9) SCC 225)<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 173<lb/> and Jaswant Singh v. State of Haryana (2000 (4) JT<lb/> (SC) 114).&quot;<lb/> Therefore, the paramount consideration of this<lb/> Court while exercising the jurisdiction under Section 386<lb/> Cr.P.C. is to ensure that miscarriage of justice is prevented.<lb/> As observed by the Supreme Court, miscarriage of justice<lb/> which may arise from acquittal of the guilty is no less than<lb/> from the conviction of an innocent.<lb/> In a case where<lb/> admissible evidence is ignored, a duty is cast upon the<lb/> Appellate Court to reappreciate the evidence even where<lb/> the accused has been acquitted, for the purpose of<lb/> ascertaining as to whether any of the accused committed<lb/> any offence or not.<lb/> Therefore, in the light of these<lb/> observations of the Supreme Court, as already observed, we<lb/> have reappreciated the entire evidence brought on record<lb/> by the prosecution.<lb/> (Underline supplied).<lb/> 97]<lb/> After discussing the evidence of the eye<lb/> witnesses, medical evidence, spot panchanama, inquest<lb/> panchanama and other evidence placed on record by the<lb/> prosecution, we are of the opinion that, the prosecution did<lb/> firmly establish that the incident had taken place in the<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 174<lb/> courtyard of the house of complainant Baburao. It has<lb/> come in the evidence of P.W.16 Baburao and also evidence<lb/> of other prosecution witnesses that in the Gram Panchayat<lb/> election of the village Jamga, complainant&apos;s panel secured<lb/> majority and rival panel, headed by accused Shivaji Kadaji<lb/> Pawar lost the elections of Gram Panchayat. Thereafter,<lb/> prosecution has brought on record that at the time of<lb/> election of Sarpanch, there was obstruction at the hands of<lb/> rival group headed by Shivaji Kadaji Pawar, as a result of<lb/> which, election of Sarpanch was postponed to next day of<lb/> the scheduled date and complainant&apos;s daughterinlaw got<lb/> elected as Sarpanch.</figure>

			<p>The complainant has also stated in<lb/> his evidence that threats were extended that the elected<lb/> body would not be allowed to carry on their functions or to<lb/> hold Gram Sabha. In the present case, there are as many<lb/> as eleven eye witnesses; out of which, six are injured<lb/> witnesses, three of which sustained grievous injuries,<lb/> dangerous to their lives and though the other eye witnesses,<lb/> according to the prosecution, were assaulted, their injuries<lb/> were not visible. Therefore, in such a case, where there is<lb/> direct evidence in the nature of eye witnesses, the motive<lb/> loses its importance. We have already discussed in detail<lb/></p>

			<figure>::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> the evidence of each witness and the position which<lb/> emerges from the evidence of complainant and some of the<lb/> eye witnesses i.e. PW22, PW18, PW17, PW21, PW22,<lb/> PW25 etc. is that, the mob of more than 30 -40 persons,<lb/> with deadly weapons like swords, knife, Katti and also<lb/> sticks, iron rods came to the house of the complainant in<lb/> between 7 to 7.30 p.m. The fact that some members of the<lb/> said group were armed with swords and also knife and<lb/> other sharp weapons, is a clear indication that using such<lb/> weapons would certainly result into grievous injuries and<lb/> death and, with such knowledge, the members of the said<lb/> group participated, they were aggressors inasmuch as, a<lb/> group of 30 -40 persons proceeded to the house of the<lb/> complainant Baburao, they entered in the house and<lb/> committed murder of Gyandeo son of the complainant.<lb/></figure>

			<p>And caused grievous injury to Shahuraj, Vijaykumar and<lb/> Sanjay whereas, simple injuries to other three witnesses.<lb/></p>

			<p>There cannot be a room for doubt that the members of the<lb/> said assembly had knowledge that use of such weapons<lb/> would certainly result into casualties. The behaviour of the<lb/> assembly while proceeding towards the house of<lb/> complainant, as stated by the witnesses, was certainly<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 176<lb/> violent, some of them were giving slogans that they would<lb/> ensure that no member of the complainant&apos;s family is left<lb/> alive.<lb/></p>

			<p>Apart from that, they were instigating and<lb/> encouraging each other for commission of offence.<lb/></p>

			<p>Therefore, if the evidence of the complainant and other<lb/> witnesses is considered in its entirety, an inevitable<lb/> conclusion is that each member of the unlawful assembly<lb/> had knowledge that there would be commission of offence /<lb/> casualties. The members knew that weapons which were<lb/> carried by some of the members of the assembly, if used,<lb/> certainly would result into death or grievous injuries and<lb/> therefore, behaviour of the assembly prior to the incident<lb/> and at the time of incident and the fact that deadly weapons<lb/> were used, leads to only conclusion that they formed an<lb/> unlawful assembly in furtherance of their common object to<lb/> assault / cause grievous hurt, in order to kill every member<lb/> of the family of complainant Baburao, and in furtherance of<lb/> that common object, as a matter of fact, Gyandeo was<lb/> assaulted with swords and other weapons and as a result,<lb/></p>

			<figure>he died. Out of eleven eye witnesses, six are injured<lb/> witnesses; three of them suffered grievous injuries,<lb/> dangerous to their lives.<lb/> The overwhelming medical<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 177<lb/> evidence clearly corroborates the version / evidence of the<lb/> eye witnesses. P.W.27 Dr.Pralhad Solanke and P.W.28 Dr.<lb/> Shivanand Biradar were the medical officers examined by<lb/> the prosecution and we have already discussed their<lb/> evidence in detail in para 37 to 41. Therefore, it is not<lb/> necessary to repeat the same once again. In order to hold<lb/> that the assembly was unlawful, it is necessary to meet the<lb/> ingredients of sections 141 and 142 of IPC. In the present<lb/> case, the prosecution has established beyond doubt that<lb/> there was assembly of more than five persons and the case<lb/> in hand would be covered by the provisions of section 141 of<lb/> IPC. Section 141 of IPC reads, thus:<lb/> &quot; 141. Unlawful assembly.An assembly of five or<lb/> more persons is designated an &quot;unlawful assembly&quot;, if<lb/> the common object of the persons composing that<lb/> assembly is<lb/> First.To overawe by criminal force, or show of<lb/> criminal force, or the Central or any State<lb/> Government or Parliament or the Legislature of any<lb/> State, or any public servant in the exercise of the<lb/> lawful power of such public servant; or<lb/> Second.To resist the execution of any law, or of any<lb/> legal process; or<lb/> Third.To commit any mischief or criminal trespass,<lb/> or other offence; or<lb/> Fourth.By means of criminal force, or show of<lb/> criminal force, to any person to take or obtain<lb/> possession of any property, or to deprive any person<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 178<lb/> of the enjoyment of a right of way, or of the use of<lb/> water or other incorporeal right of which he is in<lb/> possession or enjoyment, or to enforce any right or<lb/> supposed right; or<lb/> Fifth.By means of criminal force, or show of criminal<lb/> force, to compel any person to do what he is not<lb/> legally bound to do, or to omit to do what he is legally<lb/> entitled to do. Explanation.An assembly which was<lb/> not unlawful when it assembled, may subsequently<lb/> become an unlawful assembly.&quot;<lb/> 98]<lb/> Upon careful perusal of the provisions of section<lb/> 141 of IPC, the present case is covered under &quot;Clause<lb/> Third&quot;.<lb/> The assembly entered in the house of the<lb/> complainant and thereby committed criminal trespass.<lb/> They have also committed offence and therefore, ingredients<lb/> of section 141 are met in the present case. The accused<lb/> persons more than five in number, in furtherance of<lb/> common object to assault / cause grievous hurt to members<lb/> of complainant&apos;s family, so as to kill every member of the<lb/> family of complainant Baburao, proceeded to the house of<lb/> the complainant with deadly weapons, their behaviour prior<lb/> to commission of offence and at the time of commission of<lb/> offence was certainly in furtherance of common object.<lb/> Their involvement was not passive. They knew the result of<lb/> forming such an unlawful assembly. As a matter of fact, the<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 179<lb/> members of the unlawful assembly who are named and<lb/> overt act attributed to them, actually participated in<lb/> commission of murder of Gyandeo and injured other eye<lb/> witnesses.<lb/></figure>

			<p>99] Section 142 of IPC reads, thus:<lb/> &quot; 142. Being member of unlawful assembly.Whoever,<lb/> being aware of facts which render any assembly an<lb/> unlawful assembly, intentionally joins that assembly,<lb/> or continues in it, is said to be a member of an<lb/> unlawful assembly.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>As already observed, members of the unlawful<lb/> assembly were aware as to for what purpose they have<lb/> assembled and were proceeding to the house of Baburao,<lb/> they were aggressors, they formed an unlawful assembly<lb/> knowing the object, joined the assembly and they continued<lb/> their association till the actual offence was committed.<lb/></p>

			<p>Therefore, in the present case, the prosecution has proved<lb/> that in furtherance of the common object, the accused<lb/> persons formed an unlawful assembly and they proceeded<lb/> to the house of the complainant Baburao so as to assault /<lb/> cause grievous hurt, to finish every member of his family<lb/> and succeeded in killing his son Gyandeo and injuring other<lb/> six eye witnesses from his blood relation.<lb/></p>

			<p>The other<lb/></p>

			<head>414.11crapl<lb/> 180<lb/></head>

			<p>witnesses have also received injuries but, those were not<lb/> visible and the medical officer has not examined them.<lb/></p>

			<head>100]<lb/></head>

			<p>At this juncture, it would be relevant to refer the<lb/> provisions of section 149 of IPC which read. Thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;149. Every member of unlawful assembly guilty<lb/> of offence committed in prosecution of common<lb/> object.If an offence is committed by any<lb/> member of an unlawful assembly in prosecution<lb/> of the common object of that assembly, or such<lb/> as the members of that assembly knew to be<lb/> likely to be committed in prosecution of that<lb/> object, every person who, at the time of the<lb/> committing of that offence, is a member of the<lb/> same assembly, is guilty of that offence</p>

			<figure type="table">.&quot;<lb/> 101]<lb/> By applying the test / criteria laid down in the<lb/> case of Masalti (supra) that in case of mob attack, in order<lb/> to ascertain whether there was actual participation of each<lb/> accused, the Court should ensure that two or more than<lb/> two witnesses have actually deposed about the involvement<lb/> of accused in commission of offence. If said test is applied<lb/> in respect of accused Shivaji Kadaji Pawar, P.W.25<lb/> Vijaykumar, P.W.21 Mahadev, P.W.22 Shahuraj and P.W.16<lb/> Baburao i.e. complainant have in clear words stated his<lb/> involvement and overtacts.<lb/> He assaulted deceased<lb/> Gyandeo with sword on chest and to that effect, there is<lb/> corroboration through medical evidence.<lb/> All other eye<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 181<lb/> witnesses have also deposed that accused Shivaji assaulted<lb/> Gyandeo with sword. After assaulting Gyandeo, he even<lb/> assaulted other eye witnesses i.e. P.W.22 Shahuraj and<lb/> other witnesses. Therefore, so far as Shivaji Kadaji Pawar is<lb/> concerned, the evidence of prosecution witnesses is<lb/> consistent and gets corroboration from the medical<lb/> evidence. As already observed, P.W.27 Dr.Pralhad Solanke<lb/> and P.W.28 Dr. Shivanand Biradar were examined as<lb/> medical officers and they have deposed in their evidence<lb/> about the injuries sustained by the deceased Gyandeo and<lb/> other eye witnesses.<lb/> As far as accused Shivaji Kadaji Pawar is<lb/> concerned, the eye witnesses namely, P.W.16, P.W.17,<lb/> P.W.18, P.W.19, P.W.20, P.W.21, P.W.22, P.W.23, P.W.24,<lb/> P.W.25, P.W.26, attributed overtacts to Shivaji stating that<lb/> he inflicted sword blows on the person of deceased Gyandeo,<lb/> injured Sheshrao and Shahuraj.<lb/> 102]<lb/> So far as accused Namdeo Shivaji Pawar is<lb/> concerned, again the evidence of<lb/> P.W.25 Vijaykumar,<lb/> P.W.21 Mahadev, P.W.22 Shahuraj and P.W.16 Baburao i.e.<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/></figure>

			<figure>414.11crapl<lb/> 182<lb/> complainant is consistent that Namdeo assaulted with a<lb/> sword not only to the deceased Gyandeo but, even to other<lb/> witnesses. Since the evidence of all the witnesses have been<lb/> already discussed in detail, it is not necessary to repeat the<lb/> same. Suffice it to say that, as regards accused Namdeo<lb/> Shivaji Pawar is concerned, eye witnesses namely, P.W.16,<lb/> P.W.17, P.W.18, attributed overtacts to accused Namdeo<lb/> that he inflicted Jambiya blows to Gyandeo deceased and<lb/> Vijaykumar -injured, P.W.20 attributed that he inflicted<lb/> Jambiya blow to Gyandeo P.W.21 stated that he gave<lb/> Jambiya blow to<lb/> Shahuraj, P.W.22, P.W.23, P.W.24,<lb/> P.W.25, P.W.26 attributed overtacts to accused Namdeo<lb/> that he gave Jambiya blow to deceased Gyandeo. P.W.25<lb/> also attributed overtacts to Namdeo that he gave Jambiya<lb/> blow him i.e. P.W.25 Vijaykumar.<lb/> Suffice it to say that by applying the test in the<lb/> case of Masalti (supra), there is overwhelming evidence<lb/> regarding involvement of Namdeo Shivaji Pawar in the<lb/> commission of offence.<lb/> The eye witness account gets<lb/> corroboration from the medical evidence. The other eye<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 183<lb/> witnesses have also stated about his involvement. Though<lb/> it was argued by the learned Counsel for the accused that<lb/> Namdeo is not named in the FIR or complaint, FIR is not an<lb/> encyclopedia and evidence of eleven eye witnesses is before<lb/> us and involvement of Namdeo is proved by the prosecution<lb/> beyond reasonable doubt. The eye witness account gets<lb/> corroboration from medical evidence and other evidence on<lb/> record.<lb/> 103]<lb/> P.W.25 Vijaykumar, P.W.21 Mahadev, P.W.22<lb/> Shahuraj and P.W.16 Baburao i.e. complainant and almost<lb/> all eye witnesses have stated about presence of Vimalbai<lb/> Pawar in the unlawful assembly. Not only that, a specific<lb/> overtact has been attributed to her that she assaulted on<lb/> the ribs of Gyandeo with a knife. If medical evidence is<lb/> perused carefully and in particular, Injury No.5 sustained<lb/> by deceased Gyandeo, the evidence of prosecution witnesses<lb/> about the overtact played by Vimalbai Pawar gets<lb/> corroboration from medical evidence.<lb/> As far as accused Vimalbai Pawar is concerned,<lb/> P.W.16, P.W.18, P.W.20, P.W.21, P.W.22, P.W.23, P.W.24,<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 184<lb/> P.W.25, P.W.26 attributed overtacts to accused Vimalbai<lb/> that she inflicted knife blow on the back of deceased<lb/> Gyandeo.<lb/></figure>

			<p>The trial Court acquitted her on the ground that<lb/> there is no proper recovery of knife from her. In our<lb/> opinion, it appears that the trial Court failed in its duty to<lb/> take into consideration the substantive piece of evidence in<lb/> the nature of eye witnesses and also the medical evidence.<lb/></p>

			<p>Merely because, there is no proper recovery of knife, that by<lb/> itself cannot be a ground to ignore the evidence of eleven eye<lb/> witnesses, which gets corroboration from the medical<lb/> evidence and, therefore, her involvement as a member of the<lb/> unlawful assembly and actual commission of offence has<lb/> been proved by the prosecution mainly through the evidence<lb/></p>

			<figure>of P.W.25 Vijaykumar, P.W.21 Mahadev, P.W.22 Shahuraj<lb/> and P.W.16 Baburao i.e. complainant and other eye<lb/> witnesses.<lb/> 104]<lb/> Therefore, if the test in the case of Masalti<lb/> (supra) is applied, the prosecution case against the accused<lb/> Shivaji Kadaji Pawar, Namdeo Shivaji Pawar and Vimalbai<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 185<lb/> Shivaji Pawar is fully established. It is relevant to mention<lb/> at this juncture that P.W.25 Vijaykumar was seriously<lb/> injured and he sustained injuries dangerous to his life.<lb/> Therefore, his evidence assumes importance and his<lb/> evidence does not suffer from any contradictions, omissions<lb/> or improvements. Like in the same manner, evidence of<lb/> P.W.21 Mahadeo, so far the above three accused are<lb/> concerned, does not suffer from any contradictions,<lb/> omissions or improvements.<lb/> 105]<lb/> P.W.25 Vijaykumar, P.W.21 Mahadev, P.W.22<lb/> Shahuraj and P.W.16 Baburao i.e. complainant, all of them<lb/> have stated that the persons from the mob were pelting<lb/> stones, then mob came in the courtyard, mob was<lb/> comprising of 30 -40 persons, on hearing shouts Gyandeo<lb/> came outside first and P.W.25 Vijaykumar followed him.<lb/> Other persons in the house also came in the courtyard.<lb/> Accused Satish Vaijinath Pawar, Udhav Shivaji Pawar and<lb/> Tukaram Pawar caught hold Gyandeo and at that time,<lb/> Shivaji Kadaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on left chest of<lb/> Gyandeo.<lb/> Almost all eye witnesses including P.W.25<lb/> Vijaykumar, P.W.21 Mahadev, P.W.22 Shahuraj and P.W.16<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 186<lb/> Baburao i.e. complainant are consistent in their deposition<lb/> that the above mentioned three accused caught hold<lb/> Gyandeo and then Shivaji Pawar inflicted sword blow on left<lb/> chest of Gyandeo. Therefore, involvement of these three<lb/> accused in caught holding Gyandeo facilitated accused<lb/> persons and in particular, Shivaji Pawar to give blow with<lb/> sword on the chest of Gyandeo and also to other accused to<lb/> assault Gyandeo and Vijaykumar. The other witnesses have<lb/> also stated that after Gyandeo fell down, Satish Baburao<lb/> Pawar, Vaijinath Pawar, Venkat Vaijinath Pawar caught<lb/> hold P.W.25 Vijaykumar. Therefore, involvement of Satish<lb/> Baburao Pawar, Vaijinath Pawar, Venkat Vaijinath Pawar in<lb/> caught holding P.W.25 Vijaykumar is also stated by the<lb/> prosecution witnesses.<lb/></figure>

			<p>As regards accused Uddhav Shivaji Pawar,<lb/> Satish <ref type="biblio">Vaijinath Pawar and Tukaram Shivaji Pawar,<lb/> P.WS.16, 17, 18, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25 and 26 attributed<lb/></ref> overtacts to these accused that they caught hold Gyandeo<lb/> thereby facilitating other accused to assault him.<lb/> P.<ref type="biblio">Ws.16, 17, 18 and 25</ref></p>

 also attributed overt<lb/> acts to accused Uddhav that he assaulted Vijaykumar by<lb/> iron rod. P.Ws.21 and 25 attributed overtacts to Satish<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 187<lb/> that he caught hold Vijaykumar.<lb/> As regards accused Vilas Shivaji Pawar, P.Ws.16<lb/> &amp; 18 attributed overtacts to Vilas stating that assaulted<lb/> Vijaykumar and Shahuraj by stick, P.WS.17 &amp; 25 stated<lb/> that he assaulted with stick to Vijaykumar, P.W.22 stated<lb/> that Vilas assaulted with stick to Shahuraj.<lb/> As regards accused Ashok Kadaji Pawar,<lb/> P.Ws.16, 17, 18 and 24 attributed overtacts to Ashok that<lb/> he assaulted injured Sheshrao with Katti.<lb/> As regards accused Waman Dadarao Pawar,<lb/> P.Ws.16, and 17 attributed overtacts to Waman that he<lb/> assaulted Baburao with stick on back and P.W.18<lb/> attributed overtacts to Waman that he assaulted Varsha<lb/> with stick.<lb/> As regards accused Dayanand Maroti Bhingole<lb/> (absconding), P.Ws.16, 17, 18, 20 to 26 attributed overtacts<lb/> to Dayanand that he assaulted deceased Gyandeo with<lb/> sword.<lb/> As regards accused Madhav Shivaji Pawar<lb/> (absconding), P.Ws.16. 21 &amp; 25 stated that Madahv inflicted<lb/> sword/Jambiya blow to Gyandeo and Vijaykumar, P.Ws.17<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 188<lb/> &amp; 18 attributed overtacts to accused Madhav that he<lb/> assaulted injured Gyandeo, Vijaykumar and Sanjay with<lb/> sword like Jambiya. P.W.26 stated that accused Madhav<lb/> assaulted Gyandeo and Sanjay with sword -Jambiya.<lb/> P.Ws.20, 22, 23, 24 attributed overtacts to accused<lb/> Madhav that he assaulted Gyandeo with sword.<lb/> As regards accused Haridas Manik Pawar,<lb/> P.Ws.17 &amp; 25 attributed overtacts to accused Haridas that<lb/> he assaulted injured Vijaykumar with iron rod.<lb/> As regards accused Devidas Pralhad Pawar,<lb/> P.Ws.16, 17, 18 and 23 attributed overtacts to accused<lb/> Devidas that he assaulted injured Bhagwat with stick.<lb/> As regards accused Venkat Vaijinath Pawar,<lb/> P.Ws.21 &amp; 25 attributed overtacts to accused Venkat that<lb/> he caught hold injured Vijaykumar.<lb/> As regards accused Vaijinath Vithal Pawar,<lb/> P.Ws.21 &amp; 25 attributed overtacts to accused Vaijinath that<lb/> he caught hold injured Vijaykumar.<lb/> As regards accused Satish Baburao Pawar,<lb/> P.W.21 Mahadeo Pawar attributed overtact to accused<lb/> Satish Baburao Pawar stating that along with other accused<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 189<lb/> he caught hold Vijaykumar. Even, P.W.25 Vijaykumar<lb/> stated that Satish Pawar caught hold him. Vijaykumar<lb/> identified the accused Satish Baburao Pawar along with<lb/> other accused present in the court.<lb/> As regards accused Prakash Kadaji Pawar,<lb/> P.Ws.16,17, 18, 22 attributed overtacts to accused Prakash<lb/> that he assaulted injured Shahuraj with iron rod.<lb/> Therefore, their presence in the unlawful<lb/> assembly and their overtacts has been stated by the<lb/> prosecution witnesses, which facilitated other accused to<lb/> assault Gyandeo and also P.W.25 Vijaykumar. We have<lb/> also observed that the mob formed an unlawful assembly in<lb/> furtherance of their common object to finish the members of<lb/> complainant&apos;s family and, therefore, the provisions of<lb/> section 149 of IPC are very much attracted and, therefore,<lb/> each member of the unlawful assembly is equally<lb/> responsible being part of the unlawful assembly. Therefore,<lb/> the proselcution has proved beyond reasonable doubt<lb/> involvement of Satish Vaijinath Pawar, Udhav Shivaji Pawar<lb/> and Tukaram Pawar who caught hold Gyandeo and Satish<lb/> Baburao Pawar, Venkat Vaijinath Pawar and Vaijinath<lb/> Pawar caught hold Vijaykumar, which facilitated other<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 190<lb/> accused to inflict blows with their weapons.<lb/> 106]<lb/> So far as accused Ashok Kadaji Pawar is<lb/> concerned, there is evidence of P.W.21 that he was holding<lb/> Katti and assaulted injured witness Shesherao. P.W.16 has<lb/> also assigned specific role to him. Some of other witnesses<lb/> have also deposed to that effect.<lb/> 107]<lb/> In case of accused Venkat Pawar, the P.W.25<lb/> Vijaykumar attributed overtact to accused Venkat that he<lb/> along other accused caught hold this witness while Madhav<lb/> Shivaji Pawar and Namdeo Pawar inflicted sword blows to<lb/> him. So also P.W.21 Mahadeo also attributed overtact to<lb/> accused Venkat that he caught hold Vijaykumar and<lb/> facilitated inflicting of sword blows by by Madhav Shivaji<lb/> Pawar.<lb/> 108]<lb/> So far as accused Haridas Manik Pawar is<lb/> concerned, P.W.25 Vijaykumar in his evidence stated that<lb/> he assaulted by iron rod on his back. Likewise, accused<lb/> Prakash Kadaji Pawar assaulted P.W.22 by iron rod. The<lb/> said fact is deposed by P.W.16 Baburao and also P.W.22<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 191<lb/> and also other eye witnesses. So far as accused Devidas<lb/> Pralhad Pawar is concerned, P.W.16 Baburao has deposed<lb/> that Devidas assaulted Bhagwat Pawar with stick. So far as<lb/> accused Satish Baburao Pawar is concerned, P.W.21 stated<lb/> that he caught hold P.W.25 Vijaykumar and also P.W.25<lb/> deposed to that effect. Other witnesses have also stated<lb/> that Satish Pawar caught hold Vijaykumar.<lb/> The injuries suffered by the deceased Gyandeo and<lb/> the injured witnesses are as, under:<lb/> (1) Deceased Gyandeo:<lb/> i]<lb/> C L W at left Temporal Region Size 3 x 2 x<lb/> 1 cm.<lb/> ii]<lb/> Deep incised wound at left anterior axillary<lb/> region, at 5 th and 6 th Inter costal space with 3 x 2<lb/> x Deep dimension.<lb/> iii]<lb/> Deep incised wound at epigastric region 3<lb/> x 2 x Deep.<lb/> iv]<lb/> Deep incised wound at left hypochamdric<lb/> region size 3 x 2 x Deep.<lb/> v]<lb/> Deep incised wound at left infrascapular<lb/> region. Size 3 x 2 x Deep.<lb/> vi]<lb/> Parallel wound deep of same dimension, 5<lb/> Cm on left of 5 th wound.<lb/> Internal injuries found on the dead body:<lb/> i]<lb/> Fracture of 5 th and 6 th left rib.<lb/> ii]<lb/> Tear at Ventricular region.<lb/> iii]<lb/> Left Ventricle get punctured with 1.5 Cm<lb/> dimensions.<lb/> iv]<lb/> Deep incised wound at left lung<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 192<lb/> paranchyme on back.<lb/> v]<lb/> Stomach get punctured of dimensions 2<lb/> Cm.<lb/> (2) Injuries suffered by Sheshrao S/o Baburao<lb/> Pawar:<lb/> i]<lb/> Clean Incised wound over left dorsum of<lb/> forearm, horizontal, near wrist. Size 3 x 1 x 1<lb/> Cm. deep.<lb/> ii] Clean Incised wound over left forearm near<lb/> wrist lower onethird, oblique, dorsoventrally<lb/> on radial side. Size 8 x 1.5 x 1.5 depth Cms.<lb/> It was bleeding.<lb/> iii] Clean Incised wound on medical aspect of<lb/> injury No.2, left forearm.<lb/> iv] Contusion over wrist joint left. Size 3 x 4 x<lb/> 1 Cm<lb/> Movements were painful<lb/> and restricted.<lb/> (3) Injuries suffered by Shahuraj S/o Baburao<lb/> Pawar:<lb/> Incised wound penetrating over right renal<lb/> angle over back, oblique. Size 4 x 1 Cm<lb/> penetrating depth not recorded as deep. It<lb/> was grievous in nature, caused by hard and<lb/> sharp weapon, within 6 hours.<lb/> (4) Injuries suffered by Sanjay S/o Baburao<lb/> Pawar:<lb/></figure>

			<p>Incised penetrating injury over right iliac<lb/> fossa. Size 5 x 2.5 Cm. penetrating. It was<lb/> grievous in nature, caused by hard and<lb/> sharp weapon, within 6 hours.<lb/></p>

			<head>414.11crapl<lb/> 200<lb/></head>

			<p>State of TravancoreCochin 6 , while explaining section 149<lb/> and 300 IPC, held that section 149 applies not only to<lb/> offences actually committed in pursuance of the common<lb/> object but also to offences that members of the assembly<lb/> know are likely to be committed.<lb/></p>

			<p>Yet, in another judgment in the case of Lalji and<lb/> others v. State of U.P., <ref type="biblio">7</ref> the Supreme Court held that the<lb/> members of unlawful assembly cannot be acquitted for lack<lb/> of corroboration as to their participation in the offence.<lb/></p>

			<p>While explaining scope of section 149 of IPC, it is held that<lb/> said section makes every member of an unlawful assembly<lb/> at the time of committing offence guilty of that offence.<lb/></p>

			<p>Section created a constructive or vicarious liability of the<lb/> members of the unlawful assembly for the unlawful acts<lb/> committed pursuant to the common object by any other<lb/> member of that assembly.<lb/></p>

			<p>Yet, in another judgment in the case of State of A.P.<lb/></p>

			<p>V Thakkidiram Reddy 8 , the Supreme Court held in para<lb/> 17, thus:<lb/> &quot;17. From the above judgments of this Court it is<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 201<lb/> evident that to ascertain whether a particular person<lb/> shared the common object of the unlawful assembly it<lb/> is not essential to prove that he committed some<lb/> illegal overt act or had been guilty of some illegal<lb/> omission in pursuance of the common object. Once it<lb/> is demonstrated from all the facts an d circumstances<lb/> of a given case that he shared the common object of<lb/> the unlawful assembly in furtherance of which some<lb/> offence was committed or he knew was likely to be<lb/> committed by any other person, he would be guilty<lb/> of that offence. Undoubtedly, commission of an overt<lb/> act by such a person would be one of the tests to<lb/> prove that he shared the common object, but it is not<lb/> the sole test. Coming now to the present case, the fact<lb/> that at the dead of night a mob of persons armed with<lb/> various weapons forcibly trespassed into the house of<lb/> the deceased after breaking open the door, clearly<lb/> indicates that they had formed an unlawful assembly<lb/> with a common object to commit some offence and<lb/> each of them would be liable for the offence committed<lb/> or knew likely to be committed by any of the members<lb/> of the mob. To ascertain what was the common object<lb/> of the above unlawful assembly, we will advert later.<lb/> Suffice it to say, at this stage, that in the facts and<lb/> circumstances of this case the six accused (with<lb/> whom only we are concerned in these appeals) would<lb/> be guilty for the offence committed by any other<lb/> member of the mob, in furtherance of the common<lb/> object, without proof of any overt act committed by<lb/> them. We do not, however, wish to dilate on this<lb/> aspect of the matter any further as we find the second<lb/> ground canvassed by the High Court that the ocular<lb/> evidence regarding overt acts committed by A2 to A5<lb/> and A9 is not supported by medical evidence, is<lb/> factually incorrect.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<head>112]<lb/></head>

			<p>In case of Dani Singh and others vs. State of<lb/> Bihar 9 , the Supreme Court, relying upon the judgment in<lb/> the case of Masalti (supra) and also other judgments, in<lb/> 9 (2004) 13 SCC 203;<lb/></p>

			<p>414.11crapl<lb/> 202<lb/> para 19 held that, where parties go with a common purpose<lb/> to execute a common object, each and every person<lb/> becomes responsible for the act of each and every other in<lb/> execution and furtherance of their common purpose; as the<lb/> purpose is common, so must be the responsibility.<lb/></p>

			<head>113]<lb/></head>

			<p>Recently, the Supreme Court in case of State of<lb/> U.P. vs. Chandrika 10 , in the facts of that case held that,<lb/> there was prompt lodging of F.I.R. common object of<lb/> unlawful assembly armed with Gun was to commit murder.<lb/></p>

			<p>Testimonies of injured witnesses present at spot could not<lb/> be doubted being corroborated with eye witnesses as well as<lb/> medical evidence. Finding of acquittal recorded by trial<lb/> Court ignoring materials on record oral as well as<lb/> documentary evidence fully supported by medical evidence.<lb/></p>

			<p>Acquittal of accused found to be based basically on dying<lb/> declaration whose maker was alive. Said statement was not<lb/> admissible in evidence. On appraisal of evidence on record it<lb/> was amply clear that prosecution had fully proved its case<lb/> beyond doubts. Judgment and order of acquittal reversed<lb/> and all the accused were convicted by allowing government<lb/></p>

			<figure>10 2014(2) ACR 1756;<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 203<lb/> appeal.<lb/> In case of Phodol vs. State of C.G. 11 , Chhattisgarh<lb/> High Court, in the facts of that case, held that injuries<lb/> found over bodies of deceased were incised wounds,<lb/> lacerated wounds and depressed fracture of head.<lb/> Appellants were holding battleaxe and other weapons and<lb/> they had caused homicidal death of three persons and also<lb/> caused fatal injuries to prosecution witness by battleaxe<lb/> and other weapons.<lb/> Evidence adduced on behalf of<lb/> prosecution and defence taken by appellants were sufficient<lb/> to establish fact that appellants had formed unlawful<lb/> assembly having its common object to commit murder of<lb/> deceased and in furtherance of common object of assembly,<lb/> they were armed with deadly weapons. Therefore,<lb/> Chhattisgarh High Court maintained order of conviction of<lb/> the accused therein.<lb/> In case of Manilal vs. State of Kerala, 12 the Kerala<lb/> High Court while explaining scope of section 149 of IPC,<lb/> held that even if the identity of some of the accused forming<lb/> part of the unlawful assembly is not established or even if<lb/> 11 2014 CRI.L.J.4704;<lb/> 12 ILR2014(2)Kerala871; 2014(2)KLT800;<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 204<lb/> one or more of the accused are acquitted granting benefit of<lb/> doubt, that does not absolve the other accused from being<lb/> proceeded against under Section 149 of the Indian Penal<lb/> Code.<lb/> The facts in the case in hand and those in case of Om<lb/> Prakash vs. State of Haryana, 13 are almost similar. In<lb/> the said case, the Supreme Court, while considering the<lb/> provisions of Section 141, 142, 148 and 149 and also<lb/> sections 302 and 319 of IPC, held that there was no delay in<lb/> lodging FIR.<lb/> Ocular testimony gets corroborated from<lb/> medical evidence. All accused persons came together armed<lb/> with lathis and gun.<lb/> Eye witnesses who are natural<lb/> witnesses, being brothers, have deposed in unequivocal<lb/> manner about assault by all accused persons. Common<lb/> object is clearly evident. In such situation, attribution of<lb/> specific individual overt act has no role to play. All requisite<lb/> tests to attract section 149 established by prosecution and<lb/> the contentions raised by appellants therein were rejected<lb/> and the Supreme Court upheld the order of conviction<lb/> passed by the High Court. If the evidence in the present<lb/> case is considered in the light of the judgment of the<lb/> 13 (2014) 5 SCC 753;</figure>


	</text>
</tei>
