<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_2ef89474aaecdea2f5d1219b2884d710.pdf"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">


		<figure type="table">

            <note>::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>26(3) 27(3) Indian Arms Act and 135 of<lb/> Bombay Police Act.<lb/> Name of the Informant :<lb/> 1) Baburao Bhagwanrao @ Bhavan<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>26(3) 27(3)<lb/> Indian Arms Act and 135 of Bombay Police<lb/> Act. On the spot, the complainant was<lb/> present. He demonstrated the spot of<lb/> incident. He narrated facts of incident.<lb/> Accordingly, we, the panchas, accepted<lb/> the same and agreed to act as panchas.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>The complainant, who was present<lb/> at the spot,<lb/> stated his name to be<lb/> Baburao Bhagwanrao @ Bhavan Pawar,<lb/> R/o Jamga, Tal. Nilanga, Dist. Latur. He<lb/> narrated the incident before the panchas.<lb/> In the year 2007, elections of Gram<lb/> panchyat were held. In that election, our<lb/> panel got majority. My daughterin law<lb/> was elected as Sarpanch of the village<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 41<lb/> Gram panchayat. Being aggrieved by the<lb/> said election, rival group, headed by viz<lb/> Shivaji Kadaji and his associates was<lb/> having grudge in their mind, from the date<lb/> of election till election of Sarpanch and<lb/> Upsarpanch.<lb/> They deliberately created<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>hurdles in the day to day work of Gram<lb/> Sabha. As the Sarpanch of village was<lb/> from our family, they decided to kill the<lb/> family members. The accused namely<lb/> Shivajii Kadaji Pawar and other 35 to 36<lb/> persons, by holding weapons like sword,<lb/> knife, sickle, sticks, iron bars and axe in<lb/> their hands and giving slogans, suddenly,<lb/> on 09012008 at about 7.15 p.m, came<lb/> to our house. They pelted stones. They<lb/> asked all family members to come out of<lb/> the house. They threatened that they will<lb/> not leave any body from his family to<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>remain alive.<lb/> They<lb/> will finish entire<lb/> family.<lb/> On the call, we, the family<lb/> members, viz, sons, daughterinlaws,<lb/> brothers, sisterinlaws, and the relatives,<lb/> who were gathered<lb/> on account of a<lb/> function known as &quot;Kanduri&quot;, came out of<lb/> the house, in the court yard. All accused<lb/> assaulted my son namely Dnyadeo with<lb/> the help of sword, knife and sickle in the<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 42<lb/> court yard and committed murder of my<lb/> son. They also assaulted my son Sanjay<lb/> Bhau Vijaykumar and nephew Shahuraj<lb/> with sword and sickle, causing serious<lb/> injuries. Myself, my family members and<lb/> relatives were also<lb/> beaten.<lb/> The<lb/> complainant also shown the spot of<lb/> incident where deceased Gyndeo, injured<lb/> Vijaykumar, Shesharao and<lb/> Shahurao<lb/> Bhagwat were lying.<lb/> While observing the said spot, it is<lb/> noticed that the said location is a new<lb/> habitat village Jamga, towards the road<lb/> leading Nilanga to Sonkhed, towards<lb/> EastWest side,<lb/> where house of<lb/> Shri.Baburao Bhagwanrao @ Bhavan<lb/> Pawar is situated. Said house is situated<lb/> in the newly occupied area having its face<lb/> on West side, adjacent to the road towards<lb/> SouthNorth corner. The house of Baburao<lb/> Pawar is situated in his own land bearing<lb/> Gut No. 48(b). The area of said residential<lb/> house is 95 X 75 feet, towards EastWest<lb/> and North South. Said spot is adjacent to<lb/> the tar road, at the distance of 22 feet and<lb/> one room, constructed with brick and<lb/> cement, consisting of 25 X 18 size,<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 43<lb/> having door of tinshutter, which is used<lb/> as front hall, wherein,<lb/> sags of grains<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>have been kept. The said room is also<lb/> having a door of small shutter, wherein,<lb/> an arrangement of electric light has also<lb/> been made. Adjacent to the said room, a<lb/> heap of sand has also been noticed. From<lb/> the said spot, it is said that, open space<lb/> of informant is situated at a distance of<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>50 feet,<lb/> where a<lb/> stones were lying<lb/> scattered.<lb/> The room which was<lb/> constructed by cement and bricks is also<lb/> having 20 feet open space towards Eastern<lb/> side.<lb/> A roof of 18 X 15 size, made of a<lb/> sheet of dried steams or twigs,<lb/> is also<lb/> fixed. On the Eastern side, a tin shed<lb/> was fixed, as if a wall to the said house.<lb/> A wooden frame, having a latch and a lock<lb/> affixed and two folded wooden doors, has<lb/> also been affixed. While inspecting and<lb/> entering in the tin shade house, from the<lb/> door, three sides of wall made up with<lb/> tin, were noticed. One wooden almirah<lb/> was found kept adjacent to the door and<lb/> near<lb/> a partition of tin which runs<lb/> towards North side.<lb/> It was noticed that,</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>Emphasis supplied]<lb/> 20]<lb/> The prosecution has examined Dnyanoba Kadaji<lb/> Sagare as PW14, who acted as panch. He stated in his<lb/> evidence before the Court that, he came to know about<lb/> murder of Gyandeo and then came to Jamga. Police had<lb/> called him for panchanama at the house of Baburao Pawar.<lb/> Baburao, Dilip, Chandrakant, Kamlakar Jadhav etc. were<lb/> present. Baburao showed them the spot of incident. At the<lb/> spot of incident, 5 sticks and 2 iron rods were noticed.<lb/> There were plates, smallplates and the pot having cooked<lb/> Mutton. One bulb was in the roof of courtyard. There was<lb/> also bulb in the shop which part of the house. Near the<lb/> shop by the side of road, there was bulb on electric pole. At<lb/> two places on the earth, blood was noticed. Police collected<lb/> blood mixed earth in two bags. Lables bearing signature of<lb/> PW14 and another panch were affixed on the sticks and<lb/> iron rod. Police had brought with them cameraman and he<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 49<lb/> snapped photographs of the place of incident.<lb/> Police<lb/> prepared panchnama at the spot and obtained his<lb/> signature. Panchnama now shown to him is the same. It<lb/> bears his signature. Panchnama is at Exh.225. Sticks, iron<lb/> rods shown to him are the same, which bears their<lb/> signatures lables. Those are articles 2 and 3.<lb/> This witness was cross examined on behalf of<lb/> accused Nos. 3 and 29. Through his cross examination<lb/> defence tried to bring it on record that, this witness is<lb/> relative of the complainant Baburao. It is true that, this<lb/> witness has admitted that, the complainant is his brother in<lb/> law. However, he specifically stated that, panchnama was<lb/> effected from 7.30 to 8.30 a.m. on 10 th January, 2008.<lb/> Place of incident is a plot admeasuring 95 x 75 sq. ft. The<lb/> plot is located in the land of Baburao. The construction is<lb/> at two places in that plot. Incident took place in the portion<lb/> on backside of shop and front side of the house. The said<lb/> vacant portion where incident took place admeasuring 25 x<lb/> 18 sq. ft. Pot containing cooked Mutton was inside the<lb/> house. There was only one pot. There were ten dinner<lb/> plates and 10 small plates. He has specifically denied the<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 50</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>Narayanrao Patil, who was working as Junior Engineer with<lb/> MSEDCL, Nilanga, Unit Rural 2 at the relevant time. In his<lb/> examination in chief, he stated that, he is serving since<lb/> 1999. He is attached to Nilanga Unit as Junior Engineer<lb/> since 2006.<lb/> Police had addressed one letter dated<lb/> 29.02.2008 to his office. It is the same, shown to him. It is<lb/> his signature on that letter. It is at Exhibit 156. He had<lb/> given reply to that letter. It is the same shown to him. It<lb/> bears his signature. It is at Exhibit 157. He did bring the<lb/> Daily Load Record Register. He has given reply to the letter</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <figDesc>His evidence is at Exhibit 168.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>He stated that, he was called by the Police in the Court on<lb/> 28 th March, 2008. The complaint was read over to him. The<lb/> complaint was relating to the incident occurred in the village<lb/> Jamga. Police demanded Form No. VIII regarding house of<lb/> Baburao Bhagwan Pawar. Accordingly, he issued extract to<lb/> 414.11crapl the Police. He stated that, the extract shown to him is the<lb/> same, which is at Exhibit 169. He specifically denied the<lb/> suggestion in the cross examination that, he did not issue<lb/> VIIIA extract, as per the original to the Police. He further<lb/> stated that, at the relevant time daughter in law of the<lb/> complainant was Sarpanch of the village Jamga. Therefore,<lb/> the prosecution has proved that, the house where incident<lb/> had taken place is belonging to the complainant Baburao.<lb/> 22]<lb/> The inquest panchanama of dead body of<lb/> Gyandeo is at Exhibit62. The said inquest panchanama<lb/> has been proved by the prosecution by examining Rajendra<lb/> Pandu More as PW1, whose evidence is at Exhibit61. In<lb/> his evidence, he stated before the Court that, on<lb/> 10.01.2008, he had been to Nilanga. On 09.01.2008 at<lb/> 11.00 p.m. he received telephonic call that, there was an<lb/> attack on the house of his relative, and the relatives had<lb/> come to Nilanga, and so, he came to Nilanga. He came to<lb/> Nilanga on 10.01.2008 at Sub District Hospital at Nilanga.<lb/> He was called by Police at 7.30 a.m. for panchanama, as he<lb/> was relative of the complainant. The other panch Shahuraj<lb/> Patil was also called by police. They both panch witnesses</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>The inquest panchnama is also proved by the prosecution<lb/> through Investigating Officer and Shahurao Baburao Patil.<lb/> 25]<lb/> It appears that, clothes of the deceased Gyandeo<lb/> were seized on 10.01.2010. The panchanama to that effect<lb/> has been prepared. The said is given Exhibit65. It appears<lb/> that, Tanaji Nagorao Gade and Satyanarayan Pandurang<lb/> Dapake were the panchas for the said seizure panchanama.<lb/> Rajeshwar Dhondiba Hampalle was examined as PW3. His<lb/> evidence is at Exhibit 94. He stated that, on 10.01.2008, he<lb/> was present in Sub District Hospital, Nilanga when there<lb/> was post mortem of deceased Gyandeo. He has taken the<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>::</note>

            <head>: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>Pawar, Ashok Kadaji Pawar, Shivaji Kadaji Pawar were not<lb/> seized in his presence. However, he has not stated that,<lb/> clothes on the person of Gyandeo were not seized in his<lb/> presence. It appears that, clothes of the deceased Gyandeo,<lb/> which were seized were sent to the Regional Forensic<lb/> Science Laboratory, State of Maharashtra, Old Nizam<lb/> Bungalow Cantonment, Aurangabad. The description of the<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>::</note>

            <head>: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>The Police seized clothes of those accused by preparing<lb/> separate 10 panchnamas. The panchnamas were<lb/> commenced at 5.00 to 5.15 p.m. and were completed till<lb/> 10.20 p.m.<lb/> He can identify the clothes seized in his<lb/> presence, if shown to him. He further stated that, the police<lb/> prepared 10 separate panchnamas of seizure of clothes.<lb/> Each panchanama shown to him bears his signature.<lb/> Content of each panchnamas, which are at Exhibit 77 and<lb/> 86. The panchanamas at Exh.81 to 86 was shown to this<lb/> witness before the Court and he stated that, there were<lb/> blood stains on all clothes seized under the panchnama at<lb/> Exh.77 to 86. During his cross examination, the defence<lb/> has brought on record that, he is in blood relations of the<lb/> complainant Baburao.<lb/> He has specifically denied<lb/> suggestion that, he was not able to identify accused<lb/> persons. He has denied the suggestion that, Police prepared</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>Pawar has given memorandum statement that, he has<lb/> concealed stick in his house and he would hand over the<lb/> same. The said memorandum was reduced into writing by<lb/> Police. It bears his signature and also signature of other</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>414.11crapl<lb/> 61<lb/> 29]<lb/> The prosecution did examine Ramakant Uttam<lb/> Solanke as PW6. In his evidence, he stated that, accused<lb/> Ashok Pawar gave memorandum in his presence and<lb/> showed willingness to hand over one stick from his house.<lb/> He identified the memorandum panchnama. He stated that,<lb/> Yuvraj Solunke was another panch. He stated that, the<lb/> accused entered in the house and handed over one stick to<lb/> Police. The said stick was at the corner of the room behind<lb/> row of earthen pots. Nothing useful has been brought on<lb/> record by the defence so as to disbelieve his version in the<lb/> examination in chief.<lb/> 30]<lb/> The<lb/> prosecution<lb/> examined<lb/> one<lb/> Goroba<lb/> Chanderrao Ghorpade as PW7, who was as Naik Police<lb/> Constable, B.No.1114, Police Station, Latur on 13.01.2008.<lb/> He stated that, on 13.01.2008, he had been to Civil<lb/> Hospital, Latur. Four injured persons were under medical<lb/> treatment in the said Hospital. He has taken clothes of<lb/> injured persons from the said Hospital to the Police Station,<lb/> Aurad Shahajani and he handed over those clothes to PSO,<lb/> ASI Shri Chavan. He further stated that, those clothes were<lb/> seized under the panchnama. Accordingly, he submitted<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>::</note>

            <head>: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:38 :::</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>3, 14 and 29. In his cross<lb/> examination, he stated that, accused Pandhari and Haridas<lb/> are real brothers inter se. Both these are nephews of<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>Waman Limbaji Pawar, who had come to his house for<lb/> dinner.<lb/> Accused Pandhari has no concern with the<lb/> incident. He further deposed that, it is not true to say that,<lb/> he falsely implicated accused Haridas at the instance of<lb/> witness Waman Pawar. He specifically denied suggestion<lb/> that, accused Waman Pawar did not assault him by stick,<lb/> and that accused Haridas Pawar did not assault Vijaykumar<lb/> by iron rod.<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 87<lb/> 47]<lb/> PW16 was reexamined by the Special Public<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>Prosecutor for State. In his reexamination, he stated that,<lb/> on the next day of incident, Police had come to him and<lb/> recorded his statement. He was also cross examined by the<lb/> Advocate for accused Nos. 1, 4, 11 to 13, 17, 18, 20, 25, 30<lb/> to 32 and 34, he stated that, complaint was given on<lb/> 10.01.2008 at 4.00 a.m.<lb/> Funeral was performed on<lb/> 10.01.2008 at 2.00 p.m. Spot panchnama was conducted<lb/> on 10 th January, 2008 at 10.00 a.m. Police recorded his<lb/> statement on 10.01.2008 at 10.00 a.m. At that time,<lb/> condition of his mind was not good. While recording his<lb/> supplementary statement, he stated that, accused Satish,<lb/> Tukaram and Udhav had caught hold Gyandeo when Shivaji<lb/> assaulted him by sword. He stated that, he cannot assign<lb/> any reason why Police did not record to that effect in his<lb/> supplementary statement. He specifically denied suggestion<lb/> that, police did not record his supplementary statement. It<lb/> appears that, this witness was reexamined. In his recross<lb/> examination, he denied suggestion that, he did not state<lb/> before the Police about assault by Haridas by iron road, and<lb/> accused Waman Pawar assaulted by stick.</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>414.11crapl<lb/> 91<lb/> eye witnesses.<lb/> 49]<lb/> Upon careful perusal of his examination in<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>cross, his evidence in the examination in chief has not been<lb/> shattered in slightest manner, on the contrary, he has<lb/> reiterated his assertions in the examination in chief during<lb/> his cross examination.<lb/> Nothing substantial has been<lb/> brought on record by the defence useful to accused to<lb/> disbelieve his version in the examination in chief. However,<lb/> fact remains that, though the prosecution has named as<lb/> many as 39 accused. He has not named all 39 accused in<lb/> his evidence. In his cross examination in para No.10, he<lb/> has stated that, Komal Maruti Pawar has no concerned with<lb/> the incident in question. He has specifically stated that, the<lb/> names of the accused mentioned in para No.10 of his cross<lb/> examination have no concerned with the incident.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>Therefore, upon considering the evidence of PW<lb/> 16 complainant, we find that, his evidence is fully<lb/> trustworthy, reliable, truthful and not shaken in the cross<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>examination. His evidence on all points -aspects is truthful<lb/> and deserves acceptance.<lb/> <note>::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 92<lb/> 50]<lb/> The learned counsel Mr. Joydeep Chatterji<lb/> appearing for the accused Nos.1 Shivaji, accused No.11<lb/> Vilas and accused No.13 Namdeo, submitted that, so far<lb/> Namdeo is concerned, his name is not mentioned in the<lb/> First Information Report, and he deserves to be given benefit<lb/> of doubt, cannot be accepted. The First Information Report<lb/> is not an encyclopedia. In his evidence before the Court,<lb/> PW16 has named Namdeo and also specific overt act is<lb/> attributed to him. It appears that, he was one of the main<lb/> assailant, who inflicted blows by sword on the deceased<lb/> Gyandeo and also other injured persons.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>51]<lb/> The prosecution witness Nos.22 to 26 are<lb/> injured witnesses. Their evidence assumes significance<lb/> inasmuch as some of them have sustained grievous injuries,<lb/> which would have caused their death, if timely treatment<lb/> would not have been given to them.<lb/> 52]<lb/> There are in all eleven eye witnesses to the<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>incident who are examined by the prosecution. We have<lb/> already discussed in detail about the evidence. Of P.W.16 -<lb/><note>::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>Vijaykumar Pawar as PW23. His evidence is at Exhibit<lb/> 279. In his examination in chief, he stated that, deceased<lb/> Gyandeo was his cousin. Incident took place on 09.01.2008<lb/> at about 7.15 p.m. at his house in the courtyard. It was<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>next day of Vel Amawasya. On that day, Chandrakant<lb/> Solanke, r/o. Chandori, Maroti Dhanaji Jadhav, r/o.<lb/> <note>::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on 18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 110<lb/> 63]<lb/> The prosecution has examined Sanjay Baburao<lb/> Pawar as PW26. His evidence is at Exhibit286. In his<lb/> examination in chief, he stated that, complainant Baburao<lb/> is his father. Deceased Gyandeo was his real brother.<lb/> Incident took place on 09.01.2008 in the courtyard. At that<lb/> time, guests Chandrakant Solanke, r/o. Chandori, Maroti<lb/> Jadhav r/o. Sawangira, villagers Anant Pawar, Tatyarao<lb/> Bhingole, Waman Pawar and he himself, Baburao,<lb/> Shahuraj, Sheshrao, Bhagwat, Dilip, Vijaykumar, Varsha,<lb/> Babita, Santoshi, Anuradha, Urmila, Popatbai were present<lb/> in his house. On that day, there was dinner arranged at his<lb/> house on account of next day of Vel Amawasya. He further<lb/> stated that, at about 7.00 to 7.15 p.m., they were about to<lb/> sit for dinner. At that time, electric light was on. From the<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>road in front of house, they heard shouts relating to abuses,<lb/> &apos;Babya, Vijya, Gyana, Shahuraj, Gotya, Sheshrao, Sanjya,<lb/> come out side. Mob was pelting stones on his house. Then<lb/> mob came in his courtyard. He further stated that, then<lb/> they came outside from the house. Gyandeo came out of<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>house first of all. Satish Vaijinath Pawar, Tukaram Shivaji<lb/> Pawar and Udhav Shivaji Pawar caught hold Gyandeo.</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 118<lb/> evidence remained unshaken.<lb/> It appears from his<lb/> statement that, police have narrated his version in the<lb/> police statement u/s 161 of Cr.P.C. not in the manner in<lb/> which he stated about the incident and, therefore, portion<lb/> marked in his police statement cannot be considered as an<lb/> omission. His substantive evidence before the court gets<lb/> corroboration from the evidence of complainant and also<lb/> from the evidence of P.W.25 Vijaykumar and all other eye<lb/> witnesses to the incident, coupled with medical evidence<lb/> and therefore, in our opinion, there is no substance in the<lb/> contention of the learned Counsel appearing for the accused<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>Namdeo that, Namdeo could have been given benefit of<lb/> doubt since this witness has not named Namdeo Shivaji<lb/> Pawar and not attributed any overtacts in his police<lb/> statement.<lb/> Therefore, evidence of P.W.17 Chandrakant<lb/> Solanke on all aspects is reliable, trustworthy and truthful.<lb/> 67]<lb/> Prosecution has examined Dilip Bhagwanrao<lb/> Pawar as PW18 who is an eye witness. His evidence is<lb/> at Exhibit -269. In his examination in chief, he stated<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>that, he is brother of the complainant Baburao. They all<lb/> are three brothers. Vijaykumar is their third brother.<lb/> <note>::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>to 32 and 34. He stated in his<lb/> cross examination that, he did not state before police<lb/> the portion marked A read over to him from his<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>Mahadeo S/o Sheshrao Pawar was<lb/> examined as PW21. His evidence is at Exhibit -274. In<lb/> his examinationinchief, he stated that, Baburao is his<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>grandfather.<lb/> Vijaykumar<lb/> is<lb/> also<lb/> grandfather.<lb/> Deceased was his uncle. Sanjay, Shahuraj are also his<lb/> uncles. Sheshrao is his father. Bhagwat is his cousin<lb/> brother. He stated that, incident took place on<lb/> 09.01.2008 at about 7.15 p.m. On that day, this<lb/> witness, Baburao, Vijaykumar, Bhagwat, Sheshrao,<lb/> Sanjay, Shahuraj, Gyandeo and other females were at<lb/> the house. On that day, it was next day of Vel<lb/> Amawasya and so dinner of chicken was arranged at<lb/> their house. For the dinner, guests Chandrakant<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>.&quot;<lb/> 101]<lb/> By applying the test / criteria laid down in the<lb/> case of Masalti (supra) that in case of mob attack, in order<lb/> to ascertain whether there was actual participation of each<lb/> accused, the Court should ensure that two or more than<lb/> two witnesses have actually deposed about the involvement<lb/> of accused in commission of offence. If said test is applied<lb/> in respect of accused Shivaji Kadaji Pawar, P.W.25<lb/> Vijaykumar, P.W.21 Mahadev, P.W.22 Shahuraj and P.W.16<lb/> Baburao i.e. complainant have in clear words stated his<lb/> involvement and overtacts.<lb/> He assaulted deceased<lb/> Gyandeo with sword on chest and to that effect, there is<lb/> corroboration through medical evidence.<lb/> All other eye<lb/> 414.11crapl<lb/> 181<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>witnesses have also deposed that accused Shivaji assaulted<lb/> Gyandeo with sword. After assaulting Gyandeo, he even<lb/> assaulted other eye witnesses i.e. P.W.22 Shahuraj and<lb/> other witnesses. Therefore, so far as Shivaji Kadaji Pawar is<lb/> concerned, the evidence of prosecution witnesses is<lb/> consistent and gets corroboration from the medical<lb/> evidence. As already observed, P.W.27 Dr.Pralhad Solanke<lb/> and P.W.28 Dr. Shivanand Biradar were examined as<lb/> medical officers and they have deposed in their evidence<lb/> about the injuries sustained by the deceased Gyandeo and<lb/> other eye witnesses.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>As far as accused Shivaji Kadaji Pawar is<lb/> concerned, the eye witnesses namely, P.W.16, P.W.17,<lb/> P.W.18, P.W.19, P.W.20, P.W.21, P.W.22, P.W.23, P.W.24,<lb/> P.W.25, P.W.26, attributed overtacts to Shivaji stating that<lb/> he inflicted sword blows on the person of deceased Gyandeo,<lb/> injured Sheshrao and Shahuraj.<lb/> 102]<lb/> So far as accused Namdeo Shivaji Pawar is<lb/> concerned, again the evidence of<lb/> P.W.25 Vijaykumar,<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>P.W.21 Mahadev, P.W.22 Shahuraj and P.W.16 Baburao i.e.<lb/> <note>::: Uploaded on -23/02/2015<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:53:39 :::</note>
		</figure>



    </text>
</tei>

