<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="358c2215280a80b31e2c37509d227d83"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>IN THE HIGH COURT OF JUDICATURE AT BOMBAY<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<address>NAGPUR BENCH, NAGPUR.<lb/> WRIT PETITION NO. 934/94, 967/92, 1179/93, 3085/93, 1784/92,<lb/> 1034/95, 1512/2000, 1136/93, 2322/92, 822/99, 1070/2000 &amp;<lb/> 5145/07.<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">allotment has been made. Therefore, there cannot be any fault, which<lb/> can be found out with the allotment being made in favour of the<lb/> allottees, who have applied in consonance to the advertisement and<lb/> fulfilled the terms and conditions of the agreement. NIT has allotted the<lb/> public utility land to following institutions; which are : Maharashtra<lb/></div>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Rashtrabhasha Sabha, Nagpur,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Hostel for Women, South Indian<lb/> Educational Society, Deaf and Dumb&apos;s School, Indian Medical<lb/> Association, Institutions like Nagrik Sahakari Rugnalaya,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kusumtai<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Wankhede Hall, Shri Guru Raghvendra Swami Bhajan Mandal, Maharana<lb/> Pratap Smuruti Mandir Sanstha, Matru Sewa Sangh, Shashkiya<lb/> Chitrakala Mahavidyalaya,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Chaitanya International Hospital, L.A.D.<lb/> College, Vidarbha Bridge Association, Kalakunj, Yogabhayasi Mandal,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Rani Laxmibai Jhansichi Smarak Samiti, Bhagwad Pad Sabha, Bhratru<lb/> Mandal, Yogabhasi Mandal, Karnatak Sangh, Ved Dharma Shastra<lb/> Papipalan Sabha, Satchikitsa Prasarak Mandal, Mahila Sewa Samaj,<lb/> Nagendra Digambar Jain Samaj, Khaire Kumbhi Samaj, Sewadal<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Education Society, Shri Sant Tukaram Gyan Mandir, Nagpur Houses of<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Mary Immanulate, Bhartiya Bhasha Dnyan Mandir, Dr. Hedgewar Smarak<lb/> Samiti, Sant Gulab Baba Sewa Ashram, Gayatri Parivar Trust,<lb/> Keshaonagar Sanskrutik Mandir, Stree Shikshan Prasarak Mandal,<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:43 :::
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
