<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_358c2215280a80b31e2c37509d227d83.pdf"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">


        <figure>

            CORAM: ANOOP V. MOHTA &amp; C.L. PANGARKAR, JJ.<lb/> DATED: AUGUST 29, 2008.</content>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>that they cannot transfer or allot open space as shown by letters<lb/> &quot;A,B,C,D,A&quot; in Annexure-3 by bifurcating the same to an institution for<lb/> institutional purpose. In the year 1969, the petitioner-society purchased<lb/> land bearing khsara no.87 patwari halka no.44 of Mouza Bhamti Parsodi<lb/> in Nagpur vide registered sale deeds dated 16/10/1968, 12/12/1968,<lb/> 26/3/1969 and 3/4/1969 for valuable consideration. It is submitted that<lb/> the said lands previously belonged to Padole family from whom the<lb/> petitioner-Society purchased the same as stated above. The petitioner<lb/> applied to the NIT for necessary sanction of lay out and the said lay out<lb/> was sanctioned on executing various documents including an agreement<lb/> in question. All the development work in the lay out has been done by<lb/> NIT and the cost on such development work has been paid by the<lb/> petitioner-society in full.<lb/> 7.<lb/> As per condition no.9 in the agreement and condition no.4 of<lb/> the Memorandum, the open spaces have to be transferred to the<lb/> respondent-Trust. Areas covered by sewer, water pipe line, open spaces<lb/> for public utility purposes have to be transferred to the respondents.<lb/> However, it is submitted that the same has not been transferred. The<lb/> tittle of the said open spaces remains with the petitioner.<lb/> 8.<lb/> The petitioner was surprised to see an advertisement published<lb/> by the respondent NIT in various local dailies of Nagpur, whereby they<lb/> wanted to transfer the land shown by letters A,B,C,D &quot;A&quot; in Annexure 3 to<lb/> various private institutions. The open spaces by letters A,B.C,D &quot;A&quot; has<lb/> been bifurcated in three different portions and sought to be allotted to<lb/> various private institutions The said land is reserved for public utility<lb/> purpose and not for institutional purposes as per the sanctioned layout<lb/> plan.<lb/> The respondent NIT wanted to transfer the said open space<lb/> reserved for public utility purpose to the three institutions.<lb/> 9.<lb/> That, the petitioner thus submits that the action of the NIT in<lb/> advertising and intending to transfer on allotment of this public utility<lb/> land without there being any title, is void. The agreement clause nos.8<lb/> and 9 are void as no law permits transfer of public utility space open<lb/> space i.e. Public utility space to the NIT free of cost. There is no provision<lb/> under the Nagpur Improvement Trust Act nor there is any law by which<lb/> the open space in the lay out or public utility land can be transferred like<lb/> this and therefore, the entire action of advertising and bifurcating this<lb/> land in to plots for its allotment is clearly void and illegal and the same is<lb/> liable to be set aside.<lb/> 10.<lb/> In Writ Petition No. 1179/93 the petitioner-Society has<lb/> challenged the action of respondent no.1 and further declaration that they<lb/> cannot transfer or allot open space as shown by letters A,B,C,D, and D in<lb/> Annexure-2 by bifurcating the same to an institution for institutional<lb/> purpose. The petitioner-society purchased the land bearing Khasra No.78<lb/> to 82 of Mouza Bhamti Taluka District Nagpur and sale deeds were<lb/> executed on 10/4/1969 for valuable consideration, of the said land from<lb/> Padole Family. The petitioner applied to the Trust for sanction of lay out<lb/> and in order to get sanction, the petitioner was required to execute<lb/> various documents. That, accordingly the layout plan was sanctioned.<lb/> That, an agreement in question was drawn between the Nagpur<lb/> Improvement Trust and the petitioner-society. In the sanctioned lay out<lb/> plan various open space were left in the lay out for public convenience<lb/> and specific land shown by letters A,B,C,D and D in Annexure 2 were kept<lb/> for public utility purpose. All the development work in the lay out is<lb/> being done by respondent-Trust and the cost of such development were<lb/> paid by the petitioner-society in full. As per one of the condition in<lb/> agreement, the open space has to be transferred to the respondent-Trust,<lb/> the area covered by sewer, water pipe line etc., has to be transferred to<lb/> the Nagpur Municipal Corporation. The petitioner society is in possession<lb/> of the land. The title is not yet transferred.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>the petition. Shri Parsodkar for petitioner says that open land and public<lb/> utility land left by the petitioner is in excess of the land. If that be so, it is<lb/> to the petitioner to get their land modified so as to utilize the excess land<lb/> for the purpose of making additional plots Order accordingly&quot;<lb/> That in view of the above order, Halba Maha Sangh has constructed<lb/> Community Hall. The same has been in use since then.<lb/> 13.<lb/> It is, therefore, submitted that the clause and the entire action<lb/> of advertising and bifurcating this land in to plots are void and illegal and<lb/> be set aside.<lb/> 14.<lb/> In Writ Petition No. 3085/98, the petitioner has challenged the<lb/> action of respondent based upon the agreement dated 27/1/1970<lb/> executed between the petitioner and the respondent NIT. The petitioner<lb/> Society was registered under Maharashtra Cooperative Societies Act vide<lb/> registration No.246. On 23/2/1968, the petitioner-society purchased land<lb/> area 6.81 Hects. Kh.No.15 and 17 of mouza Khamla from one Shri<lb/> Vithoba Nigote. On 21/3/1969 the sub-Divisional Officer, Nagpur<lb/> granted permission for change of user of the land from Agriculture to non-<lb/>agricultural purpose. Respondent no.1 has sanctioned the layout vide<lb/> agreement dated 27/1/1970. As per norm, some portion of the land is<lb/> reserved for public utility purpose like primary school or civic center. It</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            15.<lb/> In Writ Petition </content>
 
            <figDesc>No. 1784/92, the petitioner is a Society<lb/> registered under the Societies Registration Act. Basically it consists of the<lb/> residents of Laxmi Nagar locality. By this petition, the challenge is to an<lb/> advertisement dated 18.01.1992 proposing allotment of plot no. 301/1 to<lb/> 5 issued by respondent-NIT. By an agreement subsequently, as it was<lb/> released/allotted in favour of respondent no. 2-Society. The challenge<lb/> was raised accordingly. The challenge is same in the present petition also<lb/> on similar lines with other petitions against NIT with regard to the<lb/> unauthorised allotment/distribution of plots not owned by NIT; there is<lb/> no question of automatic transfer agreement and as such the action is null<lb/> and void and it is beyond the scope and power of NIT. The whole action<lb/> need to be quashed and set aside as NIT grabbed the land free of cost. By<lb/> order dated 25.08.1992, this Court has granted order of status quo. The<lb/> status quo order has been continuing till this date. Respondent no. 1/NIT<lb/> by their written submission resisted the case on all counts on similar lines<lb/> along with other petitions and accordingly heard also.<lb/> 16.<lb/> In Writ Petition No. 1034/95, the petitioners have challenged<lb/> the validity of action of respondent no. 2 NIT of allotting open space from<lb/> Khasra no. 65, Mouja Ajni in favour of respondent no. 3. Respondent no.<lb/> 2 admittedly entered into an agreement with respondent no. 3 for<lb/> sanction of the layout on 21.02.1985 and pursuance to the agreement, the<lb/> petitioner agreed to transfer the open space in favour of respondent no 2.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            17.<lb/> In Writ Petition </content>
 
            <figDesc>No. 1512/2000, the petitioner has challenged<lb/> the action of respondent based upon the agreement dated 9/7/1979<lb/> executed between the petitioner and the respondent NIT. The petitioner<lb/> Society is a Housing Society registered under the Maharashtra<lb/> Cooperative Societies Act. The Society has developed various layouts and<lb/> flat schemes for its members. In one of its layout at Deendayal Nagar,<lb/> Nagpur, the Society intended to use its public utility land for construction<lb/> of hostel of working women or for adult education activity and<lb/> accordingly asked for necessary permission from respondents. However,<lb/> respondent vide notification dated 31/3/2000 and corrigendum dated<lb/> 7/4/2000 is seeking to acquire the said public utility land in the layout of<lb/> the petitioner society for allotment to some other trusts/societies for<lb/> being used for public utility, denying the claim of the petitioner. The<lb/> petitioner has also challenged excess reservation sought to be made for<lb/> public utility purpose in the land of the Society. Hence, this petition.<lb/> The common submissions are raised along with the other petitions based<lb/> upon the similar clauses and agreements in question.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>petitioner had purchased agricultural land vide Sale Deed dated<lb/> 14/06/1968 having Khasra No. 130 of Mouza Parsodi.<lb/> The land is<lb/> admeasuring 10 acres. Respondent No.1 had sanctioned and developed<lb/> the layout. The copy of the sanctioned plan is at Annexure &apos;B&apos;. While<lb/> sanctioning the plan, respondent No.1 left open place reserved for<lb/> Primary School, and an open area. Respondent No. 1 also entered into<lb/> an agreement in question of development with petitioner on 27/01/1970.<lb/> Since last 29 years, the open land is in possession of the petitioner<lb/> Society, being absolute owner by virtue of the Sale Deed dated<lb/> 14/06/1968. All of a sudden without responding to the earlier<lb/> correspondence the open land owned by the petitioner allotted to<lb/> respondent No. 2 without the consent of the petitioner. The petitioner,<lb/> therefore, immediately sent a letter on 14/12/1998 and legal notice<lb/> through counsel on 20/12/1998, but there is no reply from respondent<lb/> No.1. The main challenge of the petitioner revolve around Clause 10 of<lb/> the Agreement and action arising out of the same claiming it to be illegal,<lb/> arbitrary, malafide and bad in law, void ab-initio and further it is contrary<lb/> to the guidelines of the Government of Maharashtra dated 10.06.1996.<lb/> 21.<lb/> In Writ Petition No. 1070/2000, petitioner-Cooperative Housing<lb/> Society has challenged the decision and action of NIT of taking action<lb/> pursuance to agreement dated 10.03.1970 between petitioner and NIT<lb/> claiming allotment of the plot to the exclusion of other Education Society.<lb/> The petitioner adopted all the grounds and arguments made in Writ<lb/> Petition No. 934 of 1994 Friends Cooperative Housing Society Vs.<lb/> Nagpur Improvement Trust and 3 Others.<lb/> 22.<lb/> In Writ Petition No. 5145/07, the petitioner has challenged the<lb/> action of respondent no.2 NIT in refusing to allot the public utility land<lb/> belonging to the petitioner society to the society itself and instead<lb/> allotting it to respondent no.4 society. On 23.8.1965 the petitioner society<lb/> had purchased land admeasuring 9.38 acres of Khasra No.22 of Mouza<lb/> Khamla from its original owner by a sale-deed.<lb/> On 30.3.1966 the<lb/> diversion of the said land to non-agricultural use was permitted by Sub-<lb/>Divisional Officer, Nagpur.<lb/> 23.<lb/> The layout plan for development of the land was sanctioned by<lb/> Respondent no.2 and an agreement was entered into between the<lb/> petitioner society and NIT. As per the agreement the petitioner has<lb/> reserved 10% of the total land admeasuring about 14941.60 sq. ft. for<lb/> public utility purpose and transferred the same to NIT free of cost. On<lb/> 18.6.1982 the petitioner had applied for re-allotment of the land and on<lb/> making such application NIT had vide its communication dated 18.6.1982<lb/> demanded an amount of Rs.22,413/-@ Rs.1.50 per sq. ft. from the<lb/> petitioner and the said amount was deposited by the petitioner. On<lb/> 15.11.1990 the NIT published an advertisement for allotment of the<lb/> Public Utility Land and out of the total public utility land a portion of land<lb/> was allotted to one Nagarjun Medical Trust. On 14.6.1996 the petitioner<lb/> had preferred a Writ Petition No. 539/1994 challenging the said<lb/> allotment. However, this Court vide order dated 14.6.1996 refused to<lb/> entertain the petition. On 15.3.1999 &amp; 30.1.2000 the NIT published an<lb/> advertisement in the newspaper for allotment of remaining portion of<lb/> public utility land. On 19.4.2000 the petitioner society made an<lb/> application for allotment of the remaining portion of public utility land.<lb/> On 19.4.2005 the petitioner issued a legal notice to the respondents for<lb/> allotment of the remaining portion of land to the petitioner society. The<lb/> petitioner made number of representations to the respondents regarding<lb/> allotment of the land. However, the respondent NIT did not consider the<lb/> request of the petitioner and allotted the said land to some other society.<lb/> The petitioner therefore, made an application to NIT on 17.7.2007 under<lb/> the Right to Information Act.<lb/> N.I.T. vide its letter dated 8.8.2007<lb/> informed that the remaining portion of land admeasuring about 961.58<lb/> sq. mtrs. Has been allotted to one Sneh Mahila Vikas Sanstha. The<lb/> petitioner has, therefore, challenged this action of the respondent Trust by<lb/> way of this petition.<lb/> 24.<lb/> Respondent No.2 NIT resisted the petition by its reply dated<lb/> 12.12.2007. Respondent no.4 has also opposed the petition on various<lb/> grounds. The parties have filed their Written Submissions also.<lb/> 25.<lb/> In view of this, principally following interlinked points arise for<lb/> consideration :-<lb/>a) Whether the clause contained in the agreement entered into between<lb/> the various petitioners and NIT by which the petitioners have<lb/> voluntarily agreed to surrender a portion of their land from the layout<lb/> to NIT free of cost for being used for public purpose is unenforceable,<lb/> void being unconscionable, grossly unequal in bargaining power and<lb/> opposed to public policy ? .....No.<lb/> b) Whether anything including the decision reported in AIR 1995 SC 470<lb/> (Pt. Chaitram&apos;s case) precludes NIT from receiving and allotting the<lb/> land voluntarily surrendered by the petitioners without paying any<lb/> monetary compensation and valid transfer of the land in view of the<lb/> binding agreements/undertakings in the facts and circumstances of the<lb/> case ? ......No.<lb/> c) Is the alleged clause and contract void and, therefore, needs any<lb/> declaration to that effect ? .....No.<lb/> d) Is the contract void for want of consideration/registration ? ....No.<lb/> e) Whether the principles of law of limitation, delay, laches, waiver and<lb/> other equitable principles apply to the present Writ Petitions ? ...Yes.<lb/> f) Is NIT legally entitled to allot/lease out the said land to public<lb/> institutions or public trusts by following the process of law ? ......Yes.<lb/> g) Whether the petitioners have first or exclusive right to allotment of the<lb/> land in question ? .......No.<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> The common reasons :-<lb/>26.<lb/> Writ Petition No</content>

            <figDesc>. 5145/07 is not maintainable in view of the<lb/> decision in Writ Petition No. 539/94 which was between the same<lb/> parties. While dismissing the earlier Writ Petition, this Court has<lb/> observed as under :-<lb/>&quot;(A) As per initial agreement with the Nagpur<lb/> Improvement Trust on 5.2.1971 vide Clause 9, it was<lb/> specifically agreed by the petitioners society to hand over the<lb/> public utility plot in favour of the Nagpur Improvement Trust<lb/> free of cost. The validity of the said clause has not been<lb/> challenged at the relevant time. (Emphasis supplied),<lb/> (B) Sometime in 1982, the petitioner applied for re-<lb/>allotment of the said plot and offered certain price. However,<lb/> the same was not finally materialized.<lb/> This was also not<lb/> challenged.&quot;<lb/> It is clear that the earlier Writ Petition was dismissed on the ground of<lb/> delay and laches. There was no challenge to the validity of Clause 9 of<lb/> the agreement between the petitioner and NIT in question, at the<lb/> relevant time. The said judgment has attained finality and, therefore,<lb/> binds the parties. The contention now raised and reagitated in the<lb/> present petition is impermissible. (Gorie Gouri Naidu (Minor) and<lb/> another .vs. Thandrothu Bodemma &amp; others : (1997) 2 SCC 552).</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>28.<lb/> The relevant Sections 23 &amp; 25 of the Contract Act read as<lb/> under:-<lb/>&quot;Section 23 : What consideration and objects are<lb/> lawful, and what not :-The consideration or object of an<lb/> agreement is lawful, unless ----<lb/>it is forbidden by law; or<lb/> is of such a nature that, if permitted, it would<lb/> defeat the provisions of any law; or is fraudulent; or<lb/> involves or implies, injury to the person or<lb/> property of another; or<lb/> the Court regards it as immoral, or opposed to<lb/> public policy.<lb/> In each of these cases, the consideration or object of an<lb/> agreement is said to be unlawful. Every agreement of<lb/> which the object or consideration is unlawful is void.&quot;<lb/> &quot;Section 25. Agreement without consideration, void,<lb/> unless it is in writing and registered or is a promise to<lb/> compensate for something done or is a promise to pay a<lb/> debt barred by limitation law -An agreement made<lb/> without consideration is void, unless--<lb/>1)it is expressed in writing and registered under the law<lb/> for the time being in force for the registration of<lb/> documents and is made on account of natural love and<lb/> affection between parties standing in a near relation to<lb/> each other; or unless,<lb/> 2) it is a promise to compensate, wholly or in part, a<lb/> person who has already voluntarily done something for<lb/> the promisor, or something which the promisor was<lb/> legally compellable to do or unless,<lb/> 3)it is a promise, made in writing and signed by the person to<lb/> be charged therewith, or by his agent generally or specially<lb/> authorised in that behalf, to pay wholly or in part a debt of<lb/> which the creditor might have enforced payment but for the<lb/> law for the limitation of suits.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>Explanation 1.--Nothing in this section shall affect the<lb/> validity, as between the donor and donee, of any gift<lb/> actually made,<lb/> Explanation 2.--An agreement to which the consent of the<lb/> promisor is freely given is not void merely because the<lb/> consideration is inadequate; but the inadequacy of the<lb/> consideration may be taken into account by the Court in<lb/> determining the question whether the consent of the<lb/> promisor was freely given.&quot;<lb/> 29.<lb/> The Clause 16 of the agreement (in Writ Petition No. 934/94):-<lb/>&quot;16. It is hereby agreed between the parties hereto<lb/> that in the event of breach on the part of party no.2 of any of<lb/> themes expressed herein or his failure to comply with any of<lb/> the terms expressed herein mentioned the party no.1 will not<lb/> grant permission for constructing the buildings or any plot(s)<lb/> in this layout or in any part thereof.&quot;<lb/> 30.<lb/> The material Sections and Scheme of the Nagpur Improvement<lb/> Trust Act (the &quot;NIT Act&quot;) are :-<lb/>&quot;Section 58 : Power to purchase or lease land by<lb/> agreement:<lb/> The Trust may enter into an agreement with any person for the<lb/> acquisition, by purchase, lease or exchange by the Trust from such<lb/> person, of any land within the area comprised in a sanctioned scheme.&quot;<lb/> &quot;Section 68 : Abandonment of acquisition in<lb/> consideration of special payment :<lb/> 1)Wherever in any area comprised in any improvement scheme<lb/> under this Act the State Government has sanctioned the<lb/> acquisition of land which is subsequently discovered to be<lb/> unnecessary for the execution of the scheme, the owner of<lb/> the land, or any person having an interest therein may make<lb/> an application to the Trust (requesting that the acquisition of<lb/> the land not required for the purposes of the scheme should<lb/> be abandoned on his executing an agreement to observe<lb/> conditions specified by the Trust in respect of the<lb/> development of the property and to pay a charge to be<lb/> calculated in accordance with sub-section (2) of section 69 of<lb/> the Act.<lb/> 2) The Trust shall admit every such application if it --<lb/>a) reaches it before the time fixed by the Deputy<lb/> Commissioner under section 9 of the Land Acquisition Act,<lb/> 1894, for making claims in reference to the land, and<lb/> b) is made by any person who has an interest in the land or<lb/> holds a lease thereof, with an unexpired period of seven<lb/> years,<lb/> 3) On the admission by the Trust of any such application, it<lb/> shall forthwith inform the Deputy Commissioner, and the<lb/> Deputy Commissioner shall thereupon stay for a period of<lb/> three months all further proceedings for the acquisition of the<lb/> land, and the Trust shall proceed to fix the conditions on<lb/> which the acquisition of the land may be abandoned.<lb/> 4)When an agreement has been executed in pursuance of sub-<lb/>section (1) in respect of any land the proceedings for the<lb/> acquisition of the land shall be deemed to be abandoned,<lb/> 5)The provisions contained in sections 70, 71, 72, 73 and 74<lb/> relating to the assessment, interest, recovery and payment of<lb/> betterment charge and civil suits shall apply mutatis mutandis<lb/> to the assessment, interest, recovery and payment of<lb/> abandonment charge and civil suits in respect thereof.&quot;<lb/> &quot;S. 45. Notification of sanction of improvement scheme<lb/> and other regarding vesting of property in Trust :-<lb/>1) Whenever the State Government sanctions an improvement<lb/> scheme, it --<lb/>a) shall announce the fact by notification and, except in the<lb/> case of a deferred street scheme, development scheme,<lb/> or future expansion or improvement scheme, the Trust<lb/> shall forthwith proceed to execute the same,<lb/> b) may order that any street, square, park, open space or<lb/> other land, or any part thereof, which is the property of<lb/> the Government and managed by the Central<lb/> Government or the State Government shall, subject to<lb/> such conditions as it may impose, vest in the trust for<lb/> the purpose of the scheme.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>31.<lb/> NIT is created by the State Government for the improvement<lb/> of the city of Nagpur through its various improvement schemes.<lb/> Section 26 of the NIT Act empowers the Trust to frame various schemes.<lb/> Section 39 provides that such schemes framed by the NIT are required<lb/> to be published by notification. Section 39 is equivalent to Section 4<lb/> of the Land Acquisition Act. The provisions of Sections 40, 41, 42,<lb/> 43 &amp; 44 further clarify that the improvement schemes are sanctioned by<lb/> the Government by notification issued under Section 45 of the NIT Act<lb/> which is equivalent to Section 6 of the Land Acquisition Act. The<lb/> alteration/improvement to the scheme is permissible under Section 46<lb/> of the NIT Act. NIT, therefore, has jurisdiction over the areas/lands<lb/> which fall within the sanctioned improvement schemes being part and<lb/> parcel of notification under Section 6 which is equivalent to Section 45<lb/> of the NIT Act. Having once sanctioned the scheme by Government, the<lb/> NIT need to implement the said scheme as per the mandate of Section<lb/> 45 of the NIT Act. NIT thereafter can proceed to implement the scheme<lb/> by acquiring the entire land and further can use the said land for the<lb/> purpose of scheme. The Trust is further entitled to utilise/dispose of the<lb/> remaining land as per its Land Disposal Rules (for short &quot;the NIT<lb/> Rules&quot;). Section 76 of the NIT Act permits NIT to dispose of the land.<lb/> Section 76 reads as under :-<lb/>&quot;76. Power to dispose of land :-Subject to Rules made by<lb/> the State Government under this Act, the Trust may retain or<lb/> may let on hire, lease, sale, exchange or otherwise dispose of<lb/> any land vested in or acquired by it under this Act.&quot;<lb/> It is clear that Section 58 of NIT Act empowers/authorises the Trust to<lb/> enter into an agreement with any person for the acquisition, by<lb/> purchase, lease or exchange by the Trust from such person of land<lb/> within the area comprised in a sanctioned scheme.<lb/> 32.<lb/> In totality, the Act provides and permits NIT to enter into an<lb/> agreement with any person. The petitioner society and/or individual<lb/> person have accordingly knowing fully the scheme of NIT and purpose<lb/> and object of the same voluntarily without any influence and/or<lb/> misrepresentation of any kind by NIT, approached NIT and voluntarily<lb/> entered into the commercial transaction/agreement in question. The<lb/> application was moved/filed for sanction of the private layout. The said<lb/> private layout was sanctioned and the petitioner society/person in view<lb/> of the agreed terms acted upon and enjoyed all the benefits including<lb/> selling of the plots to its respective members.<lb/> The said plot<lb/> owners/members individually applied for obtaining sanction knowing<lb/> fully the terms and conditions of those clauses.<lb/> The subsequent<lb/> purchasers/members also understood the said clauses and obtained the<lb/> individual sanctions. The respective members/individual members have<lb/> further utilised the said plots/layouts and constructed the buildings/flats<lb/> and enjoyed all the benefits in view of the said agreement and sanction of<lb/> the private layout by NIT.<lb/> 33.<lb/> There is nothing on record to justify their challenge now to the<lb/> said agreements and basically the Clause. The petitioners are admittedly<lb/> not challenging the whole agreement. The petitioners have admittedly<lb/> acted upon and have been enjoying the benefits pursuant to the said<lb/> agreement till this date.<lb/> 34.<lb/> We have noted that there is no specific pleading as to how the<lb/> contract or the clause in the contract is void at the instance of the<lb/> petitioners, who entered into such commercial contract with full<lb/> knowledge of those clauses/conditions and factually acted upon the same<lb/> till the date. Therefore, in the absence of pleading, material and proof,<lb/> such plea is unacceptable. (State of Kerala &amp; another .vs. M.</figDesc>

            A. Mathai<lb/> (2007) 10 SCC 195) and Union of India .vs. Surjit Singh Atwal<lb/> (1979) 1 SCC 520.<lb/> 35.<lb/> The </content>
 
            <figDesc>present contract, unless set aside or declared to be void by<lb/> the Court, is binding especially to the parties who voluntarily entered into<lb/> such contracts acted upon and enjoyed all the benefits. </figDesc>

             Sultan Sadik<lb/> .vs. Sanjay Raj Subba and others (2004) 2 SCC 377, Velamuri<lb/> Venkata Sivaprasad (Dead), By Lrs. .vs. Kothuri Venkateswarlu,<lb/> (Dead) By Lrs. and others<lb/> (2000) 2 SCC 139, Tayyabbhai,<lb/> Mohammedbhai Bagasarwalla and </content>
 
            <figDesc>another 1997(2) Mh.L.J. 1.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>be unconscionable and void terms in contract as submitted based upon<lb/> Central Inland Water Transport Corporation Limited .vs. Brojonath<lb/> Ganguly reported in (1986) 3 SCC 156 &amp; LIC of India and another<lb/> .vs. Consumer Education and Research Centre and others reported in<lb/> (1995) 5 SCC 482. This can never be said to be an unconscionable<lb/> bargain as noted, the terms and conditions have been settled over the<lb/> years which are formed by consent with the persons having commercial</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            Premsingh and others .vs. Birbal and others (2006) 5 SCC 353,<lb/> Yamunabai Anatrao Adhav .vs. Anantrao Shivraj Adhav (1988) 1 SCC<lb/> 530 that there </content>
 
            <figDesc>is no need of a decree to set aside such document as<lb/> Clause 9/8 is void ab initio, especially when the agreement as well as<lb/> clause in question are clear and there is no ambiguity at any point of<lb/> time.<lb/> The nature of transaction in the background read with the<lb/> surrounding and attending circumstances and especially when the<lb/> document/agreement in question is a commercial document, in no way<lb/> said to be unclear or with any infirmity or ambiguity (</figDesc>

            State Bank of<lb/> India and another .vs. Mulla Sahakari Sakhar Karkhana Limited<lb/> (2006) 6 SCC 293, Sappani Mohammad Mohideen .vs. R.V.<lb/> Sethusubramania Pillai (1974) 1 SCC 615.<lb/> 38.<lb/> The </content>
 
            <figDesc>terms and conditions in questions are binding between the<lb/> parties. (Bihar State Electricity Board, Patna and others .vs. M/s.<lb/> Green Rubber Industries and others : AIR 1990 SC 699). They have<lb/> already acted upon those terms and conditions. Therefore, the entire<lb/> agreement need to be respected in totality. There is no question of<lb/> reading and/or severing any unequal clause in isolation or in parts. The<lb/> party to an agreement cannot be allowed to approbate and reprobate as<lb/> expressed by the Supreme Court in the case of Harshad </figDesc>
 Kumar<lb/> Natwarlal Dalal and others (1981) 1 SCC 538.<lb/> Paragraph 48 is<lb/> reproduced below :-<lb/>&quot;48. It </content>
 
            <figDesc>is a fundamental principle of general application that<lb/> if a person of his own accord, accepts a contract on certain<lb/> terms and works out the contract, he cannot be allowed to<lb/> adhere to and abide by some of the terms of the contract which<lb/> proved advantageous to him and repudiate the other terms of<lb/> the same contract which might be disadvantageous to him.<lb/> The maxim is qui approbat non reprobat (one who approbates<lb/> cannot reprobate). This principle, though originally borrowed<lb/> from Scots Law, is now firmly embodied in English Common<lb/> Law. According to it, a party to an instrument or transaction<lb/> cannot take advantage of one part of a document or transaction<lb/> and reject the rest. That is to say, no party can accept and<lb/> reject the same instrument or transaction (Per Scrutton, L.J.,<lb/> Verschures Creameries Ltd. v. Hull &amp; Netherlands Steamship<lb/> Co.; see Douglas Menzies v. Umphelby; see also Stroud&apos;s<lb/> Judicial Dictionary, Vol. I, page 169, 3 rd Edn.).<lb/> The Apex Court has further reiterated the principle of approbate and<lb/> reprobate and dismissed the matter on that count also. (Kashmir Singh<lb/> .vs. Union of India and other; (2008) 7 SCC 259).<lb/> 39.<lb/> In the case of Prem Singh and others .vs. Birbal and others<lb/> (2006) 5 SCC 353, the Supreme Court has held that with respect to<lb/> both void, as well as voidable transactions, the action has to be brought<lb/> within the period of limitation. We cannot overlook the fact that in the<lb/> present case, the petitioner has invoked Article 226 &amp; 227 of the<lb/> Constitution of India and raised these challenges after more than 11<lb/> years. Therefore, the facet of the period of limitation though not strictly<lb/> applicable to writ jurisdiction, still in cases like this the principle of filing<lb/> of suit for cancellation of such transaction as governed by Article 59 even<lb/> if any just cannot be overlooked. The relevant Articles of Limitation Act<lb/> are Article 58 (any declaration) or Article 59 (for cancellation or setting<lb/> aside of instrument) or Article 113 (residuary clause). Therefore, in all<lb/> these cases, limitation would not be more than 3 years. The petitions,<lb/> therefore, suffer from grave delay which is not explained at all. </figDesc>

             State of<lb/> Madhya Pradesh and another .vs. Bhailal Bhai and others AIR 1964<lb/> SC 1006.<lb/> 40.<lb/> The Apex Court </content>
 
            <figDesc>in State of Madhya Pradesh (supra) has<lb/> observed in paragraph no.21 as under :-<lb/>&quot;21.The learned Judges appear to have failed to notice that the<lb/> delay in these petitions was more than the delay in the petition<lb/> made in Bhailal Bhai&apos;s case, 1960 M.P.C. 304 out of which Civil<lb/> Appeal No. 362 of 62 has arisen. On behalf of the respondents-<lb/>petitioners in these appeals (C.A. Nos. 861 to 867 of 1962) Mr.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>cases on or shortly after January 17, 1956 the delay in making<lb/> these applications should be considered unreasonable. If, on<lb/> the other hand, as Mr. Andley seems to argue, that the mistake<lb/> discovered much later this would be a controversial fact which<lb/> cannot conveniently be decided in writ proceedings. In either<lb/> view of the matter, we are of opinion that the orders for refund<lb/> made by the High Court in these seven cases cannot be<lb/> sustained.&quot;<lb/> 41.<lb/> The Apex Court in Union of India .vs. Surjit Singh Atwal<lb/> reported in (1979) 1 SCC 520 refused to allow plea of illegality of the<lb/> agreement after 13 years even in a civil suit. In the present facts and<lb/> circumstances, there is no case at all to allow to raise such pleas restricted<lb/> only to the Clause of the agreement after more than 13 to 20 years. It is<lb/> not correct submission that no limitation would be applicable in the event<lb/> the transaction/agreement is void (Prem Singh (supra). In the present<lb/> case, the challenge is raised by invoking the writ jurisdiction only to the<lb/> Clause of the binding agreement. It is not the case like a decree being<lb/> void or nullity at the inception as a whole. The Apex Court has further<lb/> clarified in Eastern Coalfields Limited .vs. Dugal Kumar; 2008 (10)<lb/> SCALE 449 that the delay or laches on the part of the petitioner can be<lb/> considered at the time of final hearing also whether relief should be<lb/> granted in favour of such petitioner or not. Inordinate delay, in the<lb/> present case, is also an additional factor to refuse to exercise discretion in<lb/> favour of the petitioner.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>is void, in view of provisions contained under Section 23/25 of the<lb/> Indian Contract Act being opposed to public policy; violative of<lb/> fundamental rights of the petitioner; violative of the right of property of<lb/> petitioner/society; because of unequal bargain power; being forbidden by<lb/> law and further in view of Section 25 of the Contract Act, as the<lb/> agreement to transfer is without consideration and the same was not<lb/> registered, have no force.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            of both the parties.<lb/> 46.<lb/> The doctrine/</content>

            <figDesc>principle of waiver, while referring to an earlier<lb/> judgment reported in 1959 Supp 2 SCR 217 (Waman Shriniwas Keni<lb/> versus Ratilal Bhagwandas &amp; Company) has been defined by the Hon&apos;ble<lb/> Apex Court in Paragraph No.5 in the case of Diwan Singh .versus.<lb/> Champat Singh &amp; Ors., reported in 1969 (3) SCC 445 as below :<lb/> &quot;waiver is the abandonment of a right which normally<lb/> everybody is at liberty to waive. A waiver is nothing else it amounts to<lb/> release. It signifies nothing more than an intention not to insist upon the<lb/> right.&quot;<lb/> 47.<lb/> The Apex Court in the case of Satyanarayan versus Yelloji Rao,<lb/> AIR 1965 Supreme Court, 1405 has explained the said principle in<lb/> Paragraph No.11, as below :-<lb/>&quot;We have used the expression waiver in its legally accepted<lb/> sense, namely,<lb/> &quot;waiver is contractual, and may constitute a cause of action: it<lb/> is an agreement to release or not to assert a right.&quot;<lb/> 48.<lb/> The principle of waiver is based on the maxim of law &quot;quilibet<lb/> potest renunciare juir pro se introducto&quot; which means, &quot;an individual may<lb/> renounce a law made for his special benefit&quot;. (Reference : 1994 </figDesc>
 (4) SCC<lb/> 422.<lb/> 49.<lb/> The Apex Court </content>
 
            <figDesc>in Sikkim Subba Associates vs. State of<lb/> Sikkim reported in (2001) 5 SCC 629 further elaborated and reiterated<lb/> the meaning of &quot;waiver&quot; and &quot;consideration&quot; in reference to an<lb/> agreement with the State in following words by observing that &quot;he who<lb/> seeks equity must do equity&quot; :-<lb/>&quot;Waiver involves a conscious, voluntary and<lb/> intentional relinquishment or abandonment of a known,<lb/> existing legal right, advantage, benefit, claim or privilege,</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>upon and now avoiding to perform their part of the obligations by<lb/> challenging the Clause of the agreement without any basic pleading and<lb/> prayer. The submission, therefore, that there was no consideration paid<lb/> or received by the person like the petitioner has no force. The reciprocal<lb/> obligation, in the facts and circumstances of the case, itself falls within<lb/> the ambit of the term &quot;consideration&quot; as per the Contract Act. Knowing<lb/> fully the terms and conditions both the parties have abandoned and<lb/> waived their various rights and acted upon the said agreement<lb/> voluntarily; firstly, by surrendering the portion of the land to the Trust<lb/> voluntarily for public purpose. NIT has released the property from<lb/> acquisition which was admittedly notified pursuant to Sections 31, 37 &amp;<lb/> 46 of the NIT Act. There is no dispute that as per Section 45 of the NIT<lb/> Act, once the land/scheme is notified which is conclusively of duly<lb/> formed and sanctioned scheme, NIT pursuant to this policy and<lb/> agreement permitted the person like the petitioner to develop the layouts<lb/> ::: on -18/03/2022 19:40:43 :::<lb/> and further permitted to be sub-divided into plots. In totality, the object<lb/> of releasing the property from acquisition and then getting the same<lb/> portion of land from the land owner. The Trust has been utilising and<lb/> allotting the said portion of surrendered land for charitable and public<lb/> purpose. There is nothing to show that the sanctioned scheme and/or<lb/> lands and layouts are contrary to the development plan. In view of this,<lb/> there is no force in contention that the agreement and/or clause is void<lb/> for want of consideration and it is beyond or opposed to public policy.<lb/> 50.<lb/> In Babulal Verma .vs. Surat Municipal Corporation reported<lb/> in 2008 (3) SCALE 206 : In Halsbury&apos;s Law of England, Volume 16(2) 4 th<lb/> Edition, para 907, it is stated :-<lb/>&quot;The expression &apos;waiver&apos; may, in law, bear different<lb/> meanings. The primary meaning has been said to be the<lb/> abandonment of a right in such a way that the other party is<lb/> entitled to plead the abandonment by way of confession and<lb/> avoidance if the right is thereafter asserted, and is either<lb/> express or implied from conduct. It may arise from a party<lb/> making an election, for example whether or not to exercise a<lb/> contractual right... Waiver may also be by virtue of equitable<lb/> or promissory estoppel; unlike waiver arising from an election,<lb/> no question arises of any particular knowledge on the part of<lb/> the person making the representation, and the estoppel may be<lb/> suspensory only.... Where the waiver is not express, it may be<lb/> implied from conduct which is inconsistent with the<lb/> continuance of the right, without the need for writing or for<lb/> consideration moving from, or detriment to, the party who<lb/> benefits by the waiver, but mere acts of indulgence will not<lb/> amount to waiver, nor may a party benefit from the waiver<lb/> unless he has altered his position in reliance on it.&quot;<lb/> In the present case, as we have noted both the parties have altered their<lb/> position. The petitioners have already got the benefit out of the same.<lb/> This is a case of express waiver. The legal principle emerging from these<lb/> decisions is also stated in Craies on Statute Law (6 th Edn.) at page 369 as<lb/> follows :-<lb/>&quot;As a general rule, the conditions imposed by statutes<lb/> which authorise legal proceedings are treated as being<lb/> indispensable to giving the court jurisdiction. But if it<lb/> appears that the statutory conditions were inserted by the<lb/> legislature simply for the security or benefit of the parties to<lb/> the action themselves, and that no public interests are<lb/> involved, such conditions will not be considered as<lb/> indispensable, and either party may waive them without<lb/> affecting the jurisdiction of the court.&quot;<lb/> Applying the above principles to the present case, it must be<lb/> held that the benefit of notice provided under the Act and Rules being for<lb/> the benefit of the Appellant in which no public interests are involved, he<lb/> has waived the same.&quot;</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>10. A right can be waived by the party for whose benefit<lb/> certain requirements or conditions had been provided for by a<lb/> statute subject to the condition that no public interest is<lb/> involved therein. Whenever waiver is pleaded it is for the<lb/> party pleading the same to show that an agreement waiving<lb/> the right in consideration of some compromise came into<lb/> being. Statutory right, however, may also be waived by his<lb/> conduct.&quot;<lb/> [See also Bank of India v. O.P. Swarnakar (2003) 2 SCC<lb/> 721].</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>It was on that legal principle, this Court in State of Gujarat v.<lb/> Shantilal Mangaldas &amp; others [1969 (3) SCR 341], opined<lb/> that when a development is made, the owner of the property<lb/> gets much more than what would have he got, if the same<lb/> remained undeveloped in the process as by reason thereof he<lb/> gets the benefit of living in a developed town having good<lb/> town planning.&quot;<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> (emphasis added).<lb/> 54.<lb/> In Ranganayakamma and another v. K.S. Prakash (D) by<lb/> L.Rs. and others (JT 2008 (8) SC </content>
 
            <figDesc>510) in reference to Sections 23 &amp; 25<lb/> of the Contract Act, 1872 the Apex Court has elaborated the aspect of<lb/> &quot;consideration&quot; including nominal and inadequate consideration as<lb/> under:-<lb/>&quot;49. Mr. Chandrasekhar, however, has drawn our attention to</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            states :<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <head>&quot;</head>

            <figDesc>Nominal consideration&apos; and &apos;nominal sum&apos; appear...... as terms of<lb/> art, to refer to a sum as consideration which can be mentioned as<lb/> consideration but is not necessarily paid.......&quot;<lb/> &quot;50. The same principle might have been applied in the Indian<lb/> Contract Act, &quot;Consideration&quot; has been defined in Section 2(d) of the<lb/> Indian Contract Act, which reads as under :-<lb/>&quot;(d) When, at the desire of the promisor, the promisee or any<lb/> other person has done or abstained from doing, or does or abstains from<lb/> doing, or promises to do or to abstain from doing, something, such act or<lb/> abstinence or promise is called a consideration for the promise.&quot;<lb/> &quot;51. Consideration even in the Indian context would mean a<lb/> reasonable equivalent or other valuable benefit passed on by the promisor<lb/> to the promisee or by the transferor to the transferee. Love and affection<lb/> is also a consideration within the meaning of Sections 122 and 123 of the<lb/> Transfer of Property Act.&quot;<lb/> 55.<lb/> In Writ Petition No. 3208/89 Pragati Housing Society .vs.<lb/> Nagpur Improvement Trust, a Division Bench of this Court by order<lb/> dated 7.2.1990 after considering the similar rival contentions observed as<lb/> under :<lb/> &quot;Having obtained sanction on that basis it is impermissible<lb/> for the petitioners to go behind the same. There is nothing<lb/> illegal in the agreement. The property vests by surrender in<lb/> the Trust for the limited purpose of having a planned<lb/> development. Under the circumstances, no question of<lb/> paying compensation by the Trust can arise. Provisions<lb/> relating to acquisition and payment of compensation<lb/> (Section 56 of the Nagpur Improvement Trust Act) are not<lb/> attracted in such surrenders.&quot;<lb/> In Writ Petition No. 539/94, another Division Bench of this<lb/> Court by order dated 14.6.1996 considering the similar agreements and<lb/> challenge rejected the Writ Petition by observing as under :-<lb/>&quot;(A) As per the initial agreement with the Nagpur<lb/> Improvement Trust on 5.2.1971 vide Clause 9, it was<lb/> specifically agreed by the petitioner society to hand over the<lb/> public utility plots in favour of the Nagpur Improvement<lb/> Trust free of costs. The validity of the said clause has not<lb/> been challenged at the relevant time.&quot;<lb/> It is worth to mention that this Court in Writ Petition No.<lb/> 2978/98 while considering the similar agreement under the Maharashtra<lb/> Municipalality Act, 1965 whereby the person like the petitioners agreed<lb/> to hand over 10% of the land free of cost to respondent no.1, the<lb/> Amravati Municipal Corporation and State Corporation to retain<lb/> possession for public purpose, it was specifically provided that the<lb/> petitioner shall have no right or ownership on the said land. Another<lb/> agreement was entered between the parties. The said plot was thereafter<lb/> allotted to other society like the petitioners and leased out for 30 years on<lb/> nominal rent. The petitioner thereafter based upon Pandit Chetram case<lb/> raised quite similar points. A Division Bench based upon the agreements<lb/> rejected the similar contentions in that petition also on the ground of<lb/> estoppel. The Civil Appeal Nos. 3389/2000 and 3390/2000 Ganesh<lb/> Sahakari .vs. Amravati Municipal Corporation against the said<lb/> judgment were also dismissed by the Supreme Court by order dated<lb/> 3.8.2005.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>for public purpose and/or acquisition of portion of land for public<lb/> purpose is not an unknown phenomenon. In M.C. Mehta .vs. Union of<lb/> India &amp; others (1996) 4 SCC 351, the Supreme Court has issued<lb/> direction that land which would become available on account of shifting<lb/> and relocation of hazardous industries from the city of Delhi shall be used<lb/> in the manner as provided for in the said judgment, thereby the land<lb/> owner was declared to develop a portion of the said land after<lb/> surrendering and deducting to the Delhi Development Authority, a<lb/> portion of the land for development of green belts and other places. The<lb/> land which was required to be surrendered was upto 68%. The Apex<lb/> Court rejecting the case of landowners for compensation in lieu of<lb/> surrender of portion of land declined the said compensation on the<lb/> ground that the FSI permitted to be used on the land retained by the<lb/> owner was 1.5% of the permissible FSI and hence the same was a<lb/> consideration for surrendering the land. (M.C. Mehta .vs. </figDesc>

             Union of<lb/> India &amp; others 2000 (5) SCC 525). The Apex Court in Bombay Dyeing<lb/> &amp; Manufacturing Company Limited .vs. Bombay Environmental<lb/> Action Group and others (2006) 3 SCC </content>
 
            <figDesc>434 has upheld the Clauses of<lb/> the Development Control Rules, 1958 applicable to Bombay which<lb/> provide for surrender of the land if the landholder seeks to develop the<lb/> remaining land for other purposes as provided under the Rules.<lb/> The<lb/> decision as relied in Vrajlal Jinabhai Patel, since deceased through his<lb/> L.Rs. Smt. Jagrati Vrajlal Patel and another .vs. State of Maharashtra<lb/> and others 2003(3) Mh.L.J. 215 to submit that an ownership in open<lb/> space under the layout could be vested or transferred to the Municipal<lb/> Council is not applicable on facts and circumstances as referred above.<lb/> This is not a case also where there is any question of blocking and<lb/> encroachment upon the open space and plot or area of the locality. The<lb/> respondents State and/or NIT are bound to stick to the development plan<lb/> and scheme as announced. The Apex Court in Chairman, Indore Vikas<lb/> Pradhikaran .vs. Pure Industrial Coke &amp; Chemicals Limited and<lb/> others (2007) 8 SCC 705 while dealing with the aspect of Town<lb/> Planning and Articles 300-A, 14 &amp; 17 of the Constitution of India has also<lb/> observed :<lb/> &quot;...........The courts must make an endeavour to strike a<lb/> balance between the public interest on the one hand and<lb/> protection of a constitutional right to hold property, on the<lb/> other. For the aforementioned purpose, an endeavour should<lb/> be made to find out as to whether the statute takes care of<lb/> public interest in the matter vis-a-vis the private interest, on<lb/> the one hand, and the effect of lapse and/or positive inaction<lb/> on the part of the State and other planning authorities, on the<lb/> other.&quot;<lb/> NIT or such other local authority need to consider the purpose, scheme,<lb/> development plan and the circular issued from time to time by striking a<lb/> balance of public and private interest. The petitioners are bound by the<lb/> agreement and undertaking as given. In fact, both the parties are bound<lb/> by the agreements. In totality the permissible action of respondent NIT<lb/> is within the frame of law and the record. There is no substance in these<lb/> petitions.<lb/> 57.<lb/> Furthermore, factually, the Clause of the agreement is not<lb/> void and illegal for want of consideration. After considering the whole<lb/> scheme of the NIT Act and especially Sections 29 to 70 &amp; 121 read with<lb/> the agreement entered into by the parties shows that the said agreement<lb/> creates reciprocal rights/obligations with following major objects as<lb/> rightly contended by the learned Counsel appearing for<lb/> respondents/allottees.<lb/> (a) Abandonment of the land from acquisition of NIT,<lb/> (b)Permission to develop the said land and sanction of a scheme of a<lb/> layout therein,<lb/> (c) Entrustment of the job of supervision of such development on NIT,<lb/> (d) Transfer of the public utility land, reserved in the said layout, to the<lb/> NIT,<lb/> (e) immediate and reciprocal permission to develop the land by making a<lb/> layout in the said land and permission to sell plots therein, i.e.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>voluntarily.<lb/> The quantum of consideration and/or nature of<lb/> consideration cannot be permitted to be agitated now in the Writ<lb/> Petitions. It is the mutual understanding based upon the total terms and<lb/> conditions of the said agreement. There is no question of any registration<lb/> in this background of the matter. NIT as per scheme wants to reallot or<lb/> lease out for public purpose, these public utility plots. The submission<lb/> that theory of waiver of right to receive compensation for the said land<lb/> still results in void agreement is not correct. In this background, the<lb/> Apex Court decision as relied, in Waman Shriniwas Kini .vs. Ratilal<lb/> Bhagwandas &amp; Co. 1959 Supp. (2) SCC 217 = AIR 1959 SC 689 is of<lb/> no assistance.<lb/> The law and principle of Sections 23 &amp; 25 is not in<lb/> dispute. The agitation is the applicability of those principles to the facts<lb/> and circumstances of the present case. There is nothing to justify that the<lb/> plea of waiver cannot be raised in the present case. There is nothing<lb/> opposed to public policy in the present case. It is not the case that the<lb/> whole agreement is against the public policy, but only the clause which is<lb/> said to be void. The clause as referred above is interconnected and<lb/> provides intermixed obligations and conditions, voluntarily entered into<lb/> by the parties.<lb/> 62.<lb/> In Pandit Chet Ram (supra), there was no occasion in that<lb/> case to consider the agreement like present one whereby the parties<lb/> themselves already acted upon and enjoyed the benefits.<lb/> The<lb/> consideration so got by the petitioners in lieu of so-called compensation is<lb/> already elaborated and especially when they themselves agreed for the<lb/> same, that itself distinguishes the facts and circumstances of the present<lb/> case with that of Pandit Chet Ram.<lb/> There was no such voluntary agreement involved in the said<lb/> matter. The said challenge is raised only by a very few people of the<lb/> society. Most of them have enjoyed the benefits of the the NIT scheme.<lb/> NIT pursuant to their scheme instead of acquiring the land sanctioned<lb/> permitted the petitioners to enjoy the position and utilised the same for<lb/> their individual members&apos; benefit by keeping their power and authority to<lb/> allot the already declared public utility plots to the educational<lb/> institutions and/or public Trusts by following the due procedure of law of<lb/> advertisement. Such facts were not in the background of Pandit Chetram<lb/> case. Supreme Court has dealt with sub-section (3) of Section 313 of<lb/> Delhi Municipal Corporation Act.<lb/> Even the case of Pandit Chetram<lb/> (supra) was considered and the challenge was negatived long back by<lb/> accepting the case of respondents in identically placed facts and<lb/> circumstances of the case.<lb/> 63.<lb/> The same is the case in Yogendra Pal (supra). The facts and<lb/> circumstances of the said Supreme Court case are also different and<lb/> distinguishable in view of the reasoning given in view of above paras.<lb/> Such agreements cannot be said to be violative of fundamental rights of<lb/> persons like the petitioners and/or opposed to public policy. It is not in<lb/> breach of any rights as guaranteed under Article 31 and Article 300-A as<lb/> submitted by the petitioners. The Apex Court&apos;s decisions in Central<lb/> Inland Water Transport Corporation Ltd. .vs. Brojonath Ganguly<lb/> (1986) 3 SCC 156 and LIC of India and another .vs. Consumer<lb/> Education and Research Centre and others (1995) 5 SCC 482 are,<lb/> therefore, also of no assistance to the petitioner. The doctrine and<lb/> principle as laid down is in no dispute. The facts and circumstances of<lb/> that case and present case makes the position distinct and<lb/> distinguishable. In Yogendrapal (supra), there was challenge to the<lb/> provisions of the Punjab Municipal Act. There is no challenge in the<lb/> present case at any point of time to the provisions as well as to the<lb/> scheme as announced by the respondent NIT at relevant time and till this<lb/> date. The petitioners have in fact agreed voluntarily and enjoyed the<lb/> benefits and after so many years restricting their challenge only to the<lb/> Clause of the agreement whereby they are refusing to perform their part<lb/> of reciprocal obligations which were basic terms and conditions of the<lb/> consent contract as respondent NIT has already acted upon the said<lb/> conditions and sanctioned the plot and further layouts upon which<lb/> respective members and/or even third persons have constructed the<lb/> building. As noted, the land could have been acquired by NIT but for the<lb/> policy and the agreement it was permitted to retain with the petitioners<lb/> on condition of leaving the portion in question for reallotment for the<lb/> educational or other institutions.<lb/> 64.<lb/> The aspect of resolution passed by the petitioners (in W.P. No.<lb/> 937/93) and others whereby they agreed/resolved to surrender public<lb/> utility plot pursuant to the said agreement just cannot be overlooked<lb/> while considering the challenges as raised by the petitioners in the<lb/> present petition. The petitioners cannot blow hot and cold like this,<lb/> especially after such long time and in the petitions like this merely<lb/> because respondent NIT is also a &apos;State&apos; falling within the meaning of<lb/> Article 12 of the Constitution of India.<lb/> 65.<lb/> There is force in the submission raised by the respondents that<lb/> they are estopped from challenging the agreement. The doctrine of<lb/> estoppel of acquiescence in challenging the only clause 9/8 of the<lb/> agreement is squarely applicable. The Apex Court in P.S. Gopinath .vs.<lb/> State of Kerala &amp; others : 2008(4) SCC 85,<lb/> has rejected such<lb/> petitions/action of person like the petitioner based upon this doctrine<lb/> itself.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>agreement is incorrect. Clause 16 read with Clause 9 and whole<lb/> agreement only makes the contract valid and binding to the parties,<lb/> especially when all the parties pursuant to the same agreed and acted<lb/> upon uninterruptedly knowing fully the provisions of law, the power of<lb/> NIT and their respective obligations. As noted, Clause 9 of agreement is<lb/> not severable from the rest of the clauses. All are inter-connected and<lb/> interlinked and, therefore, the persons like petitioners have enjoyed all<lb/> the benefits out of the same. The challenge after more than 10 to 15<lb/> years to the said Clause by relying on doctrine of &apos;blue pencil&apos; </figDesc>

             or severance<lb/> is totally impermissible.<lb/> (Beed District Central Cooperative Bank<lb/> Limited .vs. State of Maharashtra and others reported in (2006) 8<lb/> SCC 514) &amp; Shin Satallite Public Company Limited .vs. Jain Studios<lb/> Limited reported in (2006) 2 SCC </content>
 
            <figDesc>628 are totally not applicable in the<lb/> facts and circumstances of the present case. The whole agreement is not<lb/> challenged and having enjoyed the benefits because at that time the<lb/> petitioners and such other persons thought it to be valid now cannot<lb/> invoke the doctrine of severability to the terms by ignoring the terms and<lb/> the whole agreement. The submission that this Clause/actions are no<lb/> actions in the eyes of law and do not create any right or obligation in the<lb/> parties and, therefore, severable is not correct and impermissible. We are<lb/> of the view that there is no ambiguity in the clause of the agreement. All<lb/> clauses are clear. The background, the intention of the parties at the<lb/> relevant time and surrounding circumstances apart from the conduct of<lb/> the parties is sufficient to reject this contention.<lb/> Reliance on State of<lb/> India and another .vs. Mulla Sahakari Sakhar Karkhana Limited<lb/> (2006) 6 SCC 293 and Sappani Mohammad Mohideen .vs. R.V.<lb/> Sethusubramania Pillai (1974) 1 SCC 615 are of no assistance because<lb/> of distinguishable facts and circumstances.<lb/> 70.<lb/> The petitioner even now has gone to the extent of saying after<lb/> enjoying the whole fruit of the said agreement that the society has no<lb/> title in the said P.U. Plots and the plot holders have undivided shares<lb/> and, therefore, the resolution passed by the society was also without any<lb/> authority and is of no consequence to surrender the said land by the<lb/> society as it would be without authority. This itself shows the whole<lb/> conduct of the petitioner and its members. It is difficult to accept such<lb/> pleas as agitated in the present matter at the instance of such petitioners.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>authority to advertise and allot the plots in favour of allottee respondents<lb/> or such other public Trusts or such institutions.<lb/> 72.<lb/> NIT, right from its inception, has disposed of the public utility<lb/> land in the layouts of NIT from time to time. It is further submitted that<lb/> near about 99.9% of the allottees have accepted and acted upon the<lb/> agreement and accordingly, NIT has allotted the lands to the allottees<lb/> adhering to the Rules.<lb/> The petitioners themselves had filed an<lb/> application for allotment of the public utility lands to them and as they<lb/> are not qualified as per the Land Disposal Rules, they have approached<lb/> this Court in seeking the declaration that the lands should be allotted to<lb/> them. The petitioners have not challenged any clause or any rule of the<lb/> Rules. It is submitted that the allotment is being made strictly in<lb/> consonance to the Rules.<lb/> NIT after giving an advertisement, invites<lb/> applications from the charitable or educational institutions as per the<lb/> terms and conditions of the advertisement.<lb/> Those applications are<lb/> scrutinized and the Board of the Nagpur Improvement Trust recommends<lb/> the allotment to be made in favour of the prospective allottees. The said<lb/> recommendations have been got approved from the Government in view<lb/> of Rule 20 of the Rules and on approval of the Government, the said<lb/> Printers Guild, Manav Uttam Sewa Samiti, Eastern Sports Club, Punjab<lb/> Sewa Samaj, Shri Radhakrishna Charitable Trust, Shioprasad Poddar<lb/> Charitable Trust, Shri Charottar Patidar Samaj, Mathadi Hamal and Area<lb/> Transport Works Union, Nagpur General Works Union, Parampujya<lb/> Parmatma Ek Sewak Mandal, Steel and Hardware Chamber of<lb/> Commerce, Nag Vidarbha Chamber of Commerce, Lohana Mahajan<lb/> Samaj, Hariyana Nagrik Sangh, Vidarbha Dal Miller Association, Sugar<lb/> Vachanalaya, Mrugwa Swami Vyayam Shala, Nagpur Gujarathi Kewalani<lb/> Mandal, Indian Red Cross Society, Gurunanak Sindhi Hindi Vidya Samiti,<lb/> Shri Chokhamela Samaj Girl&apos;s High School, Sikh Education Society,<lb/> Bhartiya Boudha Mahasabha, Nagpur Bidi Majdoor Sangh, Gondwana<lb/> Vikas Mandal, Bharat Sewak Samaj/Cancer Relief Society, Nagpur Nagar<lb/> Akhada Sanghtan Samiti, Employees State Insurance Corporation, Indian<lb/> Cancer Relief Society, Bhartiya Boudhajan Mahasabha. It is not the case<lb/> in the facts and circumstances of the case that the respondent NIT by this<lb/> policy and scheme has unjustly enriched itself. The whole action is in the<lb/> interest of public at large.<lb/> 73.<lb/> The reliance on Supreme Court judgments; that alternative<lb/> remedy is no bar (Assistant Collector of Central Excise .vs. Jaison<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> Hosiery Industries (1979) 4 SCC 22, Popcorn Entertainment and<lb/> another .vs. SIDCO and another 2007(9) SCC 593 and Whirlpool<lb/> Corporation .vs. Registrar of Trademarks, Mumbai and others (1998)<lb/> 8 SCC 1) </content>
 
            <figDesc>and; Writ Petition in the sphere of contracts though needed<lb/> detailed investigation, High Court may exercise jurisdiction under Article<lb/> 226; Hindustan Petroleum Corporation Ltd. and another .vs. Dolly<lb/> Das (1994) 4 SCC 450 and Himmatlal .vs. State of M.P. AIR 1954 SC<lb/> 403 would also not assist the petitioner to support his case for the relief<lb/> as claimed in the facts and circumstances of the case itself.<lb/> 74.<lb/> The additional vague challenge is about the validity of Rule 20<lb/> of the Land Disposal Rules of NIT. Considering the scheme and purpose<lb/> of NIT Act and in view of the above reasons given, there is no substance in<lb/> this challenge also. The same is within the framework of law. For the<lb/> above reasons, the G.R. dated 10.6.1996 as relied in Writ Petition No.</figDesc>
        </figure>



    </text>
</tei>

