<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_358c2215280a80b31e2c37509d227d83.pdf"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">


		<figure type="table">

            <table>1. Nagpur Improvement Trust,<lb/> through its Chairman, Near<lb/> Liberty Cinema Building, Sadar,<lb/> Nagpur.<lb/> 2. Vidarbha Cricket Association,<lb/> Opp. I. B. M. Building, Sadar,<lb/> Nagpur through its President.<lb/> RESPONDENTS.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>Shri A. R. Patil, Counsel for the petitioner.<lb/> Shri S. K. Mishra, Counsel for respondent No. 1.<lb/> Shri A. S. Jaiswal, Counsel for respondent No. 2.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>(11)<lb/> WRIT PETITION NO. 1070 OF 2000<lb/> Friends Cooperative Housing<lb/> Society Ltd. Nagpur, duly registered<lb/> under the Maharashtra Cooperative<lb/> Societies Act, 1960, bearing<lb/> Registration No. HSG/NGP/123 of<lb/> 1962, having its registered office at<lb/> 41, Tatya Tope Nagar, Nagpur-15,<lb/> through its Secretary.<lb/> PETITIONER.<lb/> VERSUS<lb/> 1. The Nagpur Improvement Trust,<lb/> through its Chairman, Civil<lb/> Lines, Nagpur.<lb/> 2. The State of Maharashtra,<lb/> through its Secretary,<lb/> Department of Urban Land<lb/> Development, Mantralaya,<lb/> Annexe, Mumbai-32.<lb/> 3. The Nagpur Municipal<lb/> Corporation, Nagpur,<lb/> through its Municipal<lb/> Commissioner.<lb/> RESPONDENTS.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>Shri. U. S. Dastane, Counsel for the petitioner.<lb/> Mr. A.S. Fulzele, A.G.P. for respondent no.2,<lb/> Shri S.K. Mishra, Counsel for respondent No.1.<lb/> <note>(12)<lb/> WRIT PETITION NO. 5145 OF 2007.<lb/> The Greater Nagpur Cooperative<lb/> Development and Housing Society<lb/> Limited, having its Head Office at<lb/> 51, Alhad Jyoti Apartment, Ramkrishna<lb/> Nagar, Khamla, Nagpur-25, through<lb/> its President Chandrashekhar K.<lb/> Najpande, R/o Ramkrishna Nagar,<lb/> Khamla, Nagpur-25.<lb/> ....<lb/> PETITIONER.<lb/> ....Versus....<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>1. State of Maharashtra, through its<lb/> Secretary to the Urban Development<lb/> Departments, Mantralaya, Mumbai-32,<lb/> 2. Nagpur Improvement Trust, through<lb/> its Secretary, having its office at<lb/> Kingsway, Sadar, Nagpur,<lb/> 3. The Corporation of the City of Nagpur,<lb/> through its Commissioner, having its<lb/> Office at Civil Lines, Nagpur,<lb/> 4. Sneh Manila Vikas Sanstha, through<lb/> its Secretary, Nagpur.<lb/> ....<lb/> RESPONDENTS.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>Mr. Anand Parchure, Advocate for the petitioner,<lb/> Mrs. K.S. Joshi, A.G.P. for respondent no.1,<lb/> Mr. S.K. Mishra, Counsel for respondent no.2,<lb/> Mr. S.V. Manohar, Counsel for respondent no.4.</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>18.<lb/> In Writ Petition No. 1136/93 the petitioner has challenged the<lb/> action of respondent based upon the agreement dated 11/3/1970 in<lb/> question, executed between the petitioner and respondent NIT. The<lb/> petitioner Society was formed and registered under Maharashtra<lb/> Cooperative Societies Act vide registration No. NGP/HSG/202. The<lb/> object of the Society is to provide houses/Flats to its Members. On<lb/> 17/9/1966, in furtherance of the object of the Society, the Society<lb/> purchased land in S.No.90/3 admeasuring 11.84 acres in village Ajni,<lb/> P.H.No.9 from Shri S.S.Mahajan of Nagpur. On 20/9/1962, the vendor<lb/> Shri S.S. Mahajan had already obtained permission from S.D.O., Nagpur<lb/> for converting this land for non-agricultural use. On 16/1/1969 the land<lb/> in question came within the purview of Ajni Street Scheme of Respondent<lb/> No.1 and sanctioned by State Government. On 11/3/1970, an Agreement<lb/> was executed between the petitioner society and the N.I.T. for sanction of<lb/> layout as the land came under the control of Respondent no.1 because of<lb/> sanctioned Street Scheme. Thereafter layout was sanctioned.<lb/> On<lb/> 13/2/1993, respondent no.1 issued a notice asking the petitioner Society<lb/> to demolish the structure constructed on public utility plot marked A in<lb/> Site Plan, which was constructed for library. Similar notice was being<lb/> issued on 15/12/1990 also which was replied by petitioner society on<lb/> 27/12/1990. In March, 1993, NIT demolished the structure marked &apos;A&apos;<lb/> in the site plan. Hence this petition, challenging the action of respondent<lb/> no.1 of selling/leasing out the plot to respondent no.2, on similar<lb/> grounds.<lb/> 19.<lb/> In Writ Petition No. 2322/92, the petitioner has challenged<lb/> the action of respondent based upon the agreement dated 20/8/1973 in<lb/> question executed between the petitioner and respondent NIT. As per<lb/> petitioner, on 19/10/1954, the petitioner and Mr. Patil purchased an<lb/> agricultural field by a registered sale deed from its original owner. On<lb/> 2/1/1964, the said field diverted to non-agricultural use by the<lb/> permission of the S.D.O. Nagpur. On 20/8/1973, the agreement was<lb/> executed between the petitioner Shri Patil and respondent no.2. On<lb/> 23/2/1984, respondent no.2 published an advertisement in news paper<lb/> &apos;Lokmat&quot; invited the offers from the public for allotting the said public<lb/> utility land. On 16/3/1985, the petitioner wrote a letter to Executive<lb/> Officer, NIT Nagpur regarding the advertisement.<lb/> On 4/10/1992,<lb/> respondent no.2 and 3 again issued a letter to petitioner asking to<lb/> handover the possession. The petitioner replied to the letter dated<lb/> 4/10/1992. On 4/9/1992, respondent no.4 has informed the circle<lb/> Engineer -II that it is holding possession of the public utility and open<lb/> land. Hence, this petition on identical grounds with other writ petitions.<lb/> 20.<lb/> In Writ Petition No. 822/99, the petitioner Cooperative<lb/> Housing Society has challenged the action of respondent no.1 NIT of<lb/> allotting a plot in favour of respondent No. 2 pursuance to an agreement<lb/> dated 27/01/1970 between petitioner and NIT. The petitioner is the<lb/> Cooperative Housing Society registered under the Maharashtra<lb/> Cooperative Societies Act, 1960 having its registration No. 1265, working<lb/> since last 38 years. The petitioner had developed four lay outs in Nagpur<lb/> City. All these layouts are approved and sanctioned by the NIT. The</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <figDesc>view of the above reasons, all the Writ Petition Nos. 934/94,<lb/> 967/92, 1179/93, 3085/93, 1784/92, 1034/95, 1512/2000, 1136/93,<lb/> 2322/92, 822/99, 1070/2000 &amp; 5145/07 are dismissed. Interim order so<lb/> granted also stands vacated. No order as to costs.</figDesc>
		</figure>



    </text>
</tei>

