<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_3a7e1eaac4a793bf8c475d0d2e1e8038.pdf"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">


        <figure>

            4.<lb/> On 4-9-</content>

            <figDesc>2006, this Court (in fact, I) delivered a judgment in<lb/> Ahuja S/o Nandkishore Dongre Vs. State of Maharashtra and another,<lb/> reported at 2006 ALL MR (Cri) 3357, in respect of jurisdiction in cases of<lb/> offence punishable under Section 138 of the Negotiable Instruments Act,</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>learned counsel for the respondent further submitted that in face of my<lb/> judgment in Ahuja Nandkishore Dongre&apos;s case, which was binding on the<lb/> learned Magistrate, the Magistrate could not have decided the case<lb/> differently.<lb/> 8.<lb/> In this factual context, the rival contentions would have to<lb/> be examined. The learned counsel for the appellant is correct in contending<lb/> that if the learned Magistrate held that he had no jurisdiction, the only<lb/> course open to him was to return the complaint under Section 201 of the<lb/> Code of Criminal Procedure for presentation to proper Court. In fact, such<lb/> is the direction in Ahuja Nandkishore Dongre&apos;s case. Therefore, acquittal of<lb/> respondent by a Court professing lack of jurisdiction is unsustainable.<lb/> 9.<lb/> The learned counsel for the appellant next submitted that<lb/> the judgment in<lb/> Ahuja Nandkishore Dongre&apos;s case was delivered<lb/> on 4-9-2006, long after the complaints were filed on 3-2-2004. No<lb/> objection had been raised to the jurisdiction of the Court till practically the<lb/> trial was over and, therefore, such objection could not have entertained by<lb/> the learned Magistrate. He submitted that in Ahuja Nandkishore Dongre&apos;s<lb/> case, the accused had filed an application taking objection to jurisdiction of<lb/> the Court immediately after process was issued and had approached this<lb/> Court under Section 482 of the Code of Criminal Procedure upon rejection<lb/> of his application. Such were not the facts in this bunch of cases.<lb/> Therefore, the judgment in<lb/> Ahuja Nandkishore Dongre&apos;s case was<lb/> inapplicable. He pointed out that Section 462 of the Code of Criminal<lb/> Procedure even leaves undisturbed judgments rendered by Courts which<lb/> lacked territorial jurisdiction, unless it appears that such error has in fact<lb/> occasioned a failure of justice.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>that the observations must be read in the context of five components of the<lb/> offence enumerated in para 14 of K. Bhaskaran&apos;s judgment. To contend<lb/> that jurisdictional question has become irrelevant and that irrespective of<lb/> the fact that none of the five components occurred within the jurisdiction of<lb/> a Court, it could entertain a complaint, would amount to reading sentences<lb/> out of context.<lb/> 23.<lb/> That in spite of &quot;wide amplitude&quot;, jurisdictional question is<lb/> still relevant is clear from a later judgment of the Hon&apos;ble Apex Court in<lb/> Mosaraf Hossain Khan Vs. Bhagheeratha Engg. Ltd. and others, reported at<lb/> AIR 2006 SC 1288= (2006) 3 SCC 658. Complainant in that case had filed<lb/> complaints in the Court of Chief Judicial Magistrate, Birbhum at Suri in<lb/> respect of several cheques that had been dishonoured. The respondent<lb/> (accused Company) had undertaken work of construction of major bridges<lb/> in West Bengal. The complainant was supplying crushed stone aggregates.<lb/> In respect of the amount outstanding towards supply of raw material, the<lb/> accused Company had issued post-dated cheques from the registered office<lb/> of the Company in Kerala. The cheques were deposited by the complainant<lb/> with Mayurakhi Gramin Bank, Suri Branch and were returned by the banker<lb/> stating &quot;full cover not received&quot;. Upon service of notice of demand, a part<lb/> of the sum was paid, leaving a big balance. The Chief Judicial Magistrate<lb/> issued process on the complaints and summonses were served at Kolabhat,<lb/> Midnapore, West Bengal. Instead of appearing before the Chief Judicial<lb/> Magistrate, the accused filed a writ petition before the High Court of Kerala<lb/> for quashing the complaints. The accused Company contended that since<lb/> the cheques were issued from registered office of the Company in Kerala, a<lb/> part of cause of action arose within the State of Kerala.<lb/> 24.<lb/> The High Court of Kerala entertained the petition and<lb/> granted interim reliefs. After considering the question of jurisdiction of the<lb/> High Court to entertain in such a petition, the Apex Court also considered<lb/> the question as to which Magisterial Court would have jurisdiction to<lb/> entertain the complaints. After considering decision in OM Hemrajani Vs.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>complaint of offence punishable under Section 138 of the Negotiable<lb/> Instrument Act. In that case, a notice making demand was made first<lb/> on 17-2-1995. Cheque was presented again on 6-7-1995 and after it was<lb/> dishonoured fresh notice of demand was sent on 24-7-1995 and, therefore,<lb/> complaint was filed. In this context, the Court held as under in paras 9<lb/> and 10.<lb/> &quot;9.<lb/> In a generic and wide sense (as in section 20 of the<lb/> Civil Procedure Code, 1908 (in short &apos;CPC&apos;) &quot;cause of action&quot;<lb/> means every fact which it is necessary to establish to support a<lb/> right or obtain a judgment. Viewed in that context, the<lb/> following facts are required to be proved to successfully<lb/> prosecute the drawer for an offence under Section 138 of the<lb/> Act :<lb/> (a)<lb/> that the cheque was drawn for payment of an<lb/> amount of money for discharge of a debt/liability<lb/> and the cheque was dishonoured;<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> (b)<lb/> that the cheque was presented within the prescribed<lb/> period;<lb/> (c)<lb/> that the payee </content>
 
            <figDesc>made a demand for payment of the<lb/> money by giving a notice in writing to the drawer<lb/> within the stipulated period; and<lb/> (d)<lb/> that the drawer failed to make the payment within<lb/> 15 days of the receipt of the notice.&quot;<lb/> &quot;10.<lb/> Proceeding on the basis of the generic meaning of the<lb/> term cause of action, certainly each of the above facts would<lb/> constitute a part of the cause of action but clause (b) of section<lb/> 142 gives it a restrictive meaning, in that, it refers to only one<lb/> fact which will give rise to the cause of action and that is the<lb/> failure to make the payment within 15 days from the date of<lb/> the receipt of the notice. A combined reading of sections 138<lb/> and 142 makes it clear that cause of action is to be reckoned<lb/> accordingly. The combined reading of the above two sections<lb/> of the Act leaves no room for doubt that cause of action within<lb/> the meaning of section 142(c) arises -and can arise -only<lb/> once.&quot;<lb/> This is the observation which was referred to by the Apex Court in Mosaraf<lb/> Hossain&apos;s case.<lb/> 27.<lb/> Judgment in Mosaraf Hossain Khan&apos;s case, in my humble<lb/> view, would show that :-<lb/>(1) Jurisdictional question is very much relevant in cases<lb/> under Section 138 of the Negotiable Instruments Act.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>It is settled legal position that even obiter dicta of the Supreme Court are<lb/> binding on all the Courts in India, in the absence of a direct pronouncement<lb/> on the subject by the Supreme Court, as held in para 26 of the judgment in<lb/> para 26 of the judgment in Oriental Insurance Vs. Meena Variyal, reported at<lb/> 2007(5) SCC 428. As the foregoing enumeration would show, it is clear that<lb/> dicta of the Hon&apos;ble Apex Court in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case have been followed.<lb/> If the judgment in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case gives an impression that law laid<lb/> down by the Hon&apos;ble Apex Court has not been followed in letter and spirit, it<lb/> may only be an regrettable lapse in articulation. The attempt, in fact, was to<lb/> discern correctly as to what the Apex Court had ruled in order to accurately<lb/> apply it to the facts of the said case.<lb/> 30.<lb/> In Emkay Exports, Mumbai and another Vs. Madhusudan<lb/> Shrikrishna, reported at 2008(4) Mh.L.J. 843, on which the learned counsel<lb/> for the respondent placed reliance, a Full Bench of this Court, speaking<lb/> through the Hon&apos;ble the Chief Justice, considered the concepts of precedent,<lb/> ratio, stare decisis in the following erudite words :<lb/> &quot;6.<lb/> The concept of precedent has attained important<lb/> role in administration of justice in the modern times. The case<lb/> before the Court should be decided in accordance with law and<lb/> the doctrines. The mind of the Court should be clearly<lb/> reflecting on the material in issue with regard to the facts of<lb/> the case. The reason and spirit of case make law and not the<lb/> letter of a particular precedent. Halsbury&apos;s &quot;The Laws of<lb/> England&quot;, explained the word &quot;ratio decidendi&quot; as &quot;It may be<lb/> laid down as a general rule that that part alone of a decision<lb/> by a Court of Law is binding upon Courts of coordinate<lb/> jurisdiction and inferior Courts which consists of the<lb/> enunciation of the reason or principle upon which the question<lb/> before the Court has really been determined. This underlying<lb/> principle which forms the only authoritative element of a<lb/> precedent is often termed the ratio decidendi.&quot; It is by the<lb/> choice of material facts that the Court create law. The law so<lb/> created would be a good precedent for similar subsequent cases<lb/> unless it falls within the exceptions hereinafter indicated.&quot;<lb/> &quot;7.<lb/> The doctrine of precedent relates to following of<lb/> previous decisions within its limitations. It introduces the<lb/> concept of finality and adherence to the previous decisions and<lb/> while attaining it, it creates consistency in application of law.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            45.<lb/> In Criminal Writ </content>
 
            <figDesc>Petition No.7 of 2008 before the High<lb/> Court of Bombay at Goa, by an order dated 7-2-2008, an Hon&apos;ble Single<lb/> Judge referred the matter to a larger Bench. Copy of that order was made<lb/> available by the Registry, in order to enable me to ascertain as to what part<lb/> of judgment in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case was found to be incorrect. In para 2, the<lb/> Hon&apos;ble Single Judge observes as under :<lb/> &quot;2.<lb/> I have perused both the decisions delivered by the<lb/> learned Single Judges of this Court. In Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case,<lb/> the learned Single Judge has held that a cheque as a<lb/> negotiable instrument is statutorily required to be discharged<lb/> at the place mentioned therein and a reference is made in that<lb/> regard to Section 72 of the Negotiable Instruments Act.<lb/> Referring to the decision of the Apex Court in K. Bhasaran v.<lb/> Sankaran Vaidhyan Balan, reported in AIR 1999 SC 3762,<lb/> it was held that in K. Bhasaran&apos;s case as a matter of fact it<lb/> was held as proved that the cheques in question had been<lb/> issued at the shop of P.W.3 with the territorial limits of the<lb/> trial Court&apos;s jurisdiction. Having so observed, it was further<lb/> held by the learned Single Judge that the five ingredients<lb/> enumerated by the Court in para 14 of the Judgment would<lb/> undisputedly attract the provisions of clause (d) of Section 178<lb/> of the Code of Criminal Procedure, since it could not be said<lb/> that the offence punishable under Section 138 of the<lb/> Negotiable Instruments Act consists of the five acts,<lb/> enumerated in paragraph 14 of the judgment.&quot;<lb/> (Emphasis supplied)<lb/> The learned Single Judge then paraphrases interpretation put by me on the<lb/> expressions &quot;presented&quot; and &quot;the drawee bank&quot;. In para 3, the Hon&apos;ble<lb/> Judge quotes from K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case, and in paras 5 and 6 observes as to<lb/> what the Apex Court has held in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case. The sentence in para 6<lb/> wherein the Hon&apos;ble Judge refers to judgment in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case reads<lb/> as under :<lb/> &quot;... The decision of the Apex Court therefore is very clear to the<lb/> effect that the jurisdiction for initiating action under Section<lb/> 138 of the Negotiable Instruments Act is not restricted to the<lb/> place where the drawee bank is situated and, hence, in my<lb/> considered opinion, and with utmost respect to the learned<lb/> Judge in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case, the view therein is directly<lb/> contrary to the law laid down by the Apex Court in K.<lb/> Bhaskaran&apos;s case.&quot;<lb/> The portion underlined in para 2 of the order would show that the Hon&apos;ble<lb/> Single Judge correctly concluded that it was held in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case that<lb/> the five ingredients enumerated by the Court in para 14 of the judgment<lb/> would undisputedly attract the provisions of clause (d) of Section 178 of the<lb/> Code of Criminal Procedure. But reading by the Hon&apos;ble Single Judge of the<lb/> remaining part of same sentence in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case is, however different<lb/> from that in the report of the judgment at 2006(6) All Bom R 201, which the<lb/> Hon&apos;ble Single Judge had referred to (as may be seen from para 1 of his<lb/> order). The sentence in para 14 of the judgment in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case<lb/> reads as under :<lb/> &quot;The five ingredients enumerated by the Court in paragraph<lb/> 14 of the judgment would undisputedly attract the oprovisions<lb/> of Clause (d) of Section 178 of the Code of Criminal<lb/> Procedure, since it can be said that the offence punishable<lb/> under Section 138 of the Negotiable Instruments Act consists<lb/> of the five acts, enumerated in paragraph 14 of the judgment.&quot;</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>had no territorial jurisdiction to try the case since the cheque<lb/> was dishonoured by the Branch Office of the Bank situated in<lb/> a different district. But all other acts like drawing of the<lb/> cheque, its presentation for encashment, its return after<lb/> dishonour, and issuance of demand notice etc. had taken place<lb/> within the territorial limits of the trial court at Adoor. The<lb/> cheque was presented before the branch of the Syndicate Bank<lb/> at Kayamkulam and it was returned due to insufficiency of<lb/> funds in the accountof the accused. Apart from the above sole<lb/> act of presentation of the cheque before a branch outside the<lb/> jurisdiction of the trial court, all other acts as noticed by the<lb/> Supreme Court had, occurred within the territorial limits of<lb/> the trial court itself. Their Lordships had, in the above facts<lb/> and circumstances of the case, held that the trial Court was<lb/> not justified in refusing to exercise jurisdiction and deal with<lb/> the case in accordance with law.&quot;<lb/> &quot;19.<lb/> I have referred to the above observations of the<lb/> Apex Court to emphasis the fact that any one of the 5<lb/> conditions enumerated by their Lordships in Bhaskaran&apos;s<lb/> case may not by itself invariably clinch the issue while<lb/> deciding the question of jurisdiction. That question has to<lb/> be decided keeping in view the entire sequence of events<lb/> starting from issuance of the cheque in the ultimate<lb/> culmination of refusal to pay.&quot;<lb/> &quot;21.<lb/> Having regard to the entire facts and<lb/> circumstances of the case on hand, I am satisfied that the<lb/> complainant is not entitled to institute the complaint<lb/> before the court at Pathanamthitta. since the major part<lb/> of the transaction like issuance of the cheque, its<lb/> presentation and dishonour, having taken place at Adoor,<lb/> it may not be just or proper to allow the complainant to<lb/> prosecute the petitioner/accused before the Chief Judicial<lb/> Magistrate&apos;s Court at Pathanamthitta solely for the reason<lb/> that the complainant had engaged a counsel at<lb/> Pathanamthitta to issue the statutory demand notice. In<lb/> my view, the method adopted by the complainant is clear<lb/> intended to harass the petitioner.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            56.<lb/> The learned counsel </content>
 
            <figDesc>for the appellant referred to the<lb/> following observations of the Supreme Court in Mosaraf Hossain&apos;s case in<lb/> para 35 of the judgment reported at AIR 2006 SC 1288.<lb/> &quot;35.<lb/> The appellant did not deny or dispute any of the<lb/> averments made in the complaint petition. In the writ petition<lb/> it merely wanted some time to make the payment. It is now<lb/> well known that the object of the provision of Section 138 of<lb/> the Act is that for proper and smooth functioning of business<lb/> transaction in particular, use of cheques as negotiable<lb/> instruments would primarily depend upon the integrity and<lb/> honesty of the parties. It was noticed that cheques used to be<lb/> issued as a device inter alia for defrauding the creditors and<lb/> stalling the payments. It was also noticed in a number of<lb/> decisions of this Court that dishonour of a cheque by the bank<lb/> causes incalculable loss, injury and inconvenience to the payee<lb/> and the entire credibility of the business transactions within<lb/> and outside the country suffers a serious setback. It was also<lb/> found that the remedy available in a civil court is a long<lb/> drawn process and an unscrupulous drawer normally takes<lb/> various pleas to defeat the genuine claim of the payee.&quot;</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>57.<lb/> It is not clear as to how this argument factually favours the<lb/> complainant. The complainant had to simply file cases in Delhi where he<lb/> was supposed to be paid for goods sold by him. He has chosen to file cases<lb/> in Nagpur for no rhyme or reason, except that Courts here would be able to<lb/> deliver speedy justice. The concerns of traders aired by the learned counsel<lb/> are in fact addressed by the Apex Court in para 34 of the judgment in<lb/> Mosaraf Hossain&apos;s case by observing to the effect that jurisdiction would vest<lb/> in the Court within whose territorial jurisdiction payment was to be made.<lb/> 58.<lb/> While in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case, five components are<lb/> enumerated, the wordings of Section 138 of the Negotiable Instruments Act<lb/> would underline that the cheque is but a means of fulfilling the more basic<lb/> obligation -namely, &quot;for the discharge, in whole or in part, of any debt or<lb/> other liability&quot;. Therefore, the place where the debt or other liability was<lb/> required to be discharged is of crucial importance in deciding jurisdictional<lb/> issue, as is held in Mosaraf Hossain&apos;s case. This should answer the<lb/> appellant&apos;s apprehensions about difficulties of businessmen in realising<lb/> outstation cheques for goods sold.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>59.<lb/> It has to be borne in mind that once a superior Court sets a<lb/> precedent by allowing place of trial to be changed on such considerations,<lb/> the place could as well be deliberately chosen so as to cause maximum<lb/> inconvenience and harassment. Today, a Delhi trial is being sought to be<lb/> shifted to Nagpur because trials here are speedy. Tomorrow, money<lb/> lenders/financers may set up offices in remote areas where Courts have little<lb/> work only in order to drag opponents to such Courts to coerce a settlement.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>acquittal of the accused. He should have directed return of complaints for<lb/> being filed in appropriate Court.<lb/> 60.<lb/> The learned counsel for the appellant submitted that while<lb/> ordering such return of complaints, the Courts at Delhi to whom the<lb/> complaints would be presented may be directed to proceed on the basis of<lb/> evidence already tendered and a de novo trial should not be ordered as held<lb/> in State of M.P. Vs. Bhooraji and others, reported at (2001) 7 SCC 679<lb/> (already discussed). There is no question of this Court ordering de novo<lb/> trials, since these are summary criminal cases, evidence (excluding<lb/> affidavits) is in form of notes taken by the Magistrate, and it may not be<lb/> possible for the Magistrate at Delhi to proceed on those notes. However,<lb/> this aspect is best left open for the parties and the concerned Court to be<lb/> worked out in a manner which will ensure avoiding loss of scarce judicial<lb/> time.<lb/> 61.<lb/> In view of the foregoing discussion, all these appeals are<lb/> partly allowed. The impugned judgments and acquittal of the respondent<lb/> are set aside and the complaints along with evidence recorded are directed<lb/> to be returned under Section 201 of the Code of Criminal Procedure Code<lb/> for being presented to proper Court.</figDesc>
        </figure>



    </text>
</tei>

