<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_3a7e1eaac4a793bf8c475d0d2e1e8038.pdf"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">


		<figure type="table">

            <table>Versus<lb/> 1. M/s. Dinesh Associates,<lb/> Proprietorship Concern,<lb/> 3796/2, Gali Lohe Wali,<lb/> Behind Namkeen Shop,<lb/> Charkhewalan, Chawari Bazar,<lb/> Delhi-110 006.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>2. Dinesh s/o Gopichand Gupta,<lb/> Proprietor of M/s. Dinesh Associates,<lb/> R/o D-145, &quot;Priyadarshini Vihar&quot;,<lb/> Opp. Lovely Public School,<lb/> Shahadara, Delhi.<lb/> ...Respondent/<lb/> Accused<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>Criminal Application No.2426 of 2008<lb/> In<lb/> Criminal Appeal No.392 of 2008<lb/> M/s. Jinraj Paper Udyog,<lb/> 2/26, Ansari Road, Delhi,<lb/> Office also at Jejani Sadan,<lb/> Itwari Bhaji Mandi, Nagpur,<lb/> through its Proprietor,<lb/> Jinraj s/o Ramkisan Jain.<lb/> ... Applicant<lb/> Versus<lb/> 1. M/s. Dinesh Associates,<lb/> Proprietorship Concern,<lb/> 3796/2, Gali Lohe Wali,<lb/> Behind Namkeen Shop,<lb/> Charkhewalan, Chawari Bazar,<lb/> Delhi-110 006.<lb/> 1. M/s. Dinesh Associates,<lb/> Proprietorship Concern,<lb/> 3796/2, Gali Lohe Wali,<lb/> Behind Namkeen Shop,<lb/> Charkhewalan, Chawari Bazar,<lb/> Delhi-110 006.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>2. Dinesh s/o Gopichand Gupta,<lb/> Proprietor of M/s. Dinesh Associates,<lb/> R/o D-145, &quot;Priyadarshini Vihar&quot;,<lb/> Opp. Lovely Public School,<lb/> Shahadara, Delhi.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>...Respondent/<lb/> Accused<lb/> Criminal Appeal No.391 of 2008<lb/> M/s. Jinraj Paper Udyog,<lb/> 2/26, Ansari Road, Delhi,<lb/> Office also at Jejani Sadan,<lb/> Itwari Bhaji Mandi, Nagpur,<lb/> through its Proprietor,<lb/> Jinraj s/o Ramkisan Jain.<lb/> ... Appellant<lb/> Versus<lb/> 1. M/s. Dinesh Associates,<lb/> Proprietorship Concern,<lb/> 3796/2, Gali Lohe Wali,<lb/> Behind Namkeen Shop,<lb/> Charkhewalan, Chawari Bazar,<lb/> Delhi-110 006.<lb/> 2. Dinesh s/o Gopichand Gupta,<lb/> Proprietor of M/s. Dinesh Associates,<lb/> R/o D-145, &quot;Priyadarshini Vihar&quot;,<lb/> Opp. Lovely Public School,<lb/> Shahadara, Delhi.<lb/> ...Respondent/<lb/> Accused<lb/> Criminal Appeal No.392 of 2008<lb/> M/s. Jinraj Paper Udyog,<lb/> 2/26, Ansari Road, Delhi,<lb/> Office also at Jejani Sadan,<lb/> Itwari Bhaji Mandi, Nagpur,<lb/> through its Proprietor,<lb/> Jinraj s/o Ramkisan Jain.<lb/> ... Appellant<lb/> Versus<lb/> 1. M/s. Dinesh Associates,<lb/> Proprietorship Concern,<lb/> 3796/2, Gali Lohe Wali,<lb/> Behind Namkeen Shop,<lb/> Charkhewalan, Chawari Bazar,<lb/> Delhi-110 006.<lb/> 2. Dinesh s/o Gopichand Gupta,<lb/> Proprietor of M/s. Dinesh Associates,<lb/> R/o D-145, &quot;Priyadarshini Vihar&quot;,<lb/> Opp. Lovely Public School,<lb/> Shahadara, Delhi.<lb/> ...Respondent/<lb/> Accused<lb/> Criminal Appeal No.393 of 2008<lb/> M/s. Jinraj Paper Udyog,<lb/> 2/26, Ansari Road, Delhi,<lb/> Office also at Jejani Sadan,<lb/> Itwari Bhaji Mandi, Nagpur,<lb/> through its Proprietor,<lb/> Jinraj s/o Ramkisan Jain.<lb/> ... Appellant<lb/> Versus<lb/> 1. M/s. Dinesh Associates,<lb/> Proprietorship Concern,<lb/> 3796/2, Gali Lohe Wali,<lb/> Behind Namkeen Shop,<lb/> Charkhewalan, Chawari Bazar,<lb/> Delhi-110 006.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>2. Dinesh s/o Gopichand Gupta,<lb/> Proprietor of M/s. Dinesh Associates,<lb/> R/o D-145, &quot;Priyadarshini Vihar&quot;,<lb/> Opp. Lovely Public School,<lb/> Shahadara, Delhi.<lb/> ...Respondent/<lb/> Accused<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>Criminal Appeal No.399 of 2008<lb/> M/s. Jinraj Paper Udyog,<lb/> 2/26, Ansari Road, Delhi,<lb/> Office also at Jejani Sadan,<lb/> Itwari Bhaji Mandi, Nagpur,<lb/> through its Proprietor,<lb/> Jinraj s/o Ramkisan Jain.<lb/> ... Appellant<lb/> Versus<lb/> 1. M/s. Dinesh Associates,<lb/> Proprietorship Concern,<lb/> 3796/2, Gali Lohe Wali,<lb/> Behind Namkeen Shop,<lb/> Charkhewalan, Chawari Bazar,<lb/> Delhi-110 006.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>2. Dinesh s/o Gopichand Gupta,<lb/> Proprietor of M/s. Dinesh Associates,<lb/> R/o D-145, &quot;Priyadarshini Vihar&quot;,<lb/> Opp. Lovely Public School,<lb/> Shahadara, Delhi.<lb/> ...Respondent/<lb/> Accused<lb/> Shri R.P. Joshi, Advocate for Applicant/Appellant.<lb/> S/Shri Anand.S. Joshi, and Shri D.M. Gabhane, Advocates for Respondent.<lb/> <note>Coram : R.C. Chavan, J.<lb/> Date of Reserving the Judgment : 23-10-2008<lb/> Date of Pronouncing the Judgment : 10-11-2008<lb/> JUDGMENT :<lb/> Criminal Application Nos.2424, 2425, 2426, 2427 and 2428 of 2008<lb/> By these applications under Section 378(4) of the Code of<lb/> Criminal Procedure Code original complainant seeks leave to file appeals<lb/> against the judgments of acquittal rendered by the learned Judicial<lb/> Magistrate First Class, Nagpur in five Summary Criminal Cases relating to<lb/> office punishable under Section 138 of the Negotiable Instruments Act.</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>Bhaskaran Vs. Sankaran Vaidhyan Balan, reported at 1999 ALL MR (Cri)<lb/> 1845 (S.C.). In any case, a judgment, declaratory of law, would apply even<lb/> on the date the appellant filed criminal complaints before the learned<lb/> Magistrate. Further, according to the learned counsel, occasions for an<lb/> accused to disclose his stand would arise first, only in course of cross-<lb/>examination of complainant, which the accused had done by eliciting in the<lb/> cross-examination that the lis had no causal connection with the forum. He<lb/> further submitted that accused could undoubtedly have followed the course<lb/> chosen by Ahuja Dongre, namely, applying for objecting to jurisdiction, but,<lb/> failure to do so has no consequences, since accused was under no duty or<lb/> obligation to follow only that course.<lb/> 11.<lb/> The learned counsel for the respondent submitted that in<lb/> fact proper stage for raising jurisdictional question is the trial itself and this<lb/> Court had discouraged application under Section 482 of the Code of<lb/> Criminal Procedure for quashing a complaint on account of lack of<lb/> jurisdiction in A. Chinnaswami Vs. M/s. Bilakchand Gyanchand Company,<lb/> reported at 1998(3) Bom.C.R. 120. In that case too, jurisdiction of Court of<lb/> Judicial Magistrate First Class, Chopada was invoked because cheques were<lb/> &quot;presented&quot; at Chopada branch of State Bank of India, though the<lb/> transaction had allegedly taken place at Coimbatore. In this context, this<lb/> <note>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 :::</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>Supreme Court in State of M.P. Vs. Bhooraji and others, reported at (2001) 7<lb/> SCC 679, where the Court held that a trial held before a competent Court<lb/> would not be vitiated by a procedural lapse. The High Court of Madhya<lb/> Pradesh in Meerabai Vs. Bhujbal Singh, reported at 1995 Cri LJ 2376 (MP),<lb/> had held that cases under the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes<lb/> (Prevention of Atrocities) Act needed to be committed to the Special Court<lb/> of Session. This was overruled by a Full Bench of the same Court, which<lb/> held that the Special Court could directly take cognizance without<lb/> commitment. This in turn was overruled by the Apex Court in Gangula<lb/> Ashok Vs. State of A.P., reported in (2000) 2 SCC 504, making commitment<lb/> necessary. Bhooraji&apos;s case was tried by appropriate Court, but without its<lb/> having been committed. The High Court ordered a fresh trial. On appeal,<lb/> the Supreme Court set aside the judgment, observing as under in para 21:<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>&quot;21.<lb/> The expression &quot;a court of competent jurisdiction&quot;<lb/> envisaged in Section 465 is to denote a validly constituted<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>court conferred with jurisdiction to try the offence or offences.<lb/> Such a court will not get denuded of its competence to try the<lb/> case on account of any procedural lapse and the competence<lb/> would remain unaffected by the non-compliance with the<lb/> procedural requirement. The inability to take cognizance of<lb/> an offence without a committal order does not mean that a<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>duly constituted court became an incompetent court for all<lb/> purposes. If an objection was raised in that court at the<lb/> earliest occasion on the ground that the case should have been<lb/> committed by a Magistrate, the same specified court has to<lb/> exercise a jurisdiction either for sending the records to a<lb/> Magistrate for adopting committal proceedings or return the<lb/> police report to the Public Prosecutor or the police for<lb/> presentation before the Magistrate. Even this could be done<lb/> only because the court has competence to deal with the case.<lb/> Sometimes that court may have to hear arguments to decide<lb/> that preliminary issue. Hence the argument advanced by the<lb/> learned counsel on the strength of the aforesaid decisions is of<lb/> no avail.&quot;<lb/> 15.<lb/> It may be seen that in Bhooraji&apos;s case, it was not that the<lb/> Court which tried the offenders had no jurisdiction. Upon commitment, the<lb/> case would have been tried by the same Court. Such is not the present case.<lb/> Here, the question whether Court at Nagpur has jurisdiction is very much in<lb/> issue. The question here is not of procedural lapse, but of the very<lb/> competence of the Court to take cognizance for want of jurisdiction. The<lb/> question here is not connected with procedural error covered by Section 465<lb/> of the Code of Criminal Procedure, dealing with irregular proceedings, and<lb/> so Bhooraji&apos;s case has no application, as rightly contended by the learned<lb/> counsel for the respondent.<lb/> 16.<lb/> In this view of the matter, it would be necessary to examine<lb/> whether the learned Judicial Magistrate, First Class, was right in concluding<lb/> that he lacked jurisdiction. The learned counsel for the respondent<lb/> submitted that in the face of judgment of this Court in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case,<lb/> the learned Magistrate could not have held otherwise and, therefore, the<lb/> judgment is unassailable.<lb/> 17.<lb/> The learned counsel for the appellant submitted that<lb/> judgment in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case is itself rendered per incuriam and it was<lb/> impermissible for this Court to &quot;distinguish&quot; the ratio of judgment of the<lb/> Apex Court in K. Bhaskaran Vs. Sankaran Vaidhyan Balan, reported at<lb/> (1999) 7 SCC 510=AIR 1999 SC 3762. Therefore, according to the learned<lb/> counsel, the judgment in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case need not have been applied<lb/> and in any case, may not be applied, since it cannot stand with judgments of<lb/> Supreme Court on which the learned counsel sought to rely.<lb/> 18.<lb/> Before going into the question whether Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case<lb/> was decided per incuriam, it would be useful to recount as to what was<lb/> decided by the Hon&apos;ble Apex Court in the case of K. Bhaskaran and how this<lb/> judgment was considered in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case. The material part of<lb/> observations of the Apex Court on the question of jurisdiction, contained in<lb/> paras 14 to 16 of the judgment as reported at AIR 1999 SC 3762 may be<lb/> usefully reproduced as under :<lb/> &quot;14.<lb/> The offence under Section 138 of the Act can be<lb/> completed only with the con-catenation of a number of acts.<lb/> Following are the acts which are components of the said<lb/> offence : (1) Drawing of the cheque, (2) Presentation of the<lb/> cheque to the bank, (3) Returning the cheque unpaid by the<lb/> drawee bank, (4) Giving notice in writing to the drawer of the<lb/> cheque demanding payment of the cheque amount, (5) failure<lb/> of the drawer to make payment within 15 days of the receipt<lb/> of the notice.&quot;<lb/> &quot;15.<lb/> It is not necessary that all the above five acts should<lb/> have been perpetrated at the same locality. It is possible that<lb/> each of those five acts could be done at 5 different localities.<lb/> But concatenation of all the above five is a sine qua non for<lb/> the completion of the offence under Section 138 of the Act. In<lb/> this context a reference to Section 178(d) of the Code is useful.<lb/> It is extracted below :<lb/> &quot;Where the offence consists of several acts done in<lb/> different local areas, it may be inquired into or tried by a<lb/> Court having jurisdiction over any of such local areas.&quot;<lb/> &quot;16.<lb/> Thus it is clear, if the five different acts were done in<lb/> five different localities any one of the Courts exercising<lb/> jurisdiction in one of the five local areas can become the place<lb/> of trial for the offence under Section 138 of the Act. In other<lb/> words, the complainant can choose any one of those Courts<lb/> having jurisdiction over any one of the local areas within the<lb/> territorial limits of which any one of those five acts was done.<lb/> As the amplitude stands so widened and so expansive it is an<lb/> idle exercise to raise jurisdictional question regarding the<lb/> offence under Section 138 of the Act.&quot;<lb/> The above observations were considered in paras 14, 15, 17 to 19, 22 and<lb/> 23 in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case as under :<lb/> &quot;14.<lb/> In Bhaskaran&apos;s case, as a matter of fact, it was held<lb/> as proved that cheques in question have been issued at the<lb/> shop of P.W.3 within territorial limits of trial Court&apos;s<lb/> jurisdiction. The five ingredients enumerated by the Court in<lb/> paragraph 14 of the judgment would undisputedly attract the<lb/> provisions of Clause (d) of Section 178 of the Code of<lb/> Criminal Procedure, since it can be said that the offence<lb/> punishable under Section 138 of the Negotiable Instruments<lb/> Act consists of the five acts, enumerated in paragraph 14 of the<lb/> judgment. It may be seen that clauses (2) and (3) in<lb/> paragraph 14 of the judgment refer to presentation of &quot;the<lb/> cheque&quot; to &quot;the Bank&quot; and returning the cheque unpaid by<lb/> &quot;the drawee Bank&quot;. A reference to Section 138 of the<lb/> Negotiable Instruments Act, would also show that the section<lb/> begins, with reference to &quot;a banker&quot; and then goes on to refer<lb/> to &quot;the banker&quot;...... &quot;is returned by the bank&quot;, ...... &quot;by an<lb/> agreement made with that bank&quot;...... &quot;the cheque has been<lb/> presented to the bank within thirty days from information by<lb/> him to the bank&quot; etc. Thus, the reference to presentation of<lb/> the cheque or return of the cheque dishonoured is in relation<lb/> to the bank on which the cheque is drawn. Considering the<lb/> usage of indefinite articles &quot;a&quot; and &quot;an&quot; and definite article<lb/> &quot;the&quot; it would not be permissible to hold that reference to the<lb/> bank extends to any bank where the cheque is presented, or<lb/> any bank from which holder in due course eventually gets<lb/> information of dishonour. This is amply made clear by the<lb/> Apex Court by prefixing the words &quot;bank&quot; and &quot;drawee bank&quot;<lb/> in items (1) and (2) in paragraph 14 of the judgment with<lb/> definite article &quot;the&quot;.&quot;<lb/> &quot;15.<lb/> The Apex Court must have chosen to prefix the word<lb/> &quot;bank&quot; by definite article &quot;the&quot; in order to avoid the confusion<lb/> and problems that would be created by using indefinite article<lb/> &quot;a&quot;. A cheque is negotiable instrument and by appropriate<lb/> endorsement and delivery it can be negotiated. If instead of<lb/> the Courts at the place where the bank on which the cheque<lb/> was drawn, the Courts at the place where the cheque was<lb/> presented were to have jurisdiction, drawers of the cheque<lb/> would be exposed to an unforeseen risk. When a person issues<lb/> a cheque to another, he intends to make payment to that<lb/> another, for a consideration which he has received at the bank<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>on which the cheque is drawn. That other, may, in turn,<lb/> negotiate the cheque in favour of third person for a liability<lb/> which that other may have to discharge towards such third<lb/> person. The drawer of the cheque cannot be said to have<lb/> foreseen that, by such negotiation, his cheque would land at<lb/> place far away from the place at which it was meant to be<lb/> paid, making him liable to be hauled up in a Court at a place<lb/> where the cheque was presented by the holder in due course.<lb/> Therefore, with utmost humility and with great respect to the<lb/> observations made by Andhra Pradesh High Court, it is<lb/> difficult to deduce the ratio elicited by the Andhra Pradesh<lb/> High Court, from the observations of the Supreme Court from<lb/> K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case. It must be held that the observations in<lb/> Bhaskaran&apos;s case do not support such a view of law.&quot;<lb/> &quot;17.<lb/> While creating an offence punishable under Section<lb/> 138 of the Negotiable Instruments Act, the parliament has not<lb/> changed the whole scheme of the Act. Under Section 6 of the<lb/> Act, a cheque is still defined at a bill of exchange, drawn on a<lb/> specified banker. The &quot;drawee&quot; is the person directed to pay<lb/> under Section 7, and Section 61 requires that a bill of<lb/> exchange has to be presented to &quot;the drawee&quot; (&amp; not to any<lb/> banker), and if the bill is directed to a drawee at a particular<lb/> place, it must be presented at that place. Section 72 makes the<lb/> requirement in respect of a cheque clear and lays down as<lb/> under :<lb/> &quot;72. Presentment of cheque to charge drawer :--<lb/>(Subject to the provisions of Section 84) a cheque must, in<lb/> order to charge the drawer, be presented at the bank upon<lb/> which if is drawn before the relation between the drawer and<lb/> his banker has been altered to the prejudice of the drawer.&quot;<lb/> Since all these provisions are left intact a cheque has<lb/> to be presented to the drawee bank at the place mentioned on<lb/> the cheque.&quot;<lb/> &quot;19.<lb/> The choice of definite article &quot;the&quot; by the Apex Court<lb/> in items (1) and (2) in paragraph 14 of Bhaskaran&apos;s judgment<lb/> merely gives effect to these statutory requirements.&quot;<lb/> &quot;22.<lb/> The words in paragraph 16 of the judgment<lb/> regarding widened amplitude have to be read in this<lb/> background. The Apex Court must not be understood to have<lb/> held that question of jurisdiction in a proceeding for offence<lb/> punishable under Section 138 of N.I. Act is utterly irrelevant,<lb/> or that there is absolutely no restriction on the choice of place<lb/> of suing. These observations have to be read in the context of<lb/> what is held in paragraph 14 and therefore the amplitude<lb/> must be taken to have widened to the extent indicated in<lb/> paragraph 14.&quot;<lb/> &quot;23.<lb/> Same holds good about observations in paragraph<lb/> 12 of Bhaskaran&apos;s judgment in respect of the word &quot;ordinarily&quot;<lb/> appearing in Section 177, Cr.P.C. The Apex Court must be<lb/> understood to have held that ordinarily the place of suing<lb/> must have a nexus to the lis, but upon making out a case for<lb/> deviating from this rule, action could be initiated even at some<lb/> other place. It is not the word &quot;Ordinarily&quot; gives an unbridled<lb/> freedom to a complainant to choose his forum for hauling up<lb/> an accused.&quot;<lb/> (Emphasis supplied)</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>State of U.P. and another, reported at (2005) 1 SCC 617, about jurisdiction<lb/> in cases of offences committed abroad, the Apex Court held as under :<lb/> &quot;31.<lb/> A bare perusal of the complaint petition would<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>clearly go to show that according to the complainant the entire<lb/> cause of action arose within the jurisdiction of the District<lb/> Court of Birbhum and in that view of the matter it is that<lb/> court which will have jurisdiction to take cognisance of the<lb/> offence. In fact the jurisdiction of the Court of CJM, Birbhum,<lb/> Suri, is not in question. It is not contended that the<lb/> complainant had suppressed material fact and which if not<lb/> disclosed would have demonstrated that the offence was<lb/> committed outside the jurisdiction of the said court. Even if<lb/> Section 178 of the Code of Criminal Procedure is attracted, the<lb/> Court of the Chief Judicial Magistrate, Birbhum will alone<lb/> have jurisdiction in the matter.&quot;<lb/> &quot;32.<lb/> Sending of cheques from Erakulam or the<lb/> respondents having an office at that place did not form an<lb/> integral part of &quot;cause of action&quot; for which the complaint<lb/> petition was filed by the appellant and cognisance of the<lb/> offence under Section 138 of the Negotiable Instruments Act,<lb/> 1881 was taken by the Chief Judicial Magistrate, Suri. We<lb/> may moreover notice that the situs of the accused wherefor<lb/> jurisdiction of a court can be invoked and which is an<lb/> exception to the aforementioned provisions as contained in<lb/> Section 188 of the Code of Criminal Procedure recently came<lb/> up for consideration by this Court in Om Hemrajani v. State of<lb/> U.P. It was held that the said provisions may be interpreted<lb/> widely. The law was laid down in the following terms: (SCC<lb/> pp. 621-22, paras 8-9)<lb/> &quot;8.<lb/> Section 177 postulates that ordinarily<lb/> offence shall be inquired into and tried by a court<lb/> within whose local jurisdiction it was committed.<lb/> Section 178, inter alia, deals with situations when it<lb/> is uncertain in which of several local areas an offence<lb/> is committed or partly committed in one area and<lb/> partly in another. The section provides that the<lb/> offence can be inquired into or tried by a court<lb/> having jurisdiction over any of the local areas<lb/> mentioned therein. ...&quot;<lb/> 9. ...<lb/> &quot;33.<lb/> In this case, the averments made in the writ petition<lb/> filed by the respondent herein even if given face value and<lb/> taken to be correct in their entirety would not confer any<lb/> jurisdiction upon the Kerala High Court. The agreement was<lb/> entered into within the jurisdiction of the Calcutta High<lb/> Court. The project for which the supply of stone chips and<lb/> transportation was being carried out was also within the State<lb/> of West Bengal. Payments were obviously required to be made<lb/> within the jurisdiction of the said Court where either the<lb/> contract had been entered into or where payment was to be<lb/> made&quot;<lb/> &quot;34.<lb/> The appellant did not deny or dispute any of the<lb/> averments made in the complaint petition. In the writ<lb/> petition it merely wanted some time to make the payment. It<lb/> is now well known that the object of the provision of Section<lb/> 138 of the Act is that for proper and smooth functioning of<lb/> business transaction in particular, use of cheques as<lb/> negotiable instruments would primarily depend upon the<lb/> integrity and honesty of the parties. It was noticed that<lb/> cheques used to be issued as a device inter alia for defrauding<lb/> the creditors and stalling the payments. It was also noticed in<lb/> a number of decisions of this Court that dishonour of a cheque<lb/> by the bank causes incalculable loss, injury and inconvenience<lb/> to the payee and the entire credibility of the business<lb/> transactions within and outside the country suffers a serious<lb/> setback. It was also found that the remedy available in a civil<lb/> court is a long-drawn process and an unscrupulous drawer<lb/> normally takes various pleas to defeat the genuine claim of the<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>payee.&quot;<lb/> &quot;35.<lb/> In Prem Chand Vijay Kumar v. Yashpal Singh<lb/> [(2005) 4 SCC 417] we may, however, notice that it was held<lb/> that for securing conviction under the Negotiable Instruments<lb/> Act, 1881 the facts which are required to be proved are: (SCC<lb/> p. 423, para 10)<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>&quot;10. (a) that the cheque was drawn for payment of<lb/> an amount of money for discharge of a debt/liability and the<lb/> cheque was dishonoured;<lb/> (b) that the cheque was presented within the<lb/> prescribed period;<lb/> (c)<lb/> that the payee made a demand for payment of<lb/> the money by giving a notice in writing to the drawer within<lb/> the stipulated period; and<lb/> (d) that the drawer failed to make the payment<lb/> within 15 days of the receipt of the notice.&quot;<lb/> &quot;36.<lb/> For the purpose of proving the aforementioned<lb/> ingredients of the offence under Section 138 of the Act, the<lb/> complainant appellant was required to prove the facts<lb/> constituting the cause of action therefor none of which arose<lb/> within the jurisdiction of the Kerala High Court. It is apt to<lb/> mention that in Prem Chand Vijay Kumar this Court held that<lb/> cause of action within the meaning of Section 142(b) of the<lb/> Act can arise only once.&quot;<lb/> The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court then allowed the appeal, setting aside orders by<lb/> the Kerala High Court. Had the question of jurisdiction become irrelevant<lb/> the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court would not have said so. It may be recalled that<lb/> the Supreme Court not only held that Courts at Birbhum, Suri had<lb/> jurisdiction (because in any case some part of cause of action arose there),<lb/> but held that the entire cause of action arose within the jurisdiction of<lb/> District Court of Birbhum, in spite of the fact that cheques were allegedly<lb/> issued from Kerala. It ruled that sending cheques from Ernakulam did not<lb/> form an integral part of cause of action. Para 33 of the judgment quoted<lb/> above is decisive of what would be crucial in determining jurisdiction in<lb/> such cases.<lb/> 25.<lb/> It is true that the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court had not<lb/> considered judgment in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case while making these<lb/> observations. But it would be impermissible to even suggest that the Apex<lb/> Court had not considered if &quot;drawing of the cheque&quot;, enumerated as the first<lb/> component in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case, had a bearing on the question of<lb/> jurisdiction in cases under Section 138 of the Negotiable Instruments Act or<lb/> not. In fact, this aspect was considered and yet the Court held that it was<lb/> not an integral part of cause of action.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>26.<lb/> In Premchand Vijay Kumar Vs. Yashpal Singh, reported at<lb/> 2005(4) Mh.L.J. 100, which had been referred to in Mosaraf Hossain&apos;s case,<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>the question was not of jurisdiction, but that of cause of action to file a</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>According to Sir John<lb/> Salmond, &quot;a precedent is a judicial decision, which contains in<lb/> itself a principle.<lb/> The only principle which forms its<lb/> authoritative element is often termed the &apos;ratio decidendi&apos;. The<lb/> concrete decision is binding between the parties to it, but it is<lb/> the abstract ratio decidendi which alone has the force of law<lb/> as regards the world at large&quot;. According to Austin, the<lb/> general reasons or principles of judicial decisions abstracted<lb/> from peculiarities of the case are commonly styled by writers<lb/> on jurisprudence as &apos;ratio decidendi&apos;.&quot;<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>&quot;10<lb/> The Hon&apos;ble Apex Court further observed that a<lb/> caution need to be taken while applying the principle of<lb/> judicial precedents as decision of the Court and its<lb/> observations must be read in context in which they appear. In<lb/> a judgment discussion is meant to explain and not to define.<lb/> In this regard, reference can be made to the case of Haryana<lb/> Financial Corporation and anr. vs. M/s. Jagdamba Oil Mills<lb/> and anr., J.T. 2002(1) SC 484.&quot;<lb/> &quot;12.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>In order to apply a judgment as a precedent, the<lb/> relevant laws and earlier judgment should be brought to the<lb/> notice of the Court and they should be correctly applied. Mere<lb/> observations in a previous judgment may not be binding on a<lb/> subsequent Bench if they are not truly applicable to the facts<lb/> and controversies in a subsequent case as per settled principle<lb/> of &quot;ratio decidendi&quot;. ...&quot;<lb/> &quot;13.<lb/> In the case of Commissioner of Customs (Fort) vs.<lb/> Toyota Kirloskar Motor (P) Ltd., (2007) 5 SCC 371, the<lb/> Supreme Court stated the law relating to precedents and held<lb/> that a decision, as is well known, is an authority for what it<lb/> decides and not what can logically be deduced therefrom. The<lb/> ratio of a decision must be culled out from the facts involved<lb/> in a given case and need not be an authority in generality<lb/> without reference to the reasons, discussions and facts of the<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>case.&quot;<lb/> &quot;15.<lb/> Furthermore, ratio decidendi of a judgment has to<lb/> be found out only on reading the entire judgment. The ratio<lb/> of the judgment is what is set out in the judgment itself.<lb/> Answer to the question necessarily would have to be read in<lb/> the context what is set out in the judgment and not in<lb/> isolation. In case of any doubt as regards any observations,<lb/> reasons or principles, the other part of the judgment must be<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>looked into. By reading a line here and there from the<lb/> judgment, one cannot find out the entire ratio decidendi of the<lb/> judgment. The reasoning could be deciphered upon reading<lb/> the judgment in its entirety and then applying these principles<lb/> to the subsequent cases. (Reference : (i) Union of India vs.<lb/> Godfrey Philips India Ltd., AIR 1996 SC 806, (ii) Union of<lb/> India vs. Dhanwanti Devi, (1996) 6 SCC 44, (iii) State of<lb/> Tripura vs. Tripura Bar Association, AIR 1999 SC 1494 and<lb/> (iv) Islamic Academy of Education vs. State of Karnatake,<lb/> (2003) 6 SCC 697).&quot;<lb/> (Emphasis Supplied)<lb/> 31.<lb/> In Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case, an attempt to read the observations<lb/> in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case in the context of applicable law has been made and,<lb/> therefore, it is not possible to accept the submission that the judgment is per<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>incuriam.<lb/> 32.<lb/> The learned counsel for the appellant submitted that<lb/> interpreting a judgment of the Supreme Court is itself impermissible and for<lb/> this purpose cited judgment of the Supreme Court in G.K. Dudani and others<lb/> Vs. S.D. Sharma and others, reported at AIR 1986 SC 1455. In that case, a<lb/> Division Bench of Gujarat High Court had sought to interpret the words<lb/> &quot;promotees regularly appointed&quot; in a judgment of Supreme Court in N.K.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>Chauhan v. State of Gujarat, reported at AIR 1977 SC 251. The Supreme<lb/> Court observed as under in para 19 :<lb/> &quot;19.<lb/> Even apart from the question of res judicata, the<lb/> Division Bench was not right in its approach to Chauhan&apos;s<lb/> Case. The interpretation placed by the Division Bench upon<lb/> the words &quot;promotees regularly appointed&quot; in direction (d) in<lb/> Chauhan&apos;s case was wholly erroneous. Under the guise of<lb/> interpreting the judgment in that case, the Division Bench of<lb/> the High Court virtually sat in appeal over the judgment of<lb/> this Court and modified it. The High Court ought to have<lb/> taken the words in that judgment in the sense in which they<lb/> were used and ought to have applied them to the facts before it<lb/> instead of trying to put words in the mouth of this Court. ...&quot;<lb/> It is not clear as to how the judgment could be an authority for the<lb/> proposition that a High Court cannot attribute to the words in an Apex<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>Court judgment, meaning assigned in the relevant enactment. True, High<lb/> Court should not put words in the mouth of the Apex Court. But if an<lb/> attempt is made to put a strained meaning on words in a judgment without<lb/> considering the context, a High Court would be duty bound to repel such<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>attempt and read the words in the context of the relevant enactment. This<lb/> is what was done in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case.<lb/> 33.<lb/> In Ballabhdas Mathuradas Lakhani and others Vs.<lb/> Municipal Committee, Malkapur, reported at AIR 1970 SC 1002, the Supreme<lb/> Court held that its earlier decision on the question of validity of levy of tax<lb/> by Municipality was binding on the High Court and the High Court could<lb/> not ignore it because they thought that relevant provisions were not brought<lb/> to the notice of the Supreme Court. Such is not the present case.<lb/> 34.<lb/> The learned counsel for the appellant next relied on a<lb/> judgment of High Court of Rajasthan in M/s. Bhanwar Lal Brij Gopal and etc.<lb/> <note>etc. v. State of Rajasthan and others, reported at AIR 1983 Rajasthan 104, to<lb/> contend that even if same aspect of a matter was not considered by the Apex<lb/> Court, it would not enable a High Court to re-agitate the issue. In that case,<lb/> validity of a notification dated 23-5-1981 was challenged before the High<lb/> Court, when the very same notification had been held valid by the Apex<lb/> Court in a judgment in Surajmal Kailash Chand Vs. Union of India, reported<lb/> at AIR 1982 SC 130. The Court made the following observations in para 22 :<lb/> &quot;22.<lb/> This raises a serious question as to what would be<lb/> the effect of the decision of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court, more<lb/> so when the same Notification being declared valid by the<lb/> Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court and the High Court has declared<lb/> invalid on the same day. Undoubtedly Art. 141 makes it<lb/> explicit and beyond doubt that the law laid down by the<lb/> Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court is to be obeyed by all concerned.<lb/> Even otherwise so far as the High Court is concerned the<lb/> Supreme Court is of a superior jurisdiction and law laid down<lb/> by the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court is binding, even if Article 41<lb/> and Article 144 would not be there.&quot;<lb/> It then quoted from a judgment of Supreme Court in Ambica Prasad Mishra<lb/> Vs. State of U.P., reported at AIR 1980 SC 1762, in para 23 as under :<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>&quot;23. ... The answer to this problem need not be given by me<lb/> but in Ambica Prasad Mishra v. State of U.P. (AIR 1980 SC<lb/> 1762), the Supreme Court have taken pains to answer what<lb/> would be the effect of raising additional points or such points<lb/> later. It was observed as under :--<lb/></table>
<lb/>
            <note>&quot;Constitution of India, art. 141--<lb/>reconsideration of binding precedent -when permissible.<lb/> Every new discovery or argumentative novelty cannot undo or<lb/> compel reconsideration of a binding precedent.<lb/> It is<lb/> fundamental that the nation&apos;s constitution is not kept in<lb/> constant uncertainty by judicial review every season because it<lb/> paralyses, by perennial suspense, all legislative and<lb/> administrative action, on vital issues deterred by the brooding<lb/> threat of forensic blow-up. This, if permitted, may well be a<lb/> kind of judicial destabilisation of State action too dangerous<lb/> to be indulged in save where national crisis of great moment<lb/> to the life, liberty and safety of this country and its millions<lb/> are at stake, or the basic direction of the nation itself is in<lb/> peril of a shake-up.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>It is wise to remember that fatal flaws silenced by earlier<lb/> rulings cannot survive after death because a decision does not<lb/> lose its authority &quot;merely because it was badly argued,<lb/> inadequately considered and fallaciously &quot;reasoned&quot; &apos;&apos;<lb/> 35.<lb/> The judgment in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case does not even hint that<lb/> K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case was badly argued, inadequately considered or<lb/> fallaciously reasoned. Far from this, K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case, being the first<lb/> authoritative pronouncement, which not only comprehensively considered<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>all aspects but also ruled in expression aptly chosen for defining the five<lb/> components, in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case, it is followed strictly. Ahuja Dongre&apos;s<lb/> case merely repels an attempt to put colloquial or loose meaning on the<lb/> expression used in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case.<lb/> 36.<lb/> Same holds good about reliance by the learned counsel for<lb/> the appellant on the judgment of the Supreme Court in Suganthi Suresh<lb/> Kumar v. Jagdeeshan, reported at (2002) 2 SCC 420, where the Supreme<lb/> Court had disapproved High Courts overruling decisions of the Apex Court<lb/> on the ground that it had laid down the legal position without considering<lb/> any other point. This objection cannot be raised in respect of judgment in<lb/> Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case since the Supreme Court in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case chose to<lb/> use the expression &quot;presented&quot; and &quot;the bank&quot; and the Supreme Court did<lb/> not rule that depositing the cheque with drawer&apos;s bank was also a relevant<lb/> component. </note>
 
            <figDesc>Judicial discipline to abide by the declaration of law by the<lb/> Supreme Court is the foremost consideration for a High Court, as held in<lb/> Suga Ram alias Chhugaram Vs. State of Rajasthan and others, reported at<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>(2006) 8 SCC 641, and judgment in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case strictly follows K.<lb/> Bhaskaran&apos;s case.<lb/> 37.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>It is not clear as to why the learned counsel for the appellant<lb/> chose to cite judgment in Smt. Kausalya Devi Bogra and others Vs. Land<lb/> Acquisition Officer, Aurangabad and another, reported at (1984) 2 SCC 324.</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>Having read the judgment of the High Court and<lb/> considering the manner in which the first appeals have been<lb/> disposed of, we have no doubts in our mind that the High<lb/> Court exceeded its jurisdiction in dealing with the first appeals.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>This Court in exercise of appellate powers vested in it under<lb/> Article 136 (sic Article 133) of the Constitution had set aside<lb/> the Bench decision of the High Court delivered in 1971 and<lb/> that judgment for all intents and purposes had become non-<lb/>existent. The present Division Bench of the High Court was<lb/> not entitled, by any process known to law, to resurrect that<lb/> judgment into life.&quot;</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>Supreme Court in Umesh<lb/> Korga Bhandari Vs. Mahanagar Telephone Nigam Ltd. and another, reported<lb/> at (2005) 13 SCC 691, to suggest such a course. In that case, the Supreme<lb/> Court observed that since decision in Bangalore Water Supply Board&apos;s case<lb/> had been referred in 2005 to a larger Bench in State of U.P. Vs. Jai Bir Singh,<lb/> it would be appropriate to await the decision of larger Bench.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>44.<lb/> This submission could have been made when the matters<lb/> first came up before Hon&apos;ble Shri Justice A.H. Joshi for admission<lb/> on 4-9-2008, when notice of final disposal was issued. After a matter is<lb/> heard at length, no useful purpose would be served by keeping it pending,<lb/> since there is no way to know when the Special Leave Petition or the<lb/> reference to larger Bench would be decided, as Courts have other pressing<lb/> work as well.</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <figDesc>learned counsel for the appellant next submitted that<lb/> the Supreme Court had held in Harbans Lal Vs. State of Haryana and<lb/> another, reported at 1999 ALL MR (Cri) 390, that when gold was<lb/> transported from Pakistan to a place near Bahadurgarh in Haryana, each of<lb/> the Courts, through whose jurisdiction the contraband passed, would have<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>jurisdiction to try offence punishable under the Customs Act. Therefore,<lb/> according to him, when notice demanding payment has been issued from<lb/> Nagpur, jurisdiction of Nagpur Court could not be excluded. As regards<lb/> significance of service of notice, apart from K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case, the learned<lb/> counsel also relied on judgment of the Supreme Court in M/s. Sarav<lb/> Investment &amp; Financial Consultants Pvt. Ltd. &amp; Anr. Vs. Llyods Register of<lb/> Shipping Indian Office Staff Provident Fund &amp; Anr., reported at<lb/> 2008 ALL MR (Cri) 300 (S.C.). There was no question of jurisdiction<lb/> involved. </table>
 
            <figDesc>The question was about service of notice by hand delivery, which<lb/> the High Court had held to be sufficient. The Supreme Court, allowing the<lb/> appeal, and setting aside the judgment of the High Court, after quoting<lb/> from K. Bhaskaran, observed in paras 16 and 19 as under :<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>&quot;16.<lb/> Section 138 of the Act contains a penal provision.<lb/> It is a special statute. It creates a vicarious liability. Even the<lb/> burden of proof to some extent is on the accused. Having<lb/> regard to the purport of the said provision as also in view of<lb/> the fact that it provides for a severe penalty, the provision<lb/> warrants a strict construction. Proviso appended to Section<lb/> 138 contains a non-obstante clause. It provides that nothing<lb/> contained in the main provision shall apply unless the<lb/> requirements prescribed therein are complied with. Service of<lb/> notice is one of the statutory requirements for initiation of a<lb/> criminal proceeding. Such notice is required to be given<lb/> within 30 days of the receipt of the information by the<lb/> complainant from the bank regarding the cheque as unpaid.<lb/> Clause (c) provides that the holder of the cheque must be<lb/> given an opportunity to pay the amount in question within 15<lb/> days of the receipt of the said notice. Complaint Petition,<lb/> thus, can be filed for commission of an offence by a drawee of<lb/> a cheque only 15 days after service of the notice. What are the<lb/> requirements of service of a notice is no longer res-integra in<lb/> view of the recent decision of this Court in C.C</table>

            <head>. Alavi Haji Vs.<lb/> Palapetty Muhammed &amp; Anr. [JT 2007(7) SC 498 : 2007<lb/> giving </head>
 
            <figDesc>of notice often receive liberal interpretation&apos; (vide<lb/> p.99 of the 12 th Ed.). The context envisaged in Section<lb/> 138 of the act invites a liberal interpretation for the<lb/> person who has the statutory obligation to give notice<lb/> because he is presumed to be the loser in the transaction<lb/> and it is for his interest the very provision is made by the<lb/> legislature. The words in clause (b) of the proviso to<lb/> Section 138 of the Act show that the payee has the<lb/> statutory obligation to &apos;make a demand&apos; by giving notice.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>The thrust in the clause is one the need to &apos;make a<lb/> demand&apos;. It is only the mode for making such demand<lb/> which the legislature has prescribed. A payee can send the<lb/> notice for doing his part for giving the notice. Once it is<lb/> dispatched his part is over and the next depends on what<lb/> the sendee does.&quot;<lb/> This question too had never been in doubt, and the law laid down in<lb/> K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case in this behalf had in fact been applied even in Ahuja<lb/> Dongre&apos;s case.<lb/> 48.<lb/> The learned counsel for the respondent, however, submitted<lb/> that the question of giving notice had also been considered by this Court in<lb/> M/s. </table>
 
            <figDesc>Yashomala Engineering Pvt. Ltd. and others Vs. Tata SSL Ltd. and<lb/> another, reported at 1998 Cri.L.J. 4350. The following observations in paras<lb/> 13 and 14 may have a bearing on the issue.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>&quot;13.<lb/> The learned Advocate for the petitioner has strongly<lb/> urged that if notice is held to be an integral part of offence it</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>, by judgment dated 5-7-2006, i.e. a little before<lb/> Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case was decided, a learned Single Judge of this Court had<lb/> considered the significance of place from where notice of demand was<lb/> issued. This judgment in Laxmi Travels, Nagpur Vs. G.E. Countrywide<lb/> Consumer and another, reported at 2006(5) AIR Bom R 316 (in September<lb/> 2006 issue), was not available to me while deciding Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case. In<lb/> that case, the facts were as under :<lb/> &quot;2.<lb/> The basic transaction between the parties took place<lb/> at Nagpur. The parties are residing at Nagpur. The cheques<lb/> are also presented at Canara Bank at Nagpur. As it was<lb/> bounced, the endorsement also made by the Canara Bank at<lb/> Nagpur. However, the complainant had issued notice of<lb/> demand from Aurangabad and as there was no compliance of<lb/> the same, the present complaint has been filed at<lb/> Aurangabad.&quot;<lb/> The learned Single Judge then considered the contentions based upon<lb/> pronouncement in K. Bhaskaran, M/s. Prem Chand Vijaykumar Vs. Yashpal<lb/> Singh, and Mosaraf Hossain Khan, and concluded in para 7 as under :<lb/> &quot;7.<lb/> The contention as raised by the learned counsel in<lb/> favour of complainant that the above judgment of the Apex<lb/> Court in K. Bhaskaran (AIR 1999 SC 3762) (supra) supports<lb/> his case to this extent that giving of notice in writing to the<lb/> drawer of the cheque demanding payment of the cheque<lb/> amount and failure of the drawer to make payment within 15<lb/> days from the notice gives cause of action only at Aurangabad.<lb/> This contention has no force. The Apex Court, nowhere dealt<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>with this aspect. What has been decided by the Apex Court in<lb/> K. Bhaskaran and M/s. Prem Chand (supra) refers to the<lb/> basic ingredients which are necessary for an offence under<lb/> S.138 of the Act. There is no dispute about this that all these<lb/> ingredients are necessary. We are concerned with the cause of<lb/> action in the present matters. The demand notice is a must.<lb/> But a place of issuance of notice and no payment thereafter<lb/> cannot sufficient to file complaint under S.138 of N.I. Act.<lb/> The notice was though sent from Aurangabad, but received at<lb/> Nagpur. The party failed to make the payment as per notice.<lb/> Therefore, issuance of notice from Aurangabad itself cannot<lb/> give cause of action to file complaint at Aurangabad. The<lb/> object of issuing notice as observed by the Apex Court in<lb/> Rajneesh Aggarwal v. Amit J. Bhalla, reported in (2001) 1<lb/> SCC 631 : (AIR 2001 SC 518) is as under :</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>discretion is given to the complainants to choose the forum of<lb/> litigation, it may create judicial havoc, to say the least.&quot;<lb/> &quot;13.<lb/> As mentioned earlier, instances galore where<lb/> unscrupulous money lenders have misused the blank cheques<lb/> extracted by them from their borrowers by inserting inflated<lb/> amounts, claiming conscionable and unbelievable rates of<lb/> interest. If the drawee of a cheque who is bent upon harassing<lb/> his borrower is permitted to select the forum of his choice, a<lb/> situation may arise where a complainant living in<lb/> Trivandrum, at the southern end of the State will choose to file<lb/> a complaint before the Court at Kasaragod situated at the<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>northern extremity, after issuing a demand notice through a<lb/> counsel at Kasaragod, though the entire transaction between<lb/> the complainant and the accused had taken place at<lb/> Trivandrum. It may be true that the complainant may also<lb/> have to appear before the Court at Kasaragod in that<lb/> eventuality. But in a case where the complainant is aware<lb/> that the accused may not be in a position to undertake such<lb/> frequent journeys from the southern most part of the State to<lb/> the northern end, it may not be improbable that such an<lb/> ingenious method would not be adopted by a complainant.The<lb/> above instance may be hypothetical, but it may not be entirely<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>improbable or impossible at all.&quot;<lb/> situation was totally different from the one available in the<lb/> case on hand. In that case, the trial Court had held that it</note>
		</figure>



    </text>
</tei>

