<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Judgment <lb/>1 <lb/>WP2412.20 <lb/>ANSARI <lb/>IN THE HIGH COURT OF JUDICATURE AT BOMBAY, <lb/>NAGPUR BENCH, NAGPUR. <lb/>WRIT PETITION NO. 2412/2020 <lb/>Sachin S/o Rameshwarrao Bhople, <lb/>Aged about 46 years, Occ. Service, <lb/>R/o. 05, Aryabhatta Colony, Opposite <lb/>Ghate Nursing Home, Near Gourkshan <lb/>Trust, Gourkshan Road, Akola 444004 (M.S.) <lb/>…. PETITIONER <lb/>// VERSUS // <lb/>1] <lb/>Dr. Panjabrao Deshmukh Krishi Vidyapeeth, <lb/>PO Krishinagar, Akola, <lb/>Through its Registrar <lb/>2] <lb/>Vice Chancellor,, <lb/>Dr. Panjabrao Deshmukh Krishi Vidyapeeth, <lb/>PO. Krishinagar, Akola 444 104 <lb/>3] <lb/>State of Maharashtra, <lb/>through its Secretary, <lb/>Department of Agricultural, Animal Husbandry, <lb/>Dairy Development and Fisheries, Mantralaya, <lb/>Mumbai -400 032, Maharashtra <lb/>4] <lb/>Maharashtra Agricultural Universities Recruitment Board, <lb/>Pune, Maharashtra <lb/>Council for Agricultural Research, through <lb/>its Chairman, 132-B, Bhamburda Bhosale Nagar, <lb/>Pune -7, Maharashtra <lb/>5] <lb/>Dr. Amrapali W/o Atul Akhare, <lb/>Aged : 41 years, Occ. Service, <lb/>R/o. Ravi Nagar, near Sudhir Colony, Akola <lb/>Tq. &amp; Dist. Akola <lb/>6] <lb/>Ms. Vanita Khushatrao Khobarkar, <lb/>Aged : 40 years, Occ. Service, <lb/>R/o. Gurudwarar Gurunanak Ashram <lb/>At post Kondhali, Tq. Katol, District Nagpur <lb/>::: Uploaded on -11/12/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:49 ::: <lb/>Judgment <lb/>2 <lb/>WP2412.20 <lb/>ANSARI <lb/></front>

			<body>7] <lb/>Dr. Shivaji Chaitram Nagpure, <lb/>aged : 49 years, Occ. Service, <lb/>R/o. Datta Colony, Trimurti Nagar, <lb/>behind Gorakshan Sawanthan, <lb/>181-7/8, Akola <lb/>8] <lb/>Dr. Manish Ramdas Deshmukh, <lb/>aged : 49 years, Occu, Service, <lb/>R/o. Shrikrupa Society, Near T.T.N. College, <lb/>Keshao Nagar, Akola <lb/>9] <lb/>Dr. Sanjay Uttamrao Kakade, <lb/>aged : 47 years, Occu. Service, <lb/>R/o. Flat No.B-1, Ma-Vaishnavi Residency -7, <lb/>Ravi Nagar, Akola <lb/>10] Dr. Prashant C. Pagar, <lb/>Aged : 50 years, Occu : Service, <lb/>Office of Associate Dean, College of Agriculture, <lb/>Maharajbag, Nagpur, Maharashtra <lb/>11] Dr. Sachin N. Potkile, <lb/>Aged : 50 years, Occ. Service, <lb/>Office of Associate Dean, College of Agriculture, <lb/>Maharajbag, Nagpur, Maharashtra <lb/>12] Dr. Varsha A. Apotikar, <lb/>Aged : 44 years, Occ. Service, <lb/>Office of Associate Dean, College of Agriculture, <lb/>Krishinagar, Akola, Maharashtra <lb/>13] Dr. Vikas V. Goud, <lb/>Aged : 45 years, Occ. Service, <lb/>Officer Incharge, Agriculture Research Station, <lb/>Washim, Dist. Washim, Maharashtra <lb/>14] Dr. Vinod A. Khadse, <lb/>Aged : 52 years, Occ. Service, <lb/>Office of Director of Extension Education, <lb/>Dr. Panjabrao Deshmukh Krishi Vidyapeeth, <lb/>Krushi Nagar, Akola, Maharashtra <lb/></body>

			<front>::: Uploaded on -11/12/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:49 ::: <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Judgment <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">WP2412.20 <lb/>ANSARI <lb/></note>

			<body>15] Dr. D. D. Mankar, <lb/>Aged : 56 years, Occ. Service, <lb/>Office of Associate Dean, College of Agriculture, <lb/>Maharajbag, Nagpur, Maharashtra <lb/>16] Dr. Pravin V. Mahatale <lb/>Aged : 43 years, Occ. Service, <lb/>Office of Associate Dean, College of Agriculture, <lb/>Sonapur, Dist. Gadchiroli, Maharashtra <lb/>17] Dr. U. T. Dangore, <lb/>Aged : 48 years, Occ. Service, <lb/>Office of Associate Dean, College of Agriculture, <lb/>Nagpur, Maharashtra <lb/>18] Dr. V. J. Rathod, <lb/>Aged : 49 years, Occ. Service, <lb/>Office of Associate Dean, College of Agriculture, <lb/>Nagpur, Maharashtra <lb/>19] Dr. Manish Y. Ladole, <lb/>Aged : 45 years, Occ. Service, <lb/>College of Agriculture, Akola, <lb/>Dr. Panjabrao Deshmukh Krishi Vidyapeeth, <lb/>P. O. Krushi Nagar, Akola -444 104, Maharashtra <lb/>20] Dr. Manoj W. Marwar, <lb/>Aged : 55 years, Occ. Service, <lb/>College of Agriculture, Akola, <lb/>Dr. Panjabrao Deshmukh Krishi Vidyapeeth, <lb/>P. O. Krushi Nagar, Akola -444 104, Maharashtra <lb/>21] Dr. Praful P. Gawande, <lb/>Age : 42 years, Occ. Service, <lb/>Central Demonstration Farm, <lb/>Wani Rambhapur, Dr. Panjabrao <lb/>Deshmukh Krishi Vidyapeeth, <lb/>Post Nipana, Tq. Akola, <lb/>Dist. -444 102, Maharashtra <lb/>22] Dr. Rajendra D. Ratnaparkhi, <lb/>Age : 51 years, Occ. Service, <lb/>Department of Agriculture Botany, <lb/>Post Graduate Institute, Dr. Panjabrao <lb/>Deshmukh Krishi Vidyapeeth, <lb/></body>

			<front>::: Uploaded on -11/12/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:49 ::: <lb/>Judgment <lb/>4 <lb/>WP2412.20 <lb/>ANSARI <lb/>P. O. Krushi Nagar, Akola -444 104, <lb/>Maharashtra <lb/>…. RESPONDENT(S) <lb/>********************************************************************* <lb/>Shri S. Khedkar, Advocate for the petitioner <lb/>Shri A. Sambre, Advocate for the respondent no. 1 <lb/>Shri M.J. Khan, AGP for the respondent/State <lb/>Shri R.V. Shiralkar, Advocate for the respondent nos. 10 to 14, 16 to 21 <lb/>Shri M.M. Sudame, Advocate for the respondent nos. 5,6, 7, 8 &amp; 9 <lb/>********************************************************************* <lb/>CORAM : DIPANKAR DATTA C.J. &amp; <lb/>VINAY JOSHI, J. <lb/></front>

			<body>DATE : DECEMBER 09, 2021 <lb/>ORAL JUDGMENT : (PER:-DIPANKAR DATTA, C.J.) <lb/>1] <lb/>W.P. No. 2412/2020 has been instituted by Shri Sachin <lb/>Rameshwarrao Bhople seeking the following relief: -<lb/>&quot;It is, therefore, most humbly and respectfully prayed that this <lb/>Hon&apos;ble Court may kindly be pleased to issue an appropriate writ, <lb/>order or direction and thereby be pleased to hold and declare that <lb/>the judgment &amp; order dated 27/02/2020, passed by this Hon&apos;ble <lb/>Court in W.P. No. 2444/19, 2471/2019 &amp; 2806/2019 (Annex-N) is <lb/>obtained by misrepresentation by the respondent No. 5 to 9 &amp; <lb/>further be pleased to: -<lb/>i) <lb/>quash &amp; set aside/recall the said judgment &amp; order dated <lb/>27/02/2020 (Annex-N) passed by this Hon&apos;ble Court in W.P. <lb/>No. 2444/19, 2471/2019 &amp; 2806/2019 (Annex-J to L), in the <lb/>interest of justice; <lb/>ii) <lb/>issue an appropriate writ, order or direction and thereby be <lb/>pleased to quash &amp; set aside the impugned communication <lb/>dated 09/07/2020 (Annex-T) issued by the respondent No. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -11/12/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:49 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Judgment <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>WP2412.20 <lb/>ANSARI <lb/>1/University, cancelling the promotion of the petitioner on <lb/>the post of Associate Professor &amp; further be pleased to direct <lb/>the respondent No. 1/University &amp; respondent No. 2/Vice-<lb/>Chancellor to restore the petitioner on the said post, with <lb/>continuity &amp; all benefits, in the interest of justice; <lb/>iii) <lb/>during the pendency and final disposal of the present <lb/>petition, stay the effect &amp; operation of the impugned <lb/>communication dated 09.07.20 (Annex-T), issued by the <lb/>respondent No. 1/University and further restrain the <lb/>respondent No. 1/University from proceeding ahead with <lb/>the said selection process of promotion of Associate <lb/>Professor in the respondent No. 1/University, in the interest <lb/>of justice;&quot; <lb/>2] <lb/>Since order has been claimed for a declaration is prayed for <lb/>quashing and/or setting aside the judgment and order passed by a co-<lb/>ordinate Bench of this Court, on the ground of alleged misrepresentation, <lb/>Mr. Sudame, learned advocate representing the respondents 5 to 7 has <lb/>raised a preliminary objection to the maintainability of the writ petition. <lb/>According to him, the judgment and order dated February 27, 2020 by <lb/>which the petitioner feels aggrieved has attained finality by reason of no <lb/>appeal being carried therefrom to the Supreme Court as well as no review <lb/>application having been filed in line with the principles flowing from <lb/>section 114 read with Order XLVII of the Code of Civil Procedure. These <lb/>being the remedies made available by law to the petitioner, it is contended <lb/>that he ought to have elected one such remedy but writ remedy is not <lb/>available to him in the circumstances. He also contends that relief as <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -11/12/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:49 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Judgment <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>WP2412.20 <lb/>ANSARI <lb/>claimed by the petitioner cannot be granted since it is not open to us to <lb/>quash and/or set aside the judgment and order of a co-ordinate Bench in <lb/>exercise of judicial review powers; if at all the petitioner is aggrieved, his <lb/>remedy lies elsewhere. It is, thus, prayed that the writ petition be <lb/>dismissed. <lb/>3] <lb/>Mr. Khedkar, learned advocate representing the petitioner <lb/>counters such preliminary objection by placing reliance on a decision of <lb/>the Supreme Court reported in (2007) 14 SCC 108 : Deepa Gourang <lb/>Murdeshwar Katre vs. Principal, V.A.V. College of Arts and others. <lb/>According to him, the said decision is an authority for the proposition that <lb/>if an order has been passed by a Court of law based on fraud or <lb/>misrepresentation, the Court can recall its order in exercise of its inherent <lb/>power. It is, therefore, submitted that this Court may examine whether the <lb/>contention of the petitioner that the judgment and order dated February <lb/>27, 2020 was obtained by misrepresentation has substance or not; if yes, <lb/>the Court may proceed to grant such relief as it may consider appropriate <lb/>in the circumstances. <lb/>4] <lb/>Before dealing with the preliminary objection, it would be <lb/>appropriate for us to notice what was under challenge in W.P. Nos. <lb/>2444/2019, 2471/2019 &amp; 2806/2019 and what the judgment and order <lb/>dated February 27, 2020 (hereafter &quot;the said judgment&quot;, for short), <lb/>::: Uploaded on -11/12/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:49 ::: <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Judgment <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>WP2412.20 <lb/>ANSARI <lb/>whereby these writ petitions were disposed of, directed. Incidentally, the <lb/>said three writ petitions were instituted by the respondents before us who <lb/>are represented by Mr. Sudame. <lb/>5] <lb/>The first of these writ petitions [W.P. No. 2444/2019], at the <lb/>instance of Ms. Amrapali W/o Atul Akhare, challenged the promotional <lb/>orders of appointments of the respondents 2 to 5 therein on the post of <lb/>Associate Professor, Agricultural Botany. The second writ petition [W.P. No. <lb/>2471/2019] was instituted by Dr. Manish Ramdas Deshmukh &amp; one other, <lb/>wherein the appointments on promotion on the post of Associate <lb/>Professor, Agronomy of the respondents 4 to 10 were challenged. In the <lb/>third writ petition [W.P. No.2806/2019], wherein Ms. Vanita Khushalrao <lb/>Khobarkar was the petitioner, challenge was laid to the appointments on <lb/>promotion of the respondents 2 and 3 on the post of Associate Professor, <lb/>Agricultural Economics. All the appointments under challenge were made <lb/>by Dr. Panjabrao Deshmukh Krishi Vidyapeeth (hereafter &quot;the University&quot;, <lb/>for short). The said three writ petitions were heard together and the <lb/>operative part of the said judgment reads as follows: -<lb/>&quot;28. <lb/>Since it has been found that the manner in which the <lb/>concerned respondents have been promoted to the post of <lb/>Associate Professor is not in accordance with ]law, we have no <lb/>hesitation in setting aside the orders of promotion as issued to the <lb/>respondent nos.2 to 5 in Writ Petition No. 2444 of 2019 in the <lb/>subject of Agricultural Botany, respondent nos.4 to 10 in Writ <lb/>Petition No. 2471 of 2019 in the subject of Agronomy and <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -11/12/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:49 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Judgment <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>WP2412.20 <lb/>ANSARI <lb/>respondent nos.2 and 3 in Writ Petition No.2806 of 2019 in the <lb/>subject of Agricultural Economics. The Selection Committee is free <lb/>to consider the proposals as received by 06.11.2017 by applying <lb/>the criteria that was prevailing on the said date for effecting <lb/>promotions to the post of Associate Professor. As regards other <lb/>Associate Professors who have been promoted but who have not <lb/>been impleaded in these writ petitions, the matter is left to the <lb/>wisdom of the University to take appropriate steps in accordance <lb/>with law if so advised. It is clarified that we have not examined the <lb/>legality of the promotions of such Associate Professors who are not <lb/>parties in these writ petitions. It is also declared that Resolution <lb/>No.26 of 2019 passed by the Executive Council dated 07.01.2019 to <lb/>the extent it has the effect of modifying the criteria prescribed in <lb/>the matter of effecting promotions which is in variance with <lb/>Statutes 52 and 73 would not operate till the procedure as <lb/>contemplated by Section 38 of the said Act is complied with. Rule <lb/>in each writ petition is made absolute in aforesaid terms leaving <lb/>the parties to bear their own costs.&quot; <lb/>(emphasis ours) <lb/>6] <lb/>It is not in dispute that in terms of the operative directions as <lb/>quoted above, the University (where the petitioners as well as the private <lb/>respondents in the aforesaid three writ petitions are employed) initiated <lb/>action for fresh selection and appointment. In course of such process being <lb/>undertaken by the University, the present petitioner who was appointed <lb/>on promotion on the post of Associate Professor in Horticulture was <lb/>served with an order dated July 9, 2020, whereby he was reverted to the <lb/>post of Assistant Professor in Horticulture. Upon this writ petition being <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -11/12/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:49 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Judgment <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>WP2412.20 <lb/>ANSARI <lb/>moved, a co-ordinate Bench of this Court by its order dated October 5, <lb/>2020 stayed the order of reversion with the effect that the petitioner has <lb/>continued to function as an Associate Professor in Horticulture. However, <lb/>the Court granted liberty to the University to finalize the process of fresh <lb/>selection and we are informed that the process has been completed and <lb/>the consequent recommendation kept in a sealed cover. <lb/>7] <lb/>The vital circumstance that can never be overlooked and <lb/>would always loom large is that the petitioner was not a party to the <lb/>proceedings of W.P. Nos. 2444/2019, 2471/2019 &amp; 2806/2019. <lb/>8] <lb/>Bearing in mind the aforesaid facts and circumstances, we are <lb/>now tasked to decide the preliminary objection as to whether this writ <lb/>petition is maintainable. The question of grant of relief, if any, would arise <lb/>only if the preliminary objection is overruled. <lb/>9] <lb/>Mr. Sudame, Mr. Khedkar and Mr. Sambre, learned advocates <lb/>for the University, respondent no. 1, have been heard and the materials on <lb/>record perused. <lb/>10] <lb/>We are inclined to overrule the objection of Mr. Sudame and <lb/>hold the writ petition to be maintainable having regard to the Constitution <lb/>Bench decision of the Supreme Court reported in AIR 1963 1909 : Shivdeo <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -11/12/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:49 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Judgment <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>WP2412.20 <lb/>ANSARI <lb/>Singh vs. State of Punjab. There, certain agricultural lands were allotted to <lb/>a number of displaced persons including the appellants on a quasi-<lb/>permanent basis under the administration of Evacuee Property Act, 1950 <lb/>and Rules made thereunder in a particular village. It was an admitted fact <lb/>the appellants fell under the category of &quot;non-faujis&quot;. On October 9, <lb/>1951, the Director of Relief and Rehabilitation, Punjab, made an order <lb/>adverse to the interest of the appellants Shivdeo Singh and others. To <lb/>maintain the character of the said village as &quot;fauji&quot;, he directed that the <lb/>appellants have to move out for being accommodated in some other <lb/>village. Soon after this order was made, the appellants preferred a writ <lb/>petition before the High Court of Punjab for quashing the order. The <lb/>Director of Rehabilitation alone was made a party thereto. The petition <lb/>was allowed by Hon&apos;ble Khosla, J. (as His Lordship then was). Eventually <lb/>the respondents 3 to 14 in the appeal before the Supreme Court, who were <lb/>members of &quot;fauji&quot; families and in whose favour either allotment had been <lb/>made or was intended to be made, preferred a petition before the High <lb/>Court under Article 226 of the Constitution for impleading them as parties <lb/>in the appellants&apos; petition and re-hearing the whole matter. The petition <lb/>was entertained by the High Court and Hon&apos;ble Khosla, J. allowed it. The <lb/>appellants preferred a Letters Patent appeal before the High Court which <lb/>having been dismissed, the Supreme Court was approached in appeal by <lb/>special leave. Hon&apos;ble J.R. Mudholkar, J. (as His Lordship then was) <lb/>speaking for the Bench ruled as follows: <lb/>::: Uploaded on -11/12/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:49 ::: <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Judgment <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>WP2412.20 <lb/>ANSARI <lb/>&quot;8. <lb/>The other contention of Mr Gopal Singh pertains to the second <lb/>order of Khosla, J., which, in effect, reviews his prior order. Learned <lb/>counsel contends that Article 226 of the Constitution does not confer <lb/>any power on the High Court to review its own order and, therefore, <lb/>the second order of Khosla, J., was without jurisdiction. It is sufficient <lb/>to say that there is nothing in Article 226 of the Constitution to pre-<lb/>clude a High Court from exercising the power of review which inheres <lb/>in every Court of plenary jurisdiction to prevent miscarriage of justice <lb/>or to correct grave and palpable errors committed by it. Here the pre-<lb/>vious order of Khosla, J., affected the interests of persons who were not <lb/>made parties to the proceeding before him. It was at their instance <lb/>and for giving them a hearing that Khosla, J., entertained the second <lb/>petition. In doing so, he merely did what the principles of natural jus-<lb/>tice required him to do. It is said that the respondents before us had <lb/>no right to apply for review because they were not parties to the pre-<lb/>vious proceedings. As we have already pointed out, it is precisely be-<lb/>cause they were not made parties to the previous proceedings, though <lb/>their interests were sought to be affected by the decision of the High <lb/>Court, that the second application was entertained by Khosla, J.&quot; <lb/>(emphasis ours) <lb/>11] <lb/>The ratio of such decision has been followed in the decision <lb/>reported in (2004) 6 SCC 126 : Pohla Singh vs. State of Punjab. The law <lb/>declared in such decision is that, if a decision rendered in a writ petition <lb/>adversely affects the interest of a third person who was not impleaded as <lb/>a party in the writ petition, it is always open to him to ask for recall of the <lb/>judgment which has been rendered without affording any opportunity of <lb/>hearing to him. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -11/12/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:49 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Judgment <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>WP2412.20 <lb/>ANSARI <lb/>12] <lb/>The facts of the present case appear to be unusually similar <lb/>to those arising for consideration in Shivdeo Singh (supra) and Pohla Singh <lb/>(supra). Admittedly, the petitioner was not included in the array of <lb/>respondents in any of the three writ petitions which were allowed by the <lb/>said judgment. We have noted from paragraph 15 of the said judgment that <lb/>objection had been raised to the effect that all the promotees were not <lb/>impleaded as respondents in the writ petitions. The expressed by the <lb/>Bench while dealing with such objection needs to be noted. <lb/>Paragraph 15 records as follows: <lb/>&quot;15. <lb/>Another objection raised is the absence of all <lb/>promotees being impleaded as respondents in the writ petitions. <lb/>According to the promoted respondents, since the entire process of <lb/>promotion was being challenged by the petitioners, it was <lb/>necessary for them to implead all the Assistant Professors who had <lb/>been promoted as Associate Professors. In reply, it has been <lb/>submitted by the petitioners that only those Assistant Professors <lb/>who were less meritorious than the petitioners but had been <lb/>promoted as Associate Professors were impleaded as respondents. <lb/>The justification for the same is that if the procedure as prescribed <lb/>by the Statutes is adopted, the concerned respondents being less <lb/>meritorious than the petitioners, they were not liable to be <lb/>promoted. The petitioners therefore have chosen to challenge the <lb/>promotions of such promotees who were less meritorious than the <lb/>petitioners. <lb/>In the light of the specific challenge raised by the <lb/>petitioners and as they are aggrieved by the adoption of a different <lb/>procedure than the one prescribed by the Statutes which has <lb/>resulted in less meritorious candidates being promoted, we are <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -11/12/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:49 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Judgment <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>WP2412.20 <lb/>ANSARI <lb/>inclined to examine the challenge as raised on merits and we do <lb/>not find it appropriate to non-suit the petitioners only on the <lb/>ground that all promoted Associate Professors have not been <lb/>impleaded as respondents. In any event, the petitioners have no <lb/>grievance with the promotion of such Associate Professors who are <lb/>more meritorious than them and hence in this backdrop, such <lb/>more meritorious candidates are not found to be even proper <lb/>parties. We are conscious of the position that promotions of such <lb/>Assistant Professors who have been promoted but have not been <lb/>impleaded cannot be challenged in their absence. <lb/>(emphasis ours) <lb/>13] <lb/>Once the co-ordinate Bench in the said judgment has <lb/>observed that it was conscious of the legal position that promotions of <lb/>such Assistant Professors as Associate Professors who have not been <lb/>impleaded as respondents could not be challenged in their absence, our <lb/>task becomes easy. We are inclined to the view that the observation in the <lb/>operative directions quoted above constitute an error apparent on the face <lb/>of the record which, in the exercise of the inherent power of this Court <lb/>(being a court of plenary jurisdiction) deserves to be reviewed. The <lb/>observation in paragraph 28 is plainly inconsistent with the conclusion <lb/>recorded in paragraph 15 and, thus, interests of justice would require that <lb/>the two inconsistent views be reconciled, if possible; if not, to review the <lb/>said judgment and relieve such of the promotees, who were not parties to <lb/>the earlier proceedings, from being visited with adverse civil <lb/>consequences not only on the ground of their non-impleadment but <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -11/12/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:49 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Judgment <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>WP2412.20 <lb/>ANSARI <lb/>because of the clear stand of the petitioners in course of hearing of the said <lb/>three writ petitions that only selection and appointment of less <lb/>meritorious promotee candidates had been challenged consequent <lb/>whereto only such promotees were impleaded as respondents. The co-<lb/>ordinate Bench having found that the highly meritorious candidates were <lb/>not even proper parties, the observation made in paragraph 28 be <lb/>applied only to candidates who were not as meritorious as the petitioners <lb/>in W.P. Nos. 2444/2019, 2471/2019 &amp; 2806/2019; but such observation <lb/>had no application qua a candidate like the petitioner, who was not only <lb/>not a respondent, but is claimed to be a highly meritorious candidate. Also, <lb/>the petitioner could not have figured in the scheme of things since none of <lb/>the respondents, who instituted the said three writ petitions as <lb/>petitioners, were Assistant Professors in Horticulture. Their subjects being <lb/>different, the observation in paragraph 28 could not have been made the <lb/>sheet anchor to direct reversion and fresh selection, and carried forward <lb/>to the detriment and prejudice of the petitioner. The University while <lb/>reading paragraph 28 seems to have been clearly oblivious of the <lb/>unambiguous conclusion recorded in paragraph 15 by Their Lordships. <lb/>14] <lb/>In such view of the matter, in exercise of our power of review, <lb/>we hold that any action taken by the University to divest the petitioner of <lb/>the fruits of promotion as an Associate Professor, Horticulture, triggered <lb/>by the observation in paragraph 28, must be regarded as inoperative and <lb/>ineffective having regard to the observation made in paragraph 15 of the <lb/>::: Uploaded on -11/12/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:49 ::: <lb/>Judgment <lb/>15 <lb/>WP2412.20 <lb/>ANSARI <lb/>said judgment. As a consequence, we hold that the reversion of the <lb/>petitioner by the University by the order dated July 9, 2020 not at all being <lb/>lawful, in the sense that the University was nudged to act on the basis of <lb/>the observation in paragraph 28 of the said judgment by the respondents <lb/>represented by Mr. Sudame despite the observation in paragraph 15 <lb/>thereof, merits to be set aside. We order accordingly. <lb/>15] <lb/>The result of the aforesaid direction would be that the <lb/>petitioner shall be deemed to have continued in service on the promoted <lb/>post of Associate Professor, Horticulture from the initial date of his <lb/>promotion notwithstanding the action taken by the University in terms of <lb/>the said judgment. The selection process that the University has initiated, <lb/>pursuant to the impugned order of this Court, needs to be aborted and <lb/>shall not be carried forward any further. We, therefore, allow the writ <lb/>petition with the aforesaid directions. Since the petitioner has not suffered <lb/>adversely because of the timely intervention by this Court by its aforesaid <lb/>interim order, we refrain from imposing costs. <lb/>16] <lb/>We, however, make it clear that this order does not affect any <lb/>action taken by the University against the promotees who were <lb/>respondents in the said three writ petitions and which were disposed of <lb/>by the said judgment. Any process initiated against any of the respondents <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -11/12/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:49 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Judgment <lb/></note>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">WP2412.20 <lb/>ANSARI <lb/></note>

			<body>in such writ petitions may be taken to its logical conclusion, in accordance <lb/>with law. <lb/>17] <lb/>Pending application(s), if any, stand(s) disposed of. <lb/>(VINAY JOSHI, J.) <lb/>(CHIEF JUSTICE) <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -11/12/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:49 ::: </note>


	</text>
</tei>
