<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_3c9fa8196e4f6b7a19d0c83d35b2db09.pdf"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">


        <figure>

            WP2412.20<lb/> ANSARI<lb/> whereby these writ </content>
 
            <figDesc>petitions were disposed of, directed. Incidentally, the<lb/> said three writ petitions were instituted by the respondents before us who<lb/> are represented by Mr. Sudame.<lb/> 5]<lb/> The first of these writ petitions [W.P. No. 2444/2019], at the<lb/> instance of Ms. Amrapali W/o Atul Akhare, challenged the promotional<lb/> orders of appointments of the respondents 2 to 5 therein on the post of<lb/> Associate Professor, Agricultural Botany. The second writ petition [W.P. No.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            WP2412.20<lb/> ANSARI<lb/> moved, a </content>
 
            <figDesc>co-ordinate Bench of this Court by its order dated October 5,<lb/> 2020 stayed the order of reversion with the effect that the petitioner has<lb/> continued to function as an Associate Professor in Horticulture. However,<lb/> the Court granted liberty to the University to finalize the process of fresh<lb/> selection and we are informed that the process has been completed and<lb/> the consequent recommendation kept in a sealed cover.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            WP2412.20<lb/> ANSARI<lb/> Singh vs. </content>
 
            <figDesc>State of Punjab. There, certain agricultural lands were allotted to<lb/> a number of displaced persons including the appellants on a quasi-<lb/>permanent basis under the administration of Evacuee Property Act, 1950<lb/> and Rules made thereunder in a particular village. It was an admitted fact<lb/> the appellants fell under the category of &quot;non-faujis&quot;. On October 9,<lb/> 1951, the Director of Relief and Rehabilitation, Punjab, made an order<lb/> adverse to the interest of the appellants Shivdeo Singh and others. To<lb/> maintain the character of the said village as &quot;fauji&quot;, he directed that the<lb/> appellants have to move out for being accommodated in some other<lb/> village. Soon after this order was made, the appellants preferred a writ<lb/> petition before the High Court of Punjab for quashing the order. The<lb/> Director of Rehabilitation alone was made a party thereto. The petition<lb/> was allowed by Hon&apos;ble Khosla, J. (as His Lordship then was). Eventually<lb/> the respondents 3 to 14 in the appeal before the Supreme Court, who were<lb/> members of &quot;fauji&quot; families and in whose favour either allotment had been<lb/> made or was intended to be made, preferred a petition before the High<lb/> Court under Article 226 of the Constitution for impleading them as parties<lb/> in the appellants&apos; petition and re-hearing the whole matter. The petition<lb/> was entertained by the High Court and Hon&apos;ble Khosla, J. allowed it. The<lb/> appellants preferred a Letters Patent appeal before the High Court which<lb/> having been dismissed, the Supreme Court was approached in appeal by<lb/> special leave. Hon&apos;ble J.R. Mudholkar, J. (as His Lordship then was)<lb/> speaking for the Bench ruled as follows:<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -11/12/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:49 :::<lb/> WP2412.20<lb/> ANSARI<lb/> &quot;8.</content>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            WP2412.20<lb/> ANSARI<lb/> inclined to examine </content>
 
            <figDesc>the challenge as raised on merits and we do<lb/> not find it appropriate to non-suit the petitioners only on the<lb/> ground that all promoted Associate Professors have not been<lb/> impleaded as respondents. In any event, the petitioners have no<lb/> grievance with the promotion of such Associate Professors who are<lb/> more meritorious than them and hence in this backdrop, such<lb/> more meritorious candidates are not found to be even proper<lb/> parties. We are conscious of the position that promotions of such<lb/> Assistant Professors who have been promoted but have not been<lb/> impleaded cannot be challenged in their absence.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            WP2412.20<lb/> ANSARI<lb/> because of the </content>
 
            <figDesc>clear stand of the petitioners in course of hearing of the said<lb/> three writ petitions that only selection and appointment of less<lb/> meritorious promotee candidates had been challenged consequent<lb/> whereto only such promotees were impleaded as respondents. The co-<lb/>ordinate Bench having found that the highly meritorious candidates were<lb/> not even proper parties, the observation made in paragraph 28 be<lb/> applied only to candidates who were not as meritorious as the petitioners<lb/> in W.P. Nos. 2444/2019, 2471/2019 &amp; 2806/2019; but such observation<lb/> had no application qua a candidate like the petitioner, who was not only<lb/> not a respondent, but is claimed to be a highly meritorious candidate. Also,<lb/> the petitioner could not have figured in the scheme of things since none of<lb/> the respondents, who instituted the said three writ petitions as<lb/> petitioners, were Assistant Professors in Horticulture. Their subjects being<lb/> different, the observation in paragraph 28 could not have been made the<lb/> sheet anchor to direct reversion and fresh selection, and carried forward<lb/> to the detriment and prejudice of the petitioner. The University while<lb/> reading paragraph 28 seems to have been clearly oblivious of the<lb/> unambiguous conclusion recorded in paragraph 15 by Their Lordships.<lb/> 14]<lb/> In such view of the matter, in exercise of our power of review,<lb/> we hold that any action taken by the University to divest the petitioner of<lb/> the fruits of promotion as an Associate Professor, Horticulture, triggered<lb/> by the observation in paragraph 28, must be regarded as inoperative and<lb/> ineffective having regard to the observation made in paragraph 15 of the<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -11/12/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:49 :::<lb/> Judgment<lb/> 15<lb/> WP2412.20<lb/> ANSARI<lb/> said judgment. </content>
 
            <figDesc>As a consequence, we hold that the reversion of the<lb/> petitioner by the University by the order dated July 9, 2020 not at all being<lb/> lawful, in the sense that the University was nudged to act on the basis of<lb/> the observation in paragraph 28 of the said judgment by the respondents<lb/> represented by Mr. Sudame despite the observation in paragraph 15</figDesc>
        </figure>



    </text>
</tei>

