<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_3f0cbc6d2689f1a392bbe01488772744.pdf"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">


        <figure>

            <figDesc>Mohd. Riyazur Rehman Siddiqui<lb/> )<lb/> S/o Mohd. Abdur Rehman Siddiqui<lb/> )<lb/> Age 50 years, Occ.: Service with . )<lb/> resident of Nobel Colony, Udgir<lb/> )<lb/> District Latur now at Murum, Tal.</figDesc>
: Omerga<lb/> )<lb/> District Osmanabad<lb/> ).. Appellant<lb/> (Org. Claimant)<lb/> Versus<lb/> Deputy Director of Health Services<lb/> )<lb/> through the District Health Officer<lb/> )<lb/> Zilla Parishad, Latur, Tal. &amp; District Latur<lb/> ).. Respondent<lb/> ( Resp.No.1)<lb/> Mr M M Patil, Advocate holding for Mr M B Sabnis for<lb/> the Appellant.<lb/> Mr N B Khandare, Government Pleader, for State.<lb/> Mr P R Tandale, Advocate for Respondent.<lb/> WITH<lb/> CIVIL APPLICATION NO. 1407 OF 2006<lb/> IN<lb/> LETTERS PATENT APPEAL STAMP NO. 20447 OF 2005<lb/> 1) Sonabai w/o Deorao Takale<lb/> )<lb/> Age 54 years, Occ.: Household<lb/> )<lb/> 2) Sunita w/o Kalyan Takale<lb/> )<lb/> Age 32 years, Occ.: Agriculture<lb/> )<lb/> 3) Appasaheb s/o Kalyan Takale<lb/> )<lb/> Age 16 years, Occ.: Student<lb/> )<lb/> 4) Bharat </content>
 
            <figDesc>s/o Kalyan Takale<lb/> )<lb/> Age 14 years, Occ.: Student<lb/> )<lb/> Both u/g of their mother-Appellant No.2 )<lb/> All r/o Rohilgad, Tq.: Ambad,Dist.: Jalna )</figDesc>

            .. APPLICANTS<lb/> (Org. Claimants)<lb/> Versus<lb/> 1) Baban alias Punjaji s/o Tulsiram Jawale<lb/> )<lb/> Age 28 years, Occu.: Driver<lb/> )<lb/> R/o Chandanzira, Jalna<lb/> )<lb/> (Deleted as per Order dated 13/8/07)<lb/> )<lb/> 2) Akram Khan s/o Ahsaan Khan Kaisar<lb/> )<lb/> Age 45 years, Occu: Business<lb/> )<lb/> R/o Kaisar Colony, Aurangabad<lb/> )<lb/> 3) Managar, United India Insurance Company)<lb/> R.P. Road, Jalna.<lb/> ).. RESPONDENTS<lb/> (Org.Respondents)<lb/> None present for the Applicants.<lb/> Respondent No.1 deleted.<lb/> Respondent No.2 served.<lb/> Mr R F </content>
 
            <figDesc>Totla, Advocate for Respondent No.3.<lb/> Tribunal, Latur, which was contested and decided finally by the Tribunal<lb/> vide its judgment and award dated 5 th May 1989 awarding compensation of<lb/> Rs.51,000/-only with interest at the rate of 10% per annum from the date of<lb/> the claim petition. This judgment of the Tribunal was impugned by the<lb/> Claimant by filing First Appeal No.638 of 1989 before this Court praying for<lb/> enhancement of the compensation awarded. The owner-driver of the jeep<lb/> died on 16 th July, 1987 during the pendency of the Claim Petition before the<lb/> Tribunal. The Insurance Company had denied its liability and the present<lb/> Appeal was only preferred against the Respondent No.1-owner of the<lb/> vehicle. The Deputy Director of Health Services-original Respondent No.1,<lb/> being owner of the jeep also preferred Appeal being First Appeal No. 637 of<lb/> 1989 impugning the judgment of the Tribunal. First Appeal No.637 of 1989<lb/> was dismissed by a learned Single Judge of this Court vide common<lb/> judgment dated 12 th February 2004. The Appeal filed by the Claimant (First<lb/> Appeal No.638 of 1989) was partly allowed and the compensation was<lb/> enhanced to Rs.56,000/-with interest at the rate of 9% per annum.<lb/> Dissatisfied from the judgment of the learned Single Judge, the Claimant<lb/> filed Letters Patent Appeal No. 35 of 2005 praying for further enhancement.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            2.<lb/> Civil Application No</content>

            <figDesc>. 1407 of 2006 has been filed in Letters<lb/> Patent Appeal (Stamp) No. 20447 of 2006 for condonation of delay of 212<lb/> days caused in filing Letters Patent Appeal against judgment of the learned<lb/> Single Judge in First Appeal No. 129 of 1998.<lb/> There was no serious objection on behalf of the learned Counsel<lb/> appearing for the Respondents for condonation of delay in filing the<lb/> present Appeal. We have perused the Application. Since sufficient<lb/> cause for condonation of delay is shown, the Civil Application is<lb/> allowed. The delay of 212 days in filing the present appeal is<lb/> condoned. The Civil Application is accordingly disposed of. Registry<lb/> to register and number the Letters Patent Appeal accordingly.<lb/> 3.<lb/> First Appeal No. 129 of 1998 was filed challenging judgment<lb/> and award of the Motor Accident Claims Tribunal, Jalna. The Claimants<lb/> therein are the dependents of deceased Kalyan Takale, aged 28 years, who<lb/> died on 16 th April 1995 due to injuries sustained in an accident arising out of<lb/> use of motor vehicle which occurred on 15 th April 1995. The accident<lb/> occurred when motor-cycle No.MH-21 driven by the deceased was dashed<lb/> by Taxi No. MH-20-A-7090 driven by Respondent No.1 in a rash or<lb/> negligent manner. The taxi was owned by Respondent No.2 and was<lb/> insured with Respondent No.3. The Motor Accident Claims Tribunal, Jalna<lb/> by Judgment and Award dated 4 th April 1997 directed Respondent Nos.1 to<lb/> 3 to pay amount of Rs.1,50,000/-(inclusive of no fault liability) to<lb/> Claimants with interest at the rate of 12% per annum. The Judgment/Award<lb/> of the Tribunal was challenged in First Appeal No. 129 of 1998 in which the<lb/> learned Single Judge by Judgment and Award dated 25 th January 2005<lb/> modified the Award by substituting figure of Rs.2,00,000/-(Two lakhs) in<lb/> place of Rs.1,00,000/-(One lakh). This Judgment/Award of the learned<lb/> Single Judge is challenged by filing Letters Patent Appeal (Stamp) No.<lb/> 20447 of 2005 by Claimants seeking further enhancement in the amount of<lb/> compensation.<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ORDER OF REFERENCE:<lb/> 4.<lb/> When the matter </content>
 
            <figDesc>came up for hearing before a Division Bench<lb/> of this Court on 22 nd February 2008, the learned Counsel appearing for the<lb/> respective parties relied upon different judgments of this Court as well as of<lb/> the Supreme Court to argue for and against the very maintainability of the<lb/> Letters Patent Appeal in view of the provisions of Sections 100A of the<lb/> Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, Section 173 of the Motor Vehicles Act, 1988<lb/> (hereinafter referred to as the &quot;M.V. Act&quot;) Clause 15 of the Letters Patent.<lb/> The Division Bench of this Court noticed the view expressed by another<lb/> Division Bench of this Court in the case of Asha d/o Bhalchandra Joshi vs<lb/> National Insurance Co. Ltd., 2008 (1) Mh.L.J. 724, and the view of the<lb/> other Benches and noticing the difference of opinion expressed in different<lb/> judgments, directed the matter to be referred to a larger Bench for settling<lb/> the legal issue involved in the present case with regard to the maintainability<lb/> of the Letters Patent Appeal.<lb/> 5.<lb/> It will be useful to refer to the Order of Reference dated 22 nd<lb/> February 2008 which reads as under:-<lb/>&quot;1.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>formulate the questions which are likely to arise repeatedly before the<lb/> Court and even otherwise are questions of law of some significance as<lb/> under :-<lb/>(a)<lb/> Whether, upon amendment to Section 100A of<lb/> the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 ( with effect<lb/> from 1 st July, 2002 ), the Letters Patent Appeal<lb/> against the judgment rendered by the learned<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> Single Judge of<lb/> High<lb/> Court would be<lb/> maintainable ?<lb/> (b)<lb/> Whether an appeal </content>
 
            <figDesc>arising out of special statute<lb/> like Motor Vehicles Act, 1988 ( even if<lb/> assuming that it is a special statute ) would be<lb/> maintainable under Clause 15 of the Letter<lb/> Patent against the judgment passed by the<lb/> learned Single Judge of this Court in exercise of<lb/> its appellate jurisdiction ?<lb/> RELEVANT PROVISIONS OF LAW AND THEIR IMPACT ON THE<lb/> LEGAL ISSUES FORMULATED.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>It will be appropriate to examine the legislative<lb/> amendment to the Code of Civil Procedure. The Code of Civil<lb/> Procedure, 1882 was replaced by Code of 1908. However, Section<lb/> 100A was introduced for the first time by amending Act 104 of 1976.<lb/> The intent was to bar third appeal before a Division Bench of the High<lb/> Court from a judgment of the Single Judge deciding a matter in a<lb/> Second Appeal. By the amending Act of 1999, the earlier Section<lb/> 100A was substituted. Section 100A as introduced by amending Act<lb/> 46 of 1999, though attained the assent of the President on 30 th<lb/> December 1999, it was not enforced because of various factors. Clause<lb/> (b) of Section 100A was subsequently deleted finally and as already<lb/> noticed, by the amending Act of 2002, present Section 100A was<lb/> introduced. Present Section 100A reads as under :-<lb/>&quot;Section 100A. Notwithstanding anything contained in<lb/> any Letters Patent for any High Court or in any other<lb/> instrument having the force of law or in any other law<lb/> for the time being in force, where any appeal from an<lb/> original or appellate decree or order is heard and<lb/> decided by a single judge of a High Court, no further<lb/> appeal shall lie from the judgment and decree of such<lb/> single judge.&quot;<lb/> 11.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>prospective and would not affect the right and remedies of an<lb/> Appellant who had filed the Appeal prior to 1 st July 2002. In other<lb/> words, accrued right of appeal vested in a suitor was not affected.<lb/> This view was also taken by a Full Bench of the Punjab &amp; Haryana<lb/> High Court in the case of Parashottam Dass vs State of Haryana, AIR<lb/> 2003 P&amp;H 301. The Full Bench of this Court in the case of Rahul<lb/> Sharad vs Ratnakar, 2004 (3) Mh. L.J. 706, took the same view which<lb/> is approved by the Apex Court in Bento De Souza Egipsy vs Yvette<lb/> Alvares Colaco, (2004) 13 SCC 438. The Supreme Court in a more<lb/> recent case of Kamla Devi vs Kushal Kanwar and another, (2006) 13<lb/> SCC 295 referring to Bento De Souza (supra) and Sanjay Z Rane vs<lb/> Saibai S Dubaxi, (2004) 13 SCC 439 wherein it is opined that Section<lb/> 100A of the Code has no retrospective effect observed that the Letters<lb/> Patent Appeal filed prior to coming into force of the 2002 Act would<lb/> be maintainable.<lb/> 15.<lb/> The right of Appeal is a substantive right. The vested right<lb/> of appeal can be taken away only by a subsequent enactment if so<lb/> provided expressly or by necessary intendment and not otherwise.<lb/> 16.<lb/> The Supreme Court in the case of Garikapati Veeraya vs N<lb/> Subbiah Choudhry, AIR 1957 SC 540, spelt out the five propositions as<lb/> precepts to right of appeal. The formulated propositions read as<lb/> under :-</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>17.<lb/> Once the Legislature has decided to take away the right of<lb/> Second Appeal the intra-Court appeals are impermissible specifically in<lb/> face of the fact that constitutional validity of Section 100A has been<lb/> upheld. The scope of Section 100A is so wide that it would take into<lb/> its sweep not only other laws but even the Letters Patent of a High<lb/> Court. The intention of the Legislature in taking away of right of<lb/> appeal by abolishing an intra-Court appeal to a Bench of two Judges of<lb/> the very High Court against a decision rendered by a Single Judge, is<lb/> in no way prejudicial to the protected right of appeal of a litigant. The<lb/> Scheme of Section 100A thus indicates that intra-Court appeal from an<lb/> appellate jurisdiction of a Single Judge of the High Court is not<lb/> permissible.<lb/> 18.<lb/> The Motor Vehicle Act, 1988 is considered and was<lb/> enacted as social welfare legislation to provide adequate compensation<lb/> to the people who sustained bodily injuries or to dependents of<lb/> persons who are killed in vehicular accident expeditiously. This Act<lb/> has been considered even as a self-contained Code as it provides<lb/> methodology to be adopted for institution of claim petition, powers of<lb/> the Tribunal and passing of an award and how such an award would<lb/> be executed. The Tribunal is established for adjudicating such claims<lb/> by a State Notification issued under the provisions of Section 165 of<lb/> the Act. On receipt of an application for compensation claimed under<lb/> Section 166 of the Act, the Claims Tribunal is expected to issue<lb/> notice/afford an opportunity of being heard to parties, hold inquiry<lb/> into the claim and then to make an award determining the amount of<lb/> compensation payable to the claimants. The Tribunal determines all<lb/> questions of law and fact while arriving at a conclusion. The<lb/> jurisdiction of the Tribunal does not limit to determine compensation<lb/> but even as to the party/parties liable to pay compensation and its<lb/> extent.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            19.<lb/> While holding an </content>
 
            <figDesc>inquiry as contemplated under Section<lb/> 168 of the Act, the Claims Tribunal has to follow summary procedure<lb/> as the Tribunal thinks fit, subject to the rules made in this behalf.<lb/> However, it has all the powers of a civil court for the purpose of taking<lb/> evidence on oath and of enforcing the attendance of witnesses and of<lb/> compelling the discovery and production of documents and material<lb/> objects and for such other purposes as may be prescribed. Further the<lb/> Claims Tribunal shall be deemed to be a civil court for all purposes of<lb/> Section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure,<lb/> 1973. Section 175 mandates that where any Claims Tribunal has been<lb/> constituted for any area, no civil court shall have jurisdiction to<lb/> entertain any question relating to any claim for compensation which<lb/> may be adjudicated upon by the Claims Tribunal.<lb/> The State<lb/> Government is competent to frame rules for the purposes of carrying<lb/> into effect the provisions of Sections 165 to 174 of the Act and it can<lb/> frame rules which may provide for the matters indicated in that<lb/> section and in particular, the procedure to be followed by a Claims<lb/> Tribunal in holding an inquiry under the said Chapter XXVI and in<lb/> terms of Section 176(c) of the Act, the powers vested in a civil court<lb/> which may be exercised by a Claims Tribunal.<lb/> 20.<lb/> In exercise of its power vested in it under Section 176, the<lb/> State of Maharashtra has framed rules known as &quot;Maharashtra Motor<lb/> Vehicles Rules, 1989&quot; and Rules 275 and 276 thereof deal with the<lb/> powers of a civil court which may be exercised by Claims Tribunal and<lb/> the procedure to be followed by a Claims Tribunal in holding inquiries<lb/> respectively. The Tribunal is fully empowered to exercise powers<lb/> vested in a civil court in relation to the procedural matters and is<lb/> vested with wide powers including Sections 151, 152 and 153 of the<lb/> Code.<lb/> Some of the other provisions of the Code of Criminal<lb/> Procedure are also applicable to the proceedings before the Tribunal.<lb/> Some of the provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure i.e. Orders V, VI,<lb/> VII, IX, XI, XII, XIII, XIV, XVI, XVII, XVIII, XIX, XX, XXI, XXII, XXIII,<lb/> XXIV, XXVI, XXVII, XXVIII, XXIX, XXX, XXXII, XXXVII AND XXXIX are<lb/> also applicable to the proceedings before the Tribunal.<lb/> These<lb/> provisions clearly indicate that the Tribunal has all trapping of a civil<lb/> court may be in stricto senso it is not a court within the meaning of the<lb/> provisions of Code of Civil Procedure. The provisions of the Code of<lb/> Civil Procedure by and large are applicable in all matters to the<lb/> proceedings before the Tribunal.<lb/> The Tribunal in exercise of its<lb/> power is obliged to determine all issues in controversy of fact and law<lb/> in accordance with the provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure. As<lb/> already noticed, even the provisions relating to amendment of<lb/> pleadings additional evidence, service of summons and proceedings by<lb/> an indigent person, all are applicable to the Tribunal.<lb/> 21.<lb/> As early as in 1950s, the Supreme Court in the case of The<lb/> Bharat Bank Limited, Delhi v. The Employees of the Bharat Bank<lb/> Limited, Delhi, and the Bharat Bank Employee&apos;s Union, Delhi, reported<lb/> in AIR 1950 SC 184, enunciated the principle that an industrial<lb/> tribunal performs all duties and functions of a court. The provisions of<lb/> that Act also shows that the Tribunal is discharging functions very<lb/> near to those of a court, although it is not a court in the technical<lb/> sense of the word.<lb/> 22.<lb/> In the case of Jaswant Sugar Mills Ltd. Meerut v. Lakshmi<lb/> Chand &amp; Ors., reported in AIR 1963 SC 677, the Court while<lb/> considering the essential characteristics of judicial adjudication by<lb/> process of determination culminating in the judicial decision observed<lb/> that a judicial decision always postulates the existence of a duty laid</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>Though the Tribunals<lb/> occupy a special position of their own under the<lb/> scheme of the Courts and Tribunals and special matters<lb/> and questions are entrusted to them for their decision<lb/> yet they share with the Courts one common<lb/> characteristic viz.; both the Courts as well as Tribunals<lb/> are constituted by the State and are invested with<lb/> judicial functions as distinguished from purely<lb/> administrative or executive functions. It is the State&apos;s<lb/> inherent judicial power which is discharged by the<lb/> Courts and Tribunals. If the Company Law Board<lb/> constituted under the Companies Act in its<lb/> adjudicatory powers has the trappings of a Court and<lb/> an appeal under Section 10F of the Companies Act<lb/> from its order to the single Judge is not amenable to<lb/> further appeal (Letters Patent) to the Division Bench of<lb/> the same Court because of Section 100A of the Code of<lb/> Civil Procedure, a fortiori, an order passed by the<lb/> Single Judge in appeal under Section 173 of the Motor<lb/> Vehicles Act from the order/award of the Motor<lb/> Accident Claims Tribunal shall not be subject to intra-<lb/>Court appeal in view of the bar created by Section<lb/> 100A of the Code of Civil Procedure effective from 1 st<lb/> July, 2002.&quot;<lb/> ( Emphasis supplied )<lb/> 31.<lb/> In the light of the above judgment and consistent view<lb/> taken by the courts there can hardly be any doubt that the Tribunal<lb/> does have trappings of a court. It satisfies all the tests stated above.<lb/> In any case, it has power to summon, record statements on oath,<lb/> compel attendance of the witnesses, determine controversies by a<lb/> public adjudicatory process and even has the power to punish the<lb/> defaulters. It can get its award executed in accordance with the law.<lb/> Besides all these, it is performing duties and functions of<lb/> administration of justice under the power of the State and in fact<lb/> under a statute. At this stage itself, we may notice that the Division<lb/> Bench of this Court in the case of Asha d/o Bhalchandra Joshi vs.<lb/> National Insurance Co. Ltd., reported in 2008 (1) Mh. L.J. 724 did<lb/> not consider the judgment of the Supreme Court in Kamal Kumar<lb/> Dutta&apos;s case (supra) and of this Court in Gurucharansing Hardayalsing<lb/> Sethi vs Narhari Laxman Shinde and others, (1996) 4 Bom. C.R. 298,<lb/> besides it has ignored the basic principles applicable for determination<lb/> i.e. whether the Tribunal has a trappings of a Court or not. With<lb/> respect, we are unable to follow the view taken by a Division Bench in<lb/> that case in this regard.<lb/> 32.<lb/> As far as the appeals under the Motor Vehicle Act are<lb/> concerned, it specifically provides that the award of the Tribunal made<lb/> under Section 165 of the Act would be appeallable to the High Court<lb/> under Section 173 of the Act. Section 173 of the Act thus reads as<lb/> under: -<lb/>&quot;173. Appeals : (1) Subject to the provisions of sub-<lb/>section (2), any person aggrieved by an award of a<lb/> Claims Tribunal may, within ninety days from the date<lb/> of the award, prefer an appeal to the High Court :</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>bare reading of Section 173 of the Act shows that the<lb/> provisions are self-contained in all respects. It provides for filing an<lb/> appeal by any person aggrieved by an award of the Claim Tribunal<lb/> provided the amount in appeal is not less than Rs.10,000/-. Such<lb/> appeals are to be filed within 90 days and the appeal would be<lb/> entertained by the High Court subject to satisfaction of the conditions<lb/> stipulated under the proviso 1 of Section 173(1) of the Act. In terms<lb/> of proviso 2 of Section 173(1) of the Act, the High Court can entertain<lb/> an appeal even after the expiry of 90 days if it has shown sufficient<lb/> cause for preferring an appeal beyond time. In other words, this<lb/> provision indicates the scope of powers of the High Court while<lb/> entertaining an appeal under the said provision. The ambit, scope and<lb/> the powers thus have been outlined by the Legislature itself and may<lb/> not be dependent on the provisions of other laws.<lb/> There is no<lb/> provision in the entire M.V. Act which provides for further appeal from<lb/> the judgment passed by the High Court in exercise of its appellate<lb/> jurisdiction under Section 173 of the M.V. Act.<lb/> 34.<lb/> Once the M.V. Act provides for a remedy of First Appeal<lb/> and does not specify availability of any further right of appeal, it is<lb/> obvious that the Legislature does not intend to give any further right<lb/> of appeal within the provisions of the Act particularly in relation to<lb/> intra-Court appeal. The right to appeal and in fact all remedial<lb/> provisions do not emerge from any fundamental or vested right. It is a<lb/> grant or a statute under which such right of appeal is available. In<lb/> view of this settled principle, the absence of any provision providing a<lb/> further appeal in terms of Section 173 of the Act would obviously lead<lb/> to one inevitable conclusion that the special law (i.e. Motor Vehicle<lb/> Act) in comparison to general laws (i.e. Code of Civil Procedure) does<lb/> not contemplate maintainability of a second appeal against the<lb/> judgment of the learned Single Judge.<lb/> It may also be noticed that<lb/> remedy of appeal being a statutory right, cannot be introduced by<lb/> judicial interpretative process. The Court would be very reluctant to<lb/> read into the statute, a right of appeal in absence of any such specific<lb/> provision.<lb/> NATURE OF RIGHT OF APPEAL:<lb/> 35.<lb/> According to Salmond, (Salmond on Jurisprudence,<lb/> Twelfth Edition), the right in the strict sense is duty which is<lb/> something owed by one to another. Correspondingly, the latter has a<lb/> right against the former. The expression `right&apos; is capable of being<lb/> used in wider sense. Thus the rights are concerned with interest, yet<lb/> right and interest are not identical. Bentham introduced the concept<lb/> of natural law and natural rights which, according to him, are two<lb/> kinds of fictions or metaphors which play a greater part in books of<lb/> legislation that they deserve to be examined by themselves. Of<lb/> course, this concept has not found much acceptance so far in<lb/> legislative or judicial analysis. A legal right is commonly accompanied<lb/> by the power of instituting legal proceedings for enforcement of it.<lb/> Legal rights are normally enforceable by process of law. There could<lb/> be a situation where a legal right itself is imperfect and, therefore,<lb/> becomes unenforceable in law. Every legal right has distinguishable<lb/> characteristics, like it is vested in a person, it is available against a<lb/> person and such right is enforceable in accordance with the provisions<lb/> of law. A legal right could also be a vested right as it gives right to a<lb/> person aggrieved to prefer an appeal in accordance with the principles<lb/> of that statute. In simple language, a right to appeal is a statutory<lb/> right, it is neither a natural nor a fundamental right.<lb/> 36.<lb/> An appeal is an application to a superior Court or Tribunal<lb/> praying for reversal or varying or setting aside a judgment under<lb/> appeal. A right which is conferred by statute or equivalent legislative<lb/> authority is not a matter of practice or procedure and neither the<lb/> superior nor the inferior Court or Tribunal nor both combined can<lb/> create or take away such a right. Even the Civil Division of the Court<lb/> of Appeal in England is bound by its own decisions. No appeal lies<lb/> from a decision of the Court of Appeal as to whether a judgment or<lb/> order is, for any purpose connected with an appeal to that Court, final<lb/> or interlocutory. Right to appeal thus should be created by vested<lb/> specific jurisdiction. (Halsbury Law of England, Fourth Edition).</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            40.<lb/> This view was </content>
 
            <figDesc>reiterated with approval by the<lb/> Supreme Court in the case of Gujarat Agro Industries Co. Ltd. Vs<lb/> Municipal Corporation of the City of Ahmedabad and others,<lb/> (1999) 4 SCC 468, where the Court stated that even right of<lb/> appeal can be made conditional or qualified and it is a creation<lb/> of a statute alone. The Court held as under :-</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            41.<lb/> Right of appeal </content>
 
            <figDesc>is neither a natural nor inherent right<lb/> vested in a party. It is substantive statutory right regulated by the<lb/> statute creating it. (Kondiba Dagadu Kadam vs Savitribai Sopan Gujar<lb/> and others, (1999) 3 SCC 722, and Kashmir Singh vs Harnam Singh<lb/> and another, 2008 AIR SCW 2417).<lb/> 42.<lb/> Thus, it is evident that the right to appeal is not a right<lb/> which can be assumed by logical analysis much less by exercise of<lb/> inherent jurisdiction. It essentially should be provided by the law in<lb/> force. In absence of any specific provision creating a right in a party to<lb/> file an appeal, such right can neither be assumed nor inferred in<lb/> favour of the party. On the bare reading of provisions of Section 173<lb/> and in absence of any other specific provision providing further<lb/> appeal, it is difficult to accept the view that with the aid of any of the<lb/> provisions or by general practice the appellate order passed under<lb/> Section 173 by a Single Judge of this Court would be further<lb/> appealable by intra-Court appeal.<lb/> RIGHT OF APPEAL UNDER LETTERS PATENT :<lb/> 43.<lb/> It has been held that Letters Patent is a word of definite<lb/> legal meaning. It is derived from the latin words literae patents. The<lb/> Letters Patent are so called because they are open letters, they are not<lb/> sealed up, but exposed to view, with the great seal pendant at the<lb/> bottom and are usually directed or addressed by the King to all his<lb/> subjects at large. Different Letters Patent have been handed down by<lb/> the Sovereign in British India to Chartered High Courts which included<lb/> only judicature of Bengal, Madras, Bombay, North-West Provinces,<lb/> Patna, Lahore and Rangoon. (See Blackstone&apos;s Commentaries on<lb/> the Laws of England, Vol. II. pp. 284-85).<lb/> 44.<lb/> Now, we may examine the impact of Clause 15 of the<lb/> Letters Patent which provides for intra-Court appeal. Clause 15 of the<lb/> Letters Patent does not create a substantive right of appeal from the<lb/> decision of the Single Judge, but such right is obviously subject to the<lb/> application of the stipulated condition. Right of appeal can be<lb/> exercised only in accordance with the limitations specified in the<lb/> provision granting right of appeal. Clause 15 of the Letters Patent<lb/> reads as under :-<lb/>&quot;15. Appeal to the High Court from Judges of the<lb/> Court:-And We do further ordain that an appeal shall<lb/> lie to the said High Court of Judicature at Bombay from<lb/> the judgment (not being a judgment passed in the<lb/> exercise of appellate jurisdiction by a Court subject to<lb/> the superintendence of the said High Court, and not<lb/> being an order made in the exercise of revisional<lb/> jurisdiction and not being a sentence or order passed or<lb/> made in the exercise of the power of superintendence<lb/> under the provisions of section 107 of the Government<lb/> of India Act, or in the exercise of criminal jurisdiction)<lb/> of one Judge of, the said High Court or one Judge of<lb/> any Divisional Court, pursuant to section 108 of the<lb/> Government of India Act, and that notwithstanding<lb/> anything herein before provided an appeal shall lie to<lb/> the said High Court from a Judgement of one Judge of<lb/> the said High Court from a Judge of any Division<lb/> Court, pursuant to section 108 of the Government of<lb/> India Act, made on or after the first day of February<lb/> one thousand nine hundred and twenty-nine in the<lb/> exercise of appellate jurisdiction; in respect of a decree<lb/> or order made in the exercise of appellate jurisdiction<lb/> by a Court subject to the superintendence of the said<lb/> High Court, where the Judge who passed the judgment<lb/> declares that the case is fit one for appeal; but that the<lb/> right of appeal from other judgments of Judge of the<lb/> High Court or of such Division Court shall be to Us,<lb/> Our heirs of successors in Our or Their Privy Council,<lb/> as hereinafter provided.&quot;<lb/> 45.<lb/> Clause 15 of the Letters Patent is the provision which<lb/> grants right of appeal to the aggrieved party against the judgment of<lb/> the learned Single Judge of the Court to Letters Patent Bench. The<lb/> exception carved out to this right of appeal is that the judgment not<lb/> being a judgment passed in the exercise of appellate jurisdiction in<lb/> respect of a decree or order made in the exercise of appellate<lb/> jurisdiction by a Court subject to the superintendence of the said High<lb/> Court, and not being an order made in the exercise of revisional<lb/> jurisdiction and not being a sentence or order passed or made in the<lb/> exercise of the power of superintendence under the provisions of<lb/> section 107 of the Government of India Act, or in the exercise of<lb/> criminal jurisdiction. In other words, where the clause grants right of<lb/> appeal, it has inbuilt exception and limitation applicable to said right<lb/> of appeal. It is also a settled proposition of law that a right to appeal<lb/> can be regulated and/or restricted by the provisions of Section<lb/> providing such right. The legal right that is available to a party to<lb/> prefer an appeal from the judgment of the learned Single Judge thus is<lb/> not a unrestricted or unfettered right. Besides the requirement that<lb/> the order of the learned Single Judge as understood in common<lb/> parlance has to be a judgment within the meaning of the said<lb/> expression of clause 15 of the Letters Patent to perfect a right of<lb/> appeal to litigant. Once it clears the parameter of a judgment and is<lb/> not hit by any of the exceptions stated in the clause itself, an appeal<lb/> may lie to a letters patent bench. Various aspects of Letters Patent<lb/> Appeal and especially what is a judgment within Clause 15 of the<lb/> Letters Patent has been dealt with by a Division Bench of this Court in<lb/> a recent judgment delivered on 19 th June, 2008 ( The Bombay<lb/> Diocesan Trust Association Pvt. Ltd. v. The Pastorate Committee of the<lb/> Saint Andrews Church &amp; Ors.). A relevant observations of the said<lb/> judgment are as under:-<lb/>&quot;10. While relying upon the case of<lb/> Vinita M.<lb/> Khanolkar v. Pragna M. Pai and others, 1998(</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>.</head>
....<lb/> ......<lb/> .......</content>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>noticed a judgment of Full Bench of Calcutta High<lb/> Court in Mohendra Lall Mitter v. Anundo Coomar<lb/> Mitter, (1897) 25 Cal. 236 (F.B.) and declined to<lb/> accept the view firstly as it was not binding and<lb/> specifically for the reason that decision of the Calcutta<lb/> High Court was in absence of any reason for the<lb/> conclusion arrived at and ultimately rejected the<lb/> contention that an order refusing the application to<lb/> commit a person for contempt was appealable. The<lb/> same principle was approved and distinguished by the<lb/> Full Bench of this court in the case of Collector of<lb/> Bombay v. Issac Penhas, AIR (35) 1948 Bombay 103,<lb/> where the court held as under:</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>20. This High Court has always preferred to<lb/> follow the Calcutta High Court rather than the<lb/> Madras High Court: or, in other words, it has<lb/> undoubtedly given a more restricted meaning<lb/> to the expression &quot;judgment&quot; than the Madras<lb/> High Court has done-see the observations of<lb/> Sir Basil Scott C.J. In 11 Bom. L.R. 241.<lb/> ....................................</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>) of<lb/> the Civil Procedure Code. It cannot mean in the<lb/> context the statement given by the Judge of the<lb/> grounds of a decree or order. It must mean a<lb/> judgment which finally decides all matters in<lb/> controversy in the suit. Similar view has been<lb/> expressed by the Supreme Court in Shri Radhey Shyam<lb/> v. Shyam Behari Singh, 1970(2) SCC 405.<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> .....<lb/> .....<lb/> .....</content>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>the provisions of clause 15 are subject to legislative powers of the<lb/> Governor-General in Legislative Council and also of the Governor-<lb/>General in Council under Section 71 of the Government of India Act,<lb/> 1915. Clause 44 of the Letters Patent specifically contemplates that<lb/> the provisions of Letters Patent are subject to the exercise of legislative<lb/> powers by the competent legislature. In other words, Clause 15 of the<lb/> Letters Patent does not confer an absolute or unqualified right to<lb/> appeal. This remedy is subject to the other laws enacted by competent<lb/> Legislature. Viewed from that angle, the restrictions contemplated<lb/> under Section 100-A of the Code of Civil Procedure would be a<lb/> relevant consideration which would control right of appeal as<lb/> envisaged under Clause 15 of the Letters Patent.<lb/> 47.<lb/> Clause 12 of Letters Patent is an independent clause which<lb/> relates to the exercise of ordinary original jurisdiction in suits by this<lb/> Courts. The orders which are passed by the High Court in exercise of<lb/> its original jurisdiction would be apparently covered under clause 12<lb/> of the Letters Patent but of course to the limitation stated in the<lb/> provision itself. But, in the present case, jurisdiction under Clause 12<lb/> is not a relevant consideration to answer the questions of law posed<lb/> before us.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            48.<lb/> In Shah Babulal </content>
 
            <figDesc>Khimji&apos;s case (supra), the Supreme Court ,<lb/> while explaining the ingredients of a judgment, held that Section 104<lb/> with Order XLIII Rule 1 of the Code of Civil Procedure is neither<lb/> inconsistent, nor override, nor controls clause 15 of the Letters Patent.<lb/> The judgment was in relation to the orders passed by the learned<lb/> Single Judge of this Court in exercise of its original jurisdiction.<lb/> 49.<lb/> Similar view was also expressed by the Supreme Court in<lb/> Vinita M. Khanolkar&apos;s case (supra) where the Court held that the order<lb/> passed by the learned Single Judge in the proceedings under Section 6<lb/> of the Specific Reliefs Act would be appealable under Clause 15 of the<lb/> Letters patent. The Courts stated the principle that the powers of the<lb/> appellate court and right provided under the provision to appeal can<lb/> be excluded by a statute expressly and it cannot be excluded by<lb/> juridical provision barring the appeal.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            provisions.&quot;<lb/> 54.<lb/> Above stated principles </content>
 
            <figDesc>clearly show that the Court can<lb/> safely apply rudiments of plain construction to legislative intent and<lb/> object sought to be achieved by the enactment while interpreting the<lb/> provision of an Act. It is not necessary for the Court to implant or<lb/> exclude words or over emphasize the language of a provision where it<lb/> is plain and simple. We have already noticed that Section 100-A<lb/> opens with a non obstante clause and clause 44 of the Letters Patent<lb/> refers to the aspect that the letters patent would be read in community<lb/> with the legislative enactment.<lb/> A clause beginning with<lb/> `notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time<lb/> being in force including the Letters Patent&apos; normally would show the<lb/> intent and the view of the Legislature enacting part of the section to<lb/> give overriding effect over the provision of that Act or other laws in<lb/> case of conflict.<lb/> The enactment following it will have its full<lb/> operation or that the provisions embraced in the non obstante clause<lb/> will not be an impediment for the operation of the enactment. In the<lb/> case of Union of India &amp; Anr. v. G.M. Kokil &amp; Ors., reported in<lb/> 1984(Supp) SCC 196, the Supreme Court observed thus:-<lb/>&quot;A non obstante clause is a legislative device which is<lb/> usually employed to give overriding effect to certain<lb/> provisions over some contrary provisions that may be<lb/> found either in the same enactment or some other<lb/> enactment, that is to say, to avoid the operation and<lb/> effect of all contrary provisions.&quot;<lb/> 55.<lb/> The above observations have also been reiterated by the<lb/> Supreme Court in the case of Pannalal Bansilal Patil v. State of Andhra<lb/> Pradesh, reported in AIR 1996 SC 1023 and in the case of T.R.<lb/> Thandur v. Union of India, reported in AIR 1996 SC 1643. Of course,<lb/> a non obstante clause has to be distinguished from the phrase &quot;without<lb/> prejudice&quot;. A provision enacted &quot;without prejudice&quot; to another<lb/> provision does not have the effect of affecting the operation of the<lb/> other provision and any action taken under it must not be inconsistent<lb/> with other provision. It is also to be kept in mind that the wide<lb/> meaning of non obstante clause and the enacting words following it<lb/> cannot be curtailed when the use of wide language accords with the<lb/> object by the Act.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            56.<lb/> While dealing with </content>
 
            <figDesc>interpretation of statutes regulating<lb/> appeals the treatise of principles of statutory interpretation by Justice<lb/> G.P. Singh ( 11 th Edition 2008) explains:-<lb/>&quot;An appeal is the &quot;right of entering a superior court<lb/> and invoking its aid and interposition to redress an<lb/> error of the court below&quot; and &quot;though procedure does<lb/> surround an appeal the central idea is a right&quot;. The<lb/> right of appeal has been recognised by judicial<lb/> decisions as a right which vests in a suitor at the time<lb/> of institution of original proceedings. Any change in<lb/> the law relating to appeals, after institution of original<lb/> proceedings, which adversely touches this vested right<lb/> is presumed not to be retrospective.&quot;<lb/> 57.<lb/> In the case of A.G. Varadarajulu &amp; Anr. vs State of T.N. &amp;<lb/> Ors., reported in (1998) 4 SCC 231, the Supreme Court held as<lb/> under: -</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>reported in (2005) 2 SCC 145, the Supreme Court, while relying<lb/> upon the judgment of the of the Constitution Bench in the case of P.S.<lb/> Sathappan vs Andhra Bank Ltd., reported in (2004) 11 SCC 672 did<lb/> not accept the contention that the provision of superior legislation viz.<lb/> Code of Civil Procedure would override the provision of the Letters<lb/> Patent but clearly noticed firstly that there was no conflict between<lb/> Section 104 of the Code of Civil Procedure and the Letters Patent and<lb/> they could be harmoniously interpreted and permitted to operate in<lb/> their field but specifically approved earlier view that once there was<lb/> specific exclusion the provisions of Letters Patent would be overridden<lb/> by the provisions of the Code. This was with reference to the<lb/> language of Section 4 of the Code. Once there was specific provision<lb/> to the contrary applicability of the special law could be excluded. It<lb/> categorically specified and referred view of constitution bench in P.S.<lb/> Sattapan&apos;s case (supra) that the specific provisions of this kind would<lb/> be a provision like Section 100-A of the Code.<lb/> 59.<lb/> On the clear analysis and application of judicial<lb/> interpretative process, it is clear that Section 100-A of the Code of<lb/> Civil Procedure and the Clause 15 of the Letters Patent would have to<lb/> be construed on their plain reading and without any conflict.<lb/> DISCUSSION ON MERITS :<lb/> 60.<lb/> The factual matrix of the case has already been stated by<lb/> us above. Suffice it to note that the present appeals have been filed<lb/> after coming into force a provision of Section 100-A of the Code of<lb/> Civil Procedure (i.e. 1 st July, 2002). All these appeals have been<lb/> preferred against the judgment of the learned Single Judge passed in<lb/> exercise of its appellate jurisdiction. The appeals before the learned<lb/> Single Judge were preferred in terms of Section 173 of the Motor<lb/> Vehicles Act and were accordingly decided by the learned Single<lb/> Judge vide judgments dated 12 th February, 2004 and 25 th January,<lb/> 2005. There is undoubtedly no provision contained in the M.V. Act</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>62.<lb/> We have already noticed that the Tribunal has the<lb/> trapping of a Civil Court and various procedural and effective<lb/> provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure have been made applicable<lb/> substantially to the proceeding before the Tribunal. After the Award is<lb/> passed by the Tribunal, an Appeal under Section 173 is maintainable<lb/> before the High Court and the High Court would exercise its appellate<lb/> jurisdiction arising from a statute with the help of the provisions of the<lb/> Code of Civil Procedure. Section 100A was introduced by the<lb/> Legislature with a specific object. The object being to curtail the right<lb/> of Second Appeal and attach finality to the judgment of the first<lb/> appellate Court in normal course of law. That is the reason why the<lb/> Legislature has specifically worded Section 100A while opening the<lb/> Section with a non-obstante clause and provided over-riding effect<lb/> over the provisions of Letters Patent, other law and even other<lb/> instrument having the force of law. The intent of the Legislature to<lb/> provide precedence to enforcement of Section 100A is patently clear<lb/> from the unambiguous and definite language of Section 100A. We<lb/> must notice here that both the Motor Vehicles Act and the Code of<lb/> Civil Procedure are Central enactments. No State amendment has<lb/> been carried by the State of Maharashtra to dilute or alter the effect of<lb/> the language of either Section 173 of the Motor Vehicles Act or<lb/> Section 100A of the CPC. The Legislature was fully aware of the<lb/> provisions of Section 173 as well as of the Letters Patent when it<lb/> introduced Section 100A which came into force on 1 st July 2002. Once<lb/> the Legislature , being aware of the existing law, has worded Section<lb/> 100A in specific terms, then it has to be given its natural and effective<lb/> meaning. The Court while construing these provisions by applying the<lb/> principles of harmonious construction or otherwise, cannot frustrate<lb/> the object of provisions of Section 100A which has been given over-<lb/>riding effect by use of non-obstante clause and with specific exclusion<lb/> of other laws. Clause 15 of the Letters Patent thus would have to be<lb/> read in conjunction with Clause 44 of the said Letters Patent and<lb/> Section 100A of the CPC that too in light of the language of Section<lb/> 173 of the Motor Vehicles Act. The cumulative reading and analysis of<lb/> these provisions in consonance with the Rules of interpretation stated<lb/> above, would lead to simple and one conclusion that the Letters Patent<lb/> appeal or an appeal against the judgment of the learned Single Judge<lb/> passed in exercise of its appellate jurisdiction against the appellate<lb/> judgment passed by the Court subordinate to the High Court, would<lb/> not be appealable. Where Section 100A constitutes a complete bar<lb/> against right to prefer an appeal against an appellate decision, there<lb/> appeal cannot be preferred with the aid of Clause 15 of the Letters<lb/> Patent against such judgment.<lb/> Thus, either way, the obvious<lb/> conclusion would be that no intra-Court appeal is maintainable in the<lb/> High Court against the judgment passed by the learned Single Judge<lb/> in exercise of its appellate powers in terms of Section 173 of the Motor<lb/> Vehicles Act.<lb/> 63.<lb/> Another aspect which would support the view which we<lb/> are taking is that the whole object of introducing Section 100A was to<lb/> curtail litigation by regulating the right of appeal. Attempt obviously<lb/> is to attach finality to the judgment of the learned Single Judge of the<lb/> High Court particularly where he has passed the judgment while<lb/> exercising appellate jurisdiction of the High Court. Where the<lb/> judgment of the Tribunal and the learned Single Judge is treated as a<lb/> judgment within the meaning of Clause 15 of the Letters Patent or not<lb/> or under the provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure, would hardly<lb/> make any difference on the conclusion inasmuch as even against an<lb/> order of the Single Judge in exercise of appellate jurisdiction, a further<lb/> appeal is prohibited in terms of Section 100A. The Legislative object<lb/> of regulating the right of appeal and rendering Second Appeal from<lb/> appellate order or judgment impermissible would stand defeated by<lb/> any other interpretation. The rule of mischief contemplates that what<lb/> remedy the Parliament resolved and attempted to cure the disease<lb/> should be permitted to operate rather than the same be defeated by<lb/> process of interpretation. The Court while performing its function of<lb/> interpretation of law would make such construction as shall suppress<lb/> the mischief and advance the remedy and to suppress subtle<lb/> inventions and evasions for continuance of the mischief and pro<lb/> privato commodo. The mischief which is sought to be controlled and<lb/> avoided by the Legislature is not to grant repeated right of appeal and<lb/> to introduce the concept of finality to the appellate judgment, decree<lb/> or order. The provisions of the Motor Vehicles Act do not recognise<lb/> an appeal from an appellate jurisdiction of the High Court passed<lb/> under Section 173 of the Motor Vehicles Act. On the contrary, Section<lb/> 100A specifically bars filing of an appeal against such judgment. The<lb/> provisions of Section 100-A have a precedence and take limited<lb/> exception to the provisions of Clause 15 of the Letters Patent. On<lb/> plain reading of Clause 15 of the Letters Patent, an appeal to a<lb/> Division Bench of the High Court from the judgment of the learned<lb/> Single Judge passed while deciding an appeal against the appellate<lb/> judgment, and decree or order passed by the Court of competent<lb/> jurisdiction subordinate to the High Court would not be maintainable.<lb/> The only exception to this general rule is that where the learned Single<lb/> Judge grants a certificate of fitness as contemplated under the<lb/> language of Clause 15 of the Letters Patent. This we have noticed only<lb/> to elucidate the point that Clause 15 will have to be read with Clause<lb/> the Code of Civil Procedure. The cumulative reading of all these<lb/> provisions would thus show that Clause 15 of the Letters Patent<lb/> cannot be treated as a provision granting independent right of appeal<lb/> de hors the other relevant provisions noticed by us in this judgment.<lb/> 64.<lb/> The Supreme Court in the case of P S Sathappan (supra)<lb/> clearly stated while referring to Clause 44 of the Letters Patent that<lb/> provisions of Letters Patent were subject to legislative powers of the<lb/> Governor-General-in-Legislative Council and, therefore, in the present-<lb/>day context, subject to legislative power of the appropriate legislature.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>High </head>
 
            <figDesc>Court under Section 10F and after referring to the pre-<lb/>amendment provisions held that no appeal was maintainable against<lb/> the order of the learned Single Judge passed in appeal in face of<lb/> Section 100A and despite the language of Clause 15 of the Letters<lb/> Patent of the Calcutta High Court and held as under :-<lb/>&quot;16. Appeal lies under Letters Patent from the<lb/> judgment of the learned Single Judge of the High Court<lb/> to the Division bench. In this connection, learned<lb/> counsel placed reliance on a decision of this Court in<lb/> the case of Garikapatti Veeraya vs N Subbiah<lb/> Choudhury reported in 1957 SCR 488 and submitted<lb/> that the appeal is vested right and it cannot be taken<lb/> away. Alternative submission was if clause 15 does not<lb/> apply, appeal lies under Section 483 of the Act. In this<lb/> connection reliance was placed on decisions of this<lb/> Court in the case of Arati Dutta vs M/s Eastern Tea<lb/> Estate (P) Ltd reported in (1988) 1 SCC 523 and the in<lb/> the case of Maharashtra Power Development<lb/> Corporation Limited vs DabholPower Company &amp; Ors.,<lb/> reported in (2003) 117 Company Cases 651. As against<lb/> this, learned senior counsel for the appellants<lb/> submitted that Section 10F of the Act came into being<lb/> with effect from 31.5.1991. Prior to that application<lb/> under Sections 397 and 398 of the Act was being filed<lb/> with the Company Judge in the High Court. But after<lb/> the amendment of the Act by Act 31 of 1988, this<lb/> power under Sections 397 &amp; 398 of the Act has been<lb/> given to the CLB. Under Section 10E of the Act, the<lb/> Company Law Board was created. It deals with<lb/> applications under Sections 397 and 398 of the Act.<lb/> Therefore, learned Single Judge has not exercised<lb/> original jurisdiction and as such the appeal<lb/> contemplated under clause 15 of the Letters Patent is<lb/> not maintainable. Learned senior counsel invited our<lb/> attention to Section 100A of the Code of Civil<lb/> Procedure which came into being with effect from<lb/> 1.7.2002. This section starts with non-obstante clause<lb/> that notwithstanding anything contained in any Letters<lb/> Patent for any High Court or in any other instrument<lb/> having the force of law or in any other law for the time<lb/> being in force, where any appeal from an original or<lb/> appellate decree or order is heard and decided by a<lb/> single Judge of a High Court, no further appeal shall lie<lb/> from the judgment and decree of such single Judge.<lb/> Therefore, it was pointed out that in view of the latest<lb/> amendment in the Code of Civil Procedure, Letters<lb/> Patent or intra court appeal will not lie when the<lb/> learned Single Judge has exercised appellate<lb/> jurisdiction. In fact, this amendment seems to have<lb/> been brought about on the recommendations of the<lb/> Malimath Committee report that right to appeal should<lb/> be curtained and only one appellate forum should be<lb/> available. Therefore, in view of this recommendations,<lb/> this amendment was brought about. In support of this<lb/> contention learned senior counsel invited our attention<lb/> to the following decisions.<lb/> (i) (2004) 11 SCC 672 ( P.S. Sathappan (dead) by<lb/> Lrs Vs. Andhra Bank Ltd. &amp; Ors.)<lb/> (ii) (2003) 10 SCC 361 (Subal Paul vs Malina Paul &amp;<lb/> Anr.)<lb/> (iii) AIR 2003 AP 458 (Gandla Pannala Bhulaxmi vs.<lb/> Managing Director, APSRTC &amp; Anr.)<lb/> (iv) (1987) 62 Company Cases 504 (Rev. C.S. Joseph<lb/> &amp; Ors. vs. T.J. Thomas &amp; Ors.)<lb/> (v) AIR 2004 Ker. 111 (Kesava Pillai Sreedharan<lb/> Pillai &amp; etc. vs. State of Kerala &amp; Ors.)<lb/> 17. We have considered the rival submissions of the<lb/> parties. The first question that we have to examine is<lb/> whether the appeal against the order of the learned<lb/> Single Judge lies before the Division Bench under<lb/> Letters Patent or not. It may be relevant to mention<lb/> here that prior to the amendment of the Act, the power<lb/> under Sections 397 &amp; 398 used to be exercised by the<lb/> Company Judge of the High Court. Appeal against that<lb/> order of the learned Single Judge lies under Section<lb/> 483 of the Act before the Division Bench of the High<lb/> Court. Section 483 of the Act reads as under :</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>. The Parliament while<lb/> amending Section 100A of the Code of Civil Procedure,<lb/> by amending Act 22 of 2002 with effect from 1.7.2002,<lb/> took away the Letters Patent power of the High Court<lb/> in the matter of appeal against an order of learned<lb/> single Judge to the Division Bench.<lb/> Section 100A of the Code of Civil Procedure<lb/> reads as .........................................................................</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>against that order appeal lay to the Division Bench of<lb/> the High Court under Section 483 of the Act. In that<lb/> context, their Lordships observed that mere absence of<lb/> procedural rules would not deprive the litigant&apos;s of<lb/> substantive right conferred by the statute. We have<lb/> already explained above that earlier the power under<lb/> Sections 397 &amp; 398 of the Act was being exercised by<lb/> learned Company Judge in the High Court and<lb/> therefore, appeal lay to the Division Bench under<lb/> Section 483 of the Act. If the power has been exercised<lb/> by the Company Judge in the High Court, then one<lb/> appeal shall lie before the Division Bench of the High<lb/> Court under Section 483 of the Act. But that is not the<lb/> situation in the present case. Therefore, this decision<lb/> cannot be of any help to respondents.&quot;<lb/> 67.<lb/> This judgment in fact is a complete answer to the<lb/> arguments raised on behalf of the Appellants. In that case, the<lb/> Supreme Court even took the view that a body like Company Law<lb/> Board has the trapping of a Civil Court and it exercises original<lb/> jurisdiction under Sections 397/398 of the Companies Act against<lb/> which an appeal lies to the Single Judge. It also rejected the<lb/> contention that Section 100A does not create a specific bar. While<lb/> referring to the judgment of the Supreme Court in Subal Paul vs<lb/> Malina Paul and another, (2003) 10 SCC 361, the Court referred with<lb/> approval the dictum of the Court which reads as follows :<lb/> &quot;Whenever the statute provides such a bar, it is so<lb/> expressly stated, as would appear from Section 100-A<lb/> of the Code of Civil Procedure.&quot;<lb/> Motor Accident Claims Tribunal which has all the trapping of a Civil<lb/> Court, discharges its judicial functions subject to the superintendence<lb/> and control of the High Court. In fact, the High Court being its<lb/> appellate Court, would exercise all the control over the Motor<lb/> Accident Claims Tribunal.<lb/> 68.<lb/> It can be useful to notice at this stage itself that in Kamal<lb/> Kumar Dutta (supra), the view taken by a Division Bench of this Court<lb/> in the case of Maharashtra Power Development Corporation Limited vs<lb/> Dabhol Power Company and others, (2003) 117 Company Cases 651<lb/> = AIR 2004 BOM 38, that appeal shall lie against the judgment of the<lb/> Single Judge passed in Appeal against the order of Company Law<lb/> Board as the Letters Patent Appeal or a statutory appeal under special<lb/> enactment and will not be affected by the provisions of Section 100-A,<lb/> was specifically rejected and the view taken by this Court was held to<lb/> be incorrect proposition of law.<lb/> 69.<lb/> In the case of Municipal Corporation of Brihanmumbai and<lb/> another vs State Bank of India, (1999) 1 SCC 123, the Court was<lb/> concerned with maintainability of a Letters Patent Appeal under<lb/> Clause 15 from the judgment and order of the Single Judge passed on<lb/> an Appeal under Section 218-D of Bombay Municipal Corporation Act.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>Bench of Rajasthan High Court in the case of<lb/> HYPERLINK &quot;http://R.S.R.T.C/&quot; HYPERLINK &quot;http://R.S.R.T.C/&quot;R.S.R.T.C. &amp; etc.<lb/> etc. vs Vaibhav Kumar and others, etc., AIR 2007 RAJASTHAN 147,<lb/> while dealing with identical questions relating to maintainability of a<lb/> Letters Patent Appeal against the appellate order passed by the Single<lb/> Judge of the High Court under Section 173 of the Motor Vehicles Act,<lb/> held that the further intra-Court appeal is barred by Section 100-A of<lb/> the Code of Civil Procedure. It mainly relied upon the judgment of<lb/> the Kamal Kumar Dutta&apos;s case (supra), while also referring to other<lb/> provisions including a view of Full Bench of the Andhra Pradesh High<lb/> Court in the case of M/s United India Insurance Co. Ltd. vs. S. Surya<lb/> Prakash Reddy and another, 2006 (4) Andh L T 448, The Court held<lb/> as under :-<lb/>&quot;16. A Full Bench of the Andhra Pradesh High Court in<lb/> the case of Gandla Pannala Bhulaxmi v APRTC and<lb/> another, AIR 2003 AP 458, was seized with the<lb/> question whether the right of appeal available under<lb/> the Letters Patent is taken away by Section 100A of the<lb/> Civil Procedure Code in respect of the matter arising<lb/> under special enactments or other instruments having<lb/> the force of law. That was a case where Letters Patents<lb/> Appeal was preferred from the order of a Single Judge<lb/> passed in an appeal under Section 173 of the Motor<lb/> Vehicles Act. The Full Bench of the Andhra Pradesh<lb/> High Court upon consideration of the amended<lb/> provision of Section 100A and the judgment of the<lb/> Supreme Court in the case of Vinita M Khanolkar v<lb/> Pragna M Pal, AIR 1998 SC 424 and another decision of<lb/> the Supreme Court in Sharda Devi v State of Bihar, AIR<lb/> 2002 SC 1357, held that Section 100A of the Code of<lb/> Civil Procedure in clear and specific terms prohibits<lb/> further appeal against the judgment and decree of a<lb/> Single Judge to a Division Bench notwithstanding<lb/> anything contained in the Letters Patents. It was held<lb/> that the Letter Patents which provides for further<lb/> appeal to a Division bench remains intact but the right<lb/> to prefer a further appeal is taken away even in respect<lb/> of the matters arising under a special enactment or<lb/> other instruments having the force of law.<lb/> 17. The view of the Kerala High Court is on the same<lb/> lines. A Full Bench of Kerala High Court in the case of<lb/> Kesava Pillai Sreedharan Pillai and etc. v State of Kerala<lb/> and others, AIR 2004 Kerala 111, was concerned with<lb/> the question whether an appeal from a judgment,<lb/> decree or order passed by the Single Judge on an<lb/> appeal against the order of a Court or tribunal is<lb/> maintainable despite Section 100A of the Code of Civil<lb/> Procedure effective from 1 st July, 2002.<lb/> 18. The Full Bench of the Kerala High Court noticed<lb/> that the intention of the Legislature by enacting Section<lb/> 100A was to abolish an intra-Court appeal to the Bench<lb/> of two Judges of the same High Court from a decision<lb/> rendered by a Single Judge. It held that Section 100A<lb/> of the Code of Civil Procedure would prevail over the<lb/> provisions contained in Section 5(ii) of the Kerala High<lb/> Court Act. We may observe here that the said provision<lb/> is similar to erstwhile Section 18 of the Rajasthan High<lb/> Court Ordinance, 1949 regarding further appeal to the<lb/> Bench of two Judges from the decision of the Single<lb/> Judge. The Full Bench of Kerala High Court has thus<lb/> held that the right of further appeal as provided under<lb/> Section 5 (ii) of the Kerala High Court Act stands<lb/> abrogated by Section 100A of the Civil Procedure Code<lb/> w. e. f. 1 st July, 2002.<lb/> 19. The Supreme Court in Subal Paul v Malina Paul<lb/> and another, (2003) 10 SCC 3611 : AIR 2003 SC 1928,<lb/> was concerned with the question whether the Letters<lb/> Patent Appeal would lie from the judgment of a Single<lb/> Judge of the High Court filed under Section 299 of the<lb/> Indian Succession Act. Pertinently in Subal Paul&apos;s case<lb/> the Supreme Court observed that whenever a statute<lb/> provided such a bar it did so expressly as would appear<lb/> from Section 100A of the Code of Civil Procedure. It is<lb/> also important to notice that in Subal Paul an appeal<lb/> was preferred before the Division Bench from the order<lb/> of the Single Judge prior to 1 st July, 2002.<lb/> 20. The Constitution Bench of the Supreme Court in<lb/> P.S. Sathappan (dead) by L.Rs. V Andhra Bank Ltd. &amp;<lb/> Ors., (2004) 11 SCC 672 : AIR 2004 SC 5152,<lb/> extensively dealt with the provisions contained in<lb/> Section 100A and the other provisions of the Code of<lb/> Civil Procedure, more particularly, Sections 4 and 104<lb/> and had held that when the Legislature wanted to<lb/> exclude the Letters Patent Appeal, it specifically did so<lb/> and the words used in Section 100a were not by way of<lb/> abundant caution. That is what the Supreme Court<lb/> said in P.S. Sathappan (supra) (Para 30 of AIR ) :-</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>&quot;</head>

            <figDesc>100-A : .............................................................</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>23. The legal position exposited by the Supreme<lb/> Court in Kamal Kumar Dutta, 2006 AIR SCW 4694,<lb/> applies on all fours to the order/award passed by the<lb/> Motor Accident Claims Tribunal under Section 168 of<lb/> the Motor Vehicles Act and where such order/award is<lb/> carried in an appeal under Section 173 of that Act.<lb/> Even if it be assumed that the Motor Accident Claims<lb/> Tribunal is not a Court as is the term ordinarily<lb/> understood, it is beyond doubt that such Tribunal has<lb/> all the trapping of a Court. Though the Tribunals<lb/> occupy a special position of their own under the<lb/> scheme of the Courts and Tribunals and special matters<lb/> and questions are entrusted to them for their decision<lb/> yet they share with the Courts one common<lb/> characteristic viz. : both the Courts as well as Tribunals<lb/> are constituted by the State and are invested with<lb/> judicial functions as distinguished from purely<lb/> administrative or executive functions. It is the State&apos;s<lb/> inherent judicial power which is discharged by the<lb/> Courts and Tribunals, if the Company Law Board<lb/> constituted under the Companies Act in its adjudicatory<lb/> powers has the trappings of a Court and an appeal<lb/> under Section 10F of the Companies Act from its order<lb/> to the Single Judge is not amenable to further appeal<lb/> (Letters Patent) to the Division Bench of the same<lb/> Court because of Section 100A of the Code of Civil<lb/> Procedure, a fortiori, an order passed by the Single<lb/> Judge in appeal under Section 173 of the Motor<lb/> Vehicles Act from the order/award of the Motor<lb/> Accident Claims Tribunal shall not be subject to intra-<lb/>Court appeal in view of the bar created by Section 100A<lb/> of the Code of Civil Procedure effective from 1 st July,<lb/> 2002.&quot;<lb/> 72.<lb/> The Bench also noticed the distinction between the decree,<lb/> order and the award. It held that decision of the Single Judge in<lb/> Appeal under Section 173 of the Motor Vehicles Act is nothing but a<lb/> judgment. We adopt the reasoning and have no hesitation in coming<lb/> to the conclusion that the Award of the Tribunal and in any case the<lb/> judgment of the learned Single Judge passed under Section 173 of the<lb/> Motor Vehicles Act in appeal has all the ingredients of a judgment<lb/> within the meaning of Section 15 of the Letters Patent and/or under<lb/> the Code of Civil Procedure.<lb/> 73.<lb/> The provisions of Letters Patent, being a special law, as<lb/> opposed to Civil Procedure Code which would be generally applicable<lb/> to all Courts, would have normally taken precedence and regulated<lb/> the right to file an appeal, but for the non-obstante clause and specific<lb/> exclusion of its application in terms of Section 100A of the Code of<lb/> Civil Procedure. In the case of P.S. Sathappan (supra) as well as in the<lb/> case of Iridium India Telecom Ltd. (supra), it was held that the<lb/> provision of Section 100A is the provision which specifically excludes<lb/> application of other laws.<lb/> 74.<lb/> We have discussed in some elaboration, the reasons for<lb/> arriving at a conclusion that the Letters Patent Appeal against the<lb/> appellate judgment passed in exercise of powers conferred on the<lb/> court under Section 173 of the Motor Vehicles Act is not maintainable.<lb/> Similar view was taken by a Five Judge Bench of the Andhra Pradesh<lb/> High Court in the case of M/s United India Insurance Co. Ltd. vs. S.<lb/> Surya Prakash Reddy and another, 2006 (4) Andh L T 448, and a Full<lb/> Bench of the Madhya Pradesh High Court in the case of Laxminarayan<lb/> vs Shivlal Gujar, 2003 91) MPLJ (FB) 10 = AIR 2003 MP 49 (FB).</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            75.<lb/> It is a </content>
 
            <figDesc>settled principle of law that appeal is continuation of<lb/> original proceedings and the procedural law regulating the right of<lb/> appeal would be prospective unless and until it is clearly spelt out to<lb/> the contrary. Equally well settled is the principle that right of appeal<lb/> being a statutory right can be regulated and/or even taken away by a<lb/> subsequent Legislation. There being no fundamental right or a<lb/> general right to prefer appeals, the appeals instituted prior to 1 st July<lb/> 2002, before introduction of Section 100-A on the statute of Code of<lb/> Civil Procedure would be controlled by earlier law and the appeals<lb/> filed thereafter would be regulated by the present provisions of<lb/> Section 100-A of the Code.<lb/> 76.<lb/> In the case of Kamla Devi vs Kushal Kanwar and another,<lb/> (2006) 13 SCC 295, the Supreme Court, where the Appeal before the<lb/> learned Single Judge under the provisions of the Indian Succession Act<lb/> was filed in the year 1992 against the order passed by the learned<lb/> Single Judge dated 13 th February 1992, held that the Letters Patent<lb/> Appeal would be maintainable as it was filed prior to coming into<lb/> force of the Amending Act of 2002 Act. The Supreme Court also<lb/> noticed the judgments in the case of Kamal Kumar Dutta (supra) and<lb/> Subal Paul (supra). The main contention in these cases was with<lb/> regard to retrospective or prospective operation of Section 100-A and<lb/> also that for appeals filed prior to Amendment Act, it had not taken<lb/> away the right of appeal provided the ingredients of Clause 15 of the<lb/> Letters Patent were satisfied.<lb/> Obviously, one of the relevant<lb/> considerations would be as to when the right to file an appeal arose.<lb/> As noticed in the case of Kamla Devi (supra), the judgment was passed<lb/> on 13 th February 2002 and appeal itself was filed at that time and,<lb/> therefore, was controlled by the law prior to the amendment of 1 st July<lb/> 2002.<lb/> 77.<lb/> Having noticed the relevant principles of law and the<lb/> interpretation that the relevant provisions of law need to be<lb/> interpreted on settled canons of interpretative jurisprudence, now we<lb/> may analyse the view taken by a Division Bench of this Court in the<lb/> case of Asha Joshi (supra) which is the very basis for the present<lb/> Reference. In paragraph 40 of the said judgment, the Bench<lb/> concluded as under :-<lb/>&quot;40. To sum up, we hold that :<lb/> (a) Section 100-A of the Code of Civil Procedure<lb/> would apply on to the proceedings governed by<lb/> the Code;<lb/> (b) Proceedings under section</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>(a) Despite the fact that the judgment was pronounced<lb/> on 12 th December 2007, the judgment of the<lb/> Supreme Court in Kamal Kumar Dutta (supra)<lb/> decided on 11 th August 2006, which has a direct<lb/> bearing and to a large extent answers the<lb/> controversies in issue was not brought to the notice<lb/> of the Bench. The ratio decidendi stated in Kamal<lb/> Kumar Dutta (supra) case being squarely applicable<lb/> to the facts of the present case, would have been<lb/> the correct precept for answering the questions of<lb/> law.<lb/> (b) The Division Bench did not notice and interprete<lb/> the language of Section 100-A of the Code of Civil<lb/> Procedure in relation to the cases where the<lb/> appeals were filed subsequent to st July 2002.<lb/> (c) Clause 44 of the Letters Patent was not brought to<lb/> the notice of the Bench so as to grant precedence to<lb/> the provisions of Section 100-A even after the<lb/> provisions of Clause 15 of the Letters Patent were<lb/> attracted in the present case.<lb/> (d) The Bench treated the Motor Vehicles Act as a<lb/> special law, however, no material was placed<lb/> before the Bench to the effect that under the<lb/> special statute the order passed by the Single Judge<lb/> in exercise of its appellate jurisdiction under<lb/> Section 173 was made appealable. In other words,<lb/> no Second Appeal was provided under the Motor<lb/> Vehicles Act.<lb/> (e) The Full Bench of the Madhya Pradesh High Court<lb/> in the case of Laxminarayan (supra) and this Court<lb/> in the case of Rahul Sharad (supra) were primarily<lb/> concerned<lb/> with<lb/> the<lb/> retrospectivity<lb/> and<lb/> prospectivity of the provisions of Section 100-A<lb/> which in fact already stand settled by the judgment<lb/> of the Supreme Court in Bento De Souza Egipsy vs<lb/> Yvette Alvares Colaco, (2004) 13 SCC 438, and<lb/> Kamla Devi (supra) and the said provisions being<lb/> prospective and appeals in the case before the<lb/> Bench having been filed subsequent o 1 st July 2002<lb/> and as such they will be covered by the provisions<lb/> of Section 100-A of the Code.<lb/> (f) The view of the Division Bench that the Tribunal<lb/> was neither a Civil Court nor had the trapping<lb/> thereof, in our humble opinion, is not correct<lb/> position of law in view of the well settled position<lb/> of law as afore-noticed. The Tribunal has all the<lb/> trapping of a Civil Court and its orders are<lb/> judgments or orders as even known in the common<lb/> parlance. The learned Single Judge exercises<lb/> powers of an appellate Court in terms of the Code<lb/> of Civil Procedure while hearing an appeal<lb/> preferred to that Court in terms of Section 173 of<lb/> the Motor Vehicles Act.<lb/> The Tribunal and<lb/> particularly the appellate Court does not lose the<lb/> trapping of a Civil Court while exercising such<lb/> jurisdiction.<lb/> (g) The Division Bench placed heavy reliance upon the<lb/> observations of the Supreme Court in the case of<lb/> Sharda Devi (supra) stating that the provisions of<lb/> Letters Patent were akin to the constitutional<lb/> powers of the Court, but it was clarified and in fact<lb/> not accepted by the Constitution Bench in P.S.<lb/> Satthapan&apos;s case (supra) where the Court held as<lb/> under :<lb/> &quot;.... At this stage it must be clarified that during<lb/> arguments, relying on the sentence &quot;the powers<lb/> given to a High Court under the Letters Patent are<lb/> akin to the constitutional powers of a High Court&quot;<lb/> in para 9 of this judgment it had been suggested<lb/> that a Letters Patent had the same status as the<lb/> Constitution.<lb/> In our view these observations<lb/> merely lay down that the powers given to a High<lb/> Court are the powers with which that High Court is<lb/> constituted. These observations do not put Letters<lb/> Patent on a par with the Constitution.&quot;<lb/> (h) In our considered view, the Division Bench while<lb/> determining the controversy before it could have<lb/> hardly relied upon the judgment of the Supreme<lb/> Court in the case of Jindal Vijaynagar Steel vs<lb/> Jindal Praxair Oxygen Co. Ltd., (2006) 11 SCC<lb/> 521, where the Supreme Court was primarily<lb/> concerned with interpretation of Clause 12 of the<lb/> Letters Patent of the Bombay High Court and<lb/> Section 20 of the Civil Procedure code in relation<lb/> to determination of jurisdiction. The question in<lb/> that case related to the determination of Ordinary<lb/> Original Civil Jurisdiction under the Letters Patent<lb/> Act in relation to a cause of action arising within<lb/> the jurisdiction of the Court and on construction of<lb/> Sections 20 and 120 of the Code read with<lb/> Arbitration Act, 1940, it was held that the Court<lb/> would exercise jurisdiction in terms of Clause 12 of<lb/> the Letters Patent.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <label>79</label>

            <head>.<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>Another aspect, which needs to be examined by us, is that<lb/> the Division Bench in Asha&apos;s case (supra) in paragraph 33 noticed<lb/> another judgment of a Division Bench of this Court in the case of<lb/> Bhenoy G. Dembla &amp; Anr. vs M/s. Prem Kutir P. Ltd., reported in<lb/> 2003(4) Mh.L.J. 883, where the Division Bench had taken the view<lb/> that keeping in view the provisions of Section 100-A of the Code of<lb/> Civil Procedure and Section 10F of the Companies Act, 1956, an<lb/> appeal from the judgment of the learned Single Judge in exercise of its<lb/> appellate jurisdiction under Section 10-F of the Companies Act would<lb/> not lie after 1 st July, 2002. The Bench held that :<lb/> &quot;.......... There is no express conferment of a right of<lb/> a further appeal to the Division Bench against the<lb/> decision of a learned Single Judge. That being the<lb/> position, an appeal to the Division Bench is clearly<lb/> not maintainable against the decision of the Single<lb/> Judge rendered after 1 st July, 2002.&quot;<lb/> 80.<lb/> In our view, the most appropriate course of action in<lb/> consonance with the judicial propriety and discipline would have been<lb/> that the Division Bench dealing with Asha&apos;s case (supra) should have<lb/> referred the matter to a larger Bench rather than expressing the<lb/> contrary view to that of equi bench judgment in Bhenoy G. Dembla&apos;s<lb/> case (supra) which had been pronounced much earlier. Be that as it<lb/> may, we would leave the matter at that stage and proceed to discuss<lb/> paragraph 33 of the judgment in Asha&apos;s case (supra) where the Bench<lb/> distinguished the judgment in Bhenoy G. Dembla&apos;s case (supra) that the<lb/> proceedings in that case had arisen from the provisions of Section 10-F<lb/> of the Companies Act. The Division Bench in Asha&apos;s case (supra) had<lb/> referred to earlier Division Bench Judgment of this Court in the case of<lb/> Maharashtra Power Development Corporation Limited&apos;s case (supra) which<lb/> had taken the contrary view and held that the judgment of Company<lb/> Court pronounced in the appeal under Section 10-F of the Companies<lb/> Act would not be a judgment and decree within the meaning of the<lb/> provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure, and therefore, the appeal<lb/> was not barred in terms of Section 100-A of the Code of Civil<lb/> Procedure. The Division Bench in Asha&apos;s case (supra) ignored the fact<lb/> that the view of the Division Bench of Bombay High Court in<lb/> Maharashtra Power Development Corporation Limited&apos;s case (supra) was<lb/> not approved by the Supreme Court in Kamal Kumar Dutta&apos;s case<lb/> (supra), and in fact, diametrically opposite view has been expressed by<lb/> the Supreme Court which we have already discussed in some detail.<lb/> It was expected from the learned counsel appearing for the respective<lb/> parties to bring these judgments to the notice of the Division Bench,<lb/> which, if brought, we have no doubt in our mind that the Bench would<lb/> have come to a different conclusion and preferably to the one<lb/> indicated above.<lb/> 81.<lb/> It is a settled norm of interpretation of statute that the<lb/> enactment should be examined in its entirety and the Court essentially<lb/> are considering the legislative scheme and object and intent of the<lb/> Legislature even while applying the rule of plain interpretation.<lb/> Reference to one or two odd provisions of the Act, Code or Rules<lb/> framed under that Act may not thus sufficiently satisfy the<lb/> requirements of law. We have discussed in some elaboration the<lb/> various provisions of the Civil Procedure Code that have been made<lb/> specifically applicable to the Motor Vehicles Act. The functions and<lb/> powers of the Tribunal in the process of determination are controlled<lb/> by the specific provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure as indicated in<lb/> Section 169 of the Motor Vehicles Act and Rules 257 and 276 of the<lb/> Maharashtra Motor Vehicles Rules framed under the Motor Vehicles<lb/> Act. It has to entertain an application filed under Section 165 of the<lb/> Act and has to exercise its adjudicatory powers required for the<lb/> purpose permitting to file reply, give hearing and adequate<lb/> opportunity to prove its case, then hear the arguments and decide the<lb/> claim petition in accordance with law. The entire adjudicatory process<lb/> is thus primarily and substantially controlled by the provisions of the<lb/> Code. It is difficult for us to come to the conclusion that the Tribunal<lb/> is not having the trapping of Civil Court. Technically or grammatically<lb/> speaking, the Tribunal may not be a Civil Court, but it has all the<lb/> trapping of the Court and it pronounces an Award which is<lb/> determination of rights of parties and which has all the ingredients of<lb/> a judgment and an order as known under civil jurisprudence.<lb/> 82.<lb/> Now, we will proceed to deal with the judgment of the<lb/> Supreme Court relied upon by the appellants. Heavy reliance was<lb/> placed on the judgment in Subal Paul&apos;s case (supra) where the<lb/> Supreme Court, while dealing with the provisions of Section 299 of<lb/> the Succession Act, observed that this was not governed by Section<lb/> 104 of the Code of Civil Procedure and against the order passed by the<lb/> learned Single Judge in exercise of that jurisdiction, letters patent<lb/> appeal would lie. Firstly, the provisions of Section 100-A of the Code<lb/> of Civil Procedure are not the subject matter of discussion in this case.<lb/> Secondly, the appeal before the learned Single Judge had been filed<lb/> prior to coming into force the provisions of Section 100-A of the Code<lb/> i.e. 1 st July, 2002. The Supreme Court was primarily concerned with<lb/> the interpretation of sub-section (2) of Section 104 and held that, that<lb/> provision will not bar a remedy which otherwise is provided under any<lb/> other law. We may find it necessary to refer to at this stage itself that<lb/> the provision of Section 104 unlike the provision of Section 100-A of<lb/> the Code of Civil Procedure does not contain any non obstante clause<lb/> or legislative exception. In paragraph 20 of the judgment, the Supreme<lb/> Court has specifically noticed that the provisions of Section 104 does<lb/> not contemplate order or decree passed under a special statute and<lb/> thus the restrictions carved out under Section 104 would not prohibit<lb/> an appeal in terms of Section 299 of the Succession Act. The real<lb/> catchword of the judgment of the Supreme Court in this case is: -<lb/>&quot;20.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>In that case, the Supreme Court was concerned with an appeal to a<lb/> Division Bench against the judgment of a learned Single Judge of the<lb/> High Court as in terms of Section 54 of the Land Acquisition Act. The<lb/> Court noticed that the expression &quot;only&quot; occurring in Section 54 after<lb/> non obstante clause refers to forum of appeal i.e. an appeal would lie<lb/> to the High Court, and not to any other Court and appeal would take<lb/> within its sweep Letters Patent Appeal, while noticing that Section 54<lb/> does not specifically excludes the provisions of the Letters Patent. The<lb/> Court specifically noticed that the right to entertain appeal would not<lb/> get excluded unless the concerned statutory enactment excludes an<lb/> appeal under the Letters Patent. The language of Section 100-A of<lb/> the Code of Civil Procedure specifically excludes the application of the<lb/> Letters Patent. As already held by the Constitution Bench of the<lb/> Supreme Court, the Letters Patent is not akin to constitutional powers.<lb/> We may also notice here that the judgment of the Supreme Court in<lb/> Sharada Devi&apos;s case (supra) was pronounced on 13 th March, 2002 i.e.<lb/> prior to 1 st July, 2002 when the provision of Section 100-A of the Code<lb/> of Civil Procedure was added and none of the contentions which we<lb/> have considered above were raised before the Supreme Court. In<lb/> these circumstances, again this judgment is of no help to the<lb/> appellants.<lb/> 85.<lb/> It is always not possible to state the legal proposition and<lb/> answers to them with absolute precision. Still the Court makes<lb/> attempt to answer the proposition of law accurately and adequately,<lb/> with reference to the material facts as well as the points to be decided.<lb/> The Courts are guided by the written laws, which they interpret and<lb/> develop a meaningful set of rules by the process of case by case<lb/> adjudication. The reasons for deciding the earlier case have been<lb/> provided as the guidelines for future decision. We have attempted to<lb/> cull out the reasons for taking the view that we have taken above.<lb/> &quot;Experientia docet&quot; and &quot;Expedit rei publicae ut sit finis litium&quot; are the<lb/> two accepted maxims which are equally applicable to the<lb/> interpretation of statutes. We have to keep in mind the intent of the<lb/> Legislature that in no uncertain terms, it decided to put an end to<lb/> intra-Court appeal by debarring entertainment of the second appeal<lb/> where the learned Single Judge of the High Court has pronounced an<lb/> order or judgment in exercise of its appellate jurisdiction. In terms of<lb/> Section 100-A of the Code of Civil Procedure, the unambiguous and<lb/> definite expressions in Section 100-A of the Code of Civil Procedure<lb/> clearly demonstrate this legislative intent.<lb/> Clause 15 read with<lb/> Clause 44 of the Letters Patent would squarely fall within the sweep of<lb/> provisions of Section 100-A of the Code, which specifically by definite<lb/> language excludes the provisions of the Letters Patent. There is no<lb/> provision in the special i.e. M.V. Act providing further appeal against<lb/> the appellate judgment passed by the learned Single Judge under<lb/> Section 173 of the M.V. Act.<lb/> 86.<lb/> Thus, we proceed to record and answer propositions of<lb/> law formulated by us in paragraph 5 of the judgment as follows:<lb/> (a)<lb/> Upon amendment of Section 100-A of the<lb/> Code of Civil Procedure by Amending Act of<lb/> before this Bench, we have no hesitation in holding that these appeals<lb/> are not maintainable.<lb/> Consequently, both these Appeals are<lb/> dismissed. However, in the facts and circumstances of the cases, the<lb/> parties are left to bear their own costs.<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> CHIEF JUSTICE<lb/> P.V. HARDAS, J.<lb/> N.D. DESHPANDE, J<lb/> ashwin/res</content>

            <figDesc>.jts/lpa35-05.sxw</figDesc>
        </figure>



    </text>
</tei>

