<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_3f0cbc6d2689f1a392bbe01488772744.pdf"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">


		<figure type="table">

            <table>in the case of Associated Cement Companies Ltd. vs<lb/> P.N. Sharma &amp; Anr., reported in AIR 1965 SC 1595, it was stated by<lb/> the Supreme Court that the presence of some of the trappings may<lb/> assist the determination of the question as to whether the power<lb/> exercised by the authority which possesses the said trapping, is the<lb/> judicial power of the State or not, and the main and the basic test,<lb/> however, is whether the adjudicating power which is the particular<lb/> authority is empowered to exercise, has been conferred on it by a<lb/> statute and can be described as a part of the State&apos;s inherent power<lb/> exercised in discharging its judicial function. Applying this principle,<lb/> it was held by the Supreme Court that the Tribunal constituted under<lb/> the Punjab Welfare Officers Recruitment and Conditions of Service<lb/> Rules, 1952 was a Tribunal having the trappings of a court.<lb/> 25.<lb/> More so, in the case of State of Haryana vs Smt. Darshana<lb/> Devi &amp; Ors., </table>
 
            <head>reported in (1979)2 SCC 236, the Supreme </head>
 
            <table>Court, while<lb/> dealing with a case under the provisions of Motor Vehicles Act, 1939,<lb/> stated that as under:-<lb/>&quot;The reasoning of the High Court in holding that Order<lb/> XXXIII will apply to the Tribunals which have the<lb/> trappings of the civil court finds our approval. We<lb/> affirm the decision.&quot;<lb/> 26.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>It is said that all Tribunals are not courts, though all the<lb/> courts are Tribunals. The word &quot;courts&quot; is used to designate those<lb/> Tribunals which are set up in an organized State for the<lb/> Administration of Justice. The Administration of Justice is meant to<lb/> be the exercise of judicial power of the State to maintain and uphold<lb/> rights and to punish &quot;wrongs&quot;. Whenever there is an infringement of a<lb/> right or an injury, the courts are there to restore the vinculum juris,<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>which is disturbed.<lb/> 27.<lb/> In addition to the above general principles, some of the<lb/> courts have taken a specific view stating the principle that the Tribunal<lb/> constituted under the M.V. Act is a court subordinate to the High<lb/> Court in terms of Section 24 of the Code of Civil Procedure, The<lb/> Karnataka High Court in Mrs. Noreen R. Srikantaiah v. L. Dasarath<lb/> Ramaiah, Gulbarga &amp; Anr., reported in AIR 1985 Karnataka 208, held<lb/> as under:</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>which arose<lb/> out of the decision of the Punjab &amp; Haryana High<lb/> Court in Smt. Darshana Devi v. Sher Singh, AIR 1978<lb/> Punj &amp; Har 265. The question before the High Court in<lb/> that case was whether a claimant before the Tribunal<lb/> constituted under S. 110 of the `Act&apos; is entitled to the<lb/> benefit of O.33 R.1 C.P. C. The Tribunal had, in that<lb/> case, negatived this claim holding that O.33, C.P. C.<lb/> was not one of those provisions which had expressly<lb/> been made applicable by the Punjab Motor Accidents<lb/> Claims Rules, 1964. In support of its view the Tribunal<lb/> had relied upon an earlier opinion expressed by Dua, J.<lb/> that S.110-C of the M.V. Act by no means clothed the<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>Tribunal with all the characteristics of a Civil Court.<lb/> But in Darshana Devi&apos;s case, (AIR 1978 Punj &amp; Har<lb/> 265), Koshal, C.J. did not subscribe to the earlier view<lb/> of Dua, J. but referred, with approval, to a Full Bench<lb/> judgment of that Court in Shanti Devi v. General<lb/> Manager, haryana Roadways, Ambala, AIR 1972 Punj<lb/> &amp; Har 65 (FB), in which, Jain, J. speaking for the Full<lb/> Bench had said (at p.72):</figDesc>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>&quot;In view of the observations of this Court in State<lb/> of Haryana v. Dharshan Devi, we are of the view that<lb/> the Motor Accidents Claims Tribunal constituted under<lb/> the M.V. Act is a Civil Court for the purposes of S.25 of<lb/> the Civil P.C. We are satisfied that the cases before us<lb/> are fit cases for being transferred from the file of the<lb/> Motor Accidents Claims Tribunal, Moradabad to the<lb/> file of the Motor Accidents Claims Tribunal Delhi<lb/> ................&quot;<lb/> (Emphasis supplied)<lb/> This pronouncement of the Supreme Court should now<lb/> serve to put the controversy at rest. In view of this<lb/> pronouncement, the view taken in State of Karnataka<lb/> v. Subbanna (AIR 1974 Kant 109) and in Revanappa&apos;s<lb/> case (AIR 1983 Kant 164) that such a Tribunal is not a<lb/> `Court&apos; cannot continue to hold the field.&quot;<lb/> 28.<lb/> A Bench of this Court in Gurucharansing Hardayalsing<lb/> Sethi v. Narhari Laxman Shinde &amp; Ors., reported in 1996(4) Bom.C. R.<lb/> 298 observed that the Motor Accident Claims Tribunal is a persona<lb/> designata and stated that it is a court subordinate to High Court under<lb/> Section 115 of the Code of Civil Procedure.<lb/> The Court observed<lb/> thus:-<lb/>&quot;Though amongst various High Courts there was<lb/> difference of opinion as to whether the Motor<lb/> Accident Claims Tribunal is persona designeta or the<lb/> Court subordinate to the high Court within the<lb/> meaning of section 115 C.P. C., but after the Apex<lb/> Court in (State of Haryana v. Smt. Darshana Devi &amp;<lb/> Others), A.I. R. 1979 S.C. 855, observed that the<lb/> Motor Accident Claims Tribunal has the trappings of<lb/> the Civil Court, the later decisions of various High<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>::</note>

            <head>: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:18 :::<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>Courts are consistent that the Motor Accident Claims<lb/> Tribunal, for all intents and purposes, is Court<lb/> subordinate to the High Court and has trappings of<lb/> Civil Court and amenable to revisional jurisdiction of<lb/> the High Court under section 115 C.P. C. I fully<lb/> agree with the view that Motor Accident Claims<lb/> Tribunal is not a persona-designeta but a Court<lb/> subordinate to the High Court under section 115 C.P.<lb/> C.&quot;<lb/> 29.<lb/> The Supreme Court in a very recent judgment in the<lb/> case of Kamal Kumar Dutta &amp; Anr. v. Ruby General Hospital Ltd.<lb/> &amp; Ors., reported in 2006 AIR SCW 4594, while dealing with the<lb/> case under Sections 397 and 398 of the Companies Act also took<lb/> the view that the Company Law Board has adjudicatory power<lb/> to decide all questions of law and facts, and held that :-<lb/>&quot;There is no two opinion in the matter that when the<lb/> CLB exercises its power under Ss.397 &amp; 398, it<lb/> exercised a quasi-judicial power as the original<lb/> authority. It may not be a Court but it has all trapping<lb/> of a Court.&quot;<lb/> 30.<lb/> A Bench of Rajasthan High Court in the case of R.S. R.T. C.<lb/> &amp; etc. etc. vs Vaibhav Kumar &amp; Ors., </table>
 
            <head>reported in AIR 2007 Rajasthan<lb/> 147, held </head>
 
            <figDesc>as under:-<lb/>&quot;23. The legal position exposited by the Supreme<lb/> Court in Kamal Kumar Dutta, 2006 AIR SCW 4594,<lb/> applies on all fours to the order /award passed by the<lb/> Motor Accident claims Tribunal under Section 168 of<lb/> the Motor Vehicles Act and where such order/award is<lb/> carried in an appeal under Section 173 of that Act.<lb/> Even if it be assumed that the Motor Accident Claims<lb/> Tribunal is not a Court as is the term ordinarily<lb/> understood, it is beyond doubt that such Tribunal has<lb/> all the trapping of a Court.</figDesc>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>The<lb/> courts normally would not imply anything in them which is<lb/> inconsistent with the words expressly used by the statute. In other<lb/> words, the Court would keep in mind that its function is jus dicere, not<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>jus dare. The right of appeal being creation of a statute and being a<lb/> statutory right does not invite unnecessary liberal or strict<lb/> construction. The best norm would be to give literal construction<lb/> keeping the legislative intent in mind.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>*<lb/> 1.<lb/> Maxwell on The Interpretation of Statutes, Twelfth Edition by P.St. J. Langan-<lb/>Tripathi Publication.<lb/> 2.<lb/> Principles of Statutory Interpretation by Justice G.P. Singh, 11 th Edition 2008 -Wadhwa<lb/> Publication, Nagpur.<lb/> 52.<lb/> The Supreme Court in the case of Shiv Shakti Co-op.<lb/> Housing Society, Nagpur vs Swaraj Developers and Others, reported in<lb/> (2003) 6 SCC 659, while referring to the principles for interpretation of<lb/> statutory provisions, held as under: -<lb/>&quot;19. It is a well-settled principle in law that the court<lb/> cannot read anything into a statutory provision which<lb/> is plain and unambiguous. A statute is an edict of the<lb/> legislature. The language employed in a statute is the<lb/> determinative factor of legislative intent. Words and<lb/> phrases are symbols that stimulate mental references to<lb/> referents. The object of interpreting a statute is to<lb/> ascertain the intention of the legislature enacting it.<lb/> (See Institute of Chartered Accountants of India v. Price<lb/> Waterhouse.)</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>140, 163-A or 166 of<lb/> the Motor Vehicles Act are not governed by the<lb/> Code and Claims Tribunal is not a Civil Court;<lb/> (c) Award by Tribunal is not a decree or order of a<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>Civil Court;<lb/> (d) Such award is not a decree or order made in<lb/> exercise of appellate jurisdiction by a Court subject<lb/> to superintendence of the High Court;<lb/> (e) A single judge of this Court hearing appeals under<lb/> section 173 of the Motor Vehicles Act from awards<lb/> of Claims Tribunal consequently does not deliver a<lb/> judgment in exercise of appellate jurisdiction in<lb/> respect of a decree or order made in exercise of<lb/> appellate jurisdiction;<lb/> (f) It would, therefore, follow that such judgment of<lb/> Single Judge would be subject to an appeal under<lb/> Clause 15 of the Letters Patent.&quot;</table>
		</figure>



    </text>
</tei>

