<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 1 of 169 <lb/>IN THE HIGH COURT OF JUDICATURE AT BOMBAY <lb/>ORDINARY ORIGINAL CIVIL JURISDICTION <lb/>IN ITS COMMERCIAL DIVISION <lb/>COMMERCIAL ARBITRATION PETITION NO. 371 OF 2017 <lb/>Maharashtra State Road Development <lb/>] <lb/>Corporation Limited, near Priyadarshini <lb/>] <lb/>Park, Napeansea Road, Mumbai -400036 <lb/>] … Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>PLUS BKSP TOLL LTD., a company <lb/>] <lb/>incorporated under the Companies Act, 1956 ] <lb/>having its office at Gala No.1, 2 and 3, <lb/>] <lb/>Siddhivinayak Residency, Plot No.40, Sector ] <lb/>9, Kamothe, Navi Mumbai -410209 <lb/>] ... Respondent <lb/>Mr. Iqbal Chagla Sr. Counsel a/w Rajiv Kumar Sr. Counsel a/w <lb/>Aliabbas Delhiwala and Mr. Jehaan Mehta, Jayendra Kapadia, <lb/>Fozan Lakdawala a/w Ms Riddhi Pawar i/b Little &amp; Co. for the <lb/>Petitioner. <lb/>Mr. Darius Khambatta, Sr. Counsel a/w Zal Andhyarujina, Sr. <lb/>Counsel, Anshul Tyagi, Prithvi Sidhu and Saloni Sharma i/b <lb/>Yakshay Chheda for the Respondent. <lb/>CORAM : B.P. COLABAWALLA, J. <lb/>Reserved on <lb/>: 22 nd February, 2021 <lb/>Pronounced on :19 th April, 2021 <lb/>JUDGMENT : <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></titlePage>

			<front>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 2 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>1. <lb/>By this petition filed under section 34 of the Arbitration <lb/>&amp; Conciliation Act, 1996 (for short &quot;the Act&quot;), the petitioner <lb/>challenges the Interim Award dated 25 th April, 2017, passed by the <lb/>Arbitral Tribunal to the extent it awards and determines: <lb/>(i) <lb/>that the Concession Agreement dated 25 th August, 2006 <lb/>was validly terminated, both on account of Political <lb/>Force Majeure Events and material default on the part of <lb/>the Petitioner thereby holding / finding that the issue of <lb/>liability against the Petitioner is finally determined; <lb/>(ii) that the hearing stands bifurcated and all quantum <lb/>related issues deferred to a second phase to decide the <lb/>quantum of the Respondent&apos;s claims; <lb/>(iii) the issues that would arise in the second stage of the <lb/>arbitration as set out in paragraph 83 of the Impugned <lb/>Award; <lb/>(iv) that there was no conciliation under the Arbitration and <lb/>Conciliation Act, 1996; <lb/>(v) that the second phase may involve a brief set of <lb/>pleadings whereby the Respondent may make fresh <lb/>quantum claims, and the Petitioner may file its response <lb/></body>

			<titlePage>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 3 of 169 <lb/>to the quantum, claims, and documents may be relied <lb/>upon by parties; <lb/>(vi) that the need for any oral or expert evidence would be <lb/>determined by the Tribunal in the second phase; and <lb/>(vii) that its decision on the Counter Claim is deferred. <lb/>2. <lb/>A further direction is sought to set aside the impugned <lb/>Award insofar as it rejects the petitioner&apos;s case and contentions. <lb/>3. <lb/>The basic grounds of challenge to the impugned Interim <lb/>Award are as under: <lb/>I <lb/>Reliance placed by the Arbitral Tribunal on <lb/>evidence which was inadmissible in law; <lb/>II <lb/>Upholding the validity of the termination of <lb/>the Concession Agreement dated 25 th <lb/>August, 2006; <lb/>III(A) <lb/>The Award is contrary to the procedure <lb/>agreed upon between the parties as <lb/>provided by section 19(2) of the Act; <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 4 of 169 <lb/>III(B) <lb/>Legal misconduct on the part of the <lb/>Tribunal; and <lb/>III(C) <lb/>Failure of the Tribunal to consider and <lb/>decide the Counter Claim filed by the <lb/>petitioner. <lb/>4. <lb/>Before I examine these grounds of challenge, it would be <lb/>necessary to encapsulate the brief facts of the matter. The present <lb/>dispute arises out of a Concession Agreement dated 25 th August, <lb/>2006 (for short &quot;the Concession Agreement&quot;) which was entered <lb/>into between the petitioner and the respondent for the purpose of <lb/>four-laning, improvement and maintenance of the Bhiwandi-Kalyan <lb/>Shil-Phata Highway (for short &quot;the Project Highway&quot; and/or the <lb/>&quot;Project Road&quot;). The Project Highway is a road in the Mumbai <lb/>Metropolitan Region which provides an East-West Link and <lb/>connects NH3 to NH4. This Project Highway bears a heavy load of <lb/>commercial traffic as well as caters to passenger vehicles <lb/>commuting between Kalyan-Bhiwandi and Dombivali. The road <lb/>measures 21.6 kilometers in length of which four kilometers was a <lb/>four lane Highway from before and the rest of the road was of poor <lb/>quality and a two-lane undivided carriageway. Additionally, over <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></titlePage>

			<front>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 5 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>fifty percent of the road length had stretches with poor driving <lb/>conditions and was in need of immediate attention for road <lb/>strengthening etc. The Project comprised of strengthening the <lb/>existing four lane dual carriageway and widening the existing two-<lb/>lane carriageway to a four lane dual carriageway. <lb/>5. <lb/>In order to carry out work on the Project Highway, the <lb/>Government of Maharashtra, by its letter dated 31 st January, 2005, <lb/>and Notification dated 24 th July, 2006, appointed the petitioner <lb/>(MSRDC) as an entrepreneur to implement the said Project with a <lb/>concession period of 15 years 8 months and 15 days in two phases <lb/>on a build, operate and transfer (BOT) basis. Phase-I was for <lb/>strengthening the existing two lane divided carriageway and <lb/>widening the existing two-way carriageway to a four lane divided <lb/>carriageway. Phase-I concession period was for 9 years, 10 months <lb/>and 15 days. Phase-II was for constructing the Kalyan Bypass with <lb/>a major bridge on Ulhas river and Railway Over Bridge (&quot;ROB&quot;) on <lb/>the Central Railway Line along with the approach roads. <lb/>6. <lb/>In order to carry out the aforesaid work, the petitioner <lb/>invited bids on 19 th July, 2005. Pursuant thereto, a consortium of <lb/></body>

			<front>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 6 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>&quot;Plus Expressways Berhad&quot; and &quot;Concept Management and <lb/>Consulting Private Limited&quot; bid for the said Project and was found to <lb/>be the successful bidder having offered the lowest concession period <lb/></body>

			<titlePage>of 6 years, 8 months and 4 days. &quot;Plus Expressway Berhad&quot; is <lb/>stated to be wholly owned by the investment arm of the Government <lb/>of Malaysia. <lb/>The consortium partner, &quot;Concept Management <lb/>Consulting Private Limited&quot; is a company incorporated in India <lb/>under the Companies Act, 1956. The bid of this consortium, namely <lb/>the Plus -Concept Consortium was accepted by the MSRDC vide a <lb/>letter dated 12 th May, 2006. Subsequently, as required under the <lb/>agreement, the consortium promoted and constituted a special <lb/>purpose vehicle called &quot;Plus BKSP Toll Limited&quot; and who was the <lb/>Claimant in the arbitration proceedings (the respondent herein). <lb/>Accordingly, the petitioner, the respondent and the consortium <lb/>entered into a Concession Agreement dated 25 th August, 2006, and <lb/>which is the Agreement out of which the present disputes arise. For <lb/>the sake of convenience, the petitioner shall be referred to as <lb/>&quot;MSRDC&quot; and the respondent shall be referred to as &quot;PLUS&quot;. <lb/>7. <lb/>As per the Concession Agreement, M/s. S.N. Bhobe and <lb/>Associates Private Limited was appointed as an Independent <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 7 of 169 <lb/>Consultant (for short the &quot;IC&quot;) for the Project. The IC was <lb/>appointed by MSRDC under clause 20 of the Concession Agreement. <lb/>Clause 20.1, inter alia, provided that MSRDC will monitor and <lb/>supervise the Project. However, MSRDC could appoint a consulting <lb/>firm for this purpose by following an appropriate selection process <lb/>and the name of the finally selected IC was to be communicated to <lb/>the Concessionaire (PLUS). <lb/>8. <lb/>In accordance with the terms and conditions of the <lb/>Concession Agreement, the date of the commencement of <lb/>construction was reckoned as 25 th August, 2006. The Commercial <lb/>Operations Date (&quot;COD&quot;) was to be 24 th February, 2008 and was the <lb/>date on which MSRDC was to issue the completion certificate or <lb/>provisional completion certificate. The concession period was to run <lb/>until 28 th April, 2013, namely, the period from the date of signing of <lb/>the Concession Agreement and ending on the termination date. <lb/>9. <lb/>According to MSRDC, it was agreed between the parties <lb/>that PLUS would not be entitled to recover Toll until after receipt of <lb/>the completion certificate or the provisional completion certificate <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></titlePage>

			<front>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 8 of 169 <lb/>and after removing the defects, if any. The provisional completion <lb/>certificate came to be issued to PLUS on 22 nd June, 2009, subject to <lb/>certain terms and conditions. In the meantime, the Government of <lb/>Maharashtra issued a Toll Notification on 13 th August, 2009, <lb/>authorizing PLUS to collect and retain the Toll from 22 nd August, <lb/>2009 till 28 th April, 2013. In a meeting held on 23 rd October, 2009 <lb/>between PLUS and MSRDC, it was decided that the date of the <lb/>provisional completion certificate would be deemed to be 22 nd <lb/>August, 2009. <lb/>10. <lb/>Thereafter, on 30 th October, 2009, MSRDC granted PLUS <lb/>an extension of the construction period until 29 th December, 2009, <lb/>which was an extension of 674 days from the original schedule <lb/>Project completion date. As there was a delay in completion of the <lb/>construction of the Project, PLUS addressed a letter to MSRDC and <lb/>the IC, inter alia, requesting MSRDC to pay a sum of Rs.161.65 <lb/>crores (being the difference between the actual cost incurred by <lb/>PLUS and the original Project cost) towards additional direct cost <lb/>incurred due to the alleged material default of the Concession <lb/>Agreement by MSRDC as well as a Force Majeure Event. Thereafter, <lb/>on 16 th April, 2010, PLUS, while referring to its letter dated 24 th <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 9 of 169 <lb/>February, 2010, inter alia, stated that it was seeking compensation <lb/>for all additional direct costs suffered and incurred by it and called <lb/>upon MSRDC to pay the purported dues for which it provided the <lb/>certificate from the statutory auditors. According to MSRDC, since <lb/>disputes arose between the parties, PLUS, by its letter dated 10 th <lb/>May, 2010, called upon the IC to act in accordance with clause <lb/>39.1(b) of the Concession Agreement and referred six claims to it <lb/>for conciliation. I must note that this is seriously disputed by PLUS <lb/>as, according to it, only one claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; was <lb/>referred to the IC under clause 39.1(b) and not all six claims. I will <lb/>deal with this aspect later in my judgment. <lb/>11. <lb/>Be that as it may, the IC, by its letter dated 15 th May, <lb/>2010, agreed to act as a Mediator in accordance with clause 39.1(b). <lb/>Thereafter, several meetings were held and correspondence was <lb/>exchanged between the parties for the purpose of and in pursuance <lb/>of the request for conciliation/mediation. Finally, MSRDC and PLUS <lb/>forwarded a joint proposal to the Government of Maharashtra for its <lb/>consideration. During the pendency of the said proposal, PLUS, by <lb/>its two letters dated 19 th March, 2013 terminated the Concession <lb/>Agreement. However, PLUS did not stop collecting Toll from the <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 10 of 169 <lb/>said date and vide its letters dated 8 th April, 2013 and 22 nd April, <lb/>2013 requested for an amicable settlement. <lb/>The Concession <lb/>Agreement thereafter came to an end on 28 th April, 2013. PLUS, <lb/>therefore, by its letter dated 25 th April, 2014, made a reference of all <lb/>disputes and differences, including the Counter Claim between <lb/>MSRDC and PLUS to the Vice Chairman and Managing Director of <lb/>MSRDC. Thereafter, several discussions and meetings took place <lb/>between the parties. As the disputes could not be resolved, PLUS, by <lb/>its letter dated 31 st July, 2015, invoked arbitration and appointed <lb/>the Hon&apos;ble Mr. Justice Aftab Alam (Retired) as their nominee <lb/>Arbitrator. On the other hand, MSRDC by its letter dated 27 th <lb/>August, 2015, appointed Mr. R.M. Premkumar (Retired), an IAS <lb/>Officer, as their Nominee Arbitrator and all disputes and differences <lb/>were referred to arbitration. Thereafter, the Indian Council for <lb/>Arbitrators, by their letter dated 15 th December, 2015, appointed <lb/>the Hon&apos;ble Mr. Justice Shafee Syed Parkar (Retired) as the <lb/>Presiding Arbitrator. Accordingly, the Arbitral Tribunal was duly <lb/>constituted. <lb/></front>

			<titlePage>12. <lb/>In its first meeting held on 20 th February, 2016, the <lb/>Arbitral Tribunal, in consultation with the parties and their <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 11 of 169 <lb/>advocates, passed a detailed Procedural Order. <lb/>By the said <lb/>Procedural Order, the Arbitral Tribunal fixed a detailed procedure <lb/>and passed directions for filing of the pleadings, documents, <lb/>evidence etc, including the dates for cross-examination of witnesses <lb/>by each party and also the dates for oral hearing. It was made clear <lb/>that only in exceptional circumstances, extension of time would be <lb/>granted, but under no circumstances, the scheduled dates of <lb/>hearings fixed by the Arbitral Tribunal would be affected or altered. <lb/>The relevant portion of this Procedural Order reads as under: <lb/>&quot;Practice Directions [under Section 19(3) of the Arbitration and <lb/>Conciliation Act, 1996] <lb/>After discussion, the Learned Counsel for the parties have agreed <lb/>on this practice and procedure to be followed and in accordance <lb/>therewith the following directions are issued by the Tribunal: <lb/>1. <lb/>Extension of time shall be granted by the Tribunal in its <lb/>discretion: <lb/>(a) <lb/>in exceptional cases only; <lb/>(b) <lb/>provided that a request is submitted before the date <lb/>scheduled; and <lb/>(c) <lb/>as soon as it appears that the deadline cannot be complied <lb/>with. <lb/>The Parties may also agree between themselves for short <lb/>extensions of time, on the basis of mutual courtesy, as long as <lb/>those extensions do not materially affect the time table (the dates <lb/>scheduled for the sittings of the Tribunal must not be affected) and <lb/>that the Tribunal is informed prior to the scheduled deadline.&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 12 of 169 <lb/>13. <lb/>Accordingly, as per the Procedural Order dated 20 th <lb/>February, 2016, PLUS filed its Statement of Claim. MSRDC, by its <lb/>advocate&apos;s letter dated 28 th April, 2016, sought four weeks&apos; time to <lb/>file the Statement of Defence and Counter Claim for the reasons <lb/>more particularly stated in the said letter. PLUS objected to <lb/>granting further time to MSRDC to file its Statement of Defence and <lb/>Counter Claim on the ground that the schedule fixed by the Arbitral <lb/>Tribunal on 20 th February, 2016, was prepared after discussing and <lb/>obtaining the consent of the lawyers for both parties. The Arbitral <lb/>Tribunal, by its order dated 4 th May, 2016, granted two weeks&apos; time <lb/>to MSRDC to file its Statement of Defence and Counter Claim. <lb/>Thereafter, by its Procedural Order dated 12 th May, 2016, the <lb/>Arbitral Tribunal rescheduled the dates only to the extent to which <lb/>it concerned filing of the pleadings, documents and evidence. The <lb/>dates fixed for cross-examination of witnesses as well as for oral <lb/>hearings was kept unchanged. In other words, the time fixed for <lb/>cross-examination of witnesses from 17 th January, 2017 to 21 st <lb/>January, 2017, remained unchanged and similarly, the dates fixed <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 13 of 169 <lb/>for oral arguments from 31 st January, 2017 to 4 th February, 2017 <lb/>also remained unchanged. <lb/>14. <lb/>Thereafter, the respondent filed its Statement of Defence <lb/>and Counter Claim before the Arbitral Tribunal, taking up various <lb/>defences. The record reflects that thereafter PLUS filed an <lb/>application for production of documents which was objected to by <lb/>MSRDC on various grounds. One of the main grounds was that the <lb/>documents sought to be produced were expressly barred under <lb/>sections 75 and 81 of the Act and/or section 23 of the Evidence Act <lb/>and/or that they were privileged and/or were confidential. The <lb/>Arbitral Tribunal held a meeting on 17 th October, 2016, wherein it <lb/>deferred all issues raised by the parties at the final hearing. By the <lb/>said order dated 17 th October, 2016, the Tribunal once again <lb/>confirmed the fact that the other directions given in the Procedural <lb/>Order dated 20 th February, 2016, shall remain unchanged. <lb/>15. <lb/>Thereafter, as per the schedule fixed by the Arbitral <lb/>Tribunal, from 17 th January, 2017 to 21 st January, 2017 cross-<lb/>examination of witnesses of both parties was done and the <lb/>arguments were heard from 31 st January, 2017 to 4 th February, <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 14 of 169 <lb/>2017. On 4 th February, 2017, the hearing concluded and the <lb/>Arbitral Tribunal directed the parties to file their written <lb/>submissions and the matter was reserved for passing an Award. It <lb/>was made clear by the Arbitral Tribunal that there would be no more <lb/>hearings unless the Arbitral Tribunal was of the opinion that after <lb/>going through the written submissions some clarification was <lb/>required. Thereafter, on 26 th April, 2017, MSRDC received from the <lb/>Arbitral Tribunal, a photocopy of the Interim Award dated 25 th <lb/>April, 2017, and which is impugned in the present petition. It is <lb/>aggrieved by this Interim Award that MSRDC is challenging the <lb/>same on the grounds mentioned by me earlier. <lb/>16. <lb/>As noted above, the Interim Award is challenged on five <lb/>different grounds. I find that ground (i) the Award is contrary to <lb/>the procedure agreed to between the parties [ground IIIA]; (ii) the <lb/>failure of the Tribunal to consider / decide the Counter Claim <lb/>[ground IIIC]; and (iii) legal misconduct on the part of the Tribunal <lb/>[ground IIIB]; are all inter-twined together and, therefore, my <lb/>findings on these three grounds will be decided together. The two <lb/>other independent grounds I find are with reference to (i) the <lb/>Tribunal placing reliance on inadmissible evidence which vitiates <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 15 of 169 <lb/>the Award [ground I]; and (ii) upholding the validity of the <lb/>termination of the Concession Agreement [ground II]. I shall deal <lb/>with these two grounds first and separately before I decide the other <lb/>three grounds of challenge. <lb/>I. <lb/>RELIANCE ON INADMISSIBLE EVIDENCE VITIATES <lb/>THE AWARD: <lb/>SUBMISSIONS OF MSRDC: <lb/>17. <lb/>Mr. Chagla, the learned senior counsel appearing on <lb/>behalf of MSRDC, submitted that the Arbitral Tribunal has arrived <lb/>at its findings by relying upon documents and purported admissions <lb/>made in documents which in law were inadmissible and hence could <lb/>not be relied upon or looked at by the Tribunal. This argument is <lb/>premised on the basis that the documents relied upon by the <lb/>Tribunal were documents that were exchanged between the parties <lb/>during the course of mediation /conciliation /settlement proceedings <lb/>before the IC as contemplated under clause 39.1(b) of the <lb/>Concession Agreement. He submitted that the documents and/or <lb/>admissions exchanged between the parties during the course of such <lb/>mediation/conciliation proceedings could not be relied upon as it is <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></titlePage>

			<front>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 16 of 169 <lb/>impermissible in law. To substantiate this argument, Mr. Chagla <lb/>submitted that PLUS made six claims before the IC as a mediator <lb/>under clause 39.1(b) of the Concession Agreement. He submitted <lb/>that clause 31.2 of the Concession Agreement categorically <lb/>stipulates that in the event of MSRDC being in material default and <lb/>such default is cured before termination, MSRDC shall pay to the <lb/>Concessionaire, as compensation, all additional direct cost suffered <lb/>or incurred by the Concessionaire arising out of such material <lb/>default by MSRDC in one lumpsum within thirty days of receiving <lb/>the demand or, at MSRDC&apos;s option, in three equal annual <lb/>instalments, with interest. Mr. Chagla submitted that the term <lb/>&apos;additional direct cost&apos; under the Concession Agreement is, <lb/>therefore, an omnibus term referring to all costs suffered or <lb/>incurred by PLUS in any capacity as long as it arises out of a <lb/>material default by MSRDC. He submitted that this is borne out by <lb/>the correspondence on record before the termination of the <lb/>Concession Agreement. He submitted that PLUS&apos; letter dated 24 th <lb/>February, 2010 to MSRDC categorically refers to &apos;additional direct <lb/>cost&apos; reimbursement due to material default by MSRDC of the <lb/>Concession Agreement. By the said letter, PLUS sought Rs.161.65 <lb/>crores as &apos;additional direct cost&apos; incurred due to material default of <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 17 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>MSRDC under clauses 4.1(b), 4.3, 10.1(i), 10.1(ii) and 10.1(iii). <lb/>Therefore, by the said letter, PLUS sought all additional direct costs <lb/>incurred by it on account of material defaults on the part of MSRDC. <lb/>In other words, it was the submission of Mr. Chagla that all claims <lb/>were referred to mediation/conciliation under clause 39.1(b) and <lb/>not just one claim, namely claim No.5 for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; as <lb/>held by the Arbitral Tribunal. <lb/>18. <lb/>Mr. Chagla thereafter brought to my attention, another <lb/>letter dated 16 th April, 2010, which again reiterates that PLUS had <lb/>sought compensation from MSRDC for all additional direct costs <lb/>suffered and incurred by them arising out of the purported material <lb/>defaults by MSRDC. Mr. Chagla pointed out that a similar letter was <lb/>again written by PLUS on 30 th April, 2010. Finally, on 10 th May, <lb/>2010, PLUS invoked clause 39.1(b) of the Concession Agreement <lb/>and called upon the IC to mediate and assist in resolving the <lb/>reimbursement demands already raised in respect of compensation <lb/>for all additional direct costs suffered due to material defaults of the <lb/>Concession Agreement by MSRDC under clause 31.2 of the <lb/>Concession Agreement. The subject of the letter is identical to the <lb/>earlier letters and the letter itself refers to the letter of 30 th April, <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 18 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>2010, and to all preceding communication to MSRDC on the <lb/>abovementioned subject. Therefore, Mr. Chagla submitted that by <lb/>the said letter, various alleged material defaults on the part of <lb/>MSRDC were referred to the IC, including the claims arising out of <lb/>material defaults under clause 10.1(v) of the Concession <lb/>Agreement. Mr. Chagla submitted that after a meeting on 5 th June, <lb/>2010, scheduled by the IC, in pursuance of PLUS&apos; invocation of <lb/>conciliation, PLUS, inter alia, stated that it was continuing to suffer <lb/>huge losses in revenue and that there was reduction in Toll income <lb/>and that it was seeking compensation for all direct losses suffered by <lb/>PLUS arising out of the erection of barrier by the Government <lb/>Agency (The Commissioner of Police). PLUS also stated that it was <lb/>willing to accept the extension of the concession period in lieu of <lb/>cash payment in light of loss in Toll revenue which was stated as <lb/>Rs.103.9 crores. Mr. Chagla thereafter also brought to my attention <lb/>the letter written by the IC dated 14 th July, 2010 to MSRDC which <lb/>categorically submitted the revised calculations in respect of the <lb/>loss in total revenue due to delay in issue of Toll Notification, non-<lb/>payment of Toll by KDMT and NMMT buses and loss due to diversion <lb/>of heavy vehicles. He thereafter brought to my attention the letter <lb/>written by the IC to MSRDC dated 23 rd June, 2011, wherein one <lb/></body>

			<front>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 19 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>Dhruv Consultant provided the expenditure figures and stated that <lb/>the IC had revised the same to Rs.161.19 cores and incidentally <lb/>Annexure B to the said letter explicitly calculates the loss due to <lb/>diversion of heavy traffic. He also brought to my attention other <lb/>letters written by the IC to MSRDC dated 9 th July, 2011 and 2 nd <lb/>August, 2011. He also submitted that subsequent thereto, MSRDC, <lb/>on 20 th October, 2011, made an offer to PLUS in respect of the <lb/>request for conciliation under their letter dated 10 th May, 2010 by <lb/>proposing an extension in the concession period until 10 th July, <lb/>2024 in lieu of claim Nos.1, 4, 5 and 6 and rejecting the claim for <lb/>compensation for loss of revenue on account of delay in issuing the <lb/>Toll Notification and KDMT and NMMT buses refusing to pay Toll. <lb/>This offer was accepted by PLUS by its letter dated 4 th November, <lb/>2011. He submitted that pursuant thereto, PLUS drafted the terms <lb/>of a Settlement Agreement and Recital D thereof is very relevant. <lb/>Mr. Chagla was at pains to point out Recital D of the draft terms of <lb/>Settlement Agreement clearly stipulates as under: <lb/>&quot;D. Further, in pursuance of Clause 39.1 (&quot;Amicable Resolution&quot;) of <lb/>the Concession Agreement, the Concessionaire, vide its letter no. <lb/>BKSP/PD/CA/E/C/435-10-5-2010 dated May 10, 2010, and earlier <lb/>letters on the subject, raised six (6) claims (as more particularly <lb/>described under &quot;Annexure A&quot; hereto) with MSRDC (&quot;Claim <lb/>Letter&quot;). <lb/>Subsequently, pursuant to recommendations of <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 20 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>independent consultant appointed by MSRDC, M/s S.N. Bhobhe &amp; <lb/>Associates Pvt. Ltd. ( hereinafter referred to as &quot;Independent <lb/>Consultant&quot;) contained in various letters resting with the last letter <lb/>on the subject matter bearing no. SNBAPL/MSRDC-33/BKSP/PLA-<lb/>EST/2010-11/P-113/545-D/1530 dated July 19, 2011 which <lb/>contained revised cash flows on the claims submitted on the Claim <lb/>Letter, and upon complying with various internal procedures and <lb/>approvals within MSRDC, including the approval from MSRDC <lb/>Board of Directors Resolution vide Item Number 06 dated <lb/>September 27, 2011, MSRDC, vide its letter number <lb/>MSRDC/02/JMD(I) BKSH/F.No. 142/3987 dated October 20, 2011 <lb/>made an offer of an amicable settlement to the Concessionaire <lb/>regarding the six(6) claims presented by the Concessionaire vide <lb/>the Claim Letter (&quot;MSRDC Offer&quot;) (as detailed in &quot;Annexure B&quot; <lb/>hereto). <lb/>The MSRDC Offer was duly accepted by the <lb/>Concessionaire vide the letter no. BKSP/PD/CA/E/C986-04-11-<lb/>2011 dated November 4, 2011 (&quot;Acceptance Letter) (as annexed <lb/>hereto as &quot;Annexure C&quot;)&quot; . <lb/>19. <lb/>Relying upon the aforesaid recital, Mr. Chagla submitted <lb/>that even according to PLUS, all six claims were referred to <lb/>conciliation under clause 39.1(b) and, therefore, it was wholly <lb/>incorrect on the part of the Arbitral Tribunal to come to the <lb/>conclusion that only one claim, namely, for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; <lb/>was referred to conciliation and not the other claims. He submitted <lb/>that this was contrary to the entire record, including what was <lb/>stated in the termination notice issued by PLUS dated 19 th March, <lb/>2013. <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 21 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>20. <lb/>Mr. Chagla then submitted that even in PLUS&apos; own <lb/>pleadings [in the Statement of Claim], under the heading &quot;Facts <lb/>about traffic diversion due to ban on entry of heavy vehicles on the <lb/>BKSP Road&quot;, PLUS has clearly averred that it invoked clause 39.1 <lb/>for amicable dispute resolution and requested the IC to mediate and <lb/>assist. All this material, therefore, clearly establishes that even on <lb/>PLUS&apos; own pleaded case, conciliation proceedings, while under the <lb/>nomenclature of &apos;additional direct cost&apos;, actually encompassed all <lb/>claims raised by PLUS. He submitted that, therefore, the findings of <lb/>the Tribunal that the offer of conciliation was only in relation to the <lb/>claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; and that the conciliation <lb/>proceedings were only invoked in relation thereto, is directly <lb/>contrary to the documents on record and the express admissions <lb/>made by PLUS and are, therefore, perverse and completely <lb/>unsustainable. <lb/>SUBMISSIONS OF PLUS: <lb/>21. <lb/>On the other hand, Mr. Khambatta, the learned senior <lb/>counsel appearing on behalf of PLUS, submitted that the IC was <lb/>appointed by MSRDC to monitor and supervise the Project on its <lb/>behalf in terms of clause 20 of the Concession Agreement. The IC <lb/></body>

			<front>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 22 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>was to act as an agent / representative of MSRDC for supervising the <lb/>Project. All communications addressed by MSRDC or PLUS were <lb/>sent to the IC or the IC was also marked on the said communication. <lb/>Apart from this, the IC also wore another hat under the Concession <lb/>Agreement which is as a Mediator in respect of such disputes which <lb/>were specifically referred to him under clause 39.1(b). Under clause <lb/>39.1(b) there were two modes of mediation. In case of a dispute <lb/>between MSRDC and PLUS, either party could, with regard to that <lb/>specific issue or dispute, call upon the IC to mediate that particular <lb/>dispute. Failing mediation by the IC or without the intervention of <lb/>the IC, either party could refer such dispute to the Vice Chairman <lb/>and Managing Director of MSRDC and the Chairman of the Board of <lb/>Directors of PLUS, for an amicable settlement. In the facts of the <lb/>present case, MSRDC appointed M/s. S.N. Bhobe and Associates <lb/>Private Limited as the IC for the current Project. <lb/>22. <lb/>Mr. Khambata submitted that the six claims submitted <lb/>by PLUS to the IC can be divided into two types. Firstly, those <lb/>claims that were lodged by PLUS with the IC on account of various <lb/>reasons during the usual course of business. Secondly, those claims <lb/>in respect of which there was a dispute and PLUS had invoked <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 23 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>clause 39.1(b) of the Concession Agreement for mediation by the IC. <lb/>Mr. Khambatta submitted that in the facts of the present case, the <lb/>six claims submitted to the IC were as under: <lb/>Claim No.1 <lb/>Extension in Concession Period due to <lb/>revision of COD to 29.12.2009. <lb/>Claim No.2 <lb/>Loss in Toll revenue due to delay in Toll <lb/>Notification. <lb/>Claim No.3 <lb/>Loss in Toll revenue due to ban on heavy <lb/>vehicles on the Project Highway. <lb/>Claim No.4 <lb/>Loss in Toll revenue due to refusal to pay <lb/>the Toll fee by KDMT/NMMT for their <lb/>buses plying on the Project Highway. <lb/>Claim No.5 <lb/>Additional direct cost reimbursement due <lb/>to material default of the Concession <lb/>Agreement by MSRDC. -Submitted for <lb/>mediation of the IC under clause <lb/>39.1(b). <lb/>Claim No.6 <lb/>Variation in project cost due to changes in <lb/>the Scope of Work. <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>23. <lb/>Mr. Khambatta submitted that only claim No.5 and <lb/>which was for &apos;additional direct cost&apos;, was referred to mediation of <lb/>the IC under clause 39.1(b). He submitted that this was clear from <lb/>the fact that PLUS by its letter dated 26 th February, 2010, addressed <lb/></body>

			<front>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 24 of 169 <lb/>to MSRDC, filed the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; reimbursement <lb/>as a result of the material defaults of the Concession Agreement by <lb/>MSRDC. This claim was for Rs.161.65 crores. PLUS wrote another <lb/>letter on 16 th April, 2010, to MSRDC demanding reimbursement of <lb/>the &apos;additional direct cost&apos; due to material default of MSRDC. <lb/>Thereafter, on 30 th April, 2010, PLUS addressed another letter to <lb/>MSRDC stating the urgency of resolving the issue of &apos;additional <lb/>direct cost&apos; within the defined time lines. Since MSRDC did not <lb/>make any payments, with reference to the &apos;additional direct cost&apos;, <lb/>PLUS wrote a letter dated 10 th May, 2010 to the IC invoking the <lb/>provisions of clause 39.1(b) for assistance and contractual <lb/>mediation in resolving the issue of &apos;additional direct cost&apos; <lb/>reimbursement and no other claim. Further, on receipt of the <lb/>aforesaid communication, the IC, vide its letter dated 15 th May, <lb/>2010, informed MSRDC that PLUS had invoked clause 39.1(b) of the <lb/>Concession Agreement in relation to the issue of &apos;additional direct <lb/>cost&apos;. MSRDC thereafter by its letter dated 29 th May, 2010, <lb/>requested both PLUS and the IC to attend a meeting for resolution <lb/>under clause 39.1(b) in relation to the issue of &apos;additional direct <lb/>cost&apos; reimbursement. Thereafter, the IC, in its communication dated <lb/>11 th October, 2010, addressed to MSRDC discussed various claims <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 25 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>submitted by PLUS. However, what is important to note is that the <lb/>IC categorically mentioned that clause 39.1(b) was invoked only <lb/>with reference to &apos;additional direct cost&apos;. The IC subsequently, on <lb/>23 rd June, 2011, wrote to MSRDC in relation to the calculation for <lb/>the &apos;additional direct cost&apos; reimbursement whereby the revised <lb/>amount was Rs.161.19 crores. Mr. Khambatta submitted that on <lb/>looking at this letter it was abundantly clear that the claim was only <lb/>for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; in the sum of Rs.161.19 crores and not <lb/>the other claims which were independent of the claim for &apos;additional <lb/>direct cost&apos;. He pointed out that thereafter, by a letter dated 3 rd <lb/>February, 2011, MSRDC informed PLUS stating that they had <lb/>referred all the claims of PLUS to a Committee of Directors <lb/>consisting of the Vice Chairman and Managing Director of MSRDC. <lb/>The Committee was to consider the claims and decide on their <lb/>admissibility and thereafter quantify the same. The Committee was <lb/>to also determine the conversion of the quantified claim to the <lb/>concession period in terms of the Concession Agreement and the <lb/>resultant increase in the concession period. He submitted that all <lb/>claims were referred to the Committee of Directors for the purpose <lb/>of compensating PLUS by extending the Toll period in lieu of cash. <lb/>Mr. Khambatta submitted that this Committee of Directors was not <lb/></body>

			<front>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 26 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>the joint mediation envisaged under clause 39.1(b) and which was <lb/>to consist of (i) the Vice Chairman and Managing Director of MSRDC <lb/>and (ii) the Chairman of PLUS. This Committee of Directors was an <lb/>internal Committee of MSRDC. He thereafter brought to my <lb/>attention, the report of the Committee of Directors of July, 2011. He <lb/>submitted that the Committee of Directors considered all the claims <lb/>and presented its report in respect thereof. In the said report it is <lb/>mentioned that PLUS had lodged six claims with the IC. The report <lb/>analysed <lb/>each <lb/>claim <lb/>individually <lb/>and <lb/>gave <lb/>separate <lb/>recommendations for each claim. Out of the six claims, the <lb/>Committee accepted claim Nos.1, 3, 4 and 6 to be admissible <lb/>whereas claim No.2 was not accepted as a valid claim. With <lb/>reference to claim No. 5, and which related to &apos;additional direct cost&apos;, <lb/>the Committee of Directors stated as under: <lb/>&quot;The Concessionaire has already requested for resolution of this <lb/>issue under the provisions of dispute resolution as per clause <lb/>39.1(Annexure 13) of the Concession Agreement, for which <lb/>MSRDC has appointed Mr. A.V. Deodhar, Superintending <lb/>Engineer, MSRDC to represent itself in the dispute resolution <lb/>proceedings. <lb/>It is most suitable that this issue is resolved as per the provisions of <lb/>the Concession Agreement for determination of the value of <lb/>additional direct cost and grant of extension in concession period to <lb/>the Commissionaire as compensation based on the computed <lb/>value of additional cost which will also save MSRDC from <lb/>substantial financial burden of paying cash compensation.&quot; <lb/></body>

			<front>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 27 of 169 <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>24. <lb/>Mr. Khambatta submitted that the Committee <lb/>summarized its findings, reiterating that claim Nos.1, 3, 4 and 6 <lb/>were accepted in terms of the recommendations of the IC and claim <lb/>No.2 was rejected. However, regarding claim No.5, i.e. &apos;additional <lb/>direct cost&apos;, the Committee recommended &quot;Resolution of dispute as <lb/>per the provisions of the Concession Agreement for settlement of <lb/>issue&quot;. He submitted that from this report of the Committee of <lb/>Directors, it is clear that the Committee either accepted or rejected <lb/>the claims of PLUS, except the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; <lb/>which was claim No.5. This claim was to be resolved by mediation of <lb/>the IC as per clause 39.1(b) of the Concession Agreement. Mr. <lb/>Khambatta submitted that keeping in line with this, the IC also, in <lb/>its communication dated 2 nd August, 2011, addressed to MSRDC, <lb/>listed out six claims, including the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos;. <lb/>The IC thereafter dealt with each individual claim separately. As far <lb/>as claim No.5 is concerned, the IC recommended that PLUS has <lb/>already requested for resolution of this claim under the provisions of <lb/>dispute resolution as per clause 39.1 of the Concession Agreement <lb/>for which MSRDC has appointed Mr. A.V. Deodhar, Superintending <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 28 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>Engineer, MSRDC to represent itself in the dispute resolution <lb/>proceedings. The IC recommended that it is most suitable that this <lb/>issue is resolved amicably as per the provisions of clause 39.1 of the <lb/>Concession Agreement through negotiated settlement with PLUS for <lb/>determining the value of &apos;additional direct cost&apos; and grant of <lb/>extension in the concession period as compensation based on the <lb/>negotiated value of the additional cost and which also would save <lb/>MSRDC from a substantial financial burden of paying cash <lb/>compensation. Mr. Khambatta submitted that all this material <lb/>clearly goes to show that only the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; in <lb/>the sum of Rs.161.19 crores was referred for conciliation under <lb/>clause 39.1(b) and not all the claims as sought to be contended on <lb/>behalf of MSRDC. He submitted that, in fact, the claim of additional <lb/>direct cost has been reduced by the IC from Rs.161.69 crores to <lb/>Rs.40.04 crores and which was accepted by PLUS. This is another <lb/>factor which clearly goes to show that &apos;additional direct cost&apos; was a <lb/>completely separate claim and only that claim was referred to <lb/>mediation/conciliation under clause 39.1(b). <lb/>25. <lb/>This apart, Mr. Khambatta submitted that there is ample <lb/>correspondence on record to show that MSRDC has engaged in <lb/></body>

			<front>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 29 of 169 <lb/>correspondence with several third parties in which they admitted <lb/>their own defaults and which cannot be termed as correspondence <lb/>entered into during conciliation proceedings. <lb/>He, therefore, <lb/>submitted that the contention of MSRDC that all claims were <lb/>referred to mediation is wholly without substance and deserves to <lb/>be rejected. Mr. Khambatta also submitted that when one reads the <lb/>findings of the Arbitral Tribunal on this issue, it is quite clear that <lb/>from the documents on record, it is certainly a plausible view and if <lb/>that be the case, no interference is called for under section 34 of the <lb/>Act. He, therefore, submitted that the aforesaid argument holds no <lb/>merit and ought to be rejected. <lb/>FINDINGS OF THE COURT: <lb/>26. <lb/>I have heard the learned counsel for the parties at length <lb/>and have perused the papers and proceedings in the above petition. <lb/>The point to be decided here is whether all six claims were <lb/>submitted by PLUS to the IC under clause 39.1(b), as sought to be <lb/>contended by Mr. Chagla, or whether only the claim for &apos;additional <lb/>direct cost&apos; was submitted under the said clause. To put it in a nut-<lb/>shell, according to Mr. Chagla, if all claims were submitted for <lb/>conciliation under clause 39.1(b), then all correspondence <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 30 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>exchanged between the parties during the period of conciliation <lb/>would be privileged and/or confidential and could not be relied upon <lb/>for any purpose by the Tribunal. On the other hand, if only the claim <lb/>for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; was submitted for conciliation, the <lb/>situation would be quite different. <lb/>27. <lb/>To understand this controversy, one must understand <lb/>the role of the IC. The IC is defined in the definitions clause (clause <lb/>1.1). It stipulates that the IC (Independent Consultant) shall have <lb/>the meaning ascribed to it in clause 20.1. Correspondingly, clause <lb/>20 of the Concession Agreement deals with the appointment of the <lb/>IC and his duties and obligations. Clause 20 of the Concession <lb/>Agreement reads thus: <lb/>&quot;20. <lb/>INDEPENDENT CONSULTANT <lb/>20.1 <lb/>MSRDC will monitor &amp; supervise the Project. However <lb/>MSRDC may appoint a consulting engineering firm for this purpose <lb/>by following an appropriate selection process. The name of the <lb/>finally selected such Independent Consultant will be communicated <lb/>to the Commissionaire. <lb/>20.2 <lb/>The appointment of the Independent Consultant <lb/>pursuant to Clause 20.1 shall initially be for a period of one and half <lb/>(1.5) years from the date of its appointment. MSRDC may in its <lb/>discretion thereafter renew such appointment or appoint another <lb/>person. <lb/>20.3 <lb/>The Independent Consultant shall report to MSRDC <lb/>about their work, services, and activities pursuant hereto through <lb/></body>

			<front>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 31 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>regular periodic reports (at least once every month) as the situation <lb/>may warrant. Such report of Independent Consultant shall include <lb/>but not be limited to the matters and things set forth in said <lb/>Schedule &apos;O&apos;. <lb/>20.4 <lb/>The cost of supervision and monitoring by MSRDC / <lb/>Independent Consultant shall be borne by Concessionaire. An <lb/>amount of Rs.15,00,000/-(Rupees Fifteen Lakhs) per month during <lb/>Construction Period and an amount of Rs.5,00,000/-(Rupees Five <lb/>Lakhs) per month after COD up to the end of Concession Period <lb/>shall be paid by Concessionaire to MSRDC before 10 th of every <lb/>month. <lb/>20.5 <lb/>MSRDC may terminate the appointment of the <lb/>Independent Consultant at any time subject to appointment of their <lb/>replacement by another Independent Consultant in accordance with <lb/>this Article XXII. <lb/>20.6 <lb/>If the Concessionaire has reason to believe that the <lb/>Independent Consultant is not discharging its duties in a fair, <lb/>efficient and diligent manner, it may make a written representation <lb/>to MSRDC, stating its reasons in detail, seeking termination of the <lb/>appointment of the Independent Consultant. Upon receipt of such <lb/>representation, MSRDC shall hold a tripartite meeting with the <lb/>Concessionaire and Independent Consultant for amicable <lb/>resolution of the dispute. If the dispute remains unresolved, it shall <lb/>be resolved in accordance with the Dispute Resolution Procedure. <lb/>In case the appointment of Independent Consultant is terminated <lb/>under this Clause, it shall be replaced by another Independent <lb/>Consultant in accordance with this Article XX. <lb/>20.7 <lb/>If either party disputes any advice, instruction or <lb/>award of the Independent Consultant, the dispute shall be resolved <lb/>in accordance with the Dispute Resolution Procedure.&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>28. <lb/>As can be seen from the aforesaid clauses, it was the <lb/>obligation of MSRDC to monitor and supervise the Project. However, <lb/>MSRDC could appoint a Consulting Engineering Firm for this <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 32 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>purpose, namely, to monitor and supervise the Project. The <lb/>Independent Consultant (IC) was to report to MSRDC about the <lb/>working, services and activities through regular periodic reports. <lb/>Such reports were to include but not limited to the matters and <lb/>things set forth in Schedule-O. MSRDC also had the right to <lb/>terminate the appointment of the IC at any time, subject to <lb/>appointment of their replacement by another IC in accordance with <lb/>Article XXII. From the aforesaid clauses, it is clear that the IC was a <lb/>person appointed by MSRDC to monitor and supervise the Project <lb/>and was to report to MSRDC regarding its progress by filing regular <lb/>periodic reports. Apart from this role, the IC had another role to <lb/>play. This was to act as a Mediator as contemplated under clause <lb/>39.1(b) of the Concession Agreement. For the sake of convenience, <lb/>Clause 39.1 is reproduced hereunder: <lb/>&quot;39. DISPUTE RESOLUTION <lb/>39.1 Amicable Resolution <lb/>(a) <lb/>Save where expressly stated to the contrary in the <lb/>Agreement, any dispute, difference or controversy of whatever <lb/>nature howsoever arising under, out of or in relation to this <lb/>Agreement including incompletion of the Project Highway <lb/>between the Parties and so notified in writing by either Party to <lb/>the other (the &quot;Dispute&quot;) in the first instance shall be attempted <lb/>to be resolved amicably in accordance with the conciliation <lb/>procedure set forth in Sub-clause (b) below. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 33 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>(b) <lb/>In the event of any Dispute between the Parties, either <lb/>Party may call upon the Independent Consultant to mediate <lb/>and assist the Parties in arriving at an amicable settlement <lb/>thereof. Failing mediation by the Independent Consultant or <lb/>without the intervention of the Independent Consultant, either <lb/>Party may require such Dispute to be referred to the VC &amp; MD <lb/>of MSRDC and the Chairman of the Board of Directors of the <lb/>Concessionaire, for the time being for amicable settlement. <lb/>Upon such reference, the said two Authorities shall meet not <lb/>later than 7 (seven) days of the date of such request to <lb/>discuss and attempt to amicably resolve the Dispute. If such <lb/>meeting does not take place within the said period or the <lb/>Dispute is not amicably settled within 15 (fifteen) days of such <lb/>meeting between the said two Authorities, either Party may <lb/>refer the dispute to arbitration in accordance with the <lb/>provisions of Clause 39.2. <lb/>(c) <lb/>If the Dispute is not resolved as evidenced by the <lb/>signing of the written terms of settlement within 30 (thirty) <lb/>working days of the aforesaid notice in writing or such longer <lb/>period as may be mutually agreed by the Parties then the <lb/>provisions of Clause 39.2 shall apply.&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>29. <lb/>As can be seen from clause 39.1, where there was any <lb/>dispute, difference or controversy of whatever nature arising under, <lb/>out of, or in relation to the Concession Agreement, the aggrieved <lb/>party could, by writing, inform the other party about such dispute <lb/>and the same was to be attempted to be resolved amicably in <lb/>accordance with the conciliation procedure set forth in sub-clause <lb/>(b) of clause 39.1. Sub-clause (b) stipulates that in the event of any <lb/>dispute between the parties, either party may call upon the IC to <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 34 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>mediate and assist the parties in arriving at an amicable settlement <lb/>thereof. Failing mediation by the IC, or without the intervention of <lb/>the IC, either party may require such dispute to be referred to (i) the <lb/>VC and MD of MSRDC and (ii) the Chairman of the Board of <lb/>Directors of PLUS, for an amicable settlement. In other words, <lb/>conciliation proceedings under clause 39.1(b) could be undertaken <lb/>either by (i) the IC; or (ii) the VC and MD of MSRDC alongwith the <lb/>Chairman of the Board of Directors of PLUS. Reading these clauses, <lb/>I find considerable force in the argument of Mr. Khambatta that the <lb/>IC, under the Concession Agreement, wore two different hats. <lb/>Firstly, he was a person who was supposed to monitor and supervise <lb/>the Project and report to MSRDC. The second was to act as a <lb/>Mediator under clause 39.1(b), if the said clause was so invoked by <lb/>either party. <lb/>30. <lb/>Having said this, I shall now examine whether the <lb/>factual situation before me is one where mediation / conciliation was <lb/>invoked with reference to all six claims submitted by PLUS to the IC <lb/>or whether it was only the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; that was <lb/>the subject matter of mediation/conciliation under clause 39.1(b). <lb/>In this regard, I find considerable force in the arguments canvassed <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 35 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>by Mr. Khambatta. Clause 39.1(b) was invoked by PLUS vide its <lb/>letter dated 10 th May, 2010. This letter was issued in relation to the <lb/>claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos;. On receipt of the aforesaid <lb/>communication, the IC, vide its letter dated 15 th May, 2010, <lb/>informed MSRDC that PLUS had invoked clause 39.1(b) of the <lb/>Concession Agreement in relation to the issue of &apos;additional direct <lb/>cost&apos;. MSRDC thereafter, by its letter dated 29 th May, 2010, <lb/>requested both PLUS and the IC to attend a meeting for dispute <lb/>resolution under clause 39.1(b) in relation to the issue of &apos;additional <lb/>direct cost&apos; reimbursement. Thereafter, the IC in its communication <lb/>dated 11 th October, 2010, addressed to MSRDC discussed the six <lb/>claims submitted by PLUS. However, what is important to note is <lb/>that the IC categorically mentioned that clause 39.1(b) was invoked <lb/>only with reference to the claim of &apos;additional direct cost&apos; which <lb/>arose due to the delay in the Commercial Operations Date (COD) and <lb/>not for other claims. In fact, on the face of it, claim Nos.3 &amp; 4, and <lb/>which related to (i) loss in Toll revenue due to ban on heavy vehicles <lb/>on the Project Highway and (ii) loss in Toll revenue due to refusal to <lb/>pay the Toll fee by KDMT/NMMT for their buses plying on the <lb/>Project Highway, are not, as they could not have been, claims made <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 36 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>due to the delay in the Commercial Operations Date (COD) at all. The <lb/>relevant portion of the said letter reads thus: <lb/>&quot;… … … <lb/>6) <lb/>Additional Direct Cost due to material default of the <lb/>concession agreement by MSRDC: This claim is due to the <lb/>delay in COD of the project highway and additional direct costs <lb/>suffered by the concessionaire as a result of this delay. The <lb/>sequence of events and concessionaire&apos;s claim are as follows: <lb/>a. <lb/>As per the terms of the Concession Agreement, it was a <lb/>condition precedent under clause 4.1(b) and an obligation of <lb/>MSRDC under clause 10.1(i) to grant the concessionaire way <lb/>leaves required in connection of the project highway and provide <lb/>the right of way for the alignment of the project free from any <lb/>encumbrances. <lb/>b. <lb/>The above matter resulted in delay in COD by 674 days. <lb/>c. <lb/>Subsequently, in order to ensure completion of the project <lb/>highway construction despite the material default, with the <lb/>cognizance of the causes of delay, the construction period and <lb/>date and COD were extended by 674 days to 29.12.2009 by <lb/>MSRDC vide its letter no.MSRDC/02/JMD(1)/BKS:1/File <lb/>No.102/49999 dt. 30.10.2009. <lb/>To provide this extension, <lb/>MSRDC invoked Force Majeure clauses 29.4 and 29.6(b), latter <lb/>being the only clause in the concession agreement which <lb/>provides for extending the concession period. <lb/>d. <lb/>Concessionaire vide letter no.BKSP/PD/CA/E/C/366 dated <lb/>February 24, 2010, and various subsequent letters on the subject <lb/>matter, demanded that they should be compensated for <lb/>additional direct costs suffered due the delay in COD for which it <lb/>is contractually entitled under clause 31.2, that provides for <lb/>compensation in the event of MSRDC being in material default of <lb/>the concession agreement and also under 29.6(d) read with <lb/>clause 29.7(c) that provide for reimbursement of cost actually <lb/>incurred and certified by the statutory auditors of concessionaire <lb/>in case of Political Force Majeure event. <lb/>e. <lb/>MSRDC vide its letter referred at sr. no. 9 above <lb/>communicated to the concessionaire its denial on material default <lb/>of the concession agreement. <lb/></body>

			<front>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></front>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 37 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>f. <lb/>Concessionaire vide its letter referred at sr. no. 10 <lb/>has provided its response, reiterating the basis for compensation, <lb/>clarifying that the extension in construction period merely <lb/>attempts to restore the original operations period which was <lb/>drastically reduced due to delay in COD and does not <lb/>compensation for the additional direct costs suffered due to the <lb/>delay; further maintaining its stand that it was an event of <lb/>material default of the concession agreement by MSRDC. <lb/>g <lb/>As per clause 39.1(b) of the concession agreement, <lb/>concessionaire has called upon us to mediate and assist in <lb/>arriving at an amicable settlement of the issue vide its letters <lb/>numbered 435 and 439 dated 10.05.2010 and 26.05.2010 <lb/>respectively. <lb/>… … …&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>31. <lb/>Apart from this, I find that all the claims submitted by <lb/>PLUS were referred by MSRDC to a Committee of Directors <lb/>consisting of the Vice Chairman and Managing Director of MSRDC. <lb/>This Committee of Directors thereafter prepared a report in July, <lb/>2011 wherein it considered all the claims of PLUS and presented its <lb/>report in respect thereof. The said report categorically mentions <lb/>that PLUS had lodged six claims with the IC. The report analysed <lb/>each claim individually and gave separate recommendations for <lb/>each claim. Out of the six claims submitted by PLUS, the Committee <lb/>accepted claim Nos.1, 3, 4 and 6 (set out earlier) to be admissible, <lb/>whereas claim No.2 was not accepted as a valid claim. With <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 38 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>reference to claim No.5 and which related to &apos;additional direct cost&apos;, <lb/>the Committee of Directors noted that PLUS had requested for <lb/>resolution of this issue under the provisions of the Dispute <lb/>Resolution as per clause 39.1 of the Concession Agreement and for <lb/>which MSRDC had appointed Mr. A.V. Deodhar to represent itself in <lb/>the dispute resolution proceedings. It was thereafter recommended <lb/>that it would be more suitable that this issue is resolved as per the <lb/>provisions of the Concession Agreement for determination of the <lb/>value of &apos;additional direct cost&apos; and to grant extension in the <lb/>concession period which will also save MSRDC a substantial <lb/>financial burden of paying cash compensation. <lb/>32. <lb/>From all this material, I find that Mr. Khambatta is <lb/>correct in his submission that only the claim for &apos;additional direct <lb/>cost&apos; [namely, claim No. 5], was the claim that was referred to <lb/>mediation / conciliation under clause 39.1(b) of the Concession <lb/>Agreement. I am unable to agree with Mr. Chagla that the words <lb/>&apos;additional direct cost&apos; should be read in an omnibus fashion which <lb/>would include every single claim that was submitted by PLUS to the <lb/>IC. This is not how the IC understood it and neither was it the <lb/>understanding of MSRDC or the Committee of Directors of MSRDC. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 39 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>33. <lb/>This apart, I find the discussion on this aspect by the <lb/>Arbitral Tribunal is at paragraphs 65, 75 and 76 respectively. The <lb/>Tribunal has noted that the letter dated 10 th May, 2010, and the <lb/>letters issued earlier to it do not actually refer to the six claims, but <lb/>rather only to the claim of &apos;additional direct cost&apos;. This claim was <lb/>first put forward by a letter dated 24 th February, 2010 where PLUS <lb/>claimed an amount of Rs.161 crores as the escalated project cost on <lb/>account of material default of MSRDC. Subsequently, this claim was <lb/>pursued by further letters dated 16 th April, 2010 and 30 th April, <lb/>2010. Finally, by means of the letter dated 10 th May, 2010, PLUS <lb/>proposed conciliation. It is in this light that the Arbitral Tribunal <lb/>came to a finding that the offer of conciliation was in relation only to <lb/>the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos;. The Tribunal held that though <lb/>it is true that other claims had also been raised by that time, these <lb/>were by means of separate letters and were separately pursued. It <lb/>is only much later, by a communication dated 2 nd August, 2011, that <lb/>the Independent Consultant clubs the various claims under the six <lb/>heads and makes its recommendations with relation to each claim. <lb/>With reference to claim No.5 (&apos;additional direct cost&apos;), the IC once <lb/>again notes that PLUS has already requested for resolution of this <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 40 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>issue under the provisions of the Dispute Resolution as per clause <lb/>39.1 of the Concession Agreement and it is most suitable that this <lb/>issue is resolved amicably as per the provisions of clause 39.1 <lb/>through negotiated settlement and granting extension in the <lb/>concession period will save MSRDC a substantial financial burden of <lb/>paying cash compensation. The Tribunal further notes the strong <lb/>objection of MSRDC regarding the admissibility of not only the <lb/>Director&apos;s report referred to above, but to a very large number of <lb/>documents / correspondence exchanged between PLUS, the IC and <lb/>MSRDC in regard to the claims raised. It notes that the objection to <lb/>the admissibility of these documents is the most prominent and <lb/>consistent theme of the case of MSRDC. The main objection is that <lb/>the correspondence between the parties was made in the course of <lb/>conciliation proceedings and, therefore, protected by confidentiality <lb/>on account of sections 75 and 81 in Part III of the Arbitration &amp; <lb/>Conciliation Act, 1996 and/or section 23 of the Evidence Act. After <lb/>considering the material and giving a careful consideration to the <lb/>objection raised by MSRDC, the Tribunal finds no merit in this <lb/>contention. The Tribunal holds that firstly the conciliation <lb/>proceedings were only invoked in relation to the claim for <lb/>&apos;additional direct cost&apos; whereas the figure of Rs.112 crores includes <lb/></body>

			<front>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 41 of 169 <lb/>loss on other grounds as well (loss of Toll revenue on account of <lb/>traffic regulations and non-payment of Toll by Municipal buses). The <lb/>Tribunal, therefore, holds that the alleged confidentiality attached to <lb/>the conciliation proceedings can, at best, be attached to matters <lb/>pertaining to the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos;, but not the other <lb/>claims. The Tribunal also correctly holds that the Concession <lb/>Agreement never envisaged or contemplated a conciliation as <lb/>contemplated under Part III of the Act and neither any such <lb/>procedure was followed. It also noted that the IC was a nominee of <lb/>MSRDC performing MSRDC&apos;s obligations under the agreement <lb/>which it could outsource to the IC. Part III of the Act, however, <lb/>requires that there should be an independent and impartial third-<lb/>party Conciliator to mediate and assist in the resolution dispute. <lb/>Given that the IC was a nominee of MSRDC, it could never, therefore, <lb/>have performed the role of a Conciliator as understood and <lb/>envisaged under Part III of the Act. It could, at best, have been a <lb/>contractual conciliation procedure. The third point that the Tribunal <lb/>holds on this issue is that clause 39.1(b) of the Agreement did not <lb/>expressly contain any confidentiality restrictions with regard to the <lb/>correspondence exchanged during the conciliation procedure and <lb/>nor are any documents marked &apos;without prejudice&apos;. It is in these <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 42 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>circumstances that the Tribunal rejected the contention of MSRDC <lb/>that the documents exchanged between the parties was a part of <lb/>conciliation and, therefore, inadmissible in the proceedings. The <lb/>Tribunal thereafter, though holding that the documents were <lb/>admissible, categorically recorded that it would still be required to <lb/>be determined as to the weightage that could be attached to these <lb/>documents as evidence of an admitted quantification of the loss <lb/>suffered by PLUS. <lb/>34. <lb/>Having gone through the findings given by the Arbitral <lb/>Tribunal in the relevant paragraphs mentioned above, it can hardly <lb/>be stated that the view taken by the Tribunal suffers from any <lb/>patent illegality or is perverse. The Tribunal has examined the <lb/>record, heard the parties and thereafter come to its conclusion. The <lb/>Arbitral Tribunal has categorically held that after looking at the <lb/>correspondence on record, the conciliation proceedings were only <lb/>invoked in relation to the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; and not <lb/>with reference to any other claim. This finding can hardly be <lb/>termed as perverse and is certainly a plausible view taken by the <lb/>Tribunal to hold that the objection to the admissibility of the <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 43 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>documents on the ground that they are part of conciliation <lb/>proceedings is without any merit. <lb/>35. <lb/>Before concluding on this issue, it would only be fair to <lb/>deal with the reliance placed by Mr. Chagla on Recital &apos;D&apos; of the draft <lb/>settlement agreement (reproduced above). I find that the reliance <lb/>placed by Mr. Chagla on Recital &apos;D&apos; is wholly misplaced. Firstly, <lb/>PLUS itself sought to rely upon this draft (to establish admission of <lb/>liability) and which was negated by the Tribunal on the ground that <lb/>the same was never signed by either of the parties and hence could <lb/>not be relied upon. I then fail to see how MSRDC can rely upon it <lb/>when it does not admit the same. Secondly, Recital &apos;D&apos; talks about <lb/>the six claims that were raised pursuant to a letter dated 10 th May, <lb/>2010 and earlier letters on the subject. In fact, the letter dated 10 th <lb/>May, 2010 (and the earlier letters) clearly shows that six claims <lb/>were never raised and only the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; was <lb/>raised under the said letters which culminated into conciliation <lb/>proceedings under clause 39.1(b). <lb/>The Tribunal too, after <lb/>examining the correspondence on record, categorically records that <lb/>the letter dated 10 th May, 2010 and the letters issued earlier to it, <lb/>do not actually refer to the six claims, but rather only to the claim <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 44 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>for &apos;additional direct cost&apos;. In fact, the Tribunal also records that <lb/>though it is true that other claims had also been raised by that time, <lb/>these were by means of separate letters and were separately <lb/>pursued. This being the position, I find that the reliance placed by <lb/>Mr. Chagla on Recital &apos;D&apos; of the draft settlement agreement is wholly <lb/>misplaced. Similar is the case in relation to the pleadings filed <lb/>before the Arbitral Tribunal. The Tribunal has considered the <lb/>pleadings and has thereafter come to the conclusion that it was only <lb/>the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; that was referred to mediation / <lb/>conciliation and not any other claim. In these circumstances, I do <lb/>not find that the Tribunal was in any error in holding that it was <lb/>only the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; that was referred to <lb/>mediation / conciliation under clause 39.1(b) and not any other <lb/>claim. I, therefore, do not find any reason to interfere with the <lb/>Interim Award on this issue. <lb/>II. UPHOLDING THE VALIDITY OF THE TERMINATION <lb/>OF THE CONCESSION AGREEMENT: <lb/>SUBMISSIONS OF MSRDC: <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 45 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>36. <lb/>Mr. Chagla submitted that the findings of the Arbitral <lb/>Tribunal upholding the termination of the Concession Agreement is <lb/>contrary to the record and, therefore, wholly illegal and perverse. <lb/>He submitted that the Concession Agreement could be terminated <lb/>under two different clauses, namely, clause 32.4 and clause 29.8 of <lb/>the Concession Agreement. Clause 32.4 gave a right to PLUS to <lb/>terminate the Concession Agreement in the event of any default <lb/>committed by MSRDC. On the other hand, clause 29.8 gave a right <lb/>to either party to terminate the agreement if a Force Majeure event <lb/>subsisted for a period of 180 days or more within a continuous <lb/>period of 365 days. Under clause 32.4.1, the termination notice was <lb/>to be given in writing by giving a ninety days&apos; notice under clause. <lb/>37. <lb/>Mr. Chagla submitted that the findings given by the <lb/>Arbitral Tribunal in paragraph 70 of the Award upholding the <lb/>termination of the Concession Agreement under clauses 32.4.1(1) <lb/>and 32.4.1(3) thereof, are wholly illegal and perverse. He submitted <lb/>that PLUS, by its termination notice dated 19 th March, 2013, sought <lb/>to terminate the Concession Agreement under clause 32.4 thereof. <lb/>In order for it to be a valid termination, clause 32.4 requires four <lb/>conditions that need to be satisfied, namely: (1) that there is a <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 46 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>breach of the Concession Agreement; (2) The breach should have a <lb/>material adverse effect on the project; (3) that a 90 days&apos; notice be <lb/>given; and (4) MSRDC failing to cure the said breach or take <lb/>effective steps for curing the said breach within 90 days of receipt of <lb/>the notice. Mr. Chagla submitted that in the facts of the present <lb/>case, none of the aforesaid conditions are satisfied. He submitted <lb/>that firstly clause 32.4 mandatorily required termination to be 90 <lb/>days after a written notice in respect thereto was given to MSRDC. <lb/>It is an admitted position that the 90 days&apos; notice has not been <lb/>given. Despite this, the Arbitral Tribunal, in paragraph 70 of the <lb/>Award records that though a 90 day notice was required, the notice <lb/>period was complied with as PLUS had only refrained from issuing a <lb/>formal termination notice on the assurance of MSRDC and, <lb/>therefore, MSRDC had much more than the 90 day notice period to <lb/>cure the breach. The Tribunal has, in this respect, referred to a <lb/>letter dated 4 th February, 2013. Mr. Chagla submitted that even <lb/>assuming whilst denying that this letter amounted to a written <lb/>notice under clause 32.4, the time period from 4 th February, 2013 to <lb/>28 th April, 2013, did not satisfy the 90 day notice period. He <lb/>submitted that termination under clause 32.4 requires strict <lb/>compliance and failure to give notice of 90 days clearly renders the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 47 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>termination illegal and invalid. He, therefore, submitted that on this <lb/>ground alone it should be held that the Award is illegal and perverse <lb/>as it runs directly contrary to the express wordings of clause 32.4. <lb/>38. <lb/>Mr. Chagla then submitted that in any event, the <lb/>termination under clause 32.4 cannot be held to be valid as there <lb/>was no breach on the part of MSRDC. He submitted that MSRDC was <lb/>obliged to provide the land for the approach road to the Railway <lb/>Over Bridge (ROB). MSRDC had complied with its obligation by the <lb/>time the Railways modified the dimensions of the ROB. This <lb/>modification necessitated additional land to be acquired and also for <lb/>the drawings to be approved by the Railways. The preparation and <lb/>approval of the drawings were the obligations of PLUS. Therefore, <lb/>until the drawings were approved, the ROB could not be constructed. <lb/>The Arbitral Tribunal has completely ignored the obligation of PLUS <lb/>as contained in clause 2 of Schedule B, clause 9.8(ii), notes 3 and 4 <lb/>to the drawing of the Katai ROB and clause 9.4(v) of the Concession <lb/>Agreement. Mr. Chagla submitted that the admitted position is that <lb/>MSRDC had acquired the additional land before the drawings were <lb/>approved by the Railways as recorded in the letters dated 2 nd May, <lb/>2009 and 11 th September, 2009. Therefore, there was no delay <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 48 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>occasioned or prejudice caused to PLUS by reason of the delay in <lb/>acquisition in land and, therefore, no breach was committed by <lb/>MSRDC. <lb/>39. <lb/>Mr. Chagla thereafter submitted that even assuming <lb/>that there was a breach on the part of MSRDC, there was no <lb/>material adverse effect on PLUS. He submitted that the only <lb/>evidence led by PLUS before the Arbitral Tribunal was the <lb/>correspondence addressed complaining of &quot;losses&quot;; constraint on its <lb/>&quot;cash flow position&quot;; that its operations were being jeopardized; and <lb/>mentioning alleged figures of loss etc. PLUS led no evidence in <lb/>support of the alleged losses or constraint on its cash flow or its <lb/>operations being jeopardized, save and except what transpired <lb/>before the IC in the course of conciliation proceedings. As recorded <lb/>by the Tribunal in paragraph 77 of the Award, various figures of loss <lb/>were proposed by either side in the spirit of settlement while they <lb/>were trying to work out a rough and ready compromise. These were <lb/>sought to be relied upon by PLUS as admissions of liability and <lb/>which were expressly rejected by the Arbitral Tribunal. In fact, the <lb/>finding of the Tribunal is that it is for PLUS to prove and quantify <lb/>the loss it has suffered and claim damages on that basis and that the <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 49 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>claim for Rs.112 crores was based only on admissions made by <lb/>MSRDC in the course of conciliation which the Arbitral Tribunal did <lb/>not accept. Mr. Chagla submitted that for the Tribunal to come to a <lb/>finding that there had been a material adverse effect, it was <lb/>essential for the Tribunal to examine the evidence and conclude that <lb/>PLUS had suffered loss or damage which, in turn, would be the <lb/>material adverse effect caused to PLUS. <lb/>On coming to the <lb/>conclusion that on the available evidence, the Tribunal was not in a <lb/>position to conclude that there was a loss or damage, the Arbitral <lb/>Tribunal could not have concluded that there was a material <lb/>adverse effect. The findings in this regard, therefore, are patently <lb/>illegal and wholly perverse, was the submission of Mr. Chagla. <lb/>40. <lb/>In the alternative to the above argument, Mr. Chagla <lb/>submitted that even assuming that MSRDC had committed a breach, <lb/>it had taken effective steps to cure the same. He submitted that <lb/>clause 32.4 allows MSRDC a period of 90 days to cure the alleged <lb/>breach. The Arbitral Tribunal has held that MSRDC had granted an <lb/>extension of 674 days to the construction period vide its letter dated <lb/>18 th June, 2010. The said letter clearly records that the extension <lb/>was granted under clause 29.6(b) of the Concession Agreement and, <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 50 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>therefore, the monetary claim was rejected by MSRDC. Further, <lb/>MSRDC had also got an interim Toll Notification issued on 26 th April, <lb/>2013 permitting PLUS to collect Toll for a period three months from <lb/>28 th April, 2013. PLUS refused the said interim Notification on the <lb/>ground that there was a new condition of depositing the amount of <lb/>Toll in an Escrow Account. Mr. Chagla submitted that there was no <lb/>new condition of depositing the money in the Escrow Account as the <lb/>same was already provided for in clauses 6.3. 6.4, 25 and 34.11 of <lb/>the Concession Agreement. He submitted that it is pertinent to note <lb/>that the Arbitral Tribunal has categorically held that the default of <lb/>the MSRDC is not the failure to have a Toll Notification issued in <lb/>respect of the proposed extended concession period. In light of all <lb/>this, Mr Chagla submitted that MSRDC had taken all effective steps <lb/>to cure the breach, if any. In any event, PLUS terminated the <lb/>Concession Agreement even before the 90 day period was over and, <lb/>therefore, the Tribunal could not have held that MSRDC had not <lb/>cured the breach within the period of 90 days. <lb/>In these <lb/>circumstances, Mr. Chagla submitted that the finding of the Arbitral <lb/>Tribunal upholding the termination of the Concession Agreement <lb/>under clause 32.4.1 is patently illegal and perverse and ought to be <lb/>set aside. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 51 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>41. <lb/>Similarly, Mr. Chagla submitted that the findings of the <lb/>Arbitral Tribunal upholding the termination of the Concession <lb/>Agreement under clause 29.8 are also patently illegal and ought to <lb/>interfered with. Mr. Chagla submitted that in the termination notice <lb/>dated 19 th March, 2013, PLUS sought to terminate the Concession <lb/>Agreement under clause 29.8, inter alia, on the following grounds: <lb/>(a) Non issuance of Toll Notification by the Government <lb/>of Maharashtra till 10 th July, 2024 in pursuance of <lb/>the Settlement Agreement; <lb/>(b) Refusal of KDMT and NMMT buses to pay Toll; and <lb/>(c) Traffic Control Notification dated 11 th May, 2009, <lb/>banning entry of multi axle vehicles through <lb/>Kalyan city and Notification dated 29 th December, <lb/>2009 closing entry of all heavy vehicles on the said <lb/>Project Road. <lb/>42. <lb/>Mr. Chagla brought to my attention that the Arbitral <lb/>Tribunal upheld the termination of the Concession Agreement under <lb/>clause 29.8 on grounds (b) and (c) above and rejected the <lb/>termination on ground (a). Mr. Chagla took me through clause 29 of <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 52 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>the Concession Agreement and which deals with the events of Force <lb/>Majeure. He submitted that in the present case, PLUS has claimed <lb/>existence of a Political Force Majeure event and which is defined in <lb/>clause 29.4. He submitted that a Political Force Majeure event shall <lb/>mean one or more of the acts of events by or on account of MSRDC, <lb/>GOM or any other Governmental agency, as more particularly set <lb/>out in clauses 29.4(i) and 29.4(iii). <lb/>Whilst interpreting the <lb/>aforesaid clauses, Mr. Chagla submitted that it was clear that five <lb/>conditions required fulfilling. They were: (a) the event should be a <lb/>Political Force Majeure event as defined in clause 29.4 of the <lb/>Concession Agreement; (b) the said event should prevent the party <lb/>from performing its obligations under the Concession Agreement; <lb/>(c) the said event is beyond the reasonable control and not arising <lb/>out of the fault of the affected party; (d) the affected party is unable <lb/>to overcome the said event by exercise of due diligence and <lb/>reasonable efforts, skill and care, including through expenditure of <lb/>reasonable sums of money; and (e) the said event has a material <lb/>adverse effect on the Project. Mr. Chagla submitted that the <lb/>Arbitral Tribunal held that refusal of KDMT and NMMT buses to pay <lb/>Toll [ground (b) above] is an expropriation of the rights of PLUS <lb/>and, therefore, constitutes a Political Force Majeure event within <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 53 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>the meaning of clause 29.4 of the Concession Agreement. This <lb/>finding can be found at paragraph 61 of the Award. Mr. Chagla <lb/>submitted that the said finding offends the plain dictionary meaning <lb/>of the word &apos;expropriation&apos; in that the refusal to pay Toll, can by no <lb/>stretch of the imagination, be termed as an expropriation. In this <lb/>regard, he relied upon the Black&apos;s Law Dictionary and the Oxford <lb/>English Dictionary meanings of the word &quot;expropriation&quot;. <lb/>43. <lb/>This apart, Mr. Chagla submitted that in any event PLUS <lb/>was not prevented from performing its obligations. The finding that <lb/>PLUS was prevented from performance of its obligations is illegal <lb/>and perverse as it is contrary to a categorical admission made by the <lb/>Director of PLUS during cross-examination, wherein he admitted <lb/>that PLUS had the ability to perform its obligations. In this regard, <lb/>he brought to my attention a question put to the Director of PLUS <lb/>wherein he was asked as to whether it would be correct to say that <lb/>from 4 th November, 2011 to 28 th April, 2013, PLUS was not <lb/>prevented from performing its obligations under the Concession <lb/>Agreement. The answer to this question was &quot;We had the ability to <lb/>perform because the toll notification was there and we were able to <lb/>collect toll upto 28 th April, 2013&quot;. <lb/>Mr. Chagla submitted that <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 54 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>despite this admission, the Arbitral Tribunal, in paragraph 62 of the <lb/>Award, completely disregards and dismisses the same as an isolated <lb/>statement, holding instead that regard must be had to the entirety of <lb/>the documents on record to ascertain whether, in fact, PLUS was <lb/>prevented in performance of its obligations. Mr. Chagla submitted <lb/>that the said finding has been arrived at without identifying the <lb/>documentary evidence on record in support of such a finding. This <lb/>finding is also contrary to the Arbitral Tribunal&apos;s own finding in <lb/>paragraph 43 of the Award wherein it held that the period from <lb/>November, 2011 to April, 2013, PLUS was still able to collect and <lb/>retain Toll on account of the original Toll Notification till 28 th April, <lb/>2013. <lb/>Mr. Chagla submitted that, therefore, the findings in <lb/>paragraph 62 of the Award are not only self-contradictory but also <lb/>contrary to the admission made by the witness of PLUS. <lb/>44. <lb/>Mr. Chagla next submitted that even if a Political Force <lb/>Majeure event arose, the same was on account of the fault of PLUS. <lb/>He submitted that the finding of the Arbitral Tribunal that the said <lb/>event, namely, refusal of KDMT and NMMT buses to pay Toll was <lb/>entirely beyond the control of PLUS and certainly not on account of <lb/>any fault of PLUS, is patently illegal and perverse inasmuch as the <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 55 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>said event occurred solely on account of the failure on the part of <lb/>PLUS to perform its obligations under the Concession Agreement. <lb/>Mr. Chagla submitted that clause 18.1 of the Concession Agreement <lb/>obliged PLUS to prevent unauthorised entry and exit from the <lb/>Project Road. Further, it was the duty and obligation of PLUS to levy <lb/>and collect Toll from the users of the Project Road and refuse entry <lb/>of any vehicle if the Toll fee was not paid. Mr. Chagla submitted that <lb/>the finding of the Arbitral Tribunal on this aspect is arrived at <lb/>without considering the material clauses of the Concession <lb/>Agreement and has resulted in PLUS being virtually absolved from <lb/>its obligations under the Concession Agreement and which is clearly <lb/>impermissible. He submitted that PLUS could have overcome the <lb/>event by exercising due diligence and reasonable efforts, skill and <lb/>care, including through expenditure of reasonable sums of money. <lb/>The finding of the Arbitral Tribunal that PLUS exercised necessary <lb/>due diligence and that precipitating matters any further could lead <lb/>to serious law and order repercussions is incorrect and contrary to <lb/>its own conclusion that it was for PLUS to exercise legal remedies to <lb/>enforce its rights under the Toll Notification. Mr. Chagla submitted <lb/>that the Arbitral Tribunal has arrived at this finding on the basis of <lb/>assumptions and presumptions and has virtually absolved PLUS of <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 56 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>its obligations to collect Toll and prevent entry of any vehicle that <lb/>was not authorised to use the Project Road. Since PLUS chose not to <lb/>collect Toll from the KDMT and NMMT buses though they were <lb/>entitled to under the Concession Agreement, PLUS now cannot claim <lb/>that the same amounts to a Political Force Majeure event which <lb/>entitles them to terminate the agreement. To put it differently, Mr. <lb/>Chagla submitted that PLUS cannot take advantage of its own <lb/>wrong. <lb/>45. <lb/>Mr. Chagla lastly submitted that in any event there was <lb/>no material adverse effect caused to PLUS by KDMT and NMMT <lb/>buses not paying the Toll. He submitted that the Arbitral Tribunal <lb/>has held that it is unable to arrive at a quantum determination <lb/>based on the existing record and submissions and the Tribunal <lb/>cannot place much weight on the quantum figures arrived at during <lb/>the stage of settlement. Further, the loss on account of Toll revenue <lb/>from KDMT and NMMT buses was also submitted to the IC during <lb/>conciliation proceedings initiated by PLUS. There was, therefore, no <lb/>evidence or material before the Tribunal on the basis of which the <lb/>Tribunal could have arrived at a finding that there was any material <lb/>adverse effect. Further, the Arbitral Tribunal has not referred to <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 57 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>any evidence in order to arrive at the said finding, was the <lb/>submission of Mr. Chagla. He, therefore, submitted that the finding <lb/>of the Arbitral Tribunal in this respect is patently illegal and <lb/>perverse. <lb/>46. <lb/>Mr. Chagla then submitted that similar is the case with <lb/>reference to the ban on heavy vehicles and multi axle vehicles <lb/>[ground (c) above]. He submitted that the ban on heavy vehicles and <lb/>multi axle vehicles did not constitute a Political Force Majeure event <lb/>and the same is evident from the fact that the ban on the said <lb/>vehicles did not amount to a change in law and there was no <lb/>material adverse effect on account of the said ban. Mr. Chagla <lb/>submitted that the finding of the Arbitral Tribunal that PLUS was <lb/>not aware of the resolution passed by KDMC allowing heavy vehicles <lb/>to ply on the project road/project highway only from 10.00 p.m. to <lb/>6.00 a.m. is contrary to the evidence on record. He submitted that <lb/>PLUS was all along aware about the circular dated 20 th March, 2006 <lb/>as by the very circular itself, NOC was granted to KDMC to carry out <lb/>the work. The said NOC was admittedly obtained by PLUS as <lb/>recorded in the Minutes of the Meeting held on 31 st July, 2006 and <lb/>which Minutes were forwarded to MSRDC by PLUS by its letter <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 58 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>dated 3 rd August, 2006. The finding of the Arbitral Tribunal that <lb/>PLUS was unaware of the said circular is belied by the deposition <lb/>and cross-examination of MSRDC&apos;s witness wherein the witness of <lb/>MSRDC has clearly stated that the ban on heavy vehicles was <lb/>applicable much before the tender was issued for the Project Road <lb/>and the said Resolutions dated 9 th March, 2006 and 20 th March, <lb/>2006 were public documents and known to the public. Mr. Chagla <lb/>submitted that the Notifications of 11 th May 2009 and 29 th <lb/>December, 2009 imposing a complete ban did not amount to a <lb/>change in the law or an expropriation of the rights of PLUS within <lb/>the meaning of clause 29. He, therefore, submitted that the ban on <lb/>heavy vehicles, in any event, did not amount to a Political Force <lb/>Majeure event as it did not amount to a change in law. <lb/>47. <lb/>Even assuming for the sake of argument that it would <lb/>amount to a Political Force Majeure event, Mr. Chagla submitted <lb/>that there was no material adverse effect as a result of the said ban. <lb/>The finding of the Arbitral Tribunal that undoubtedly the event had <lb/>a material adverse effect on the Project as the amount of uncollected <lb/>Toll was allegedly in excess of Rs.60 crores is perverse as the <lb/>Arbitral Tribunal has arrived at this conclusion in the absence of <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 59 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>any evidence as no loss has been proved by PLUS. In any event, this <lb/>finding in respect of the figure of Rs.60 crores is also on the basis of <lb/>a figure worked out by the IC during the course of conciliation <lb/>proceedings. PLUS has even admitted in paragraph 6.53 of the <lb/>Statement of Claim that the loss on account of ban on heavy vehicles <lb/>was calculated by the IC vide its letter dated 14 th July, 2010, in <lb/>furtherance of the conciliation proceedings initiated by it. This <lb/>finding has been arrived at by relying upon documents exchanged <lb/>between the parties during the course of mediation and/or <lb/>conciliation and/or amicable settlement. Further, the said figure of <lb/>Rs.60 crores is included in the figure of Rs.112 crores. The Arbitral <lb/>Tribunal has rejected the said claim as is evident from the finding of <lb/>the Arbitral Tribunal in paragraphs 77, 79, 86 and 87 of the Award. <lb/>Therefore, the finding of the Arbitral Tribunal that ban on heavy <lb/>vehicles resulted in a material adverse effect is not only self-<lb/>contradictory, but without any basis. He, therefore, submitted that <lb/>even the termination under clause 29.8 was wholly unwarranted <lb/>and the findings of the Tribunal in this regard are contrary to the <lb/>record and are patently illegal and perverse and ought to be <lb/>interfered with under section 34 of the Arbitration &amp; Conciliation <lb/>Act, 1996. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 60 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>SUBMISSIONS OF PLUS: <lb/>48. <lb/>On the other hand, Mr. Khambatta, the learned senior <lb/>counsel appearing on behalf of PLUS, submitted that in the present <lb/>case, the issue whether the termination of the contract was valid or <lb/>not is a finding of fact. If it is a finding of fact, the challenge to the <lb/>findings on the termination being valid is not maintainable under <lb/>section 34 as the Arbitral Tribunal is the final Judge of the facts of <lb/>the matter. He submitted that this Court under section 34 does not <lb/>sit in appeal over the findings given by the Arbitral Tribunal. He <lb/>submitted that the Concession Agreement was terminated by two <lb/>separate termination notices, both dated 19 th March, 2013. One was <lb/>for termination on the ground of Political Force Majeure (under <lb/>clause 29.8) and the other was for defaults committed by MSRDC <lb/>(under clause 32.4). Mr. Khambatta submitted that the termination <lb/>notice issued pursuant to clause 32.4 of the Concession Agreement <lb/>was on account of defaults committed by MSRDC in failing to pay the <lb/>admitted claims of the petitioner, including the &apos;additional direct <lb/>cost&apos; incurred by PLUS due to the lapses of MSRDC. Mr. Khambatta <lb/>brought to my attention paragraph 70 of the Award wherein the <lb/>Tribunal clearly observed that the terms of the Agreement leave no <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 61 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>doubt that it was MSRDC&apos;s obligation to make the Project site <lb/>available and MSRDC defaulted on this obligation. Thus, MSRDC <lb/>was in breach of its obligations under clause 4.1(b) as well as <lb/>clauses 10.1(i), 10.1(ii) and 10.1(iii). The Tribunal, therefore, held <lb/>that there does exist a valid basis for termination, both under clause <lb/>32.4.1(1) and 32.4.1(3). Mr. Khambatta also brought to my <lb/>attention that the Tribunal has also observed in paragraph 70 of the <lb/>Award that there were enough documents on record wherein the IC <lb/>and MSRDC have acknowledged that MSRDC was responsible for <lb/>making the Project site available. In fact, MSRDC itself admitted <lb/>that PLUS was entitled to extension both on account of delayed <lb/>acquisition of land as well as for the delay in the construction of the <lb/>Railway Over Bridge (ROB). Even as far as the 90 day notice period <lb/>is concerned, Mr. Khambatta submitted that the Tribunal correctly <lb/>held in paragraph 70 that the requirements under clause 32.4 of the <lb/>Concession Agreement for a 90 day notice was complied with by <lb/>PLUS since it had held out the prospect of termination long before it <lb/>was terminated and had refrained from issuing a formal notice due <lb/>to MSRDC&apos;s assurance that the issue would be sorted out. This being <lb/>the case, Mr. Khambatta submitted that if one goes through the <lb/>Award on the issue of termination under clause 32.4, it is clear that <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 62 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>the Tribunal has taken everything into consideration and has <lb/>thereafter come to its finding that the termination is valid under the <lb/>said clause. He submitted that the finding of the Tribunal on this <lb/>aspect can certainly not be termed as either patently illegal or <lb/>perverse and is certainly a plausible view. If this be the case, then, <lb/>there is no question of interfering with the impugned Award on this <lb/>count, was the submission. <lb/>49. <lb/>Similarly, Mr. Khambatta submitted that even <lb/>termination under clause 29.8 (for a Political Force Majeure event) <lb/>is legal and valid as held by the Arbitral Tribunal. Mr. Khambatta <lb/>pointed out that paragraphs 61 and 62 of the Interim Award hold <lb/>that the right to collect Toll is an entitlement of PLUS under clause <lb/>6.1 of the Concession Agreement. The refusal to pay Toll by KDMT <lb/>and NMMT Government buses was held as amounting to <lb/>expropriation or taking away the rights of PLUS to collect and retain <lb/>Toll from these buses in accordance with the Toll Notification. He <lb/>submitted that in paragraph 62, the Tribunal held that PLUS took up <lb/>this issue with KDMT and NMMT, and MSRDC was also alerted in <lb/>January, 2010 that these Government buses were not paying Toll. <lb/>Further, it was also observed that an account was kept of the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 63 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>number of Government buses passing through the Toll on a daily <lb/>basis and PLUS, therefore, took all necessary steps to overcome the <lb/>Political Force Majeure event. The Tribunal further held that non-<lb/>payment of Toll by the Government buses seriously impacted the <lb/>amount of revenue that was to be received by PLUS under the Toll <lb/>Notification. <lb/>50. <lb/>Mr. Khambatta submitted that the Government buses of <lb/>KDMT and NMMT were specifically shown in the Project <lb/>Information Memorandum (PIM) and the Concession Agreement as <lb/>a category of vehicles which would have to pay Toll and was not <lb/>listed as exempted vehicles either in the Concession Agreement or <lb/>in the Toll Notification. Accordingly, the bid submitted by PLUS was <lb/>on the basis that these buses would be paying Toll. MSRDC always <lb/>admitted that PLUS had a right to collect Toll as is evident from its <lb/>letter dated 18 th July, 2011 to the Transport Commissioner, KDMT. <lb/>MSRDC also wrote to the Government of Maharashtra asking it to <lb/>ensure that KDMT and NMMT pay the Toll failing which MSRDC <lb/>itself would have to pay the balance Toll. Mr. Khambatta pointed <lb/>out that these letters can never be termed as letters exchanged <lb/>during conciliation proceedings as this was correspondence <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 64 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>addressed to third parties. This was a clear admission on the part of <lb/>MSRDC that KDMT and NMMT were refusing to pay the Toll. This <lb/>non-payment amounts to an expropriation of PLUS rights to collect <lb/>and retain the Toll under clause 6.1 of the agreement. Not only that, <lb/>it was also an obligation of PLUS under clause 9.1(xv) to levy and <lb/>collect Toll from users of the Project Highway as per the rates set <lb/>forth in the Toll Notification and in accordance with the Concession <lb/>Agreement and regulate the traffic on the Project Highway in <lb/>accordance with the applicable laws. Mr. Khambatta, therefore, <lb/>submitted that non-payment of the Toll by these Government buses <lb/>was thus clearly a Political Force Majeure event as it satisfied all the <lb/>ingredients required as per clause 29.1 of the Concession Agreement <lb/>and correctly spelt out by the Tribunal in paragraph 58 of the <lb/>impugned Award. <lb/>51. <lb/>Mr. Khambatta then submitted that the Tribunal has <lb/>correctly held that the termination under clause 29.8 is valid also <lb/>on account of the ban / diversion of heavy and multi axle vehicles <lb/>and which also constituted a Political Force Majeure event. In this <lb/>regard, Mr. Khambatta brought to my attention, paragraph 63 of the <lb/>Interim Award regarding the ban on heavy vehicles by the Police <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 65 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>authorities. The Tribunal held that all the ingredients (as set out in <lb/>paragraph 58 of the Award), for a Political Force Majeure event are <lb/>made out. It was further held that the said statutory traffic <lb/>Notifications passed under section 15 of the Motor Vehicles Act, <lb/>1988 amounted to a change in law in terms of Article 29.4(i). Mr. <lb/>Khambatta submitted that as per the PIM, the Concession <lb/>Agreement and the Toll Notification, heavy vehicles, including two <lb/>axle, three axle and multi axle vehicles were shown as a category of <lb/>vehicles which would use the Project Highway and pay Toll and were <lb/>not in the exempted category. As per clause 10.1(v) of the <lb/>Concession Agreement, it was the duty of MSRDC to ensure that no <lb/>barriers were put on the Highway. However, the Police authorities <lb/>issued a Notification dated 11 th May, 2009, whereby these multi <lb/>axle vehicles were completely banned and heavy vehicles were <lb/>partially banned from the said Project Road. <lb/>These Traffic <lb/>Regulation Notifications were issued by the Maharashtra Police <lb/>which is a limb of the Government of Maharashtra and, therefore, a <lb/>Governmental agency. These Government Notifications, therefore, <lb/>clearly amounted to a change in law. Mr. Khambatta submitted that <lb/>this does not stop here. In fact, MSRDC admits that PLUS has a <lb/>right to collect Toll from heavy and multi axle vehicles. This is <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 66 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>evident from the letter dated 2 nd August, 2010 written by MSRDC to <lb/>the Police authorities asking them to lift the ban on multi axle <lb/>vehicles. Even upon the termination of the Concession Agreement, <lb/>MSRDC began collecting Toll and itself wrote several letters to the <lb/>Chief Secretary, Home Department asking for lifting the traffic ban <lb/>on heavy vehicles. He, therefore, submitted that all this material <lb/>would show that the complete ban imposed on multi axle vehicles <lb/>and a partial ban on heavy vehicles from using the Project Road was <lb/>clearly a Political Force Majeure event which entitled PLUS to <lb/>terminate the Concession Agreement under clause 29.8 thereof. <lb/>52. <lb/>Mr. Khambatta, lastly submitted that if one goes through <lb/>the Award and especially its findings with reference to termination, <lb/>either under clause 29.8 or clause 32.4, it is clear that the findings <lb/>given therein are purely factual in nature and the said findings are <lb/>rendered after examining the record and the evidence led by the <lb/>parties. In such circumstances, it is not for this Court under section <lb/>34 to sit in appeal over those findings. The findings arrived at are <lb/>certainly a view which is a possible view and hence ought not to be <lb/>interfered with under section 34 of the Act. <lb/>Consequently, he <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 67 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>submitted that even this ground raised by the petitioner is of no <lb/>merit and ought to be rejected. <lb/>FINDINGS OF THE COURT: <lb/>53. <lb/>I have heard the learned counsel for the parties at length <lb/>on this issue and have also perused the papers and proceedings in <lb/>the above petition, including the impugned Award. In the impugned <lb/>Award, the Tribunal had framed the following issues/points for <lb/>determination:-<lb/>&quot;(a) the validity of the termination under Clause 29.8 on the <lb/>ground of various force majeure events, as alleged; <lb/>(b) <lb/>The validity of the termination under Clause 32.4 on the <lb/>ground of various acts/ omissions / delays in performance of <lb/>its obligations by MSRDC which had a material adverse <lb/>impact on the Claimant; <lb/>(c) <lb/>The relief to which the Claimant is entitled if either or both of <lb/>the termination notices are upheld as being valid. <lb/>(d) <lb/>The amount to which the Respondent MSRDC is entitled on <lb/>account of Counter Claims filed by it.&quot; <lb/>54. <lb/>Issue (a) was whether the Concession Agreement was <lb/>validly terminated under Clause 29.8 on the ground of various Force <lb/>Majeure Events and issue (b) was whether the termination was <lb/>valid under Clause 32.4 on the ground of various acts/ omissions / <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 68 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>delays in performance of its obligations by MSRDC which had a <lb/>material adverse impact on PLUS. The Tribunal noted that although <lb/>the issues (a) and (b) have been framed separately, it would in fact <lb/>be sufficient if PLUS were in a position to justify the termination <lb/>either under clause 29.8 or 32.4. This is for the simple reason that <lb/>the Concession Agreement could be terminated only once. <lb/>Therefore, termination could be held to be valid either under clause <lb/>29.8 (the Force Majeure events) or clause 32.4 (material default by <lb/>MSRDC), if the same are made good by PLUS. Further the Tribunal <lb/>held that even within each of these grounds there are several sub-<lb/>grounds, and it would be enough for PLUS to show that any one <lb/>particular Political Force Majeure event existed/occurred as a basis <lb/>for terminating the Concession Agreement, or any one particular <lb/>material default is committed by MSRDC for terminating the said <lb/>Agreement. <lb/>55. <lb/>While discussing the facts of the matter, the Tribunal <lb/>noted that PLUS&apos; grievances were three-fold: (i) the delays in land <lb/>acquisition as well as in finalization of plans for the Railway Over <lb/>Bridge (for short &quot;ROB&quot;) at Katai which led to an overall delay in the <lb/>construction of the project. This resulted in an &apos;additional direct <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 69 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>cost&apos; being incurred by PLUS; (ii) that traffic police restricted the <lb/>entry of certain heavy vehicles on the Project Highway, thus <lb/>reducing the traffic flow, which in turn led to a reduction in Toll <lb/>received; and (iii) that the municipality buses (namely KDMT and <lb/>NMMT buses) refused to pay Toll that they ought to have paid and <lb/>which also led to a reduction in Toll received by PLUS. The Tribunal <lb/>records that these grievances unfolded at different points in time <lb/>during the execution of the project, and voluminous correspondence <lb/>has been exchanged by the parties and the IC on each of these <lb/>issues, much of which has been placed on record before the Tribunal. <lb/>The Tribunal notes that to some extent, the stand taken by MSRDC <lb/>in these proceedings is at variance with the position adopted by it in <lb/>the contemporaneous correspondence exchanged between the <lb/>parties. Therefore, while the Tribunal found it unnecessary to refer <lb/>to each and every document, it referred to some of the key <lb/>correspondence exchanged between the parties as the project <lb/>progressed. The Tribunal noted that the 18 month period from the <lb/>signing of the Concession Agreement [during which construction <lb/>was expected to be completed], was to end on 24 th February, 2008. <lb/>Immediately prior to this, in a communication dated 22 nd February, <lb/>2008, MSRDC itself acknowledged that 95% of the work was <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 70 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>completed. It further noted that the remaining work was delayed on <lb/>account of land acquisition issues as well as the delay in approval of <lb/>the design of the Katai ROB, by the Railways. The Tribunal, after <lb/>examining the record, noted the correspondence exchanged <lb/>between the parties for completion of the construction due to delays <lb/>in land acquisition as well as the delayed approvals of the design of <lb/>the ROB at Katai. <lb/>In effect, PLUS sought extension of the <lb/>construction period up till 12 th January, 2010. Despite this request, <lb/>PLUS actually completed the work by 23 rd May, 2009 and claims to <lb/>have done so by making a significant capital commitment to bring in <lb/>extra resources. The Tribunal notes that from the correspondence <lb/>referred to, it is clear that (i) there were delays with land <lb/>acquisition as well as with the approval from the Railways with <lb/>regard to the ROB at Katai; (ii) that these delays were on account of <lb/>MSRDC (or, at any rate, not on account of PLUS), and were <lb/>acknowledged by both, the IC and MSRDC at the time; (iii) the <lb/>construction period was extended from time to time, and ultimately <lb/>extended by a period of 674 days up till 29 th December, 2009; (iv) <lb/>PLUS had requested a consequent extension in the concession <lb/>period and the IC had endorsed the request by making a <lb/>recommendation that the concession period be extended; (v) the <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 71 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>ultimate extension granted by MSRDC did not expressly state that <lb/>the concession period had also been extended, but noted that it <lb/>would be determined after taking into account various other factors. <lb/>56. <lb/>Thereafter, the Tribunal also notes that on 11 th May, <lb/>2009, i.e. a week before PLUS was to complete the actual <lb/>construction of the project, the Police Commissioner (Thane) issued <lb/>a Traffic Regulation Notification banning the entry of heavy <lb/>commercial vehicles in Kalyan city. Though PLUS does not appear <lb/>to have protested immediately, it wrote to MSRDC on 18 th <lb/>September, 2009 protesting the traffic restriction and cited clauses <lb/>10.1(v) and (vii) of the Concession Agreement to contend that <lb/>MSRDC had an obligation to ensure that no barrier was erected to <lb/>the collection of Toll. It, therefore, requested MSRDC to take this up <lb/>with the police authorities so that an amicable resolution could be <lb/>found. Despite this protest, on 29 th December, 2009, another <lb/>Notification came to be issued by the Police Commissioner (Thane) <lb/>banning/restricting the entry of certain other categories of vehicles <lb/>on the Project Highway. On 25 th February, 2010, PLUS wrote to the <lb/>Police Department, with a copy marked to MSRDC, requesting that <lb/>the traffic restrictions be lifted and the same be re-diverted onto the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 72 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>Project Highway. The Tribunal notes that there is extensive <lb/>correspondence exchanged between PLUS, MSRDC, the IC and also <lb/>the Police Department on the losses being suffered by PLUS on <lb/>account of the traffic restrictions and it, therefore, states that apart <lb/>from the &apos;additional direct cost&apos; claim, the traffic restrictions <lb/>leading to a loss in Toll collection, constituted an independent basis <lb/>for a claim by PLUS. Similar is the case with reference to non-<lb/>payment of Toll by the Municipal buses. The Tribunal notes that on <lb/>23 rd January, 2010, PLUS wrote to MSRDC alerting them that <lb/>KDMT buses were using the Project Highway, but refusing to pay <lb/>Toll. As a result, PLUS had incurred losses for which it sought <lb/>compensation. <lb/>It also requested MSRDC to issue necessary <lb/>instructions to KDMC for their buses to pay the Toll. A week later, <lb/>on 30 th January, 2010, PLUS issued a similar letter to MSRDC about <lb/>non-payment of Toll by NMMT buses. The Tribunal notes that <lb/>despite these grievances being pointed out by PLUS, this stalemate <lb/>continued and these buses continued to use the Project Highway, but <lb/>did not pay the Toll. PLUS maintained that restraining/stopping <lb/>these buses would have led to a law and order situation, given the <lb/>voluminous number of trips made by such buses and the fact that <lb/>they were transporting ordinary citizens. Thus, the only option for <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 73 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>PLUS was to maintain a record/details of the trips done by such <lb/>buses on a daily basis, and compute and maintain the amount of the <lb/>forsaken Toll, which was informed to MSRDC at regular intervals. <lb/>The amount of loss naturally kept increasing as the period of such <lb/>non-payment of Toll was continuing. The Tribunal notes that there <lb/>is correspondence to suggest that MSRDC agreed with the position <lb/>that these buses ought to pay Toll, and has even stated as such to <lb/>the concerned Municipal Commissioner (Transport), on certain <lb/>occasions. However, MSRDC was unable to resolve the deadlock and <lb/>impress upon KDMT and NMMT to have their buses pay the <lb/>requisite Toll. The Tribunal notes that from November 2011 to early <lb/>2013, the parties exchanged correspondence without the matter <lb/>progressing any further. During this period, PLUS was still able to <lb/>collect and retain Toll on account of the original Toll Notification, <lb/>which subsisted till 28 th April, 2013. However, according to the <lb/>Tribunal, it was quite clear that as the expiry of that Notification <lb/>drew near, PLUS was increasingly anxious about the finalization of <lb/>the settlement terms and the consequent extension in the Toll <lb/>Notification. On 4 th February, 2013, PLUS wrote to MSRDC again <lb/>pointing out that it retains the right to terminate the Agreement. <lb/>On 8 th February, 2013, MSRDC writes to PLUS dissuading it from <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 74 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>terminating and assuring it that the rights accrued to it under the <lb/>amicable settlement remain unaffected and the matter is <lb/>progressing. <lb/>Quite evidently, these words of comfort were <lb/>insufficient to assuage PLUS and with the matter having dragged on <lb/>for more than a year, PLUS finally issued two termination notices, <lb/>both dated 19 th March, 2013. One was issued under Clause 29.8 and <lb/>the other under Clause 32.4 of the Concession Agreement. <lb/>57. <lb/>After examining both the termination notices as well as <lb/>the correspondence exchanged between the parties, the Tribunal in <lb/>paragraph 53 set out certain basic features that appear from the <lb/>facts and circumstances narrated in the impugned Award. They <lb/>were:-<lb/>(i) <lb/>Despite repeatedly pointing to the economic un-<lb/>viability of the project and holding out threats of <lb/>termination, it was clear that PLUS was in fact <lb/>anxious to carry on with the project. Perhaps it <lb/>hoped that the project would turn profitable if <lb/>MSRDC acceded to its demands, or perhaps it <lb/>looked upon this project as a launching pad for <lb/>further such projects in this country. Whatever be <lb/>the reason, PLUS did its very best to accommodate <lb/>so that the issues could somehow be resolved, until <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 75 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>the matters reached an absolute breaking point <lb/>when it was constrained to terminate the <lb/>Agreement; <lb/>(ii) MSRDC and the IC consistently acknowledged that <lb/>there was substance in the grievances being raised <lb/>by PLUS at different points in time under different <lb/>heads, and yet, even while acknowledging this, <lb/>MSRDC stopped short of committing itself to any <lb/>position, and resorted to the easier course of <lb/>referring matters to the Government of <lb/>Maharashtra; and <lb/>(iii) The Government of Maharashtra, for its part, <lb/>adopted a somewhat casual approach in simply <lb/>sitting idle even though various issues of pressing <lb/>importance to the project had been referred to it by <lb/>MSRDC. While MSRDC had referred the matters to <lb/>the Government of Maharashtra, the Government <lb/>of Maharashtra failed to take any decision at all. <lb/>58. <lb/>It is in this background that the Tribunal framed the <lb/>four issues referred to earlier. <lb/>59. <lb/>Turning to the termination on the ground of Political <lb/>Force Majeure (clause 29.8), the Tribunal discussed the same from <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 76 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>paragraphs 58 to 64 of the impugned Award. The Tribunal notes <lb/>that there are five key ingredients that must exist for there to be a <lb/>finding that a Force Majeure event exists. These ingredients are:-<lb/>(a) the existence of an event, namely, a non-political <lb/>event or an indirect political event or a political <lb/>event as defined in the Concession Agreement. <lb/>Since, in the present case, the allegation is that <lb/>there was a political event, it may be noticed that <lb/>clause 29.4, in turn, identifies three categories of <lb/>political events. Briefly, they are (i) change in law; <lb/>(ii) expropriation by any governmental agency of <lb/>any project assets or rights of the Concessionaire <lb/>(PLUS); or (iii) unjustified refusal to grant or renew <lb/>any consent or approval required by the <lb/>Concessionaire (PLUS); <lb/>(b) the event must frustrate the performance of <lb/>obligations, namely, those events must be such that <lb/>they prevent the party claiming the Force Majeure <lb/>Event from performing its obligations under the <lb/>Agreement; <lb/>(c) that the event was beyond the control of the party <lb/>claiming the Force Majeure and not arising on <lb/>account of its own fault; <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 77 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>(d) duty to mitigate, namely, the party claiming Force <lb/>Majeure has an obligation to attempt to overcome <lb/>the event by exercising due diligence and <lb/>reasonable efforts, skill and care, including the <lb/>expenditure of reasonable sums of money; and <lb/>(e) the event must have a material adverse impact on <lb/>the project. <lb/>60. <lb/>The Tribunal also noted that once a Force Majeure Event <lb/>is found to exist, the effect of that Force Majeure Event depends on <lb/>the stage at which such event occurs. In cases where the event <lb/>occurs after the Commercial Operations Date (COD) under the <lb/>Concession Agreement, the effect is provided in Clause 29.6 (c). <lb/>However, in certain cases, if the Force Majeure Event subsists for a <lb/>period of more than 180 days within a continuous period of 365 <lb/>days, it furnishes a right to either party to terminate the Agreement <lb/>with a notice period of thirty days. <lb/>61. <lb/>In this background, the Tribunal thereafter went on to <lb/>examine the Force Majeure Events. The first Force Majeure Event <lb/>alleged by PLUS was that the parties had reached a settlement on <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 78 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>account of exchange of letters dated 20 th October, 2011 and 4 th <lb/>November, 2011 and by virtue of such settlement, a Toll Notification <lb/>was to be issued for the extended concession period. The non-<lb/>issuance of such Toll Notification was claimed as a Political Force <lb/>Majeure Event. This Force Majeure Event was negated by the <lb/>Tribunal as can be seen from paragraph 60 of the impugned Award. <lb/>62. <lb/>Thereafter, the second Force Majeure Event canvassed <lb/>by PLUS was the non-payment of Toll by the NMMT and KDMT <lb/>buses, which is alleged to be an expropriation of the rights of the <lb/>Concessionaire (PLUS), and therefore, a Political Force Majeure <lb/>Event. In this regard, the Tribunal held that the right to collect Toll <lb/>is an entitlement of PLUS under Clause 6.1 of the Concession <lb/>Agreement. The concerned Municipal undertakings are undeniably <lb/>Government agencies within the meaning of clause 29.4 (ii) of the <lb/>Concession Agreement. The refusal to pay Toll by the buses owned <lb/>by these undertakings is an expropriation of the rights of the <lb/>Concessionaire (PLUS), and specifically the right to collect and <lb/>retain Toll in accordance with the Toll Notification. The Tribunal, <lb/>therefore, found that this did constitute a Political Force Majeure <lb/>Event within the meaning of Clause 29.4. The Tribunal thereafter <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 79 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>went on to examine whether the other elements necessary for <lb/>constituting a Force Majeure Event are also made out. In paragraph <lb/>62, the Tribunal examined the other elements. The Tribunal held <lb/>that MSRDC (in its Written Submissions: Part VI) has relied upon <lb/>the cross-examination transcript to contend that it is an admitted <lb/>position that PLUS was not prevented from performing its <lb/>obligations under the Concession Agreement. The Tribunal further <lb/>found that the reliance on an isolated statement in response to one <lb/>question put in cross-examination may not be conclusive on <lb/>whether, in fact, PLUS was prevented from performing its <lb/>obligations. Moreover, regard must be had to the terms of the <lb/>Concession Agreement (which specify the obligations of each party) <lb/>and also to the entirety of the documentary evidence on record, to <lb/>ascertain whether in fact PLUS was prevented in the performance of <lb/>its obligations. The Tribunal further held that the collection and <lb/>retention of Toll is not just an entitlement, but also an obligation of <lb/>PLUS in terms of clause 9.1(xv) of the Concession Agreement. The <lb/>performance of this obligation was directly interfered with by the <lb/>actions of NMMT and KDMT buses and, therefore, the Political <lb/>Event did prevent PLUS from performing its obligations. It further <lb/>held that this was entirely beyond the control of PLUS and certainly <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 80 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>not on account of any fault of PLUS. The Tribunal thereafter opined <lb/>that the position with respect to duty to mitigate is more finely <lb/>balanced. The Tribunal held that it is reasonable to contend, as <lb/>MSRDC has done, that the Toll Notification statutorily authorized <lb/>PLUS to collect Toll from all vehicles other than those specifically <lb/>exempted, and it was for PLUS to exercise legal remedies to enforce <lb/>its rights under the Toll Notification. At the same time, it must be <lb/>borne in mind that Municipal buses account for a large part of the <lb/>traffic on the Project Highway, and such buses make several trips in <lb/>a day, ferrying different passengers, some of whom may have no <lb/>other mode of transport. Preventing the passage of these vehicles <lb/>would, in the circumstances, have created a law and order situation <lb/>and PLUS cannot be faulted for not carrying these matters ahead. <lb/>PLUS has also pointed out that stopping the Municipal buses would <lb/>have jammed the entire Toll plaza, and led to PLUS being in breach <lb/>of its obligations under the Concession Agreement. The Tribunal <lb/>also held that it is not as if PLUS was idle or slept over its rights or <lb/>failed entirely to press its legitimate claims. The matter was taken <lb/>up with the concerned Municipal Authorities, and MSRDC was also <lb/>alerted as early as January 2010 that NMMT and KDMT buses were <lb/>not paying Toll, even though they were required to do so in terms of <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 81 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>the Notification. Further, this issue was raised repeatedly, and an <lb/>account was kept of the number of such vehicles passing the Toll <lb/>collection point on a daily basis. This data was made available to <lb/>MSRDC at regular intervals (as well as to the Municipal <lb/>Authorities), and MSRDC by and large appeared to have accepted <lb/>the claim of PLUS and even took up the matter with the concerned <lb/>Municipal Commissioners. The Tribunal, therefore, held that PLUS <lb/>made several efforts to prevail upon the concerned Municipal <lb/>undertakings to issue necessary directions for the Municipal buses <lb/>to pay the Toll. In these circumstances, the Tribunal was of the view <lb/>that PLUS had exercised necessary due diligence and precipitating <lb/>the matters any further could have had serious law and order <lb/>repercussions, as well as an impact on traffic regulation at the Toll <lb/>Plaza. The Tribunal, therefore, came to a finding that the steps <lb/>necessary in the circumstances to overcome the Force Majeure <lb/>Event were duly taken by PLUS. Finally, even the loss of revenue to <lb/>PLUS from non-payment of Toll by so many vehicles making so <lb/>many trips over so many months, clearly amounted to a material <lb/>adverse effect on the project. The Tribunal held that there is ample <lb/>correspondence to show that the failure to collect Toll contributed to <lb/>the cash flow issues faced by PLUS, which had an impact on loan <lb/></body>

			<front>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></front>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 82 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>servicing as well as operational expenses. The Tribunal, therefore, <lb/>was of the view that there was a material adverse effect on the <lb/>project. Accordingly, the non-payment of Toll by the Municipal buses <lb/>was a Force Majeure event within the meaning of Clause 29.1 of the <lb/>Concession Agreement. Since the said event subsisted for more <lb/>than 180 days within a continuous period of 365 days (it <lb/>commenced on 22 nd August, 2009, from which date the Toll <lb/>collection commenced, and continued up till the termination date <lb/>and beyond), it did give rise to a right to terminate the Concession <lb/>Agreement under Clause 29.8. The Tribunal, therefore, held that <lb/>the termination notice was valid on this ground. <lb/>63. <lb/>The third Force Majeure Event which was alleged by <lb/>PLUS was the traffic regulation banning the entry of heavy vehicles <lb/>during certain specified hours. It was the case of PLUS that this <lb/>amounted to a change in law, or alternatively expropriation of its <lb/>rights, and therefore, a Political Force Majeure Event occurred. In <lb/>response to this, MSRDC contended that the ban on heavy vehicles <lb/>pre-dated the Agreement, and PLUS was aware of this fact, or at any <lb/>rate, ought to have been aware. MSRDC relied on a Resolution of the <lb/>Municipal Corporation, which notes that &quot;heavy vehicles are allowed <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 83 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>to run on this road from 10 p.m. to 6 a.m. and it should not be <lb/>changed.&quot; The Tribunal found that this resolution was not a public <lb/>document and PLUS, therefore, cannot be expected to be aware of it. <lb/>Further, even if the said decision was communicated to MSRDC, it <lb/>was for MSRDC to refer to it in the Project Information <lb/>Memorandum (PIM). <lb/>The PIM, however, contained no such <lb/>reference and bids were invited on the basis that heavy commercial <lb/>vehicles would be part of the traffic flow which determines the <lb/>revenue base of PLUS. The Tribunal thereafter held that in any <lb/>event PLUS is correct to point out that (i) the restrictions that were <lb/>imposed in May 2009 went further and beyond the resolution to <lb/>impose a total ban on entry of certain categories of vehicles; and (ii) <lb/>the Notifications were statutory Notifications issued under the <lb/>Motor Vehicles Act, 1988 and it was only with the issuance of such <lb/>Notifications that a ban/restriction operationally came into effect. <lb/>The Tribunal noted that it is not even MSRDC&apos;s contention that prior <lb/>to this, there was any such Notification issued under the Motor <lb/>Vehicles Act, 1988. The Tribunal, therefore, was of the view that <lb/>this amounted to a change in law and in the alternative would, in <lb/>any event, amount to an expropriation of the rights of PLUS as the <lb/>project bid had been made on the basis of certain traffic projections. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 84 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>The ban/restrictions that were imposed on various categories of <lb/>vehicles had a drastic effect on those projections, as it severely <lb/>curtailed the heavy vehicular traffic on the said road. Thus, the <lb/>Tribunal was of the view that there was a Political Force Majeure <lb/>Event. The Tribunal held that all other ingredients of the Force <lb/>Majeure Event were also made out. It noted that PLUS was <lb/>prevented from performing its obligations (collecting Toll) under the <lb/>agreement. It was also prevented for reasons beyond its control and <lb/>not on account of its own fault. PLUS did exercise the necessary due <lb/>diligence to overcome this event by taking up the issue with the <lb/>police authorities as well as with MSRDC and undoubtedly the event <lb/>had a material adverse effect on the project, as the amount of <lb/>uncollected Toll was allegedly in excess of Rs.60 Crores. Further, <lb/>the event subsisted for the requisite period as specified under Clause <lb/>29.8 of the agreement, and therefore, PLUS was justified in <lb/>terminating the Agreement. The Tribunal, therefore, held that the <lb/>termination on this ground was valid. In conclusion, the Tribunal <lb/>held that as far as the termination on account of Force Majeure is <lb/>concerned, the validity of the said termination is upheld to the <lb/>extent it was occasioned by non-payment of Toll by Municipal buses <lb/>and the traffic restrictions on heavy vehicular traffic. The Tribunal <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 85 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>also noted that the termination on the ground of non-issuance of the <lb/>Toll Notification for the extended period pursuant to an alleged <lb/>settlement/ agreement between the parties, stood rejected. <lb/>64. <lb/>Looking at the facts adverted to by the Tribunal (set out <lb/>above) and its findings in relation thereto, I find that the Tribunal <lb/>has carefully examined all the facts, including the correspondence <lb/>between the parties and thereafter come to its conclusion. I am in <lb/>full agreement with Mr. Khambatta that all these findings are really <lb/>findings of facts. Clause 6.1 of the Concession Agreement clearly <lb/>stipulates that the right to claim Toll is an entitlement of PLUS. <lb/>Refusal to pay Toll by KDMT and NMMT buses was held as <lb/>amounting to expropriation or taking away the rights of PLUS to <lb/>collect Toll from these buses in accordance with the Toll <lb/>Notification. It is not as if PLUS sat idle and did nothing. This issue <lb/>was specifically taken up by PLUS with KDMT &amp; NMMT, and MSRDC <lb/>was also alerted of the same. In fact, PLUS also kept an account of all <lb/>these buses passing through the Toll Plaza without paying Toll and <lb/>which was regularly submitted to MSRDC. It can therefore hardly <lb/>be contended that in such a scenario the same did not have a <lb/>material adverse effect on the project. Merely because the exact loss <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 86 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>wasn&apos;t quantified would make little difference. The fact that these <lb/>buses (and which were large in number) were to pay Toll and which <lb/>they refused to do, would clearly indicate that there was a material <lb/>adverse effect on the project. Further, these Government buses were <lb/>specifically shown in the PIM and the Concession Agreement as <lb/>category of vehicles which would pay Toll and were not listed as <lb/>exempted vehicles. In fact, by its letter dated 18 th July, 2011, <lb/>MSRDC informed the Transport Commissioner of KDMT that PLUS <lb/>had the right to collect Toll under the Concession Agreement. <lb/>MSRDC also wrote to the Government of Maharashtra asking it to <lb/>ensure that KDMT and NMMT buses pay the Toll, failing which <lb/>MSRDC itself would have to pay the balance Toll. This is a clear <lb/>admission on the part of MSRDC that KDMT and NMMT were <lb/>refusing to pay Toll. Even if I was to assume for the sake of argument <lb/>that certain correspondence between MSRDC and PLUS forming the <lb/>subject matter of the Arbitration are inadmissible (and which I have <lb/>rejected earlier), the letters written by MSRDC to the Transport <lb/>Commissioner of KDMT and to the Government of Maharashtra is <lb/>correspondence addressed to third parties, and therefore, can never <lb/>amount to correspondence entered into between MSRDC and PLUS <lb/>during conciliation proceedings. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 87 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>65. <lb/>Even the Notifications issued under the Motor Vehicles <lb/>Act, 1988 banning of heavy vehicles, MSRDC admits that PLUS has <lb/>a right to collect Toll from heavy and multi axle vehicles. This is <lb/>evident from the letter dated 2 nd August, 2010 written by MSRDC to <lb/>the Police authorities asking them to lift the ban on multi axle <lb/>vehicles. Even upon the termination of the Concession Agreement, <lb/>MSRDC began collecting Toll and itself wrote several letters to the <lb/>Chief Secretary, Home Department asking for lifting the traffic ban <lb/>on heavy vehicles. When one looks at the findings given by the <lb/>Tribunal, I find that the Tribunal has given appropriate and cogent <lb/>reasons for upholding the termination of the Concession Agreement <lb/>under Clause 29.8 thereof. The Tribunal has considered the <lb/>relevant documents and the evidence on record, the arguments <lb/>canvassed by the parties and thereafter come to its conclusion. Not <lb/>only do I find that the said conclusion is correct, but even otherwise <lb/>it is certainly a plausible conclusion. The Tribunal has considered <lb/>everything on record and thereafter held that the Concession <lb/>Agreement is validly terminated due to Force Majeure Events. I do <lb/>not find anything patently illegal or perverse in the said findings so <lb/>as to interfere with the same under Section 34 of the Act. I am <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 88 of 169 <lb/>unable to agree with the submissions of Mr. Chagla that the findings <lb/>in the impugned Award on this issue are either contradictory or <lb/>ignores any vital evidence. The Tribunal has considered all the <lb/>evidence, including the so called admission made by the witness of <lb/>PLUS. What weightage is to be given to the evidence is left entirely <lb/>upto the Tribunal and this Court is not supposed to sit in appeal and <lb/>re-examine and re-appreciate the evidence. The Tribunal, after <lb/>noting the admission, held that one isolated statement cannot form <lb/>a basis of their finding. The entirety of the documents on record has <lb/>to be looked into, as well as the evidence, to ascertain whether in <lb/>fact PLUS was prevented in performance of its obligations. I do not <lb/>find that the approach of the Tribunal in this regard can be faulted. <lb/>As mentioned earlier, I find that the impugned Award on this issue <lb/>has given appropriate and cogent reasoning which requires no <lb/>interference. In these circumstances, in so far as the Tribunal holds <lb/>that the Concession Agreement was validly terminated under clause <lb/>29.8 (due to Force Majeure Events) requires no interference by this <lb/>Court. <lb/>66. <lb/>Apart from upholding the termination of the Concession <lb/>Agreement due to Force Majeure Events, the Tribunal also held that <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 89 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>the said Agreement was validly terminated under Clause 32.4 on <lb/>account of material defaults by MSRDC. The discussion and the <lb/>findings with reference to termination under Clause 32.4 can be <lb/>found from paragraphs 65 to 70 of the impugned Award. In <lb/>paragraph 65, the Tribunal held that the termination notice refers <lb/>to a letter dated 10 th May, 2010 and the letters issued earlier to it, <lb/>which are stated to be relied upon by PLUS. However, the letters do <lb/>not actually refer to six claims, but rather only to the claim for <lb/>&apos;additional direct cost&apos;. This claim was forwarded by letter dated <lb/>24 th February, 2010 wherein PLUS claimed an amount of Rs.161 <lb/>Crores as the escalated project cost on account of material default <lb/>by MSRDC. Subsequently, this claim was pursued by further letters <lb/>and finally by means of the letter dated 10 th May, 2010 PLUS <lb/>proposed conciliation. Thus, the offer for conciliation was in relation <lb/>to the claim of the &apos;additional direct cost&apos; and not the other claims. <lb/>The Tribunal noted that it is true that other claims had also been <lb/>raised by that time and those were by means of separate letters and <lb/>were separately pursued. It is only much later that the IC, by its <lb/>communication dated 2 nd August, 2011, clubbed various claims <lb/>under six heads and which I have adverted to earlier. The Tribunal <lb/>therefore, proceeded to examine whether any defaults by MSRDC <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 90 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>furnished a valid basis for terminating the Concession Agreement <lb/>under clause 32.4. The Tribunal noted that the principal claim with <lb/>respect to material default is the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos;. <lb/>This claim has been clubbed with the claim of project costs together <lb/>with escalated project costs. PLUS contended that this claim arises <lb/>due to default on the part of the MSRDC to complete the land <lb/>acquisition process in a timely manner and also on account of delays <lb/>in getting design approvals from the Railway Authorities in respect <lb/>of the Katai ROB. The discussion on this can be found in paragraph <lb/>70 of the Award which reads thus:-<lb/>&quot;70 The principal claim with respect to material default is the <lb/>claim for direct additional cost. This claim has been clubbed with <lb/>the claim for variation in project work. Together, they resulted in an <lb/>escalation of project cost. Together, they resulted in an escalation <lb/>of project cost. The Claimant&apos;s contention is that the delay resulted <lb/>on account of the failure of the MSRDC to complete the land <lb/>acquisition process in a timely manner, and also on account of <lb/>delays in getting design approvals from the Railway Authorities in <lb/>respect of Katai ROB. As a factual matter, on a review of the <lb/>documentary record, it is very clear that the delays did in fact take <lb/>place, and that these delays were acknowledged both by the IC <lb/>and the MSRDC. Two days before construction was scheduled to <lb/>be completed, in its letter dated 22.2.2008, the MSRDC noted that <lb/>95% of the project work was complete, and the remaining could not <lb/>be completed because of land acquisition issues and delays in <lb/>getting approvals. This was also acknowledged by the IC on <lb/>several occasions. The details of this correspondence have <lb/>already been set out in the factual narration above, and need not <lb/>be repeated. The Claimant put forward a detailed summary of the <lb/>various causes of delay in its communication dated 11.5.2009. This <lb/>ultimately led to the construction period being extended, and a <lb/>consequent extension in the concession period. However, by its <lb/>communication dated 24.2.2010 (Exh. CD 52), the Claimant stated <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 91 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>that the revised project cost was in excess of Rs.280 crore, and <lb/>made a claim for Rs.161.5 crore as direct additional cost (i.e. <lb/>escalation in project cost because of the delays and defaults). It <lb/>stated that it was an acknowledged and documented position that <lb/>the MSRDC had defaulted in its obligations to make the project site <lb/>available free from all encumbrances and to assist in the obtaining <lb/>of all applicable permits. The claim, at that stage, was put forward <lb/>both as a material default claim and as a force majeure claim. The <lb/>Claimant sought compensation under Clause 31.2 and costs for <lb/>subsisting force majeure under Clause 29.7 (c). However, in the <lb/>subsequent termination notices, and in these proceedings, the <lb/>claim for direct additional costs is presented only as a claim based <lb/>on MSRDC&apos;s material default, and not as a force majeure claim. <lb/>We are of the view that the record is replete with acknowledgments <lb/>from IC and MSRDC regarding the delays that took place with <lb/>regard to making available the project site. The record is further <lb/>replete with correspondence from the Claimant pointing out how <lb/>this delay is constraining its cash flow position, and jeopardizing <lb/>operations. The terms of the Agreement leave no doubt that it was <lb/>MSRDC&apos;s obligation to make the project site available, and MSRDC <lb/>defaulted on this obligation. Thus, MSRDC was in breach of its <lb/>obligations under Clause 4.1(b) of the Agreement, as well as <lb/>Clauses 10.1 (i) , 10.1(ii) and 10.1(iii). Accordingly, there does exist <lb/>a valid basis for termination both under Clause 32.4.1(1) and <lb/>Clause 32.4.1(3). Accordingly, the termination for MSRDC default <lb/>is upheld to this extent. We may clarify, here, that the default of <lb/>MSRDC is not the failure to have a toll notification issued in respect <lb/>of the proposed extended concession period. As we have notified <lb/>earlier, there was no final settlement with regard to the extended <lb/>concession period, as it was necessarily subject to approval from <lb/>Government of Maharashtra, which approval was never <lb/>forthcoming. However, the underlying defaults, which provided the <lb/>basis for the direct additional cost claim, remain -and the Claimant <lb/>was entitled to terminate the Agreement on this notice. We may <lb/>further point out that although Clause 32.4 requires 90 days notice <lb/>to be given, and the Claimant provided less than 90 days from its <lb/>notice dated 19.3.2013, the notice period must be viewed in the <lb/>overall context of the entirety of correspondence. The Claimant <lb/>had held out the prospect of termination long before 19.3.2013, and <lb/>had only refrained from issuing a formal notice at the specific <lb/>request of MSRDC, with the assurance that matters would be <lb/>sorted out. MSRDC had much more than the required 90 days <lb/>notice period to actually cure the defaults, if it had so intended. <lb/>Instead, it kept holding out a carrot to the Claimant, and dragging <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 92 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>matters perilously close to the expiry of the period covered by the <lb/>toll notification. In these circumstances, in our view, the notice <lb/>period must be held to have been complied with.&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>67. <lb/>As can be seen from the paragraph reproduced above, <lb/>the Tribunal opined that the record before the Tribunal was replete <lb/>with acknowledgments from the IC and MSRDC regarding the delays <lb/>that took place with regard to making available the project site. The <lb/>record is replete with further correspondence from PLUS pointing <lb/>out how this delay is constraining its cash flow position and <lb/>jeopardizing operations. The Tribunal further held that the terms of <lb/>the Agreement leave no doubt that it was MSRDC&apos;s obligation to <lb/>make the project site available, and MSRDC defaulted on this <lb/>obligation. MSRDC was, therefore, in breach of its obligations under <lb/>Clause 4.1(d) as well as Clauses 10.1(i), 10.1(ii) and 10.1(iii). The <lb/>Tribunal, therefore, came to a finding that there exists a valid basis <lb/>for termination, both under clauses 32.4.1(1) and Clause 32.4.1(3). <lb/>68. <lb/>Before I examine this aspect, it would be apposite to set <lb/>out clause 32.4.1 which reads thus:-<lb/>&quot;32.4 Termination for MSRDC Event of Default. <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 93 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>32.4.1 The Concessionaire may after giving 90 <lb/>(ninety) days notice in writing to MSRDC <lb/>terminate this Agreement upon the occurrence <lb/>and continuation of any of the following events <lb/>(each a MSRDC Event of Default) unless any <lb/>such MSRDC Event of Default has occurred <lb/>as a result of Concessionaire Event of Default <lb/>or due to Force Majeure Event. <lb/>(1) <lb/>MSRDC is in breach of this Agreement <lb/>and such breach has a Material <lb/>Adverse Effect on the Concessionaire <lb/>and MSRDC has failed to cure such <lb/>breach or take effective steps for curing <lb/>such breach within 90 (ninety) days of <lb/>receipt of notice in this behalf from the <lb/>Concessionaire; <lb/>(2) <lb/>MSRDC repudiates this Agreement or <lb/>otherwise evidences an irrevocable <lb/>intention not to be bound by this <lb/>Agreement; <lb/>(3) <lb/>MSRDC or GOM or any Government <lb/>Agency have by an act of commission <lb/>or omission created circumstances that <lb/>have a Material Adverse Effect on the <lb/>performance of its obligations by the <lb/>Concessionaire and have failed to cure <lb/>the same within 90 (ninety) days of <lb/>receipt of notice by MSRDC in this <lb/>behalf from the Concessionaire; <lb/>(4) <lb/>MSRDC has delayed any payment that <lb/>has fallen due under this Agreement if <lb/>such delay exceeds 90 (ninety) days.&quot; <lb/>69. <lb/>Clause 32.4.1 entitles PLUS to terminate the Concession <lb/>Agreement on the occurrence of any of the events listed in the said <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 94 of 169 <lb/>clause and described as MSRDC&apos;s event of default, by giving a 90 <lb/>day notice in writing to MSRDC. In the event MSRDC&apos;s event of <lb/>default has occurred because of PLUS&apos; default or due to Force <lb/>Majeure events, then PLUS would not be entitled to terminate <lb/>Concession Agreement under the said clause. Clause 32.4.1(1) <lb/>stipulates that PLUS is entitled to terminate if MSRDC is in breach of <lb/>the Concession Agreement and such breach has a material adverse <lb/>effect on PLUS and MSRDC has failed to cure such breach or take <lb/>effective steps for curing the same within 90 days of receipt of a <lb/>notice in that behalf from PLUS. Similarly, clause 32.4.1(3) <lb/>stipulates that if MSRDC or the Government of Maharashtra or any <lb/>Government Agency have, by an act of commission or omission <lb/>created circumstances that had a material adverse effect on the <lb/>performance of the obligations of PLUS and have failed to cure the <lb/>same within 90 days of receipt of a notice issued by PLUS to MSRDC, <lb/>PLUS would be entitled to terminate the Agreement. On a conjoint <lb/>reading of clauses 32.4.1(1) and 32.4.1(3), it is clear that the <lb/>following conditions need to be fulfilled: (i) that there is an event of <lb/>default by MSRDC; (ii) The said default should have a material <lb/>adverse effect on PLUS; (iii) PLUS must give a 90 day notice in <lb/>writing to MSRDC to terminate the Concession Agreement; and (iv) <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 95 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>MSRDC fails to cure the said default / breach or take effective steps <lb/>for curing the same within 90 days of receipt of such notice. <lb/>70. <lb/>In the present case, it is not in dispute that the 90 day <lb/>notice (as contemplated in clause 32.4.1) was not given by PLUS to <lb/>MSRDC. It is specifically recorded by the Tribunal in paragraph 70 <lb/>of the Award, that although clause 32.4 requires a 90 day notice to <lb/>be given, and PLUS provided less than 90 days from its notice dated <lb/>19 th March, 2013, the notice period must be viewed in the overall <lb/>context. The Tribunal held that PLUS had held out the prospect of <lb/>termination long before 19 th March, 2013 and it also refrained from <lb/>issuing a formal notice at the specific request of MSRDC, with the <lb/>assurance that matters would be sorted out. The Tribunal held that <lb/>MSRDC had much more than the required 90 day notice period to <lb/>actually cure the defaults, if it had so intended. Instead, it kept <lb/>holding out a carrot to PLUS and dragging matters perilously close <lb/>to the expiry of the period covered by the Toll Notification. It is in <lb/>these circumstances that the Tribunal held that the notice period <lb/>must be held to have been complied with. <lb/>71. <lb/>I am unable to understand how the Tribunal has come to <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 96 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>this finding. The termination notice dated 19 th March, 2013 reads <lb/>as under:-<lb/>&quot;PLUS <lb/>PLUS BKSP Toll Limited <lb/>March 19, 2013. <lb/>The Vice Chairman &amp; Managing Director <lb/>Maharashtra State Road Development Corporation <lb/>Limited <lb/>Near Priyadarshini Park, <lb/>Nepean Sea Road, <lb/>Mumbai 400 036 -India. <lb/>Sub:-TERMINATION NOTICE UNDER CLAUSE 32.4 OF <lb/>THE CONCESSION AGREEMENT DATED AUGUST 25, <lb/>2006 (&quot;CONCESSION AGREEMENT&quot;) ENTERED INTO <lb/>BETWEEN MAHARASHTRA STATE ROAD <lb/>DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION LIMITED (&quot;MSRDC&quot;) <lb/>AND PLUS BKSP TOLL LIMITED (&quot;PLUS BKSP&quot;) <lb/>Dear Sir, <lb/>1. <lb/>With reference to the Concession Agreement, <lb/>PLUS BKSP had, vide a letter dated May 10, <lb/>2010 and earlier letters, raised 6 claims on <lb/>MSRDC which related to losses incurred by <lb/>PLUS BKSP due to acts/ omissions/ delays in <lb/>performance of obligations under the Concession <lb/>Agreement by MSRDC. <lb/>2. <lb/>MSRDC subsequently made an offer of an <lb/>amicable settlement to PLUS BKSP vide its letter <lb/>dated October 20, 2011 (&quot;Offer Letter&quot;). In the <lb/>said Offer Letter, MSRDC offered an extension of <lb/>the Concession Period until July 10, 2024 in lieu <lb/>of cash payments for compensating PLUS BKSP. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 97 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>3. <lb/>In the spirit of resolving the matter, PLUS BKSP <lb/>has accepted MSRDC&apos;s offer; PLUS BKSP&apos;s <lb/>acceptance is contained in its letter dated <lb/>November 4, 2011 (&quot;Acceptance Letter&quot;). With the <lb/>acceptance of MSRDC&apos;s offer, PLUS BKSP was <lb/>hopeful that MSRDC will be able to expedite the <lb/>issuance of toll notification until the proposed <lb/>extended term of the Concession Agreement i.e. <lb/>July 10, 2024 (&quot;Toll Notification&quot;). <lb/>4. <lb/>We note that unfortunately till date MSRDC has <lb/>not been able to cause issuance of the Toll <lb/>Notification while the present toll notification is <lb/>due to end on April 28, 2013, which is fast <lb/>approaching. <lb/>5. <lb/>Hence, we are hereby issuing this notice under <lb/>Clause 32.4 of Concession Agreement. The <lb/>breaches/ acts/ omissions by MSRDC under the <lb/>Concession Agreement have caused a Material <lb/>Adverse Effect on PLUS BKSP and thus, making <lb/>PLUS BKSP entitled to compensation under <lb/>Clause 31.2 and to exercise its right of <lb/>termination under Clause 32.4. <lb/>6. <lb/>PLUS BKSP previously refrained to terminate the <lb/>concession in response to MSRDC&apos;s request to <lb/>do so in its letter dated Feb 8, 2013. Please note <lb/>that PLUS BKSP will not be able to proceed with <lb/>its operations beyond April 28, 2013 until the <lb/>issuance of the Toll Notification. Therefore, kindly <lb/>issue by April 28, 2013, the extension of the <lb/>concession period and Toll Notification to July 10, <lb/>2024. <lb/>If MSRDC shall fail to do so, the <lb/>Concession Agreement shall terminate on April <lb/>28, 2013 and MSRDC shall be liable to pay us the <lb/>Termination Payment as provided in Clause <lb/>32.4.2 and the settlement of claims as provided in <lb/>Clause 31.2 both with interest until date of <lb/>payment. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 98 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>7. <lb/>Without prejudice to any rights accrued/ available <lb/>to PLUS BKSP under law or otherwise, the <lb/>Parties shall continue to be bound by the clauses <lb/>of the Concession Agreement which survive <lb/>termination, including without limitation, the <lb/>clauses relating to Termination Payment, <lb/>Compensation, <lb/>Divestment <lb/>Requirements, <lb/>release of funds lying in Escrow Account and <lb/>release of Performance Security. <lb/>8. <lb/>For avoidance of doubt, it is hereby clarified that <lb/>the initially capitalized term used herein but not <lb/>defined shall have the same meaning as <lb/>assigned to them in the Concession Agreement. <lb/>Yours faithfully, <lb/>Sd/-<lb/>NOORIZAH HJ. ABD. HAMID <lb/>Chairman.&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>72. <lb/>From the aforesaid termination notice, it is clear that <lb/>the said notice was issued under clause 32.4 of the Concession <lb/>Agreement. Clause 32.4.1 clearly required PLUS to give a 90 day <lb/>notice in writing to MSRDC for terminating the Agreement upon <lb/>occurrence and continuation of any of the events of default as set <lb/>out therein. The 90 day period was to enable MSRDC to cure any <lb/>breach or to take effective steps for curing the same. However, in <lb/>the aforesaid notice, PLUS requests MSRDC to issue, by 28 th April, <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 99 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>2013, the extension of the concession period and the Toll <lb/>Notification upto 10 th July, 2024 failing which the Concession <lb/>Agreement is to stand terminated on 28 th April, 2013. From the <lb/>aforesaid notice it is clear that time was granted to MSRDC to cure <lb/>any defect on its part from 19 th March, 2013 to 28 th April, 2013. <lb/>This is far less than the period of 90 days as stipulated in clause <lb/>32.4.1. On a plain reading of the said notice, I find that the <lb/>submission of Mr. Chagla is well founded when he submits that the <lb/>findings given by the Tribunal that MSRDC had much more than 90 <lb/>days to cure the breaches, is factually incorrect. I must mention that <lb/>the Tribunal whilst coming to the aforesaid finding opined that PLUS <lb/>had held out the prospect of termination long before 19 th March, <lb/>2013 and refrained from issuing a formal notice at the specific <lb/>request of MSRDC. In this regard, the only letter referred to by the <lb/>Tribunal is a letter dated 4 th February, 2013 issued by PLUS to <lb/>MSRDC (paragraph 43 of the impugned Award). By the said letter, <lb/>PLUS informs MSRDC that in the spirit of amicable settlement, PLUS <lb/>desires to draw the attention of MSRDC to the Toll Notification <lb/>which is valid upto 28 th April, 2013 whereas their actual original <lb/>concession period runs upto 3 rd March, 2015. It therefore informs <lb/>MSRDC that despite the present Toll Notification expiring less than <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 100 of 169 <lb/>90 days from the date of the said letter, PLUS&apos; right to serve a <lb/>termination notice under the Concession Agreement remains intact <lb/>and in full force and they reserve their right to exercise the right of <lb/>termination any time before 28 th April, 2013 and such notice, if and <lb/>when served upon MSRDC, shall be fully binding on MSRDC with <lb/>respect to its obligation to pay Termination Payment as certified by <lb/>the statutory auditors of PLUS. This letter is clearly not a <lb/>termination notice as contemplated under clause 32.4.1 of the <lb/>Concession Agreement. Be that as it may, even if I was to assume <lb/>that this letter is a notice as contemplated under clause 32.4.1, the <lb/>time period between 4 th February, 2013 till 28 th April, 2013 (the <lb/>date on which the Toll Notification came to an end), still does not <lb/>comply with the period of 90 days, as contemplated under the <lb/>aforesaid clause. I am in agreement with Mr. Chagla that <lb/>termination of a contract has serious consequences. Therefore, <lb/>termination under clause 32.4.1 requires strict compliance. Failure <lb/>to give notice of 90 days would clearly render the termination under <lb/>clause 32.4.1 of the Concession Agreement illegal and invalid. I <lb/>therefore am of the view that the finding of the Tribunal in so far as <lb/>it upholds the termination of the Concession Agreement under <lb/>clause 32.4 suffers from a patent illegality as its findings run in the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 101 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>teeth of the plain language of clause 32.4.1 and hence cannot be <lb/>sustained. <lb/>73. <lb/>As far as the argument of Mr. Chagla that the <lb/>actions/omissions of MSRDC did not have a material adverse effect <lb/>on the project, I am unable to agree with the same as that is a <lb/>question of fact which is examined by the Tribunal. The Tribunal <lb/>finds that the record is replete with correspondence from PLUS <lb/>pointing out how this delay is constraining its cash flow position, <lb/>and jeopardizing operations. This would clearly amount to a <lb/>material adverse effect on the project. However, as mentioned <lb/>earlier, termination under Clause 32.4.1 cannot be held to be valid <lb/>in view of the fact that a 90 day notice was not given by PLUS to <lb/>MSRDC as contemplated in clause 32.4.1 of the Concession <lb/>Agreement. <lb/>74. <lb/>Despite having held that the termination of the <lb/>Concession Agreement under clause 32.4 cannot be held to be valid, <lb/>I find that it makes little difference in the present matter. As noted <lb/>earlier, the Concession Agreement could be terminated under <lb/>Clauses 29.8 as well as 32.4. Even if one of them is held to be valid <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 102 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>then the Concession Agreement would stand validly terminated. <lb/>Considering that I have held that the findings of the Tribunal <lb/>regarding termination of the Concession Agreement under Clause <lb/>29.8 does not require any interference, it makes little difference <lb/>whether termination under Clause 32.4 is held valid or otherwise. <lb/>This is more so when one takes into consideration that the <lb/>Termination Payment formula under clause 29.9(c) and 32.4.2 is <lb/>exactly the same. <lb/>III(A) -AWARD IS CONTRARY TO THE PROCEDURE <lb/>AGREED UPON BETWEEN THE PARTIES AS PER SECTION <lb/>19(2) OF THE ACT; <lb/>III(B) -LEGAL MISCONDUCT ON THE PART OF THE <lb/>TRIBUNAL; AND <lb/>III(C) -FAILURE OF THE ARBITRAL TRIBUNAL TO <lb/>CONSIDER/DECIDE THE COUNTER CLAIM FILED BY <lb/>MSRDC: <lb/>SUBMISSIONS OF MSRDC: <lb/>75. <lb/>As mentioned earlier, I find that the aforesaid three <lb/>grounds of challenge, namely: (i) the Award is contrary to the <lb/>procedure agreed to between the parties; (ii) the failure of the <lb/>Tribunal to consider / decide the Counter Claim of MSRDC; and (iii) <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 103 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>legal misconduct on the part of the Tribunal; are all inter-twined <lb/>together and hence these three grounds are being decided together. <lb/>76. <lb/>Firstly, Mr. Chagla submitted that the Tribunal, with the <lb/>consent of the parties, laid down the entire schedule for the arbitral <lb/>proceedings as recorded in the minutes of the meeting dated 20 th <lb/>February, 2016. In the said minutes, the Tribunal passed a detailed <lb/>procedural order wherein the Tribunal made it clear that the dates <lb/>fixed for hearing, i.e. for the evidence and final arguments were <lb/>inflexible. Mr. Chagla submitted that the Tribunal reiterated upon <lb/>the inflexibility of the aforesaid dates in its further procedural <lb/>orders dated 4 th May, 2016 and 12 th May, 2016. He submitted that <lb/>on a conjoint reading of the procedural orders passed by the <lb/>Tribunal from time to time, namely, procedural orders dated 20 th <lb/>February, 2016, 4 th May, 2016, 12 th May, 2016 and 17 th October, <lb/>2016, read along with the transcripts dated 17 th January, 2017, <lb/>20 th January, 2017, 3 rd February, 2017 and 4 th February, 2017, <lb/>establish beyond a doubt that the dates fixed by the Tribunal were <lb/>not only inflexible, but the proceedings were to be conducted as one <lb/>consolidated proceeding and the Tribunal was to pass one Award. <lb/>He submitted that the Tribunal&apos;s directions to make payment of the <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 104 of 169 <lb/>full fees for hearings scheduled on 17 th January, 2017 to 21 st <lb/>January, 2017 and thereafter from 31 st January, 2017 to 4 th <lb/>February, 2017 also indicated that there was to be only one <lb/>consolidated hearing and was not to be broken up, as was done in <lb/>the present case. He submitted that the transcript of 4 th February, <lb/>2017, and which was the last date of hearing, expressly records that <lb/>arguments were closed. <lb/>77. <lb/>Mr. Chagla submitted that party autonomy is considered <lb/>to be the backbone of arbitration and failure to follow the procedure <lb/>agreed upon between the parties vitiates the entire arbitral <lb/>procedure. He submitted that by its procedural order dated 17 th <lb/>October, 2016, the Tribunal directed that all documents were taken <lb/>on record, subject to the proof of objection as to admissibility. PLUS <lb/>filed four affidavits of evidence and MSRDC filed three affidavits of <lb/>evidence on record along with all the documentary evidence in their <lb/>custody. He submitted that in the present case, the parties led <lb/>evidence before the Arbitral Tribunal, both oral and documentary. <lb/>Parties also advanced oral arguments and filed written submissions <lb/>in support of their respective cases. At no point of time did PLUS <lb/>seek an opportunity to lead any further evidence or to amend its <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 105 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>claims. The Arbitral Tribunal was, therefore, bound to decide all <lb/>issues as set out in paragraph 54 of the Award and not break up the <lb/>hearing as was sought to be done by the impugned Award. Mr. <lb/>Chagla submitted that what was even more shocking was that after <lb/>considering the complete evidence and the submission of the parties, <lb/>the Tribunal rejected certain specific claims of PLUS and expressed <lb/>its inability to decide the other claims on the available evidence. He <lb/>submitted that the parties are required in law to produce all <lb/>evidence in support of their case which, in the present case, PLUS <lb/>claimed it had done and having regard to the findings of the Arbitral <lb/>Tribunal, the claims of PLUS ought to have been dismissed. He <lb/>submitted that the findings of the Arbitral Tribunal amount to a final <lb/>adjudication and the nomenclature &quot;Interim Award&quot; is misplaced <lb/>and unwarranted and has been done only to permit PLUS to file <lb/>further pleadings and lead further evidence. Mr. Chagla submitted <lb/>that, in effect, the Tribunal ex-facie seeks to review its own final <lb/>adjudication, which is impermissible in law. <lb/>78. <lb/>Mr. Chagla thereafter brought to my attention the <lb/>findings of the Arbitral Tribunal in respect of various claims made <lb/>by PLUS. The first claim made by PLUS was for Termination <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 106 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>Payment of Rs.495 crores. Mr. Chagla submitted that this claim was <lb/>purportedly made under clause 29.9(c) and clause 32.4.2 of the <lb/>Concession Agreement. He submitted that it was the express case of <lb/>PLUS that Termination Payment became mechanically / <lb/>automatically due and payable on the expiry of thirty days from the <lb/>date of the Statutory Auditor&apos;s certificate certifying the <lb/>&apos;Termination Payment&apos; being submitted to MSRDC. It was also the <lb/>contention of PLUS that once the same became due and payable, <lb/>there was no mechanism in the Concession Agreement to reverse <lb/>the same and no further evidence, apart from the Statutory <lb/>Auditor&apos;s certificate, was required to be led by it to prove its claim. <lb/>MSRDC, on the other hand, contended that as per the formula for <lb/>the calculation of Termination Payment, the same could not be <lb/>applied mechanically and that damages could not be awarded unless <lb/>PLUS proved that it had suffered actual losses / damages and the <lb/>quantum thereof. Mr. Chagla submitted that in this connection, the <lb/>Arbitral Tribunal in paragraph 72 of the Award has, inter alia, held <lb/>as under: <lb/>&quot;Prima facie the Tribunal would need to be satisfied about the <lb/>element of proportionality in the working of the Termination <lb/>Payment clause. We notice that the MSRDC has strongly contested <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 107 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>the Termination Payment also on the ground of each individual <lb/>head that is to be calculated under the formula, and it would be <lb/>beneficial to the Tribunal to invite further hearing and <lb/>on this issue.&quot; <lb/>79. <lb/>Mr. Chagla submitted that if the Tribunal required any <lb/>further hearings and submissions, it should have fixed such further <lb/>hearings and heard the submissions on the issue and not defer the <lb/>same to a further arbitral hearing after passing the impugned <lb/>Award. He submitted that, in effect, when one reads the aforesaid <lb/>paragraph, the claims of PLUS, on the available evidence and <lb/>submissions, stood rejected. <lb/>80. <lb/>Mr. Chagla submitted that similar is the case for the <lb/>claim of Rs.469 crores and which is in the alternative to the claim <lb/>for Termination Payment. He submitted that the alternative claim <lb/>of Rs.469 crores was allegedly based on amounts invested by the <lb/>shareholders of PLUS. He submitted that the Tribunal held that this <lb/>figure was virtually a proxy claim for Termination Payment. In <lb/>view of this finding, the Tribunal ought to have rejected this claim. <lb/>Instead, the Tribunal held that since the Tribunal is inclined to defer <lb/>its decision on the issue of Termination Payment, the decision on <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 108 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>this alternative claim also stood deferred. In this regard, Mr. Chagla <lb/>brought to my attention, paragraph 73 of the Award. <lb/>81. <lb/>Mr. Chagla then brought to my attention that over and <lb/>above the aforesaid two claims, a claim of Rs.112 crores was also <lb/>made for reimbursement of &apos;additional direct cost&apos;, the loss of Toll <lb/>revenue and restoration charges. <lb/>In the arbitration, PLUS <lb/>proceeded on the express basis that these amounts were admitted <lb/>by MSRDC in the correspondence exchanged in the course of <lb/>settlement/conciliation. However, the Tribunal conclusively held <lb/>that these cannot be said to constitute admissions of quantum of <lb/>liability as placing weight on the quantum figures exchanged <lb/>between the parties while working out a compromise would not be <lb/>fair as they were made during the course of settlement. In this <lb/>regard, Mr. Chagla brought to my attention the finding of the <lb/>Tribunal in paragraph 77 of the Award. He submitted that the <lb/>Tribunal further held that the same would not be a sound basis to <lb/>arrive at any conclusion on the quantum of loss. It was the <lb/>submission of Mr. Chagla that reading paragraphs 77, 79 and 86 of <lb/>the Award clearly constituted a rejection of PLUS&apos; claims. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 109 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>82. <lb/>Mr. Chagla then submitted that the finding of the <lb/>Arbitral Tribunal in paragraph 86 of the Award, namely, &quot;The <lb/>Tribunal cannot arrive at a quantum determination based on the <lb/>existing record and submissions&quot; applied to all claims made by PLUS <lb/>and is final and binding. The said finding has not been challenged by <lb/>PLUS and has, therefore, attained finality and operates as res <lb/>judicata and/or issue estoppel between the parties. Mr. Chagla <lb/>submitted that looking at the way the matter progressed before the <lb/>Arbitral Tribunal (and which is clear from the different Procedural <lb/>Orders as well as the transcripts referred to above), what emerges is <lb/>that (i) there was to be one consolidated hearing determining the <lb/>claims of PLUS as well as the Counter Claim filed by MSRDC; (ii) the <lb/>dates fixed by the Tribunal were to be strictly adhered to and were <lb/>inflexible; (iii) the evidence of both parties was complete; (iv) <lb/>arguments on all the issues were addressed before the Tribunal and <lb/>even the written submissions filed by both parties covered the claim <lb/>and the Counter Claim on all issues; (v) the hearing was finally <lb/>concluded on 4 th February, 2017 and the matter was stood over only <lb/>for pronouncement of the Award. He submitted that from the record <lb/>it was clear that no further hearing was contemplated except a short <lb/>focused hearing, if required by the Tribunal and that too after they <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 110 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>perused the written submissions filed by the parties. He submitted <lb/>that no further procedural order was passed after 4 th February, <lb/>2017 and no further hearing was held before the passing of the <lb/>Interim Award, either for a clarification or otherwise. He submitted <lb/>that neither the parties nor the Tribunal ever contemplated the <lb/>passing of an Interim Award and deferring the hearing on the <lb/>quantum at a later date. He submitted that, in fact, the parties had <lb/>led their entire evidence before the Arbitral Tribunal and the <lb/>Tribunal, therefore, could not have given the directions it did in <lb/>paragraphs 77, 79, 84 and 85 of the impugned Award. Mr. Chagla <lb/>submitted that in effect, once having come to the conclusion that the <lb/>evidence led by PLUS was inadequate to decide on the quantum of <lb/>the claims, it should have rejected the claims of PLUS for want of <lb/>evidence. Instead, it has effectively allowed PLUS to improve its <lb/>case by leading further evidence, if necessary. Mr. Chagla submitted <lb/>that this was wholly impermissible in law, especially considering <lb/>that the Tribunal itself had made it clear that there would be only <lb/>one Award for the entire proceedings and both parties had led their <lb/>respective evidence in its entirety to prove their respective claims. <lb/>In these circumstances, there was no question of allowing either <lb/>party to lead further evidence to prove their claims. If the evidence <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 111 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>was inadequate, the only option available to the Tribunal was to <lb/>reject the claims. He submitted that adoption of such a procedure by <lb/>the Tribunal not only vitiates the Award on the ground of <lb/>perversity, but also suffers from a patent illegality, and clearly <lb/>amounts to legal misconduct on the part of the Arbitral Tribunal. <lb/>Mr. Chagla submitted that the record would clearly establish that <lb/>the counsel for MSRDC asked for further time for cross-examination <lb/>and for presentation of its arguments which was rejected by the <lb/>Tribunal. However, the Tribunal nevertheless granted liberty to <lb/>PLUS to fill up any lacuna in its pleadings and evidence by making <lb/>the observations as mentioned in paragraphs 77, 79 and 85 of the <lb/>Award. This clearly amounted to legal misconduct on the part of the <lb/>Tribunal and which indicated a definite bias in favour of PLUS and <lb/>against MSRDC. To put it in a nutshell, Mr. Chagla submitted that <lb/>the Tribunal had not treated the parties equally and had acted in <lb/>violation of section 18 of the Act and would, therefore, clearly <lb/>amount to legal misconduct on the part of the Tribunal. <lb/>83. <lb/>Lastly, Mr. Chagla submitted that the transcripts clearly <lb/>show that the procedure was agreed and the parties also always <lb/>understood that there would be one consolidated Award and one <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 112 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>consolidated proceeding, including a decision on the Counter Claim <lb/>filed by MSRDC. Though MSRDC made a Counter Claim of around <lb/>Rs.93 crores under twelve different heads, and despite the Tribunal <lb/>framing an issue as to what would be the amount to which MSRDC <lb/>would be entitled to on account of its Counter Claim, the finding of <lb/>the Arbitral Tribunal in paragraph 85 of the Award that sufficient <lb/>time was not devoted to the Counter Claim is patently illegal and <lb/>perverse considering that pursuant to the directions passed by the <lb/>Tribunal, both, the claim and Counter Claim were heard. In fact, the <lb/>parties filed their detailed written submissions in support of and in <lb/>reply to the Counter Claim. Despite this, the fact that the Counter <lb/>Claim was not adjudicated upon by the Arbitral Tribunal vitiates the <lb/>Award. In support of this submission, Mr. Chagla relied upon the <lb/>following: <lb/>a. <lb/>An Award should be final and the arbitrator cannot, in <lb/>his Award, reserve to himself the power of performing in <lb/>future, any act of a judicial nature in respect of the <lb/>matters submitted. [Russel on the Law of Arbitration <lb/>24 th Edition, para (b)] <lb/>b. <lb/>Failure by the arbitral tribunal to deal with all the issues <lb/>that were put to it would amount to serious irregularity <lb/>and the Award can be challenged on that ground <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 113 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>[Halsbury&apos;s Law of England 5 th Edition, volume 2, <lb/>para 1277] <lb/>c. <lb/>Vijay Kari &amp; Ors. v. Prysmian Cavi E Sistemi SRL &amp; <lb/>Ors. [2020 SCC OnLine SC 177]; para 86. <lb/>d. <lb/>K.V. George v. Secy. To Govt., Water and Power <lb/>Deptt., [(1989) 4 SCC 595]; para 12. <lb/>84. <lb/>In conclusion, Mr. Chagla, therefore, submitted that the <lb/>entire Award is vitiated as the same was in violation of the agreed <lb/>procedure as contemplated under section 19, legal misconduct on <lb/>the part of the Tribunal as well as on the ground that it failed to <lb/>consider the Counter Claim filed by MSRDC. Consequently, he <lb/>submitted that the arbitration Petition be allowed and the impugned <lb/>Award be set aside. <lb/>SUBMISSIONS OF PLUS: <lb/>85. <lb/>On the other hand, Mr. Khambatta, the learned senior <lb/>counsel appearing on behalf of PLUS submitted that the entire <lb/>decision to bifurcate the arbitral proceedings into two phases, first <lb/>to make an Interim Award and thereafter defer the hearing to <lb/>decide on the quantum of the claims was neither contrary to the <lb/>agreed procedure and nor was it patently illegal or against the <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 114 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>fundamental policy of Indian law. He submitted that the Tribunal is <lb/>empowered to devise its own procedure. In this regard, he brought <lb/>to my attention, sections 19(2) and 19(3) of the Act which, inter <lb/>alia, stipulate that subject to Part I of the Act, the parties are free to <lb/>agree on the procedure to be followed by the Arbitral Tribunal in <lb/>conducting the proceedings and failing any such agreement between <lb/>the parties, the Arbitral Tribunal may conduct the proceedings in <lb/>the manner it considers appropriate. Mr. Khambatta submitted that <lb/>section 19(3) of the Act clearly empowers the Tribunal to devise its <lb/>own procedure, unless there is an agreement between the parties to <lb/>the contrary. It was his submission that in the present case, there <lb/>was no agreement regarding the procedure to be followed by the <lb/>Tribunal and, therefore, the Tribunal devised its own procedure <lb/>under section 19(3). He submitted that in its procedural order <lb/>dated 20 th February, 2016, the Tribunal gave directions in respect of <lb/>the procedure it proposed to follow. This was after discussion with <lb/>the parties who agreed to the practice and procedure suggested by <lb/>the Tribunal. Mr. Khambatta submitted that these directions were <lb/>not exhaustive of the procedure and neither did they restrict the <lb/>Tribunal to pass a single unified Award. He submitted that under <lb/>section 19(3) of the Act, the Arbitrators have procedural autonomy, <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 115 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>unless the same is restricted or modified by the parties by <lb/>agreement. He submitted that in the facts of the present case, there <lb/>is no restriction placed by the parties on the Tribunal&apos;s power to <lb/>bifurcate the proceedings and to pass two Awards. Mr. Khambatta <lb/>strongly relied upon paragraph 15 of the procedural order dated <lb/>20 th February, 2016 to contend that the Tribunal expressly <lb/>reserved the discretion to itself to amend or modify the procedure <lb/>pursuant to such further directions or procedural orders as the <lb/>Tribunal may, from time to time, consider necessary. He submitted <lb/>that the said procedural order was passed after discussion with the <lb/>parties who agreed to the practice and procedure to be followed, <lb/>including paragraph 15 of the said order. Thus, the Tribunal was <lb/>entitled to amend the procedure for conducting the proceedings if it <lb/>considered it necessary, was the submission of Mr. Khambatta. In <lb/>any event, Mr. Khambatta submitted that the said procedural order <lb/>did not exclude the power of the Tribunal under section 19(3) of the <lb/>Act to determine the procedure nor did it describe that there would <lb/>be only one final Award. <lb/>He, therefore, submitted that the <lb/>submission of Mr. Chagla that the procedure contemplated by the <lb/>Tribunal was to pass one final Award is not well founded. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 116 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>86. <lb/>Mr. Khambatta then submitted that it is not uncommon <lb/>in both International and domestic arbitrations for a Tribunal to <lb/>pass an Interim or Partial Award, bifurcating the proceedings. <lb/>Under section 2(c) of the Act, an Arbitral Award includes an Interim <lb/>Award. Section 31(6) of the Act provides for passing an Interim <lb/>Award. The Interim Award is a final Award in relation to issues <lb/>which are finally decided therein. An Interim Award finally decides <lb/>an issue without necessarily disposing off all the claims. He <lb/>submitted that the term &quot;Interim Award&quot; is often used <lb/>synonymously with the term &quot;Partial Award&quot;. In the present case, <lb/>Mr. Khambatta pointed out that by way of an Interim Award, issues <lb/>(a) and (b) [framed by the Tribunal in paragraph 54 of the Award] <lb/>regarding the validity of the termination notices were finally <lb/>decided by the Tribunal and issues (c) and (d) relating to quantum <lb/>of the claims [of PLUS] and the Counter Claims [of MSRDC] were <lb/>deferred to the second phase. He submitted that there was <lb/>absolutely nothing wrong in the Tribunal adopting this procedure, <lb/>especially considering that the Tribunal was empowered to do so <lb/>under section 19(3) of the Act. He submitted that this has also been <lb/>held to be valid by the Supreme Court in the case of McDermott <lb/>International Inc. vs. Burn Standard Company Ltd. &amp; Ors., <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 117 of 169 <lb/>[(2006) 11 SCC 181]. Mr. Khambatta submitted that even under <lb/>section 27 of the Arbitration Act, 1940 [corresponding to section <lb/>31(6) of the Act], the Arbitral Tribunal had the power to make an <lb/>Interim Award, deciding the question of liability first and permitting <lb/>the leading of evidence thereafter on the question of damages. In <lb/>this regard, Mr. Khambatta relied upon a decision of a Division <lb/>Bench of this Court in the case of Manganese Ore (India) Ltd. &amp; <lb/>Ors. Vs. Ram Bahadur Thakur Limited [2006 SCC Online Bom. <lb/>507]. Mr. Khambatta submitted that even the second edition of <lb/>Gary B. Born, International Commercial Edition recognises the <lb/>utility and benefits of bifurcating the proceedings and the passing of <lb/>Interim or Partial Awards. Only clear and unambiguous language <lb/>should be permitted to produce the unusual and inefficient result of <lb/>denying the arbitrators the authority to make Partial Awards. <lb/>Allowing the arbitrator to pass Partial Awards enables the Tribunal <lb/>and the parties to focus on and resolve issues sequentially, rather <lb/>than in a single decision. This sometimes has very significant <lb/>advantages in terms of efficiency and speed. A Tribunal&apos;s decision <lb/>whether or not to bifurcate proceedings and to resolve certain issues <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 118 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>before others usually turns on minute assessments of efficiency that <lb/>are the domain of the Arbitral Tribunal, was the submission. <lb/>87. <lb/>Mr. Khambatta then submitted that PLUS has placed all <lb/>material / proof in support of its claims before the Tribunal including <lb/>the one for Termination Payment. What the Tribunal has done is <lb/>that it has only deferred the quantum of those claims and not <lb/>rejected them as sought to be contended by Mr. Chagla. He <lb/>submitted that Mr. Chagla&apos;s reliance on a single sentence of <lb/>paragraph 86 of the impugned Award is completely misplaced and <lb/>out of context. Mr. Khambatta submitted that the Concession <lb/>Agreement provided for Termination Payment in terms of clause <lb/>29.9(c) and 32.4.2 thereof and which are identical in nature. He <lb/>submitted that such a clause is inserted to encourage Public Private <lb/>Partnership. The concept of a Public Private Partnership (for short <lb/>&quot;PPP&quot;) Project is introduced to help in developing public <lb/>infrastructure through private investment which otherwise would <lb/>have to be funded by the Government. In PPP Projects, the concept <lb/>of Termination Payment has been introduced by which, in the event <lb/>of termination of the contract, regardless of who has committed the <lb/>default, Termination Payment has to be paid by the Government or <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 119 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>the PSU in all cases of termination. This concept helps in attracting <lb/>private entities and provides adequate security to the lenders as it is <lb/>not possible to secure them through collateral assets as the assets <lb/>belong to the public. He submitted that Termination Payment is not <lb/>the same as damages or even liquidated damages. When the <lb/>Concession Agreement is terminated for default by either party, the <lb/>Government takes over the asset and the amount paid for such <lb/>taking over of the asset is termed as &apos;Termination Payment&apos;. <lb/>Termination payment represents only a return on equity and <lb/>repayment of debt as per the pre-agreed formula. On the other hand, <lb/>damages or liquidated damages can never be claimed by a defaulting <lb/>party whereas in case of Termination Payment in a PPP contract, <lb/>even on the default of the Concessionaire, the Concessionaire would <lb/>be entitled to Termination Payment. <lb/>88. <lb/>Mr. Khambatta submitted that all that the Tribunal has <lb/>done is deferred the first claim for Termination Payment <lb/>(Rs.4,95,80,21,040/-along with interest) to consider the issue of <lb/>proportionality and which was actually done purely for the benefit <lb/>of MSRDC. <lb/>He submitted that all documents required for <lb/>quantification of Termination Payment were duly filed and proved <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 120 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>by PLUS. The quantum of Termination Payment has to be done by <lb/>applying the figures of debt, equity and subordinate debt to the <lb/>formula as provided in clause 29.9(c) and 32.4.2 of the Concession <lb/>Agreement and which are identical. <lb/>He submitted that the <lb/>Statutory Auditor&apos;s certificate, which provided the amount of <lb/>Termination Payment payable, was never challenged by MSRDC. <lb/>Under clause 28.1, the accounts of PLUS audited and certified by its <lb/>Statutory Auditors would form the basis of various payments by <lb/>either party under the Concession Agreement. MSRDC also chose <lb/>not to appoint another firm of Chartered Accounts to audit and <lb/>verify the Auditor&apos;s certificate which MSRDC was entitled to do as <lb/>per clause 28.4. Reliance upon the Auditor&apos;s certificate by PLUS at <lb/>paragraph 6.91 of the Statement of Claim was clearly met with <lb/>merely a bald denial at paragraph 7.54 of the Statement of Defence. <lb/>Hence, Mr. Khambatta submitted that as per clause 32.6 of the <lb/>Concession Agreement, MSRDC was required to pay to PLUS the <lb/>Termination Payment within thirty days of the demand being made <lb/>by PLUS accompanied by such Statutory Auditor&apos;s certificate. Mr. <lb/>Khambatta submitted that MSRDC accepts the fact that it is liable to <lb/>make payment to PLUS. This is clear from the fact that the Toll <lb/>Notifications that were issued by the Government of Maharashtra <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 121 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>after the termination of the Concession Agreement authorised <lb/>MSRDC to collect the Toll and directed the amount so collected to be <lb/>kept in an Escrow Account so that the same could be utilised to <lb/>settle the claims of PLUS. <lb/>89. <lb/>Mr. Khambatta submitted that in paragraph 11 of the <lb/>Interim Award, the Tribunal has observed that the point at which <lb/>termination might take place did not have any bearing on the <lb/>computation of the Termination Payment. <lb/>Nevertheless, in <lb/>paragraph 72, the Tribunal stated that it needed to be satisfied <lb/>about the proportionality in the working of the Termination <lb/>Payment clause as MSRDC had contested the said payment also <lb/>under each individual head that was to be calculated under the <lb/>formula and for this reason, the Tribunal wanted to have a further <lb/>hearing and submissions. From all this material, Mr. Khambatta <lb/>submitted that adopting proportionality as a factor in addition to the <lb/>formula [as laid down in clauses 29.9(c) and 32.4.2], worked to <lb/>MSRDC&apos;s advantage. Mr. Khambatta submitted that this was, in <lb/>fact, done for the benefit and, in fact, benefitted MSRDC and, <lb/>therefore, it does not lie in their mouth to contend that the Tribunal <lb/>could not have done so. This is for the simple reason that otherwise <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 122 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>PLUS would have been entitled to Termination Payment as per the <lb/>formula set out in clauses 29.9(c) and 32.4.2 and which were <lb/>identical in nature. The deferment to consider the proportionality <lb/>was really for the benefit of MSRDC and not to the benefit of PLUS. <lb/>90. <lb/>Mr. Khambatta thereafter submitted that even the <lb/>deferment of quantum of the second claim of PLUS towards damages <lb/>on account of breaches committed by MSRDC (for Rs.112 crores) <lb/>operates to the benefit of MSRDC and not to the benefit of PLUS. He <lb/>submitted that this claim arose in terms of clause 32.8 of the <lb/>Concession Agreement under the head &quot;Other Claims&quot;. The loss <lb/>suffered by PLUS was on account of breaches by MSRDC prior to the <lb/>termination date. The loss had, therefore, accrued much before the <lb/>termination and the amount would have merely compensated PLUS <lb/>for the said loss. Mr. Khambatta submitted that PLUS had filed and <lb/>proved documents in support of its claim by primarily relying on <lb/>admissions by MSRDC on both, liability and quantum contained in <lb/>MSRDC&apos;s various documents, including the letters dated 20 th <lb/>October, 2011, 18 th July, 2011, 4 th March, 2008, 24 th / 25 th June, <lb/>2009, 2 nd May, 2013, 2 nd August, 2010 and MSRDC&apos;s Director&apos;s <lb/>Report for the year 2011. <lb/>MSRDC had claimed that these <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 123 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>documents were part of the conciliation proceedings and, therefore, <lb/>inadmissible, which contention was rejected by the Tribunal. The <lb/>Tribunal did not determine the quantum based on the figures quoted <lb/>during the settlement discussions holding it would be unfair on <lb/>MSRDC to do so. The Tribunal held that despite the fact that the <lb/>documents were admissible, the Tribunal felt that it is still required <lb/>to determine the weight that can be attached to these documents as <lb/>evidence of an admitted quantum of loss. The Tribunal was of the <lb/>view that it would be unfair on MSRDC to determine the issue of <lb/>quantum with reference to the figures quoted during settlement <lb/>discussions and in these circumstances, it would not be fair to place <lb/>much weight on the quantum figures exchanged by the parties while <lb/>working out the settlement. The Tribunal held that these cannot be <lb/>said to constitute admissions of quantum of liability. Mr. Khambatta <lb/>submitted that despite the fact that the amounts claimed under the <lb/>head &apos;Other Claims&apos; were admitted by MSRDC in various documents, <lb/>the Tribunal nevertheless held as follows: <lb/>&quot;If, on the other hand, the Tribunal ultimately reaches the <lb/>conclusion that the Termination Payment is not possible (despite <lb/>there being a valid termination), then it is for the Claimant to prove <lb/>and quantify the loss that it has suffered, and claim damages on <lb/>that basis. The Tribunal is not inclined -at this stage -to award <lb/>Rs. 112 crore in damages, based on any admissions by the <lb/>MSRDC, as alleged. Since this figure is arrived at in course of <lb/></body>

			<front>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 124 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>correspondence exchanged during the settlement phase, although <lb/>the documentation itself is admissible, the Tribunal feels that it <lb/>would not be a sound basis to arrive at any conclusion on the <lb/>quantum of loss based on these figures alone. We are, therefore of <lb/>the view that even on this issue, further hearing and submissions <lb/>are required. We clarify that in making these submissions, the <lb/>Claimant need not be restricted to the amounts allegedly admitted <lb/>by MSRDC, but may even claim amounts higher than that should it <lb/>elect to do so. However, if would need to prove and quantify its <lb/>loss by leading appropriate evidence if necessary. Similarly, the <lb/>MSRDC shall not be bound by any alleged admissions made during <lb/>the settlement phase, but may independently rebut the Claimant&apos;s <lb/>claim for damages, including by way of leading appropriate <lb/>evidence if necessary.&quot; <lb/>91. <lb/>Mr. Khambatta submitted that it is in this context that <lb/>the findings of the Tribunal have to be read and understood. When <lb/>read and understood in that context, it is clear that the deferment <lb/>was purely to benefit MSRDC and was not to be benefit of PLUS at <lb/>all. This being the case, it can hardly lie in the mouth of MSRDC that <lb/>any injustice has been done to them by the Tribunal by deferring the <lb/>issue of quantum of PLUS&apos; claims at a later stage. <lb/>92. <lb/>Even as far as MSRDC&apos;s Counter Claims are concerned <lb/>(for Rs.93,04,88,558/-), Mr. Khambatta submitted that the same <lb/>was deferred to allow MSRDC a full opportunity of presenting its <lb/>case. Mr. Khambatta submitted that it is evident on a bare perusal <lb/>of paragraph 85 of the Interim Award that the parties had filed <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 125 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>several volumes in respect of the Counter Claims filed by MSRDC. <lb/>However, during the hearings, sufficient attention was not devoted <lb/>to the Counter Claims as the parties concentrated mainly on the <lb/>claims made by PLUS and MSRDC&apos;s defence thereto. It was, <lb/>therefore, decided by the Tribunal that it would not be fair to decide <lb/>the rights and liabilities of the parties with respect to the Counter <lb/>Claims without affording a fair opportunity to the parties to present <lb/>their case qua each Counter Claim. It is in this light that the <lb/>Tribunal, therefore, deferred the decision on the Counter Claim also <lb/>to the second phase. Mr. Khambatta submitted that the Tribunal <lb/>has thus given an opportunity to MSRDC to make good its case. It is <lb/>in this context the one sentence relied upon by Mr. Chagla in <lb/>paragraph 86 of the Interim Award has to be read and understood. <lb/>Mr. Khambatta submitted that the Tribunal in paragraph 86, is not <lb/>referring to insufficiency of evidence led by PLUS. In any event, <lb/>whether or not the evidence was insufficient to award payment / <lb/>damages is a matter to be dealt with while examining the final <lb/>Award. Moreover, paragraph 87 of the Interim Award makes it <lb/>clear that this observation is only prima facie in nature as the <lb/>determinative findings in the Interim Award are only in respect of <lb/>liability. He, therefore, submitted that all this clearly goes to show <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 126 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>that there is absolutely no merit in the contention of Mr. Chagla that <lb/>the Tribunal could not have bifurcated the proceedings which <lb/>vitiates the Award. If this be the case, Mr. Khambatta submitted <lb/>that there is no legal misconduct on the part of the Arbitral <lb/>Tribunal. Consequently, he submitted that there was no merit in the <lb/>aforesaid objection to the Interim Award and the same ought to be <lb/>rejected. He therefore submitted that the above Petition has no <lb/>merit and the same ought to be dismissed with costs. <lb/>FINDING OF THE COURT: <lb/>93. <lb/>I have heard the learned counsel for the parties at great <lb/>length on this issue. To understand the present controversy, it <lb/>would be necessary to understand how the arbitration proceedings <lb/>progressed before the Arbitral Tribunal. On 20 th February, 2016, <lb/>the Arbitral Tribunal passed a detailed procedural order giving <lb/>various directions. A time-frame was set out by which the Statement <lb/>of Claim as well as the Statement of Defence and Counter Claim were <lb/>to be filed, so also the Statement of Defence of PLUS to MSRDC&apos;s <lb/>Counter Claim. Directions were also given to MSRDC and PLUS to <lb/>submit their affidavit of denial / dispute in respect of any document <lb/>filed by each other and/or request for inspection and/or production <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 127 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>of documents. In the said procedural order, it was directed that the <lb/>Tribunal will have sittings from 17 th January, 2017 to 21 st January, <lb/>2017 for cross-examination of witnesses of each party by the other <lb/>side and oral arguments would be heard by the Tribunal from 31 st <lb/>January, 2017 to 4 th February, 2017. The timing for all sittings was <lb/>fixed from 11.00 a.m. to 5.00 p.m. with an hour&apos;s break for lunch. In <lb/>the said procedural order, Practice Directions under section 19(3) of <lb/>the Act were also set out in great detail. The relevant portion of the <lb/>Practice Directions read thus: <lb/>&quot;Practice Directions [under Section 19(3) of the <lb/>Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996] <lb/>After discussion, the Learned Counsel for the parties <lb/>have agreed on the practice and procedure to be <lb/>followed and in accordance therewith the following <lb/>directions are issued by the Tribunal: <lb/>1. Extension of time shall be granted by the Tribunal in its <lb/>discretion: <lb/>(a) in exceptional cases only; <lb/>(b) provided that a request is submitted before the date <lb/>scheduled; and <lb/>(c) as soon as it appears that the deadline cannot be <lb/>complied with. <lb/>The Parties may also agree between themselves for <lb/>short extensions of time, on the basis of mutual <lb/>courtesy as long as those extensions do not materially <lb/>affect the time table (the dates scheduled for the sittings <lb/>of the Tribunal must not be affected) and that the <lb/>Tribunal is informed prior to the scheduled deadline. <lb/>… … … … <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 128 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>6. In arbitral disputes, it is not necessary to frame or <lb/>settle issues. However, for the purpose of focusing <lb/>attention of the parties and the Tribunal, the points for <lb/>determination / list of disputes on which the Tribunal <lb/>would be called upon to adjudicate may be settled. For <lb/>this purpose, the Learned Counsel for the parties would <lb/>exchange in advance draft / proposed points for <lb/>determination (list of disputes) on which adjudication by <lb/>the Tribunal would be needed. The Tribunal would <lb/>appreciate if the Learned Counsel may sit together and <lb/>file before the Tribunal an agreed memo of points for <lb/>determination. <lb/>7. Filing by either party of any pleading, document, <lb/>application and communication etc., shall be deemed to <lb/>have been effectively done and completed only on <lb/>having been delivered to the Tribunal and its copy <lb/>having been previously or simultaneously delivered to <lb/>the opposite party. <lb/>… … … … <lb/>15. The Procedural Order may be amended or <lb/>supplemented, and the procedures for conduct of this <lb/>Arbitration modified, pursuant to such further directions <lb/>or Procedural Orders as the Tribunal may from time to <lb/>time consider necessary and issue. <lb/>… … … … &quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>94. <lb/>What can be seen from the aforesaid detailed procedural <lb/>order is that the procedure was fixed by the Tribunal under section <lb/>19(3) of the Act and after discussion with the learned counsel for <lb/>the parties who agreed to the same. In the said procedural order, it <lb/>was made clear that extension of time would be granted only in <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 129 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>exceptional circumstances and as long as the extensions do not <lb/>materially affect the time table (the dates scheduled for the sittings <lb/>of the Tribunal should not be affected) and that the Tribunal was <lb/>informed prior to the scheduled deadline. The Tribunal also <lb/>reserved to itself, to amend the procedural order or supplement the <lb/>same for conducting the arbitration proceedings by issuing further <lb/>directions or further procedural orders as the Tribunal may, from <lb/>time to time, consider necessary. <lb/>95. <lb/>Since MSRDC could not adhere to the time-table for filing <lb/>its Statement of Defence and Counter Claim, on 28 th April, 2016, it e-<lb/>mailed the Arbitral Tribunal asking for four weeks&apos; extension. This <lb/>was objected to by the counsel of PLUS. Whilst dealing with the <lb/>aforesaid extension, the Tribunal, by its order dated 4 th May, 2016, <lb/>inter alia held as under: <lb/>&quot;The respondent&apos;s request is based primarily on three <lb/>grounds; (i) the respondent is still in the process of tracing <lb/>out and ascertaining the necessary correspondences / <lb/>documents relevant in the matter, (ii) The concerned <lb/>engineers/officers of the respondent who were dealing in <lb/>the said matter have either retired or transferred and <lb/>hence, it is taking sometime for the respondent to trace <lb/>out and ascertain all the relevant documents and (iii) The <lb/>pleadings and documents filed by the claimants are <lb/>voluminous in nature. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 130 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>It may be recalled that the schedule of proceedings under <lb/>the Procedural Order passed on 20 th February 2016 were <lb/>fixed in consultation with the counsel for the parties and <lb/>dates were assigned to the parties to take steps in the <lb/>arbitration proceedings, allowing full accommodation to <lb/>the request made by the counsel appearing on their <lb/>behalf. Though, the claimant was allowed four weeks&apos; <lb/>time for filing the Statement of Claim, on the request of the <lb/>counsel for the respondent, six weeks&apos; time was allowed <lb/>for filing Statement of Defence and Counter-claim. At the <lb/>same time it was also made clear to all concerned that the <lb/>schedule fixed in the Procedural Order was inflexible and <lb/>must be adhered to by both the sides. A stipulation to this <lb/>effect was also made in the very opening paragraph of the <lb/>Practice Directions given at the end of the schedule of <lb/>dates. <lb/>All the grounds on which the request for four weeks&apos; <lb/>further time for filing Statement of Defence and Counter-<lb/>claim is made were fully within the knowledge of the <lb/>respondent even on the date the Procedural Order was <lb/>passed or at any rate when the claimant submitted its <lb/>Statement of Claim as per the schedule on 19 th March, <lb/>2016. <lb/>It is, therefore, clear that the request for extension of time <lb/>by four weeks is quite unreasonable and the point of time <lb/>at which it is made (just two days before the date of <lb/>submission) makes it even more so. Further, acceding to <lb/>the respondent&apos;s request for extension of time by four <lb/>weeks would completely disrupt the entire schedule and it <lb/>will become nearly impossible to hold the final sittings, as <lb/>fixed in the schedule, from 30 th January to 4 th February <lb/>2017. <lb/>However, rejecting the respondent&apos;s request for extension <lb/>of time altogether at this stage would mean shutting out <lb/>the respondent completely from raising any defence or <lb/>any counter claim in the matter. Such a consequence <lb/>would be indeed quite unjust and the Tribunal would <lb/>certainly not like any procedural order passed by it to lead <lb/>to such consequences. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 131 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>Balancing the rights of the parties, the respondent is <lb/>allowed two weeks&apos; further time for submission of <lb/>Statement of Defence and Counter-claim, if any. The <lb/>respondent may thus submit its Statement of Defence and <lb/>Counter Claim, if any by 15 th May 2016. <lb/>It is made clear that no further extension of time will be <lb/>allowed for submission of the Statement of Defence and <lb/>Counter Claim. It is further made clear once again that <lb/>the Tribunal intends to maintain the dates fixed for the <lb/>final sittings undisturbed. Hence, suitable adjustments will <lb/>have to be made in the rest of the schedule by shortening <lb/>the time allowed to the parties by a few days at the <lb/>different stages in the proceedings before the final sittings. <lb/>The parties will be intimated of the amended schedule in <lb/>due course. <lb/>The parties are once again advised to realise that the <lb/>schedule fixed under the Procedural Order passed on 20 th <lb/>February 2016 is inflexible and if any request for <lb/>adjournment is made at all, it must be made in accordance <lb/>with the provision in the Practice Directions.&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>96. <lb/>As can be seen from this order, the Tribunal had made it <lb/>clear to all concerned that the schedule fixed in the procedural <lb/>order dated 20 th February, 2016 was inflexible and must be adhered <lb/>to by both sides. It held that the request for four weeks&apos; further time <lb/>for filing the Statement of Defence and Counter Claim was on <lb/>grounds which were fully within the knowledge of MSRDC even on <lb/>the date of the procedural order dated 20 th February, 2016 and, in <lb/>any event, when PLUS submitted its Statement of Claim on 19 th <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 132 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>March, 2016. The Tribunal further felt that the request for <lb/>extension of time by four weeks was quite unreasonable as granting <lb/>the aforesaid extension would completely disrupt the entire <lb/>schedule and it would become nearly impossible to hold the final <lb/>sittings as scheduled from 31 st January, 2017 (wrongly mentioned <lb/>as 30 th January, 2017) to 4 th February, 2017. However, the <lb/>Tribunal felt that rejecting MSRDC&apos;s request for extension <lb/>altogether would be unjust and, therefore, to balance the equities, <lb/>MSRDC was allowed two weeks&apos; time for submission of its Statement <lb/>of Defence and Counter Claim. It was made clear that no further <lb/>time would be allowed and that the Tribunal intends to maintain the <lb/>dates fixed for the final sittings undisturbed. Hence, suitable <lb/>adjustments would have to be made in the rest of the schedule by <lb/>shortening the time allowed to the parties by a few days at the <lb/>different stages in the proceedings before the final sittings and the <lb/>parties would be intimated of the amended Schedule in due course. <lb/>It was once again reiterated that the Schedule fixed under the <lb/>procedural order passed on 20 th February, 2016 was inflexible and <lb/>if any request for adjournment was made, it would have to be in <lb/>accordance with the Practice Directions issued on 20 th February, <lb/>2016. <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 133 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>97. <lb/>Pursuant to the aforesaid order dated 4 th May, 2016, on <lb/>12 th May, 2016, the Arbitral Tribunal, accordingly, changed the <lb/>dates by which the pleadings and evidence of the parties was to be <lb/>filed. The Tribunal set out that the dates mentioned in the <lb/>procedural order from Sr. Nos.1 to 10 were uniformly extended by a <lb/>fortnight as set out in the said order. The dates with reference to <lb/>the cross-examination of witnesses from 17 th January, 2017 to 21 st <lb/>January, 2017 as well as the sittings of the Tribunal to hear oral <lb/>arguments from 31 st January, 2017 to 4 th February, 2017 remain <lb/>unchanged. <lb/>98. <lb/>Thereafter, in the meeting of the Tribunal on 17 th <lb/>October, 2016, the Tribunal considered several applications filed by <lb/>the parties. They were: (i) the application of PLUS regarding <lb/>averments submitted along with the affidavit of admission/denial of <lb/>documents; (ii) application dated 31 st August, 2016 filed by MSRDC <lb/>for production of documents by PLUS; (iii) application by MSRDC for <lb/>leave to file sur-rejoinder; (iv) application for production of <lb/>documents by PLUS and MSRDC respectively; and (v) application by <lb/>PLUS to file additional documents. After considering all these <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 134 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>applications and passing its order thereon, the Tribunal, inter alia, <lb/>clarified that the remaining schedule as per the amended procedural <lb/>order dated 20 th February, 2016, shall remain the same. In other <lb/>words, the arbitration sittings fixed for cross-examination of <lb/>witnesses from 17 th January, 2017 to 21 st January, 2017 as well as <lb/>for hearing oral arguments from 31 st January, 2017 to 4 th February, <lb/>2017, were to remain unaffected. <lb/>99. <lb/>On reading all the aforesaid procedural orders, two <lb/>things become absolutely clear: (i) both parties, namely, PLUS as <lb/>well as MSRDC were to file their pleadings and evidence in a time-<lb/>bound manner. If any party sought an extension, the same was to be <lb/>granted only in exceptional circumstances and as long as those <lb/>extensions did not materially affect the sittings of the Tribunal that <lb/>were to be held between 17 th January, 2017 to 21 st January, 2017 <lb/>and from 31 st January, 2017 to 4 th February, 2017; (ii) the dates for <lb/>hearing the matter, namely, for cross-examination of witnesses <lb/>(from 17 th January, 2017 to 21 st January, 2017) and for hearing <lb/>oral arguments (from 31 st January, 2017 to 4 th February, 2017) <lb/>were inflexible. This was made abundantly clear by the Tribunal in <lb/>its various procedural orders referred to above. Another thing that <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 135 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>emerges from these procedural orders is that both parties were to <lb/>lead their entire evidence in support of their respective claims. In <lb/>none of these procedural orders was there any indication to either of <lb/>the parties that the proceedings would be bifurcated wherein the <lb/>Tribunal would first decide on issues (a) and (b) set out in <lb/>paragraph 54 of the impugned Award [relating to the validity of the <lb/>termination of the Concession Agreement] and defer the hearing for <lb/>deciding issues (c) and (d) [which related to quantum of the claims <lb/>and Counter Claim]. I may hasten to add that I am not for a moment <lb/>suggesting that the Tribunal could not have done the same, <lb/>especially considering that the Practice Directions that were issued <lb/>by the Tribunal were under section 19(3) of the Act where the <lb/>Tribunal is empowered to decide its own procedure. The only reason <lb/>I am stating this is because the Tribunal insisted on both sides filing <lb/>their complete pleadings as well as leading the entire evidence at <lb/>one go. It was not in contemplation of either of the parties that <lb/>evidence would be led in a piece-meal manner, whereby first it would <lb/>be on the issue of whether there was a valid termination of the <lb/>Concession Agreement and depending on the finding thereof, further <lb/>evidence would be led on the quantum of the claims and Counter <lb/>Claim. In fact, the arguments were also closed on 4 th February, 2017 <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 136 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>and only the passing of the Award was reserved. This will become <lb/>further clear when I refer to the relevant portions of the transcripts <lb/>before the Tribunal on 17 th January, 2017, 20 th January, 2017, 3 rd <lb/>February, 2017 and 4 th February, 2017, respectively. <lb/>100. <lb/>During the hearing on 17 th January, 2017, the counsel <lb/>for MSRDC (MR. KUMAR) sought a clarification as to whether they <lb/>were going to lead evidence on the Counter Claim at the same time <lb/>and whether there would be two separate Awards or there would be <lb/>one Award. The Tribunal clarified that there would only be one <lb/>Award. This was also the understanding of the counsel for PLUS <lb/>(MR. MUKHOPADHAYA). The relevant portion of the aforesaid <lb/>Minutes is reproduced hereunder: <lb/>&quot;MR. KUMAR: <lb/>I want clarification, as per the last <lb/>minutes, there is no clarification as to <lb/>whether we are going to lead evidence <lb/>on the counterclaim at the same time. <lb/>He&apos;s tendering affidavits which are in <lb/>rebuttal for the counterclaim. So, do we <lb/>take it that there&apos;s going to be common <lb/>evidence, because we were not aware <lb/>of that? <lb/>CHAIRMAN: <lb/>Yes, I think so. <lb/>MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: Yes, but normally you wouldn&apos;t expect <lb/>the witness to come back -<lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 137 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>MR. KUMAR: <lb/>No, Sir, because as far as counterclaim <lb/>is my claim and he&apos;s tendering his <lb/>affidavits in rebuttal, I don&apos;t mind. But <lb/>the minutes should then be clear on <lb/>that, that we will have separate awards <lb/>or we&apos;ll have one award. It&apos;s my claim. <lb/>CHAIRMAN: <lb/>One award. <lb/>MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: Consolidated proceedings. <lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>We&apos;ll have one award, we&apos;ll clarify it in <lb/>today&apos;s minutes. <lb/>MR. KUMAR: <lb/>Very well. Then my time constraint will <lb/>change. <lb/>MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: Because as far as time is concerned, I <lb/>want submissions as we all went on the <lb/>basis of a 5-day hearing which is equal <lb/>time two and a half days each, and we <lb/>have to structure our cross-examination <lb/>based on that. I have two witnesses to <lb/>cross-examine, but I must do it in two <lb/>and a half days, whether I do it in less, <lb/>that&apos;s a different matter, but even if I <lb/>can&apos;t take more than that, because <lb/>that&apos;s the basis on which you proceed <lb/>and you finish the cross-examination. <lb/>You don&apos;t have to put every document, <lb/>everything of your case, you have to put <lb/>your main case, you have to make sure <lb/>that you have put the main case. There <lb/>are ancillary points, suggestions, for <lb/>example, we take it is not necessary if <lb/>you don&apos;t give a particular suggestion, <lb/>doesn&apos;t mean that it will be held against <lb/>you, as long as you put your main case. <lb/>You can save time. <lb/>CHAIRMAN: <lb/>We can record that you have not put <lb/>your case for denial, just simply for <lb/>denial. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 138 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>MR. KUMAR: <lb/>No, sir, I understand, there&apos;s no need to. <lb/>But on the last occasion when we met, <lb/>we did not have their affidavit of <lb/>evidence, we only had the pleadings. <lb/>After we have received their affidavit of <lb/>evidence there are several documents <lb/>which have been introduced by way of <lb/>his evidence and there are several <lb/>documents which are incomplete, which <lb/>we want to point out just now and we <lb/>were not aware about the counterclaim. <lb/>We had the understanding that as far as <lb/>the counterclaim is concerned, my <lb/>witness will go in the box and then they <lb/>will step in for rebuttal. <lb/>CHAIRMAN: <lb/>That <lb/>will <lb/>be <lb/>more <lb/>convenient. <lb/>Separately we record this one. <lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>It will only extend the proceedings you <lb/>want to split it into two &quot;proceedings&quot;, it <lb/>will extend the proceedings, time <lb/>constraint, expenses involved, but it&apos;s up <lb/>to you. I thought that will be one <lb/>consolidated proceeding. <lb/>MR. KUMAR: <lb/>Then, sir, personally, I have no objection <lb/>to that. Only thing is that time constraint <lb/>of two and a half days should not apply <lb/>to me. But that&apos;s my only request. I&apos;ll <lb/>try my best to complete. <lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>What time you think -<lb/>MR. KUMAR: <lb/>I would like to then take this entire <lb/>session, because if the counterclaim is <lb/>involved, then I will have to take that <lb/>entire session. <lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>Then we come back to the same <lb/>situation, because it will be -<lb/>MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: We have serious reservations about <lb/>that, because even I have to cross-<lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 139 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>examine on his counterclaim, as also his <lb/>defence, within that two and a half days. <lb/>That&apos;s how it is done always, when we <lb/>do have time restrictions, we have to <lb/>manage our affairs in that way, it is not <lb/>unusual, in fact it is done in every case <lb/>that you do claims and counterclaims to <lb/>the witness in one shot, so the witness <lb/>doesn&apos;t have to come back. So I&apos;m the <lb/>claimant, I&apos;m putting him in rebuttal, as <lb/>we know each other&apos;s case, we know <lb/>which documents are on the record, so <lb/>it is possible to ---<lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>No, but if he says that he needs more <lb/>time, we must allow him to explain his <lb/>position. <lb/>MR. KUMAR: <lb/>I&apos;ll try to keep myself within the two and <lb/>a half, three days period, but as I see <lb/>from the documents, I don&apos;t think that <lb/>will be possible. So I must tell the <lb/>tribunal. I&apos;ll try my best. <lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>We don&apos;t have that manual kind of <lb/>taking down of the witness statement. <lb/>These ladies are going very fast. <lb/>MR. KUMAR: <lb/>That&apos;s right, I know. I&apos;m aware of that. I&apos;ll <lb/>try my best. That&apos;s all I can say. <lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>Please. <lb/>MR. KUMAR: <lb/>Only I&apos;ll request your Lordships to keep <lb/>that in mind that in view of the affidavit <lb/>which <lb/>is <lb/>dealing <lb/>with <lb/>several <lb/>documents, <lb/>there <lb/>are <lb/>some <lb/>inconsistencies between the statement <lb/>of claim and the evidence. I may take <lb/>more time. Now that the counterclaim is <lb/>also introduced, I will have to now deal <lb/>with though he&apos;s taking a risk by calling <lb/>his witness and he is understood the <lb/>counterclaim. For me, I will not object to <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 140 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>that. But to deal with that, it will be a <lb/>different aspect altogether. <lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>Let us proceed. Let us see how it <lb/>unfolds.&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>101. <lb/>Thereafter, the cross-examination continued on 18 th <lb/>January, 2017 and 19 th January, 2017 where the Tribunal <lb/>consistently called upon the counsel for MSRDC to tell them as to <lb/>what would be the reasonable time required to complete the <lb/>evidence on the Counter Claim. In fact, the counsel for PLUS <lb/>submitted before the Tribunal that there was no question of the <lb/>Counter Claim coming later as there were two sets of dates for <lb/>completing the entire proceedings. During the cross-examination, <lb/>on 20 th January, 2017, it appears that the Tribunal was quite <lb/>peeved at the fact that the counsel for MSRDC was not adhering to <lb/>the strict time schedule. The relevant portion of the transcripts of <lb/>20 th January, 2017 read thus: <lb/>&quot;MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>I&apos;m anxious that you complete by the <lb/>lunchtime. I&apos;m feeling a little bad, but <lb/>you seem to be telling us that you just <lb/>don&apos;t care for the schedule fixed by the <lb/>tribunal and you will go as you think best <lb/>and as you please. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 141 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>MR. KUMAR: <lb/>No sir, I&apos;m sorry if I have given you that <lb/>impression. <lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>See the first order. The schedule was in <lb/>presence of both sides with the express <lb/>consent of both sides. You knew the <lb/>magnitude of the case then. Of course, <lb/>you were not there in the first hearing, <lb/>but after you came and you thought that <lb/>this matter may take longer time, you <lb/>could have always asked us, told us that <lb/>this schedule is not realistic, it needs to <lb/>be reviewed. We had fixed five days for <lb/>witnesses examination. Three and a <lb/>half days still over. So what time will he <lb/>get? This will completely change the <lb/>entire schedule. <lb/>We have other commitments. He might <lb/>have other commitments. If you thought <lb/>that this five days for witnesses was not <lb/>realistic, you could have told us, <lb/>requested for a review of the schedule, <lb/>months or weeks ago. <lb/>MR. KUMAR: <lb/>That I should have done. We should <lb/>have done that. I&apos;m sorry about that. <lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>We are at a stage when the whole <lb/>schedule is getting disturbed and, as I <lb/>said, that the order that we passed, the <lb/>first procedural order is practically <lb/>meaningless. <lb/>MR. KUMAR: <lb/>I&apos;ll only say one thing. <lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>If you take four days, he may also say. <lb/>MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: My I make one suggestion? I think that <lb/>even if he finishes by the end of the day <lb/>today and that should be the ultimate <lb/>time limit, no longer than that, I have <lb/>one full day tomorrow. I will complete <lb/>the cross-examination of Mr. Kulkarni, <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 142 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>who&apos;s the main witnesses tomorrow <lb/>itself. On the second witness, who&apos;s Mr. <lb/>Jadhav, he&apos;s speaking on a very limited <lb/>aspect. That is during a period of 14 <lb/>January 2014 to some time in 2015 on <lb/>costs incurred by them, which is in <lb/>relation to the counterclaim only. Maybe <lb/>we don&apos;t even need to cross-examine <lb/>him. I&apos;ll discuss with Mr. Kumar at the <lb/>end of the day on that and see whether <lb/>we can reach an agreement as to what <lb/>the status of his affidavit should be, <lb/>given the time constraints that have <lb/>developed. Otherwise, I mean, anyway, <lb/>I could have done his cross-examination <lb/>about two hours maximum, maybe even <lb/>less. <lb/>But we can dispense with that, if we can <lb/>reach an agreement on -<lb/>MR. KUMAR: <lb/>You have already told me in the <lb/>morning. I&apos;ll talk to the clients about it. <lb/>Sir, I must tell you --<lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>Please don&apos;t misunderstand me. <lb/>MR. KUMAR: <lb/>Not at all, sir. <lb/>MR. JUJSTICE ALAM: <lb/>I respect you and think that you&apos;re <lb/>entitled to your cross-examination but in <lb/>that case, we should have been <lb/>informed earlier. Then we would have <lb/>considered changing the schedule then. <lb/>This leads me to ask, what about the <lb/>hearing dates? <lb/>MR. KUMAR: <lb/>Hearing dates, I must tell you, I will need <lb/>five days. I&apos;m telling you now. <lb/>MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: I have one submission on that. I don&apos;t <lb/>think a hearing of this nature needs five <lb/>days. I think two and a half days each is <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 143 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>more than enough. <lb/>It&apos;s documents <lb/>which are on the record that we have to <lb/>deal with. <lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>Mr. Mukhopadhaya, everyone has his <lb/>own way of making submissions. <lb/>MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: No, there are time constraints to every <lb/>tribunal, time constraints to parties and <lb/>the cost involved in every day&apos;s hearing. <lb/>CHAIRMAN: <lb/>Do you have time for rejoinder in the <lb/>argument? <lb/>MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: I&apos;ll take one and a half hours for <lb/>rejoinder, that&apos;s it. We&apos;ll give written <lb/>submissions after the hearing, so that <lb/>whatever time is --this is done in all <lb/>major arbitrations. <lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>You will make submissions first. <lb/>MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: Yes, as claimant, I would make the <lb/>submissions first. <lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>You will take how much time? <lb/>MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: I will finish in two days maximum, so <lb/>that he can have two and a half days for <lb/>his reply. <lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>We can give you a maximum of three <lb/>days. <lb/>MR. KUMAR: <lb/>I&apos;m telling you now that my request is I <lb/>need five days. <lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>No, we can give you three days and <lb/>after that, you can give us your written <lb/>submissions. <lb/>Kindly <lb/>tailor <lb/>your <lb/>arguments that way.&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 144 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>102. <lb/>In the very same transcript (of 20 th January, 2017), <lb/>during cross-examination, the Tribunal, in fact, made a comment on <lb/>the way the documents were being marked considering that there <lb/>was going to be one consolidated Award. The relevant portion of this <lb/>portion of the transcript of 20 th January, 2017 reads thus: <lb/>&quot;MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>I wish to say something about the <lb/>marking of the documents. If there&apos;s <lb/>going to be one consolidated award, it <lb/>will create a lot of confusion. So kindly <lb/>re-number or re-mark your documents. <lb/>MR. DELHIWALA: <lb/>Only RD three will be a problem. <lb/>MR. KUMAR: <lb/>We said CCD because commercial <lb/>documents. <lb/>MR. TYAGI: <lb/>In RD also it will be only 15 documents, <lb/>because you have filed only till RD15. <lb/>MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: Now 16. <lb/>MR. TYAGI: <lb/>Now 18. So after that, it is only RRDS. <lb/>So it is only about those 18 documents. <lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>Whatever. <lb/>MR. TYAGI: <lb/>We&apos;ll work that out. <lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>Be careful, because I think in the award, <lb/>there will be a lot of confusion. I don&apos;t <lb/>know at what stage somehow or other <lb/>you took it that there would be two <lb/>different proceedings.&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 145 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>103. <lb/>From the aforesaid two transcripts of 17 th January, <lb/>2017 and 20 th January, 2017, it clearly appears that the parties <lb/>were to lead their entire evidence on all issues and the Tribunal was <lb/>going to pass one consolidated Award. This was made clear, not only <lb/>in the transcript of 17 th January, 2017, but also in the transcript of <lb/>20 th January, 2017. Thereafter, the cross-examination continued <lb/>and was completed on the scheduled date of 21 st January, 2017. The <lb/>arguments thereafter commenced as per the schedule laid down by <lb/>the Tribunal. The transcript of 1 st February, 2017, in fact, indicates <lb/>as to how the matter was under progress during oral arguments. <lb/>The parties, in fact, were directed to file their written submissions <lb/>by the dates mentioned in the said transcript. The relevant portion <lb/>of the said transcript of 1 st February, 2017 reads thus: <lb/>&quot;MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>Both of them will submit their respective <lb/>written submissions by 14 th . With liberty <lb/>to file reply to the other side&apos;s by 20 th . <lb/>And then we will decide whether we <lb/>need any clarification or any further <lb/>sittings. <lb/>MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: That&apos;s fair. <lb/>MR. PREMKUMAR: <lb/>Right now, the discipline imposed by the <lb/>schedule, I think we need to follow that <lb/>in terms of completing it and then written <lb/>submissions. <lb/>CHAIRMAN: <lb/>Both of you file your written submissions <lb/>by 14 th and then thereafter you will both <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 146 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>have the occasion to reply to each <lb/>other&apos;s submissions, then we will <lb/>consider whether we need the hearing. <lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>We will consider in two or three days <lb/>and intimate whether we need a further <lb/>hearing or not. <lb/>MR. KUMAR: <lb/>Therefore, he will file submissions, I will <lb/>submissions of what we argue? <lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>With copies to each other. It will be <lb/>open to both of you to file your reply to <lb/>the written submissions filed by the <lb/>other side by 20 th . Definitely by 20 th . <lb/>You may.&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>104. <lb/>On 3 rd February, 2017, the Arbitral Tribunal passed <lb/>certain directions with reference to payment of their fees. The <lb/>relevant portion reads thus: <lb/>&quot;CHAIRMAN: <lb/>Now, we have to issue certain directions <lb/>about the payment of the arbitrators&apos; <lb/>fees. <lb/>You are requested to pay deposit for the <lb/>fees of arbitrators for a period of three <lb/>days working. That is two days for <lb/>internal <lb/>discussion <lb/>among <lb/>the <lb/>arbitrators and one day for the <lb/>pronouncement of the award. <lb/>MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: What about writing of the award itself? <lb/>That also takes time. <lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>Two sittings for that. Third sitting for <lb/>pronouncement. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 147 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>CHAIRMAN: <lb/>So three days&apos; fees for the arbitrators at <lb/>the rate of --<lb/>MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: 50 per cent. <lb/>CHAIRMAN: <lb/>--2 lakhs per arbitrator per day. That to <lb/>be deposited by 28 February.&quot; <lb/>105. <lb/>Then, we come to the transcript of 4 th February, 2017. <lb/>After the hearing was over, on 4 th February, 2017, this is what <lb/>transpired before the Tribunal: <lb/>&quot;17.08 <lb/>We will give that in our submission. <lb/>MR. PREMKUMAR: <lb/>I think in all fairness we will require a <lb/>little more time for this. <lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>If both sides agree, we are willing to sit. <lb/>MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: The problem is the time, really speaking, <lb/>that is the difficulty. If we had booked <lb/>earlier, seven days, eight days, we <lb/>would have kept our diaries open for <lb/>that. <lb/>MR. PREMKUMAR: <lb/>I mention if both sides agree, we can sit <lb/>for a day or something. <lb/>MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: It is better to do it after the submissions. <lb/>MR. PREMKUMAR: <lb/>So that we have more clarity. <lb/>MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: What some tribunals do, if I may <lb/>suggest, before the hearing also if your <lb/>Lordships <lb/>have <lb/>any <lb/>clarification <lb/>questions, <lb/>because <lb/>instead <lb/>of <lb/>addressing everything again, your <lb/>Lordships have heard everything, but if <lb/>there are specific points which your <lb/>Lordships need clarification on, just say <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 148 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>that these are the points on which we <lb/>want clarification, so we are prepared <lb/>with that and it can be a short, focused <lb/>hearing, everything else will be on <lb/>written submissions. If your Lordships <lb/>feel it is necessary we have no difficulty <lb/>with that. <lb/>CHAIRMAN: <lb/>So arguments from both sides are <lb/>closed today. Both sides are given time <lb/>approved, 14 February to file their <lb/>written submissions. <lb/>[Offline discussion] <lb/>CHAIRMAN: <lb/>So your submissions by 20 February <lb/>and thereafter by 27 February you can <lb/>file reply, if any, to these submissions by <lb/>the other side. Thereafter, if we feel that <lb/>it requires some hearing clarifications <lb/>after going through your submissions, <lb/>the date will be fixed for the further <lb/>hearing if any required. <lb/>MR. KUMAR: <lb/>Sir, my request would be that in case <lb/>you do decide to hold the hearing, <lb/>between 25 March and 5 April, I will <lb/>have a difficulty. <lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM: <lb/>The date will be fixed only by consent. <lb/>CHAIRMAN: <lb/>We are closed for the day. <lb/>MR. KUMAR: <lb/>We are grateful to your Lordships for at <lb/>least tolerating us. It is a pleasure <lb/>appearing before your Lordships. And I <lb/>must thank my learned friend. <lb/>CHAIRMAN: <lb/>Both sides helped us very well. <lb/>(5:14 p.m.) <lb/>(The hearing concluded)&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 149 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>106. <lb/>What is clear from this transcript is that arguments <lb/>from both sides were closed and both sides were given time to file <lb/>their written submissions. <lb/>After going through the written <lb/>submissions, if the Tribunal felt that it required any hearing for <lb/>clarifications, a date would be fixed for a further hearing. In fact, <lb/>this transcript makes it very clear that after going through the <lb/>submissions given by the parties, if the Tribunal required any <lb/>clarification in relation thereto, it would fix a further focused <lb/>hearing. <lb/>107. <lb/>When one reads the procedural orders set out earlier <lb/>along with the transcripts referred to above, it becomes clear that on <lb/>4 th February, 2017, all arguments were concluded and all evidence <lb/>was led and all that was required to be done was to pass an Award. <lb/>After going through the submissions of the parties, if the Tribunal <lb/>felt that it required any clarification, only then it would fix a further <lb/>hearing. On reading these procedural orders and transcripts, I find <lb/>that it was never in contemplation, either of the parties or the <lb/>Tribunal, that the proceedings would be bifurcated wherein the <lb/>Tribunal would pass an Interim Award, first deciding on the issue of <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 150 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>termination of the Concession Agreement and thereafter defer the <lb/>hearing on the question of quantum of the respective claims. The <lb/>way the matter has proceeded before the Tribunal, it is quite clear to <lb/>me that parties were directed to lead their entire evidence on all <lb/>issues, including the quantum, and the arguments also proceeded on <lb/>that basis. I, therefore, fail to see as to what was the need to <lb/>bifurcate the proceedings by first passing an Interim Award on the <lb/>issue of termination and thereafter defer the hearing on the <lb/>question of quantum. I am not for a moment suggesting that an <lb/>Arbitral Tribunal is not empowered to do so. It certainly does. In <lb/>fact, in the present case, if the Tribunal had simply said that they <lb/>want to hear further arguments on the question of quantum <lb/>[without suo-moto giving liberty to the parties to file fresh pleadings <lb/>and lead further evidence], I do not think there could have been any <lb/>objection to the bifurcation of the proceedings as set out in the <lb/>Interim Award. However, that is not the case. What the Tribunal <lb/>has done in the impugned Award is allowed the parties to file fresh <lb/>pleadings and lead further evidence in the second stage of the <lb/>arbitration. In fact, after considering the evidence and submissions <lb/>of the parties, the Tribunal rejected certain specific claims of PLUS <lb/>and expressed its inability to decide the other claims on the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 151 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>available evidence. It is even the case of PLUS that it had produced <lb/>all the evidence in support of its case and never made any request to <lb/>the Tribunal for leading any further evidence. Despite this, when it <lb/>came to the issue of Termination Payment, both under clause <lb/>29.9(c) and clause 32.4.2, the Tribunal in the Interim Award, inter <lb/>alia, held that prima facie Termination Payment payable to PLUS <lb/>would have to be decided on the element of proportionality in the <lb/>working of the Termination Payment clause. The Tribunal noticed <lb/>that MSRDC had strongly contested the Termination Payment also <lb/>on the ground of each individual head that is to be calculated under <lb/>the formula and it would be beneficial to the Tribunal to invite <lb/>further hearings and submissions on this issue. As far as the <lb/>alternative to the claim for Termination Payment (of Rs.469 crores) <lb/>is concerned, the Tribunal was of the opinion that since it was <lb/>deferring its decision on the issue of Termination Payment, the <lb/>decision on the alternative claim also ought to stand deferred. <lb/>Paragraphs 72 and 73 of the impugned Award clarifies the above <lb/>position. The said paragraphs read thus: <lb/>&quot;72. As regards Termination Payment, both under Clause <lb/>29.9 and Clause 32.4.2, an issue arises as to whether <lb/>such payment becomes ipso facto payable in the event of <lb/>a termination, without regard to either the stage at which <lb/>the Agreement is terminated or the losses caused to the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 152 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>Claimant / Concessionaire. To take an example, if the <lb/>Agreement were to be terminated at the inception stage <lb/>(say, for example, after a mere seven months post the <lb/>COD), would such termination attract the same <lb/>Termination Payment as a case where the Concessionaire <lb/>has been collecting toll for the entire duration of the toll <lb/>notification, and elects to terminate the Agreement on the <lb/>very last day of the toll collection period, having exhausted <lb/>its revenue stream. This is particularly relevant because <lb/>many of the costs in such projects may be incurred up-<lb/>front, or at any rate, may be front-loaded. Therefore a <lb/>termination in the early stages of the Agreement, would <lb/>arguably leave a Concessionaire stranded having incurred <lb/>significant costs, and not having had the opportunity to <lb/>recover any revenue. But a termination on the last date of <lb/>the subsistence of a toll notification finds the <lb/>Concessionaire in a position where he has finished <lb/>collecting revenue for a period of several years, as per the <lb/>original toll notification. Should two such cases be treated <lb/>the same, inasmuch as should the same Termination <lb/>Payment be payable -as a mechanical application of the <lb/>formula in the Agreement. Prima facie, the Tribunal would <lb/>need to be satisfied about the element of proportionality in <lb/>the working of the Termination Payment clause. We <lb/>notice that the MSRDC has strongly contested the <lb/>Termination Payment also on the ground of each <lb/>individual head that is to be calculated under the formula, <lb/>and it would be beneficial to the Tribunal to invite further <lb/>hearing and submissions on this issue. <lb/>73. As an alternative to its claim for Termination Payment, <lb/>the Claimant has also made a claim of approximately <lb/>Rs.469 crore, based on amounts invested by shareholders <lb/>and an assumed return of 14.74%. This alternative claim <lb/>is virtually a proxy claim for Termination Payment, but <lb/>calculated not as per the contractual formula, but based <lb/>on the actual amount invested by shareholders. Since the <lb/>Tribunal is inclined to defer its decision on the issue of <lb/>Termination Payment, the decision on this alternative <lb/>claim of Rs.469 crore approximately also stands deferred.&quot; <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 153 of 169 <lb/>108. <lb/>Thereafter, the Tribunal deals with the claim for Rs.112 <lb/>crores which claim the Tribunal records is largely predicated and <lb/>premised on the alleged admissions of liability (and quantum) made <lb/>by MSRDC and recorded in the Director&apos;s Report of July, 2011. The <lb/>objection taken with reference to these admissions by MSRDC was <lb/>that all the alleged admissions were made during conciliation <lb/>proceedings and hence were inadmissible. Despite over-ruling this <lb/>objection, the Tribunal opined that it was still required to determine <lb/>what weight could be attached to these documents as evidence of an <lb/>admitted quantum of loss. The Tribunal was of the view that it would <lb/>be unfair on MSRDC to determine the issue of quantum with <lb/>reference to the figures quoted during settlement discussions. The <lb/>Tribunal did not agree with PLUS that the figures cited in the IC&apos;s <lb/>correspondence necessarily reflected any independent analysis or <lb/>calculation of loss, either by the IC or MSRDC. The Tribunal was <lb/>prima facie of the view that these figures were put forward by PLUS&apos; <lb/>representatives and accepted (with minor modifications) by the IC. <lb/>In fact, the Tribunal noted that initially on the specific issue of <lb/>&apos;additional direct cost&apos;, PLUS&apos; representative put forward a figure of <lb/>Rs.162.37 crores, which was then accepted by the IC with minor <lb/>modifications as the revised project cost of Rs.161.19 crores. The <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 154 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>Tribunal also further noted that a huge difference in the revised <lb/>project cost first projected by PLUS on 24 th February, 2010 and the <lb/>other put forward by its representative (as recorded in the letter <lb/>dated 23 rd June, 2011) is itself indicative of the fact that figures <lb/>quoted in the correspondence have themselves fluctuated with time <lb/>and that too, quite significantly. This, according to the Tribunal, was <lb/>further indicative of the fact that these figures were proposed by <lb/>either side in the spirit of settlement while they were trying to work <lb/>out a rough and ready compromise. It is in these circumstances that <lb/>the Tribunal was of the opinion that it would not be fair on their part <lb/>to place much weight on the quantum figures exchanged by the <lb/>parties while working out a settlement. According to the Tribunal, <lb/>these figures did not constitute admissions of quantum of liability. <lb/>The Tribunal thereafter also opined that PLUS had made its claim <lb/>for damages of Rs.112 crores in addition to its claim for Termination <lb/>Payment. Prima facie, the Tribunal was of the view that this claim <lb/>can only be in the alternative. If PLUS was to satisfy the Tribunal <lb/>that Termination Payment is payable, then that would exhaust all <lb/>reliefs and would be to the exclusion of other reliefs that PLUS had <lb/>made under section 73 of the Contract Act or otherwise. If, on the <lb/>other hand, the Tribunal ultimately reached the conclusion that <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 155 of 169 <lb/>Termination Payment was not payable (despite there being a valid <lb/>termination), then, it would be for PLUS to prove and quantify the <lb/>loss that it had suffered and claim damages on that basis. The <lb/>Tribunal was, therefore, not inclined at that stage to award Rs.112 <lb/>crores in damages based on the alleged admissions of MSRDC. The <lb/>Tribunal was, therefore, of the view that even on this issue, further <lb/>hearings and submissions were required. It was clarified that in <lb/>making these submissions, PLUS need not be restricted to the <lb/>amounts allegedly admitted by MSRDC, but may even claim <lb/>amounts higher than that, should it be allowed to do so. However, it <lb/>would need to prove and quantify its loss by leading appropriate <lb/>evidence, if necessary. Similarly, MSRDC was not bound by any <lb/>alleged admissions and was free to independently reject PLUS&apos; claim <lb/>for damages, including by way of leading appropriate evidence, if <lb/>necessary. It is thereafter highlighted in paragraph 86 of the Award <lb/>that while deferring the quantum issue to a second stage, the <lb/>Tribunal is very mindful of the fact that such a second phase of the <lb/>arbitration is likely to involve both time and expense. The Tribunal <lb/>further holds that this is unavoidable in the circumstances as the <lb/>Tribunal cannot arrive at a quantum determination based on the <lb/>existing record and submissions. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 156 of 169 <lb/></note>

			<body>109. <lb/>It is all these parts of the Award and which I have set out <lb/>earlier, to which Mr. Chagla has taken strong objection and in which <lb/>I find considerable merit. As mentioned earlier, the arbitration <lb/>proceedings had commenced and continued before the Arbitral <lb/>Tribunal on the basis that the entire evidence was led by both <lb/>parties. In fact, the written submissions also filed before the <lb/>Tribunal by both parties would reflect the same. If the Tribunal was <lb/>not satisfied with the evidence led by either of the parties, it ought to <lb/>have rejected the claims on which the evidence was inadequate. <lb/>After making the parties lead their entire evidence, the Tribunal <lb/>could not have allowed either party to lead further evidence to <lb/>substantiate their claims when neither party made any such <lb/>request. If the Tribunal was of the opinion that the evidence was <lb/>inadequate, either to grant any claim of PLUS or any Counter Claim <lb/>of MSRDC, it ought to have rejected the claim / Counter Claim, as the <lb/>case may be. This entire exercise by the Tribunal of suo-moto <lb/>allowing the parties to lead further evidence, once the evidence was <lb/>closed and final arguments were also concluded, to my mind, clearly <lb/>vitiates the Award in so far as it allows parties to file fresh pleadings <lb/>and lead further evidence. The Tribunal has no power to allow a <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 157 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>party to lead further evidence after the evidence is closed without <lb/>the concerned party seeking leave of the Tribunal to lead further <lb/>evidence in that regard. I say this because if an application to lead <lb/>further evidence [after it is closed] is made by either party, the <lb/>Arbitral Tribunal would be bound to permit the other party to <lb/>respond to the same and thereafter render its decision thereon. <lb/>Failing to do so [i.e. granting the opposite party an opportunity to <lb/>contest the application for leading further evidence] would itself <lb/>render the Award vulnerable inter alia on the ground of breach of <lb/>principles of natural justice. The Tribunal, after the evidence is <lb/>closed, cannot suo-moto allow either party to lead further evidence <lb/>merely to accommodate a party to improve its case. That would be <lb/>contrary to all principles of fair play in any adversarial litigation <lb/>and would be in breach of the provisions of section 18 of the Act. In <lb/>the present case, the situation would have been quite different if the <lb/>Tribunal had made it clear to the parties that they need to lead <lb/>evidence only with reference to the issue of termination first, and <lb/>depending on the answer to the aforesaid issue, further evidence <lb/>would be allowed to be led by the parties regarding the quantum. <lb/>The situation would also have been different if the Tribunal had <lb/>bifurcated the proceedings to hear further arguments on the <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 158 of 169 <lb/>quantum issue on the basis of the evidence already led by the <lb/>parties. However, that is not the case. The parties led their entire <lb/>evidence before the Tribunal and arguments were also canvassed in <lb/>relation thereto. Evidence was led not only with reference to <lb/>termination but also with reference to the quantum of each claim. In <lb/>other words, the parties proceeded before the Tribunal on the basis <lb/>that all issues would be decided by the Tribunal at one and the same <lb/>time and that they had presented their entire evidence and case <lb/>before the Tribunal. This being the situation, the Tribunal, on its <lb/>own, could not allow either party to lead further evidence, after the <lb/>evidence was already closed and all arguments were also canvassed <lb/>and written submissions filed. I am therefore of the view that the <lb/>Award is vitiated to the extent that it allows the parties to file fresh <lb/>pleadings and lead further evidence in the second stage of the <lb/>arbitration. <lb/>110. <lb/>I am unable to agree with the submission of Mr. <lb/>Khambatta that all this was done primarily for the benefit of MSRDC <lb/>and, therefore, it does not lie in their mouth to complain of the <lb/>procedure adopted by the Tribunal. Firstly, from the Award itself, it <lb/>is clear that with relation to Termination Payment, the Tribunal was <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 159 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>of the opinion that it would have to consider whether payment <lb/>under clause 29.9(c) or 32.4.2 ought to be mechanically granted to <lb/>PLUS or whether it ought to be done on the basis of proportionality. <lb/>If Mr. Khambatta is correct that in relation to Termination Payment, <lb/>the evidence was already on record, nothing stopped the Tribunal <lb/>from ruling in favour of PLUS on the aforesaid issue. However, <lb/>obviously the view of the Tribunal was different. It is in these <lb/>circumstances and taking into consideration the objections laid out <lb/>by MSRDC that the Tribunal felt that the question of proportionality <lb/>has to be gone into. <lb/>111. <lb/>Even as far as the claim for damages of Rs.112 crores is <lb/>concerned, the Tribunal was clearly of the view that PLUS had based <lb/>the aforesaid claim primarily on the admissions made by MSRDC <lb/>and on which not much weightage could be applied considering that <lb/>those admissions were made in the spirit of settlement. The <lb/>Tribunal, therefore, held that PLUS would have to independently <lb/>lead evidence to substantiate those claims. PLUS, clearly had not <lb/>asked for any permission of the Tribunal to lead any further <lb/>evidence. If PLUS was not interested in leading any further <lb/>evidence, the Tribunal ought to have rejected the claim of PLUS if it <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 160 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>was dissatisfied with the evidence already led by PLUS on the <lb/>aforesaid claim. The Tribunal could not have, on its own, given <lb/>liberty to the parties to lead further evidence on the aforesaid claim. <lb/>112. <lb/>Similar is the case of the Counter Claim filed by MSRDC. <lb/>MSRDC too had led all its evidence with reference to its Counter <lb/>Claim and had even made oral arguments in relation thereto. <lb/>MSRDC too had filed its written submissions before the Arbitral <lb/>Tribunal. Despite this, I fail to understand as to how the Tribunal <lb/>has come to a finding that it is deferring its decision on the Counter <lb/>Claim as adequate time had not been dedicated to the Counter Claim. <lb/>In fact, the transcripts reflect that the counsel for MSRDC had <lb/>consistently been asking for further time which was refused and was <lb/>asked to complete, not only the cross-examination, but also his <lb/>arguments in the time-frame set out by the Tribunal. Once, having <lb/>fixed those dates and which clearly the Tribunal held as inflexible, I <lb/>fail to see how the Tribunal has come to the conclusion that <lb/>inadequate time was devoted to the Counter Claim filed by MSRDC. <lb/>The entire procedure followed by the Tribunal in relation to <lb/>deferring the claim for quantum at a later date by allowing the <lb/>parties to lead further evidence and file fresh pleadings is patently <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 161 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">illegal and cannot be allowed to stand. As mentioned earlier, <lb/>considering that the procedure in relation to the arbitration <lb/>proceedings was laid down by the Tribunal under section 19(3) of <lb/>the Act, there would be nothing wrong if the Tribunal had bifurcated <lb/>the proceedings to hear further arguments on the quantum issues <lb/>[with reference to the claims of PLUS as well as the Counter Claim of <lb/>MSRDC] on the basis of the evidence already led by the parties and <lb/>the existing record before the Tribunal. However, to defer the <lb/>decision on the quantum of each claim filed by PLUS as well as the <lb/>Counter Claim filed by MSRDC to enable parties to file fresh <lb/>pleadings and lead further evidence is patently illegal and wholly <lb/>unacceptable. <lb/>113. <lb/>I must mention that the Supreme Court in the case of <lb/>Associate Builders Vs. Delhi Development Authority [(2015) 3 <lb/>SCC 49] has held that &quot;the juristic principle of a &quot;judicial approach&quot; demands <lb/>that a decision be fair, reasonable and objective. On the obverse side, anything <lb/>arbitrary and whimsical would obviously not be a determination which would <lb/>either be fair, reasonable or objective.&quot; The relevant portion of this <lb/>decision reads thus:-<lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 162 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>&quot;Fundamental Policy of Indian Law <lb/>27. Coming to each of the heads contained in Saw Pipes [(2003) 5 SCC <lb/>705 : AIR 2003 SC 2629] judgment, we will first deal with the head <lb/>&quot;fundamental policy of Indian law&quot;. It has already been seen <lb/>from Renusagar [Renusagar Power Co. Ltd. v. General Electric Co., 1994 <lb/>Supp (1) SCC 644] judgment that violation of the Foreign Exchange Act <lb/>and disregarding orders of superior courts in India would be regarded as <lb/>being contrary to the fundamental policy of Indian law. To this it could be <lb/>added that the binding effect of the judgment of a superior court being <lb/>disregarded would be equally violative of the fundamental policy of <lb/>Indian law. <lb/>28. In a recent judgment, ONGC Ltd. v. Western Geco International <lb/>Ltd. [(2014) 9 SCC 263 : (2014) 5 SCC (Civ) 12] , this Court added three <lb/>other distinct and fundamental juristic principles which must be <lb/>understood as a part and parcel of the fundamental policy of Indian law. <lb/>The Court held: (SCC pp. 278-80, paras 35 &amp; 38-40) <lb/>&quot;35. What then would constitute the &apos;fundamental policy of Indian law&apos; is <lb/>the question. The decision in ONGC [(2003) 5 SCC 705 : AIR 2003 SC <lb/>2629] does not elaborate that aspect. Even so, the expression must, in <lb/>our opinion, include all such fundamental principles as providing a basis <lb/>for administration of justice and enforcement of law in this country. <lb/>Without meaning to exhaustively enumerate the purport of the <lb/>expression &apos;fundamental policy of Indian law&apos;, we may refer to three <lb/>distinct and fundamental juristic principles that must necessarily be <lb/>understood as a part and parcel of the fundamental policy of Indian law. <lb/>The first and foremost is the principle that in every determination <lb/>whether by a court or other authority that affects the rights of a citizen or <lb/>leads to any civil consequences, the court or authority concerned is <lb/>bound to adopt what is in legal parlance called a &apos;judicial approach&apos; in <lb/>the matter. The duty to adopt a judicial approach arises from the very <lb/>nature of the power exercised by the court or the authority does not have <lb/>to be separately or additionally enjoined upon the fora concerned. What <lb/>must be remembered is that the importance of a judicial approach in <lb/>judicial and quasi-judicial determination lies in the fact that so long as <lb/>the court, tribunal or the authority exercising powers that affect the rights <lb/>or obligations of the parties before them shows fidelity to judicial <lb/>approach, they cannot act in an arbitrary, capricious or whimsical <lb/>manner. Judicial approach ensures that the authority acts bona fide and <lb/>deals with the subject in a fair, reasonable and objective manner and <lb/>that its decision is not actuated by any extraneous consideration. <lb/></body>

			<front>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 163 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Judicial approach in that sense acts as a check against flaws and faults <lb/>that can render the decision of a court, tribunal or authority vulnerable to <lb/>challenge. <lb/>*** <lb/>38. Equally important and indeed fundamental to the policy of Indian law <lb/>is the principle that a court and so also a quasi-judicial authority must, <lb/>while determining the rights and obligations of parties before it, do so in <lb/>accordance with the principles of natural justice. Besides the <lb/>celebrated audi alteram partem rule one of the facets of the principles of <lb/>natural justice is that the court/authority deciding the matter must apply <lb/>its mind to the attendant facts and circumstances while taking a view <lb/>one way or the other. Non-application of mind is a defect that is fatal to <lb/>any adjudication. Application of mind is best demonstrated by disclosure <lb/>of the mind and disclosure of mind is best done by recording reasons in <lb/>support of the decision which the court or authority is taking. The <lb/>requirement that an adjudicatory authority must apply its mind is, in that <lb/>view, so deeply embedded in our jurisprudence that it can be described <lb/>as a fundamental policy of Indian law. <lb/>39. No less important is the principle now recognised as a salutary <lb/>juristic fundamental in administrative law that a decision which is <lb/>perverse or so irrational that no reasonable person would have arrived at <lb/>the same will not be sustained in a court of law. Perversity or irrationality <lb/>of decisions is tested on the touchstone of Wednesbury [Associated <lb/>Provincial Picture Houses Ltd. v. Wednesbury Corpn., (1948) 1 KB 223 : <lb/>(1947) 2 All ER 680 (CA)] principle of reasonableness. Decisions that fall <lb/>short of the standards of reasonableness are open to challenge in a <lb/>court of law often in writ jurisdiction of the superior courts but no less in <lb/>statutory processes wherever the same are available. <lb/>40. It is neither necessary nor proper for us to attempt an exhaustive <lb/>enumeration of what would constitute the fundamental policy of Indian <lb/>law nor is it possible to place the expression in the straitjacket of a <lb/>definition. What is important in the context of the case at hand is that if <lb/>on facts proved before them the arbitrators fail to draw an inference <lb/>which ought to have been drawn or if they have drawn an inference <lb/>which is on the face of it, untenable resulting in miscarriage of justice, <lb/>the adjudication even when made by an Arbitral Tribunal that enjoys <lb/>considerable latitude and play at the joints in making awards will be <lb/>open to challenge and may be cast away or modified depending upon <lb/>whether the offending part is or is not severable from the rest.&quot; <lb/>(emphasis in original) <lb/>29. It is clear that the juristic principle of a &quot;judicial approach&quot; demands <lb/>that a decision be fair, reasonable and objective. On the obverse side, <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 164 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>anything arbitrary and whimsical would obviously not be a determination <lb/>which would either be fair, reasonable or objective. <lb/>30. The audi alteram partem principle which undoubtedly is a <lb/>fundamental juristic principle in Indian law is also contained in Sections <lb/>18 and 34(2)(a)(iii) of the Arbitration and Conciliation Act. These sections <lb/>read as follows: <lb/>&quot;18.Equal treatment of parties.-The parties shall be treated with <lb/>equality and each party shall be given a full opportunity to present his <lb/>case. <lb/>*** <lb/>34.Application for setting aside arbitral award.-(1)*** <lb/>(2) An arbitral award may be set aside by the court only if-<lb/>(a) the party making the application furnishes proof that-<lb/>*** <lb/>(iii) the party making the application was not given proper notice of the <lb/>appointment of an arbitrator or of the arbitral proceedings or was <lb/>otherwise unable to present his case;&quot; <lb/>************* <lb/>34. It is with this very important caveat that the two fundamental <lb/>principles which form part of the fundamental policy of Indian law (that <lb/>the arbitrator must have a judicial approach and that he must not act <lb/>perversely) are to be understood. <lb/>************* <lb/>Justice <lb/>36. The third ground of public policy is, if an award is against justice or <lb/>morality. These are two different concepts in law. An award can be said to <lb/>be against justice only when it shocks the conscience of the court. An <lb/>illustration of this can be given. A claimant is content with restricting his <lb/>claim, let us say to Rs 30 lakhs in a statement of claim before the <lb/>arbitrator and at no point does he seek to claim anything more. The <lb/>arbitral award ultimately awards him Rs 45 lakhs without any acceptable <lb/>reason or justification. Obviously, this would shock the conscience of the <lb/>court and the arbitral award would be liable to be set aside on the <lb/>ground that it is contrary to &quot;justice&quot;.&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 165 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">In the case of SSANGYONG Engineering and Construction Co. Ltd. <lb/>Vs. National Highways Authority of India (NHAI) [(2019) 15 <lb/>SCC 131] the Supreme Court has also explained the observations of <lb/>Associate Builders and had inter alia opined that a decision which is <lb/>perverse, will no longer being a ground for challenge under &quot;public <lb/>policy of India&quot;, but would certainly be a patent illegality appearing <lb/>on the face of the Award. The observations of the Supreme Court in <lb/>both these decisions would certainly apply to the facts of the present <lb/>case and hence I have no hesitation in holding that the Impugned <lb/>Award is vitiated to the extent that it allows the parties to file fresh <lb/>pleadings and lead further evidence in the second stage of the <lb/>arbitration. <lb/>114. <lb/>Before concluding it would only be fair to deal with the <lb/>judgements relied upon by Mr. Khambatta and referred to earlier. I <lb/>find that the reliance placed by Mr. Khambatta on the decision of the <lb/>Supreme Court in the case of McDermott International Inc. Vs <lb/>Burn Standard Co. Ltd. and Ors. [(2006) 11 Supreme Court <lb/>Cases 181] is wholly misplaced. There is no dispute on the <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 166 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>proposition that the Arbitral Tribunal certainly has the power to <lb/>pass an Interim Award /Partial Award if it so chooses to do. This <lb/>power is statutorily given to the Arbitral Tribunal even under <lb/>section 31(6) of the Act. However, that is not the issue before me. <lb/>As mentioned earlier, the entire evidence of the parties was led <lb/>before the Tribunal prior to the passing of the impugned Interim <lb/>Award. In such a situation, the Arbitral Tribunal could not have <lb/>passed an Interim Award determining the validity of the <lb/>termination notices issued by PLUS and deferred the hearing for <lb/>deciding the issue of quantum of each claim/Counter Claim at a later <lb/>date by allowing the parties to file fresh pleadings and lead further <lb/>evidence. It is this action of the Arbitral Tribunal that I find <lb/>objectionable. The power of the Tribunal to pass an Interim/ Partial <lb/>Award is certainly there and given by the Statute itself. Under what <lb/>circumstances it is to be exercised, would certainly depend on how <lb/>the arbitration has proceeded either as per the agreement between <lb/>the parties or the procedure evolved by the Arbitral Tribunal. The <lb/>reliance, therefore, placed by Mr. Khambatta on the aforesaid <lb/>decision is of no assistance to PLUS. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 167 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<body>115. <lb/>Even the decision of the Division Bench of this Court <lb/>relied upon by Mr. Khambatta in the case of Manganese Ore <lb/>(India) Ltd. &amp; Ors. Vs. Ram Bahadur Thakur Limited [2006 SCC <lb/>Online Bom. 507] is wholly misconceived. The facts of this case <lb/>would clearly reveal that the learned arbitrator made an Interim <lb/>Award and held that the appellant had committed breach of the said <lb/>agreement by failing to supply 15,000 metric tonnes of manganese <lb/>ore of 46/48% grade as required under the contract and that the <lb/>respondent was entitled to recover from the appellant damages, if <lb/>any, by reason of breach of the contract. The learned arbitrator <lb/>further held that no evidence on the quantum of damages could be <lb/>led before him unless he first came to the conclusion that there was <lb/>a breach of contract committed by the appellant, and therefore, <lb/>fixed the date for further hearing for the purpose of enabling the <lb/>parties to lead evidence on the question of damages. It was in this <lb/>factual scenario that the Division Bench of this Court took a view <lb/>that in such circumstances the procedure adopted by the arbitrator <lb/>could not be faulted. The facts of this case would reveal that the <lb/>parties had led no evidence whatsoever on the quantum of damages <lb/>as the arbitrator (in the Interim Award) was only deciding whether <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/>SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/>Page 168 of 169 <lb/>in fact there was a breach of the agreement. Only once he came to <lb/>that conclusion, he gave liberty to the parties to lead evidence on the <lb/>question of quantum. The facts of the case before me are however <lb/>totally different. In the present case, the parties led their entire <lb/>evidence, not only with reference to the validity of the termination <lb/>notices issued by PLUS but also on the quantum of each <lb/>claim/Counter Claim. Once this was done and the evidence was <lb/>closed by the Tribunal, without there being any application for <lb/>leading further evidence, the Tribunal could not have suo-moto <lb/>allowed the parties to file fresh pleadings and lead further evidence <lb/>in support of their respective claims. This being the case, I find that <lb/>the reliance placed on the aforesaid decision is also wholly <lb/>misplaced. <lb/>116. <lb/>In view of the foregoing discussion:-<lb/>(i) <lb/>The challenge to Interim Award dated 25 th April, <lb/>2017 on the ground that the Arbitral Tribunal relied <lb/>upon evidence which was inadmissible in law is <lb/>rejected; <lb/>(ii) The challenge to the Interim Award upholding the <lb/>validity of the termination of the Concession <lb/>Agreement dated 25 th August, 2006, under clause <lb/>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: <lb/>CARBP371.17.doc <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SR Pasha, Sr PS <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 169 of 169 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">29.8 [Force Majeure Event] is rejected; <lb/>(iii) The Interim Award is set aside in so far as it <lb/>upholds the termination of the Concession <lb/>Agreement dated 25 th August, 2006 under clauses <lb/>32.4.1(1) and 32.4.1(3) [for material default of <lb/>MSRDC]. However, as mentioned earlier, this would <lb/>make little difference to the termination of the <lb/>Concession Agreement as the termination under <lb/>Clause 29.8 is upheld, and therefore, the Concession <lb/>Agreement dated 25 th August, 2006 validly stands <lb/>terminated; <lb/>(iv) The Interim Award is set aside in so far as it <lb/>permits the parties to file fresh pleadings and lead <lb/>further evidence in the second stage of the <lb/>arbitration. <lb/>117. <lb/>The Arbitration Petition is disposed of in the aforesaid <lb/>terms. However, there shall be no order as to costs. <lb/>118. <lb/>All parties to act on an authenticated copy of this order <lb/>duly signed by the Private Secretary/Personal Assistant/Associate <lb/>of this Court. <lb/>B.P. COLABAWALLA, J. <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 ::: </note>


	</text>
</tei>
