<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="47bd1f45457ab1ea0d80f2d977b05ca7"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/></reference>

	CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>SR Pasha, Sr PS<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Page 8 of 169<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">and after removing the defects, if any. The provisional completion<lb/> certificate came to be issued to PLUS on 22 nd June, 2009, subject to<lb/> certain terms and conditions. In the meantime, the Government of<lb/> Maharashtra issued a Toll Notification on 13 th August, 2009,<lb/> authorizing PLUS to collect and retain the Toll from 22 nd August,<lb/> 2009 till 28 th April, 2013. In a meeting held on 23 rd October, 2009<lb/> between PLUS and MSRDC, it was decided that the date of the<lb/> provisional completion certificate would be deemed to be 22 nd<lb/></div>

	<reference>August, 2009.<lb/> 10.<lb/> Thereafter, on 30 th October, 2009, MSRDC granted PLUS<lb/> an extension of the construction period until 29 th December, 2009,<lb/></reference>

	which was an extension of 674 days from the original schedule<lb/> Project completion date. As there was a delay in completion of the<lb/> construction of the Project, PLUS addressed a letter to MSRDC and<lb/> the IC, inter alia, requesting MSRDC to pay a sum of Rs.161.65<lb/> crores (being the difference between the actual cost incurred by<lb/> PLUS and the original Project cost) towards additional direct cost<lb/> incurred due to the alleged material default of the Concession<lb/>
	<reference>Agreement by MSRDC as well as a Force Majeure Event. Thereafter,<lb/> on 16 th April, 2010, PLUS, while referring to its letter dated 24 th<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/></reference>

	CARBP371.17.doc<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>SR Pasha, Sr PS<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Page 9 of 169<lb/>
	<date>February, 2010</date>

	<div type="abstract">, inter alia, stated that it was seeking compensation<lb/> for all additional direct costs suffered and incurred by it and called<lb/> upon MSRDC to pay the purported dues for which it provided the<lb/> certificate from the statutory auditors. According to MSRDC, since<lb/> disputes arose between the parties, PLUS, by its letter dated 10 th<lb/> May, 2010, called upon the IC to act in accordance with clause<lb/> 39.1(b) of the Concession Agreement and referred six claims to it<lb/> for conciliation. I must note that this is seriously disputed by PLUS<lb/> as, according to it, only one claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; was<lb/> referred to the IC under clause 39.1(b) and not all six claims. I will<lb/> deal with this aspect later in my judgment.<lb/> 11.<lb/> Be that as it may, the IC, by its letter dated 15 th May,<lb/> 2010, agreed to act as a Mediator in accordance with clause 39.1(b).<lb/> Thereafter, several meetings were held and correspondence was<lb/> exchanged between the parties for the purpose of and in pursuance<lb/> of the request for conciliation/mediation. Finally, MSRDC and PLUS<lb/> forwarded a joint proposal to the Government of Maharashtra for its<lb/> consideration. During the pendency of the said proposal, PLUS, by<lb/> its two letters dated 19 th March, 2013 terminated the Concession<lb/></div>

	Agreement. However, PLUS did not stop collecting Toll from the<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/>
	<keyword>CARBP371.17.doc<lb/></keyword>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>SR Pasha, Sr PS<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Page 10 of 169<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">said date and vide its letters dated 8 th April, 2013 and 22 nd April,<lb/> 2013 requested for an amicable settlement.<lb/> The Concession<lb/> Agreement thereafter came to an end on 28 th April, 2013. PLUS,<lb/> therefore, by its letter dated 25 th April, 2014, made a reference of all<lb/> disputes and differences, including the Counter Claim between<lb/> MSRDC and PLUS to the Vice Chairman and Managing Director of<lb/> MSRDC. Thereafter, several discussions and meetings took place<lb/> between the parties. As the disputes could not be resolved, PLUS, by<lb/> its letter dated 31 st July, 2015, invoked arbitration and appointed<lb/> the Hon&apos;ble Mr. Justice Aftab Alam (Retired) as their nominee<lb/> Arbitrator. On the other hand, MSRDC by its letter dated 27 th<lb/> August, 2015, appointed Mr. R.M. Premkumar (Retired), an IAS<lb/> Officer, as their Nominee Arbitrator and all disputes and differences<lb/> were referred to arbitration. Thereafter, the Indian Council for<lb/> Arbitrators, by their letter dated 15 th December, 2015, appointed<lb/> the Hon&apos;ble Mr. Justice Shafee Syed Parkar (Retired) as the<lb/> Presiding Arbitrator. Accordingly, the Arbitral Tribunal was duly<lb/> constituted.<lb/></div>

	CARBP371.17.doc<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>SR Pasha, Sr PS<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Page 16 of 169<lb/> impermissible in law. To substantiate this argument, Mr.
	<div type="abstract">Chagla<lb/> submitted that PLUS made six claims before the IC as a mediator<lb/> under clause 39.1(b) of the Concession Agreement. He submitted<lb/> that clause 31.2 of the Concession Agreement categorically<lb/> stipulates that in the event of MSRDC being in material default and<lb/> such default is cured before termination, MSRDC shall pay to the<lb/> Concessionaire, as compensation, all additional direct cost suffered<lb/> or incurred by the Concessionaire arising out of such material<lb/> default by MSRDC in one lumpsum within thirty days of receiving<lb/> the demand or, at MSRDC&apos;s option, in three equal annual<lb/> instalments, with interest. Mr. Chagla submitted that the term<lb/> &apos;additional direct cost&apos; under the Concession Agreement is,<lb/> therefore, an omnibus term referring to all costs suffered or<lb/> incurred by PLUS in any capacity as long as it arises out of a<lb/> material default by MSRDC. He submitted that this is borne out by<lb/> the correspondence on record before the termination of the<lb/> Concession Agreement. He submitted that PLUS&apos; letter dated 24 th<lb/> February, 2010 to MSRDC categorically refers to &apos;additional direct<lb/> cost&apos; reimbursement due to material default by MSRDC of the<lb/> Concession Agreement. By the said letter, PLUS sought Rs.</div>

	161.65<lb/> crores as &apos;additional direct cost&apos; incurred due to material default of<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/>
	<reference>CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/></reference>

	CARBP371.17.doc<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>SR Pasha, Sr PS<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Page 24 of 169<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">to MSRDC, filed the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; reimbursement<lb/> as a result of the material defaults of the Concession Agreement by<lb/> MSRDC. This claim was for Rs.161.65 crores. PLUS wrote another<lb/> letter on 16 th April, 2010, to MSRDC demanding reimbursement of<lb/> the &apos;additional direct cost&apos; due to material default of MSRDC.<lb/> Thereafter, on 30 th April, 2010, PLUS addressed another letter to<lb/> MSRDC stating the urgency of resolving the issue of &apos;additional<lb/> direct cost&apos; within the defined time lines. Since MSRDC did not<lb/> make any payments, with reference to the &apos;additional direct cost&apos;,<lb/> PLUS wrote a letter dated 10 th May, 2010 to the IC invoking the<lb/> provisions of clause 39.1(b) for assistance and contractual<lb/> mediation in resolving the issue of &apos;additional direct cost&apos;<lb/> reimbursement and no other claim. Further, on receipt of the<lb/> aforesaid communication, the IC, vide its letter dated 15 th May,<lb/> 2010, informed MSRDC that PLUS had invoked clause 39.1(b) of the<lb/> Concession Agreement in relation to the issue of &apos;additional direct<lb/> cost&apos;. MSRDC thereafter by its letter dated 29 th May, 2010,<lb/> requested both PLUS and the IC to attend a meeting for resolution<lb/> under clause 39.1(b) in relation to the issue of &apos;additional direct<lb/> cost&apos; reimbursement. Thereafter, the IC, in its communication dated<lb/> 11 th October, 2010, addressed to MSRDC discussed various claims<lb/></div>

	::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/>
	<reference>CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/></reference>

	CARBP371.17.doc<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>SR Pasha, Sr PS<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Page 27 of 169<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">(emphasis supplied)<lb/> 24.<lb/> Mr. Khambatta submitted that the Committee<lb/> summarized its findings, reiterating that claim Nos.1, 3, 4 and 6<lb/> were accepted in terms of the recommendations of the IC and claim<lb/> No.2 was rejected. However, regarding claim No.5, i.e. &apos;additional<lb/> direct cost&apos;, the Committee recommended &quot;Resolution of dispute as<lb/> per the provisions of the Concession Agreement for settlement of<lb/> issue&quot;. He submitted that from this report of the Committee of<lb/> Directors, it is clear that the Committee either accepted or rejected<lb/> the claims of PLUS, except the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos;<lb/> which was claim No.5. This claim was to be resolved by mediation of<lb/> the IC as per clause 39.1(b) of the Concession Agreement. Mr.<lb/> Khambatta submitted that keeping in line with this, the IC also, in<lb/> its communication dated 2 nd August, 2011, addressed to MSRDC,<lb/> listed out six claims, including the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos;.<lb/> The IC thereafter dealt with each individual claim separately. As far<lb/> as claim No.5 is concerned, the IC recommended that PLUS has<lb/> already requested for resolution of this claim under the provisions of<lb/> dispute resolution as per clause 39.1 of the Concession Agreement<lb/> for which MSRDC has appointed Mr.</div>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>A.V. Deodhar, Superintending<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/>
	<reference>CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/></reference>

	CARBP371.17.doc<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>SR Pasha, Sr PS<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Page 29 of 169<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">correspondence with several third parties in which they admitted<lb/> their own defaults and which cannot be termed as correspondence<lb/> entered into during conciliation proceedings.<lb/> He, therefore,<lb/> submitted that the contention of MSRDC that all claims were<lb/> referred to mediation is wholly without substance and deserves to<lb/> be rejected. Mr. Khambatta also submitted that when one reads the<lb/> findings of the Arbitral Tribunal on this issue, it is quite clear that<lb/> from the documents on record, it is certainly a plausible view and if<lb/> that be the case, no interference is called for under section 34 of the<lb/> Act. He, therefore, submitted that the aforesaid argument holds no<lb/> merit and ought to be rejected.<lb/> FINDINGS OF THE COURT:<lb/> 26.<lb/> I have heard the learned counsel for the parties at length<lb/> and have perused the papers and proceedings in the above petition.<lb/> The point to be decided here is whether all six claims were<lb/> submitted by PLUS to the IC under clause 39.1(b), as sought to be<lb/> contended by Mr. Chagla, or whether only the claim for &apos;additional<lb/> direct cost&apos; was submitted under the said clause. To put it in a nut-<lb/>shell, according to Mr. Chagla, if all claims were submitted for<lb/> conciliation under clause 39.</div>

	1(b), then all correspondence<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/>
	<reference>CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/></reference>

	CARBP371.17.doc<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>SR Pasha, Sr PS<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Page 41 of 169<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">loss on other grounds as well (loss of Toll revenue on account of<lb/> traffic regulations and non-payment of Toll by Municipal buses). The<lb/> Tribunal, therefore, holds that the alleged confidentiality attached to<lb/> the conciliation proceedings can, at best, be attached to matters<lb/> pertaining to the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos;, but not the other<lb/> claims. The Tribunal also correctly holds that the Concession<lb/> Agreement never envisaged or contemplated a conciliation as<lb/> contemplated under Part III of the Act and neither any such<lb/> procedure was followed. It also noted that the IC was a nominee of<lb/> MSRDC performing MSRDC&apos;s obligations under the agreement<lb/> which it could outsource to the IC. Part III of the Act, however,<lb/> requires that there should be an independent and impartial third-<lb/>party Conciliator to mediate and assist in the resolution dispute.<lb/> Given that the IC was a nominee of MSRDC, it could never, therefore,<lb/> have performed the role of a Conciliator as understood and<lb/> envisaged under Part III of the Act. It could, at best, have been a<lb/> contractual conciliation procedure. The third point that the Tribunal<lb/> holds on this issue is that clause 39.1(b) of the Agreement did not<lb/> expressly contain any confidentiality restrictions with regard to the<lb/> correspondence exchanged during the conciliation procedure and<lb/> nor are any documents marked &apos;without prejudice&apos;.</div>

	It is in these<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/>
	<reference>CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::</reference>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
