<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_47bd1f45457ab1ea0d80f2d977b05ca7.pdf"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">


		<figure type="table">

            <head>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> documents on the ground that they are part of conciliation<lb/> proceedings is without any merit.<lb/> 35.<lb/> Before concluding on this issue, it would only be fair to<lb/> deal with the reliance placed by Mr. Chagla on Recital &apos;D&apos; of the draft<lb/> settlement agreement (reproduced above). I find that the reliance<lb/> placed by Mr. Chagla on Recital &apos;D&apos; is wholly misplaced. Firstly,<lb/> PLUS itself sought to rely upon this draft (to establish admission of<lb/> liability) and which was negated by the Tribunal on the ground that<lb/> the same was never signed by either of the parties and hence could<lb/> not be relied upon. I then fail to see how MSRDC can rely upon it<lb/> when it does not admit the same. Secondly, Recital &apos;D&apos; talks about<lb/> the six claims that were raised pursuant to a letter dated 10 th May,<lb/> 2010 and earlier letters on the subject. In fact, the letter dated 10 th<lb/> May, 2010 (and the earlier letters) clearly shows that six claims<lb/> were never raised and only the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; was<lb/> raised under the said letters which culminated into conciliation<lb/> proceedings under clause 39.1(b).<lb/> The Tribunal too, after<lb/> examining the correspondence on record, categorically records that<lb/> the letter dated 10 th May, 2010 and the letters issued earlier to it,<lb/> do not actually refer to the six claims, but rather only to the claim<lb/> for &apos;additional direct cost&apos;. In fact, the Tribunal also records that<lb/> though it is true that other claims had also been raised by that time,<lb/> these were by means of separate letters and were separately<lb/> pursued. This being the position, I find that the reliance placed by<lb/> Mr. Chagla on Recital &apos;D&apos; of the draft settlement agreement is wholly<lb/> misplaced. Similar is the case in relation to the pleadings filed<lb/> before the Arbitral Tribunal. The Tribunal has considered the<lb/> pleadings and has thereafter come to the conclusion that it was only<lb/> the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; that was referred to mediation /<lb/> conciliation and not any other claim. In these circumstances, I do<lb/> not find that the Tribunal was in any error in holding that it was<lb/> only the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; that was referred to<lb/> mediation / conciliation under clause 39.1(b) and not any other<lb/> claim. I, therefore, </table>
 
            <head>do not find any reason to interfere with the<lb/> Interim Award on this issue.<lb/> II. UPHOLDING THE VALIDITY OF THE TERMINATION<lb/> OF THE CONCESSION AGREEMENT:<lb/> SUBMISSIONS OF MSRDC:<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> 36.<lb/> Mr. Chagla submitted that the findings of the Arbitral<lb/> Tribunal upholding the termination of the Concession Agreement is<lb/> contrary to the record and, therefore, wholly illegal and perverse.<lb/> He submitted that the Concession Agreement could be terminated<lb/> under two different clauses, namely, clause 32.4 and clause 29.8 of<lb/> the Concession Agreement. Clause 32.4 gave a right to PLUS to<lb/> terminate the Concession Agreement in the event of any default<lb/> committed by MSRDC. On the other hand, clause 29.8 gave a right<lb/> to either party to terminate the agreement if a Force Majeure event<lb/> subsisted for a period of 180 days or more within a continuous<lb/> period of 365 days. Under clause 32.4.1, the termination notice was<lb/> to be given in writing by giving a ninety days&apos; notice under clause.<lb/> 37.<lb/> Mr. Chagla submitted that the findings given by the<lb/> Arbitral Tribunal in paragraph 70 of the Award upholding the<lb/> termination of the Concession Agreement under clauses 32.4.1(1)<lb/> and 32.4.1(3) thereof, are wholly illegal and perverse. He submitted<lb/> that PLUS, by its termination notice dated 19 th March, 2013, sought<lb/> to terminate the Concession Agreement under clause 32.4 thereof.<lb/> In order for it to be a valid termination, clause 32.4 requires four<lb/> conditions that need to be satisfied, namely: (1) that there is a<lb/> breach of the Concession Agreement; (2) The breach should have a<lb/> material adverse effect on the project; (3) that a 90 days&apos; notice be<lb/> given; and (4) MSRDC failing to cure the said breach or take<lb/> effective steps for curing the said breach within 90 days of receipt of<lb/> the notice. Mr. Chagla submitted that in the facts of the present<lb/> case, none of the aforesaid conditions are satisfied. He submitted<lb/> that firstly clause 32.4 mandatorily required termination to be 90<lb/> days after a written notice in respect thereto was given to MSRDC.<lb/> It is an admitted position that the 90 days&apos; notice has not been<lb/> given. Despite this, the Arbitral Tribunal, in paragraph 70 of the<lb/> Award records that though a 90 day notice was required, the notice<lb/> period was complied with as PLUS had only refrained from issuing a<lb/> formal termination notice on the assurance of MSRDC and,<lb/> therefore, MSRDC had much more than the 90 day notice period to<lb/> cure the breach. The Tribunal has, in this respect, referred to a<lb/> letter dated 4 th February, 2013. Mr. Chagla submitted that even<lb/> assuming whilst denying that this letter amounted to a written<lb/> notice under clause 32.4, the time period from 4 th February, 2013 to<lb/> 28 th April, 2013, did not satisfy the 90 day notice period. He<lb/> submitted that termination under clause 32.4 requires strict<lb/> compliance and failure to give notice of 90 days clearly renders the<lb/> termination illegal and invalid. He, therefore, submitted that on this</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>The Arbitral Tribunal has completely ignored the obligation of PLUS<lb/> as contained in clause 2 of Schedule B, clause 9.8(ii), notes 3 and 4<lb/> to the drawing of the Katai ROB and clause 9.4(v) of the Concession<lb/> Agreement. Mr. Chagla submitted that the admitted position is that<lb/> MSRDC had acquired the additional land before the drawings were<lb/> approved by the Railways as recorded in the letters dated 2 nd May,<lb/> 2009 and 11 th September, 2009. Therefore, there was no delay<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>::</note>

            <head>: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> occasioned or prejudice caused to PLUS by reason of the delay in<lb/> acquisition in land and, therefore, no breach was committed by<lb/> MSRDC.<lb/> 39.<lb/> Mr. Chagla thereafter submitted that even assuming<lb/> that there was a breach on the part of MSRDC, there was no<lb/> material adverse effect on PLUS. He submitted that the only<lb/> evidence led by PLUS before the Arbitral Tribunal was the<lb/> correspondence addressed complaining of &quot;losses&quot;; constraint on its<lb/> &quot;cash flow position&quot;; that its operations were being jeopardized; and<lb/> mentioning alleged figures of loss etc. PLUS led no evidence in<lb/> support of the alleged losses or constraint on its cash flow or its<lb/> operations being jeopardized, save and except what transpired<lb/> before the IC in the course of conciliation proceedings. As recorded<lb/> by the Tribunal in paragraph 77 of the Award, various figures of loss<lb/> were proposed by either side in the spirit of settlement while they<lb/> were trying to work out a rough and ready compromise. These were<lb/> sought to be relied upon by PLUS as admissions of liability and<lb/> which were expressly rejected by the Arbitral Tribunal. In fact, the<lb/> finding of the Tribunal is that it is for PLUS to prove and quantify<lb/> the loss it has suffered and claim damages on that basis and that the<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>::</note>

            <head>: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> claim for Rs.112 crores was based only on admissions made by<lb/> MSRDC in the course of conciliation which the Arbitral Tribunal did<lb/> not accept. Mr. Chagla submitted that for the Tribunal to come to a<lb/> finding that there had been a material adverse effect, it was<lb/> essential for the Tribunal to examine the evidence and conclude that<lb/> PLUS had suffered loss or damage which, in turn, would be the<lb/> material adverse effect caused to PLUS.<lb/> On coming to the<lb/> conclusion that on the available evidence, the Tribunal was not in a<lb/> position to conclude that there was a loss or damage, the Arbitral<lb/> Tribunal could not have concluded that there was a material<lb/> adverse effect. The findings in this regard, therefore, are patently<lb/> illegal and wholly perverse, was the submission of Mr. Chagla.<lb/> 40.<lb/> In the alternative to the above argument, Mr. Chagla<lb/> submitted that even assuming that MSRDC had committed a breach,<lb/> it had taken effective steps to cure the same. He submitted that<lb/> clause 32.4 allows MSRDC a period of 90 days to cure the alleged<lb/> breach. The Arbitral Tribunal has held that MSRDC had granted an<lb/> extension of 674 days to the construction period vide its letter dated<lb/> 18 th June, 2010. The said letter clearly records that the extension<lb/> was granted under clause 29.6(b) of the Concession Agreement and,<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>::</note>

            <head>: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> therefore, the monetary claim was rejected by MSRDC. Further,<lb/> MSRDC had also got an interim Toll Notification issued on 26 th April,<lb/> 2013 permitting PLUS to collect Toll for a period three months from<lb/> 28 th April, 2013. PLUS refused the said interim Notification on the<lb/> ground that there was a new condition of depositing the amount of<lb/> Toll in an Escrow Account. Mr. Chagla submitted that there was no<lb/> new condition of depositing the money in the Escrow Account as the<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>same was already provided for in clauses 6.3. 6.4, 25 and 34.11 of<lb/> the Concession Agreement. He submitted that it is pertinent to note<lb/> that the Arbitral Tribunal has categorically held that the default of<lb/> the MSRDC is not the failure to have a Toll Notification issued in<lb/> respect of the proposed extended concession period. In light of all<lb/> this, Mr Chagla submitted that MSRDC had taken all effective steps<lb/> to cure the breach, if any. In any event, PLUS terminated the<lb/> Concession Agreement even before the 90 day period was over and,<lb/> therefore, the Tribunal could not have held that MSRDC had not<lb/> cured the breach within the period of 90 days.<lb/> In these<lb/> circumstances, Mr. Chagla submitted that the finding of the Arbitral<lb/> Tribunal upholding the termination of the Concession Agreement<lb/> under clause 32.4.1 is patently illegal and perverse and ought to be<lb/> set aside.<lb/> 41.<lb/> Similarly, Mr. Chagla submitted that the findings of the<lb/> Arbitral Tribunal upholding the termination of the Concession<lb/> Agreement under clause 29.8 are also patently illegal and ought to<lb/> interfered with. Mr. Chagla submitted that in the termination notice<lb/> dated 19 th March, 2013, PLUS sought to terminate the Concession<lb/> Agreement under clause 29.8, inter alia, on the following grounds:<lb/> (a) Non issuance of Toll Notification by the Government<lb/> of Maharashtra till 10 th July, 2024 in pursuance of<lb/> the Settlement Agreement;<lb/> (b) Refusal of KDMT and NMMT buses to pay Toll; and<lb/> (c) Traffic Control Notification dated 11 th May, 2009,<lb/> banning entry of multi axle vehicles through<lb/> Kalyan city and Notification dated 29 th December,<lb/> 2009 closing entry of all heavy vehicles on the said<lb/> Project Road.<lb/> 42.<lb/> Mr. Chagla brought to my attention that the Arbitral<lb/> Tribunal upheld the termination of the Concession Agreement under<lb/> clause 29.8 on grounds (b) and (c) above and rejected the<lb/> termination on ground (a). Mr. Chagla took me through clause 29 of<lb/> the Concession Agreement and which deals with the events of Force<lb/> Majeure. He submitted that in the present case, PLUS has claimed<lb/> existence of a Political Force Majeure event and which is defined in<lb/> clause 29.4. He submitted that a Political Force Majeure event shall<lb/> mean one or more of the acts of events by or on account of MSRDC,<lb/> GOM or any other Governmental agency, as more particularly set<lb/> out in clauses 29.4(i) and 29.4(iii).<lb/> Whilst interpreting the<lb/> aforesaid clauses, Mr. Chagla submitted that it was clear that five<lb/> conditions required fulfilling. They were: (a) the event should be a<lb/> Political Force Majeure event as defined in clause 29.4 of the<lb/> Concession Agreement; (b) the said event should prevent the party<lb/> from performing its obligations under the Concession Agreement;<lb/> (c) the said event is beyond the reasonable control and not arising<lb/> out of the fault of the affected party; (d) the affected party is unable<lb/> to overcome the said event by exercise of due diligence and<lb/> reasonable efforts, skill and care, including through expenditure of<lb/> reasonable sums of money; and (e) the said event has a material<lb/> adverse effect on the Project. Mr. Chagla submitted that the<lb/> Arbitral Tribunal held that refusal of KDMT and NMMT buses to pay<lb/> Toll [ground (b) above] is an expropriation of the rights of PLUS<lb/> and, therefore, constitutes a Political Force Majeure event within<lb/> the meaning of clause 29.4 of the Concession Agreement. This<lb/> finding can be found at paragraph 61 of the Award. Mr. Chagla</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>Chagla submitted<lb/> that the said finding has been arrived at without identifying the<lb/> documentary evidence on record in support of such a finding. This<lb/> finding is also contrary to the Arbitral Tribunal&apos;s own finding in<lb/> paragraph 43 of the Award wherein it held that the period from<lb/> November, 2011 to April, 2013, PLUS was still able to collect and<lb/> retain Toll on account of the original Toll Notification till 28 th April,<lb/> 2013.<lb/> Mr. Chagla submitted that, therefore, the findings in<lb/> paragraph 62 of the Award are not only self-contradictory but also<lb/> contrary to the admission made by the witness of PLUS.<lb/> 44.<lb/> Mr. Chagla next submitted that even if a Political Force<lb/> Majeure event arose, the same was on account of the fault of PLUS.<lb/> He submitted that the finding of the Arbitral Tribunal that the said<lb/> event, namely, refusal of KDMT and NMMT buses to pay Toll was<lb/> entirely beyond the control of PLUS and certainly not on account of<lb/> any fault of PLUS, is patently illegal and perverse inasmuch as the<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>::</note>

            <head>: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>The<lb/> record is replete with further correspondence from PLUS pointing<lb/> out how this delay is constraining its cash flow position and<lb/> jeopardizing operations. The Tribunal further held that the terms of<lb/> the Agreement leave no doubt that it was MSRDC&apos;s obligation to<lb/> make the project site available, and MSRDC defaulted on this<lb/> obligation. MSRDC was, therefore, in breach of its obligations under<lb/> Clause 4.1(d) as well as Clauses 10.1(i), 10.1(ii) and 10.1(iii). The<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>Tribunal, therefore, came to a finding that there exists a valid basis<lb/> for termination, both under clauses 32.4.1(1) and Clause 32.4.1(3).<lb/> 68.<lb/> Before I examine this aspect, it would be apposite to set<lb/> out clause 32.4.1 which reads thus:-<lb/></table>
<lb/>
            <note>&quot;32.4 Termination for MSRDC Event of Default.<lb/> <note>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> 32.4.1 The Concessionaire may after giving 90<lb/> (ninety) days notice in writing to MSRDC<lb/> terminate this Agreement upon the occurrence<lb/> and continuation of any of the following events<lb/> (each a MSRDC Event of Default) unless any<lb/> such MSRDC Event of Default has occurred<lb/> as a result of Concessionaire Event of Default<lb/> or due to Force Majeure Event.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>(1)<lb/> MSRDC is in breach of this Agreement<lb/> and such breach has a Material<lb/> Adverse Effect on the Concessionaire<lb/> and MSRDC has failed to cure such<lb/> breach or take effective steps for curing<lb/> such breach within 90 (ninety) days of<lb/> receipt of notice in this behalf from the<lb/> Concessionaire;<lb/> (2)<lb/> MSRDC repudiates this Agreement or<lb/> otherwise evidences an irrevocable<lb/> intention not to be bound by this<lb/> Agreement;<lb/> (3)<lb/> MSRDC or GOM or any Government<lb/> Agency have by an act of commission<lb/> or omission created circumstances that<lb/> have a Material Adverse Effect on the<lb/> performance of its obligations by the<lb/> Concessionaire and have failed to cure<lb/> the same within 90 (ninety) days of<lb/> receipt of notice by MSRDC in this<lb/> behalf from the Concessionaire;<lb/> (4)<lb/> MSRDC has delayed any payment that<lb/> has fallen due under this Agreement if<lb/> such delay exceeds 90 (ninety) days.&quot;<lb/> 69.<lb/> Clause 32.4.1 entitles PLUS to terminate the Concession<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>Agreement on the occurrence of any of the events listed in the said<lb/> <note>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> <note>SR Pasha, Sr PS<lb/> Page 94 of 169<lb/> clause and described as MSRDC&apos;s event of default, by giving a 90<lb/> day notice in writing to MSRDC. In the event MSRDC&apos;s event of<lb/> default has occurred because of PLUS&apos; default or due to Force<lb/> Majeure events, then PLUS would not be entitled to terminate<lb/> Concession Agreement under the said clause. Clause 32.4.1(1)<lb/> stipulates that PLUS is entitled to terminate if MSRDC is in breach of<lb/> the Concession Agreement and such breach has a material adverse<lb/> effect on PLUS and MSRDC has failed to cure such breach or take<lb/> effective steps for curing the same within 90 days of receipt of a<lb/> notice in that behalf from PLUS. Similarly, clause 32.4.1(3)<lb/> stipulates that if MSRDC or the Government of Maharashtra or any<lb/> Government Agency have, by an act of commission or omission<lb/> created circumstances that had a material adverse effect on the<lb/> performance of the obligations of PLUS and have failed to cure the<lb/> same within 90 days of receipt of a notice issued by PLUS to MSRDC,<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>PLUS would be entitled to terminate the Agreement. On a conjoint<lb/> reading of clauses 32.4.1(1) and 32.4.1(3), it is clear that the<lb/> following conditions need to be fulfilled: (i) that there is an event of<lb/> default by MSRDC; (ii) The said default should have a material<lb/> adverse effect on PLUS; (iii) PLUS must give a 90 day notice in<lb/> writing to MSRDC to terminate the Concession Agreement; and (iv)<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> MSRDC fails to cure the said default / breach or take effective steps<lb/> for curing the same within 90 days of receipt of such notice.<lb/> 70.<lb/> In the present case, it is not in dispute that the 90 day<lb/> notice (as contemplated in clause 32.4.1) was not given by PLUS to<lb/> MSRDC. It is specifically recorded by the Tribunal in paragraph 70<lb/> of the Award, that although clause 32.4 requires a 90 day notice to<lb/> be given, and PLUS provided less than 90 days from its notice dated<lb/> 19 th March, 2013, the notice period must be viewed in the overall<lb/> context. The Tribunal held that PLUS had held out the prospect of<lb/> termination long before 19 th March, 2013 and it also refrained from<lb/> issuing a formal notice at the specific request of MSRDC, with the<lb/> assurance that matters would be sorted out. The Tribunal held that<lb/> MSRDC had much more than the required 90 day notice period to<lb/> actually cure the defaults, if it had so intended. Instead, it kept<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>holding out a carrot to PLUS and dragging matters perilously close<lb/> to the expiry of the period covered by the Toll Notification. It is in<lb/> these circumstances that the Tribunal held that the notice period<lb/> must be held to have been complied with.<lb/> 71.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>I am unable to understand how the Tribunal has come to<lb/> <note>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> this finding. The termination notice dated 19 th March, 2013 reads<lb/> as under:-<lb/></note>
<lb/>
            <table>&quot;PLUS<lb/> PLUS BKSP Toll Limited<lb/> March 19, 2013.<lb/> The Vice Chairman &amp; Managing Director<lb/> Maharashtra State Road Development Corporation<lb/> Limited<lb/> Near Priyadarshini Park,<lb/> Nepean Sea Road,<lb/> Mumbai 400 036 -India.<lb/> Sub:-TERMINATION NOTICE UNDER CLAUSE 32.4 OF<lb/> THE CONCESSION AGREEMENT DATED AUGUST 25,<lb/> 2006 (&quot;CONCESSION AGREEMENT&quot;) ENTERED INTO<lb/> BETWEEN MAHARASHTRA STATE ROAD<lb/> DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION LIMITED (&quot;MSRDC&quot;)<lb/> AND PLUS BKSP TOLL LIMITED (&quot;PLUS BKSP&quot;)<lb/> Dear Sir,<lb/> 1.<lb/> With reference to the Concession Agreement,<lb/> PLUS BKSP had, vide a letter dated May 10,<lb/> 2010 and earlier letters, raised 6 claims on<lb/> MSRDC which related to losses incurred by<lb/> PLUS BKSP due to acts/ omissions/ delays in<lb/> performance of obligations under the Concession<lb/> Agreement by MSRDC.<lb/> 2.<lb/> MSRDC subsequently made an offer of an<lb/> amicable settlement to PLUS BKSP vide its letter<lb/> dated October 20, 2011 (&quot;Offer Letter&quot;). In the<lb/> said Offer Letter, MSRDC offered an extension of<lb/> the Concession Period until July 10, 2024 in lieu<lb/> of cash payments for compensating PLUS BKSP.<lb/> 3.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>In the spirit of resolving the matter, PLUS BKSP<lb/> has accepted MSRDC&apos;s offer; PLUS BKSP&apos;s<lb/> acceptance is contained in its letter dated<lb/> November 4, 2011 (&quot;Acceptance Letter&quot;). With the<lb/> acceptance of MSRDC&apos;s offer, PLUS BKSP was<lb/> hopeful that MSRDC will be able to expedite the<lb/> issuance of toll notification until the proposed<lb/> extended term of the Concession Agreement i.e.<lb/> July 10, 2024 (&quot;Toll Notification&quot;).<lb/> 4.<lb/> We note that unfortunately till date MSRDC has<lb/> not been able to cause issuance of the Toll<lb/> Notification while the present toll notification is<lb/> due to end on April 28, 2013, which is fast<lb/> approaching.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>5.<lb/> Hence, we are hereby issuing this notice under<lb/> Clause 32.4 of Concession Agreement. The<lb/> breaches/ acts/ omissions by MSRDC under the<lb/> Concession Agreement have caused a Material<lb/> Adverse Effect on PLUS BKSP and thus, making<lb/> PLUS BKSP entitled to compensation under<lb/> Clause 31.2 and to exercise its right of<lb/> termination under Clause 32.4.<lb/> 6.<lb/> PLUS BKSP previously refrained to terminate the<lb/> concession in response to MSRDC&apos;s request to<lb/> do so in its letter dated Feb 8, 2013. Please note<lb/> that PLUS BKSP will not be able to proceed with<lb/> its operations beyond April 28, 2013 until the<lb/> issuance of the Toll Notification. Therefore, kindly<lb/> issue by April 28, 2013, the extension of the<lb/> concession period and Toll Notification to July 10,<lb/> 2024.<lb/> If MSRDC shall fail to do so, the<lb/> Concession Agreement shall terminate on April<lb/> 28, 2013 and MSRDC shall be liable to pay us the<lb/> Termination Payment as provided in Clause<lb/> 32.4.2 and the settlement of claims as provided in<lb/> Clause 31.2 both with interest until date of<lb/> payment.<lb/> 7.<lb/> Without prejudice to any rights accrued/ available<lb/> to PLUS BKSP under law or otherwise, the<lb/> Parties shall continue to be bound by the clauses<lb/> of the Concession Agreement which survive<lb/> termination, including without limitation, the<lb/> clauses relating to Termination Payment,<lb/> Compensation,<lb/> Divestment<lb/> Requirements,<lb/> release of funds lying in Escrow Account and<lb/> release of Performance Security.<lb/> 8.<lb/> For avoidance of doubt, it is hereby clarified that<lb/> the initially capitalized term used herein but not<lb/> defined shall have the same meaning as<lb/> assigned to them in the Concession Agreement.<lb/> Yours faithfully,<lb/> Sd/-<lb/>NOORIZAH HJ. ABD. HAMID<lb/> Chairman.&quot;<lb/> (emphasis supplied)<lb/> 72.<lb/> From the aforesaid termination notice, it is clear that<lb/> the said notice was issued under clause 32.4 of the Concession<lb/> Agreement. Clause 32.4.1 clearly required PLUS to give a 90 day<lb/> notice in writing to MSRDC for terminating the Agreement upon<lb/> occurrence and continuation of any of the events of default as set<lb/> out therein. The 90 day period was to enable MSRDC to cure any<lb/> breach or to take effective steps for curing the same. However, in<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>the aforesaid notice, PLUS requests MSRDC to issue, by 28 th April,</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>MR. KUMAR:<lb/> Then, sir, personally, I have no objection<lb/> to that. Only thing is that time constraint<lb/> of two and a half days should not apply<lb/> to me. But that&apos;s my only request. I&apos;ll<lb/> try my best to complete.<lb/> MR. JUSTICE ALAM:<lb/> What time you think -<lb/>MR. KUMAR:<lb/> I would like to then take this entire<lb/> session, because if the counterclaim is<lb/> involved, then I will have to take that<lb/> entire session.<lb/> MR. JUSTICE ALAM:<lb/> Then we come back to the same<lb/> situation, because it will be -<lb/>MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: We have serious reservations about<lb/> that, because even I have to cross-<lb/></table>
<lb/>
            <figDesc>examine on his counterclaim, as also his<lb/> defence, within that two and a half days.<lb/> That&apos;s how it is done always, when we<lb/> do have time restrictions, we have to<lb/> manage our affairs in that way, it is not<lb/> unusual, in fact it is done in every case<lb/> that you do claims and counterclaims to<lb/> the witness in one shot, so the witness<lb/> doesn&apos;t have to come back. So I&apos;m the<lb/> claimant, I&apos;m putting him in rebuttal, as<lb/> we know each other&apos;s case, we know<lb/> which documents are on the record, so<lb/> it is possible to ---<lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM:<lb/> No, but if he says that he needs more<lb/> time, we must allow him to explain his<lb/> position.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>MR. KUMAR:<lb/> I&apos;ll try to keep myself within the two and<lb/> a half, three days period, but as I see<lb/> from the documents, I don&apos;t think that<lb/> will be possible. So I must tell the<lb/> tribunal. I&apos;ll try my best.<lb/> MR. JUSTICE ALAM:<lb/> We don&apos;t have that manual kind of<lb/> taking down of the witness statement.<lb/> These ladies are going very fast.<lb/> MR. KUMAR:<lb/> That&apos;s right, I know. I&apos;m aware of that. I&apos;ll<lb/> try my best. That&apos;s all I can say.<lb/> MR. JUSTICE ALAM:<lb/> Please.<lb/> MR. KUMAR:<lb/> Only I&apos;ll request your Lordships to keep<lb/> that in mind that in view of the affidavit<lb/> which<lb/> is<lb/> dealing<lb/> with<lb/> several<lb/> documents,<lb/> there<lb/> are<lb/> some<lb/> inconsistencies between the statement<lb/> of claim and the evidence. I may take<lb/> more time. Now that the counterclaim is<lb/> also introduced, I will have to now deal<lb/> with though he&apos;s taking a risk by calling<lb/> his witness and he is understood the<lb/> counterclaim. For me, I will not object to<lb/> that. But to deal with that, it will be a<lb/> different aspect altogether.<lb/> MR. JUSTICE ALAM:<lb/> Let us proceed. Let us see how it<lb/> unfolds.&quot;<lb/> (emphasis supplied)<lb/> 101.<lb/> Thereafter, the cross-examination continued on 18 th<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>January, 2017 and 19 th January, 2017 where the Tribunal<lb/> consistently called upon the counsel for MSRDC to tell them as to<lb/> what would be the reasonable time required to complete the<lb/> evidence on the Counter Claim. In fact, the counsel for PLUS<lb/> submitted before the Tribunal that there was no question of the<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>Counter Claim coming later as there were two sets of dates for<lb/> completing the entire proceedings. During the cross-examination,<lb/> on 20 th January, 2017, it appears that the Tribunal was quite<lb/> peeved at the fact that the counsel for MSRDC was not adhering to<lb/> the strict time schedule. The relevant portion of the transcripts of<lb/> 20 th January, 2017 read thus:<lb/> &quot;MR. JUSTICE ALAM:<lb/> I&apos;m anxious that you complete by the<lb/> lunchtime. I&apos;m feeling a little bad, but<lb/> you seem to be telling us that you just<lb/> don&apos;t care for the schedule fixed by the<lb/> tribunal and you will go as you think best<lb/> and as you please.<lb/> MR. KUMAR:<lb/> No sir, I&apos;m sorry if I have given you that<lb/> impression.<lb/> MR. JUSTICE ALAM:<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>See the first order. The schedule was in<lb/> presence of both sides with the express<lb/> consent of both sides. You knew the<lb/> magnitude of the case then. Of course,<lb/> you were not there in the first hearing,<lb/> but after you came and you thought that<lb/> this matter may take longer time, you<lb/> could have always asked us, told us that<lb/> this schedule is not realistic, it needs to<lb/> be reviewed. We had fixed five days for<lb/> witnesses examination. Three and a<lb/> half days still over. So what time will he<lb/> get? This will completely change the<lb/> entire schedule.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>We have other commitments. He might<lb/> have other commitments. If you thought<lb/> that this five days for witnesses was not<lb/> realistic, you could have told us,<lb/> requested for a review of the schedule,<lb/> months or weeks ago.<lb/> MR. KUMAR:<lb/> That I should have done. We should<lb/> have done that. I&apos;m sorry about that.<lb/> MR. JUSTICE ALAM:<lb/> We are at a stage when the whole<lb/> schedule is getting disturbed and, as I<lb/> said, that the order that we passed, the<lb/> first procedural order is practically<lb/> meaningless.<lb/> MR. KUMAR:<lb/> I&apos;ll only say one thing.<lb/> MR. JUSTICE ALAM:<lb/> If you take four days, he may also say.<lb/> MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: My I make one suggestion? I think that<lb/> even if he finishes by the end of the day<lb/> today and that should be the ultimate<lb/> time limit, no longer than that, I have<lb/> one full day tomorrow. I will complete<lb/> the cross-examination of Mr. Kulkarni,<lb/> who&apos;s the main witnesses tomorrow<lb/> itself. </table>
 
            <figDesc>On the second witness, who&apos;s Mr.<lb/> Jadhav, he&apos;s speaking on a very limited<lb/> aspect. That is during a period of 14<lb/> January 2014 to some time in 2015 on<lb/> costs incurred by them, which is in<lb/> relation to the counterclaim only. Maybe<lb/> we don&apos;t even need to cross-examine<lb/> him. I&apos;ll discuss with Mr. Kumar at the<lb/> end of the day on that and see whether<lb/> we can reach an agreement as to what<lb/> the status of his affidavit should be,<lb/> given the time constraints that have<lb/> developed. Otherwise, I mean, anyway,<lb/> I could have done his cross-examination<lb/> about two hours maximum, maybe even<lb/> less.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>But we can dispense with that, if we can<lb/> reach an agreement on -<lb/>MR. KUMAR:<lb/> You have already told me in the<lb/> morning. I&apos;ll talk to the clients about it.<lb/> Sir, I must tell you --<lb/>MR. JUSTICE ALAM:<lb/> Please don&apos;t misunderstand me.<lb/> MR. KUMAR:<lb/> Not at all, sir.<lb/> MR. JUJSTICE ALAM:<lb/> I respect you and think that you&apos;re<lb/> entitled to your cross-examination but in<lb/> that case, we should have been<lb/> informed earlier. Then we would have<lb/> considered changing the schedule then.<lb/> This leads me to ask, what about the<lb/> hearing dates?<lb/> MR. KUMAR:<lb/> Hearing dates, I must tell you, I will need<lb/> five days. I&apos;m telling you now.<lb/> MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: I have one submission on that. I don&apos;t<lb/> think a hearing of this nature needs five<lb/> days. I think two and a half days each is<lb/> more than enough.<lb/> It&apos;s documents<lb/> which are on the record that we have to<lb/> deal with.<lb/> MR. JUSTICE ALAM:<lb/> Mr. Mukhopadhaya, everyone has his<lb/> own way of making submissions.<lb/> MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: No, there are time constraints to every<lb/> tribunal, time constraints to parties and<lb/> the cost involved in every day&apos;s hearing.<lb/> CHAIRMAN:<lb/> Do you have time for rejoinder in the<lb/> argument?<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: I&apos;ll take one and a half hours for<lb/> rejoinder, that&apos;s it. We&apos;ll give written<lb/> submissions after the hearing, so that<lb/> whatever time is --this is done in all<lb/> major arbitrations.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>MR. JUSTICE ALAM:<lb/> You will make submissions first.<lb/> MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: Yes, as claimant, I would make the<lb/> submissions first.<lb/> MR. JUSTICE ALAM:<lb/> You will take how much time?<lb/> MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: I will finish in two days maximum, so<lb/> that he can have two and a half days for<lb/> his reply.<lb/> MR. JUSTICE ALAM:<lb/> We can give you a maximum of three<lb/> days.<lb/> MR. KUMAR:<lb/> I&apos;m telling you now that my request is I<lb/> need five days.<lb/> MR. JUSTICE ALAM:<lb/> No, we can give you three days and<lb/> after that, you can give us your written<lb/> submissions.<lb/> Kindly<lb/> tailor<lb/> your<lb/> arguments that way.&quot;<lb/> (emphasis supplied)<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: Now 16.<lb/> MR. TYAGI:<lb/> Now 18. So after that, it is only RRDS.<lb/> So it is only about those 18 documents.<lb/> MR. JUSTICE ALAM:<lb/> Whatever.<lb/> MR. TYAGI:<lb/> We&apos;ll work that out.<lb/> MR. JUSTICE ALAM:<lb/> Be careful, because I think in the award,<lb/> there will be a lot of confusion. I don&apos;t<lb/> know at what stage somehow or other<lb/> you took it that there would be two<lb/> different proceedings.&quot;<lb/> (emphasis supplied)<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <figDesc>MR. KUMAR:<lb/> Therefore, he will file submissions, I will<lb/> submissions of what we argue?<lb/> MR. JUSTICE ALAM:<lb/> With copies to each other. It will be<lb/> open to both of you to file your reply to<lb/> the written submissions filed by the<lb/> other side by 20 th . Definitely by 20 th .<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>You may.&quot;<lb/> (emphasis supplied)<lb/> 104.<lb/> On 3 rd February, 2017, the Arbitral Tribunal passed<lb/> certain directions with reference to payment of their fees. The<lb/> relevant portion reads thus:<lb/> &quot;CHAIRMAN:<lb/> Now, we have to issue certain directions<lb/> about the payment of the arbitrators&apos;<lb/> fees.<lb/> You are requested to pay deposit for the<lb/> fees of arbitrators for a period of three<lb/> days working. That is two days for<lb/> internal<lb/> discussion<lb/> among<lb/> the<lb/> arbitrators and one day for the<lb/> pronouncement of the award.<lb/> MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: What about writing of the award itself?<lb/> That also takes time.<lb/> MR. JUSTICE ALAM:<lb/> Two sittings for that. Third sitting for<lb/> pronouncement.<lb/> CHAIRMAN:<lb/> So three days&apos; fees for the arbitrators at<lb/> the rate of --<lb/>MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: 50 per cent.<lb/> CHAIRMAN:<lb/> --2 lakhs per arbitrator per day. That to<lb/> be deposited by 28 February.&quot;<lb/> 105.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>Then, we come to the transcript of 4 th February, 2017.<lb/> After the hearing was over, on 4 th February, 2017, this is what<lb/> transpired before the Tribunal:<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>&quot;17.08<lb/> We will give that in our submission.<lb/> MR. PREMKUMAR:<lb/> I think in all fairness we will require a<lb/> little more time for this.<lb/> MR. JUSTICE ALAM:<lb/> If both sides agree, we are willing to sit.<lb/> MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: The problem is the time, really speaking,<lb/> that is the difficulty. If we had booked<lb/> earlier, seven days, eight days, we<lb/> would have kept our diaries open for<lb/> that.<lb/> MR. PREMKUMAR:<lb/> I mention if both sides agree, we can sit<lb/> for a day or something.<lb/> MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: It is better to do it after the submissions.<lb/> MR. PREMKUMAR:<lb/> So that we have more clarity.<lb/> MR. MUKHOPADHAYA: What some tribunals do, if I may<lb/> suggest, before the hearing also if your<lb/> Lordships<lb/> have<lb/> any<lb/> clarification<lb/> questions,<lb/> because<lb/> instead<lb/> of<lb/> addressing everything again, your<lb/> Lordships have heard everything, but if<lb/> there are specific points which your<lb/> Lordships need clarification on, just say<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>that </note>
 
            <figDesc>these are the points on which we<lb/> want clarification, so we are prepared<lb/> with that and it can be a short, focused<lb/> hearing, everything else will be on<lb/> written submissions. If your Lordships<lb/> feel it is necessary we have no difficulty<lb/> with that.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>CHAIRMAN:<lb/> So arguments from both sides are<lb/> closed today. Both sides are given time<lb/> approved, 14 February to file their<lb/> written submissions.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>[Offline discussion]<lb/> CHAIRMAN:<lb/> So your submissions by 20 February<lb/> and thereafter by 27 February you can<lb/> file reply, if any, to these submissions by<lb/> the other side. Thereafter, if we feel that<lb/> it requires some hearing clarifications<lb/> after going through your submissions,<lb/> the date will be fixed for the further<lb/> hearing if any required.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>MR. KUMAR:<lb/> Sir, my request would be that in case<lb/> you do decide to hold the hearing,<lb/> between 25 March and 5 April, I will<lb/> have a difficulty.</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>Termination Payment,<lb/> the Claimant has also made a claim of approximately<lb/> Rs.469 crore, based on amounts invested by shareholders<lb/> and an assumed return of 14.74%. This alternative claim<lb/> is virtually a proxy claim for Termination Payment, but<lb/> calculated not as per the contractual formula, but based<lb/> on the actual amount invested by shareholders. Since the<lb/> Tribunal is inclined to defer its decision on the issue of<lb/> Termination Payment, the decision on this alternative<lb/> claim of Rs.469 crore approximately also stands deferred.&quot;<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> <note>SR Pasha, Sr PS<lb/> Page 153 of 169</note>
		</figure>



    </text>
</tei>

