<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_47bd1f45457ab1ea0d80f2d977b05ca7.pdf"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">


        <figure>

            1.<lb/> By this petition </content>
 
            <figDesc>filed under section 34 of the Arbitration<lb/> &amp; Conciliation Act, 1996 (for short &quot;the Act&quot;), the petitioner<lb/> challenges the Interim Award dated 25 th April, 2017, passed by the<lb/> Arbitral Tribunal to the extent it awards and determines:<lb/> (i)<lb/> that the Concession Agreement dated 25 th August, 2006<lb/> was validly terminated, both on account of Political<lb/> Force Majeure Events and material default on the part of<lb/> the Petitioner thereby holding / finding that the issue of<lb/> liability against the Petitioner is finally determined;</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>1(b) and<lb/> not just one claim, namely claim No.5 for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; as<lb/> held by the Arbitral Tribunal.<lb/> 18.<lb/> Mr. Chagla thereafter brought to my attention, another<lb/> letter dated 16 th April, 2010, which again reiterates that PLUS had<lb/> sought compensation from MSRDC for all additional direct costs<lb/> suffered and incurred by them arising out of the purported material<lb/> defaults by MSRDC. Mr. Chagla pointed out that a similar letter was<lb/> again written by PLUS on 30 th April, 2010. Finally, on 10 th May,<lb/> 2010, PLUS invoked clause 39.1(b) of the Concession Agreement<lb/> and called upon the IC to mediate and assist in resolving the<lb/> reimbursement demands already raised in respect of compensation<lb/> for all additional direct costs suffered due to material defaults of the<lb/> Concession Agreement by MSRDC under clause 31.2 of the<lb/> Concession Agreement. The subject of the letter is identical to the<lb/> earlier letters and the letter itself refers to the letter of 30 th April,<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> 2010, and </content>
 
            <figDesc>to all preceding communication to MSRDC on the<lb/> abovementioned subject. Therefore, Mr. Chagla submitted that by<lb/> the said letter, various alleged material defaults on the part of<lb/> MSRDC were referred to the IC, including the claims arising out of<lb/> material defaults under clause 10.1(v) of the Concession<lb/> Agreement. Mr. Chagla submitted that after a meeting on 5 th June,<lb/> 2010, scheduled by the IC, in pursuance of PLUS&apos; invocation of<lb/> conciliation, PLUS, inter alia, stated that it was continuing to suffer<lb/> huge losses in revenue and that there was reduction in Toll income<lb/> and that it was seeking compensation for all direct losses suffered by<lb/> PLUS arising out of the erection of barrier by the Government<lb/> Agency (The Commissioner of Police). PLUS also stated that it was<lb/> willing to accept the extension of the concession period in lieu of<lb/> cash payment in light of loss in Toll revenue which was stated as<lb/> Rs.103.9 crores. Mr. Chagla thereafter also brought to my attention<lb/> the letter written by the IC dated 14 th July, 2010 to MSRDC which<lb/> categorically submitted the revised calculations in respect of the<lb/> loss in total revenue due to delay in issue of Toll Notification, non-<lb/>payment of Toll by KDMT and NMMT buses and loss due to diversion<lb/> of heavy vehicles. He thereafter brought to my attention the letter<lb/> written by the IC to MSRDC dated 23 rd June, 2011, wherein one<lb/> Dhruv Consultant provided the expenditure figures and stated that<lb/> the IC had revised the same to Rs.161.19 cores and incidentally<lb/> Annexure B to the said letter explicitly calculates the loss due to<lb/> diversion of heavy traffic. He also brought to my attention other<lb/> letters written by the IC to MSRDC dated 9 th July, 2011 and 2 nd<lb/> August, 2011. He also submitted that subsequent thereto, MSRDC,<lb/> on 20 th October, 2011, made an offer to PLUS in respect of the<lb/> request for conciliation under their letter dated 10 th May, 2010 by<lb/> proposing an extension in the concession period until 10 th July,<lb/> 2024 in lieu of claim Nos.1, 4, 5 and 6 and rejecting the claim for<lb/> compensation for loss of revenue on account of delay in issuing the<lb/> Toll Notification and KDMT and NMMT buses refusing to pay Toll.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>independent consultant appointed by MSRDC, M/s S.N. Bhobhe &amp;<lb/> Associates Pvt. Ltd. ( hereinafter referred to as &quot;Independent<lb/> Consultant&quot;) contained in various letters resting with the last letter<lb/> on the subject matter bearing no. SNBAPL/MSRDC-33/BKSP/PLA-<lb/>EST/2010-11/P-113/545-D/1530 dated July 19, 2011 which<lb/> contained revised cash flows on the claims submitted on the Claim<lb/> Letter, and upon complying with various internal procedures and<lb/> approvals within MSRDC, including the approval from MSRDC<lb/> Board of Directors Resolution vide Item Number 06 dated<lb/> September 27, 2011, MSRDC, vide its letter number<lb/> MSRDC/02/JMD(I) BKSH/F.No. 142/3987 dated October 20, 2011<lb/> made an offer of an amicable settlement to the Concessionaire<lb/> regarding the six(6) claims presented by the Concessionaire vide<lb/> the Claim Letter (&quot;MSRDC Offer&quot;) (as detailed in &quot;Annexure B&quot;<lb/> hereto).<lb/> The MSRDC Offer was duly accepted by the<lb/> Concessionaire vide the letter no. BKSP/PD/CA/E/C986-04-11-<lb/>2011 dated November 4, 2011 (&quot;Acceptance Letter) (as annexed<lb/> hereto as &quot;Annexure C&quot;)&quot; .<lb/> 19.<lb/> Relying upon the aforesaid recital, Mr. Chagla submitted<lb/> that even according to PLUS, all six claims were referred to<lb/> conciliation under clause 39.1(b) and, therefore, it was wholly<lb/> incorrect on the part of the Arbitral Tribunal to come to the<lb/> conclusion that only one claim, namely, for &apos;additional direct cost&apos;<lb/> was referred to conciliation and not the other claims. He submitted<lb/> that this was contrary to the entire record, including what was<lb/> stated in the termination notice issued by PLUS dated 19 th March,<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> 2013.<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> 20.<lb/> Mr. Chagla </content>
 
            <figDesc>then submitted that even in PLUS&apos; own<lb/> pleadings [in the Statement of Claim], under the heading &quot;Facts<lb/> about traffic diversion due to ban on entry of heavy vehicles on the<lb/> BKSP Road&quot;, PLUS has clearly averred that it invoked clause 39.1</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>dispute. Failing mediation by the IC or without the intervention of<lb/> the IC, either party could refer such dispute to the Vice Chairman<lb/> and Managing Director of MSRDC and the Chairman of the Board of<lb/> Directors of PLUS, for an amicable settlement. In the facts of the<lb/> present case, MSRDC appointed M/s. S.N. Bhobe and Associates<lb/> Private Limited as the IC for the current Project.<lb/> 22.<lb/> Mr. Khambata submitted that the six claims submitted<lb/> by PLUS to the IC can be divided into two types. Firstly, those<lb/> claims that were lodged by PLUS with the IC on account of various<lb/> reasons during the usual course of business. Secondly, those claims<lb/> in respect of which there was a dispute and PLUS had invoked<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> clause 39.1(</content>

            <figDesc>b) of the Concession Agreement for mediation by the IC.<lb/> Mr. Khambatta submitted that in the facts of the present case, the<lb/> six claims submitted to the IC were as under:<lb/> Claim No.1<lb/> Extension in Concession Period due to<lb/> revision of COD to 29.12.2009.<lb/> Claim No.2<lb/> Loss in Toll revenue due to delay in Toll<lb/> Notification.<lb/> Claim No.3<lb/> Loss in Toll revenue due to ban on heavy<lb/> vehicles on the Project Highway.<lb/> Claim No.4<lb/> Loss in Toll revenue due to refusal to pay<lb/> the Toll fee by KDMT/NMMT for their<lb/> buses plying on the Project Highway.<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> Claim No.5<lb/> Additional direct cost reimbursement due<lb/> to material default of the Concession<lb/> Agreement by MSRDC. -Submitted for<lb/> mediation of the IC under clause<lb/> 39.1(b).<lb/> Claim No.6<lb/> Variation in project cost due to changes in<lb/> the Scope of Work.<lb/> (emphasis supplied)<lb/> 23.<lb/> Mr. Khambatta </content>
 
            <figDesc>submitted that only claim No.5 and<lb/> which was for &apos;additional direct cost&apos;, was referred to mediation of<lb/> the IC under clause 39.1(b). He submitted that this was clear from<lb/> the fact that PLUS by its letter dated 26 th February, 2010, addressed<lb/> submitted by PLUS. However, what is important to note is that the<lb/> IC categorically mentioned that clause 39.1(b) was invoked only<lb/> with reference to &apos;additional direct cost&apos;. The IC subsequently, on<lb/> 23 rd June, 2011, wrote to MSRDC in relation to the calculation for<lb/> the &apos;additional direct cost&apos; reimbursement whereby the revised<lb/> amount was Rs.161.19 crores. Mr. Khambatta submitted that on<lb/> looking at this letter it was abundantly clear that the claim was only<lb/> for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; in the sum of Rs.161.19 crores and not<lb/> the other claims which were independent of the claim for &apos;additional<lb/> direct cost&apos;. He pointed out that thereafter, by a letter dated 3 rd<lb/> February, 2011, MSRDC informed PLUS stating that they had<lb/> referred all the claims of PLUS to a Committee of Directors<lb/> consisting of the Vice Chairman and Managing Director of MSRDC.<lb/> The Committee was to consider the claims and decide on their<lb/> admissibility and thereafter quantify the same. The Committee was<lb/> to also determine the conversion of the quantified claim to the<lb/> concession period in terms of the Concession Agreement and the<lb/> resultant increase in the concession period. He submitted that all<lb/> claims were referred to the Committee of Directors for the purpose<lb/> of compensating PLUS by extending the Toll period in lieu of cash.<lb/> Mr. Khambatta submitted that this Committee of Directors was not<lb/> the joint mediation envisaged under clause 39.1(b) and which was<lb/> to consist of (i) the Vice Chairman and Managing Director of MSRDC<lb/> and (ii) the Chairman of PLUS. This Committee of Directors was an<lb/> internal Committee of MSRDC. He thereafter brought to my<lb/> attention, the report of the Committee of Directors of July, 2011. He<lb/> submitted that the Committee of Directors considered all the claims<lb/> and presented its report in respect thereof. In the said report it is<lb/> mentioned that PLUS had lodged six claims with the IC. The report<lb/> analysed<lb/> each<lb/> claim<lb/> individually<lb/> and<lb/> gave<lb/> separate<lb/> recommendations for each claim. Out of the six claims, the<lb/> Committee accepted claim Nos.1, 3, 4 and 6 to be admissible<lb/> whereas claim No.2 was not accepted as a valid claim. With<lb/> reference to claim No. 5, and which related to &apos;additional direct cost&apos;,<lb/> the Committee of Directors stated as under:</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>27.<lb/> To understand this controversy, one must understand<lb/> the role of the IC. The IC is defined in the definitions clause (clause<lb/> 1.1). It stipulates that the IC (Independent Consultant) shall have<lb/> the meaning ascribed to it in clause 20.1. Correspondingly, clause<lb/> 20 of the Concession Agreement deals with the appointment of the<lb/> IC and his duties and obligations. Clause 20 of the Concession<lb/> Agreement reads thus:</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>purpose, namely, to monitor and supervise the Project. The<lb/> Independent Consultant (IC) was to report to MSRDC about the<lb/> working, services and activities through regular periodic reports.<lb/> Such reports were to include but not limited to the matters and<lb/> things set forth in Schedule-O. MSRDC also had the right to<lb/> terminate the appointment of the IC at any time, subject to<lb/> appointment of their replacement by another IC in accordance with<lb/> Article XXII. From the aforesaid clauses, it is clear that the IC was a<lb/> person appointed by MSRDC to monitor and supervise the Project<lb/> and was to report to MSRDC regarding its progress by filing regular<lb/> periodic reports. Apart from this role, the IC had another role to<lb/> play. This was to act as a Mediator as contemplated under clause<lb/> 39.1(b) of the Concession Agreement. For the sake of convenience,<lb/> Clause 39.1 is reproduced hereunder:<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> &quot;39. DISPUTE RESOLUTION<lb/> 39.1 Amicable Resolution<lb/> (a)<lb/> Save where expressly </content>
 
            <figDesc>stated to the contrary in the<lb/> Agreement, any dispute, difference or controversy of whatever<lb/> nature howsoever arising under, out of or in relation to this<lb/> Agreement including incompletion of the Project Highway<lb/> between the Parties and so notified in writing by either Party to<lb/> the other (the &quot;Dispute&quot;) in the first instance shall be attempted<lb/> to be resolved amicably in accordance with the conciliation<lb/> procedure set forth in Sub-clause (b) below.<lb/> (b)<lb/> In the event of any Dispute between the Parties, either<lb/> Party may call upon the Independent Consultant to mediate<lb/> and assist the Parties in arriving at an amicable settlement<lb/> thereof. Failing mediation by the Independent Consultant or<lb/> without the intervention of the Independent Consultant, either<lb/> Party may require such Dispute to be referred to the VC &amp; MD<lb/> of MSRDC and the Chairman of the Board of Directors of the<lb/> Concessionaire, for the time being for amicable settlement.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>accordance with the conciliation procedure set forth in sub-clause<lb/> (b) of clause 39.1. Sub-clause (b) stipulates that in the event of any<lb/> dispute between the parties, either party may call upon the IC to<lb/> mediate and assist the parties in arriving at an amicable settlement<lb/> thereof. Failing mediation by the IC, or without the intervention of<lb/> the IC, either party may require such dispute to be referred to (i) the<lb/> VC and MD of MSRDC and (ii) the Chairman of the Board of<lb/> Directors of PLUS, for an amicable settlement. In other words,<lb/> conciliation proceedings under clause 39.1(b) could be undertaken<lb/> either by (i) the IC; or (ii) the VC and MD of MSRDC alongwith the<lb/> Chairman of the Board of Directors of PLUS. Reading these clauses,<lb/> I find considerable force in the argument of Mr. Khambatta that the<lb/> IC, under the Concession Agreement, wore two different hats.<lb/> Firstly, he was a person who was supposed to monitor and supervise<lb/> the Project and report to MSRDC. The second was to act as a<lb/> Mediator under clause 39.1(b), if the said clause was so invoked by<lb/> either party.<lb/> 30.<lb/> Having said this, I shall now examine whether the<lb/> factual situation before me is one where mediation / conciliation was<lb/> invoked with reference to all six claims submitted by PLUS to the IC<lb/> or whether it was only the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; that was<lb/> the subject matter of mediation/conciliation under clause 39.1(b).<lb/> In this regard, I find considerable force in the arguments canvassed<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>by Mr. Khambatta. Clause 39.1(b) was invoked by PLUS vide its<lb/> letter dated 10 th May, 2010. This letter was issued in relation to the<lb/> claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos;. On receipt of the aforesaid<lb/> communication, the IC, vide its letter dated 15 th May, 2010,<lb/> informed MSRDC that PLUS had invoked clause 39.1(b) of the<lb/> Concession Agreement in relation to the issue of &apos;additional direct<lb/> cost&apos;. MSRDC thereafter, by its letter dated 29 th May, 2010,<lb/> requested both PLUS and the IC to attend a meeting for dispute<lb/> resolution under clause 39.1(b) in relation to the issue of &apos;additional<lb/> direct cost&apos; reimbursement. Thereafter, the IC in its communication<lb/> dated 11 th October, 2010, addressed to MSRDC discussed the six<lb/> claims submitted by PLUS. However, what is important to note is<lb/> that the IC categorically mentioned that clause 39.1(b) was invoked<lb/> only with reference to the claim of &apos;additional direct cost&apos; which<lb/> arose due to the delay in the Commercial Operations Date (COD) and<lb/> not for other claims. In fact, on the face of it, claim Nos.3 &amp; 4, and<lb/> which related to (i) loss in Toll revenue due to ban on heavy vehicles<lb/> on the Project Highway and (ii) loss in Toll revenue due to refusal to<lb/> pay the Toll fee by KDMT/NMMT for their buses plying on the<lb/> Project Highway, are not, as they could not have been, claims made<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>due to the delay in the Commercial Operations Date (COD) at all. The<lb/> relevant portion of the said letter reads thus:<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> &quot;… … …<lb/> 6)<lb/> Additional Direct Cost </content>
 
            <figDesc>due to material default of the<lb/> concession agreement by MSRDC: This claim is due to the<lb/> delay in COD of the project highway and additional direct costs<lb/> suffered by the concessionaire as a result of this delay. The<lb/> sequence of events and concessionaire&apos;s claim are as follows:<lb/> a.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>g<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>As per clause 39.1(b) of the concession agreement,<lb/> concessionaire has called upon us to mediate and assist in<lb/> arriving at an amicable settlement of the issue vide its letters<lb/> numbered 435 and 439 dated 10.05.2010 and 26.05.2010<lb/> respectively.<lb/> … … …&quot;<lb/> (emphasis supplied)<lb/> 31.<lb/> Apart from this, I find that all the claims submitted by<lb/> PLUS were referred by MSRDC to a Committee of Directors<lb/> consisting of the Vice Chairman and Managing Director of MSRDC.<lb/> This Committee of Directors thereafter prepared a report in July,<lb/> 2011 wherein it considered all the claims of PLUS and presented its<lb/> report in respect thereof. The said report categorically mentions<lb/> that PLUS had lodged six claims with the IC. The report analysed<lb/> each claim individually and gave separate recommendations for<lb/> each claim. Out of the six claims submitted by PLUS, the Committee<lb/> accepted claim Nos.1, 3, 4 and 6 (set out earlier) to be admissible,<lb/> whereas claim No.2 was not accepted as a valid claim. With<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>reference to claim No.5 and which related to &apos;additional direct cost&apos;,<lb/> the Committee of Directors noted that PLUS had requested for<lb/> resolution of this issue under the provisions of the Dispute<lb/> Resolution as per clause 39.1 of the Concession Agreement and for<lb/> which MSRDC had appointed Mr. A.V. Deodhar to represent itself in<lb/> the dispute resolution proceedings. It was thereafter recommended<lb/> that it would be more suitable that this issue is resolved as per the<lb/> provisions of the Concession Agreement for determination of the<lb/> value of &apos;additional direct cost&apos; and to grant extension in the<lb/> concession period which will also save MSRDC a substantial<lb/> financial burden of paying cash compensation.<lb/> 32.<lb/> From all this material, I find that Mr. Khambatta is<lb/> correct in his submission that only the claim for &apos;additional direct<lb/> cost&apos; [namely, claim No. 5], was the claim that was referred to<lb/> mediation / conciliation under clause 39.1(b) of the Concession<lb/> Agreement. I am unable to agree with Mr. Chagla that the words<lb/> &apos;additional direct cost&apos; should be read in an omnibus fashion which<lb/> would include every single claim that was submitted by PLUS to the<lb/> IC. This is not how the IC understood it and neither was it the<lb/> understanding of MSRDC or the Committee of Directors of MSRDC.<lb/> 33.<lb/> This apart, I find the discussion on this aspect by the<lb/> Arbitral Tribunal is at paragraphs 65, 75 and 76 respectively. The<lb/> Tribunal has noted that the letter dated 10 th May, 2010, and the<lb/> letters issued earlier to it do not actually refer to the six claims, but<lb/> rather only to the claim of &apos;additional direct cost&apos;. This claim was<lb/> first put forward by a letter dated 24 th February, 2010 where PLUS<lb/> claimed an amount of Rs.161 crores as the escalated project cost on<lb/> account of material default of MSRDC. Subsequently, this claim was<lb/> pursued by further letters dated 16 th April, 2010 and 30 th April,<lb/> 2010. Finally, by means of the letter dated 10 th May, 2010, PLUS<lb/> proposed conciliation. It is in this light that the Arbitral Tribunal<lb/> came to a finding that the offer of conciliation was in relation only to<lb/> the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos;. The Tribunal held that though<lb/> it is true that other claims had also been raised by that time, these<lb/> were by means of separate letters and were separately pursued. It<lb/> is only much later, by a communication dated 2 nd August, 2011, that<lb/> the Independent Consultant clubs the various claims under the six<lb/> heads and makes its recommendations with relation to each claim.<lb/> With reference to claim No.5 (&apos;additional direct cost&apos;), the IC once<lb/> again notes that PLUS has already requested for resolution of this<lb/> issue under the provisions of the Dispute Resolution as per clause<lb/> 39.1 of the Concession Agreement and it is most suitable that this<lb/> issue is resolved amicably as per the provisions of clause 39.1<lb/> through negotiated settlement and granting extension in the<lb/> concession period will save MSRDC a substantial financial burden of<lb/> paying cash compensation. The Tribunal further notes the strong<lb/> objection of MSRDC regarding the admissibility of not only the<lb/> Director&apos;s report referred to above, but to a very large number of<lb/> documents / correspondence exchanged between PLUS, the IC and<lb/> MSRDC in regard to the claims raised. It notes that the objection to<lb/> the admissibility of these documents is the most prominent and<lb/> consistent theme of the case of MSRDC. The main objection is that<lb/> the correspondence between the parties was made in the course of<lb/> conciliation proceedings and, therefore, protected by confidentiality<lb/> on account of sections 75 and 81 in Part III of the Arbitration &amp;<lb/> Conciliation Act, 1996 and/or section 23 of the Evidence Act. After<lb/> considering the material and giving a careful consideration to the<lb/> objection raised by MSRDC, the Tribunal finds no merit in this<lb/> contention. The Tribunal holds that firstly the conciliation<lb/> proceedings were only invoked in relation to the claim for<lb/> &apos;additional direct cost&apos; whereas the figure of Rs.112 crores includes<lb/> circumstances that the Tribunal rejected the contention of MSRDC<lb/> that the documents exchanged between the parties was a part of<lb/> conciliation and, therefore, inadmissible in the proceedings. The<lb/> Tribunal thereafter, though holding that the documents were<lb/> admissible, categorically recorded that it would still be required to<lb/> be determined as to the weightage that could be attached to these<lb/> documents as evidence of an admitted quantification of the loss<lb/> suffered by PLUS.<lb/> 34.<lb/> Having gone through the findings given by the Arbitral<lb/> Tribunal in the relevant paragraphs mentioned above, it can hardly<lb/> be stated that the view taken by the Tribunal suffers from any<lb/> patent illegality or is perverse. The Tribunal has examined the<lb/> record, heard the parties and thereafter come to its conclusion. The<lb/> Arbitral Tribunal has categorically held that after looking at the<lb/> correspondence on record, the conciliation proceedings were only<lb/> invoked in relation to the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos; and not<lb/> with reference to any other claim. This finding can hardly be<lb/> termed as perverse and is certainly a plausible view taken by the<lb/> Tribunal to hold that the objection to the admissibility of the</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> said event occurred solely on account of the failure on the part of<lb/> PLUS to perform its obligations under the Concession Agreement.<lb/> Mr. Chagla submitted that clause 18.1 of the Concession Agreement<lb/> obliged PLUS to prevent unauthorised entry and exit from the<lb/> Project Road. Further, it was the duty and obligation of PLUS to levy<lb/> and collect Toll from the users of the Project Road and refuse entry<lb/> of any vehicle if the Toll fee was not paid. Mr. Chagla submitted that<lb/> the finding of the Arbitral Tribunal on this aspect is arrived at<lb/> without considering the material clauses of the Concession<lb/> Agreement and has resulted in PLUS being virtually absolved from<lb/> its obligations under the Concession Agreement and which is clearly<lb/> impermissible. He submitted that PLUS could have overcome the<lb/> event by exercising due diligence and reasonable efforts, skill and<lb/> care, including through expenditure of reasonable sums of money.<lb/> The finding of the Arbitral Tribunal that PLUS exercised necessary<lb/> due diligence and that precipitating matters any further could lead<lb/> to serious law and order repercussions is incorrect and contrary to<lb/> its own conclusion that it was for PLUS to exercise legal remedies to<lb/> enforce its rights under the Toll Notification. Mr. Chagla submitted<lb/> that the Arbitral Tribunal has arrived at this finding on the basis of<lb/> assumptions and presumptions and has virtually absolved PLUS of<lb/> its obligations to collect Toll and prevent entry of any vehicle that<lb/> was not authorised to use the Project Road. Since PLUS chose not to<lb/> collect Toll from the KDMT and NMMT buses though they were<lb/> entitled to under the Concession Agreement, PLUS now cannot claim<lb/> that the same amounts to a Political Force Majeure event which<lb/> entitles them to terminate the agreement. To put it differently, Mr.<lb/> Chagla submitted that PLUS cannot take advantage of its own<lb/> wrong.<lb/> 45.<lb/> Mr. Chagla lastly submitted that in any event there was<lb/> no material adverse effect caused to PLUS by KDMT and NMMT<lb/> buses not paying the Toll. He submitted that the Arbitral Tribunal<lb/> has held that it is unable to arrive at a quantum determination<lb/> based on the existing record and submissions and the Tribunal<lb/> cannot place much weight on the quantum figures arrived at during<lb/> the stage of settlement. Further, the loss on account of Toll revenue<lb/> from KDMT and NMMT buses was also submitted to the IC during<lb/> conciliation proceedings initiated by PLUS. There was, therefore, no<lb/> evidence or material before the Tribunal on the basis of which the<lb/> Tribunal could have arrived at a finding that there was any material<lb/> adverse effect. Further, the Arbitral Tribunal has not referred to<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>any evidence in order to arrive at the said finding, was the<lb/> submission of Mr. Chagla. He, therefore, submitted that the finding<lb/> of the Arbitral Tribunal in this respect is patently illegal and<lb/> perverse.<lb/> 46.<lb/> Mr. Chagla then submitted that similar is the case with<lb/> reference to the ban on heavy vehicles and multi axle vehicles<lb/> [ground (c) above]. He submitted that the ban on heavy vehicles and<lb/> multi axle vehicles did not constitute a Political Force Majeure event<lb/> and the same is evident from the fact that the ban on the said<lb/> vehicles did not amount to a change in law and there was no<lb/> material adverse effect on account of the said ban. Mr. Chagla<lb/> submitted that the finding of the Arbitral Tribunal that PLUS was<lb/> not aware of the resolution passed by KDMC allowing heavy vehicles<lb/> to ply on the project road/project highway only from 10.00 p.m. to<lb/> 6.00 a.m. is contrary to the evidence on record. He submitted that<lb/> PLUS was all along aware about the circular dated 20 th March, 2006<lb/> as by the very circular itself, NOC was granted to KDMC to carry out<lb/> the work. The said NOC was admittedly obtained by PLUS as<lb/> recorded in the Minutes of the Meeting held on 31 st July, 2006 and<lb/> which Minutes were forwarded to MSRDC by PLUS by its letter<lb/> dated 3 rd August, 2006. The finding of the Arbitral Tribunal that<lb/> PLUS was unaware of the said circular is belied by the deposition<lb/> and cross-examination of MSRDC&apos;s witness wherein the witness of<lb/> MSRDC has clearly stated that the ban on heavy vehicles was<lb/> applicable much before the tender was issued for the Project Road<lb/> and the said Resolutions dated 9 th March, 2006 and 20 th March,<lb/> 2006 were public documents and known to the public. Mr. Chagla<lb/> submitted that the Notifications of 11 th May 2009 and 29 th<lb/> December, 2009 imposing a complete ban did not amount to a<lb/> change in the law or an expropriation of the rights of PLUS within<lb/> the meaning of clause 29. He, therefore, submitted that the ban on<lb/> heavy vehicles, in any event, did not amount to a Political Force<lb/> Majeure event as it did not amount to a change in law.<lb/> 47.<lb/> Even assuming for the sake of argument that it would<lb/> amount to a Political Force Majeure event, Mr. Chagla submitted<lb/> that there was no material adverse effect as a result of the said ban.<lb/> The finding of the Arbitral Tribunal that undoubtedly the event had<lb/> a material adverse effect on the Project as the amount of uncollected<lb/> Toll was allegedly in excess of Rs.60 crores is perverse as the<lb/> Arbitral Tribunal has arrived at this conclusion in the absence of<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>any evidence as no loss has been proved by PLUS. In any event, this<lb/> finding in respect of the figure of Rs.60 crores is also on the basis of<lb/> a figure worked out by the IC during the course of conciliation<lb/> proceedings. PLUS has even admitted in paragraph 6.53 of the<lb/> Statement of Claim that the loss on account of ban on heavy vehicles<lb/> was calculated by the IC vide its letter dated 14 th July, 2010, in<lb/> furtherance of the conciliation proceedings initiated by it. This<lb/> finding has been arrived at by relying upon documents exchanged<lb/> between the parties during the course of mediation and/or<lb/> conciliation and/or amicable settlement. Further, the said figure of<lb/> Rs.60 crores is included in the figure of Rs.112 crores. The Arbitral<lb/> Tribunal has rejected the said claim as is evident from the finding of<lb/> the Arbitral Tribunal in paragraphs 77, 79, 86 and 87 of the Award.<lb/> Therefore, the finding of the Arbitral Tribunal that ban on heavy<lb/> vehicles resulted in a material adverse effect is not only self-<lb/>contradictory, but without any basis. He, therefore, submitted that<lb/> even the termination under clause 29.8 was wholly unwarranted<lb/> and the findings of the Tribunal in this regard are contrary to the<lb/> record and are patently illegal and perverse and ought to be<lb/> interfered with under section 34 of the Arbitration &amp; Conciliation<lb/> Act, 1996.<lb/> SUBMISSIONS OF PLUS:<lb/> 48.<lb/> On the other hand, Mr. Khambatta, the learned senior<lb/> counsel appearing on behalf of PLUS, submitted that in the present<lb/> case, the issue whether the termination of the contract was valid or<lb/> not is a finding of fact. If it is a finding of fact, the challenge to the<lb/> findings on the termination being valid is not maintainable under<lb/> section 34 as the Arbitral Tribunal is the final Judge of the facts of<lb/> the matter. He submitted that this Court under section 34 does not<lb/> sit in appeal over the findings given by the Arbitral Tribunal. He<lb/> submitted that the Concession Agreement was terminated by two<lb/> separate termination notices, both dated 19 th March, 2013. One was<lb/> for termination on the ground of Political Force Majeure (under<lb/> clause 29.8) and the other was for defaults committed by MSRDC<lb/> (under clause 32.4). Mr. Khambatta submitted that the termination<lb/> notice issued pursuant to clause 32.4 of the Concession Agreement<lb/> was on account of defaults committed by MSRDC in failing to pay the<lb/> admitted claims of the petitioner, including the &apos;additional direct<lb/> cost&apos; incurred by PLUS due to the lapses of MSRDC. Mr. Khambatta<lb/> brought to my attention paragraph 70 of the Award wherein the<lb/> Tribunal clearly observed that the terms of the Agreement leave no<lb/> doubt that it was MSRDC&apos;s obligation to make the Project site<lb/> available and MSRDC defaulted on this obligation. Thus, MSRDC<lb/> was in breach of its obligations under clause 4.1(b) as well as<lb/> clauses 10.1(i), 10.1(ii) and 10.1(iii). The Tribunal, therefore, held<lb/> that there does exist a valid basis for termination, both under clause<lb/> 32.4.1(1) and 32.4.1(3). Mr. Khambatta also brought to my<lb/> attention that the Tribunal has also observed in paragraph 70 of the<lb/> Award that there were enough documents on record wherein the IC<lb/> and MSRDC have acknowledged that MSRDC was responsible for<lb/> making the Project site available. In fact, MSRDC itself admitted<lb/> that PLUS was entitled to extension both on account of delayed<lb/> acquisition of land as well as for the delay in the construction of the<lb/> Railway Over Bridge (ROB). Even as far as the 90 day notice period<lb/> is concerned, Mr. Khambatta submitted that the Tribunal correctly<lb/> held in paragraph 70 that the requirements under clause 32.4 of the<lb/> Concession Agreement for a 90 day notice was complied with by<lb/> PLUS since it had held out the prospect of termination long before it<lb/> was terminated and had refrained from issuing a formal notice due<lb/> to MSRDC&apos;s assurance that the issue would be sorted out. This being<lb/> the case, Mr. Khambatta submitted that if one goes through the<lb/> Award on the issue of termination under clause 32.4, it is clear that<lb/> the Tribunal has taken everything into consideration and has<lb/> thereafter come to its finding that the termination is valid under the<lb/> said clause. He submitted that the finding of the Tribunal on this<lb/> aspect can certainly not be termed as either patently illegal or<lb/> perverse and is certainly a plausible view. If this be the case, then,<lb/> there is no question of interfering with the impugned Award on this<lb/> count, was the submission.<lb/> 49.<lb/> Similarly, Mr. Khambatta submitted that even<lb/> termination under clause 29.8 (for a Political Force Majeure event)<lb/> is legal and valid as held by the Arbitral Tribunal. Mr. Khambatta<lb/> pointed out that paragraphs 61 and 62 of the Interim Award hold<lb/> that the right to collect Toll is an entitlement of PLUS under clause<lb/> 6.1 of the Concession Agreement. The refusal to pay Toll by KDMT<lb/> and NMMT Government buses was held as amounting to<lb/> expropriation or taking away the rights of PLUS to collect and retain<lb/> Toll from these buses in accordance with the Toll Notification. He<lb/> submitted that in paragraph 62, the Tribunal held that PLUS took up<lb/> this issue with KDMT and NMMT, and MSRDC was also alerted in<lb/> January, 2010 that these Government buses were not paying Toll.<lb/> Further, it was also observed that an account was kept of the<lb/> number of Government buses passing through the Toll on a daily<lb/> basis and PLUS, therefore, took all necessary steps to overcome the<lb/> Political Force Majeure event. The Tribunal further held that non-<lb/>payment of Toll by the Government buses seriously impacted the<lb/> amount of revenue that was to be received by PLUS under the Toll<lb/> Notification.<lb/> 50.<lb/> Mr. Khambatta submitted that the Government buses of<lb/> KDMT and NMMT were specifically shown in the Project<lb/> Information Memorandum (PIM) and the Concession Agreement as<lb/> a category of vehicles which would have to pay Toll and was not<lb/> listed as exempted vehicles either in the Concession Agreement or<lb/> in the Toll Notification. Accordingly, the bid submitted by PLUS was<lb/> on the basis that these buses would be paying Toll. MSRDC always<lb/> admitted that PLUS had a right to collect Toll as is evident from its<lb/> letter dated 18 th July, 2011 to the Transport Commissioner, KDMT.<lb/> MSRDC also wrote to the Government of Maharashtra asking it to<lb/> ensure that KDMT and NMMT pay the Toll failing which MSRDC<lb/> itself would have to pay the balance Toll. Mr. Khambatta pointed<lb/> out that these letters can never be termed as letters exchanged<lb/> during conciliation proceedings as this was correspondence<lb/> addressed to third parties. This was a clear admission on the part of<lb/> MSRDC that KDMT and NMMT were refusing to pay the Toll. This<lb/> non-payment amounts to an expropriation of PLUS rights to collect<lb/> and retain the Toll under clause 6.1 of the agreement. Not only that,<lb/> it was also an obligation of PLUS under clause 9.1(xv) to levy and<lb/> collect Toll from users of the Project Highway as per the rates set<lb/> forth in the Toll Notification and in accordance with the Concession<lb/> Agreement and regulate the traffic on the Project Highway in<lb/> accordance with the applicable laws. Mr. Khambatta, therefore,<lb/> submitted that non-payment of the Toll by these Government buses<lb/> was thus clearly a Political Force Majeure event as it satisfied all the<lb/> ingredients required as per clause 29.1 of the Concession Agreement<lb/> and correctly spelt out by the Tribunal in paragraph 58 of the<lb/> impugned Award.<lb/> 51.<lb/> Mr. Khambatta then submitted that the Tribunal has<lb/> correctly held that the termination under clause 29.8 is valid also<lb/> on account of the ban / diversion of heavy and multi axle vehicles<lb/> and which also constituted a Political Force Majeure event. In this<lb/> regard, Mr. Khambatta brought to my attention, paragraph 63 of the<lb/> Interim Award regarding the ban on heavy vehicles by the Police<lb/> authorities. The Tribunal held that all the ingredients (as set out in<lb/> paragraph 58 of the Award), for a Political Force Majeure event are<lb/> made out. It was further held that the said statutory traffic<lb/> Notifications passed under section 15 of the Motor Vehicles Act,<lb/> 1988 amounted to a change in law in terms of Article 29.4(i). Mr.<lb/> Khambatta submitted that as per the PIM, the Concession<lb/> Agreement and the Toll Notification, heavy vehicles, including two<lb/> axle, three axle and multi axle vehicles were shown as a category of<lb/> vehicles which would use the Project Highway and pay Toll and were<lb/> not in the exempted category. As per clause 10.1(v) of the<lb/> Concession Agreement, it was the duty of MSRDC to ensure that no<lb/> barriers were put on the Highway. However, the Police authorities<lb/> issued a Notification dated 11 th May, 2009, whereby these multi<lb/> axle vehicles were completely banned and heavy vehicles were<lb/> partially banned from the said Project Road.<lb/> These Traffic<lb/> Regulation Notifications were issued by the Maharashtra Police<lb/> which is a limb of the Government of Maharashtra and, therefore, a<lb/> Governmental agency. These Government Notifications, therefore,<lb/> clearly amounted to a change in law. Mr. Khambatta submitted that<lb/> this does not stop here. In fact, MSRDC admits that PLUS has a<lb/> right to collect Toll from heavy and multi axle vehicles. This is<lb/> evident from the letter dated 2 nd August, 2010 written by MSRDC to<lb/> the Police authorities asking them to lift the ban on multi axle<lb/> vehicles. Even upon the termination of the Concession Agreement,<lb/> MSRDC began collecting Toll and itself wrote several letters to the<lb/> Chief Secretary, Home Department asking for lifting the traffic ban<lb/> on heavy vehicles. He, therefore, submitted that all this material<lb/> would show that the complete ban imposed on multi axle vehicles<lb/> and a partial ban on heavy vehicles from using the Project Road was<lb/> clearly a Political Force Majeure event which entitled PLUS to<lb/> terminate the Concession Agreement under clause 29.8 thereof.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            COURT:<lb/> 53.<lb/> I have heard </content>
 
            <figDesc>the learned counsel for the parties at length<lb/> on this issue and have also perused the papers and proceedings in<lb/> the above petition, including the impugned Award. In the impugned<lb/> Award, the Tribunal had framed the following issues/points for<lb/> determination:-<lb/>&quot;(a) the validity of the termination under Clause 29.8 on the<lb/> ground of various force majeure events, as alleged;<lb/> (b)<lb/> The validity of the termination under Clause 32.4 on the<lb/> ground of various acts/ omissions / delays in performance of<lb/> its obligations by MSRDC which had a material adverse<lb/> impact on the Claimant;<lb/> (c)<lb/> The relief to which the Claimant is entitled if either or both of<lb/> the termination notices are upheld as being valid.<lb/> (d)<lb/> The amount to which the Respondent MSRDC is entitled on<lb/> account of Counter Claims filed by it.&quot;<lb/> 54.<lb/> Issue (a) was whether the Concession Agreement was<lb/> validly terminated under Clause 29.8 on the ground of various Force<lb/> Majeure Events and issue (b) was whether the termination was<lb/> valid under Clause 32.4 on the ground of various acts/ omissions /<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>delays in performance of its obligations by MSRDC which had a<lb/> material adverse impact on PLUS. The Tribunal noted that although<lb/> the issues (a) and (b) have been framed separately, it would in fact<lb/> be sufficient if PLUS were in a position to justify the termination<lb/> either under clause 29.8 or 32.4. This is for the simple reason that<lb/> the Concession Agreement could be terminated only once.<lb/> Therefore, termination could be held to be valid either under clause<lb/> 29.8 (the Force Majeure events) or clause 32.4 (material default by<lb/> MSRDC), if the same are made good by PLUS. Further the Tribunal<lb/> held that even within each of these grounds there are several sub-<lb/>grounds, and it would be enough for PLUS to show that any one<lb/> particular Political Force Majeure event existed/occurred as a basis<lb/> for terminating the Concession Agreement, or any one particular<lb/> material default is committed by MSRDC for terminating the said<lb/> Agreement.<lb/> 55.<lb/> While discussing the facts of the matter, the Tribunal<lb/> noted that PLUS&apos; grievances were three-fold: (i) the delays in land<lb/> acquisition as well as in finalization of plans for the Railway Over<lb/> Bridge (for short &quot;ROB&quot;) at Katai which led to an overall delay in the<lb/> construction of the project. This resulted in an &apos;additional direct<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> cost&apos; being incurred by PLUS; (ii) that traffic police restricted the<lb/> entry of certain heavy vehicles on the Project Highway, thus<lb/> reducing the traffic flow, which in turn led to a reduction in Toll<lb/> received; and (iii) that the municipality buses (namely KDMT and<lb/> NMMT buses) refused to pay Toll that they ought to have paid and<lb/> which also led to a reduction in Toll received by PLUS. The Tribunal<lb/> records that these grievances unfolded at different points in time<lb/> during the execution of the project, and voluminous correspondence<lb/> has been exchanged by the parties and the IC on each of these<lb/> issues, much of which has been placed on record before the Tribunal.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>Immediately prior to this, in a communication dated 22 nd February,<lb/> 2008, MSRDC itself acknowledged that 95% of the work was<lb/> completed. It further noted that the remaining work was delayed on<lb/> account of land acquisition issues as well as the delay in approval of<lb/> the design of the Katai ROB, by the Railways. The Tribunal, after<lb/> examining the record, noted the correspondence exchanged<lb/> between the parties for completion of the construction due to delays<lb/> in land acquisition as well as the delayed approvals of the design of<lb/> the ROB at Katai.<lb/> In effect, PLUS sought extension of the<lb/> construction period up till 12 th January, 2010. Despite this request,<lb/> PLUS actually completed the work by 23 rd May, 2009 and claims to<lb/> have done so by making a significant capital commitment to bring in<lb/> extra resources. The Tribunal notes that from the correspondence<lb/> referred to, it is clear that (i) there were delays with land<lb/> acquisition as well as with the approval from the Railways with<lb/> regard to the ROB at Katai; (ii) that these delays were on account of<lb/> MSRDC (or, at any rate, not on account of PLUS), and were<lb/> acknowledged by both, the IC and MSRDC at the time; (iii) the<lb/> construction period was extended from time to time, and ultimately<lb/> extended by a period of 674 days up till 29 th December, 2009; (iv)<lb/> PLUS had requested a consequent extension in the concession<lb/> period and the IC had endorsed the request by making a<lb/> recommendation that the concession period be extended; (v) the<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> ultimate extension granted by MSRDC did not expressly state that<lb/> the concession period had also been extended, but noted that it<lb/> would be determined after taking into account various other factors.<lb/> 56.<lb/> Thereafter, the Tribunal also notes that on 11 th May,<lb/> 2009, i.e. a week before PLUS was to complete the actual<lb/> construction of the project, the Police Commissioner (Thane) issued<lb/> a Traffic Regulation Notification banning the entry of heavy<lb/> commercial vehicles in Kalyan city. Though PLUS does not appear<lb/> to have protested immediately, it wrote to MSRDC on 18 th<lb/> September, 2009 protesting the traffic restriction and cited clauses<lb/> 10.1(v) and (vii) of the Concession Agreement to contend that<lb/> MSRDC had an obligation to ensure that no barrier was erected to<lb/> the collection of Toll. It, therefore, requested MSRDC to take this up<lb/> with the police authorities so that an amicable resolution could be<lb/> found. Despite this protest, on 29 th December, 2009, another<lb/> Notification came to be issued by the Police Commissioner (Thane)<lb/> banning/restricting the entry of certain other categories of vehicles<lb/> on the Project Highway. On 25 th February, 2010, PLUS wrote to the<lb/> Police Department, with a copy marked to MSRDC, requesting that<lb/> the traffic restrictions be lifted and the same be re-diverted onto the<lb/> Project Highway. The Tribunal notes that there is extensive<lb/> correspondence exchanged between PLUS, MSRDC, the IC and also<lb/> the Police Department on the losses being suffered by PLUS on<lb/> account of the traffic restrictions and it, therefore, states that apart<lb/> from the &apos;additional direct cost&apos; claim, the traffic restrictions<lb/> leading to a loss in Toll collection, constituted an independent basis<lb/> for a claim by PLUS. Similar is the case with reference to non-<lb/>payment of Toll by the Municipal buses. The Tribunal notes that on<lb/> 23 rd January, 2010, PLUS wrote to MSRDC alerting them that<lb/> KDMT buses were using the Project Highway, but refusing to pay<lb/> Toll. As a result, PLUS had incurred losses for which it sought<lb/> compensation.<lb/> It also requested MSRDC to issue necessary<lb/> instructions to KDMC for their buses to pay the Toll. A week later,<lb/> on 30 th January, 2010, PLUS issued a similar letter to MSRDC about<lb/> non-payment of Toll by NMMT buses. The Tribunal notes that<lb/> despite these grievances being pointed out by PLUS, this stalemate<lb/> continued and these buses continued to use the Project Highway, but<lb/> did not pay the Toll. PLUS maintained that restraining/stopping<lb/> these buses would have led to a law and order situation, given the<lb/> voluminous number of trips made by such buses and the fact that<lb/> they were transporting ordinary citizens. Thus, the only option for<lb/> PLUS was to maintain a record/details of the trips done by such<lb/> buses on a daily basis, and compute and maintain the amount of the<lb/> forsaken Toll, which was informed to MSRDC at regular intervals.<lb/> The amount of loss naturally kept increasing as the period of such<lb/> non-payment of Toll was continuing. The Tribunal notes that there<lb/> is correspondence to suggest that MSRDC agreed with the position<lb/> that these buses ought to pay Toll, and has even stated as such to<lb/> the concerned Municipal Commissioner (Transport), on certain<lb/> occasions. However, MSRDC was unable to resolve the deadlock and<lb/> impress upon KDMT and NMMT to have their buses pay the<lb/> requisite Toll. The Tribunal notes that from November 2011 to early<lb/> 2013, the parties exchanged correspondence without the matter<lb/> progressing any further. During this period, PLUS was still able to<lb/> collect and retain Toll on account of the original Toll Notification,<lb/> which subsisted till 28 th April, 2013. However, according to the<lb/> Tribunal, it was quite clear that as the expiry of that Notification<lb/> drew near, PLUS was increasingly anxious about the finalization of<lb/> the settlement terms and the consequent extension in the Toll<lb/> Notification. On 4 th February, 2013, PLUS wrote to MSRDC again<lb/> pointing out that it retains the right to terminate the Agreement.<lb/> On 8 th February, 2013, MSRDC writes to PLUS dissuading it from<lb/> terminating and assuring it that the rights accrued to it under the<lb/> amicable settlement remain unaffected and the matter is<lb/> progressing.<lb/> Quite evidently, these words of comfort were<lb/> insufficient to assuage PLUS and with the matter having dragged on<lb/> for more than a year, PLUS finally issued two termination notices,<lb/> both dated 19 th March, 2013. One was issued under Clause 29.8 and<lb/> the other under Clause 32.4 of the Concession Agreement.<lb/> 57.<lb/> After examining both the termination notices as well as<lb/> the correspondence exchanged between the parties, the Tribunal in<lb/> paragraph 53 set out certain basic features that appear from the<lb/> facts and circumstances narrated in the impugned Award. They<lb/> were:-<lb/>(i)<lb/> Despite repeatedly pointing to the economic un-<lb/>viability of the project and holding out threats of<lb/> termination, it was clear that PLUS was in fact<lb/> anxious to carry on with the project. Perhaps it<lb/> hoped that the project would turn profitable if<lb/> MSRDC acceded to its demands, or perhaps it<lb/> looked upon this project as a launching pad for<lb/> further such projects in this country. Whatever be<lb/> the reason, PLUS did its very best to accommodate<lb/> so that the issues could somehow be resolved, until<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> the matters reached an absolute breaking point<lb/> when it was constrained to terminate the<lb/> Agreement;<lb/> (ii) MSRDC and the IC consistently acknowledged that<lb/> there was substance in the grievances being raised<lb/> by PLUS at different points in time under different<lb/> heads, and yet, even while acknowledging this,<lb/> MSRDC stopped short of committing itself to any<lb/> position, and resorted to the easier course of<lb/> referring matters to the Government of<lb/> Maharashtra; and<lb/> (iii) The Government of Maharashtra, for its part,<lb/> adopted a somewhat casual approach in simply<lb/> sitting idle even though various issues of pressing<lb/> importance to the project had been referred to it by<lb/> MSRDC. While MSRDC had referred the matters to<lb/> the Government of Maharashtra, the Government<lb/> of Maharashtra failed to take any decision at all.<lb/> 58.<lb/> It is in this background that the Tribunal framed the<lb/> four issues referred to earlier.<lb/> 59.<lb/> Turning to the termination on the ground of Political<lb/> Force Majeure (clause 29.8), the Tribunal discussed the same from<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> paragraphs 58 to 64 of the impugned Award. The Tribunal notes<lb/> that there are five key ingredients that must exist for there to be a<lb/> finding that a Force Majeure event exists. These ingredients are:-<lb/>(a) the existence of an event, namely, a non-political<lb/> event or an indirect political event or a political<lb/> event as defined in the Concession Agreement.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>(</head>

            <figDesc>ii) expropriation by any governmental agency of<lb/> any project assets or rights of the Concessionaire<lb/> (PLUS); or (iii) unjustified refusal to grant or renew<lb/> any consent or approval required by the<lb/> Concessionaire (PLUS);<lb/> (b) the event must frustrate the performance of<lb/> obligations, namely, those events must be such that<lb/> they prevent the party claiming the Force Majeure<lb/> Event from performing its obligations under the<lb/> Agreement;<lb/> (c) that the event was beyond the control of the party<lb/> claiming the Force Majeure and not arising on<lb/> account of its own fault;<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> (d) duty to mitigate, namely, the party claiming Force<lb/> Majeure has an obligation to attempt to overcome<lb/> the event by exercising due diligence and<lb/> reasonable efforts, skill and care, including the<lb/> expenditure of reasonable sums of money; and</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>61.<lb/> In this background, the Tribunal thereafter went on to<lb/> examine the Force Majeure Events. The first Force Majeure Event<lb/> alleged by PLUS was that the parties had reached a settlement on<lb/> account of exchange of letters dated 20 th October, 2011 and 4 th<lb/> November, 2011 and by virtue of such settlement, a Toll Notification<lb/> was to be issued for the extended concession period. The non-<lb/>issuance of such Toll Notification was claimed as a Political Force<lb/> Majeure Event. This Force Majeure Event was negated by the<lb/> Tribunal as can be seen from paragraph 60 of the impugned Award.<lb/> 62.<lb/> Thereafter, the second Force Majeure Event canvassed<lb/> by PLUS was the non-payment of Toll by the NMMT and KDMT<lb/> buses, which is alleged to be an expropriation of the rights of the<lb/> Concessionaire (PLUS), and therefore, a Political Force Majeure<lb/> Event. In this regard, the Tribunal held that the right to collect Toll<lb/> is an entitlement of PLUS under Clause 6.1 of the Concession<lb/> Agreement. The concerned Municipal undertakings are undeniably<lb/> Government agencies within the meaning of clause 29.4 (ii) of the<lb/> Concession Agreement. The refusal to pay Toll by the buses owned<lb/> by these undertakings is an expropriation of the rights of the<lb/> Concessionaire (PLUS), and specifically the right to collect and<lb/> retain Toll in accordance with the Toll Notification. The Tribunal,<lb/> therefore, found that this did constitute a Political Force Majeure<lb/> Event within the meaning of Clause 29.4. The Tribunal thereafter<lb/> went on to examine whether the other elements necessary for<lb/> constituting a Force Majeure Event are also made out. In paragraph<lb/> 62, the Tribunal examined the other elements. The Tribunal held<lb/> that MSRDC (in its Written Submissions: Part VI) has relied upon<lb/> the cross-examination transcript to contend that it is an admitted<lb/> position that PLUS was not prevented from performing its<lb/> obligations under the Concession Agreement. The Tribunal further<lb/> found that the reliance on an isolated statement in response to one<lb/> question put in cross-examination may not be conclusive on<lb/> whether, in fact, PLUS was prevented from performing its<lb/> obligations. Moreover, regard must be had to the terms of the<lb/> Concession Agreement (which specify the obligations of each party)<lb/> and also to the entirety of the documentary evidence on record, to<lb/> ascertain whether in fact PLUS was prevented in the performance of<lb/> its obligations. The Tribunal further held that the collection and<lb/> retention of Toll is not just an entitlement, but also an obligation of<lb/> PLUS in terms of clause 9.1(xv) of the Concession Agreement. The<lb/> performance of this obligation was directly interfered with by the<lb/> actions of NMMT and KDMT buses and, therefore, the Political<lb/> Event did prevent PLUS from performing its obligations. It further<lb/> held that this was entirely beyond the control of PLUS and certainly<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> not on account of any fault of PLUS. The Tribunal thereafter opined<lb/> that the position with respect to duty to mitigate is more finely<lb/> balanced. The Tribunal held that it is reasonable to contend, as<lb/> MSRDC has done, that the Toll Notification statutorily authorized<lb/> PLUS to collect Toll from all vehicles other than those specifically<lb/> exempted, and it was for PLUS to exercise legal remedies to enforce<lb/> its rights under the Toll Notification. At the same time, it must be<lb/> borne in mind that Municipal buses account for a large part of the<lb/> traffic on the Project Highway, and such buses make several trips in<lb/> a day, ferrying different passengers, some of whom may have no<lb/> other mode of transport. Preventing the passage of these vehicles<lb/> would, in the circumstances, have created a law and order situation<lb/> and PLUS cannot be faulted for not carrying these matters ahead.<lb/> PLUS has also pointed out that stopping the Municipal buses would<lb/> have jammed the entire Toll plaza, and led to PLUS being in breach<lb/> of its obligations under the Concession Agreement. The Tribunal<lb/> also held that it is not as if PLUS was idle or slept over its rights or<lb/> failed entirely to press its legitimate claims. The matter was taken<lb/> up with the concerned Municipal Authorities, and MSRDC was also<lb/> alerted as early as January 2010 that NMMT and KDMT buses were<lb/> not paying Toll, even though they were required to do so in terms of<lb/> the Notification. Further, this issue was raised repeatedly, and an<lb/> account was kept of the number of such vehicles passing the Toll<lb/> collection point on a daily basis. This data was made available to<lb/> MSRDC at regular intervals (as well as to the Municipal<lb/> Authorities), and MSRDC by and large appeared to have accepted<lb/> the claim of PLUS and even took up the matter with the concerned<lb/> Municipal Commissioners. The Tribunal, therefore, held that PLUS<lb/> made several efforts to prevail upon the concerned Municipal<lb/> undertakings to issue necessary directions for the Municipal buses<lb/> to pay the Toll. In these circumstances, the Tribunal was of the view<lb/> that PLUS had exercised necessary due diligence and precipitating<lb/> the matters any further could have had serious law and order<lb/> repercussions, as well as an impact on traffic regulation at the Toll<lb/> Plaza. The Tribunal, therefore, came to a finding that the steps<lb/> necessary in the circumstances to overcome the Force Majeure<lb/> Event were duly taken by PLUS. Finally, even the loss of revenue to<lb/> PLUS from non-payment of Toll by so many vehicles making so<lb/> many trips over so many months, clearly amounted to a material<lb/> adverse effect on the project. The Tribunal held that there is ample<lb/> correspondence to show that the failure to collect Toll contributed to<lb/> the cash flow issues faced by PLUS, which had an impact on loan<lb/> servicing as well as operational expenses. The Tribunal, therefore,<lb/> was of the view that there was a material adverse effect on the<lb/> project. Accordingly, the non-payment of Toll by the Municipal buses<lb/> was a Force Majeure event within the meaning of Clause 29.1 of the<lb/> Concession Agreement. Since the said event subsisted for more<lb/> than 180 days within a continuous period of 365 days (it<lb/> commenced on 22 nd August, 2009, from which date the Toll<lb/> collection commenced, and continued up till the termination date<lb/> and beyond), it did give rise to a right to terminate the Concession<lb/> Agreement under Clause 29.8. The Tribunal, therefore, held that<lb/> the termination notice was valid on this ground.<lb/> 63.<lb/> The third Force Majeure Event which was alleged by<lb/> PLUS was the traffic regulation banning the entry of heavy vehicles<lb/> during certain specified hours. It was the case of PLUS that this<lb/> amounted to a change in law, or alternatively expropriation of its<lb/> rights, and therefore, a Political Force Majeure Event occurred. In<lb/> response to this, MSRDC contended that the ban on heavy vehicles<lb/> pre-dated the Agreement, and PLUS was aware of this fact, or at any<lb/> rate, ought to have been aware. MSRDC relied on a Resolution of the<lb/> Municipal Corporation, which notes that &quot;heavy vehicles are allowed<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>to run on this road from 10 p.m. to 6 a.m. and it should not be<lb/> changed.&quot; The Tribunal found that this resolution was not a public<lb/> document and PLUS, therefore, cannot be expected to be aware of it.<lb/> Further, even if the said decision was communicated to MSRDC, it<lb/> was for MSRDC to refer to it in the Project Information<lb/> Memorandum (PIM).<lb/> The PIM, however, contained no such<lb/> reference and bids were invited on the basis that heavy commercial<lb/> vehicles would be part of the traffic flow which determines the<lb/> revenue base of PLUS. The Tribunal thereafter held that in any<lb/> event PLUS is correct to point out that (i) the restrictions that were<lb/> imposed in May 2009 went further and beyond the resolution to<lb/> impose a total ban on entry of certain categories of vehicles; and (ii)<lb/> the Notifications were statutory Notifications issued under the<lb/> Motor Vehicles Act, 1988 and it was only with the issuance of such<lb/> Notifications that a ban/restriction operationally came into effect.<lb/> The Tribunal noted that it is not even MSRDC&apos;s contention that prior<lb/> to this, there was any such Notification issued under the Motor<lb/> Vehicles Act, 1988. The Tribunal, therefore, was of the view that<lb/> this amounted to a change in law and in the alternative would, in<lb/> any event, amount to an expropriation of the rights of PLUS as the<lb/> project bid had been made on the basis of certain traffic projections.<lb/> The ban/restrictions that were imposed on various categories of<lb/> vehicles had a drastic effect on those projections, as it severely<lb/> curtailed the heavy vehicular traffic on the said road. Thus, the<lb/> Tribunal was of the view that there was a Political Force Majeure<lb/> Event. The Tribunal held that all other ingredients of the Force<lb/> Majeure Event were also made out. It noted that PLUS was<lb/> prevented from performing its obligations (collecting Toll) under the<lb/> agreement. It was also prevented for reasons beyond its control and<lb/> not on account of its own fault. PLUS did exercise the necessary due<lb/> diligence to overcome this event by taking up the issue with the<lb/> police authorities as well as with MSRDC and undoubtedly the event<lb/> had a material adverse effect on the project, as the amount of<lb/> uncollected Toll was allegedly in excess of Rs.60 Crores. Further,<lb/> the event subsisted for the requisite period as specified under Clause<lb/> 29.8 of the agreement, and therefore, PLUS was justified in<lb/> terminating the Agreement. The Tribunal, therefore, held that the<lb/> termination on this ground was valid. In conclusion, the Tribunal<lb/> held that as far as the termination on account of Force Majeure is<lb/> concerned, the validity of the said termination is upheld to the<lb/> extent it was occasioned by non-payment of Toll by Municipal buses<lb/> and the traffic restrictions on heavy vehicular traffic. The Tribunal<lb/> also noted that the termination on the ground of non-issuance of the<lb/> Toll Notification for the extended period pursuant to an alleged<lb/> settlement/ agreement between the parties, stood rejected.<lb/> 64.<lb/> Looking at the facts adverted to by the Tribunal (set out<lb/> above) and its findings in relation thereto, I find that the Tribunal<lb/> has carefully examined all the facts, including the correspondence<lb/> between the parties and thereafter come to its conclusion. I am in<lb/> full agreement with Mr. Khambatta that all these findings are really<lb/> findings of facts. Clause 6.1 of the Concession Agreement clearly<lb/> stipulates that the right to claim Toll is an entitlement of PLUS.<lb/> Refusal to pay Toll by KDMT and NMMT buses was held as<lb/> amounting to expropriation or taking away the rights of PLUS to<lb/> collect Toll from these buses in accordance with the Toll<lb/> Notification. It is not as if PLUS sat idle and did nothing. This issue<lb/> was specifically taken up by PLUS with KDMT &amp; NMMT, and MSRDC<lb/> was also alerted of the same. In fact, PLUS also kept an account of all<lb/> these buses passing through the Toll Plaza without paying Toll and<lb/> which was regularly submitted to MSRDC. It can therefore hardly<lb/> be contended that in such a scenario the same did not have a<lb/> material adverse effect on the project. Merely because the exact loss<lb/> wasn&apos;t quantified would make little difference. The fact that these<lb/> buses (and which were large in number) were to pay Toll and which<lb/> they refused to do, would clearly indicate that there was a material<lb/> adverse effect on the project. Further, these Government buses were<lb/> specifically shown in the PIM and the Concession Agreement as<lb/> category of vehicles which would pay Toll and were not listed as<lb/> exempted vehicles. In fact, by its letter dated 18 th July, 2011,<lb/> MSRDC informed the Transport Commissioner of KDMT that PLUS<lb/> had the right to collect Toll under the Concession Agreement.<lb/> MSRDC also wrote to the Government of Maharashtra asking it to<lb/> ensure that KDMT and NMMT buses pay the Toll, failing which<lb/> MSRDC itself would have to pay the balance Toll. This is a clear<lb/> admission on the part of MSRDC that KDMT and NMMT were<lb/> refusing to pay Toll. Even if I was to assume for the sake of argument<lb/> that certain correspondence between MSRDC and PLUS forming the<lb/> subject matter of the Arbitration are inadmissible (and which I have<lb/> rejected earlier), the letters written by MSRDC to the Transport<lb/> Commissioner of KDMT and to the Government of Maharashtra is<lb/> correspondence addressed to third parties, and therefore, can never<lb/> amount to correspondence entered into between MSRDC and PLUS<lb/> during conciliation proceedings.<lb/> 65.<lb/> Even the Notifications issued under the Motor Vehicles<lb/> Act, 1988 banning of heavy vehicles, MSRDC admits that PLUS has<lb/> a right to collect Toll from heavy and multi axle vehicles. This is<lb/> evident from the letter dated 2 nd August, 2010 written by MSRDC to<lb/> the Police authorities asking them to lift the ban on multi axle<lb/> vehicles. Even upon the termination of the Concession Agreement,<lb/> MSRDC began collecting Toll and itself wrote several letters to the<lb/> Chief Secretary, Home Department asking for lifting the traffic ban<lb/> on heavy vehicles. When one looks at the findings given by the<lb/> Tribunal, I find that the Tribunal has given appropriate and cogent<lb/> reasons for upholding the termination of the Concession Agreement<lb/> under Clause 29.8 thereof. The Tribunal has considered the<lb/> relevant documents and the evidence on record, the arguments<lb/> canvassed by the parties and thereafter come to its conclusion. Not<lb/> only do I find that the said conclusion is correct, but even otherwise<lb/> it is certainly a plausible conclusion. The Tribunal has considered<lb/> everything on record and thereafter held that the Concession<lb/> Agreement is validly terminated due to Force Majeure Events. I do<lb/> not find anything patently illegal or perverse in the said findings so<lb/> as to interfere with the same under Section 34 of the Act. I am<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>SR Pasha, Sr PS<lb/> Page 88 of 169<lb/> unable to agree with the submissions of Mr. Chagla that the findings<lb/> in the impugned Award on this issue are either contradictory or<lb/> ignores any vital evidence. The Tribunal has considered all the<lb/> evidence, including the so called admission made by the witness of<lb/> PLUS. What weightage is to be given to the evidence is left entirely<lb/> upto the Tribunal and this Court is not supposed to sit in appeal and<lb/> re-examine and re-appreciate the evidence. The Tribunal, after<lb/> noting the admission, held that one isolated statement cannot form<lb/> a basis of their finding. The entirety of the documents on record has<lb/> to be looked into, as well as the evidence, to ascertain whether in<lb/> fact PLUS was prevented in performance of its obligations. I do not<lb/> find that the approach of the Tribunal in this regard can be faulted.<lb/> As mentioned earlier, I find that the impugned Award on this issue<lb/> has given appropriate and cogent reasoning which requires no<lb/> interference. In these circumstances, in so far as the Tribunal holds<lb/> that the Concession Agreement was validly terminated under clause<lb/> 29.8 (due to Force Majeure Events) requires no interference by this<lb/> Court.<lb/> 66.<lb/> Apart from upholding the termination of the Concession<lb/> Agreement due to Force Majeure Events, the Tribunal also held that<lb/> the said Agreement was validly terminated under Clause 32.4 on<lb/> account of material defaults by MSRDC. The discussion and the<lb/> findings with reference to termination under Clause 32.4 can be<lb/> found from paragraphs 65 to 70 of the impugned Award. In<lb/> paragraph 65, the Tribunal held that the termination notice refers<lb/> to a letter dated 10 th May, 2010 and the letters issued earlier to it,<lb/> which are stated to be relied upon by PLUS. However, the letters do<lb/> not actually refer to six claims, but rather only to the claim for<lb/> &apos;additional direct cost&apos;. This claim was forwarded by letter dated<lb/> 24 th February, 2010 wherein PLUS claimed an amount of Rs.161<lb/> Crores as the escalated project cost on account of material default<lb/> by MSRDC. Subsequently, this claim was pursued by further letters<lb/> and finally by means of the letter dated 10 th May, 2010 PLUS<lb/> proposed conciliation. Thus, the offer for conciliation was in relation<lb/> to the claim of the &apos;additional direct cost&apos; and not the other claims.<lb/> The Tribunal noted that it is true that other claims had also been<lb/> raised by that time and those were by means of separate letters and<lb/> were separately pursued. It is only much later that the IC, by its<lb/> communication dated 2 nd August, 2011, clubbed various claims<lb/> under six heads and which I have adverted to earlier. The Tribunal<lb/> therefore, proceeded to examine whether any defaults by MSRDC<lb/> furnished a valid basis for terminating the Concession Agreement<lb/> under clause 32.4. The Tribunal noted that the principal claim with<lb/> respect to material default is the claim for &apos;additional direct cost&apos;.<lb/> This claim has been clubbed with the claim of project costs together<lb/> with escalated project costs. PLUS contended that this claim arises<lb/> due to default on the part of the MSRDC to complete the land<lb/> acquisition process in a timely manner and also on account of delays<lb/> in getting design approvals from the Railway Authorities in respect<lb/> of the Katai ROB. The discussion on this can be found in paragraph<lb/> 70 of the Award which reads thus:-</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>2013, the extension of the concession period and the Toll<lb/> Notification upto 10 th July, 2024 failing which the Concession<lb/> Agreement is to stand terminated on 28 th April, 2013. From the<lb/> aforesaid notice it is clear that time was granted to MSRDC to cure<lb/> any defect on its part from 19 th March, 2013 to 28 th April, 2013.<lb/> This is far less than the period of 90 days as stipulated in clause<lb/> 32.4.1. On a plain reading of the said notice, I find that the<lb/> submission of Mr. Chagla is well founded when he submits that the<lb/> findings given by the Tribunal that MSRDC had much more than 90<lb/> days to cure the breaches, is factually incorrect. I must mention that<lb/> the Tribunal whilst coming to the aforesaid finding opined that PLUS<lb/> had held out the prospect of termination long before 19 th March,<lb/> 2013 and refrained from issuing a formal notice at the specific<lb/> request of MSRDC. In this regard, the only letter referred to by the<lb/> Tribunal is a letter dated 4 th February, 2013 issued by PLUS to<lb/> MSRDC (paragraph 43 of the impugned Award). By the said letter,<lb/> PLUS informs MSRDC that in the spirit of amicable settlement, PLUS<lb/> desires to draw the attention of MSRDC to the Toll Notification<lb/> which is valid upto 28 th April, 2013 whereas their actual original<lb/> concession period runs upto 3 rd March, 2015. It therefore informs<lb/> MSRDC that despite the present Toll Notification expiring less than<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> SR Pasha, Sr PS<lb/> Page 100 of 169<lb/> 90 days from </content>
 
            <figDesc>the date of the said letter, PLUS&apos; right to serve a<lb/> termination notice under the Concession Agreement remains intact<lb/> and in full force and they reserve their right to exercise the right of<lb/> termination any time before 28 th April, 2013 and such notice, if and<lb/> when served upon MSRDC, shall be fully binding on MSRDC with<lb/> respect to its obligation to pay Termination Payment as certified by<lb/> the statutory auditors of PLUS. This letter is clearly not a<lb/> termination notice as contemplated under clause 32.4.1 of the<lb/> Concession Agreement. Be that as it may, even if I was to assume<lb/> that this letter is a notice as contemplated under clause 32.4.1, the<lb/> time period between 4 th February, 2013 till 28 th April, 2013 (the<lb/> date on which the Toll Notification came to an end), still does not<lb/> comply with the period of 90 days, as contemplated under the<lb/> aforesaid clause. I am in agreement with Mr. Chagla that<lb/> termination of a contract has serious consequences. Therefore,<lb/> termination under clause 32.4.1 requires strict compliance. Failure<lb/> to give notice of 90 days would clearly render the termination under<lb/> clause 32.4.1 of the Concession Agreement illegal and invalid. I<lb/> therefore am of the view that the finding of the Tribunal in so far as<lb/> it upholds the termination of the Concession Agreement under<lb/> clause 32.4 suffers from a patent illegality as its findings run in the<lb/> teeth of the plain language of clause 32.4.1 and hence cannot be<lb/> sustained.<lb/> 73.<lb/> As far as the argument of Mr. Chagla that the<lb/> actions/omissions of MSRDC did not have a material adverse effect<lb/> on the project, I am unable to agree with the same as that is a<lb/> question of fact which is examined by the Tribunal. The Tribunal<lb/> finds that the record is replete with correspondence from PLUS<lb/> pointing out how this delay is constraining its cash flow position,<lb/> and jeopardizing operations. This would clearly amount to a<lb/> material adverse effect on the project. However, as mentioned<lb/> earlier, termination under Clause 32.4.1 cannot be held to be valid<lb/> in view of the fact that a 90 day notice was not given by PLUS to<lb/> MSRDC as contemplated in clause 32.4.1 of the Concession<lb/> Agreement.<lb/> 74.<lb/> Despite having held that the termination of the<lb/> Concession Agreement under clause 32.4 cannot be held to be valid,<lb/> I find that it makes little difference in the present matter. As noted<lb/> earlier, the Concession Agreement could be terminated under<lb/> Clauses 29.8 as well as 32.4. Even if one of them is held to be valid<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> then the Concession </content>
 
            <figDesc>Agreement would stand validly terminated.<lb/> Considering that I have held that the findings of the Tribunal<lb/> regarding termination of the Concession Agreement under Clause<lb/> 29.8 does not require any interference, it makes little difference<lb/> whether termination under Clause 32.4 is held valid or otherwise.<lb/> This is more so when one takes into consideration that the<lb/> Termination Payment formula under clause 29.9(c) and 32.4.2 is<lb/> exactly the same.<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> III(A) -AWARD IS CONTRARY TO THE PROCEDURE<lb/> AGREED UPON BETWEEN THE PARTIES AS PER SECTION<lb/> 19(2) OF THE ACT;<lb/> III(B) -LEGAL MISCONDUCT ON THE PART OF THE<lb/> TRIBUNAL; AND<lb/> III(C) -FAILURE OF THE ARBITRAL TRIBUNAL TO<lb/> CONSIDER/DECIDE THE COUNTER CLAIM FILED BY<lb/> MSRDC:<lb/> SUBMISSIONS OF MSRDC:<lb/> 75.<lb/> As mentioned earlier</content>

            <figDesc>, I find that the aforesaid three<lb/> grounds of challenge, namely: (i) the Award is contrary to the<lb/> procedure agreed to between the parties; (ii) the failure of the<lb/> Tribunal to consider / decide the Counter Claim of MSRDC; and (iii)<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>legal misconduct on the part of the Tribunal; are all inter-twined<lb/> together and hence these three grounds are being decided together.<lb/> 76.<lb/> Firstly, Mr. Chagla submitted that the Tribunal, with the<lb/> consent of the parties, laid down the entire schedule for the arbitral<lb/> proceedings as recorded in the minutes of the meeting dated 20 th<lb/> February, 2016. In the said minutes, the Tribunal passed a detailed<lb/> procedural order wherein the Tribunal made it clear that the dates<lb/> fixed for hearing, i.e. for the evidence and final arguments were<lb/> inflexible. Mr. Chagla submitted that the Tribunal reiterated upon<lb/> the inflexibility of the aforesaid dates in its further procedural<lb/> orders dated 4 th May, 2016 and 12 th May, 2016. He submitted that<lb/> on a conjoint reading of the procedural orders passed by the<lb/> Tribunal from time to time, namely, procedural orders dated 20 th<lb/> February, 2016, 4 th May, 2016, 12 th May, 2016 and 17 th October,<lb/> 2016, read along with the transcripts dated 17 th January, 2017,<lb/> 20 th January, 2017, 3 rd February, 2017 and 4 th February, 2017,<lb/> establish beyond a doubt that the dates fixed by the Tribunal were<lb/> not only inflexible, but the proceedings were to be conducted as one<lb/> consolidated proceeding and the Tribunal was to pass one Award.<lb/> He submitted that the Tribunal&apos;s directions to make payment of the<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> SR Pasha, Sr PS<lb/> Page 104 of 169</content>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>claims. The Arbitral Tribunal was, therefore, bound to decide all<lb/> issues as set out in paragraph 54 of the Award and not break up the<lb/> hearing as was sought to be done by the impugned Award. Mr.<lb/> Chagla submitted that what was even more shocking was that after<lb/> considering the complete evidence and the submission of the parties,<lb/> the Tribunal rejected certain specific claims of PLUS and expressed<lb/> its inability to decide the other claims on the available evidence. He<lb/> submitted that the parties are required in law to produce all<lb/> evidence in support of their case which, in the present case, PLUS<lb/> claimed it had done and having regard to the findings of the Arbitral<lb/> Tribunal, the claims of PLUS ought to have been dismissed. He<lb/> submitted that the findings of the Arbitral Tribunal amount to a final<lb/> adjudication and the nomenclature &quot;Interim Award&quot; is misplaced<lb/> and unwarranted and has been done only to permit PLUS to file<lb/> further pleadings and lead further evidence. Mr. Chagla submitted<lb/> that, in effect, the Tribunal ex-facie seeks to review its own final<lb/> adjudication, which is impermissible in law.<lb/> 78.<lb/> Mr. Chagla thereafter brought to my attention the<lb/> findings of the Arbitral Tribunal in respect of various claims made<lb/> by PLUS. The first claim made by PLUS was for Termination<lb/> Payment of Rs.495 crores. Mr. Chagla submitted that this claim was<lb/> purportedly made under clause 29.9(c) and clause 32.4.2 of the<lb/> Concession Agreement. He submitted that it was the express case of<lb/> PLUS that Termination Payment became mechanically /<lb/> automatically due and payable on the expiry of thirty days from the<lb/> date of the Statutory Auditor&apos;s certificate certifying the<lb/> &apos;Termination Payment&apos; being submitted to MSRDC. It was also the<lb/> contention of PLUS that once the same became due and payable,<lb/> there was no mechanism in the Concession Agreement to reverse<lb/> the same and no further evidence, apart from the Statutory<lb/> Auditor&apos;s certificate, was required to be led by it to prove its claim.<lb/> MSRDC, on the other hand, contended that as per the formula for<lb/> the calculation of Termination Payment, the same could not be<lb/> applied mechanically and that damages could not be awarded unless<lb/> PLUS proved that it had suffered actual losses / damages and the<lb/> quantum thereof. Mr. Chagla submitted that in this connection, the<lb/> Arbitral Tribunal in paragraph 72 of the Award has, inter alia, held<lb/> as under:<lb/> &quot;Prima facie the Tribunal would need to be satisfied about the<lb/> element of proportionality in the working of the Termination<lb/> Payment clause. We notice that the MSRDC has strongly contested<lb/> the Termination Payment also on the ground of each individual<lb/> head that is to be calculated under the formula, and it would be<lb/> beneficial to the Tribunal to invite further hearing and<lb/> on this issue.&quot;<lb/> 79.<lb/> Mr. Chagla submitted that if the Tribunal required any<lb/> further hearings and submissions, it should have fixed such further<lb/> hearings and heard the submissions on the issue and not defer the<lb/> same to a further arbitral hearing after passing the impugned<lb/> Award. He submitted that, in effect, when one reads the aforesaid<lb/> paragraph, the claims of PLUS, on the available evidence and<lb/> submissions, stood rejected.<lb/> 80.<lb/> Mr. Chagla submitted that similar is the case for the<lb/> claim of Rs.469 crores and which is in the alternative to the claim<lb/> for Termination Payment. He submitted that the alternative claim<lb/> of Rs.469 crores was allegedly based on amounts invested by the<lb/> shareholders of PLUS. He submitted that the Tribunal held that this<lb/> figure was virtually a proxy claim for Termination Payment. In<lb/> view of this finding, the Tribunal ought to have rejected this claim.<lb/> Instead, the Tribunal held that since the Tribunal is inclined to defer<lb/> its decision on the issue of Termination Payment, the decision on<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>this alternative claim also stood deferred. In this regard, Mr. Chagla<lb/> brought to my attention, paragraph 73 of the Award.<lb/> 81.<lb/> Mr. Chagla then brought to my attention that over and<lb/> above the aforesaid two claims, a claim of Rs.112 crores was also<lb/> made for reimbursement of &apos;additional direct cost&apos;, the loss of Toll<lb/> revenue and restoration charges.<lb/> In the arbitration, PLUS<lb/> proceeded on the express basis that these amounts were admitted<lb/> by MSRDC in the correspondence exchanged in the course of<lb/> settlement/conciliation. However, the Tribunal conclusively held<lb/> that these cannot be said to constitute admissions of quantum of<lb/> liability as placing weight on the quantum figures exchanged<lb/> between the parties while working out a compromise would not be<lb/> fair as they were made during the course of settlement. In this<lb/> regard, Mr. Chagla brought to my attention the finding of the<lb/> Tribunal in paragraph 77 of the Award. He submitted that the<lb/> Tribunal further held that the same would not be a sound basis to<lb/> arrive at any conclusion on the quantum of loss. It was the<lb/> submission of Mr. Chagla that reading paragraphs 77, 79 and 86 of<lb/> the Award clearly constituted a rejection of PLUS&apos; claims.<lb/> 82.<lb/> Mr. Chagla then submitted that the finding of the<lb/> Arbitral Tribunal in paragraph 86 of the Award, namely, &quot;The<lb/> Tribunal cannot arrive at a quantum determination based on the<lb/> existing record and submissions&quot; applied to all claims made by PLUS<lb/> and is final and binding. The said finding has not been challenged by<lb/> PLUS and has, therefore, attained finality and operates as res<lb/> judicata and/or issue estoppel between the parties. Mr. Chagla<lb/> submitted that looking at the way the matter progressed before the<lb/> Arbitral Tribunal (and which is clear from the different Procedural<lb/> Orders as well as the transcripts referred to above), what emerges is<lb/> that (i) there was to be one consolidated hearing determining the<lb/> claims of PLUS as well as the Counter Claim filed by MSRDC; (ii) the<lb/> dates fixed by the Tribunal were to be strictly adhered to and were<lb/> inflexible; (iii) the evidence of both parties was complete; (iv)<lb/> arguments on all the issues were addressed before the Tribunal and<lb/> even the written submissions filed by both parties covered the claim<lb/> and the Counter Claim on all issues; (v) the hearing was finally<lb/> concluded on 4 th February, 2017 and the matter was stood over only<lb/> for pronouncement of the Award. He submitted that from the record<lb/> it was clear that no further hearing was contemplated except a short<lb/> focused hearing, if required by the Tribunal and that too after they<lb/> perused the written submissions filed by the parties. He submitted<lb/> that no further procedural order was passed after 4 th February,<lb/> 2017 and no further hearing was held before the passing of the<lb/> Interim Award, either for a clarification or otherwise. He submitted<lb/> that neither the parties nor the Tribunal ever contemplated the<lb/> passing of an Interim Award and deferring the hearing on the<lb/> quantum at a later date. He submitted that, in fact, the parties had<lb/> led their entire evidence before the Arbitral Tribunal and the<lb/> Tribunal, therefore, could not have given the directions it did in<lb/> paragraphs 77, 79, 84 and 85 of the impugned Award. Mr. Chagla<lb/> submitted that in effect, once having come to the conclusion that the<lb/> evidence led by PLUS was inadequate to decide on the quantum of<lb/> the claims, it should have rejected the claims of PLUS for want of<lb/> evidence. Instead, it has effectively allowed PLUS to improve its<lb/> case by leading further evidence, if necessary. Mr. Chagla submitted<lb/> that this was wholly impermissible in law, especially considering<lb/> that the Tribunal itself had made it clear that there would be only<lb/> one Award for the entire proceedings and both parties had led their<lb/> respective evidence in its entirety to prove their respective claims.<lb/> In these circumstances, there was no question of allowing either<lb/> party to lead further evidence to prove their claims. If the evidence<lb/> was inadequate, the only option available to the Tribunal was to<lb/> reject the claims. He submitted that adoption of such a procedure by<lb/> the Tribunal not only vitiates the Award on the ground of<lb/> perversity, but also suffers from a patent illegality, and clearly<lb/> amounts to legal misconduct on the part of the Arbitral Tribunal.<lb/> Mr. Chagla submitted that the record would clearly establish that<lb/> the counsel for MSRDC asked for further time for cross-examination<lb/> and for presentation of its arguments which was rejected by the<lb/> Tribunal. However, the Tribunal nevertheless granted liberty to<lb/> PLUS to fill up any lacuna in its pleadings and evidence by making<lb/> the observations as mentioned in paragraphs 77, 79 and 85 of the<lb/> Award. This clearly amounted to legal misconduct on the part of the<lb/> Tribunal and which indicated a definite bias in favour of PLUS and<lb/> against MSRDC. To put it in a nutshell, Mr. Chagla submitted that<lb/> the Tribunal had not treated the parties equally and had acted in<lb/> violation of section 18 of the Act and would, therefore, clearly<lb/> amount to legal misconduct on the part of the Tribunal.<lb/> 83.<lb/> Lastly, Mr. Chagla submitted that the transcripts clearly<lb/> show that the procedure was agreed and the parties also always<lb/> understood that there would be one consolidated Award and one<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>consolidated proceeding, including a decision on the Counter Claim<lb/> filed by MSRDC. Though MSRDC made a Counter Claim of around<lb/> Rs.93 crores under twelve different heads, and despite the Tribunal<lb/> framing an issue as to what would be the amount to which MSRDC<lb/> would be entitled to on account of its Counter Claim, the finding of<lb/> the Arbitral Tribunal in paragraph 85 of the Award that sufficient<lb/> time was not devoted to the Counter Claim is patently illegal and<lb/> perverse considering that pursuant to the directions passed by the<lb/> Tribunal, both, the claim and Counter Claim were heard. In fact, the<lb/> parties filed their detailed written submissions in support of and in<lb/> reply to the Counter Claim. Despite this, the fact that the Counter<lb/> Claim was not adjudicated upon by the Arbitral Tribunal vitiates the<lb/> Award. In support of this submission, Mr. Chagla relied upon the<lb/> following:<lb/> a.<lb/> An Award should be final and the arbitrator cannot, in<lb/> his Award, reserve to himself the power of performing in<lb/> future, any act of a judicial nature in respect of the<lb/> matters submitted. [Russel on the Law of Arbitration<lb/> 24 th Edition, para (b)]</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>[</head>
Halsbury&apos;s Law of England 5 th Edition, volume 2,<lb/> para 1277]<lb/> c.<lb/> Vijay Kari &amp; Ors. v. Prysmian Cavi E Sistemi SRL &amp;<lb/> Ors. [2020 SCC OnLine SC 177]; para 86.<lb/> d.<lb/> K.V. George v. Secy. To Govt., Water and Power<lb/> Deptt., [(1989) 4 SCC 595]; para 12.<lb/> 84.<lb/> In conclusion, </content>
 
            <figDesc>Mr. Chagla, therefore, submitted that the<lb/> entire Award is vitiated as the same was in violation of the agreed<lb/> procedure as contemplated under section 19, legal misconduct on<lb/> the part of the Tribunal as well as on the ground that it failed to<lb/> consider the Counter Claim filed by MSRDC. Consequently, he<lb/> submitted that the arbitration Petition be allowed and the impugned<lb/> Award be set aside.<lb/> SUBMISSIONS OF PLUS:<lb/> 85.<lb/> On the other hand, Mr. Khambatta, the learned senior<lb/> counsel appearing on behalf of PLUS submitted that the entire<lb/> decision to bifurcate the arbitral proceedings into two phases, first<lb/> to make an Interim Award and thereafter defer the hearing to<lb/> decide on the quantum of the claims was neither contrary to the<lb/> agreed procedure and nor was it patently illegal or against the<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>fundamental policy of Indian law. He submitted that the Tribunal is<lb/> empowered to devise its own procedure. In this regard, he brought<lb/> to my attention, sections 19(2) and 19(3) of the Act which, inter<lb/> alia, stipulate that subject to Part I of the Act, the parties are free to<lb/> agree on the procedure to be followed by the Arbitral Tribunal in<lb/> conducting the proceedings and failing any such agreement between<lb/> the parties, the Arbitral Tribunal may conduct the proceedings in<lb/> the manner it considers appropriate. Mr. Khambatta submitted that<lb/> section 19(3) of the Act clearly empowers the Tribunal to devise its<lb/> own procedure, unless there is an agreement between the parties to<lb/> the contrary. It was his submission that in the present case, there<lb/> was no agreement regarding the procedure to be followed by the<lb/> Tribunal and, therefore, the Tribunal devised its own procedure<lb/> under section 19(3). He submitted that in its procedural order<lb/> dated 20 th February, 2016, the Tribunal gave directions in respect of<lb/> the procedure it proposed to follow. This was after discussion with<lb/> the parties who agreed to the practice and procedure suggested by<lb/> the Tribunal. Mr. Khambatta submitted that these directions were<lb/> not exhaustive of the procedure and neither did they restrict the<lb/> Tribunal to pass a single unified Award. He submitted that under<lb/> section 19(3) of the Act, the Arbitrators have procedural autonomy,<lb/> unless the same is restricted or modified by the parties by<lb/> agreement. He submitted that in the facts of the present case, there<lb/> is no restriction placed by the parties on the Tribunal&apos;s power to<lb/> bifurcate the proceedings and to pass two Awards. Mr. Khambatta<lb/> strongly relied upon paragraph 15 of the procedural order dated<lb/> 20 th February, 2016 to contend that the Tribunal expressly<lb/> reserved the discretion to itself to amend or modify the procedure<lb/> pursuant to such further directions or procedural orders as the<lb/> Tribunal may, from time to time, consider necessary. He submitted</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            86.<lb/> Mr. Khambatta </content>
 
            <figDesc>then submitted that it is not uncommon<lb/> in both International and domestic arbitrations for a Tribunal to<lb/> pass an Interim or Partial Award, bifurcating the proceedings.<lb/> Under section 2(c) of the Act, an Arbitral Award includes an Interim<lb/> Award. Section 31(6) of the Act provides for passing an Interim<lb/> Award. The Interim Award is a final Award in relation to issues<lb/> which are finally decided therein. An Interim Award finally decides<lb/> an issue without necessarily disposing off all the claims. He<lb/> submitted that the term &quot;Interim Award&quot; is often used<lb/> synonymously with the term &quot;Partial Award&quot;. In the present case,<lb/> Mr. Khambatta pointed out that by way of an Interim Award, issues<lb/> (a) and (b) [framed by the Tribunal in paragraph 54 of the Award]<lb/> regarding the validity of the termination notices were finally<lb/> decided by the Tribunal and issues (c) and (d) relating to quantum<lb/> of the claims [of PLUS] and the Counter Claims [of MSRDC] were<lb/> deferred to the second phase. He submitted that there was<lb/> absolutely nothing wrong in the Tribunal adopting this procedure,<lb/> especially considering that the Tribunal was empowered to do so<lb/> under section 19(3) of the Act. He submitted that this has also been<lb/> held to be valid by the Supreme Court in the case of McDermott<lb/> International Inc. vs. Burn Standard Company Ltd. &amp; Ors.,<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> SR Pasha, Sr PS<lb/> Page 117 of 169<lb/> [(2006) 11 SCC </content>
 
            <figDesc>181]. Mr. Khambatta submitted that even under<lb/> section 27 of the Arbitration Act, 1940 [corresponding to section<lb/> 31(6) of the Act], the Arbitral Tribunal had the power to make an<lb/> Interim Award, deciding the question of liability first and permitting<lb/> the leading of evidence thereafter on the question of damages. In<lb/> this regard, Mr. Khambatta relied upon a decision of a Division<lb/> Bench of this Court in the case of Manganese Ore (India) Ltd. &amp;<lb/> Ors. Vs. Ram Bahadur Thakur Limited [2006 SCC Online Bom.<lb/> 507]. Mr. Khambatta submitted that even the second edition of<lb/> Gary B. Born, International Commercial Edition recognises the<lb/> utility and benefits of bifurcating the proceedings and the passing of<lb/> Interim or Partial Awards. Only clear and unambiguous language<lb/> should be permitted to produce the unusual and inefficient result of<lb/> denying the arbitrators the authority to make Partial Awards.<lb/> Allowing the arbitrator to pass Partial Awards enables the Tribunal<lb/> and the parties to focus on and resolve issues sequentially, rather<lb/> than in a single decision. This sometimes has very significant<lb/> advantages in terms of efficiency and speed. A Tribunal&apos;s decision<lb/> whether or not to bifurcate proceedings and to resolve certain issues<lb/> before others usually turns on minute assessments of efficiency that<lb/> are the domain of the Arbitral Tribunal, was the submission.<lb/> 87.<lb/> Mr. Khambatta then submitted that PLUS has placed all<lb/> material / proof in support of its claims before the Tribunal including<lb/> the one for Termination Payment. What the Tribunal has done is<lb/> that it has only deferred the quantum of those claims and not<lb/> rejected them as sought to be contended by Mr. Chagla. He<lb/> submitted that Mr. Chagla&apos;s reliance on a single sentence of<lb/> paragraph 86 of the impugned Award is completely misplaced and<lb/> out of context. Mr. Khambatta submitted that the Concession<lb/> Agreement provided for Termination Payment in terms of clause<lb/> 29.9(c) and 32.4.2 thereof and which are identical in nature. He<lb/> submitted that such a clause is inserted to encourage Public Private<lb/> Partnership. The concept of a Public Private Partnership (for short<lb/> &quot;PPP&quot;) Project is introduced to help in developing public<lb/> infrastructure through private investment which otherwise would<lb/> have to be funded by the Government. In PPP Projects, the concept<lb/> of Termination Payment has been introduced by which, in the event<lb/> of termination of the contract, regardless of who has committed the<lb/> default, Termination Payment has to be paid by the Government or<lb/> the PSU in all cases of termination. This concept helps in attracting<lb/> private entities and provides adequate security to the lenders as it is<lb/> not possible to secure them through collateral assets as the assets<lb/> belong to the public. He submitted that Termination Payment is not<lb/> the same as damages or even liquidated damages. When the<lb/> Concession Agreement is terminated for default by either party, the<lb/> Government takes over the asset and the amount paid for such<lb/> taking over of the asset is termed as &apos;Termination Payment&apos;.<lb/> Termination payment represents only a return on equity and<lb/> repayment of debt as per the pre-agreed formula. On the other hand,<lb/> damages or liquidated damages can never be claimed by a defaulting<lb/> party whereas in case of Termination Payment in a PPP contract,<lb/> even on the default of the Concessionaire, the Concessionaire would<lb/> be entitled to Termination Payment.<lb/> 88.<lb/> Mr. Khambatta submitted that all that the Tribunal has<lb/> done is deferred the first claim for Termination Payment<lb/> (Rs.4,95,80,21,040/-along with interest) to consider the issue of<lb/> proportionality and which was actually done purely for the benefit<lb/> of MSRDC.<lb/> He submitted that all documents required for<lb/> quantification of Termination Payment were duly filed and proved<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>by PLUS. The quantum of Termination Payment has to be done by<lb/> applying the figures of debt, equity and subordinate debt to the<lb/> formula as provided in clause 29.9(c) and 32.4.2 of the Concession<lb/> Agreement and which are identical.<lb/> He submitted that the<lb/> Statutory Auditor&apos;s certificate, which provided the amount of<lb/> Termination Payment payable, was never challenged by MSRDC.<lb/> Under clause 28.1, the accounts of PLUS audited and certified by its<lb/> Statutory Auditors would form the basis of various payments by<lb/> either party under the Concession Agreement. MSRDC also chose<lb/> not to appoint another firm of Chartered Accounts to audit and<lb/> verify the Auditor&apos;s certificate which MSRDC was entitled to do as<lb/> per clause 28.4. Reliance upon the Auditor&apos;s certificate by PLUS at<lb/> paragraph 6.91 of the Statement of Claim was clearly met with<lb/> merely a bald denial at paragraph 7.54 of the Statement of Defence.<lb/> Hence, Mr. Khambatta submitted that as per clause 32.6 of the<lb/> Concession Agreement, MSRDC was required to pay to PLUS the<lb/> Termination Payment within thirty days of the demand being made<lb/> by PLUS accompanied by such Statutory Auditor&apos;s certificate. Mr.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>after the termination of the Concession Agreement authorised<lb/> MSRDC to collect the Toll and directed the amount so collected to be<lb/> kept in an Escrow Account so that the same could be utilised to<lb/> settle the claims of PLUS.<lb/> 89.<lb/> Mr. Khambatta submitted that in paragraph 11 of the<lb/> Interim Award, the Tribunal has observed that the point at which<lb/> termination might take place did not have any bearing on the<lb/> computation of the Termination Payment.<lb/> Nevertheless, in<lb/> paragraph 72, the Tribunal stated that it needed to be satisfied<lb/> about the proportionality in the working of the Termination<lb/> Payment clause as MSRDC had contested the said payment also<lb/> under each individual head that was to be calculated under the<lb/> formula and for this reason, the Tribunal wanted to have a further<lb/> hearing and submissions. From all this material, Mr. Khambatta<lb/> submitted that adopting proportionality as a factor in addition to the<lb/> formula [as laid down in clauses 29.9(c) and 32.4.2], worked to<lb/> MSRDC&apos;s advantage. Mr. Khambatta submitted that this was, in<lb/> fact, done for the benefit and, in fact, benefitted MSRDC and,<lb/> therefore, it does not lie in their mouth to contend that the Tribunal<lb/> could not have done so. This is for the simple reason that otherwise<lb/> PLUS would have been entitled to Termination Payment as per the<lb/> formula set out in clauses 29.9(c) and 32.4.2 and which were<lb/> identical in nature. The deferment to consider the proportionality<lb/> was really for the benefit of MSRDC and not to the benefit of PLUS.<lb/> 90.<lb/> Mr. Khambatta thereafter submitted that even the<lb/> deferment of quantum of the second claim of PLUS towards damages<lb/> on account of breaches committed by MSRDC (for Rs.112 crores)<lb/> operates to the benefit of MSRDC and not to the benefit of PLUS. He<lb/> submitted that this claim arose in terms of clause 32.8 of the<lb/> Concession Agreement under the head &quot;Other Claims&quot;. The loss<lb/> suffered by PLUS was on account of breaches by MSRDC prior to the<lb/> termination date. The loss had, therefore, accrued much before the<lb/> termination and the amount would have merely compensated PLUS<lb/> for the said loss. Mr. Khambatta submitted that PLUS had filed and<lb/> proved documents in support of its claim by primarily relying on<lb/> admissions by MSRDC on both, liability and quantum contained in<lb/> MSRDC&apos;s various documents, including the letters dated 20 th<lb/> October, 2011, 18 th July, 2011, 4 th March, 2008, 24 th / 25 th June,<lb/> 2009, 2 nd May, 2013, 2 nd August, 2010 and MSRDC&apos;s Director&apos;s<lb/> Report for the year 2011.<lb/> MSRDC had claimed that these<lb/> documents were part of the conciliation proceedings and, therefore,<lb/> inadmissible, which contention was rejected by the Tribunal. The<lb/> Tribunal did not determine the quantum based on the figures quoted<lb/> during the settlement discussions holding it would be unfair on<lb/> MSRDC to do so. The Tribunal held that despite the fact that the<lb/> documents were admissible, the Tribunal felt that it is still required<lb/> to determine the weight that can be attached to these documents as<lb/> evidence of an admitted quantum of loss. The Tribunal was of the<lb/> view that it would be unfair on MSRDC to determine the issue of<lb/> quantum with reference to the figures quoted during settlement<lb/> discussions and in these circumstances, it would not be fair to place<lb/> much weight on the quantum figures exchanged by the parties while<lb/> working out the settlement. The Tribunal held that these cannot be<lb/> said to constitute admissions of quantum of liability. Mr. Khambatta<lb/> submitted that despite the fact that the amounts claimed under the<lb/> head &apos;Other Claims&apos; were admitted by MSRDC in various documents,<lb/> the Tribunal nevertheless held as follows:</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>several volumes in respect of the Counter Claims filed by MSRDC.<lb/> However, during the hearings, sufficient attention was not devoted<lb/> to the Counter Claims as the parties concentrated mainly on the<lb/> claims made by PLUS and MSRDC&apos;s defence thereto. It was,<lb/> therefore, decided by the Tribunal that it would not be fair to decide<lb/> the rights and liabilities of the parties with respect to the Counter<lb/> Claims without affording a fair opportunity to the parties to present<lb/> their case qua each Counter Claim. It is in this light that the<lb/> Tribunal, therefore, deferred the decision on the Counter Claim also<lb/> to the second phase. Mr. Khambatta submitted that the Tribunal<lb/> has thus given an opportunity to MSRDC to make good its case. It is<lb/> in this context the one sentence relied upon by Mr. Chagla in<lb/> paragraph 86 of the Interim Award has to be read and understood.<lb/> Mr. Khambatta submitted that the Tribunal in paragraph 86, is not<lb/> referring to insufficiency of evidence led by PLUS. In any event,<lb/> whether or not the evidence was insufficient to award payment /<lb/> damages is a matter to be dealt with while examining the final<lb/> Award. Moreover, paragraph 87 of the Interim Award makes it<lb/> clear that this observation is only prima facie in nature as the<lb/> determinative findings in the Interim Award are only in respect of<lb/> liability. He, therefore, submitted that all this clearly goes to show<lb/> that there is absolutely no merit in the contention of Mr. Chagla that<lb/> the Tribunal could not have bifurcated the proceedings which<lb/> vitiates the Award. If this be the case, Mr. Khambatta submitted<lb/> that there is no legal misconduct on the part of the Arbitral<lb/> Tribunal. Consequently, he submitted that there was no merit in the<lb/> aforesaid objection to the Interim Award and the same ought to be<lb/> rejected. He therefore submitted that the above Petition has no<lb/> merit and the same ought to be dismissed with costs.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <head>FINDING </head>
 OF THE COURT:<lb/> 93.<lb/> I have heard </content>
 
            <figDesc>the learned counsel for the parties at great<lb/> length on this issue. To understand the present controversy, it<lb/> would be necessary to understand how the arbitration proceedings<lb/> progressed before the Arbitral Tribunal. On 20 th February, 2016,<lb/> the Arbitral Tribunal passed a detailed procedural order giving<lb/> various directions. A time-frame was set out by which the Statement<lb/> of Claim as well as the Statement of Defence and Counter Claim were<lb/> to be filed, so also the Statement of Defence of PLUS to MSRDC&apos;s<lb/> Counter Claim. Directions were also given to MSRDC and PLUS to<lb/> submit their affidavit of denial / dispute in respect of any document<lb/> filed by each other and/or request for inspection and/or production<lb/> of documents. In the said procedural order, it was directed that the<lb/> Tribunal will have sittings from 17 th January, 2017 to 21 st January,<lb/> 2017 for cross-examination of witnesses of each party by the other<lb/> side and oral arguments would be heard by the Tribunal from 31 st<lb/> January, 2017 to 4 th February, 2017. The timing for all sittings was<lb/> fixed from 11.00 a.m. to 5.00 p.m. with an hour&apos;s break for lunch. In<lb/> the said procedural order, Practice Directions under section 19(3) of<lb/> the Act were also set out in great detail. The relevant portion of the<lb/> Practice Directions read thus:<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> &quot;Practice Directions [under Section 19(3) of the<lb/> Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996]</content>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>… </head>
 … … …<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::</content>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>to by both sides. It held that the request for four weeks&apos; further time<lb/> for filing the Statement of Defence and Counter Claim was on<lb/> grounds which were fully within the knowledge of MSRDC even on<lb/> the date of the procedural order dated 20 th February, 2016 and, in<lb/> any event, when PLUS submitted its Statement of Claim on 19 th<lb/> March, 2016. The Tribunal further felt that the request for<lb/> extension of time by four weeks was quite unreasonable as granting<lb/> the aforesaid extension would completely disrupt the entire<lb/> schedule and it would become nearly impossible to hold the final<lb/> sittings as scheduled from 31 st January, 2017 (wrongly mentioned<lb/> as 30 th January, 2017) to 4 th February, 2017. However, the<lb/> Tribunal felt that rejecting MSRDC&apos;s request for extension<lb/> altogether would be unjust and, therefore, to balance the equities,<lb/> MSRDC was allowed two weeks&apos; time for submission of its Statement<lb/> of Defence and Counter Claim. It was made clear that no further<lb/> time would be allowed and that the Tribunal intends to maintain the<lb/> dates fixed for the final sittings undisturbed. Hence, suitable<lb/> adjustments would have to be made in the rest of the schedule by<lb/> shortening the time allowed to the parties by a few days at the<lb/> different stages in the proceedings before the final sittings and the<lb/> parties would be intimated of the amended Schedule in due course.<lb/> It was once again reiterated that the Schedule fixed under the<lb/> procedural order passed on 20 th February, 2016 was inflexible and<lb/> if any request for adjournment was made, it would have to be in<lb/> accordance with the Practice Directions issued on 20 th February,<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> 2016.<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> 97.<lb/> Pursuant to the </content>
 
            <figDesc>aforesaid order dated 4 th May, 2016, on<lb/> 12 th May, 2016, the Arbitral Tribunal, accordingly, changed the<lb/> dates by which the pleadings and evidence of the parties was to be<lb/> filed. The Tribunal set out that the dates mentioned in the<lb/> procedural order from Sr. Nos.1 to 10 were uniformly extended by a<lb/> fortnight as set out in the said order. The dates with reference to<lb/> the cross-examination of witnesses from 17 th January, 2017 to 21 st<lb/> January, 2017 as well as the sittings of the Tribunal to hear oral<lb/> arguments from 31 st January, 2017 to 4 th February, 2017 remain<lb/> unchanged.<lb/> 98.<lb/> Thereafter, in the meeting of the Tribunal on 17 th<lb/> October, 2016, the Tribunal considered several applications filed by<lb/> the parties. They were: (i) the application of PLUS regarding<lb/> averments submitted along with the affidavit of admission/denial of<lb/> documents; (ii) application dated 31 st August, 2016 filed by MSRDC<lb/> for production of documents by PLUS; (iii) application by MSRDC for<lb/> leave to file sur-rejoinder; (iv) application for production of<lb/> documents by PLUS and MSRDC respectively; and (v) application by<lb/> PLUS to file additional documents. After considering all these<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>applications and passing its order thereon, the Tribunal, inter alia,<lb/> clarified that the remaining schedule as per the amended procedural<lb/> order dated 20 th February, 2016, shall remain the same. In other<lb/> words, the arbitration sittings fixed for cross-examination of<lb/> witnesses from 17 th January, 2017 to 21 st January, 2017 as well as<lb/> for hearing oral arguments from 31 st January, 2017 to 4 th February,<lb/> 2017, were to remain unaffected.<lb/> 99.<lb/> On reading all the aforesaid procedural orders, two<lb/> things become absolutely clear: (i) both parties, namely, PLUS as<lb/> well as MSRDC were to file their pleadings and evidence in a time-<lb/>bound manner. If any party sought an extension, the same was to be<lb/> granted only in exceptional circumstances and as long as those<lb/> extensions did not materially affect the sittings of the Tribunal that<lb/> were to be held between 17 th January, 2017 to 21 st January, 2017<lb/> and from 31 st January, 2017 to 4 th February, 2017; (ii) the dates for<lb/> hearing the matter, namely, for cross-examination of witnesses<lb/> (from 17 th January, 2017 to 21 st January, 2017) and for hearing<lb/> oral arguments (from 31 st January, 2017 to 4 th February, 2017)<lb/> were inflexible. This was made abundantly clear by the Tribunal in<lb/> its various procedural orders referred to above. Another thing that<lb/> emerges from these procedural orders is that both parties were to<lb/> lead their entire evidence in support of their respective claims. In<lb/> none of these procedural orders was there any indication to either of<lb/> the parties that the proceedings would be bifurcated wherein the<lb/> Tribunal would first decide on issues (a) and (b) set out in<lb/> paragraph 54 of the impugned Award [relating to the validity of the<lb/> termination of the Concession Agreement] and defer the hearing for<lb/> deciding issues (c) and (d) [which related to quantum of the claims<lb/> and Counter Claim]. I may hasten to add that I am not for a moment<lb/> suggesting that the Tribunal could not have done the same,<lb/> especially considering that the Practice Directions that were issued<lb/> by the Tribunal were under section 19(3) of the Act where the<lb/> Tribunal is empowered to decide its own procedure. The only reason<lb/> I am stating this is because the Tribunal insisted on both sides filing<lb/> their complete pleadings as well as leading the entire evidence at<lb/> one go. It was not in contemplation of either of the parties that<lb/> evidence would be led in a piece-meal manner, whereby first it would<lb/> be on the issue of whether there was a valid termination of the<lb/> Concession Agreement and depending on the finding thereof, further<lb/> evidence would be led on the quantum of the claims and Counter<lb/> Claim. In fact, the arguments were also closed on 4 th February, 2017<lb/> and only the passing of the Award was reserved. This will become<lb/> further clear when I refer to the relevant portions of the transcripts<lb/> before the Tribunal on 17 th January, 2017, 20 th January, 2017, 3 rd<lb/> February, 2017 and 4 th February, 2017, respectively.<lb/> 100.<lb/> During the hearing on 17 th January, 2017, the counsel<lb/> for MSRDC (MR. KUMAR) sought a clarification as to whether they<lb/> were going to lead evidence on the Counter Claim at the same time<lb/> and whether there would be two separate Awards or there would be<lb/> one Award. The Tribunal clarified that there would only be one<lb/> Award. This was also the understanding of the counsel for PLUS<lb/> (MR. MUKHOPADHAYA). The relevant portion of the aforesaid<lb/> Minutes is reproduced hereunder:</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            103.<lb/> From the aforesaid </content>
 
            <figDesc>two transcripts of 17 th January,<lb/> 2017 and 20 th January, 2017, it clearly appears that the parties<lb/> were to lead their entire evidence on all issues and the Tribunal was<lb/> going to pass one consolidated Award. This was made clear, not only<lb/> in the transcript of 17 th January, 2017, but also in the transcript of<lb/> 20 th January, 2017. Thereafter, the cross-examination continued<lb/> and was completed on the scheduled date of 21 st January, 2017. The<lb/> arguments thereafter commenced as per the schedule laid down by<lb/> the Tribunal. The transcript of 1 st February, 2017, in fact, indicates<lb/> as to how the matter was under progress during oral arguments.<lb/> The parties, in fact, were directed to file their written submissions<lb/> by the dates mentioned in the said transcript. The relevant portion<lb/> of the said transcript of 1 st February, 2017 reads thus:</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>Tribunal, that the proceedings would be bifurcated wherein the<lb/> Tribunal would pass an Interim Award, first deciding on the issue of<lb/> termination of the Concession Agreement and thereafter defer the<lb/> hearing on the question of quantum of the respective claims. The<lb/> way the matter has proceeded before the Tribunal, it is quite clear to<lb/> me that parties were directed to lead their entire evidence on all<lb/> issues, including the quantum, and the arguments also proceeded on<lb/> that basis. I, therefore, fail to see as to what was the need to<lb/> bifurcate the proceedings by first passing an Interim Award on the<lb/> issue of termination and thereafter defer the hearing on the<lb/> question of quantum. I am not for a moment suggesting that an<lb/> Arbitral Tribunal is not empowered to do so. It certainly does. In<lb/> fact, in the present case, if the Tribunal had simply said that they<lb/> want to hear further arguments on the question of quantum<lb/> [without suo-moto giving liberty to the parties to file fresh pleadings<lb/> and lead further evidence], I do not think there could have been any<lb/> objection to the bifurcation of the proceedings as set out in the<lb/> Interim Award. However, that is not the case. What the Tribunal<lb/> has done in the impugned Award is allowed the parties to file fresh<lb/> pleadings and lead further evidence in the second stage of the<lb/> arbitration. In fact, after considering the evidence and submissions<lb/> of the parties, the Tribunal rejected certain specific claims of PLUS<lb/> and expressed its inability to decide the other claims on the<lb/> available evidence. It is even the case of PLUS that it had produced<lb/> all the evidence in support of its case and never made any request to<lb/> the Tribunal for leading any further evidence. Despite this, when it<lb/> came to the issue of Termination Payment, both under clause<lb/> 29.9(c) and clause 32.4.2, the Tribunal in the Interim Award, inter<lb/> alia, held that prima facie Termination Payment payable to PLUS<lb/> would have to be decided on the element of proportionality in the<lb/> working of the Termination Payment clause. The Tribunal noticed<lb/> that MSRDC had strongly contested the Termination Payment also<lb/> on the ground of each individual head that is to be calculated under<lb/> the formula and it would be beneficial to the Tribunal to invite<lb/> further hearings and submissions on this issue. As far as the<lb/> alternative to the claim for Termination Payment (of Rs.469 crores)<lb/> is concerned, the Tribunal was of the opinion that since it was<lb/> deferring its decision on the issue of Termination Payment, the<lb/> decision on the alternative claim also ought to stand deferred.<lb/> Paragraphs 72 and 73 of the impugned Award clarifies the above<lb/> position. The said paragraphs read thus:</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            108.<lb/> Thereafter, the </content>
 
            <figDesc>Tribunal deals with the claim for Rs.112<lb/> crores which claim the Tribunal records is largely predicated and<lb/> premised on the alleged admissions of liability (and quantum) made<lb/> by MSRDC and recorded in the Director&apos;s Report of July, 2011. The<lb/> objection taken with reference to these admissions by MSRDC was<lb/> that all the alleged admissions were made during conciliation<lb/> proceedings and hence were inadmissible. Despite over-ruling this<lb/> objection, the Tribunal opined that it was still required to determine<lb/> what weight could be attached to these documents as evidence of an<lb/> admitted quantum of loss. The Tribunal was of the view that it would<lb/> be unfair on MSRDC to determine the issue of quantum with<lb/> reference to the figures quoted during settlement discussions. The<lb/> Tribunal did not agree with PLUS that the figures cited in the IC&apos;s<lb/> correspondence necessarily reflected any independent analysis or<lb/> calculation of loss, either by the IC or MSRDC. The Tribunal was<lb/> prima facie of the view that these figures were put forward by PLUS&apos;<lb/> representatives and accepted (with minor modifications) by the IC.<lb/> In fact, the Tribunal noted that initially on the specific issue of<lb/> &apos;additional direct cost&apos;, PLUS&apos; representative put forward a figure of<lb/> Rs.162.37 crores, which was then accepted by the IC with minor<lb/> modifications as the revised project cost of Rs.161.19 crores. The<lb/> Tribunal also further noted that a huge difference in the revised<lb/> project cost first projected by PLUS on 24 th February, 2010 and the<lb/> other put forward by its representative (as recorded in the letter<lb/> dated 23 rd June, 2011) is itself indicative of the fact that figures<lb/> quoted in the correspondence have themselves fluctuated with time<lb/> and that too, quite significantly. This, according to the Tribunal, was<lb/> further indicative of the fact that these figures were proposed by<lb/> either side in the spirit of settlement while they were trying to work<lb/> out a rough and ready compromise. It is in these circumstances that<lb/> the Tribunal was of the opinion that it would not be fair on their part<lb/> to place much weight on the quantum figures exchanged by the<lb/> parties while working out a settlement. According to the Tribunal,<lb/> these figures did not constitute admissions of quantum of liability.<lb/> The Tribunal thereafter also opined that PLUS had made its claim<lb/> for damages of Rs.112 crores in addition to its claim for Termination<lb/> Payment. Prima facie, the Tribunal was of the view that this claim<lb/> can only be in the alternative. If PLUS was to satisfy the Tribunal<lb/> that Termination Payment is payable, then that would exhaust all<lb/> reliefs and would be to the exclusion of other reliefs that PLUS had<lb/> made under section 73 of the Contract Act or otherwise. If, on the<lb/> other hand, the Tribunal ultimately reached the conclusion that<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>SR Pasha, Sr PS<lb/> Page 155 of 169<lb/> Termination Payment was not payable (despite there being a valid<lb/> termination), then, it would be for PLUS to prove and quantify the<lb/> loss that it had suffered and claim damages on that basis. The<lb/> Tribunal was, therefore, not inclined at that stage to award Rs.112<lb/> crores in damages based on the alleged admissions of MSRDC. The<lb/> Tribunal was, therefore, of the view that even on this issue, further<lb/> hearings and submissions were required. It was clarified that in<lb/> making these submissions, PLUS need not be restricted to the<lb/> amounts allegedly admitted by MSRDC, but may even claim<lb/> amounts higher than that, should it be allowed to do so. However, it<lb/> would need to prove and quantify its loss by leading appropriate<lb/> evidence, if necessary. Similarly, MSRDC was not bound by any<lb/> alleged admissions and was free to independently reject PLUS&apos; claim<lb/> for damages, including by way of leading appropriate evidence, if<lb/> necessary. It is thereafter highlighted in paragraph 86 of the Award<lb/> that while deferring the quantum issue to a second stage, the<lb/> Tribunal is very mindful of the fact that such a second phase of the<lb/> arbitration is likely to involve both time and expense. The Tribunal<lb/> further holds that this is unavoidable in the circumstances as the<lb/> Tribunal cannot arrive at a quantum determination based on the<lb/> existing record and submissions.<lb/> 109.<lb/> It is all these parts of the Award and which I have set out<lb/> earlier, to which Mr. Chagla has taken strong objection and in which<lb/> I find considerable merit. As mentioned earlier, the arbitration<lb/> proceedings had commenced and continued before the Arbitral<lb/> Tribunal on the basis that the entire evidence was led by both<lb/> parties. In fact, the written submissions also filed before the<lb/> Tribunal by both parties would reflect the same. If the Tribunal was<lb/> not satisfied with the evidence led by either of the parties, it ought to<lb/> have rejected the claims on which the evidence was inadequate.<lb/> After making the parties lead their entire evidence, the Tribunal<lb/> could not have allowed either party to lead further evidence to<lb/> substantiate their claims when neither party made any such<lb/> request. If the Tribunal was of the opinion that the evidence was<lb/> inadequate, either to grant any claim of PLUS or any Counter Claim<lb/> of MSRDC, it ought to have rejected the claim / Counter Claim, as the<lb/> case may be. This entire exercise by the Tribunal of suo-moto<lb/> allowing the parties to lead further evidence, once the evidence was<lb/> closed and final arguments were also concluded, to my mind, clearly<lb/> vitiates the Award in so far as it allows parties to file fresh pleadings<lb/> and lead further evidence. The Tribunal has no power to allow a<lb/> party to lead further evidence after the evidence is closed without<lb/> the concerned party seeking leave of the Tribunal to lead further<lb/> evidence in that regard. I say this because if an application to lead<lb/> further evidence [after it is closed] is made by either party, the<lb/> Arbitral Tribunal would be bound to permit the other party to<lb/> respond to the same and thereafter render its decision thereon.<lb/> Failing to do so [i.e. granting the opposite party an opportunity to<lb/> contest the application for leading further evidence] would itself<lb/> render the Award vulnerable inter alia on the ground of breach of<lb/> principles of natural justice. The Tribunal, after the evidence is<lb/> closed, cannot suo-moto allow either party to lead further evidence<lb/> merely to accommodate a party to improve its case. That would be<lb/> contrary to all principles of fair play in any adversarial litigation<lb/> and would be in breach of the provisions of section 18 of the Act. In<lb/> the present case, the situation would have been quite different if the<lb/> Tribunal had made it clear to the parties that they need to lead<lb/> evidence only with reference to the issue of termination first, and<lb/> depending on the answer to the aforesaid issue, further evidence<lb/> would be allowed to be led by the parties regarding the quantum.<lb/> The situation would also have been different if the Tribunal had<lb/> bifurcated the proceedings to hear further arguments on the<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>SR Pasha, Sr PS<lb/> Page 158 of 169<lb/> quantum issue on the basis of the evidence already led by the<lb/> parties. However, that is not the case. The parties led their entire<lb/> evidence before the Tribunal and arguments were also canvassed in<lb/> relation thereto. Evidence was led not only with reference to<lb/> termination but also with reference to the quantum of each claim. In<lb/> other words, the parties proceeded before the Tribunal on the basis<lb/> that all issues would be decided by the Tribunal at one and the same<lb/> time and that they had presented their entire evidence and case<lb/> before the Tribunal. This being the situation, the Tribunal, on its<lb/> own, could not allow either party to lead further evidence, after the<lb/> evidence was already closed and all arguments were also canvassed<lb/> and written submissions filed. I am therefore of the view that the<lb/> Award is vitiated to the extent that it allows the parties to file fresh<lb/> pleadings and lead further evidence in the second stage of the<lb/> arbitration.<lb/> 110.<lb/> I am unable to agree with the submission of Mr.<lb/> Khambatta that all this was done primarily for the benefit of MSRDC<lb/> and, therefore, it does not lie in their mouth to complain of the<lb/> procedure adopted by the Tribunal. Firstly, from the Award itself, it<lb/> is clear that with relation to Termination Payment, the Tribunal was<lb/> of the opinion that it would have to consider whether payment<lb/> under clause 29.9(c) or 32.4.2 ought to be mechanically granted to<lb/> PLUS or whether it ought to be done on the basis of proportionality.<lb/> If Mr. Khambatta is correct that in relation to Termination Payment,<lb/> the evidence was already on record, nothing stopped the Tribunal<lb/> from ruling in favour of PLUS on the aforesaid issue. However,<lb/> obviously the view of the Tribunal was different. It is in these<lb/> circumstances and taking into consideration the objections laid out<lb/> by MSRDC that the Tribunal felt that the question of proportionality<lb/> has to be gone into.<lb/> 111.<lb/> Even as far as the claim for damages of Rs.112 crores is<lb/> concerned, the Tribunal was clearly of the view that PLUS had based<lb/> the aforesaid claim primarily on the admissions made by MSRDC<lb/> and on which not much weightage could be applied considering that<lb/> those admissions were made in the spirit of settlement. The<lb/> Tribunal, therefore, held that PLUS would have to independently<lb/> lead evidence to substantiate those claims. PLUS, clearly had not<lb/> asked for any permission of the Tribunal to lead any further<lb/> evidence. If PLUS was not interested in leading any further<lb/> evidence, the Tribunal ought to have rejected the claim of PLUS if it<lb/> was dissatisfied with the evidence already led by PLUS on the<lb/> aforesaid claim. The Tribunal could not have, on its own, given<lb/> liberty to the parties to lead further evidence on the aforesaid claim.<lb/> 112.<lb/> Similar is the case of the Counter Claim filed by MSRDC.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>arguments in the time-frame set out by the Tribunal. Once, having<lb/> fixed those dates and which clearly the Tribunal held as inflexible, I<lb/> fail to see how the Tribunal has come to the conclusion that<lb/> inadequate time was devoted to the Counter Claim filed by MSRDC.<lb/> The entire procedure followed by the Tribunal in relation to<lb/> deferring the claim for quantum at a later date by allowing the<lb/> parties to lead further evidence and file fresh pleadings is patently<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> &quot;Fundamental Policy of Indian Law<lb/> 27. </content>
 
            <figDesc>Coming to each of the heads contained in Saw Pipes [(2003) 5 SCC<lb/> 705 : AIR 2003 SC 2629] judgment, we will first deal with the head<lb/> &quot;fundamental policy of Indian law&quot;. It has already been seen<lb/> from Renusagar [Renusagar Power Co</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>28<head>. </head>
 
            <figDesc>In a recent judgment, ONGC Ltd. v. Western Geco International<lb/> Ltd. [(2014) 9 SCC 263 : (2014) 5 SCC (Civ) 12] , this Court added three<lb/> other distinct and fundamental juristic principles which must be<lb/> understood as a part and parcel of the fundamental policy of Indian law.<lb/> The Court held: (SCC pp. 278-80, paras 35 &amp; 38-40)<lb/> &quot;35. What then would constitute the &apos;fundamental policy of Indian law&apos; is<lb/> the question. The decision in ONGC [(2003) 5 SCC 705 : AIR 2003 SC<lb/> 2629]</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>30<head>. </head>
 
            <figDesc>The audi alteram partem principle which undoubtedly is a<lb/> fundamental juristic principle in Indian law is also contained in Sections<lb/> 18 and 34(2)(a)(iii) of the Arbitration and Conciliation Act. These sections<lb/> read as follows:<lb/> &quot;18.Equal treatment of parties.-The parties shall be treated with<lb/> equality and each party shall be given a full opportunity to present his<lb/> case.<lb/> ***<lb/> 34.Application for setting aside arbitral award.-(1)***<lb/> (2) An arbitral award may be set aside by the court only if-<lb/>(a) the party making the application furnishes proof that-<lb/>***<lb/> (iii) the party making the application was not given proper notice of the<lb/> appointment of an arbitrator or of the arbitral proceedings or was<lb/> otherwise unable to present his case;&quot;<lb/> *************<lb/> 34.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            (emphasis supplied)<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::</content>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>before the Tribunal prior to the passing of the impugned Interim<lb/> Award. In such a situation, the Arbitral Tribunal could not have<lb/> passed an Interim Award determining the validity of the<lb/> termination notices issued by PLUS and deferred the hearing for<lb/> deciding the issue of quantum of each claim/Counter Claim at a later<lb/> date by allowing the parties to file fresh pleadings and lead further<lb/> evidence. It is this action of the Arbitral Tribunal that I find<lb/> objectionable. The power of the Tribunal to pass an Interim/ Partial<lb/> Award is certainly there and given by the Statute itself. Under what<lb/> circumstances it is to be exercised, would certainly depend on how<lb/> the arbitration has proceeded either as per the agreement between<lb/> the parties or the procedure evolved by the Arbitral Tribunal. The<lb/> reliance, therefore, placed by Mr. Khambatta on the aforesaid<lb/> decision is of no assistance to PLUS.<lb/> 115.<lb/> Even the decision of the Division Bench of this Court<lb/> relied upon by Mr. Khambatta in the case of Manganese Ore<lb/> (India) Ltd. &amp; Ors. Vs. Ram Bahadur Thakur Limited [2006 SCC<lb/> Online Bom. 507] is wholly misconceived. The facts of this case<lb/> would clearly reveal that the learned arbitrator made an Interim<lb/> Award and held that the appellant had committed breach of the said<lb/> agreement by failing to supply 15,000 metric tonnes of manganese<lb/> ore of 46/48% grade as required under the contract and that the<lb/> respondent was entitled to recover from the appellant damages, if<lb/> any, by reason of breach of the contract. The learned arbitrator<lb/> further held that no evidence on the quantum of damages could be<lb/> led before him unless he first came to the conclusion that there was<lb/> a breach of contract committed by the appellant, and therefore,<lb/> fixed the date for further hearing for the purpose of enabling the<lb/> parties to lead evidence on the question of damages. It was in this<lb/> factual scenario that the Division Bench of this Court took a view<lb/> that in such circumstances the procedure adopted by the arbitrator<lb/> could not be faulted. The facts of this case would reveal that the<lb/> parties had led no evidence whatsoever on the quantum of damages<lb/> as the arbitrator (in the Interim Award) was only deciding whether<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::<lb/> CARBP371.17.doc<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>SR Pasha, Sr PS<lb/> Page 168 of 169<lb/> in fact there was a breach of the agreement. Only once he came to<lb/> that conclusion, he gave liberty to the parties to lead evidence on the<lb/> question of quantum. The facts of the case before me are however<lb/> totally different. In the present case, the parties led their entire<lb/> evidence, not only with reference to the validity of the termination<lb/> notices issued by PLUS but also on the quantum of each<lb/> claim/Counter Claim. Once this was done and the evidence was<lb/> closed by the Tribunal, without there being any application for<lb/> leading further evidence, the Tribunal could not have suo-moto<lb/> allowed the parties to file fresh pleadings and lead further evidence<lb/> in support of their respective claims. This being the case, I find that<lb/> the reliance placed on the aforesaid decision is also wholly<lb/> misplaced.<lb/> 116.<lb/> In view of the foregoing discussion:-<lb/>(i)<lb/> The challenge to Interim Award dated 25 th April,<lb/> 2017 on the ground that the Arbitral Tribunal relied<lb/> upon evidence which was inadmissible in law is<lb/> rejected;<lb/> (ii) The challenge to the Interim Award upholding the<lb/> validity of the termination of the Concession<lb/> Agreement dated 25 th August, 2006, under clause<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -19/04/2021<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 20:17:15 :::</content>
        </figure>



    </text>
</tei>

