<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_72062a7a70a97f325732c09a3e3fd04b.pdf"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">


        <figure>

            conditions may be instituted, continued and<lb/> enforced?<lb/> (4)<lb/> Whether in view </content>
 
            <figDesc>of the repeal of the Principal Act by<lb/> the Repeal Act, the Government of Maharashtra can:<lb/> (a) recall/ cancel/ modify the exemption order<lb/> granted either under Section 20 of the Principal Act;<lb/> (b) enforce circulars for implementation of<lb/> exemption orders issued under Section 20 of the<lb/> Principal Act prior to the repeal of the Principal Act;<lb/> (c) acquire the land by issuing notification under<lb/> Section 10(3) of the Principal Act; and<lb/> (d) take any action of whatsoever nature on<lb/> account of noncompliance/ breach of exemption<lb/> order issued under Section 20(1) of the Principal<lb/> taken in Mira Bhayandar Builders and Developers<lb/> Welfare Association v/s the Deputy Collector and<lb/> Competent Authority, Thane Urban Agglomeration and<lb/> others in Writ Petition No.5745/2009 dated 27 th<lb/> August, 2009 to the contrary should be held to be<lb/> laying down the correct principle of law?<lb/> 2<lb/> Since both sides have canvassed arguments on legal issues, in<lb/> order to appreciate them a few facts are required to be noted. We take the<lb/> facts from a lead case, namely, Writ Petition No.9872/2010. That is a Writ<lb/> Petition which has been filed by the Maharashtra Chamber of Housing<lb/> Industry and its various Units. These are associations established to<lb/> promote the housing and real estate industry. The Writ Petition is filed in<lb/> the interest of members of these Associations and real estate industry and<lb/> in the circumstances which are set out in paragraph 4 of the memo of<lb/> Writ Petition.<lb/> 3<lb/> It is the case of the Petitioners that the State of Maharashtra<lb/> and Competent Authorities under the Urban Land (Ceiling and<lb/> Regulation) Act, 1976 (hereinafter referred to as &quot;THE PRINCIPAL ACT&quot;)<lb/> continue to enforce and apply the provisions thereof despite enactment of<lb/> the Urban Land (Ceiling and Regulation) Repeal Act, 1999 (hereinafter<lb/> referred to as &quot;THE REPEAL ACT&quot;). The Repeal Act has been brought into<lb/> effect and is in force in the State of Maharashtra from 29.11.2007.<lb/> 4<lb/> The grievance of the Petitioners is that there is a circular<lb/> dated 18.03.2009 issued by the State Government, copy of which is at<lb/> AnnexureA. That circular states that the Repeal Act has been brought into<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:38 :::<lb/> force in the </content>
 
            <figDesc>State of Maharashtra w.e.f. 29.11.2007. The same expressly<lb/> saves the vesting of excess vacant land in the State as also validity of an<lb/> exemption order passed under Section 20(1) of the Principal Act.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>5<lb/> A reference is made in this circular and the steps taken to<lb/> implement the Repeal Act. The steps include two communications from<lb/> the Government dated 01.03.2008 and 03.03.2008 which outline the<lb/> scheme for development of these lands or their transfer.<lb/> 6<lb/> It has been revealed that the exempted lands are being dealt<lb/> with and for the purpose of implementation of the Slum Rehabilitation<lb/> Scheme, Rental Housing Scheme, etc.. Further, the reservations in respect<lb/> of these lands have been changed or altered from industry/ agriculture<lb/> without any reference to the Government/ Competent Authority. The<lb/> permissions in that regard have been granted without any prior approval<lb/> from the competent authorities under the Principal Act. Therefore, the<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:38 :::<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>Government has directed that the exempted lands cannot be used for any<lb/> other purpose nor their reservation can be changed unless the approvals/<lb/> remarks are called for from the competent authority under the Principal<lb/> Act. Any violation of such requirement would visit the persons concerned<lb/> with all consequences and at their costs.<lb/> 7<lb/> Prior to this circular there are certain Government<lb/> Resolutions and which enable utilization of Transferable Development<lb/> Rights (TDR) so as to use the lands for construction of houses for weaker<lb/> sections and equally to grant development permissions in relation thereto.<lb/> This is a Government Resolution dated 30.06.2007.<lb/> 8<lb/> There is also an order and which has been referred to<lb/> because it is the case of the Petitioners that their members had to obtain<lb/> several permissions from the Respondent Nos.1 and 2 for carrying out the<lb/> development. It is contended that the Government Resolutions referred by<lb/> us including dated 30.06.2007 and emphasis by the authorities on<lb/> compliance of the same continues despite the Repeal Act brought into<lb/> force with effect from 29.11.2007. There are several instances which have<lb/> been given and copies of the exemption orders passed under Section<lb/> 20(1) of the Principal Act are referred to in paragraph 7 of the memo of<lb/> Writ Petition No.9872/2010.<lb/> 9</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            ::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:38 :::<lb/> of the Principal </content>
 
            <figDesc>Act in the State of Maharashtra are wholly illegal. The<lb/> Authorities cannot compel parties like the Petitioners to seek any<lb/> extension of time to complete the scheme or to comply with the<lb/> conditions on which the order of exemption under Section 20(1) of the<lb/> Principal Act has been passed. The stand taken is that the Respondents<lb/> have no powers to enforce the Principal Act directly or indirectly. Several<lb/> instances of such alleged attempts are set out. There is reference made to<lb/> the legal provisions and finally what is prayed is that this Court must<lb/> restrain by an appropriate writ, order or direction under Article 226 of the<lb/> Constitution of India, the Respondents from enforcing the provisions of<lb/> the Principal Act insofar as such exemption orders and their terms and<lb/> conditions.<lb/> The attention of the Division Bench in Writ Petition<lb/> No.3815/2010 (Jayesh Tokarshi Shah v/s Deputy Collector and Competent<lb/> Authority, Thane Urban Agglomeration) was invited to all these judgments<lb/> and orders and stated to be conflicting. The Division Bench, therefore, in<lb/> its judgment dated 22 nd December, 2010 in the aforesaid matter observed<lb/> as under:</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>19<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>In that regard, Mr.Naphade has taken us through Sections<lb/> 20(2), 21(2) and 22(2) of the Principal Act. He submits that subsection<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:38 :::</content>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>care of by subsection (2) of Section 22. Thus, the power of exemption<lb/> has different parameters and the legislature was aware that such power<lb/> cannot survive the repeal of the Principal Act. Hence, in the teeth of this<lb/> clear language of the Repeal Act recourse to Section 6 of the General<lb/> Clauses Act, 1897 is impermissible. Once a different intention appears<lb/> from the provisions contained in the Repeal Act, then, Section 6 of the<lb/> General Clauses Act, 1897 would not apply. The question of liberal<lb/> construction of Section 3 of the Repeal Act, therefore, does not arise at<lb/> all.<lb/> 20<lb/> Mr.Naphade thereafter took us extensively through the<lb/> Repeal Act to submit that what is saved is specific. By clause (a) of sub<lb/> section (1) of Section 3 of the Repeal Act the vesting of land of which<lb/> possession has been taken by the State is saved. Meaning thereby, any<lb/> vacant land which is subject matter of declaration under Section 10(3) of<lb/> which possession has not been taken by the State Government, then its<lb/> vesting is not saved by the Repeal Act. Such land of which possession has<lb/> not been taken will have to be restored post repeal after the requirement<lb/> stipulated in subsection (2) of Section 3 of the Repeal Act is complied<lb/> with. Therefore, there is no collision between clause (a) and clause (b).<lb/> What clause (b) saves is only validity of the order granting exemption<lb/> under Section 20(1) or any action taken thereunder. The power to<lb/> withdraw the exemption is not saved. If it is held to be saved, then, clause<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:38 :::<lb/> (a) </content>
 
            <figDesc>of subsection (1) of Section 3 of the Repeal Act would be rendered<lb/> redundant. Only consequence of exemption being withdrawn is to subject<lb/> the land to applicability of ChapterIII of the Principal Act and particularly<lb/> Section 10(3) thereof. If possession of such excess vacant land cannot be<lb/> taken even after withdrawal of exemption in terms of subsection (2) of</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            ::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:38 :::<lb/> enforcing and exercising </content>
 
            <figDesc>substantive rights and powers and equally<lb/> procedural one. A forum is created so as to make and enact a complete<lb/> code. Nothing beyond the Principal Act can be seen. If the Repeal Act is<lb/> construed in this manner, then, it envisages complete destruction of the<lb/> rights under the Principal Act. Any right which is crystallized and which is<lb/> not a mere hope or chance is alone saved.<lb/> 21<lb/> Mr.Naphade also submits that Section 6 of the General<lb/> Clauses Act cannot be imported into and read when the Repeal Act is so<lb/> specific and clear. Alternatively and without prejudice to this submission<lb/> Mr.Naphade submits that if Section 6 of the General Clauses Act, 1897 is<lb/> analyzed, it by clauses (a) to (e) saves something which is in force or<lb/> existing at the time at which the repeal takes effect. It does not affect<lb/> previous operation of the Act so repealed or anything duly done or<lb/> suffered thereunder. The repeal does not affect any right, privilege,<lb/> obligation or liability acquired, accrued or incurred under the repealed<lb/> enactment. Mr.Naphade submits that clause (b) would, therefore, refer to<lb/> past or complete act and not something which is intended and<lb/> incomplete. The liabilities that are crystallized under the enactment which<lb/> is repealed alone are unaffected by repeal of the original or Principal Act<lb/> and that is clarified by clause (c). This clause cannot be imported in the<lb/> present Repealing Act for the simple reason that it would create<lb/> inconsistency. Mr.Naphade submits that clause (e) of Section 6 of the<lb/> General Clauses Act would have saved Section 20(2) of the Principal Act<lb/> had Sections 3 and 4 been not enacted in the Repeal Act. That being<lb/> clearly enacted there will be inconsistency if one imports clause (e) of<lb/> Section 6 of the General Clauses Act in Section 3(1)(b) of the Repeal Act.<lb/> For all these reasons Mr.Naphade would submit that the view taken by the<lb/> Andhra Pradesh High Court, Delhi High Court and Madras High Court<lb/> follows the Division Bench judgments of this Court from which Mira<lb/> Bhayander (supra) differs. That is the only view possible in the present<lb/> legal backdrop and we must, therefore, hold that Mira Bhayander (supra)</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            ::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:38 :::<lb/> circumstances if the </content>
 
            <figDesc>construction placed by the State on the provisions of<lb/> the Repeal Act is accepted that would result in saving of the consequences<lb/> following withdrawal of exemption. Section 20(2) of the Principal Act<lb/> envisages withdrawal of exemption and after such withdrawal what<lb/> follows is the vesting of the land in terms of Section 10(3) and its<lb/> possession as envisaged by Section 10(5) and (6). This is specifically not<lb/> saved by Section 3(1)(a) of the Repeal Act. Having regard to the clear<lb/> language of the Principal Act this is the only consequence which follows<lb/> on withdrawal of exemption. If it is not expressly saved, then, by an<lb/> indirect or oblique<lb/> method the Court cannot save it. Mr.Sathe&apos;s</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>This is envisaged by Section 1(2) of the Repeal Act. The Repeal Act comes<lb/> into force in other States after other States adopt the Repeal Act by<lb/> resolution passed in that behalf under Article 252(2) of the Constitution<lb/> of India. Mr.Sridharan, therefore, submits that this aspect must be borne<lb/> in mind while considering the submission or stand of the State regarding<lb/> applicability of Section 6 of the General Clauses Act. Mr.Sridharan<lb/> submits that Section 6 of the General Clauses Act applies only when<lb/> either the General Clauses Act or any Central Act or Regulation made<lb/> after commencement of the General Clauses Act repeals any enactment<lb/> made prior to the General Clauses Act coming into force or thereafter. In<lb/> the present case the State Government has adopted by resolution passed<lb/> under Article 252 of the Constitution of India the Repeal Act in the State<lb/> of Maharashtra with effect from 29.11.2007. In the light of such adoption<lb/> by resolution of the State Assembly the Section 6 of the General Clauses<lb/> Act cannot be resorted to or applied. That applies only when either the<lb/> General Clauses Act or any Central Act or Regulation made after<lb/> commencement of the General Clauses Act repeals any enactment made<lb/> or to be made by the Parliament. Both are Parliamentary Statues and in<lb/> such circumstances by virtue of Article 252(2) of the Constitution of India<lb/> the applicability of Section 6 of the General Clauses Act is ruled out.<lb/> 26<lb/> Alternatively, Mr.Sridharan submits that Section 3(1)(b) of<lb/> the Repeal Act is a special saving clause demonstrating a clear different<lb/> intention. Therefore, Section 3 of the Repeal Act saves only what is<lb/> specifically mentioned therein. There is no room for applying Section 6 of<lb/> the General Clauses Act, 1897 by implication or impliedly. Mr.Sridharan<lb/> also submits that in true sense we are not construing a validating statute<lb/> or clause. What is saved by clause (b) of subsection (1) of Section 3 is an<lb/> order under Section 20(1) of the Principal Act and the exemptions which<lb/> are subject matter of the same. All actions under the same are saved, but</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>unconditionally and in terms of the satisfaction in clauses (a) and (b) of<lb/> subsection (1) of Section 20 of the Principal Act. The power to exempt is<lb/> exercised by the State suomotu or otherwise meaning thereby on the<lb/> Application of the person holding the excess vacant land. The request is<lb/> not to apply the Chapter in the light of the factors and circumstances<lb/> specified therein. This request is made and granted only on the<lb/> satisfaction reached and not as a matter of course. Thus, application of<lb/> the chapter is a rule and its nonapplication is an exception. Despite<lb/> repeal of the Principal Act if the validity of the order granting exemption<lb/> under subsection (1) of Section 20 is saved by Section 3 of the Repeal<lb/> Act and such validity remains unaffected notwithstanding anything to the<lb/> contrary contained in the order of the competent court, then, full effect<lb/> will have to be given to the language of the Repeal Act. Once the Repeal<lb/> Act is so clear and does not evince anything contrary to the principles<lb/> enshrined in Section 6 of the General Clauses Act, then, on the strength of<lb/> the wording of the Repeal Act and in any event with the assistance of<lb/> Section 6 of the General Clauses Act it can safely be held that there is no<lb/> intention to destroy the rights and liabilities or consequences which flow<lb/> from a valid exemption order. In fact the language of Section 3 of the<lb/> Repeal Act supplements Section 6 of the General Clauses Act. Nothing in<lb/> Section 3 of the Repeal Act takes away applicability of the Principal Act to<lb/> the extent of enforcing the obligations in terms of the conditions imposed<lb/> in the order of exemption. The learned Advocate General submits that the<lb/> arguments of the Petitioners revolve around the saving clause enacted by<lb/> Section 3 of the Repeal Act. The submissions are that the Repeal Act<lb/> shows intention contrary to the applicability of Section 6 of the General<lb/> Clauses Act inasmuch as neither the exemption order nor any of the terms<lb/> and conditions therein can be enforced post repeal.<lb/> The learned Advocate General submitted that the provisions<lb/> of the Repeal Act and particularly Section 3(1) clauses (b) and (c) require<lb/> a harmonious interpretation. By reading these clauses together what is<lb/> apparent is that by clause (a) of subsection (1) of Section 3 of the Repeal<lb/> Act it is clarified that repeal of the Principal Act shall not affect the<lb/> vesting of any vacant land under Section 10(3) of the Principal Act,<lb/> possession of which has been taken over by the State Government or any<lb/> person duly authorized by the State in this behalf or by the competent<lb/> authority. Thus, if the steps as contemplated by subsection (3) of Section<lb/> 10 of the Principal Act and equally by subsections (5) and (6) thereof are<lb/> taken, then, the vesting of excess vacant land referred to in a Notification<lb/> published under Section 10(1) in terms of subsection (3) thereof is not<lb/> affected by repeal of the Principal Act. No person then can claim that the<lb/> excess vacant land to which the Principal Act admittedly applies and<lb/> which is deemed to have been acquired by the State does not belong to it<lb/> or the State is not entitled to it because the Principal Act has been<lb/> repealed and the vesting comes to an end. The vesting is of vacant land in<lb/> excess of ceiling limit. Undisputedly, if the land in excess of ceiling limit<lb/> can vest after the notification in terms of Section 10(1) is published in the<lb/> official Gazette, then, the declaration which is postulated or contemplated<lb/> by subsection (3) is in relation to such excess vacant land. What sub<lb/> section (3) of Section 10 really contemplates and envisages is that the<lb/> State can declare that the excess vacant land is deemed to have been<lb/> acquired by it upon publication of the declaration and particularly with<lb/> effect from the dates specified therein. By such deemed acquisition the<lb/> land is further deemed to have vested absolutely in the State free from all<lb/> encumbrances with effect from the date specified in the declaration. By<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:38 :::<lb/> the repeal what </content>
 
            <figDesc>has been clarified is that unless the State has taken over<lb/> possession of such excess vacant land and as referred to in the<lb/> Notification under Section 10(1) either by itself or through any person<lb/> duly authorized by it in this behalf or by the competent authority, its plain<lb/> and simple vesting will not enable the Government to take over<lb/> possession of the excess vacant land after coming into force of the Repeal<lb/> Act. This coming into force or commencing is reckoned in terms of sub<lb/> sections (2) and (3) of Section 1 of the Repeal Act. Thus, the State is<lb/> disabled from taking possession of the excess vacant land which has<lb/> already vested in it if it has failed to take possession. Thereupon the land<lb/> can be restored and that is how subsection (2) of Section 3 of the Repeal<lb/> Act would read. Therefore, this is not a restricted or limited saving clause<lb/> in any sense of the term. Though Section 3 is titled &quot;saving&quot; it contains<lb/> the substantive provisions. The Legislature or the Parliament did not<lb/> intend a vacuum. It did not stop by only stating that if possession of the<lb/> land vested in the State in terms of Section 10(3) is not taken, then, that<lb/> cannot be taken or the land cannot be made over to the Government after<lb/> repeal of the Principal Act. It enacts a further provision by which it is<lb/> possible for the State to restore the land to the holder and that is why<lb/> restoration is contemplated by virtue of Section 3(2). That restoration is<lb/> conditional upon repayment of an amount to the State Government by<lb/> the holder. Section 11 of the Principal Act talks of payment of amount for<lb/> the vacant land acquired under Section 10(3). That payment can be<lb/> claimed even without the land being handed over or without the<lb/> possession of the excess vacant land being taken. The deemed acquisition<lb/> by virtue of Section 10(3) enables the person or persons having interest in<lb/> the excess vacant land to claim the amount under Section 11. If any<lb/> payment has been made after such deemed acquisition, then, that amount<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:38 :::<lb/> has to be </content>
 
            <figDesc>returned to the Government and only then the excess vacant<lb/> land of which possession has not been taken will be restored to any<lb/> person or the holder as the case may be. If this was a complete<lb/> obliteration or destruction of the rights and liabilities under the Principal<lb/> Act, then, such substantive provision enabling restoration would not have<lb/> been inserted or incorporated is the submission of the learned Advocate<lb/> General. The refund of such amount and which has been paid to the<lb/> person or persons interested in the excess vacant land in terms of Section<lb/> 11 of the Principal Act alone entitles such person to claim restoration of<lb/> the land to him. If the repeal had been simplicitor and without such<lb/> substantive provision, then, it would not have been possible for the holder<lb/> or any person interested in the excess vacant land to claim its restoration.<lb/> It is, therefore, erroneous to urge that the Repeal Act evidences an<lb/> intention contrary to the applicability of Section 6 of the General Clauses<lb/> Act, 1897.<lb/> 34<lb/> Inviting our attention to clauses (b) and (c) of subsection</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            ::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:38 :::<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>ChapterIII either conditionally or otherwise. The learned Advocate<lb/> General submits that it is not just having regard to location of the land,<lb/> purpose for which the excess vacant land is being or is proposed to be<lb/> used and such other relevant factors as the circumstances of the case may<lb/> require, but it is necessary and expedient in the public interest that the<lb/> discretion to exempt such land has to be exercised. That is in terms of<lb/> clause (a) of subsection (1) of Section 20. Whereas, in terms of clause<lb/> (b) of subsection (1) of Section 20, the State is satisfied either on its own<lb/> motion or otherwise that the application of the provisions of ChapterIII<lb/> would cause undue hardship to the persons holding the vacant land in<lb/> excess of ceiling limit that the Government may by order exempt<lb/> conditionally or unconditionally the vacant land from the provisions of<lb/> ChapterIII. Further the order under clause (b) cannot be made unless the<lb/> reasons for doing so are recorded in writing. That is because clause (b)<lb/> contemplates relieving the person holding the excess vacant land from<lb/> undue hardship. Clause (a) necessarily postulates an exercise of powers to<lb/> exempt the excess vacant land in public interest. When such is the ambit<lb/> and scope of the powers and it is vacant land in excess of ceiling limit<lb/> which is exempted from the provisions of ChapterIII that too in<lb/> exceptional circumstances, then, it is futile to contend that the State<lb/> Government despite validity of its Act or order being saved by the Repeal<lb/> Act, would not be able to do anything in relation to such land post repeal<lb/> of the Principal Act. The learned Advocate General submits that in this<lb/> case the power of exemption and which is to be exercised for public good<lb/> and in public interest is so exercised by making an order in that behalf.<lb/> That the validity of such an order is saved though the Principal Act is<lb/> repealed, but the legal consequences flowing from exercise of such clause<lb/> are not saved, would be an incorrect, improper and legally untenable<lb/> reading of the saving clause and the Repeal Act itself. The true nature of<lb/> the power to exempt has not been appreciated in making such<lb/> submissions. The Petitioners&apos; arguments proceed on an unsound and<lb/> erroneous basis and namely that the power to exempt in terms of Section<lb/> 20(1) of the Principal Act is exercised by the State Government only to<lb/> benefit the holder. The argument is that it is to relieve the holder from the<lb/> consequences of applicability of ChapterIII that the State exercises such<lb/> power and therefore, nothing further can be done in pursuance of the<lb/> valid order of exemption post repeal of the Principal Act.<lb/> 35<lb/> The learned Advocate General submits that implicit and<lb/> inherent in this is the assumption that even conditional order of<lb/> exemption, though valid after repeal, cannot be enforced in any manner<lb/> post such repeal or post commencement of the Repeal Act. Meaning<lb/> thereby the condition incorporated in the order of exemption though<lb/> valid or any action taken in pursuance of such valid exemption order or<lb/> condition gets saved still further acts and consequences would not ensue<lb/> post repeal of the Principal Act. This construction of such Section 3(1)<lb/> ignores clause (c) of the said subsection totally. In that clause any<lb/> payment made to the State Government as a condition for granting<lb/> exemption under subsection (1) of Section 20 is not affected. The<lb/> condition of payment and which is for granting exemption is not affected<lb/> post repeal of the Principal Act. Then that condition can be enforced,<lb/> would be the sequitur. If that logically follows and qua one condition one<lb/> fails to understand as to why the Parliament would enact a Repealing Act<lb/> not only to save the validity of any order granting exemption under<lb/> Section 20(1) of the Principal Act or any action taken thereunder<lb/> notwithstanding any judgment of any court to the contrary, but to save<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:38 :::<lb/> only conditional payment </content>
 
            <figDesc>and leaving out all other conditions. It would<lb/> mean that a condition of payment incorporated in the order granting<lb/> exemption is valid and validity of such condition shall not be affected by<lb/> repeal, but the conditions other than payment are affected by repeal of<lb/> the Principal Act though Section 3(1)(b) saves the validity of the order<lb/> granting exemption. Such construction of the Repeal Act would lead to<lb/> absurdity and every interpretation which leads or results in such absurdity<lb/> must be avoided at all costs. Therefore, when the repeal of the Principal<lb/> Act shall not affect the validity of any order granting exemption under<lb/> Section 20(1) it means the order as whole including the conditions<lb/> incorporated therein is valid notwithstanding any judgment of any court<lb/> to the contrary. Equally any action taken thereunder is also valid<lb/> notwithstanding any judgment of any court to the contrary. The action<lb/> taken under the exemption order could be of enforcing it or any of its<lb/> conditions or withdrawing it. The repeal of the Principal Act shall not<lb/> affect the validity of all this notwithstanding any judgment of any court to<lb/> the contrary. The Parliament is presumed to be aware of the ambit and<lb/> scope of the power to exempt conferred by the Principal Act in the State<lb/> Government. It is further presumed to be aware of the fact that such<lb/> exemption orders are in force or were in force. Therefore, when the<lb/> repeal of the Principal Act is to take effect from the date of adoption of<lb/> the Repeal Act, then, the Parliament plainly intended that the repeal of<lb/> the Principal Act shall not affect the validity of any order granting<lb/> exemption under Section 20(1) or any action taken thereunder. The<lb/> Parliament was equally aware of the fact that such exemption order or<lb/> any action taken thereunder may have been declared as invalid by any<lb/> judgment of any court. Therefore, it did not stop at merely saving and not<lb/> affecting any order of exemption under subsection (1) of Section 20 or<lb/> any action taken thereunder, but by a nonobstante clause declared that<lb/> the validity of any order granting exemption or any action taken<lb/> thereunder shall not be affected by repeal of the Principal Act<lb/> notwithstanding any judgment of any Court to the contrary. Far from<lb/> evincing or demonstrating any contrary intention the saving clause vide<lb/> Section 3 protects and saves not only the initial order of exemption or any<lb/> action taken thereunder, but the exemption order or any action taken<lb/> thereunder is declared valid and expressly saved notwithstanding any<lb/> judgment of any court to the contrary. Equally, any payment made to the<lb/> State Government as a condition for granting exemption under sub<lb/> section (1) of Section 20 is saved and shall not be affected. Thus, both the<lb/> condition and the payment under same shall not be affected by repeal of<lb/> the Principal Act.<lb/> 36<lb/> The learned Advocate General submits that correct and true<lb/> understanding of the saving clause is what is the real issue. The<lb/> Petitioners&apos; arguments are based on erroneous and incorrect<lb/> understanding of such clause. A saving clause is used to preserve from<lb/> destruction certain rights, remedies or privileges already existing. It<lb/> means that it saves all the rights the party previously had. It does not give<lb/> him any new rights. The saving clauses are introduced into the Acts which<lb/> repeal others to safeguard the rights which, but for the savings, would be<lb/> lost. The Legislature may have termed Section 3 as saving provision or</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>(See: State of Bombay v/s United Motors (India) Limited<lb/> AIR 1953 SC 252). Therefore, it is not safe to hold that Section 3 of the<lb/> Repeal Act saves only limited rights or consequences.<lb/> 37<lb/> Taking us through Section 4 of the Repeal Act and<lb/> particularly its proviso the learned Advocate General submitted that all<lb/> proceedings relating to Sections 11, 12, 13 and 14 of the Principal Act<lb/> insofar as such proceedings are relatable to the vacant land, possession of<lb/> which has been taken over by the State Government, do not abate. This is<lb/> not a total abatement of legal proceedings as is contended. If the<lb/> interpretation or construction placed on the Repeal Act by the Petitioners<lb/> is accepted that would mean that the vesting of any vacant land of which<lb/> possession is taken by the State Government is not affected and therefore,<lb/> that power or right of the Government is saved. The repeal of the<lb/> Principal Act shall not affect such vesting as is clear from clause (a) of<lb/> subsection (1) of Section 3 of the Repeal Act. However, because of such<lb/> deemed acquisition and vesting of excess vacant land of which possession<lb/> is taken by the State Government or competent authority the person<lb/> holding the vacant land would stand to lose completely. He would not be<lb/> entitled to claim any payment of the deemed acquisition and vesting of<lb/> the land in the State Government free from all encumbrances and which<lb/> is unaffected by the repeal of the Principal Act. He would be totally<lb/> remedyless. Since the Principal Act is repealed Sections 11 to 14 also<lb/> would be taken as obliterated from the statute book. If they stand<lb/> obliterated and removed, then, a person holding the vacant land in excess<lb/> of ceiling limit though entitled to payment or compensation under the<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:38 :::<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>Principal Act would not be so entitled because the Principal Act is<lb/> repealed. Without the proviso, the duty of the State to compensate for<lb/> such vesting, may not have been saved or survived the repeal. It could<lb/> have been urged that the right to seek compensation from the State is lost<lb/> as the Principal Act is repealed and all proceedings thereunder abate on<lb/> the Repeal Act taking effect. That is why the Legislature by proviso to<lb/> Section 4 of the Repeal Act clarified that such excess vacant land of which<lb/> possession has been taken and its vesting is saved despite repeal of the<lb/> Principal Act does not mean that a person holding such land need not be<lb/> or cannot be compensated. He can claim payment and the proceedings<lb/> relating to Sections 11 to 14 of the Principal Act insofar as they relate to<lb/> the vacant land of which possession has been taken, do not abate. This<lb/> proviso is completely overlooked while arguing in support of the principle<lb/> of total destruction or obliteration of the rights and liabilities under the<lb/> Principal Act so also the remedies. If this is demonstrative of a positive<lb/> legislative intent and which is duly reflected in the statement of objects<lb/> and reasons of the Repeal Act, then, it would not be proper to accept the<lb/> contentions of Mr.Naphade and other Senior Counsel. If the intent and</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>original rights, liabilities in relation thereto remain unaffected. The<lb/> Repeal Act saves such rights and liabilities and which are accrued and<lb/> incurred on commencement of the Principal Act. That is why by clause (a)<lb/> of subsection (1) of Section 3 it was declared by the Parliament that the<lb/> repeal of the Principal Act shall not affect the vesting of any vacant land<lb/> under Section 10(3) the possession of which has been taken over by the<lb/> State Government otherwise, but for such express declaration it could<lb/> have been asserted that the Principal Act having been repealed the<lb/> vesting comes to an end or is obliterated. By clause (b) which cannot be<lb/> termed as merely a validating clause or saving theoretically the validity of<lb/> the exemption order, the Legislature declares that the said order is saved<lb/> with all legal consequences. This is in consonance with the object and<lb/> purpose in enacting the Repeal Act and saving from such repeal or leaving<lb/> unaffected by the repeal the exercise of some of the vital powers<lb/> conferred by the Principal Act and the actions taken thereunder.<lb/> 39<lb/> The learned Advocate General then submitted that it is not<lb/> correct to urge that the power to exempt is legislative in character. In that<lb/> behalf he took us once again through Sections 20(1) and (2), Sections 21<lb/> and 22 of the Principal Act, so also, the scheme of the Principal Act to<lb/> urge that it is an administrative order passed in the case of a excess<lb/> vacant land. Equally, the conditions imposed are inextricably linked to the<lb/> said exemption order. The public interest is paramount in imposing such<lb/> conditions and equally the Preamble of the Principal Act acts as a guide in<lb/> passing the orders of exemption under clauses (a) and (b) of subsection<lb/> (1) of Section 20. In such circumstances and when the order must contain<lb/> the reasons when it is made under clause (b) of subsection (1) of Section<lb/> 20, that order can be made on reaching the requisite satisfaction alone<lb/> and that withdrawal of the order of this nature is only after compliance<lb/> with the principles of natural justice, then, that rules out the possibility of<lb/> the power being termed as legislative in character, that submission of<lb/> Mr.Naphade has no substance. In these circumstances and when the point<lb/> is concluded by the judgment of the Constitution Bench of the<lb/> Honourable Supreme Court in the case of Bansidhar v/s State of Rajasthan<lb/> reported in (1989) 2 SCC 557, then, the reference cannot be answered,<lb/> but by holding that both subsections (1) and (2) of Section 20 of the<lb/> Principal Act are saved and not affected by repeal of the Principal Act. It is<lb/> fallacious to contend that withdrawal of the exemption order is axiomatic<lb/> or automatic on the satisfaction in terms of Section 20(2) being reached.<lb/> On the other hand what subsection (2) of Section 20 states is that it shall<lb/> be competent for the State Government to withdraw by order the<lb/> exemption if it is satisfied that any of the condition subject to which any<lb/> exemption under clause (a) or clause (b) of subsection (1) is not<lb/> complied with by any person. Further part of subsection (</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>cannot read the Repeal Act by omitting or leaving out therefrom anything<lb/> which the Legislature has specifically incorporated or inserted. We,<lb/> therefore, cannot hold that clause (a) of subsection (1) of Section 3 of<lb/> the Repeal Act which is a saving clause having saved the vesting of the<lb/> excess vacant land of which possession has been taken over and these<lb/> vacant lands may be at one time exempted, that the Legislature inserted<lb/> by way of abundant caution clauses (b) and (c) in subsection (1) of<lb/> Section 3 of the Repeal Act. The argument of Mr.Naphade and other<lb/> Senior Counsel is that this is by way of abundant caution and nothing<lb/> more.<lb/> 50<lb/> We are unable to agree with them because the excess vacant<lb/> lands being at one time exempted, but such exemption being withdrawn<lb/> later would equate such excess vacant lands with those in relation to<lb/> which the power of exemption was never exercised and the Chapter was<lb/> throughout applicable. Their status would be on par with those excess<lb/> vacant lands in relation to which no attempt was made to seek an<lb/> exemption or such attempt was made, exemption granted, but later on<lb/> withdrawn and withdrawal never questioned by the affected parties. If in<lb/> relation to such lands as well the necessary steps and in pursuance of<lb/> Section 10(1) could have been taken and prior to the repeal had the<lb/> possession of such lands been taken over, they would have vested in the<lb/> State and that vesting is saved or survives the repeal of the Principal Act,<lb/> then, there was absolutely no necessity of saving the exemption order and<lb/> which has already been acted upon or in relation to which the<lb/> consequences including those provided by Section 20(2) and ensuing the<lb/> same have already followed.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>3.<lb/> The Urban Land (Ceiling and Regulation) Repeal Bill,<lb/> 1998 was examined by the Standing Committee on<lb/> Urban and Rural Development. The Committee felt<lb/> that the land which is yet to be put to use for the<lb/> original purposes stated in the Act, under possession<lb/> of the Government should not be restored to previous<lb/> owners as such restoration may lead to avoidable<lb/> discrimination. The Committee also suggested that the<lb/> repeal Bill should contain a provision for abatement<lb/> of proceedings in the different courts. Keeping in view<lb/> the recommendations of the Committee, this Bill is<lb/> being introduced to replace the Urban Land (Ceiling<lb/> and Regulation) Repeal Ordinance, 1999 (Ord.5 of<lb/> 1999) notified on 11.01.1999 so that the State<lb/> Governments would be free to have their own<lb/> legislation commensurate with their needs and<lb/> experiences. Till this Act is repealed, States have no<lb/> power to legislate on this subject.<lb/> 4.<lb/> The proposed repeal, along with some other incentives<lb/> and simplification of administrative procedures, is<lb/> expected to revive the stagnant housing industry. The<lb/> repeal will facilitate construction of dwelling units<lb/> both in the public and private sector and help<lb/> achievement of targets contemplated under National<lb/> Agenda for Governance. The repeal will not, however,<lb/> affect vesting of any vacant land under subsection<lb/> (3) of Section 10 of the Urban Land (Ceiling and<lb/> Regulation) Act, 1976 the possession of which has<lb/> been taken over by the State Governments. It will not<lb/> affect payments made to the State Governments for<lb/> exemptions. The exemptions granted under Section 20<lb/> of the Act will continue to be operative. The amounts<lb/> paid out by the State Governments will become<lb/> refundable before restoration of the land to the<lb/> former owners.<lb/> 5.<lb/> The Bill also seeks to facilitate land assembly and a<lb/> flexible regime for administering urban land to suit<lb/> the varying local conditions based on State level<lb/> legislations or requirements.&quot;<lb/> 53<lb/> If one peruses clause 4 of the Statement of objects and<lb/> reasons carefully and particularly the part where the intent is not to affect<lb/> by repeal the exemption under Section 20 of the Principal Act will and<lb/> that continues to be operative. After adopting the Repeal Act, the States<lb/> have a freedom to legislate on the same subject as is clear from Clause 3<lb/> of the Statement of Objects and Reasons to the Repeal Act. That intent<lb/> and purpose is not achieved or served by a mere insertion of clause (a) of<lb/> subsection (1) of Section 3 of the Repeal Act. It is, therefore, that the<lb/> Legislature did not exhaust itself and added clause (b) and that too to<lb/> subsection (1) of Section 3 of the Repeal Act and by inserting the words<lb/> of wide import. It is with an intent of not affecting the exemptions<lb/> granted, but continuing them so also preserving their validity that clause<lb/> (b) has been so worded. In clause (b) not only the Legislature has saved<lb/> the validity of exemption order or any action taken thereunder, but has<lb/> protected or saved this validity notwithstanding anything to the contrary<lb/> held by a court of competent jurisdiction. The Legislature was aware that<lb/> the exemptions have been granted under Section 20 across the country by<lb/> several State Governments in exercise of their powers to exempt the<lb/> excess vacant lands from applicability of ChapterIII of the Principal Act.<lb/> These exemption orders have been passed bearing in mind the location of<lb/> excess vacant land, the purpose for which it is used or intended to be<lb/> used and such other relevant factors as the circumstances of the case may<lb/> require. The power to exempt has been exercised after the Government<lb/> reached this satisfaction and further that it is necessary and expedient in<lb/> the public interest so to do. Under clause (a) of subsection (1) of Section<lb/> 20, therefore, exemption to the excess vacant lands from the provisions of<lb/> ChapterIII is not to benefit the land holder as is urged before us. It is to<lb/> uphold and promote the larger public interest particularly of providing<lb/> affordable living accommodation and for those who are in a poor state<lb/> and entitled to public assistance. The Legislature was aware that<lb/> exemption orders have also been passed in some cases to relieve the<lb/> hardship to the persons holding excess vacant land on the requisite<lb/> satisfaction reached by the Government. That satisfaction is that unless<lb/> the vacant land in excess of ceiling limit held by such person is not<lb/> exempted from the provisions of ChapterIII undue hardship would be<lb/> caused to such person. The Legislature was equally aware while enacting<lb/> the Repeal Act that several exemption orders under clauses (a) and (b)<lb/> have been passed with conditions attached to them. The conditions may<lb/> be of imposition of penalties for delay in completion and implementation<lb/> of a housing project or scheme. The conditions imposed may interalia<lb/> visit the person or holder with the consequence of withdrawal of the<lb/> exemption and forfeiture of the amounts paid or deposited. Such<lb/> conditional orders of exemption are in force and not withdrawn because<lb/> the Government was of the opinion that the lands were being put to such<lb/> use as would serve the object and purpose in enacting the Principal Act.<lb/> That the State Governments were aware that the schemes of housing for<lb/> weaker sections in the society were promulgated and such excess vacant<lb/> lands were to be utilized to provide cheap and affordable housing to the<lb/> economically backward section or class of the society. The schemes of this<lb/> nature were under several stages of implementation. The houses or<lb/> tenements in such schemes or in housing projects earmarked for these<lb/> sections of the society, were to be handed over or were to be taken over so<lb/> as to reach the ultimate beneficiaries. It is with these objects and peculiar<lb/> facts and circumstances of each case that the State allowed the exemption<lb/> to remain in force. That at appropriate stages the extensions to the<lb/> exemption orders have been granted. Therefore, if the exemption is<lb/> granted firstly in public interest and secondly to relieve the undue<lb/> hardship, then, such exemption orders being interfered with by the courts<lb/> or struck down or quashed would cause serious prejudice and loss to the<lb/> deprived sections of the society. When these states of affairs are to the<lb/> knowledge of the Legislature, then, it is not possible to accept the<lb/> contentions of Mr.Naphade that clauses (b) and (c) of subsection (1) of<lb/> Section 3 of the Repeal Act are only added as and by way of abundant<lb/> caution. We cannot attribute to the Legislature such surplusage.<lb/> 54<lb/> The validity of exemption order is saved so as to ensure that<lb/> the same serves the purpose for which it is granted. If that is what the<lb/> Legislature had in mind, then, it is futile to suggest that the Legislature<lb/> has left unaffected by repeal only the validity of the exemption order, but<lb/> not its conditions. The argument that the conditions on which the<lb/> exemption order is based or passed are no longer valid, but it is only the<lb/> exemption order whose validity is saved, is required to be stated only for<lb/> being rejected. While canvassing such an argument the counsel lost sight<lb/> of clause (c) of subsection (1) of Section 3 of the Repeal Act. If as a<lb/> condition for grant of exemption any payment has to be made to the State<lb/> Government, then, the repeal of the Principal Act was not to affect such<lb/> payment or condition under which the same is made. The insertion of the<lb/> words &quot;as a condition for granting exemption&quot; in clause (c) of subsection<lb/> (1) of Section 3 would demonstrate the legislative intent. If the payment<lb/> made to the State Government as a condition for granting exemption and</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>for public good and in public interest. The exercise of such powers is,<lb/> therefore, presumed to be bonafide and for achieving the object and<lb/> purpose for which it is conferred. It is with these presumptions and which<lb/> were always present to the Legislature that the validity of exemption<lb/> order has been saved. Having said that and also saving the payment or<lb/> monetary aspect related to the exemption, it was not necessary for the<lb/> Parliament to then spell out separately all the legal consequences flowing<lb/> from such valid order. Even otherwise, that there is no intention contrary<lb/> to what is spelled out by Section 6 of the General Clauses Act is,<lb/> therefore, apparent. There is no substance in the argument of the<lb/> Petitioners that only the exemption order is saved, but not its terms and<lb/> conditions and further by not referring to subsection (2) of Section 20<lb/> the State&apos;s power to withdraw the exemption is taken away by repeal of<lb/> the Principal Act. The argument is that the power to withdraw the<lb/> exemption in terms of Section 20(2) of the Principal Act conferred in the<lb/> State cannot be exercised because of repeal of the Principal Act. This<lb/> argument is premised on the fact that once the State Government<lb/> withdraws the exemption order the only consequence could be that the<lb/> excess vacant land vests in the State under Section 10(3) of the Principal<lb/> Act and that vesting cannot take place after repeal of the Principal Act.<lb/> 55<lb/> In that regard if one notices Section 4 of the Repeal Act, that<lb/> would denote that the proceedings under Sections 11 to 14 of the<lb/> Principal Act are not affected by the abatement or the section in the<lb/> Repeal Act causing abatement of pending proceedings or proceedings<lb/> purported to be taken under the Principal Act. This itself throws light on<lb/> the intent of the Parliament in not completely and totally obliterating the<lb/> Principal Act. This itself shows that the Principal Act is not wiped out<lb/> from the statute book totally. Thus, after the deemed acquisition and<lb/> vesting of the vacant land in the State if possession thereof is taken,<lb/> recourse to these sections is permissible despite the Repeal of the<lb/> Principal Act.<lb/> 56<lb/> The fallacy in the above arguments can be demonstrated by<lb/> perusing Section 20 of the Principal Act. The difference in the language<lb/> in Section 19 and Section 20 is that Section 19 says that ChapterIII will<lb/> not apply to certain vacant lands whereas what Section 20 sets out is the<lb/> power to exempt the vacant land in excess of ceiling limit and which<lb/> power can be exercised by the State Government in cases covered by<lb/> clauses (a) and (b). That the said exemption can be withdrawn provided</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>declaration under Section 10(3) of the Principal Act is further undisputed.<lb/> 57<lb/> In this backdrop if Section 20 is perused that confers a power<lb/> to exempt and it opens with a nonobstante clause, namely,<lb/> notwithstanding anything contained in any of the foregoing provisions of<lb/> this Chapter, namely, ChapterIII. The clause (a) of subsection (1) of<lb/> Section 20 refers to a person holding the vacant land in excess of ceiling<lb/> limit. If the State Government is satisfied suo motu or otherwise that<lb/> having regard to the location of such land, the purpose for which such<lb/> land is used or is proposed to be used and such other relevant factors as<lb/> the circumstances of the case may require and it is necessary or expedient<lb/> in the public interest to do so, then, the Government may, by order,<lb/> exempt, subject to such conditions as may be specified in the order, such<lb/> vacant land from the provisions of ChapterIII. Thus, what is required for<lb/> exemption firstly is that a person holds the vacant land in excess of ceiling<lb/> limit, satisfaction of the State Government suo motu or otherwise that<lb/> having regard to the location of such land, purpose for which such land is<lb/> being or is proposed to be used and such other relevant factors as the<lb/> circumstances of the case may require, it is necessary or expedient in<lb/> public interest so to do. Upon such satisfaction the Government may by<lb/> order, exempt the vacant land from the provisions of ChapterIII by<lb/> making an order and which could be conditional. The word &quot;Exemption&quot;<lb/> means free from an obligation or liability. In Advanced Law Lexicon by<lb/> P.Ramanatha Iyer, 3 rd Reprint 2007, the word &quot;exempt&quot; shows that a<lb/> person is put beyond the application of law. It means to give freedom<lb/> from liability, tax or duty like any exception. It is a privilege.<lb/> 58<lb/> The argument of Mr.Naphade overlooks the position that<lb/> when the power of exemption has to be exercised notwithstanding<lb/> anything contained in any of the foregoing provisions of this Chapter,<lb/> namely, ChapterIII, then, even Section 10 is included therein. Therefore,<lb/> the land may have been notified in terms of subsection (3) of Section 10,<lb/> yet the holder of such vacant land and which is in excess of ceiling limit<lb/> can seek the Government&apos;s intervention and invoke the powers conferred<lb/> in the State Government vide Section 20(1). Similarly, by clause (b) of<lb/> subsection (1) of Section 20 where any person holds the vacant land in<lb/> excess of ceiling limit and the State Government on its own motion or<lb/> otherwise is satisfied that the application of the provisions of Chapter III<lb/> would cause undue hardship to such person, that the Government may by<lb/> an order, exempt, subject to such conditions as may be specified in the<lb/> order, such vacant land from the provisions of this Chapter. However, the<lb/> proviso clarifies that no orders under this clause, namely, clause (b) shall<lb/> be made unless the reasons for the same are recorded in writing.<lb/> 59<lb/> If the argument of Mr.Naphade is accepted, that would mean<lb/> that the powers to exempt cannot be exercised when the land is already<lb/> vested in the State in terms of Section 10. That the power under Section<lb/> 20(2) for withdrawal of exemption cannot be exercised after repeal of the<lb/> Principal Act, presupposes that exemption itself cannot be granted after<lb/> vesting takes place. Mr.Naphade and other counsel contend that effect of<lb/> withdrawal of exemption is to vest the vacant land in the State in terms of</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>whether the competent authority has to await the<lb/> decision under Sections 20 and 21 before declaring and<lb/> publishing the excess land under Section 10(3) by a<lb/> notification in the Gazette. The scheme of the Act does<lb/> indicate that until the date of the publication in the<lb/> Gazette prescribing a date on and from which the excess<lb/> land stands vested in the State, the owner continues to<lb/> be the owner of the excess land and entitled to remain in<lb/> possession thereof. On publication of the notification<lb/> under Section 10(3) and after putting a date from<lb/> which the land stands vested in the State and after<lb/> publication of the notification in the Gazette and on and<lb/> from the date mentioned therein, the excess vacant land<lb/> stands vested in the State free from all encumbrances,<lb/> subject to the decision in appeal, if any, filed according<lb/> to law.<lb/> 6. The previous owner stands divested of right, title<lb/> and interest in the land subject to the right to make<lb/> application provided under Sections 20 and 21. It is<lb/> difficult to accept the contention of the learned Counsel<lb/> for the appellants that the competent authority has no<lb/> power to have the notification under Section 10(3)<lb/> published in the Gazette until the application either<lb/> under Section 20 or 21 is disposed of. The very language<lb/> of Sections 20 and 21 and the exercise of the power<lb/> thereunder would arise only when the land stands vested<lb/> in the Government. The power of examination and<lb/> exemption would arise only when the Government<lb/> becomes the owner and the erstwhile owner seeks to<lb/> obviate the hardships under Section 20 or to subserve<lb/> the housing scheme for weaker sections under Section 21<lb/> as envisaged thereunder. Thereat, the Government is<lb/> required to consider whether the proposals made by the<lb/> erstwhile owner for undertaking the scheme as envisaged<lb/> under Section 21 or hardships as envisaged under<lb/> Section 20 for exemption would merit consideration. In<lb/> this case, admittedly, the application under Section 20<lb/> came to be filed though that was suppressed before the<lb/> High Court and this Court and came to be dismissed<lb/> before notification under Section 10(3) of the Act was<lb/> published. It also appears, as stated earlier, that<lb/> application under Section 21 was filed on March 29,<lb/> 1979, the date on which the appellants had filed the<lb/> writ petition in the High Court. It would, therefore, be<lb/> seen that the application came to be filed much after the<lb/> date of the vesting and publication of the notification<lb/> under Section 10(3) of the Act. The effect of the vesting<lb/> is not contingent upon filing an application for disposal<lb/> under either Section 20 or 21. We do not go into the<lb/> correctness of the order passed by the Government under<lb/> Section 21 for the reason that it would be open to the<lb/> Government and the Government have stated in their<lb/> order that they have already decided to allot the land for<lb/> another equally efficacious public purpose. Therefore, we<lb/> cannot sit over the decision taken by the Government<lb/> holding it illegal.&quot;<lb/> 62<lb/> Following this view and principle in a later decision reported<lb/> in Special Officer &amp; Competent Authority, Urban Land Ceilings, Hyderabad<lb/> and others v/s P.S. Rao reported in AIR 2000 SC 843, the Honourable<lb/> Supreme Court held as under:</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>. The view<lb/> taken by the High Court following the decision of this<lb/> Court in T.R. Thandur v. Union of India, (1996) 3<lb/> SCC 690 : (1996 AIR SCW 1700 : AIR 1996 SC<lb/> 1643), Darothi Clare Parreira (Smt.) v. State of<lb/> Maharashtra, (1996) 9 SCC 633 : (1996 AIR SCW<lb/> 3179 : AIR 1996 SC 2553) and State of A. P.<lb/> represented by Secretary to Govt., Revenue<lb/> Department, Hyderabad v. Valluru Venkateswara<lb/> Rao, (1997) 3 Andh. LT 417 does not call for any<lb/> interference.&quot;<lb/> 63<lb/> Once this legal position is noticed we do not see as to how<lb/> absence of subsection (2) of Section 20 of the Principal Act in clause (b)</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>in excess of ceiling limit and which has already vested in it, then, there is<lb/> no impediment in withdrawing the exemption from applicability of<lb/> ChapterIII of the Principal Act in the case of such lands. The legal<lb/> position, therefore, cannot be otherwise than what is held in the decisions<lb/> of the Honourable Supreme Court and referred by us above and both of<lb/> which have been rendered after the judgment in the case of T.R.Thandur<lb/> v/s Union of India reported in (1996) 3 SCC 690. The argument of the<lb/> learned Senior Counsel is that it would be inconsistent and contrary to<lb/> the legislative intent if we hold that the power to withdraw the exemption<lb/> conferred vide Section 20(2) of the Principal Act is saved despite the<lb/> repeal. That would mean that possession of such lands can be taken post<lb/> vesting and that is permissible even after repeal of the Principal Act. The<lb/> argument is that it would be incongruous and even absurd to hold that<lb/> the power to take possession conferred vide Section 10(5) and 10(6) of<lb/> the Principal Act is saved despite repeal of the Principal Act. It is urged<lb/> that same would make clause (a) of subsection (1) of Section 3 of the<lb/> Repeal Act wholly redundant and even meaningless. We must at once<lb/> clarify that clause (a) of subsection (1) of Section 3 of the Repeal Act is<lb/> not dealing with only exempted lands. It is dealing with all excess vacant<lb/> lands and which are subject matter of the declaration under Section 10(3)<lb/> of the Principal Act. Their vesting will not be affected only if possession<lb/> thereof is taken. Thus, clause (a) itself clarifies that the vesting of such<lb/> lands would not be affected by repeal if their possession is taken. That<lb/> only means that the Legislature was fully aware of the legal consequences<lb/> of declaration under Section 10(3) of the Principal Act. That provides for<lb/> deemed acquisition of the excess vacant land and their vesting in the<lb/> State free from all encumbrances. They vest accordingly, but since<lb/> possession thereof has not been taken that the Repeal Act enacts a<lb/> provision whereunder these lands can be restored to any person provided<lb/> he complies with subsection (2) of Section 3 of the Repeal Act. In the<lb/> case of the lands which are subject matter of a valid exemption order and<lb/> validity of which is not affected even by any court&apos;s order to the contrary<lb/> and equally any action taken thereunder is not affected by repeal of the<lb/> Principal Act and is saved though the same may not have been upheld by<lb/> the Court, then, the intent and purpose is not to allow any person holding<lb/> the excess vacant land and which is already vested in the State to escape<lb/> the legal consequences resulting from the order of exemption. If that<lb/> order is passed in order to subserve public interest and to uphold it and to<lb/> relieve undue hardship, then, such an order of exemption which may be<lb/> conditional visits the person with consequences. It is not an absolute right<lb/> or privilege as is claimed. It may be a conditional exemption. It may allow<lb/> the person to use the land for the stated purpose, but that is not relieving<lb/> him or the land from the condition or obligation imposed by Law and<lb/> equally any liability. It is not an advantage or benefit, if at all, which could<lb/> be enjoyed absolutely. It is to fulfill the object or purpose of the user and<lb/> to act in public interest or to avoid undue hardship. The applicability of<lb/> Chapter III being expressly admitted, but seeking to avert the<lb/> consequences of such applicability in exceptional circumstances that the<lb/> request to exempt is considered and granted. The power in that behalf is<lb/> to be exercised sparingly and as an exception. It is not a rule. It is a<lb/> corresponding right of the State and to be exercised to uphold larger<lb/> Public Interest. Thus, it is not a one sided right or privilege. It is not<lb/> relieving the person from the legal consequences of the power to exempt<lb/> and more so, if it is a conditional order. It is to safeguard public interest<lb/> that such power is exercised and in a given case conditionally. If relieving<lb/> somebody on account of his hardship or exempting the vacant land for a<lb/> specific purpose by holding in abeyance the applicability of provisions of<lb/> ChapterIII is the aim, then, that person cannot claim benefit or<lb/> advantage in himself much less in absolute terms. It is a relief granted to<lb/> relieve him from undue hardship caused by applicability of the provisions<lb/> of ChapterIII. If that power under clause (b) of subsection (1) of Section<lb/> 20 is exercised subject to such conditions, as can be imposed by the State<lb/> bearing in mind the object and purpose of the Principal Act and if they</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>above which are incidental and ancillary to the main power of granting<lb/> exemption. Thus, the conclusion can be reached and safely that the State<lb/> exempts the vacant land in excess of ceiling limit from applicability of<lb/> ChapterIII of the Principal Act in public interest in terms of clause (a) or<lb/> bearing in mind the undue hardship caused to the person holding it<lb/> exempts it from applicability of the same Chapter and in both events if<lb/> the power is exercised also to pass a conditional order or grant<lb/> conditional exemption, then, the right, if any, created in relation to such<lb/> land in favour of the person holding it is not absolute and it is conditional<lb/> upon fulfillment of the obligations and liabilities attached to it. If these<lb/> conditions are not satisfied, but rather breached and violated, then, the<lb/> State&apos;s power to withdraw the exemption survives the repeal of the<lb/> Principal Act in all cases including where the power to exempt under<lb/> Section 20(1) of the Principal Act is exercised post vesting of the lands in<lb/> the State. It will also survive in those cases where the power is exercised<lb/> so as to exempt the excess vacant land in terms of the same provision, but<lb/> in relation to which the unconditional or conditional exemption order is<lb/> still in force and not withdrawn. In either events the State can proceed<lb/> despite repeal of the Principal Act because that power of the State<lb/> survives the repeal. That power survives because despite the repeal the<lb/> State can enforce the exemption orders as the persons holding such lands<lb/> do not derive or get an absolute right or advantage or benefit and that is<lb/> subject to the liabilities and obligations incurred by them. These survive<lb/> the repeal of the Principal Act because had the intent was not to so<lb/> protect or save, the Parliament would not have saved the validity of the<lb/> exemption order or any action taken thereunder. Any action taken<lb/> thereunder is also valid together with the exemption order more so if the<lb/> action contemplates ensuring compliance with certain terms and<lb/> conditions of the exemption order such as obtaining open spaces and<lb/> amenities for the public, dwelling units so as to subserve larger public<lb/> interest. We cannot and do not intend to exhaust the power of the State<lb/> to enforce its order passed under Section 20(1)(a) and (b) of the<lb/> Principal Act in the light of the Repeal Act. Further, the nature and ambit<lb/> of the conditions may be such that their noncompliance and breach,<lb/> beyond a certain period and intentionally would visit the person with<lb/> either withdrawal of the exemption itself or any other penalty/ damages<lb/> in addition to complying with the terms and obligations. Such obligations,<lb/> liabilities and conditions voluntarily incurred and invited cannot be said<lb/> to be invalid or inoperative. They bind the parties. If the State can call<lb/> upon the person concerned to handover the tenements and units meant<lb/> for either weaker section or its nominees to it or to comply with other<lb/> such obligation and liability by legally permissible modes of compliance,</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>holder or retain it as an exception, but neither the State being able to<lb/> enforce the conditions if any subject to which exemption is granted or to<lb/> withdraw the said exemption. Equally, the effect of the repeal being to<lb/> save the validity of the order granting exemption under Section 20(1) or<lb/> any action taken thereunder, the person in whose favour such exemption<lb/> is granted will not be able to do anything in relation to such vacant land<lb/> which except for the exemption may have vested already in the State by<lb/> virtue of Section 10(3). He then cannot move the State and seek any<lb/> payment for acquisition and vesting. Hence, when the Legislature had in<lb/> mind the saving clause as is carved out by section 3(1)(b) and (c), its<lb/> intent was not to take away any of the powers conferred in the State nor<lb/> exclude applicability of the provisions of ChapterIII of the ULC Act to<lb/> such an extent as would make it impossible for the person to seek<lb/> payment in terms of Sections 11 to 14 or to seek enforcement of such<lb/> conditions which are reciprocal and which are to be performed by both.<lb/> Just as the State would be unable to enforce the conditions on which<lb/> exemption is granted, equally the members of the public or person<lb/> holding the excess vacant land would not be able to enforce the<lb/> conditions which are incorporated therein so as to protect their interest.<lb/> Such situation can never be envisaged by the Parliament. Such situation<lb/> being created would render all the provisions of the Repeal Act<lb/> redundant. The intent as is clear from a harmonious reading of the Repeal<lb/> Act and in the backdrop of the aims and objects of the Principal Act is to<lb/> save the applicability of the provisions contained in ChapterIII to the<lb/> excess vacant lands which are subject matter of exemption under Section<lb/> 20(1). Section 3(1)(a) covers a situation where there is no exemption<lb/> order passed under Section 20(1)(a) and (b). That covers the vacant<lb/> lands which are not subject matter of any order of exemption or such<lb/> order being not in force on the date of the Repeal Act and in regard to<lb/> which the provisions contained in ChapterIII were always applicable.<lb/> Therefore, if the State does not complete the action in relation to these<lb/> lands by taking possession thereof, their mere vesting and deemed<lb/> acquisition by virtue of Section 10(3) is not saved. Section 3(1)(b) deals<lb/> with a separate and distinct situation and that is applicable to the lands<lb/> which are vacant and in excess of ceiling limit and in relation to which<lb/> the order of exemption under Section 20(1) has been passed.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>Schedule &apos;B&apos; attached to this Order and as mentioned<lb/> in the State Government Scheme, announced on 2nd<lb/> October, 1977 for construction of houses for Weaker<lb/> Sections of Society on surplus vacant land by the land<lb/> holder. The details of construction shall not be<lb/> inferior to those already mentioned in the<lb/> application. The actual construction and the quality<lb/> of construction, will be subject to the building<lb/> regulations of the local authorities, and subject to<lb/> such other conditions as may be imposed, by the<lb/> Collector of Thane, Town Planning Authority and the<lb/> B.M.R.D.A and other Statutory Regulation.<lb/> 4) to 6) ....<lb/> 7) The said persons shall not transfer the exempted<lb/> lands (with or without buildings thereon) or any part<lb/> thereof to any other persons, except for the purpose of<lb/> mortgage in favour of any financial institution,<lb/> specified in Subsection (1) of Section 19 of the said<lb/> Act, for raising finances for the purposes of<lb/> construction or any one of the tenements mentioned<lb/> above. Breach of this condition shall mean that the<lb/> exemption granted under this Order stands<lb/> withdrawn.<lb/> 8) &amp; 9) ....<lb/> 10) The construction work under the scheme, will be<lb/> further subject to all other conditions incorporated in<lb/> the Scheme of Weaker Section Housing announced by<lb/> the State Government on 2nd October, 1977 and<lb/> subject to such other conditions as may be imposed by<lb/> the local authorities, Collector of Thane, Town<lb/> Planning Authorities and the B.M.R.D</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>. The<lb/> Government of Maharashtra by the Resolution No.<lb/> WLC1090/3422 (D XIII) in the Housing and<lb/> Special Assistance Department have laid down the<lb/> guidelines. We shall refer to the preamble and some of<lb/> the provisions thereof. The preamble indicates:<lb/> &quot;Close and effective monitoring of the<lb/> implementation of weaker sections housing schemes<lb/> sanctioned under Sections 20 and 21 of the Urban<lb/> Land (Ceiling &amp; Regulation) Act, 1976, is one of the<lb/> most important duties of the competent authorities<lb/> who have been entrusted with the task of<lb/> implementing the Urban Land Ceiling Act, 1976, in<lb/> the nine urban agglomerations in Maharashtra, viz.<lb/> Bombay, Pune, Thane, Ulhasnagar, Kolhapur,<lb/> Solapur, Sangli, Nasik and Nagpur. Competent<lb/> authorities are required to ensure that construction of<lb/> flats for the weaker sections of the society on land<lb/> exempted under Sections 20 and 21 is completed<lb/> within the timeframe stipulated in the exemption<lb/> order. They are also required to ensure that the terms<lb/> and conditions of the exemption order such as issue of<lb/> advertisements, giving particulars of the schemes, sale<lb/> of fiats at the prices approved by government, sizes of<lb/> flats, noneligibility of persons who already own a<lb/> dwelling unit in the same urban agglomeration to<lb/> purchase a flat from such schemes, handing over of<lb/> land affected by development plan, reservations to the<lb/> planning authority etc. are all complied with.<lb/> Physical implementation of Weaker sections housing<lb/> schemes in Maharashtra is one of the important<lb/> issues on the agenda at the meetings of competent<lb/> authorities convened by the Housing Department<lb/> periodically. General and special instructions<lb/> regarding effective monitoring of implementation of<lb/> the housing schemes are given to competent<lb/> authorities in such meetings. Government of<lb/> Maharashtra have carefully considered the<lb/> importance attaching to close and effective<lb/> monitoring of the implementation of weaker sections<lb/> housing schemes and is now pleased to direct by way<lb/> of codification of earlier instructions on the subject<lb/> that competent authorities should ensure that the<lb/> following instructions are scrupulously complied<lb/> with....</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>69<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>We have already referred to as to how the schemes devised<lb/> for the purposes of ensuring compliance with the exemption orders may<lb/> be at various stages of implementation. There are several conditions and<lb/> which may have been varied from time to time so as to achieve the object<lb/> of exemption. Since the exemption under clause (a) of subsection (1) of<lb/> Section 20 of the Principal Act is to be granted bearing in mind the<lb/> location of land, the purpose for which it is being used or proposed to be<lb/> used and such other relevant factors so also it is necessary and expedient<lb/> in public interest that the Government devised several schemes and<lb/> embodied in the circulars and Government Resolutions. Some of the<lb/> clauses in such schemes presented difficulties and which were resolved by<lb/> the Honourable Supreme Court. Now the schemes have become part of<lb/> the orders of the Honourable Supreme Court. These are not orders to the<lb/> contrary as envisaged by Section 3(1)(b) of the Repeal Act rather they are<lb/> in consonance with the power to exempt and carry it further. If such<lb/> orders are in place and the scheme is under various stages of<lb/> implementation, then, the repeal of the Principal Act will not in any<lb/> manner prevent the Government from enforcing the conditions and<lb/> ensuring compliance with the obligations undertaken by the Developers<lb/> and Builders.<lb/> 70<lb/> The arguments of the Petitioners to the contrary do not take<lb/> note of any of the above aspects. Even if one proceeds on the footing that<lb/> the intent of the Parliament was not to save several other provisions, but<lb/> that does not mean that what is saved by the Repeal Act or what will not<lb/> be affected by repeal of the Principal Act is exhaustive. Mr.Naphade places<lb/> reliance upon Sections 21 and 22 of the Principal Act and submits that<lb/> these provisions have not been saved, but his argument overlooks the fact</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>mean not only things done but also the legal<lb/> consequences flowing therefrom. If the interpretation<lb/> suggested by the learned Counsel for the respondents<lb/> be accepted, the saving clause would become<lb/> unnecessary. If what it saves is only the executed<lb/> contracts i.e. the contracts whereunder the goods have<lb/> been imported and received by the buyer before the<lb/> merger, no further protection is necessary as<lb/> ordinarily no question of enforcement of the contracts<lb/> under the preexisting law would arise. The<lb/> phraseology used is not an innovation but is copied<lb/> from other statutory clauses. Section 6 of the General<lb/> clauses Act (10 of 1897) says that unless a different<lb/> intention appears, the repeal of an Act shall not affect<lb/> anything duly done or suffered thereunder....&quot;<lb/> 117. Thus, a liberal and extensive construction was given<lb/> by this Court.<lb/> 118. To the same effect is also a decision of this Court in<lb/> Shri Ram Prasad (supra) wherein power to make rule<lb/> was held to be a thing done within the meaning of<lb/> Article 357(2) of the Constitution of India.<lb/> 119. In Harnek Singh (supra), this Court held:<lb/> &quot;16. The words anything duly done or suffered<lb/> thereunder used in Clause (b) of Section 6 are often<lb/> used by the legislature in saving clause which is<lb/> intended to provide that unless a different intention<lb/> appears, the repeal of an Act would not affect<lb/> anything duly done or suffered thereunder. This Court<lb/> in Hasan Nurani Malak v. S.M. Ismail, Asstt. Charity<lb/> Commr., Nagpur has held that the object of such a<lb/> saving clause is to save what has been previously done<lb/> under the statute repealed. The result of such a saving<lb/> clause is that the preexisting law continues to govern<lb/> the things done before a particular date from which<lb/> the repeal of such a preexisting law takes effect. In<lb/> Universal Imports Agency v. Chief Controller of<lb/> Imports and Exports this Court while construing the<lb/> words things done held that a proper interpretation<lb/> of the expression things done was comprehensive<lb/> enough to take in not only the things done but also<lb/> the effect of the legal consequence flowing therefrom.&quot;<lb/> 120. Furthermore, exemption from payment of tax in<lb/> favour of the appellants herein would also constitute<lb/> a right or privilege. The expression &quot;privilege&quot; has a<lb/> wider meaning than right. A right may be a vested<lb/> right or an accrued right or an acquired right. Nature<lb/> of such a right would depend upon and also vary<lb/> from statute to statute. It has been so held by this<lb/> Court, while construing Section 6 of the General<lb/> Clauses Act, in M/s Gurcharan Singh Baldev Singh v.<lb/> Yashwant Singh and Ors. [(1992) 1 SCC 428] in the<lb/> following terms:<lb/> &quot;...The objective of the provision is to ensure<lb/> protection of any right or privilege acquired under the<lb/> repealed Act. The only exception to it is legislative<lb/> intention to the contrary. That is, the repealing Act<lb/> may expressly provide or it may impliedly provide<lb/> against continuance of such right, obligation or<lb/> liability....&quot;&quot;<lb/> 73<lb/> Hence, Section 20(1) of the Principal Act and Section 3(1)(b)<lb/> and (c) of the Repeal Act have to be read together and harmoneously.<lb/> That would also save and protect the right of person to move under<lb/> Sections 11 to 14 of the Principal Act. That is why there is a proviso<lb/> which has been inserted in Section 4 of the Repeal Act. Equally, by clause<lb/> (c) of subsection (1) of Section 3 of the Repeal Act the intent was also to<lb/> allow the State Government to retain the money/sum paid to it as<lb/> condition for granting exemption under Section 20(1). All this shows that<lb/> the excess vacant land continues to be subject to the Principal Act and its<lb/> repeal does not affect applicability of the provisions of ChapterIII albeit<lb/> to a limited extent with which we are concerned. The intent is not to<lb/> allow recourse to Sections 21 and 22 of the Principal Act and that is<lb/> clearly affected by the repeal of the Principal Act. However, a saving<lb/> clause enacted in the Repeal Act and construed as above does not<lb/> manifest an intent to destroy all rights and obligations. Therefore, Section<lb/> 6 of the General Clauses Act, 1897 can be taken assistance of.<lb/> 74<lb/> While construing a repeal clause or Repeal Act or saving<lb/> clause therein the application of Section 6 of the General Clauses Act<lb/> would have to be considered in the light of the afore laid down principles.<lb/> Therefore, if having found that when the order of exemption is passed, it<lb/> is in force and conditional, then, the right or privilege created thereunder<lb/> cannot partake a different character. It would then fall squarely within<lb/> Section 6 of the General Clauses Act and in the present case we have not<lb/> found a contrary intention.<lb/> 75<lb/> We find that reliance placed by the learned Advocate General<lb/> on the decision in the case of Bansidhar (supra) is apposite. There, the<lb/> Honourable Supreme Court held that a saving provision in the repealing<lb/> statute is not exhaustive of the rights and obligations so saved and they<lb/> survive the repeal.<lb/> 76<lb/> In Bansidhar&apos;s case (supra) the contentions of the Appellants<lb/> before the Supreme Court were regarding the legality of certain<lb/> proceedings for fixation of ceiling on agricultural holdings initiated and<lb/> continued under the provisions of Chapter IIIB of the Rajasthan Tenancy<lb/> Act, 1955. That Act particularly Section 5(6A) and Chapter IIIB<lb/> thereunder was repealed by the Rajasthan Imposition of Ceiling on<lb/> Agricultural Holdings Act, 1973 (11 of 1973). The question was whether<lb/> the proceedings under the 1955 Act survive the repeal and reenactment<lb/> of the same in 1973. In that regard the Honourable Supreme Court held<lb/> as under:<lb/> &quot;3.<lb/> Chapter IIIB, pertaining to imposition of ceiling on<lb/> agricultural holdings, in the State of Rajasthan, was<lb/> introduced into the &apos;1955 Act&apos; by the Rajasthan<lb/> Tenancy (Amendment) Act, 1960. As a sequential<lb/> necessity Section was amended by the introduction in<lb/> it of Clause (6A) which defined &quot;ceilingarea&quot;. The<lb/> notifieddate, as originally fixed, was 1.4.1965; but<lb/> owing to the uncertainties imparted to the<lb/> implementation of the law by the challenged made to<lb/> the provisions of Chapter IIIB before the High Court<lb/> and the interimorders of the High Court staying the<lb/> operation of the law, Government had had to re<lb/> notify 1.4.1966 as the fresh notifieddate, after the<lb/> challenge to the validity of Chapter IIIB had been<lb/> repelled by the High Court.<lb/> 4.<lb/> By the time, the &apos;1973 Act&apos; was brought into force<lb/> disputes touching the determination of the ceiling<lb/> areas in 33, 471 cases had come to be decided in<lb/> accordance with the provisions of Chapter IIIB of the<lb/> earlier &apos;1955 Act&apos;. After the &apos;1973 Act&apos; came into force<lb/> on 1.1.1973, some 8,494 cases for the determination<lb/> of &apos;ceilingareas&apos; under IIIB of the &apos;1955 Act. came to<lb/> be initiated and were sought to be continued under<lb/> said Chapter IIIB of the repealed &apos;1955 Act&apos; on the<lb/> view that the repeal of Chapter IIIB of the 1955 Act<lb/> by the &apos;1973 Act&apos; did not affect the rights accrued and<lb/> liabilities incurred under the old law. Appellants&apos;<lb/> principal contention is that after the coming into<lb/> force of the 1973 Act which, by its 40th Section,<lb/> repealed Chapter IIIB of the &apos;1955 Act&apos;, recourse<lb/> could not be had to the repealedlaw for purposes of<lb/> commencement, conduct and conclusion of any<lb/> proceedings for fixation of ceiling as prescribed under<lb/> the old law. This contention has been repelled by the<lb/> full bench of the High Court in the judgment under<lb/> appeal. The correctness of view of the full bench arises<lb/> for consideration in these appeals.<lb/> 5.<lb/> The factual antecedents in which the controversy<lb/> arose before the High Court may be illustrated by the<lb/> facts of one of the appeals. In CA 1003 [N] of 1977,<lb/> the appellants&apos; claim to have entered into possession<lb/> and cultivation of certain parcels of land pursuant to<lb/> alleged agreements to sell dated 28.4.1957 said to<lb/> have been executed in their favour by the then land<lb/> holder, a certain Sri Had Singh. The sale deeds were<lb/> passed only on 22,8.1966, after the notified date.<lb/> Proceedings for the fixation of ceiling area in the<lb/> hands of Sri Hari Singh were commenced under the<lb/> Repealed Chapter IIIB of the &apos;1955 Act&apos;. Appellants&apos;<lb/> purchases were held to be hit by Section DD of the<lb/> said Chapter IIIB, which prescribed certain<lb/> residential qualifications, which appellants did not<lb/> possess, for the eligibility for recognition of such<lb/> transfers. Appellants&apos; contention is that if the new law<lb/> had been applied to the case of the vendor, the<lb/> transfers in their favour would have been held valid<lb/> and that &apos;invoking of Chapter IIIB of the repealed<lb/> law was impermissible. Apart from the facts of<lb/> individual cases and their particularities the basic<lb/> question is one of construction whether the<lb/> provisions of the old law are saved and survive to<lb/> govern pending cases.<lb/> 6.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>(a) &quot;family&quot; shall mean a family consisting of a<lb/> husband and wife their children and grandchildren<lb/> being dependent on them and the widowed mother of<lb/> the husband so dependent and<lb/> (b) &quot;person&quot; in the case of an individual, shall<lb/> include the family of such individual.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>It was<lb/> pointed out that material criteria relevant to the<lb/> effectuation of the newpolicy made manifest an<lb/> intention contrary to the survival of the policy under<lb/> the old law. The wide changes in the policy of the<lb/> later law which reflected a new and basically different<lb/> approach to the matter, included [i] a fundamental<lb/> rethinking on the concept of the &quot;ceilingarea&quot; by<lb/> reducing the 30 standard acres prescribed in the old<lb/> law to 18 standard acres; [ii] the redefinition of the<lb/> very concept of &apos;family&apos; and &apos;separate unit&apos;; [iii] the<lb/> point of time with reference to which the composition<lb/> and strength of the family would require to be<lb/> ascertained; [vi] a rethinking, and a fresh policy as<lb/> to the recognition of transfers made by landholders<lb/> including even those transfers made during the period<lb/> of operation of the old law; [v] the point of time of<lb/> the vesting of the surplus land in Government; [vi]<lb/> the redefining of the principles and priorities guiding<lb/> the distribution of the surplus land to landless<lb/> persons; and [vii] the amount to be paid to the land<lb/> holders for the excess land vesting in the State under<lb/> the new law.<lb/> 20.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>80<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>We are of the clear opinion that clauses (b) and (c) of Section<lb/> 6 of the General Clauses Act are thus, clearly attracted. Therefore, the<lb/> repeal will not affect the previous operation of the Principal Act or<lb/> anything duly done or suffered thereunder.<lb/> 81<lb/> In that regard, assistance can be taken of the judgment of the<lb/> Honourable Supreme Court in the case of M/s Universal Imports Agency<lb/> v/s Chief Controller of Imports and Exports reported in AIR 1961 SC 41.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            *129*<lb/> FULL.BENCH.JUDGMENT.sxw</content>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>limit on the date of commencement of the Act is subject to ChapterIII of<lb/> the Principal Act and its application thereto is undisputed. If such<lb/> undisputed absolute application is the position emerging from the statute<lb/> and because of an exceptional circumstance the applicability is held in<lb/> abeyance, then, it is not open to those persons holding such lands to<lb/> contend that the Principal Act has been repealed, therefore, it&apos;s<lb/> applicability to the lands in question will not survive the repeal. If as<lb/> contended by the learned Advocate General the exemption keeps in<lb/> abeyance the applicability of ChapterIII till such exemption order is in<lb/> force and does not rule out the applicability of the Principal Act, then, we<lb/> cannot accept the arguments of the learned Senior Counsel for the<lb/> Petitioners to the contrary. Realizing this position, Mr.Naphade and other<lb/> Senior Counsel toned down their submissions to some extent. They urged<lb/> that Section 10 of the Principal Act is the heart of the Principal Act and<lb/> once the consequences of subsection (3) of Section 10 of the Principal<lb/> Act cannot be visited on the Petitioners after repeal of the Principal Act,<lb/> then, a contrary intention is manifested. If we hold that such contrary<lb/> intention is not manifested and Section 6 of the General Clauses Act<lb/> applies to the repeal in question, then, that would result in inconsistency<lb/> and absurdity. This argument is premised on the fact that subsection (2)<lb/> of Section 20 of the Principal Act is not saved and that is not specifically<lb/> referred in clause (b) of subsection (1) of Section 3 of the Repeal Act and<lb/> hence, the above result will follow.<lb/> 90<lb/> For the reasons that we have set out hereinabove it will not<lb/> be possible to accept any of these contentions. Firstly, as understood in<lb/> the case of clause (a) of Section 20(1) of the Principal Act the exemption<lb/> is granted qua the excess vacant land and bearing in mind the factors and<lb/> circumstances indicated therein. Secondly, it is an exemption granted in<lb/> public interest and to subserve it. Thirdly, even if the exemption is<lb/> granted under clause (b) of Section 20(1) that is to relieve the undue<lb/> hardship. Under both clauses the exemption order could be conditional. If<lb/> the validity of the exemption order together with the conditions is saved<lb/> and equally any action taken thereunder, then, it will not be proper to<lb/> hold that the exemption order and conditions therein cannot be enforced<lb/> by recourse to the Principal Act. That is because if the exemption is a right<lb/> as is claimed, then, it is conditional. It is a right accrued, but the<lb/> conditions subject to which that right accrues cannot be ignored. Those<lb/> conditions are linked to the right and privilege acquired or accrued. If<lb/> that condition is in the nature of obligation or liability attached to the<lb/> privilege or right, then, a different intention not being spelled out that is<lb/> saved despite the repeal. The reasons, therefore, indicated above would<lb/> take care of these submissions of the learned Senior Counsel appearing<lb/> for the Petitioners and are enough to reject them.<lb/> 91<lb/> If an intention was to the contrary as urged by the learned<lb/> Senior Counsel for the Petitioners, then, there was no need for the<lb/> Parliament to have save the validity of any exemption order under sub<lb/> section (1) of Section 20 of the Principal Act or any action taken<lb/> thereunder and declare the same to be not affected by repeal of the<lb/> Principal Act notwithstanding any judgment of any court to the contrary.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>) of<lb/> Section 1 of the Repeal Act by the States other than the States of Haryana<lb/> and Punjab. He relied upon Article 252 of the Constitution of India and<lb/> particularly clause (2) thereof.<lb/> 93<lb/> We are unable to accept his contentions and for obvious<lb/> reasons. Article 252 of the Constitution of India confers power in the<lb/> Parliament to legislate for two or more States by consent and adoption of<lb/> such legislation by any other State. Clause (2) thereof states that any Act<lb/> passed by the Parliament may be amended or repealed by an Act of<lb/> Parliament passed or adopted in like manner, namely, as set out in clause<lb/> (1) of Article 252 of the Constitution of India by any State to which it<lb/> applies, but the State Legislature of that State cannot amend or repeal<lb/> any Act of the Parliament on its own. That it has to adopt it by resolution<lb/> passed in that behalf is clear by clause (1) of Article 252. However, we do<lb/> not find anything in the language of Section 6 of the General Clauses Act<lb/> which would enable us to hold that the same does not apply in the<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:40 :::<lb/> *136*<lb/> situation with which </content>
 
            <figDesc>we are concerned. It will have to be clarified that the<lb/> Principal Act in the case is the Central Act. It has been made after<lb/> commencement of the General Clauses Act, 1897. Equally, the Repeal Act<lb/> is an Act of Parliament made after the General Clauses Act. Just as the<lb/> Principal Act had the section of applicability and applied at once to some</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>95<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>In that regard, reliance placed by the learned Advocate<lb/> General on the judgment of the Division Bench of the Madhya Pradesh<lb/> High Court reported in AIR 1979 Madhya Pradesh 108 (Rajendra Kumar<lb/> v/s State of Madhya Pradesh) is appropriate. In paragraph 7 of this<lb/> decision the Division Bench clarified the legal position that when the<lb/> Parliament passes an Act with the consent of States the Act so passed<lb/> cannot be classified as a State Act. Further, the Division Bench clarified<lb/> the legal position in the context of Article 252 of the Constitution of India<lb/> as well. (See paras 4 and 8). Mr.Sridharan&apos;s arguments overlook the fact<lb/> that the Repeal Act has merely been adopted by the State of Maharashtra<lb/> by passing a resolution by the Legislature of that State and therefore, it is<lb/> not the resolution of the State Assembly with regard to which we are<lb/> looking at the applicability of Section 6 of the General Clauses Act.<lb/> Mr.Sridharan, therefore, rightly canvassed alternate arguments and which<lb/> are more or less on the same lines as that of Mr.Naphade and other Senior<lb/> Counsel. Additionally, Mr.Sridharan submitted that Section 3 of the<lb/> Repeal Act and particularly clause (b) of subsection (1) thereof is a<lb/> special saving and saves only that which is specifically mentioned. There<lb/> is no room for any implication or reading into it something which is not<lb/> specifically mentioned therein. It is his argument that it is not a validating<lb/> statute or clause. It saves a subordinate legislation according to him.<lb/> 96<lb/> None of these arguments are sound in law. We are concerned<lb/> with Section 3 of the Repeal Act which is titled &quot;saving&quot;, but subsection<lb/> (1) thereof states that the repeal of the Principal Act shall not affect and<lb/> what it is not affected thereby is set out in clauses (a), (b) and (c) of sub<lb/> section (1) of Section 3. By clause (a) the repeal will not affect the vesting<lb/> of any vacant land under Section 10(3), possession of which has been<lb/> taken over by the State Government. If the intention was to obliterate and<lb/> wipe out everything, then, there was no need to insert clause (a) as well.<lb/> Clause (a) has been inserted so as to save the vesting of the land under<lb/> Section 10(3) and which is in possession of the State Government. The<lb/> Legislature was aware that in the light of the repeal of the Principal Act it<lb/> would be necessary to save the vesting inasmuch as subsection (3) of<lb/> Section 10 of the Principal Act itself speaks of vesting of the excess vacant<lb/> land in the State absolutely free from all encumbrances upon its deemed<lb/> acquisition. That deemed acquisition results after a declaration is<lb/> published in the official Gazette in terms of Section 10(3). The Parliament<lb/> stepped into to save only such vesting which has resulted in the land<lb/> being taken over by the State Government and not otherwise. By a mere<lb/> declaration in terms of Section 10(3) the vesting which otherwise takes<lb/> place would not be saved if in pursuance thereof the land is not taken<lb/> over by the State. Therefore, it is incorrect to urge that Section 3 of the<lb/> Repeal Act saves a subordinate legislation. Clause (a) of subsection (1) of<lb/> Section 3 of the Repeal Act is a substantive provision and the repeal<lb/> clearly affects the vesting of land of which possession has not been taken<lb/> because by subsection (2) of Section 3 such land can be restored. Hence,<lb/> a situation where there is a declaration issued and contained in the<lb/> notification contemplated by Section 10(3) of the Principal Act, but the<lb/> State failed to act in pursuance thereof and has not exercised it&apos;s power<lb/> under subsections (5) and (6) of Section 10 of the Principal Act, is dealt<lb/> with by Section 3(1)(a) of the Repeal Act. By clause (b) a substantive<lb/> provision has been made and to deal with a different situation, namely,<lb/> the excess vacant land and which may or may not be covered by<lb/> declaration under Section 10(3), but which is exempted in exercise of the<lb/> statutory power conferred vide Section 20(1) of the Principal Act. It is the<lb/> exercise of that power to exempt and all consequences which follow a<lb/> valid exemption order that are saved by clause (b). This is as set out<lb/> above not only saving the validity of order granting exemption, but any<lb/> action taken thereunder and notwithstanding anything in any judgment<lb/> of any court to the contrary. One more aspect or matter is dealt with by<lb/> clause (c) of subsection (1) of Section 3 of the Repeal Act inasmuch as if<lb/> for granting exemption under Section 20(1) of the Principal Act there is a<lb/> condition to make payment to the State Government and if the payment<lb/> is made in compliance thereof, then, that payment made to the State<lb/> Government is also saved. Therefore, on reading Sections 3 and 4 of the<lb/> Repeal Act it is not possible to accept the arguments of Mr.Sridharan that<lb/> only a subordinate legislation is saved either by Repeal Act or Section 3.<lb/> Had it not been so Mr.Sridharan would not have further alternatively<lb/> argued and adopted the contentions of Mr.Naphade and others that the<lb/> power to withdraw the exemption or initiate an action under Section<lb/> 20(2) of the Principal Act is not saved or does not survive the repeal.<lb/> 97<lb/> We have already dealt with that argument and rejected it for<lb/> the reasons set out above. A faint attempt was made by Mr.Sridharan to<lb/> show that clause (b) has been inserted in subsection (1) of Section 3 of<lb/> the Repeal Act to protect the rights of innocent third parties or action<lb/> under the exemption orders which may affect them. It is not a substantive<lb/> provision and by no stretch of imagination revives the Principal Act is his<lb/> argument. We fail to see as to how in the absence of clause (b) a power of<lb/> exemption once exercised and when the Principal Act was in force, but<lb/> that order or any action taken thereunder being declared invalid that<lb/> could have survived the repeal even with the aid of Section 6 of the<lb/> General Clauses Act, 1897. In other words, it could have been argued that<lb/> not only there should be a power of exemption exercised, but the order in<lb/> that behalf or any action taken thereunder should have been valid, lawful<lb/> and subsisting on the date of the Repeal Act or at least when it came into<lb/> force. It could have been then said that only in such a situation that the<lb/> order would survive the repeal even without insertion of clause (b) in<lb/> subsection (1) of Section 3 of the Repeal Act with the aid of Section 6 of<lb/> the General Clauses Act. To get over this situation and position a<lb/> substantive provision has been made in the Repeal Act which says that the<lb/> repeal of the Principal Act shall not affect the validity of any order<lb/> granting exemption under Section 20(1) of the Principal Act or any action<lb/> taken thereunder notwithstanding any judgment of any court to the<lb/> contrary. This is a substantive provision and read together with other<lb/> clauses of subsections (1) and (2) of Section 3 and Section 4 of the<lb/> Repeal Act, so also, Section 6 of the General Clauses Act and<lb/> harmoniously does not revive the Principal Act as is urged, but saves the<lb/> exemption order in exercise of the powers conferred by the Principal Act<lb/> or any action taken thereunder by declaring it to be valid notwithstanding<lb/> any judgment of any court to the contrary. That would be the correct<lb/> reading of the provisions or else Mr.Sridharan would not have still further<lb/> argued that clause (c) of subsection (1) of Section 3 of the Repeal Act<lb/> does not save the liability incurred under the exemption order, but only<lb/> saves the payment made to the State Government. This further alternate<lb/> argument itself would show that Mr.Sridharan is not on a strong and<lb/> sound legal footing in urging that Section 3 of the Repeal Act is not a<lb/> substantive provision. That it is titled as &quot;savings&quot;, but contains the<lb/> substantive provisions which do not show any contrary intention to<lb/> applicability of Section 6 of the General Clauses Act is what is held by us<lb/> hereinabove. A correct and proper reading of clause (c) of Section 3(1) of<lb/> the Repeal Act would be that the Legislature had in mind a conditional<lb/> exemption order. One of the conditions could have been of making<lb/> payment to the State Government for granting exemption under Section<lb/> 20(1) of the Principal Act. If the power to exempt does not survive the<lb/> repeal, but the intent was to save the power to exempt already exercised<lb/> conditionally or otherwise that the Legislature stepped in to save even<lb/> payment made to the State Government for grant of such exemption. That<lb/> is because a beneficiary of the exercise of power of exemption should not,<lb/> post repeal of the Principal Act, urge that the State has no right to retain<lb/> the amount paid by him, but must refund it. That he has already made<lb/> payment and the power to exempt having been exercised when the<lb/> Principal Act was in force that it is clarified that the payment made to the<lb/> Government as a condition for granting exemption would survive the<lb/> Repeal. That is to take care of the plea that such payment will no longer<lb/> be valid as the exemption comes to an end post repeal. Therefore, in<lb/> order to declare that the power of exemption once exercised would<lb/> survive the repeal and equally the condition of payment thereunder that<lb/> clauses (b) and (c) have been inserted.<lb/> 98<lb/> We find that Mr.Sridharan is not right in placing reliance on<lb/> the judgments of the Honourable Supreme Court firstly in the case of Shri<lb/> Prithvi Cotton Mills Limited v/s Broach Borough Municipality reported in<lb/> 2000 (123) ELT page 3 (SC). There, the Honourable Supreme Court was<lb/> considering a case of the rate on the lands and buildings imposed under<lb/> the Bombay Municipal Boroughs Act, 1925. Certain Assessees challenged<lb/> the imposition of these rates and filed the Writ Petitions to question it and<lb/> get the assessment cancelled. During the pendency of the Writ Petitions<lb/> the Legislature of Gujarat passed the Gujarat Imposition of Taxes by<lb/> Municipalities (Validation) Act, 1963. The Writ Petitions were, therefore,<lb/> amended and the Validation Act was questioned. The Honourable<lb/> Supreme Court, therefore, was considering the validity and legality of</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>(a) and (b) of Section 20(1) of the Act. The<lb/> words &quot;or otherwise&quot; cannot be construed ejusdem<lb/> generis and are indicative of the fact that the power is<lb/> exercisable on being invoked in any other manner. The<lb/> natural corollary of this position of law is that the<lb/> petitioners have right to submit a petition invoking<lb/> the exercise of the power of exemption so conferred on<lb/> the State Government. This Legislative intendment is<lb/> also clear from the provision of courtfee on an<lb/> application for exemption of vacant land under<lb/> Section 20 of the Act made in Schedule as stated<lb/> above. The power to exempt by its very nature in cases<lb/> to which Clause (a) of Section 20(</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>)(a) of the Act it is<lb/> all the more necessary for the State Government to<lb/> hear the applicant. ........ When a citizen applies for<lb/> exemption say for example, for establishing any<lb/> industry and such proposed future user of the land is<lb/> one of the relevant factors to be counted while dealing<lb/> with an application under S. 20(1)(a) of the Act, the<lb/> citizen in such a situation would be able to explain his<lb/> difficulties more effectively if personal hearing is<lb/> granted. It is because of this far reaching effect of the<lb/> Governments decision on his prospects that we say<lb/> that the hearing is required to be read as the implicit<lb/> requirement of the provisions of the S. 20(1)(a)(b) of<lb/> the Act.<lb/> 5.<lb/> It is no doubt true that the judgment of the Madhya<lb/> Pradesh High Court was one relating to an<lb/> application for exemption under sub cl (b) of sub s.<lb/> (2) of S. 20 of the Act but the underlying principles<lb/> remain the same. As a matter of fact some petitions in<lb/> this group are the petitions for exemption under S.<lb/> 20(1)(b) itself. To our mind the underlying principles<lb/> remain the same when the Government has to<lb/> consider an application for exemption either under Cl<lb/> (a) or Cl (b) of sub s. (</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>107<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>The judgments that have been cited by Mr.Naphade must<lb/> now be noted. He strenuously urged that he is supported in his argument<lb/> by the judgment of the learned Single Judge of Andhra Pradesh High<lb/> Court in Writ Petition No.26474 of 2009 (Surendra Raj Jaiswal v/s<lb/> Government of Andhra Pradesh) decided on 24.08.2011. There, the Writ<lb/> Petition was filed challenging the rejection by the Government of the<lb/> claim of the Petitioners and permission sought by them to construct a<lb/> multiplex theatrecumshopping complex in the place of existing cinema<lb/> theatre. It was their case that they had filed declaration declaring various<lb/> extents of land held by them along with their father on the<lb/> commencement of the Principal Act. They also filed an application before<lb/> the Government seeking exemption from ChapterIII of the Principal Act<lb/> so as to run an existing cinema theatre on their property called Deepak<lb/> Mahal Cinema situate at Narayanguda in Hyderabad Urban<lb/> Agglomeration. The order of exemption was passed and with a condition<lb/> that the said land should be utilized only for running a cinema theatre<lb/> and subject to further conditions which are incorporated in the order of<lb/> exemption. It was by virtue of exemption order that cinema theatre was<lb/> being run. Thereafter, the Principal Act was repealed in the State of<lb/> Andhra Pradesh after adoption of the Repeal Act with effect from<lb/> 27.03.2008. It is in these circumstances that the Petitioners argued that<lb/> they are entitled to use the property for construction of Multiplex Theatre<lb/> cum shopping complex. We find that from paragraphs 2 to 6 the facts<lb/> are noted. Thereafter, in paragraph 8 reference is made to the Principal<lb/> Act and the power to exempt. Then in paragraph 9 reference is made to<lb/> the Repeal Act. In paragraphs 10 and 11 the learned Single Judge held as<lb/> under:<lb/> &quot;10.<lb/> From a perusal of the aforesaid provisions under<lb/> Sections 3 and 4 of the Urban Land (Ceiling and<lb/> Regulation) Repeal Act of 1999, it is clear that the<lb/> orders granting exemption under subsection (1) of<lb/> Section 20 of the principal Act are saved. It is also<lb/> clear from a perusal of the provision under Section<lb/> 3(1)(c) of the Repealing Act that repeal of the<lb/> principal Act shall not affect any payments made to<lb/> the State Government as a condition for granting<lb/> exemption under subsection (1) of Section 20 of the<lb/> principal Act. But, at the same time, the provision<lb/> under subsection (2) of Section 20 is not saved.<lb/> Section 20(1) of the principal Act empowers the<lb/> Government to exempt any land subject to certain<lb/> conditions, but under subsection (2) of Section 20 of<lb/> the principal Act, the Government was empowered to<lb/> withdraw such exemption in cases where conditions<lb/> are violated. A harmonious reading of the provisions<lb/> under Sections 20(1) and 20</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>108<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>We do not see how firstly in the teeth of the factual position<lb/> where apart from the controversy with regard to survival of the order of<lb/> exemption and conditions thereunder post repeal, could the permission to<lb/> construct a multiplex theatrecumshopping complex in place of the<lb/> existing cinema theatre have been refused by the State Government. The<lb/> user was more or less similar with the original one. Apart therefrom the<lb/> learned Single Judge of Andhra Pradesh has not referred to any of the<lb/> judgments of the Honourable Supreme Court on the point and<lb/> particularly the decision in the case of Bansidhar (supra). The learned<lb/> Single Judge&apos;s attention was not invited to several aspects of the<lb/> controversy and which we have extensively noted above. The learned<lb/> Single Judge, therefore, with greatest respect, was not right in holding<lb/> that in the absence of any reference to subsection (2) of Section 20 of the<lb/> Principal Act in clause (b) of subsection (1) of Section 3 of the Repeal<lb/> Act the conditions imposed in the order granting exemption do not<lb/> continue to operate. We do not find any reference made to Section 6 of<lb/> the General Clauses Act either. With greatest respect, we are unable to<lb/> agree with the view taken by the learned Single Judge of Andhra Pradesh<lb/> High Court in the decision referred above.<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:40 :::<lb/> *155*<lb/> FULL.BENCH.JUDGMENT.sxw<lb/> 109<lb/> While on this </content>
 
            <figDesc>point we also do not agree with Mr.Gangal<lb/> when he relies on the view taken by another Single Judge of Madras High<lb/> Court in Writ Petition No.46091 of 2002 and W.P.M.P. No.30655 of<lb/> 2004 decided on 29.01.2007 (L.Kannappan and L. Thirunavukarasu v/s<lb/> The Government of Tamil Nadu). There, the arguments were with regard<lb/> to acquisition of agricultural lands. Therein the Petitioners represented by<lb/> their father purchased the agricultural lands. After the property was<lb/> purchased the same was cultivated. The land was always agricultural<lb/> land. In relation to such an agricultural land the proceedings under the<lb/> Tamil Nadu Urban Land (Ceiling and Regulation) Act, 1978 were initiated<lb/> and were sought to be continued. The Petitioners sought to make<lb/> payment for obtaining extract from the records of right at which point of<lb/> time it was informed that the lands have been acquired in the name of<lb/> Dr.N.Sivasamy. In these circumstances and by holding that the acquisition<lb/> under the said Ceiling Act when it was in force itself was invalid that the<lb/> Writ Petition was allowed. Apart therefrom it was urged that since the<lb/> Petitioners are in possession and enjoyment of the lands as reflected in<lb/> the revenue records and possession was not taken from them the<lb/> proceedings in that regard abate by virtue of the Repeal Act. This decision<lb/> more or less is on applicability of Section 3(1)(a) of the Repeal Act and<lb/> not an authority on the point in the present case. It is, therefore, clearly<lb/> distinguishable.<lb/> 110<lb/> Mr.Naphade&apos;s reliance upon a judgment of the Delhi High<lb/> Court in the case of Tej Pratap Singh v/s Union of India in Writ Petition<lb/> (Civil) No.2455/1992 decided on 16.07.2009 must now be noted.<lb/> There, a Division Bench of the Delhi High Court had before it a situation<lb/> where the exemption was granted in terms of Section 20(1)(a) and<lb/> Section 22 of the Principal Act on 02.07.1992 subject to the condition<lb/> that the Petitioners before the Delhi High Court would make payment of<lb/> Rs.18,37,74,528/ to the Land &amp; Building Department, Delhi<lb/> Administration within 45 days. Aggrieved and dissatisfied with this<lb/> condition the Writ Petition was filed in the Delhi High Court in 1992 itself<lb/> which was styled as Writ Petition (Civil) No.2455/1992. During the<lb/> pendency thereof the Repeal Act came into force. The facts have been<lb/> noted and particularly that the Petitioner was pursuing his claim for<lb/> exemption for the purpose of redevelopment of the property. He rather<lb/> invited a decision from the Authorities on his application. That was<lb/> because his building plans were not sanctioned. A Division Bench of Delhi<lb/> High Court passed the interim order in another Civil Writ Petition which<lb/> is referred to in paragraph 4 of the judgment. That interim order was<lb/> challenged before the Honourable Supreme Court and the Honourable<lb/> Supreme Court passed an order directing the competent authority under<lb/> the Principal Act to decide the Petitioner&apos;s application. That is how the<lb/> order impugned in the subject Writ Petition was passed. The earlier Writ<lb/> Petition was disposed of as infructuous in the light of the Repeal Act being<lb/> brought into force.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>13.<lb/> This takes us to the consideration of the Savings Clause<lb/> provided in Section 3 of the Repealing Act. Section 3 (1)<lb/> (a) clearly stipulates that the repeal of the ULCR Act<lb/> shall not affect the vesting of any vacant land under sub<lb/> section (3) of Section 10, possession of which has been<lb/> taken over by the State Government or any person duly<lb/> authorized by the State Government in this behalf or by<lb/> the competent authority. We have noted above that the<lb/> possession of the property in question is still with the<lb/> petitioners and, therefore, this Clause is clearly<lb/> inapplicable. Section 3 (1) (b) stipulates that the repeal<lb/> shall not affect the validity of any order granting<lb/> exemption under subsection (1) of Section 20 or any<lb/> action taken thereunder, notwithstanding any judgment<lb/> of any court to the contrary. Section 3 (1) (c) provides<lb/> that the repeal shall not affect any payment made to the<lb/> State Government as a condition for granting exemption<lb/> under sub section (1) of Section 20. Reading sub<lb/> sections 3 (1) (a), (b) and (</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>intitle of M/s Tata Coffee. Thereafter, the successor M/s Tata Coffee<lb/> sought permission/ no objection certificate from the Joint Collector,<lb/> Ranga Reddy district for utilization of the subject land for the purpose of<lb/> development of housing scheme including providing of shelter to the<lb/> weaker sections of the society. The Collector informed that the NOC<lb/> cannot be granted unless the State Government accorded permission.<lb/> That is how the representation was made to the State Government and<lb/> which was rejected. For the reasons that we have recorded above, with<lb/> greatest respect, we are unable to agree with the view taken by the<lb/> learned Single Judge of Andhra Pradesh High Court.<lb/> 116<lb/> Mr.Naphade then placed reliance on the judgment of the<lb/> Honourable Supreme Court in Synco Industries Limited v/s Assessing<lb/> Officer, Income Tax, Mumbai reported in (2008) 4 SCC 22 wherein in the<lb/> context of interpretation placed on the Income Tax Act and some of it&apos;s<lb/> provisions, the Honourable Supreme Court held that where the<lb/> predominant majority of High Courts have taken a particular view of the<lb/> legal provision and interpreted it, the Supreme Court would lean in<lb/> favour of this predominant view, but exceptions to this principle are also<lb/> set out. Once we have set out the reasons for disagreeing with the views<lb/> taken by other High Courts, we do not see how this principle can be of<lb/> any assistance.<lb/> 117<lb/> For the reasons that we have recorded above we do not find<lb/> that the judgments relied upon by Mr.Naphade carry his submissions any<lb/> further.<lb/> 118<lb/> Now we are left with reliance placed by Mr.Naphade,<lb/> Mr.Sathe and Mr.Devitre on the judgments of this Court.<lb/> 119<lb/> Before that we would refer to some of the judgments which<lb/> have been relied upon by the learned Advocate General. Apart from<lb/> Bansidhar (supra) and the State of Punjab v/s Mohar Singh Pratap Singh<lb/> reported in AIR 1955 SC 84, the learned Advocate General relied upon<lb/> the judgment of the Honourable Supreme Court in the case of Her<lb/> Highness Maharani Shantidevi P. Gaikwad vs. Savjibhai Haribhai Patel and<lb/> Others reported in (2001) 5 SCC 101. We at once clarify that for our<lb/> purposes we are not required to decide as to whether the judgment of the<lb/> Honourable Supreme Court in the case of Smt.Atia Mohammadi Begum<lb/> v/s State of U.P. (supra) stands overruled and to what extent. What we</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>124<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>Reliance has been further placed on the judgment in the case<lb/> of Voltas Limited v/s Additional Collector &amp; Competent Authority reported<lb/> in 2008 (5) Bombay Cases Reporter 746. While it is true that the<lb/> judgment of the Honourable Supreme Court in Bansidhar&apos;s case (supra)<lb/> was cited before the Division Bench deciding Voltas, but we do not find<lb/> any reference being made to the same. First of all this judgment is not<lb/> interpreting Section 3(1)(b) of the Repeal Act. It is a judgment and it<lb/> remains a judgment analyzing and interpreting Section 3(1)(a) of the<lb/> Repeal Act. Mr.Naphade heavily relies upon this judgment and to urge<lb/> that this judgment supports his submission that the only consequence<lb/> which would follow withdrawal of exemption order by exercising the<lb/> powers under Section 20(2) of the Principal Act is to apply ChapterIII of<lb/> the Principal Act and particularly the Section enabling vesting of the same<lb/> free from all encumbrances in the State of Maharashtra. His submission<lb/> presupposes that withdrawal is mandatory or that unless the exemption is<lb/> withdrawn the terms and conditions, if any, in the exemption order<lb/> cannot be enforced. We do not see how such absolute proposition<lb/> emerges from reading of the judgment in Voltas Limited (supra). If<lb/> paragraph 11 of this judgment is carefully perused the Division Bench<lb/> while analyzing Section 3(1)(a) of the Repeal Act, so also, Section 3(2)<lb/> thereof holds that the land owner will get back title of the land only on<lb/> payment of the amount that he has received under the Principal Act from<lb/> the Government. It is in these circumstances that we are of the opinion<lb/> that this judgment must be seen as confined to this part of the Repeal Act<lb/> and cannot, therefore, be said to be construing other provisions of the<lb/> Repeal Act. The observations in paragraph 12 of this judgment in the<lb/> context of Section 6 of the General Clauses Act must be also seen as being<lb/> made so as to reinforce the conclusion with regard to applicability of<lb/> Section 3(1)(a) of the Repeal Act.<lb/> 125<lb/> Then, there is reliance placed on the judgment in the case of<lb/> Vithabai Bama Bhandari v/s State of Maharashtra reported in 2009 (3)</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>20 and in accordance with which the construction permission was<lb/> granted, construction was commenced and was completed within the<lb/> time frame prescribed for the same. It appears that the Petitioner<lb/> requested the Government/ competent authority to take possession of the<lb/> flats meant for the Government nominees, but before any further steps<lb/> could be taken, the Petitioner was informed that the exemption granted<lb/> under Section 20 itself was withdrawn. The Petitioner was served with a<lb/> notice under Section 10(5) calling upon her to handover possession of<lb/> surplus land due to non compliance of the conditions of exemption under<lb/> Section 20 of the Principal Act. That notice was challenged in the petition.<lb/> That is how the Petitioner relied upon the Repeal Act and in order to<lb/> avoid the consequences which would flow from cancellation or<lb/> withdrawal of the exemption order. The discussion in paragraphs 42, 43,<lb/> 44, 45 and 46 of the judgment would reveal that the Division Bench was<lb/> only concerned with Section 3(1)(a) of the Repeal Act. Nothing else from<lb/> the Repeal Act has been noticed far from any larger controversy. In such<lb/> circumstances we do not think that this judgment is on the point and<lb/> particularly which has been referred to us. Apart therefrom what we find<lb/> is that the Division Bench did not allow the State to rely upon Section<lb/> 3(1)(a) of the Repeal Act because the exemption order had already been<lb/> withdrawn. The question of saving such an order and when the State<lb/> desired to take possession of the land despite repeal of the Principal Act<lb/> and in the teeth of Section 3(1)(a) thereof, therefore, rightly did not<lb/> arise. However, we find that the observations made by the Division Bench<lb/> in paragraphs 38 to 51 to the extent of applicability of Section 6 of the<lb/> General Clauses Act insofar as contrary to what we have held above, do<lb/> not lay down the correct law.<lb/> In the case of Mohan Gopalrao Mate v/s Principal Secretary<lb/> reported in 2009 (1) Bom.C.R. 275, once again it must be noted that the<lb/> Petitioner therein is an exMLA. He had challenged certain Government<lb/> Resolutions which impact large number of housing schemes and affect<lb/> large number of individual flat owners. That was in relation to handing<lb/> over and sale to the Government nominees at the prescribed or<lb/> predetermined rates for the Government quota flats. It was general<lb/> grievance and projected in public interest which was dealt with by the<lb/> Division Bench. Paragraphs 3, 4 and 5 of this judgment read as under:<lb/> &quot;3.<lb/> Counsel for the petitioner has further submitted that<lb/> the petitioner has filed the present petition in the<lb/> interest of Public as the Government Resolutions</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>12.4.2007 flouting the aforesaid orders passed by<lb/> this Court in Writ Petition No.4966 of 2006 and<lb/> therefore, the Govt Resolution dt. 12.4.2007 is liable<lb/> to be quashed and set aside.&quot;<lb/> 127<lb/> Thereafter, the arguments of the Petitioner have been noted<lb/> and which we find from paragraphs 8 to 21. From paragraph 22 onwards<lb/> the Additional Government Pleader&apos;s arguments have been noted and<lb/> from paragraph 37 onwards the rival contentions are analyzed. In<lb/> paragraphs 40 to 42 the necessity to enact the Principal Act and its<lb/> objectives have been discussed. Thereafter, reference is made to Sections<lb/> 20 and 21 of the Principal Act in paragraphs 43 to 46. In paragraph 47<lb/> the Division Bench held that if there was breach of or violation of the<lb/> terms and conditions of the Development Permission or Commencement<lb/> Certificate issued under the Planning Law, then, the Government cannot<lb/> cancel these permission/ sanction/ building permit in the garb of<lb/> exercising the powers to withdraw the exemption. That is how paragraphs<lb/> 47 and 48 would read. We do not find anything in paragraph 48 which<lb/> would enable us to hold that the Division Bench has decided any<lb/> controversy and which is subject matter of the present reference. The<lb/> whole issue was whether for breach of the terms and conditions on which<lb/> the order of exemption has been passed and one of which related to the<lb/> permission to construct or develop the land, can the State while<lb/> withdrawing the exemption under Section 20(1) also set aside or<lb/> interfere with the permission under the Maharashtra Regional Town<lb/> Planning Act, 1966 or related laws. Far from anything which would touch<lb/> the issues involved in the present Reference we do not think that this<lb/> judgment lays down or holds that the validity of the order of exemption<lb/> under Section 20 or any action taken thereunder would not survive with<lb/> all consequences despite the repeal.<lb/> 128<lb/> The only reference then made to the Repeal Act is to be<lb/> found in paragraphs 63 and 64. Paragraph 64 of the judgment reads as<lb/> under:</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>(</head>

            <label>2</label>

            <head>) </head>
 
            <figDesc>of Section 20 prior to coming into force of the<lb/> Repeal Act, is also saved. However, the power of the<lb/> State Government to alter, change or modify the terms<lb/> and conditions of any of the Schemes formulated prior<lb/> to coming into force of the Repeal Act and on the basis<lb/> thereof, sanction was granted by the Planning Authority<lb/> is not saved by the saving clause.&quot;<lb/> 129<lb/> We do not think that in the light of these conclusions on<lb/> Section 3(1)(b) of the Repeal Act, any assistance could be derived from<lb/> this judgment and to answer the issues and questions posed before us.<lb/> Rather, the same support our conclusion.<lb/> 130<lb/> Then, we are left with the judgment on which reliance is<lb/> placed by the Petitioners, namely, Sundersons and others v/s State of<lb/> Maharashtra and others reported in 2008 (5) Bombay Cases Reporter<lb/> 85 : 2008(6) Mh.L.J. 332. We do not find that the said judgment dealt<lb/> with the controversy which has been raised before us. Apart therefrom we<lb/> find that not only in the said judgment, but in the further judgment of this<lb/> Court in the case of Damodar Laxman Navare v/s State of Maharashtra in<lb/> Writ Petition No.6300/2009 decided on 08.07.2010 the same Division<lb/> Bench clarified in paragraph 10 that it is not inclined to look into the<lb/> question and aspect of applicability of Section 3(1)(b) of the Repeal Act.<lb/> 131<lb/> Reference is then made to the judgment to which one of us is<lb/> a party (S.C.Dharmadhikari, J.), reported in 2013(2) Mh.L.J. 224 (Manik<lb/> M. Ragit v/s State of Maharashtra). There, the Division Bench was<lb/> concerned with the issue post repeal of the Principal Act and particularly<lb/> about changes in the revenue record. The prayer was to restore the name<lb/> of the Petitioner in the revenue record pertaining to the land. Paragraph 2<lb/> of this judgment would show that the vacant land in excess of ceiling<lb/> limit was identified. The Petitioner before this Court sought an order of<lb/> exemption under Section 20(1) of the Principal Act. He presented the<lb/> scheme in relation to half portion of the excess vacant land that scheme<lb/> was sanctioned by the competent authority. However, the scheme was not<lb/> implemented at all. Later on an attempt was made to proceed against this<lb/> excess vacant land, physical possession of which was always with the<lb/> Petitioner. He, therefore, argued that Section 3(1)(b) of the Repeal Act<lb/> would not come into play and the fact situation is fully covered by Section<lb/> 3(1)(a) of the Repeal Act. If the Respondent/ State cannot take physical<lb/> possession of the excess vacant land because the scheme has failed in<lb/> view of this express provision in the Repeal Act, then, the Petitioner&apos;s<lb/> name deserves to be restored to the revenue record was the essential<lb/> prayer. That has been granted and because there was no opposition from<lb/> the State. It is in this context that the Division Bench in paragraph 7<lb/> relied upon the Repeal Act and essentially Section 3(1)(a) of the same.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            answering the controversy.<lb/> 133<lb/> Finally, in </content>
 
            <figDesc>Mira Bhayander Developers and Welfare<lb/> Association (supra) the controversy was with regard to the letter dated<lb/> 23.06.2008 addressed by the State Government to the SubRegistrar of<lb/> Assurances, Thane City. That letter directed the said Authority to ascertain<lb/> at the time when the scheme holder presents a document for registration<lb/> as to whether he has sought extension for implementation of the scheme<lb/> meant for economically weaker sections of the society under Section 20 of<lb/> the Principal Act and not to register the document otherwise. That was<lb/> the letter impugned in the Writ Petition and the Division Bench in a short<lb/> judgment held as under:<lb/> &quot;1.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>have considered the rival contentions. In our view, if<lb/> the members of the Petitioners Association have taken<lb/> benefit of the schemes under Section 20 of the said Act<lb/> by constructing buildings, they now cannot wriggle out<lb/> of their obligations to surrender flats to the Government<lb/> which the Government could sell at a fixed rate. The<lb/> entire tenor of the above Petition appears to be that the<lb/> Petitioners do not want to fulfil their obligations under<lb/> the said schemes viz surrendering the flats to the State<lb/> Government and taking advantage of the repeal of the<lb/> said Act want to contend that their obligations under the<lb/> said schemes do not survive. In our view the impugned<lb/> letter, as rightly contended by the learned AGP, has been<lb/> issued to protect the public interest and Government<lb/> revenue. It does not befit the Petitioners who have taken<lb/> advantage of the said schemes now to contend that their<lb/> obligations do not survive, and therefore there is no need<lb/> for them to surrender the flats to the Government. We,<lb/> therefore, do not find any merit in the challenge raised<lb/> in the above Petition which is accordingly dismissed.&quot;<lb/> 134<lb/> Though this judgment is based on the broad principles of<lb/> equity and that no one can take advantage of his own wrong, yet we are<lb/> of the opinion that the conclusion therein for the reasons recorded above<lb/> is correct. The same is in consonance with the conclusions reached by us<lb/> hereinabove.<lb/> 135<lb/> As a result of the above discussion the questions referred to<lb/> us are answered as under:<lb/> (a)<lb/> That the repeal of the Principal Act shall not affect the<lb/> validity of the order of exemption under Section 20(1) of the<lb/> Principal Act and all consequences following the same<lb/> including keeping intact the power to withdraw the said<lb/> exemption by recourse to Section 20(2) of the Principal Act.<lb/> Further, merely because Section 20(2) is not specifically<lb/> mentioned in the saving clause enacted by Section 3(1)(b) of<lb/> the Repeal Act that does not mean that the power is not<lb/> saved. The said power is also saved by virtue of applicability<lb/> of Section 6 of the General Clauses Act, 1897. That Section of<lb/> the General Clauses Act, 1897 applies to Section 3(1)(b) of<lb/> the Repeal Act.<lb/> (b)<lb/> Once having held that the power to withdraw the exemption<lb/> also survives the repeal of the Principal Act, then, all<lb/> consequences must follow and the said power can be<lb/> exercised by the State Government in accordance with law.<lb/> That power and equally all ancillary and incidental powers to<lb/> the main power to impose conditions are also saved and<lb/> survive the repeal. Meaning thereby the terms and conditions<lb/> of the order of exemption can be enforced in accordance with<lb/> law.<lb/> (c)<lb/> Question Nos.1 and 2 in the AFFIRMATIVE, by holding that<lb/> Section 6 of the General Clauses Act, 1897 applies to the<lb/> savings of the exemption order including all terms and<lb/> conditions thereof, validity of which or any action taken<lb/> thereunder has been saved by Section 3(1)(b)<lb/> notwithstanding any judgment of any court to the contrary.<lb/> (d)<lb/> Question Nos.3 and 4 will have to be answered as above, but<lb/> by clarifying that though it would be open for the State to<lb/> enforce the exemption order and terms and conditions<lb/> thereof, validity of which is saved by the Repeal Act, but<lb/> having regard to the language of Section 20(2) of the<lb/> Principal Act it cannot be held that same can be enforced<lb/> only by withdrawal of the order of exemption in terms of sub<lb/> section (2) of Section 20, which power also survives the<lb/> repeal of the Principal Act. In other words, though Section<lb/> 3(1)(b) of the Repeal Act read with Section 6 of the General<lb/> Clauses Act, 1897 states that repeal of the Principal Act shall<lb/> not affect the validity of the exemption order passed under<lb/> Section 20(1) of the Principal Act or any action taken<lb/> thereunder notwithstanding any judgment of any court to the<lb/> contrary, still the obligations and liabilities incurred<lb/> voluntarily under the exemption order by the person holding<lb/> the vacant land in excess of ceiling limit need not be enforced<lb/> only by exercise of powers under subsection (2) of Section<lb/> 20 of the Principal Act, but by all other legally permissible<lb/> means.<lb/> (e)<lb/> We also clarify that though our answers to Questions 3 and 4<lb/> would be as aforesaid, still whether any of these powers<lb/> could be exercised and to what extent are all matters which<lb/> must be decided in the facts and circumstances of each case.<lb/> In the event the State desires to take any action in terms of<lb/> Section 20(2) of the Principal Act it would be open for the<lb/> aggrieved parties to urge that such an action is not<lb/> permissible in the given facts and circumstances particularly<lb/> because of enormous and unexplained delay, the parties<lb/> having altered their position to their detriment, the<lb/> proceedings as also the orders in that behalf are grossly<lb/> unfair, unjust, arbitrary, high handed, malafide and violative<lb/> of the principles of natural justice and of the Constitutional<lb/> mandate enshrined in Articles 14, 19(1)(g), 21 and 300A of<lb/> the Constitution of India. These and other contentions can<lb/> always be raised and irrespective of our conclusions,<lb/> individual orders can always be challenged and action<lb/> thereunder impugned in appropriate legal proceedings<lb/> including under Article 226 of the Constitution of India.<lb/> (f)<lb/> The aggrieved parties can also urge that while seeking to<lb/> enforce the terms and conditions of the exemption order or<lb/> recalling or withdrawing the exemption itself the competent<lb/> authorities/ State has not adhered to the provisions of law<lb/> applicable for such exercise. Meaning thereby there has to be<lb/> a specific order in that behalf and mere issuance of<lb/> administrative instructions or circulars will not suffice. All<lb/> such objections can as well be raised and in individual cases.<lb/> (g)<lb/> By our answers to Questions 1 to 4 above, we should not be<lb/> taken to have held that there is a mandate under the Repeal<lb/> Act to withdraw the order of exemption passed under Section<lb/> 20(1) of the Principal Act and the Government is obliged to<lb/> withdraw it in the event the said order or any terms or<lb/> conditions thereof have not been satisfied rather violated or<lb/> breached. In the light of the wording of Section 20(2) of the<lb/> Principal Act the State is competent to withdraw, but only<lb/> after giving a reasonable opportunity to the persons<lb/> concerned for making representation against the proposed<lb/> withdrawal. The Government is obliged to pass an order<lb/> withdrawing any exemption and needless to clarify that in<lb/> the event such an order is passed it can be impugned and<lb/> challenged by the aggrieved parties in appropriate<lb/> proceedings on the grounds that it is unreasoned and/or in<lb/> the given facts and circumstances such an order could not<lb/> have been passed or need not be passed and the Government<lb/> could have granted time to comply with the terms and<lb/> conditions or that the terms and conditions relying on which<lb/> and for breach of which the exemption order is withdrawn<lb/> are not violated or breached, they were not mandatory and<lb/> have been substantially complied with or were incapable of<lb/> being complied with because of several factors, obstacles and<lb/> hurdles each of which cannot be enumerated or termed as<lb/> exhaustive in any manner. Therefore, if the Government is<lb/> not mandated to withdraw the exemption order, but can<lb/> ensure compliance of the terms and conditions without<lb/> withdrawal of the exemption order or without recourse to<lb/> Section 20(2) of the Principal Act, then, needless to clarify<lb/> that all liabilities, obligations and equally the remedies<lb/> available to the parties are unaffected by repeal and can be<lb/> resorted to in the afore stated events.<lb/> (h)<lb/> In the light of our conclusions as enumerated in paragraph<lb/> No.125 above we hold that the view taken by the Division<lb/> Bench in Vithabai Bama Bhandari v/s State of Maharashtra<lb/> and another reported in 2009(3) Bombay Cases Reporter<lb/> 663 (Writ Petition No.4241/2008 decided on 31 st March/ 16 th<lb/> April, 2009) does not lay down the correct law and to the<lb/> extent indicated hereinabove.<lb/> (i)<lb/> The Reference is answered accordingly. Each of these Writ<lb/> Petitions shall now be placed before appropriate Division<lb/> Benches for disposal in the light of the above principles and<lb/> on merits, so also, in accordance with law. We clarify that all<lb/> contentions of both sides on merits of the said Writ Petitions<lb/> are kept open.<lb/> (j)<lb/> We are thankful for the able assistance rendered by all the<lb/> learned counsel for deciding this Reference.<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> (S.C. Dharmadhikari, J.)<lb/> (G.S. Kulkarni, J.)<lb/> ********<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:40 :::<lb/> Judgment (Per S.C. Gupte, J.) :<lb/> 1<lb/> I have gone </content>
 
            <figDesc>through the judgement prepared by my brother<lb/> Dharmadhikari J. With greatest respect, I am afraid I am unable to agree<lb/> with some of the key conclusions and reasons discussed in it. I have in<lb/> the following judgment dealt with the conclusions in respect of which I<lb/> differ from the views expressed by brother Dharmadhikari J.<lb/> 2<lb/> The questions referred to the Full Bench and the submissions<lb/> made by learned Counsel appearing on either sides have been elaborately<lb/> set out by my brother Dharmadhikari J and need not be repeated here. I<lb/> shall, wherever necessary, refer to these submissions in the context of my<lb/> conclusions and reasons for the same.<lb/> 3<lb/> Let me briefly dwell at the outset with the conflict in the<lb/> decisions of Division Benches of our court, which led to the present Full<lb/> Bench reference, so as to put the whole controversy in a proper<lb/> perspective and make its context clear. What led to the conflict of the<lb/> Division Bench decisions of this court were the circulars issued by various<lb/> Competent Authorities under the Urban Land (Ceiling and Regulation)<lb/> Act, 1976 (&quot;the Principal Act&quot;) after repeal by the Urban Land (Ceiling<lb/> and Regulation) Repeal Act, 1999 (&quot;the Repeal Act&quot;) to SubRegistrars of<lb/> Assurances and planning authorities not to register documents presented<lb/> by landholders for registration or sanction plans filed for development of<lb/> lands unless no objection certificates were issued by these Competent<lb/> Authorities. These directives were purportedly issued with a view to<lb/> implement schemes sanctioned by Competent Authorities whilst granting<lb/> exemptions to the concerned lands under Section 20 of the Principal Act.<lb/> In some cases, the landholders would have breached the provisions of<lb/> these schemes, for example, by not completing the schemes within the<lb/> stipulated periods, in which cases the concerned Competent Authorities<lb/> would not issue no objection certificates, thereby ensuring compliance on<lb/> the part of the landholders with the sanctioned schemes. These circulars<lb/> were challenged before this Court in a number of petitions.<lb/> 4<lb/> In Sundersons &amp; Ors. Vs. State of Maharashtra &amp; Ors. 1 , the<lb/> Collector had issued instructions to Subregistrars of Assurances to insist<lb/> upon an NOC from the competent authority, namely, the Collector before<lb/> registering any document.<lb/> A Division Bench of this Court held that<lb/> persual of the circular did not disclose the source of the power under<lb/> which it had been issued and that it was not open to the Collector to issue<lb/> such instructions.<lb/> 5<lb/> In Damodar Laxman Navare Vs. State of Maharashtra 2 , the<lb/> Court was concerned with two letters -one by which authorities such as<lb/> the Municipal Corporation and SubRegistrar were directed not to<lb/> sanction plans or register documents presented by landholders and the<lb/> other directing the petitioner landholder in that case to pay penalty for<lb/> extension of time for completion of a scheme sanctioned under Section 20<lb/> of the Principal Act. Both these letters were issued after the repeal of the<lb/> Principal Act. The Division Bench hearing the petitioners&apos; challenge to the<lb/> two letters struck down these directions, holding them to be illegal and<lb/> ultra vires the powers of the authorities under the Principal Act. The<lb/> challenge to these circulars on the grounds of repeal of the Principal Act<lb/> and the effect of the saving clause on the exemption orders passed under<lb/> Section 20 or actions taken thereunder, was, however, not considered by<lb/> the Division Bench in Damodar Laxman Navare (supra).<lb/> 6<lb/> Then came the decision of another Division Bench of our<lb/> Court in Mira Bhayandar Builders and Developers Welfare Association<lb/> Vs. Deputy Collector and Competent Authority. 1 In that case, members<lb/> of the Petitioner Association, who were builders and developers, had<lb/> taken benefit of the schemes meant for economically weaker sections of<lb/> the society sanctioned under Section 20 of the Principal Act. The schemes<lb/> were partly implemented on the date of the repeal of the Principal Act.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>impugned circular had been issued to protect the public interest by<lb/> ensuring implementation of schemes meant for economically weaker<lb/> sections. The Division Bench held that if the members of the Petitioner<lb/> Association had taken benefit of the schemes under Section 20 by<lb/> constructing buildings, they could not now wriggle out of their obligations<lb/> to surrender flats to the Government which the Government could sell at<lb/> fixed rates. The Division Bench accordingly rejected the Petitioners&apos;<lb/> challenge to the circular.<lb/> 7<lb/> These were then the rulings on the subject, when another<lb/> 1 Writ Petition No.5745/2009 dated 27 th August, 2009<lb/> Division Bench of our Court -in Jayesh Tokarshi Shah Vs. Deputy<lb/> Collector and Competent Authority 1 considered similar circulars issued<lb/> by the Competent Authority after the repeal of the Principal Act,<lb/> prohibiting registration of conveyances in respect of flats constructed<lb/> under schemes sanctioned under Section 20 and sold without obtaining<lb/> extension of periods of completion of the schemes or obtaining no<lb/> objection certificates from the Competent Authority under the Principal<lb/> Act. According to the Petitioners in that case, the circulars issued after the<lb/> repeal of the Principal Act were without authority of law and also that the<lb/> conditions of the exemption orders under Section 20 did not survive the<lb/> repeal. On the other hand, the State contended that the circulars were<lb/> issued for meaningful implementation of sanctions granted under Section<lb/> 20, as validity of such sanction orders remained saved from the rigours of<lb/> the Repeal Act. According to the State, the Petitioners had yet to discharge<lb/> their obligations under the schemes by handing over specified number of<lb/> tenements to the Government and paying penalty for extension of time to<lb/> complete the schemes. Based on the decision of our Court in Mira<lb/> Bhayandar Builders&apos; case (supra) it was contended by the State that it<lb/> was not open to a party, who had taken advantage of a scheme sanctioned<lb/> under Section 20 of the Principal Act, to contend that the obligations of<lb/> the scheme did not survive the repeal of the Principal Act. The Division<lb/> Bench in Jayesh Tokarshi Shah (supra) felt that the view expressed by<lb/> our Court in Sundersons &amp; Ors (supra) and Damodar Laxman Navare<lb/> (supra) led to the premise that the Competent Authority under the<lb/> Principal Act was not competent to issue such circulars, but that there was<lb/> a conflict with such premise in the view expressed by our Court in Mira<lb/> Bhayandar Builders&apos; case (supra) where challenge to a similar circular<lb/> was dispelled on the ground that the circular was issued to protect public<lb/> 1 Writ Petition No.3815/2010 decided on 26.10.2010<lb/> interest and having taken advantage of a scheme under Section 20 of the<lb/> Principal Act, the Petitioners could not wriggle out of their obligations.<lb/> The Court in Jayesh Tokarshi Shah (supra) referred to another decision<lb/> of our Court in Mohal Gopal Mate Vs. Principal Secretary 1 , which held<lb/> that the powers of the State under Section 20 in case of breach of a<lb/> condition of an exemption order were limited to withdrawal of the<lb/> exemption order only, whereupon provisions of Chapter III would apply to<lb/> such land. The Court in Jayesh Tokarshi Shah (supra) also felt that going<lb/> by strict interpretation of Sections 20 and 21 of the Principal Act, the<lb/> power of the State in case of contravention of any of the conditions of the<lb/> schemes sanctioned under these Sections by the scheme holders was<lb/> limited to withdrawal of exemption, declaring such land to be excess<lb/> vacant land and applying the provisions of Chapter III of the Principal Act<lb/> for acquisition of the same. The Court, however, felt that such view would<lb/> be in conflict with the view expressed by the Court in Mira Bhayander<lb/> Builders&apos; case (supra) and that therefore the controversy deserved to be<lb/> resolved by a Full Bench of this Court.<lb/> 8<lb/> That is how this reference has come before us. The principal<lb/> controversy before us concerns the effect of the Repeal Act on the<lb/> schemes sanctioned whilst granting exemptions under Section 20 of the<lb/> Principal Act to excess vacant lands. Do the conditions of exemption<lb/> orders survive the repeal and if so, can these conditions be enforced by<lb/> the State after the date of the repeal, if necessary by withdrawing the<lb/> exemption and applying the provisions of Chapter III to the lands which<lb/> were the subject matter of such exemption orders and schemes.<lb/> 9<lb/> At the outset, a brief overview of the Principal Act and the<lb/> 1 2009 1) BCR 275<lb/> Repeal Act may be necessary to understand the impact and reach of the<lb/> Repeal Act and whatever is left untouched by it from the provisions of the<lb/> Principal Act or actions taken thereunder.<lb/> 10<lb/> The Principal Act was enacted for (i) imposition of a ceiling<lb/> on vacant land in urban agglomerations, (ii) acquisition of land in excess<lb/> of the ceiling limit, and (iii) regulation of construction of buildings on<lb/> such land and for matters connected therewith. The declared objective of<lb/> these provisions in the Principal Act was to (i) prevent concentration of<lb/> urban land in the hands of a few persons and speculation and<lb/> profiteering therein and (ii) bring about an equitable distribution of land<lb/> in urban agglomerations to subserve the common good.<lb/> 11<lb/> Chapter III of the Principal Act contains the key provisions<lb/> for accomplishment of the aforesaid objectives. The Chapter consists of<lb/> three sets of provisions, namely, (1) Sections 3 to 18 which provide for<lb/> the ceiling limit, and ascertainment and acquisition of vacant land in<lb/> excess of such ceiling limit, (2) Sections 19 to 22 dealing with non<lb/> application or exemption from application of Chapter III to certain lands<lb/> and (3) Sections 23 and 24 which deal with disposal of vacant land<lb/> acquired under Chapter III.<lb/> 12<lb/> Section 3, which is the pivotal section in the Chapter,<lb/> proscribes any person from holding vacant land in excess of the ceiling<lb/> limit in the territories covered by the Principal Act. The ceiling limits for<lb/> various classes of agglomerations and the manner of calculating them for<lb/> various classes of persons are provided in Section 4. Section 5 provides<lb/> for a subsidiary rule for calculating the extent of vacant land in cases of<lb/> certain transfers (i.e. transfers between the appointed day and the date of<lb/> commencement of the Principal Act) and also prohibits transfers after the<lb/> date of commencement without furnishing a statement under Section 6<lb/> and publication of a notification of excess land under Section 10(1). The<lb/> machinery provisions for arriving at the extent of excess vacant land are<lb/> contained in Sections 6 to 9. The entire determination process starts with<lb/> a statement to be compulsorily filed by every person holding vacant land<lb/> in excess of ceiling limit as on the date of commencement of the Principal<lb/> Act, specifying the requisite particulars of such land. Section 7 contains<lb/> subsidiary provisions concerning filing of such statement in case such land<lb/> is situated within the jurisdiction of two or more competent authorities,<lb/> whether in the same state or in two or more states to which the Principal<lb/> Act applies. Section 8 provides for preparation of a draft statement by<lb/> the competent authority. It also requires service of such draft statement<lb/> on, and consideration of objections, if any, by, the concerned landholder.<lb/> Section 9 provides for determination of excess vacant<lb/> land and<lb/> preparation and service of a final statement concerning such excess<lb/> vacant land. Section 10 contains provisions concerning acquisition of<lb/> such excess vacant land by the State Government. Under the scheme of<lb/> Section 10, the competent authority has to first issue and publish a<lb/> notification giving particulars of excess vacant land, proposing its<lb/> acquisition and inviting claims of all persons interested in such land,<lb/> under Subsection (1) of Section 10. Subsection (2) requires the<lb/> competent authority to determine the nature and extent of such claims.<lb/> Subsection (3) empowers the competent authority to declare by<lb/> notification the acquisition of such excess vacant land with effect from a<lb/> date specified in that behalf. Upon publication of such notification the<lb/> land is deemed to be vested absolutely in the State Government with<lb/> effect from the date so specified. Subsection (4) of Section 10 provides<lb/> for an embargo on transfer of land between the dates of the publication of<lb/> the respective notifications under Subsections (1) and (3). Subsections<lb/> (5) and (6) deal with taking over of possession of the land thus vesting in<lb/> the State Government.<lb/> Subsection (5) authorizes the competent<lb/> authority to require by notice surrender or delivery of such land to the<lb/> State Government. Subsection (6) empowers the competent authority to<lb/> take possession by use of force in case of failure of the landholder to so<lb/> surrender or deliver possession. Sections 11 to 14 contain provisions<lb/> regarding payment of compensation by the State Government to the<lb/> landholder whose land is so acquired by the State Government. Section<lb/> 11 contains provisions for determination of such compensation, Section<lb/> 12 provides for appeals to a tribunal from any determination under<lb/> Section 11 and Section 13 provides for an appeal to the High Court from<lb/> the decision of the tribunal. Section 14 provides for the mode of payment<lb/> of such compensation. Sections 15 to 18 provide for subsidiary matters<lb/> such as ceiling limit on future acquisition by inheritance, etc., filing of<lb/> statement when the Principal Act is subsequently adopted by any State,<lb/> the competent authority&apos;s power to enter upon any vacant land for<lb/> carrying out the purposes of the Principal Act and penalty for<lb/> concealment of particulars of vacant land, etc.<lb/> 13<lb/> Section 19 provides cases in which the provisions of Chapter<lb/> III do not apply to certain vacant lands, e.g. lands held by the Central or<lb/> State Governments, banks, etc. Section 20 provides for the power of the<lb/> State Government to exempt any vacant land on conditions and to<lb/> withdraw such exemption on noncompliance of the conditions. (This<lb/> Section will be dealt with in detail in the following order.) Section 21<lb/> provides for circumstances in which excess vacant land may not be<lb/> treated as excess in certain cases. Section 22 provides for cases where a<lb/> landholder under certain conditions may be permitted to retain excess<lb/> vacant land.<lb/> 14<lb/> Sections 23 and 24, as noted above, provide for disposal of<lb/> vacant lands acquired by the State Government under the Principal Act.<lb/> These Sections inter alia serve the objective of equitable distribution of<lb/> land in public interest.<lb/> 15<lb/> Chapter IV enacts provisions concerning regulations of<lb/> transfers of land and use of urban property. Section 25 defines &quot;plinth<lb/> area&quot;. Section 26 provides for a notice to be given of any intended<lb/> transfer of vacant land to the competent authority, which has the first<lb/> option to purchase such land on behalf of the State Government. The<lb/> section also contains machinery provisions for completing such sale in<lb/> case the option is exercised by the competent authority. Section 27 enacts<lb/> a prohibition on transfer of urban property. Section 28 makes subsidiary<lb/> provisions for regulating registration of documents so as to effectively<lb/> implement the provisions of Sections 26 and 27. Section 29 contains<lb/> regulatory provisions for construction of buildings with dwelling units.<lb/> Demolition and stoppage of buildings constructed / being constructed in<lb/> contravention of the provisions of Section 29 is provided under Section<lb/> 30.<lb/> 16<lb/> Chapter V contains miscellaneous provisions providing for<lb/> powers of the competent authority (Section 31), jurisdiction of authorities<lb/> and tribunals (Section 32), appeal (Section 33), Revision (Section 34),<lb/> power of the State Government to issue directions (Section 35), power of<lb/> the Central Government to give directions (Section 36), returns and<lb/> reports, offences and penalties, etc. Section 42 in this chapter provides for<lb/> the overriding effect of the provisions of the Principal Act.<lb/> After the Principal Act came into force in the State of<lb/> Maharashtra, statements under Section 6 thereof were filed by<lb/> landholders. In some cases the land acquisition was completed and excess<lb/> vacant lands were taken possession of after following the procedure laid<lb/> down in Sections 8 to 10; whilst in other cases proceedings were pending<lb/> at various stages provided under Sections 8 to 10 or the appellate and<lb/> revisional stages under Sections 33 and 34 of the Principal Act. In respect<lb/> of some lands orders were passed under Sections 20 and 21 sanctioning<lb/> schemes presented by landholders and accordingly exemptions were<lb/> granted on conditions or excess vacant land was directed not to be treated<lb/> as excess, respectively, under Sections 20 and 21; and these schemes were<lb/> either completed or were at different stages of completion. In some cases,<lb/> where the conditions of exemption orders were breached, the exemptions<lb/> were withdrawn and the procedure under Sections 8 to 10 of the Principal<lb/> Act for acquisition of land thus rendered excess vacant land was being<lb/> applied to such lands and was at varying stages of completion. This was<lb/> the position in 1999, when the Parliament passed the Repeal Act.<lb/> 18<lb/> On 11 January 1999, an ordinance to repeal the Principal Act<lb/> was promulgated by the President. This was followed by a bill to repeal<lb/> the Principal Act tabled in the Parliament, being Bill No.17/1999. The bill<lb/> proposed repeal of the Principal Act in the same terms as the ordinance.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            (2) Where-<lb/>(a) </content>
 
            <figDesc>any land is deemed to have vested in the<lb/> State Government under subsection (3) of section 10<lb/> of the principal Act but possession of which has not<lb/> been taken over by the State Government or any<lb/> person duly authorised by the State Government in<lb/> this behalf or by the competent authority; and<lb/> (b) any amount has been paid by the State<lb/> Government with respect to such land,<lb/> then, such land shall not be restored unless the<lb/> amount paid, if any, has been refunded to the State<lb/> Government.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>resolution passed and adopted by both houses of State Legislature under<lb/> Article 252(2) of the Constitution of India on 29 November 2007. The<lb/> resolution adopted by the State of Maharashtra is in the following terms :<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> &quot;MAHARASTHRA<lb/> LEGISLATIVE<lb/> ASSEMBLY<lb/> RESOLUTION<lb/> Whereas, the </content>
 
            <figDesc>Maharashtra Legislative<lb/> Assembly on 5 th October 1971 and the Maharashtra<lb/> Legislative Council on the 7 th October 1971 had, in<lb/> pursuance of clause (1) of article 252 of the<lb/> Constitution of India, resolved that the imposition of<lb/> ceiling on urban immovable property and acquisition<lb/> of such property in excess of the ceiling and all<lb/> matters connected therewith or ancillary and<lb/> incidental thereto should be regulated in the State of<lb/> Maharashtra by Parliament by law :</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>1 </head>
 
            <figDesc>AIR 1955 S.C. 84 (Vol. 42 C.N. 20)<lb/> The savings clause of the Repeal Act, in our case, saves firstly<lb/> the vesting of any vacant land under subsection (3) of Section 10 of the<lb/> Principal Act, but with a caveat. Such vesting is saved only if possession of<lb/> such vacant land has already been taken over by the State Government or<lb/> any person duly authorized by the State Government in this behalf or by<lb/> the competent authority (Section 3(1)(a) of the Repeal Act). Secondly, it<lb/> saves the validity of any order granting exemption under subsection (1)<lb/> of Section 20 or any action taken thereunder, and it saves such validity<lb/> notwithstanding a judgment of any court to the contrary (Section 3(1)(b)<lb/> of the Repeal Act). Thirdly, the savings clause saves any payment made to<lb/> the State Government as a condition for granting exemption under Sub<lb/> Section (1) of Section 20 (Section 3(1)(c) of the Repeal Act). A further<lb/> saving provision is contained in subsection (2) of Section 3, which does<lb/> not require restoration of any land which is deemed to have vested in the<lb/> State Government under subsection (3) of Section 10 of the Principal<lb/> Act, but possession of which has not been taken over, subject to two<lb/> conditions -one, any amount has been paid by the State government with<lb/> respect to such land and two, such amount has not been refunded to the<lb/> State Government. In other words, if these two conditions are fulfilled,<lb/> the vesting of such land continues and is saved from the effects of the<lb/> repeal. Lastly, the savings clause saves proceedings relating to Sections 11,<lb/> 12, 13 and 14 of the Principal Act in so far as such proceedings are<lb/> relatable to the land, possession of which has been taken over by the State<lb/> Government or any person authorized by the State Government or any<lb/> person authorized by the State Government or by the competent<lb/> authority. This is a necessary corollary of saving the vesting of such land.<lb/> If the land is vested and the vesting saved by the Repeal Act, the<lb/> proceedings relating to such land for (I) determination of compensation<lb/> (Section 11), appeals to a tribunal from such determinations (Section 12),<lb/> appeals to the High Court from the appellate orders of tribunals (Section<lb/> 13) and (ii) determination of mode of payment of compensation (Section<lb/> 14), are also saved.<lb/> 22<lb/> The scheme of the Repeal Act is thus absolutely clear and<lb/> there are unambiguous indications in this scheme that the Repeal Act was<lb/> meant to completely do away with the Principal Act except in cases of<lb/> actions taken under the Principal Act which had achieved a finality. In the<lb/> first place, we may note the principal Section in the Repeal Act, i.e.<lb/> Section 2, which repeals the Principal Act as a whole without any<lb/> reservation. Secondly, the saving clause in Section 3(2) read with Section<lb/> 3(1) shows that any land which is deemed to be vested in the State<lb/> Government under Section 10(3) of the Principal Act will stand restored<lb/> to the owner of such land except in two cases. One, where the vesting is<lb/> accompanied by taking over of possession of the land (i.e. where<lb/> possession is surrendered to the State Government by the owner in<lb/> pursuance of a notice under Section 10(5) or where possession is taken by<lb/> the competent authority under Section 10(6) of the Principal Act). And<lb/> the other, where possession is not taken but any amount has been paid by<lb/> the State Government with respect to such land. In the latter case, such<lb/> land shall not be restored unless the amount paid by the State<lb/> Government is refunded to it. No vesting order except in the two<lb/> contingencies noted above is saved by the Repeal Act. Thirdly, it may be<lb/> noted that Section 3(1)(b) saves the validity of an order granting<lb/> exemption under Section 20(1) of the Principal Act or any action taken<lb/> thereunder. It does not in terms save any action to be taken thereunder,<lb/> but saves validity of any action already taken thereunder. Fourthly,<lb/> exemption order under Section 20(1) of the<lb/> Principal Act.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>24<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>These provisions are clear and loud. They imply a complete<lb/> repeal or obliteration of the law except in cases particularly provided for.<lb/> But if and to the extent there is any ambiguity (thereby permitting<lb/> external aids for interpretation of the repealing statute), we may have<lb/> reference to the Statement of Objects and Reasons of the repealing<lb/> statute. The Statement of Objects, as noted above, shows that whereas the<lb/> main purpose of the Principal Act was to prevent concentration of urban<lb/> land in a few hands and provide affordable housing to economically<lb/> weaker sections, the Act actually resulted in pushing up land prices,<lb/> practically brought the housing industry to a stop and provided<lb/> opportunities for corruption. The Objects and Reasons acknowledge a<lb/> near unanimous public opinion that the Act has failed to achieve its<lb/> objectives as expected. In these premises, the Repeal Act proposes a<lb/> complete repeal without any reservation, saving only the consequences<lb/> specially provided for.<lb/> 25<lb/> In the backdrop of what is stated above, we may now discuss<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:40 :::<lb/> *203*</content>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>26<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>Now the question is, what are the consequences of such<lb/> validity. The obvious consequences, which are provided in the Repeal Act<lb/> itself, are (a) all actions taken under the exemption order are valid and<lb/> (b) payment made thereunder to the State Government is valid. But what<lb/> are the other consequences. Could it be that the breach of the conditions<lb/> of a valid exemption order would attract the provisions of Section 20(2)<lb/> and all provisions of Chapter III including those relating to vesting of the<lb/> land would thereupon apply to such land (i.e. land becoming excess<lb/> vacant land as a result of withdrawal of exemption under Section 20(2)).<lb/> 27<lb/> There are clear indications in the Repeal Act that these<lb/> consequences are not contemplated. In the first place, withdrawal of an<lb/> exemption order renders the land &apos;excess vacant land&apos; just as any other<lb/> vacant land which is in excess of the ceiling limit and which is not subject<lb/> to an exemption order under Section 20(1). If such other vacant land<lb/> could not continue to be vested in the State Government even after the<lb/> provisions of Section 10(3) applied to it, if possession of the land was not<lb/> already taken by the Government on the date of the repeal, there is no<lb/> reason why the provisions of Section 20(2) and consequences of<lb/> withdrawal of exemption thereunder should apply to a land which is<lb/> exempted under Section 20(1), but conditions of such exemption are<lb/> breached as on, or after, the date of the repeal.<lb/> 28<lb/> If Chapter III were to apply to such land, which has become<lb/> excess vacant land by reason of withdrawal of the exemption order in<lb/> connection therewith, but not to other excess vacant lands, anomalous</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>),<lb/> actual physical possession was not taken over by the State Government or<lb/> the Competent Authority under the Principal Act by the time the Repeal<lb/> Act was brought in force; and that accordingly, the vesting of the land in<lb/> the Government was not saved. The Division Bench relied upon a<lb/> judgment of another Division Bench of our Court in Voltas Ltd. Vs.<lb/> Additional Collector and Competent Authority 1 in this behalf.<lb/> 30<lb/> The law stated in Vithabai Bama Bhandari (supra) in this<lb/> behalf has not been contested by the State. The learned Advocate<lb/> General, in his submissions, accepts that any land, earlier exempted under<lb/> Section 20(1), but exemption of which was already withdrawn under<lb/> Section 20(2) before the repeal of the Principal Act, cannot vest in the<lb/> State Government after the repeal if possession of such land was not<lb/> taken over by the State before the date of repeal. That indeed would be<lb/> the effect of Section 3(1)(a) of the Repeal Act. Once this position is<lb/> accepted, there is possibly no logic or justification for not applying this<lb/> law to the land exempted under Section 20(1) but exemption of which is<lb/> withdrawn after the date of repeal. If the power of the Government to<lb/> acquire the land in the event of withdrawal of exemption before the<lb/> repeal is not saved by the Repeal Act except in a case where the exercise<lb/> of such power is completed by not just deemed vesting under Section<lb/> 10(3) but by taking over of physical possession under Section 10(5) or<lb/> 10(6), there is no reason why such power is saved for a land, the<lb/> exemption of which is withdrawn after the repeal.<lb/> 31<lb/> Even Section 4 of the Repeal Act is a pointer to show that<lb/> 1 2008(5) Bom.C.R. 746<lb/> applicability of SubSection(2) of Section 20 of the Principal Act as also<lb/> applicability of the provisions of Chapter III to lands earlier subject to<lb/> exemptions under SubSection(1) of Section 20, but which exemptions<lb/> were withdrawn either before or after the repeal, is not saved. Section 4<lb/> makes it clear that all proceedings relating to any order made or<lb/> purported to be made under the Principal Act shall lapse save and except<lb/> proceedings under Section 11 to 14 in relation to land, possession of<lb/> which has been taken over by the State Government under the Act.<lb/> Section 4 does not make any distinction in respect of proceedings in<lb/> relation to (i) land which has become excess vacant land by reason of<lb/> withdrawal of exemption order Section 20(2) and (ii) all other excess<lb/> vacant lands. Just as in the case of all other lands, where possession is not<lb/> taken over, even in the case of lands, to which Chapter III is being applied<lb/> by reason of withdrawal of the exemption order, the proceedings would<lb/> clearly abate. Any other interpretation would be clearly contrary to the<lb/> plain reading of Section 4.<lb/> 32<lb/> The Repeal Act, thus, does not save any order passed or to be<lb/> passed under Section 20(2) withdrawing exemption under Section 20(1)<lb/> of the Principal Act and thereby applying Chapter III to the land in<lb/> question. If anything, the repealing statute would have expressly provided<lb/> so. It does not provide for saving of either Section 20(2) or any order<lb/> passed under Section 20(2). When the applicability of the whole of<lb/> Chapter III is done away with in relation to all excess vacant land other<lb/> than land of which possession is taken by the State under that chapter,<lb/> there is no discernible reason why that Chapter should apply to land<lb/> exemption of which has been withdrawn under Section 20(2) of the<lb/> Principal Act. Upon withdrawal of exemption, such land is like any other<lb/> excess vacant land and the provisions of the Principal Act including<lb/> Chapter III will cease to apply to it unless the vesting of such land in the<lb/> State Government is followed by taking over of possession. Thus, it is<lb/> clear that the saving clause of the Repeal Act does not save the land once<lb/> exempted under Section 20(1) of the Principal Act from the application of<lb/> the repeal.<lb/> 33<lb/> Let us now consider if it is saved by the provisions of Section<lb/> 6 of the General Clauses Act. Learned Advocate General relied upon the<lb/> judgment of the Supreme Court in Bansidhar Vs. State of Rajasthan 1<lb/> and submitted that a saving provision in a repealing statute is not<lb/> exhaustive of the rights and liabilities which are saved or which survive<lb/> the repeal, and Section 6 of the General Clauses Act can still be invoked<lb/> so as to save other rights, privileges, obligations and liabilities which have<lb/> been acquired or accrued or incurred under the repealed statute before<lb/> the date of the repeal. The Court in that case reiterated the law laid<lb/> down in I.T. Commissioner Vs. Shah Sadiq &amp; Sons 2 , to the following<lb/> effect: (SCC P. 524, para 15)<lb/> &quot;<lb/> .</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>whether the repealing statute exhibits a contrary intention. Section 6 of<lb/> the General Clauses Act provides the various contingencies which a repeal<lb/> does not affect, but prefaces that by providing: &quot;unless a different<lb/> intention appears&quot;. In Kalawati Devi Harlake Vs. The Commissioner of<lb/> Income Tax, West Bengal 1 , the Supreme Court was concerned with the<lb/> Income Tax Act, 1922, which was repealed by the Income Tax Act, 1961.<lb/> The Commissioner of Income Tax in that case had issued a notice<lb/> regarding incometax assessments of the assessee for the years 195253 to<lb/> 196061, which, according to the Commissioner, were erroneous and<lb/> prejudicial to the interest of the revenue, and for which the Commissioner<lb/> proposed to issue proceedings under Section 33 B of the Income Tax Act,<lb/> 1922. The assessee claimed that the Income Tax Act, 1922 was repealed<lb/> by the Income Tax Act, 1961 which came into force on April 1, 1962, and<lb/> that powers under the repealed Act under Section 33 B could not any<lb/> longer be exercised. Section 297 of the Income Tax Act, 1961 provided for<lb/> the repeal of the 1922 Act and also provided savings therefrom. Section<lb/> 297 did not cover saving of the proceedings under Section 33B of the<lb/> repealed Act after the repeal. The Department, however, relied upon<lb/> Section 6 of the General Clauses Act. The Supreme Court noted that<lb/> Section 297 of the Income Tax Act, 1961 provided for various<lb/> &apos;proceedings&apos; which may be initiated and prosecuted or continued in<lb/> respect of any past matter or assessment. The Court observed that Section<lb/> 297 was meant to provide as far as possible for all contingencies which<lb/> may arise out of the repeal of the 1922 Act and that Section 297 did not<lb/> provide for saving of provisions regarding appeals, revisions etc. in<lb/> respect of assessment orders already made or which were authorized to<lb/> be made under that Section. The Income Tax department, however,<lb/> argued that the Parliament had Section 6 of the General Clauses Act in<lb/> 1 AIR 1968 SC 162<lb/> view and therefore no express provision was made dealing with appeals<lb/> and revisions, etc. This contention was rejected the Supreme Court in the<lb/> following words: (Pg 168 of AIR 1968 SC 162)<lb/> &quot; (15)</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>1(1980) 1 SCC 149<lb/> 2[1961] A.C. 901 (P.C.)<lb/> some right should be or should not be given. On a repeal,<lb/> the former is preserved by the Interpretation Act. The latter<lb/> is not.&apos;<lb/> (emphasis supplied)<lb/> Even in Bansidhar&apos;s case the Supreme Court, whilst<lb/> construing Clauses (c) and (e) of Section 6 of the General Clauses Act,<lb/> had said this:<lb/> &quot; 30. For purposes of these clauses the &apos;right&apos;<lb/> must be &apos;accrued&apos; and not merely an inchoate<lb/> one. The distinction between what is and what<lb/> is not a right preserved by Section 6 of the<lb/> General Clauses Act, it is said, if often one of<lb/> great fineness. What is unaffected by the repeal<lb/> is a right &apos;acquired&apos; or &apos;accrued&apos; under the<lb/> repealed statute and not &apos;a mere hope or<lb/> expectation&apos; of acquiring a right or liberty to<lb/> apply for a right.&apos; &quot;<lb/> 37<lb/> Now let us see, how the provisions of the Principal Act with<lb/> which we are concerned in the present case, namely, Section 20(2) and<lb/> generally the provisions of Chapter III, fare in the context of an order<lb/> under Section 20(2), in this behalf. What is argued is that the landholder<lb/> holding an exemption under Section 20(1) attracts the liability to have<lb/> the exemption withdrawn and Chapter III of the Principal Act applied to<lb/> the land. This may certainly be called an existing liability and the<lb/> Government can be said to have a corresponding right to withdraw the<lb/> exemption and apply Chapter III to the land in question. But the question<lb/> is, is it an &quot;incurred&quot; or &quot;accrued&quot; right, as understood by law in the<lb/> context of application of Section 6. The consequence of a purported non<lb/> compliance with any of the conditions of an exemption order under</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>6</head>

            <figDesc>(c) of the General Clauses Act to the breach of a condition of an<lb/> exemption order and saving of the Government&apos;s power to withdraw the<lb/> exemption or apply Chapter III or acquire the land thereunder.<lb/> 40<lb/> Thus, neither the savings clause of the Repeal Act nor Section<lb/> 6 of the General Clauses Act saves the provisions of Section 20(2) or the<lb/> applicability of Chapter III of the Principal Act in relation to an exemption<lb/> order passed under Section 20(1). If the conditions of exemption granted<lb/> under Section 20(1) are breached, neither can the exemption be<lb/> withdrawn after the repeal nor could Chapter III be applied to the land<lb/> upon withdrawal of such exemption after the repeal. There is no question<lb/> of the State Government seeking to acquire such land any time after the<lb/> repeal.<lb/> 41<lb/> That still leaves the question: Are there any consequences<lb/> (apart from the ones discussed above) of the validity of the exemption<lb/> order saved under Section 3(1) (b) of the Repeal Act. We have noted that<lb/> the validity of an exemption order covers both the privilege, namely, the<lb/> exemption, and the conditions attached to that privilege. But we have also<lb/> noted that breach of these conditions cannot be visited with the<lb/> consequence of either withdrawal of exemption under Section 20(2) or<lb/> application of the other provisions of Chapter III after such withdrawal. If,<lb/> however, the exemption order together with its conditions could be<lb/> implemented or enforced by the State or any beneficiary of a scheme<lb/> sanctioned under Section 20(1), otherwise than by recourse to Section<lb/> 20(2) or other provisions of Chapter III of the Principal Act, when the<lb/> Principal Act was in force, there is no reason why such implementation or<lb/> enforcement is not possible after the repeal. Take the case of an<lb/> exemption order under Section 20(1) for a housing scheme with an<lb/> express condition of handing over a specified number of tenements to the<lb/> State Government. If the scheme is not implemented at all, the State has<lb/> no means of implementing the condition except by recourse to Section<lb/> 20(2) by withdrawing the exemption and applying the provisions of<lb/> Chapter III to the land. The Principal Act not being in force, this course is<lb/> not available to the State after the repeal. But if the scheme is<lb/> implemented, and a housing project is actually brought up on the land,<lb/> but the tenements have not been handed over to the State Government,<lb/> can the State Government not require the land owner to hand over the<lb/> tenements to the State Government, without withdrawing the exemption<lb/> under Section 20(2). The answer is yes. The State may go to a court of<lb/> law or devise any other means, legislative or executive, acceptable to law<lb/> to recover the possession of the tenements due to it. If the State could do<lb/> it when the principal statute was in force, there is no reason why it cannot<lb/> do so after the repeal, especially if the repealing statute expressly saves<lb/> the validity of both the exemption and the conditions on which it is based.<lb/> Take another case. An exemption order is issued under Section 20(1) in<lb/> respect of a land on a condition that such land shall be used only for<lb/> industrial purpose. This condition could have been implemented by the<lb/> State otherwise than by recourse to Section 20(2) of the Principal Act, say<lb/> by not sanctioning any plans for a non -industrial user. If the State could<lb/> do it before the repeal, it can do so even after the repeal. After all the<lb/> exemption order and its conditions are valid even after the repeal.<lb/> 42<lb/> In a sense, these are actions taken under the Principal Act<lb/> which have achieved a finality. In the case of the housing scheme referred<lb/> to in the example above, the housing scheme is completed. (It may even<lb/> be substantially completed.) The liability to hand over the tenements to<lb/> the Government has crystalized and has been incurred. The Government<lb/> in turn has acquired an enforceable right to get the tenements. In the<lb/> second case, namely, exemption on the condition of industrial user, the<lb/> exemption is a completed act. The land has been exempted under the<lb/> provisions of Section 20(1) on the condition that the only permissible user<lb/> would be the industrial user. No further act is required either on the part<lb/> of the landholder or the Government to make the condition enforceable.<lb/> The liability to not to use the land for a nonindustrial user is incurred by<lb/> the landholder and can be enforced by the Government in any manner<lb/> known to law.<lb/> 43<lb/> This, then, is the answer to the main question posed to the<lb/> Full Bench. What is saved by the saving clause of the repealing statute is<lb/> the validity of an exemption order, and it means the validity of both the<lb/> exemption and the conditions on which it is granted. But that does not<lb/> mean that the breach of any condition of the exemption order can be<lb/> visited with the consequence of either withdrawal of exemption under<lb/> Section 20(2) or application of Chapter III of the Principal Act to the land.<lb/> At the same time, if it were permissible to implement or enforce the<lb/> exemption order in any manner acceptable to law otherwise than by<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:40 :::<lb/> *218*<lb/> recourse to Section </content>
 
            <figDesc>20(2) or Chapter III of the Principal Act, such<lb/> implementation or enforcement is permissible even after the repeal.<lb/> 44<lb/> To this extent, I am not in agreement with the view expressed<lb/> by the Andhra Pradesh and Delhi High Courts, respectively, in Surendra<lb/> Raj Jaiswal vs. Government of Andhra Pradesh 1 and Tej Pratap Singh<lb/> vs. Union of India 2 . I am in respectful agreement with the view of the<lb/> learned Single Judge of Andhra Pradesh High Court in the case of<lb/> Surendra Raj Jaiswal (supra) that on noncompliance of conditions of an<lb/> exemption order, the State Government after the repeal of the Principal<lb/> Act was not empowered to withdraw the exemption granted under<lb/> Section 20(1). With respect, however, I do not agree with his view that in<lb/> the absence of the power to withdraw the exemption, the conditions have<lb/> become unenforceable and are nonest or that such land has become<lb/> freehold land irrespective of any conditions with regard to the usage of<lb/> the exempted land. So also, for the reasons discussed above, I am in<lb/> respectful disagreement with the statement of law by the Delhi High<lb/> Court in the case of Tej Pratap Singh (supra) that after the repeal, the<lb/> conditions of exemption, which remain unimplemented, cannot be<lb/> implemented because they are not specifically saved. The conditions are<lb/> saved because the exemption order as a whole is saved. They can even be<lb/> enforced, if the liability created thereby has been incurred, as discussed<lb/> above. One of the reasons cited by the Delhi High Court whilst arriving at<lb/> this conclusion was the provision of Section 3(1) (c) of the Repeal Act. In<lb/> Tej Pratap Singh&apos;s case (supra) the exemption under Section 20(1) was<lb/> granted on a condition requiring certain payment to be made to the State<lb/> Government. The Delhi High Court held that under Section 3(1) (c) the<lb/> actual payment was saved, but not the condition of payment. The Court<lb/> felt that had it not been specifically provided that the payment made to<lb/> the State Government was saved despite the repeal, the same would have<lb/> been affected by the repeal. From this, the Court deduced that in the<lb/> context of Section 6 of the General Clauses Act, the landholder&apos;s right to<lb/> exemption under Section 20(1) is specifically saved, but not the &apos;liability&apos;</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>Maharashtra and others deals with the question as to whether it was<lb/> open to the Collector and Competent Authority in that case to issue<lb/> instructions to the SubRegistrar of Assurances to not to register any<lb/> document. The view taken in that case that it was not open to the<lb/> Collector to issue such instructions as he had no Appellate, Supervisory<lb/> or Revisional powers over the Registering Officer, is correct and in<lb/> consonance with the law laid down by our Court in the case of<lb/> Sundersons &amp; Ors. Vs. State of Maharashtra &amp; Ors. The judgment in<lb/> Damodar Laxman Navare and others Vs. State of Maharashtra and<lb/> others does not deal with the question as to whether any order passed<lb/> before the repeal of the Principal Act under Section 10(1) or (3) in<lb/> respect of a land, after its exemption under Section 20(1) was withdrawn<lb/> under Section 20(2), is saved after the repeal. As held by me above, such<lb/> order does not survive the repeal of the Principal Act. In so far as the<lb/> judgment of our Court in Mira Bhayandar Builders and Developers<lb/> Welfare Association vs. The Deputy Collector and Competent<lb/> Authority is concerned, the view expressed therein that the landholders,<lb/> who have taken the benefit of the schemes under Section 20 of the<lb/> Principal Act by constructing buildings, cannot after the repeal of the<lb/> Principal Act wriggle out of their obligations to surrender flats to the<lb/> Government, is correct, but for the reasons discussed above. The legality<lb/> of the means adopted by the State Government or any other person for<lb/> holding the landholders to their respective obligations under such<lb/> schemes will, however, have to be decided in each case having regard to<lb/> the facts and circumstances of the individual case.<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> (S.C. Gupte, J.)<lb/> *********<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:40 :::<lb/> *224*<lb/> order made or </content>
 
            <figDesc>purported to be made under the principal Act pending<lb/> immediately before the commencement of this Act, before any Court, tribunal or<lb/> any other authority shall stand abated and that abatement shall not apply to the<lb/> proceedings relating to Section 11 to 14 of the principal Act, insofar as such<lb/> proceedings are relatable to the land, possession of which has been taken over by<lb/> the State Government. (Section 4)<lb/> 7.<lb/> The aforesaid consequences of the Repeal Act if seen in the context<lb/> of Section 3 of the Repeal Act, it becomes apparent that firstly the Repeal Act in<lb/> no uncertain terms saves vesting of any vacant land, possession of which has<lb/> been taken over by the State Government; secondly, the validity of any order<lb/> granting exemption under sub-section (1) of Section 20 or any action taken<lb/> thereunder is also saved.<lb/> 8.<lb/> The plain wordings of sub-clause (b) of Section 3(1) of the Repeal<lb/> Act are required to be given due meaning as they deserve. The interpretation of<lb/> sub-clause (b) of Section 3(1) is required to be meaningful so as to protect the<lb/> object which the provision intends to achieve. What is sought to be achieved is<lb/> the validity of an exemption order issued under sub-section (1) of Section 20 or<lb/> any action taken thereunder. Not only the validity of Section 20(1) is saved but<lb/> also any action taken thereunder notwithstanding any judgment of any Court to<lb/> the contrary.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>3</head>

            <figDesc>(1)(b) of the Repeal Act, an exemption order issued under Section 20(1) is<lb/> required to be kept in mind. A sample copy of the exemption order has been<lb/> tendered to the Court on behalf of the petitioners. A perusal of this exemption<lb/> exemption shall be deemed to have been withdrawn and vacant land and such<lb/> land with structures and the land appurtenant shall be acquired as per Chapter III<lb/> of ULC Act,1976.<lb/> (g)<lb/> that the exempted land with or without building shall not be transferred<lb/> except for the purpose of mortgage (in favour of financial institutions) failing<lb/> which the exemption granted shall stand withdrawn. Necessary returns are<lb/> required to be filed to the State Government in a prescribed form to show the<lb/> progress of the work done by the beneficiary. In case of breach of the order, it<lb/> shall be competent for the State Government to withdraw by an order exemption<lb/> from the date specified in the order.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>&quot; </head>
 
            <label>20</label>

            <head>. </head>
 
            <figDesc>Power to exempt: (1) Notwithstanding anything contained in any of<lb/> the foregoing provisions of this Chapter,................&quot;.(Emphasis<lb/> supplied)<lb/> It is therefore clear that power under section 20 is an independent power<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:41 :::<lb/> *230*<lb/> notwithstanding the other </content>
 
            <figDesc>provisions as contained in Chapter III namely section<lb/> 3 to section 19 and Section 21 to section 24.<lb/> If the Government exercises<lb/> powers under section 20 sub-section (1) such an exercise would be an<lb/> independent exercise, irrespective of the applicability of other provisions of the<lb/> provisions of chapter III. It certainly cannot be construed that once an<lb/> exemption order under section 20 sub-section (1) was issued, the land which is<lb/> otherwise subject to the provision of section 3 to section 19 of the Principal Act,<lb/> for the exemption becomes immune from the applicability of the said provisions,<lb/> the consequences of which are deemed to have taken place the moment of the<lb/> Act became applicable to such vacant land. Further once an exemption is granted<lb/> under section 20 (1) it is an admitted position that the land is a vacant land and<lb/> the beneficiary by his volition subjects himself to the terms and conditions of the<lb/> exemption order. Once this position is established a beneficiary of section 20 (1)<lb/> order cannot contend that everything under the exemption order has become<lb/> redundant due to the repeal of the Act. Such contention in my opinion is wholly<lb/> against the express provisions of section 3 (1) (b) of the Repeal Act which saves<lb/> the validity of an exemption order. It is therefore seen that Section 20 is in the<lb/> nature of an exception to the general rules as contained in Chapter III of the<lb/> principal Act which deal with the ceiling on vacant land and the manner in which<lb/> such lands would be dealt under the provisions of chapter III of the Act.<lb/> The intention of the Legislature which is apparent from the<lb/> wordings of Section 3(1)(b) of the Repeal Act is to save in totality the validity of<lb/> an order granting exemption under sub-section (1) of Section 20 of the Act or<lb/> any action taken thereunder. When the legislature saves the validity of a Section<lb/> 20(1) order which includes all the conditions including the condition that in case<lb/> of breach of any of the conditions provisions of Chapter III would become<lb/> applicable, then it will not be possible to read into the provisions of Section 3(1)<lb/> (b) of the Repeal Act that the legislature intended otherwise. In other words, the<lb/> validity of an exemption order as saved by Section 3(1)(b) of the Repeal Act<lb/> cannot be read de hors its conditions inasmuch as the said provision mandates<lb/> that an order granting exemption under Sub-section (1) of Section 20 is valid<lb/> wholesomely. It would be an absurdity to say that such an exemption order<lb/> would remain valid de hors the conditions on which it is issued. The word<lb/> &quot;validity&quot; as used in Section 3(1)(b) is of considerable significance. Black Law<lb/> Dictionary (8th Edition) would refer the word &quot;valid&quot; to mean as under:-<lb/>&quot;legally sufficient, binding, a valid contract&quot;<lb/> If this is what the Legislature intended then necessarily the validity<lb/> of an exemption order under Section 20(1) would include all attributes necessary<lb/> to keep an exemption order valid and therefore would also include the<lb/> applicability of Chapter III of the Principal Act. De hors the applicability of<lb/> Chapter III which is one of the prime conditions of a Section 20(1) exemption<lb/> order, the validity of such exemption order as saved by the provisions of Section<lb/> 3(1)(b) of the Repeal Act would be rendered meaningless. In any event the<lb/> beneficiary of an exemption order can be the last person to quarrel about this<lb/> proposition as he has accepted the exemption order in totality which includes<lb/> acceptance to the applicability of Chapter III of the Principal Act.<lb/> It is well settled that if the words used by the legislature in framing the<lb/> legislation have a necessary meaning, it is the duty of the Court to construe the<lb/> clause accordingly irrespective of the inconvenience that may be caused<lb/> (Argumentum Ab Inconvenienti Plurimum Valet In Lege). In the context of a<lb/> Section 20 exemption order and considering the plain reading of section 3 (1) (b)<lb/> of the Repeal Act the interpretation as suggested by the petitioners would lead to<lb/> extravagant results, away from the object which the saving provision intends to<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:41 :::<lb/> achieve.<lb/> It is settled </content>
 
            <figDesc>that a saving provision in a repeal statute is not<lb/> exhaustive of the rights, obligations so saved or rights that survives the repeal as<lb/> is clear from the judgment of the Constitution Bench in the case of &quot;Bansidhar<lb/> &amp; Ors. Vs. State of Rajasthan &amp; ors&quot; reported in (1998) 2 SCC 557 It is,<lb/> therefore, imperative that Section 6 of the General Clauses Act which provides<lb/> for the effect of a repeal, stands completely attracted. Section 6(c) of the<lb/> General Clauses Act provides that the repeal shall not affect any right, privilege,<lb/> obligation or liability acquired, accrued or incurred under any enactment was<lb/> repealed unless a different intention appears.<lb/> A proper examination of the provisions of the Repeal Act and more<lb/> particularly the provisions of Sections 3 and 4 do not indicate that it would be<lb/> the intention of the Legislature to save the validity of a Section 20(1) Exemption<lb/> Order to exclude the enforcing power being applicability of Chapter III of the<lb/> Principal Act being one of the conditions under the exemption order. It cannot<lb/> be said that the rights accrued and the liabilities incurred under Section 20(1)<lb/> exemption order stands completely effaced when the validity of such an<lb/> exemption order has been saved by the provisions of Section 3(1)(b) of the<lb/> Repeal Act. As no such contrary intention can be gathered from the provisions<lb/> of the Repeal Act, the petitioner&apos;s contentions that the validity of the exemption<lb/> order as saved by Section 3(1)(b) of the Repeal Act is valid de hors the<lb/> conditions of the exemption order cannot be accepted on the basis of the plain<lb/> wordings of Section 3(1)(b) of the Repeal Act. In the decision of the Supreme<lb/> Court in the case of &quot;Shantibai Gaikwad Vs. Shivajibhai Haribhai&quot; reported in<lb/> &quot;2005(5) SCC 101&quot;, the Supreme Court has once again recognized the principle<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:41 :::<lb/> *233*<lb/> FULL.BENCH.JUDGMENT.sxw<lb/> that a repealing </content>
 
            <figDesc>statute is not exhaustive and does not automatically extinguish<lb/> accrued rights unless they are taken away completely. The Repeal Act in no<lb/> manner expressly takes away the applicability of the conditions under Section<lb/> 20(1) exemption order. In fact the intention of the legislature is to wholesomely<lb/> save the validity of an exemption order which ipso facto include the teeth<lb/> namely to take action under Chapter III of the Principal Act in case of breach of<lb/> the condition under which an exemption has been granted for the beneficiary of<lb/> the Section 20(1) of the order.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            (a)<lb/> Section 3(1)(</content>

            <figDesc>b) of the Repeal Act saves the validity of an order<lb/> granting exemption under sub-section (1) of Section 20 or any action taken<lb/> thereunder, notwithstanding any judgment of any Court to the contrary.</figDesc>
        </figure>



    </text>
</tei>

