<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_72062a7a70a97f325732c09a3e3fd04b.pdf"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">


		<figure type="table">

            <note>Bombay<lb/> Cases Reporter 85, Damodar Laxman Navre &amp; 4 others<lb/> Vs. State of Maharashtra &amp; 4 others Writ Petition No.<lb/> 6300 of 2009, delivered previously by the Division<lb/> Bench of this Court. However, there is a conflicting view<lb/> expressed in the judgments delivered by the Division<lb/> Bench of this Court in Writ Petition No.5745 of 2009<lb/> Mira Bhayander Builders &amp; Developers Welfare<lb/> Association Vs. Dy. Collector &amp; Competent Authority,<lb/> Thane and 3 others. The Circular dated 23.6.2008 was<lb/> the epicentre of controversy in Mira Bhayander Builders<lb/> &amp; Developers Welfare Association</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:38 :::</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:38 :::</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>1<lb/> Mohamed Ashref Noor v/s State of Tamil Nadu, in<lb/> Writ Petition No.6856/2003 decided on 16.12.2009<lb/> by the Madras High Court.<lb/> 2<lb/> Surendra Raj Jaiswal v/s Government of Andhra<lb/> Pradesh, in Writ Petition No.26474/2009 decided<lb/> on 24.08.2011 by a Single Judge of Andhra Pradesh<lb/> High Court.<lb/> 3<lb/> The Principal Secretary to Government, Hyderabad<lb/> v/s Surendra, in Writ Petition No.951/2012 decided<lb/> on 25.07.2012 by the Division Bench of Andhra<lb/> Pradesh High Court.<lb/> 4<lb/> M/s Suri Industries v/s State of Tamil Nadu, in Writ<lb/> Petition No.8610/2013 decided on 06.09.2010 by<lb/> the Madras High Court.<lb/> 5<lb/> Manik M. Ragit v/s State of Maharashtra reported<lb/> in 2013 (2) Mh.L.J. 224. (WP No.1290/2012<lb/> decided on 30.07.2012 Nagpur Bench).<lb/> 6<lb/> M/s Nile Limited v/s State of Andhra Pradesh, in<lb/> Writ<lb/> Petition<lb/> No.23846/2008<lb/> decided<lb/> on<lb/> 06.11.2013 by the Andhra Pradesh High Court.<lb/> 7<lb/> State of Uttar Pradesh v/s Hari Ram reported in<lb/> (2013) 4 SCC 280.<lb/> 8<lb/> M/s </table>
 
            <figDesc>Tata Coffee Limited v/s Government of Andhra<lb/> Pradesh, in Writ Petition No.11929/2013 decided<lb/> on 22.07.2013 by the Andhra Pradesh High Court.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <note>9<lb/> Gajanan Kamlya Patil v/s Additional Collector and<lb/> Competent Authority, in Civil Appeal Nos.2070<lb/> 2071/2014 arising out of SLP (C) Nos.1490414905<lb/> of 2011 decided on 14.02.2014 by the Honourable<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>Supreme Court.<lb/> 10<lb/> M/s L.G. Polymers India Private Limited v/s State of<lb/> Andhra Pradesh, in Writ Petition No.21934/2013<lb/> decided on 28.03.2014 by the Andhra Pradesh High<lb/> Court.<lb/> 11<lb/> Synco Industries Limited v/s Assessing Officer,<lb/> Income Tax, Mumbai reported in (2008) 4 SCC 22.<lb/> 12<lb/> Tej Pratap Singh v/s Union of India, in Writ Petition<lb/> (C) No.2455/1992 decided on 16.07.2009 by the<lb/> Delhi High Court.<lb/> The submissions of Mr.Naphade have been adopted by<lb/> Mr.Milind Sathe, learned Senior Counsel appearing for the Writ<lb/> Petitioners in Writ Petition Nos.2201/2009, 3815/2010 and 9703/2010.</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>State of Uttar Pradesh<lb/> reported in (2007) 11 SCC 90.<lb/> 2<lb/> Voltas Limited v/s Additional Collector and<lb/> Competent Authority, reported in 2008 (5) Bom.<lb/> C.R. 746.<lb/> 3<lb/> Shanti Bhardwaj v/s State of U.P., reported in<lb/> (2004) 10 SCC 130.<lb/> 4<lb/> Vinayak Kashinath Shilkar v/s Deputy Collector and<lb/> Competent Authority, reported in (2012) 4 SCC<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>*25*<lb/> <note>FULL.BENCH.JUDGMENT.sxw<lb/> 15<lb/> Maharaj Singh v/s State of Uttar Pradesh, reported<lb/> in (1977) 1 SCC 155.<lb/> 16<lb/> Union of India v/s Somasundaram Viswanath,<lb/> reported in (1989) 1 SCC 175.<lb/> 17<lb/> John Thomas v/s </note>
 
            <figDesc>The Government of Tamil Nadu,<lb/> in Writ Petition No.38507/2002 decided on<lb/> 29.01.2007 by the Madras High Court.<lb/> 18<lb/> L. Kannappan and L. Thirunavukarasu v/s The<lb/> Government of Tamil Nadu, in Writ Petition<lb/> No.46091/2002 decided on 29.01.2007 by the<lb/> Madras High Court.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>19<lb/> Anil Nemichand Bafna v/s State of Maharashtra, in<lb/> Writ Petition No.153/2008 decided on 06.05.2010<lb/> by the Bombay High Court.<lb/> 20<lb/> Surendra Raj Jaiswal v/s Government of Andhra<lb/> Pradesh, in Writ Petition No.26474/2009 decided<lb/> on 24.08.2011 by a Single Judge of Andhra Pradesh<lb/> High Court.<lb/> 21<lb/> Manik M. Ragit v/s State of Maharashtra reported<lb/> in 2013 (2) Mh.L.J. 224. (WP No.1290/2012<lb/> decided on 30.07.2012 Nagpur Bench).<lb/> 22<lb/> State of Uttar Pradesh v/s Hari Ram reported in<lb/> (2013) 4 SCC 280.<lb/> 24<lb/> Mr.Naphade&apos;s submissions then have been adopted by<lb/> Mr.Gangal, learned Counsel appearing for the Petitioners in Writ Petition<lb/> No.5024/2013. He went further to contend that what is saved by virtue of<lb/> Section 3(1)(b) of the Repeal Act is the validity of the order of exemption,<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>but not the conditions subject to which such exemption is granted. In that<lb/> regard Mr.Gangal relied upon the following judgments:<lb/> <note>::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:38 :::<lb/> 1<lb/> Shanti Bhardwaj v/s State of U.P., reported in<lb/> (2004) 10 SCC 130.<lb/> 2<lb/> L. Kannappan and L. Thirunavukarasu v/s </note>
 
            <figDesc>The<lb/> Government of Tamil Nadu, in Writ Petition<lb/> No.46091/2002 decided on 29.01.2007 by the<lb/> Madras High Court.<lb/> 3<lb/> Surendra Raj Jaiswal v/s Government of Andhra<lb/> Pradesh, in Writ Petition No.26474/2009 decided<lb/> on 24.08.2011 by a Single Judge of Andhra Pradesh<lb/> High Court.<lb/> 25<lb/> Then Mr.Sridharan, learned Senior Counsel appearing for the<lb/> Petitioners in Writ Petition Nos.2243/2011 and 2244/2011, argued that<lb/> the Repeal Act envisages application of same in the first instance to the<lb/> whole of the State of Haryana and Punjab and to all the Union territories.</figDesc>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>section (1) of Section 3 the liability incurred under the exemption order is<lb/> not saved, but only the payment made to the State Government as a<lb/> condition for granting exemption under Section 20(1) is unaffected and<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>thus, saved. Beyond all this we should not read anything into the Repeal<lb/> Act. Mr.Sridharan relied upon the following decisions in support of the<lb/> <note>::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:38 :::<lb/> above contentions:<lb/> 1<lb/> Kolhapur Canesugar Works Limited v/s Union of<lb/> India, reported in (2000) 2 SCC 536.<lb/> 2<lb/> Air India v/s Union of India, reported in (1995) 4<lb/> SCC 734.<lb/> <note>3<lb/> Union of India v/s West Coast Paper Mills Limited,<lb/> reported in 2004 (164) E.L.T. 375 (SC).<lb/> 4<lb/> Shri Prithvi Cotton Mills Limited v/s Broach<lb/> Borough Municipality, reported in 2000 (123) ELT 3<lb/> (SC).<lb/> 27<lb/> It is pertinent to note that Mr.Sridharan&apos;s main argument has<lb/> not been supported or adopted by any counsel. It is clear that<lb/> Mr.Naphade&apos;s contentions and submissions as adopted by Mr.Sathe are<lb/> further adopted and elaborated by Mr.Devitre, learned Senior Counsel<lb/> appearing in the Original Side Writ Petition No.37/2010 and Mr.Samdani,<lb/> learned Senior Counsel appearing in Writ Petition No.346/2011. Both of<lb/> them have urged that a different intention appears in clause (b) of sub<lb/> section (1) of Section 3 of the Repeal Act and therefore, Section 6 of the<lb/> General Clauses Act has no application. The specific saving is for the<lb/> benefit of the land holders and therefore, there is no scope for construing<lb/> clause (b) of subsection (1) of Section 3 of the Repeal Act on equitable<lb/> principles. Once there is no room for equitable considerations and<lb/> particularly as Mr.Samdani urges because of the Principal Act being<lb/> expropriatory in nature and providing for compulsory acquisition, then,<lb/> all the more any liberal construction is ruled out. Mr.Samdani submits<lb/> that even the saving clause has to be strictly construed in this case and<lb/> the repeal of the Principal Act wipes out the same and obliterates it from<lb/> <note>::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:38 :::<lb/> the statute book completely. For all these reasons the Reference should be<lb/> answered accordingly.<lb/> 28<lb/> Mr.Devitre and Mr.Samdani relied upon the following<lb/> decisions:<lb/> 1<lb/> Mohan Gopalrao Mate v/s Principal Secretary,<lb/> reported in 2009 (1) Bom. C.R. 275.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>2<lb/> Parripati Chandrasekharrao and Sons v/s Alapati<lb/> Jalaiah, reported in (1995) 3 SCC 709.<lb/> 3<lb/> Khub Chand v/s State of Rajasthan, reported in AIR<lb/> 1967 SC 1074.<lb/> 4<lb/> Gujarat Electricity Board v/s Girdharlal Motilal,<lb/> reported in AIR 1969 SC 267.<lb/> 5<lb/> State of Maharashtra v/s B.E. Billimoria, reported in<lb/> (2003) 7 SCC 336.<lb/> 6<lb/> Corporation of the City of Victoria v/s Bishop of<lb/> Vancouver Island, reported in AIR 1921 PC 240.<lb/> 7<lb/> T.R. Thandur v/s Union of India, reported in (1996)<lb/> 3 SCC 690.<lb/> 29<lb/> Mr.Aniruddha Joshi, learned Counsel appearing for the<lb/> Petitioners in Writ Petition No.9872/2010 invites our attention to the<lb/> judgment of the Division Bench of this Court in the case of Vithabai Bama<lb/> Bhandari v/s State of Maharashtra (supra) and submits that there is<lb/> nothing sacrosanct about Section 20 of the Principal Act. By indirect<lb/> process we cannot, therefore, save what is not expressly saved by the<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>Repeal Act. Once the power to exempt cannot be exercised and not<lb/> available after the Repeal Act, then, merely because such power is<lb/> exercised during the subsistence of the Principal Act and prior to the<lb/> Repeal Act coming into force does not mean that further or incidental<lb/> power envisaged by the primary power to exempt is saved. Even this<lb/> incidental or ancillary power is unavailable after repeal of the Principal<lb/> Act. This argument is built more or less on the wording of Section 21 of<lb/> the General Clauses Act, 1897.<lb/> 30<lb/> Ms.GadreRajyadhyaksha, learned counsel appearing for the<lb/> Petitioners in Writ Petition No.556/2010, while adopting all arguments of<lb/> all the Senior Counsel only submitted that when more than one High<lb/> Court in this country have placed an interpretation on the Parliamentary<lb/> Statute or construed its provisions in a particular way, then, for the sake<lb/> of consistency and certainty this Court must follow the reasoning of the<lb/> Delhi High Court, Madras High Court and Andhra Pradesh High Court.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>31<lb/> Mr.Joshi and Ms.GadreRajyadhyaksha relied upon the<lb/> following judgments in support of the above submissions:<lb/> 1<lb/> Damodar Laxman Navare v/s State of Maharashtra,<lb/> in Writ Petition No.6300/2009 decided on<lb/> 08.07.2010 by the Bombay High Court : Reported in<lb/> 2010(6) Bom. C.R. 611.<lb/> 2<lb/> Commissioner of Income Tax, Bombay v/s Alcock<lb/> Ashdown &amp; Company Limited, reported in 1979 ITR<lb/> page 164 : in Income Tax Reference No.40/1969<lb/> decided on 07.07.1978 by the Bombay High Court.<lb/> 3<lb/> Commissioner of Income Tax, Bombay v/s T.<lb/> Maneklal Mfg. Co. Ltd., reported in 1978 ITR<lb/> Vol.115 page 725.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>4<lb/> Bhagwat Dharmaraj Radke v/s State of<lb/> Maharashtra, in Special Leave to Appeal (Civil)<lb/> No.35883/2012 decided on 31.03.2014 by the<lb/> Honourable Supreme Court.<lb/> <note>5<lb/> Government of Karnataka v/s Gowramma and<lb/> others, reported in AIR 2008 SC 863.<lb/> 32<lb/> On the other hand, Mr.Khambata, learned Advocate General<lb/> appearing on behalf of the State submits that it is fallacious to assume<lb/> that the State or other Respondents, namely, Authorities under the<lb/> Principal Act are requesting this Court to go by any equitable<lb/> consideration or liberal principle. The State has throughout maintained<lb/> that in terms of the Preamble of the Principal Act and Constitutional<lb/> philosophy as enshrined by Articles 21 and 39(b) and (c) of the<lb/> Constitution of India a ceiling has been placed by the Principal Act on the<lb/> holding of vacant land within the urban agglomeration. This ceiling limit,<lb/> as is reflected from the Principal Act and which cannot be disputed, is<lb/> placed by a statutory prescription that is to be found in Section 4 of the<lb/> Principal Act. ChapterIII of the Principal Act is titled as &quot;ceiling on vacant<lb/> land&quot;. Except as otherwise provided in the Principal Act on and from the<lb/> commencement of the Principal Act no person shall be entitled to hold<lb/> any vacant land in excess of the ceiling limit in the territories to which<lb/> this Act applies under subsection (2) of Section 1. The obligation under<lb/> the statute is, therefore, clear and absolute. It relates and dates back to<lb/> the commencement of the Principal Act. None can dispute that what is<lb/> exempted from the purview of ChapterIII and by a overriding power<lb/> conferred in the State Government is the applicability of ChapterIII to the<lb/> vacant land in excess of ceiling limit. Therefore, when the excess vacant<lb/> land is exempted in exceptional circumstances and which have been also<lb/> specified by the statute, then, all that happens is that the excess vacant<lb/> land is exempted from the provisions of ChapterIII either conditionally or<lb/> <note>::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:38 :::</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>taken thereunder, but other consequences flowing from such valid<lb/> exemption order or any valid action taken thereunder are ruled out, that<lb/> is an erroneous submission. Relying on Bansidhar&apos;s case (supra) it is<lb/> submitted that intention contrary to the applicability of Section 6 of the<lb/> General Clauses Act is not to be assumed only with reference to what is<lb/> expressly saved and it cannot be further assumed that what is not<lb/> expressly saved stands destroyed or obliterated. An express saving clause<lb/> necessarily does not reflect intention contrary to the applicability of<lb/> Section 6 of the General Clauses Act. Therefore, the reference needs to be<lb/> answered accordingly.<lb/> 40<lb/> The learned Advocate General while ending his submissions<lb/> urged that the decisions in the case of Voltas Limited v/s Additional<lb/> Collector &amp; Competent Authority reported in </table>
 
            <head>2008(5) Bom.C.R. 746,<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>Vithabai Bama Bhandari v/s State of Maharashtra reported in 2009(3)<lb/> Bom. C.R. 663 and Sundersons and others v/s State of Maharashtra and<lb/> others reported in 2008 (5) Bombay Cases Reporter 85 or any<lb/> observations therein are not binding on construction and interpretation of<lb/> Section 3(1)(b) and (c) of the Repeal Act. At best, the observations and<lb/> findings in these decisions can be applied to a case falling under Section<lb/> 3(1)(a) of the Repeal Act. In that regard as well some further conclusions<lb/> rendered in Voltas Case (supra) and all above decisions contrary to what<lb/> is held in Bansidhar&apos;s Case (supra) do not lay down the correct law. In<lb/> fact Bansidhar&apos;s case (supra) was cited before the Division Bench in Votlas<lb/> Case (supra), but the Division Bench completely omitted it from<lb/> consideration and made some sweeping observations. These observations,<lb/> findings and conclusions in Voltas (supra) have been followed in Vithabai<lb/> (supra), Sundersons (supra) and in Mohan Gopalrao Mate v/s Principal<lb/> Secretary and others </table>
 
            <head>reported in 2009(1) Bom. C.R. 275, all </head>
 
            <table>of which,<lb/> therefore and to the extent indicated above must be held to be not laying<lb/> down the correct law.<lb/> 41<lb/> These submissions of the learned Advocate General are fully<lb/> adopted by Mr.P.K.Dhakephalkar, learned Senior Counsel appearing in<lb/> some of the petitions for the State. He has take us through the scheme of<lb/> Section 6 of the General Clauses Act and particularly the words of clause<lb/> (b) thereof to urge that the exemption order including the conditions<lb/> thereunder and all legal consequences survive the repeal of the Principal<lb/> Act. That is the only construction which can be placed on Section 3 of the<lb/> Repeal Act.<lb/> 42<lb/> The learned Advocate General and Mr.Dhakephalkar have<lb/> relied upon the following decisions:<lb/> 1<lb/> State of Punjab v/s Mohar Singh Pratap Singh,<lb/> reported in AIR 1955 SC 84.<lb/> 2<lb/> Brihan Maharashtra Sugar Syndicate v/s Janardan<lb/> Ramchandra Kulkarni, reported in AIR 1960 SC<lb/> 794.<lb/> 3<lb/> Her Highness Maharani Shantidevi P. Gaikwad v/s<lb/> Savjibhai Haribhai Patel, reported in (2001) 5 SCC<lb/> reported in (2008) 14 SCC 283.<lb/> 18<lb/> Rajendra Kumar v/s State of Madhya Pradesh,<lb/> reported in AIR 1979 Madhya Pradesh 108.<lb/> 19<lb/> S.N. Rao v/s State of Maharashtra, reported in<lb/> (1988) 1 SCC 586.<lb/> 20<lb/> TCI Industries Limited v/s Municipal Corporation of<lb/> Greater Bombay, reported in 2012(5) Bom. C.R.<lb/> 353.<lb/> 21<lb/> Bansidhar and others v/s State of Rajasthan,<lb/> reported in (1989) 2 SCC 557.<lb/> 22<lb/> Hasan Nurani Malak v/s S.M.Ismail, Assistant<lb/> Charity Commissioner, reported in AIR 1967 SC<lb/> 1742.<lb/> 23<lb/> M/s Universal Imports Agency v/s Chief Controller<lb/> of Imports and Exports, reported in AIR 1961 SC 41.<lb/> 24<lb/> State of Punjab v/s Harnek Singh, reported in<lb/> (2002) 3 SCC 481.<lb/> 25<lb/> Deep Chand v/s State of U.P., reported in AIR 1959<lb/> SC 648.<lb/> 43<lb/> A brief rejoinder was given by Mr.Naphade to these<lb/> contentions and he urged that each of the judgments cited by the learned<lb/> Advocate General are with reference to the statutes which are not<lb/> parimateria with the Principal Act or the Repeal Act. Therefore,<lb/> Bansidhar&apos;s case (supra) and other judgments are distinguishable. Even<lb/> otherwise the judgments are not to be read like statutes. One cannot<lb/> construe the Repeal Act and as clear in the present case to mean reviving<lb/> the Principal Act. In Bansidhar (supra) and other cases cited there was no<lb/> plain and express repeal, but a reenactment of the earlier legislation or<lb/> law. The Rajasthan Ceiling Act of 1955 was replaced or repealed by a<lb/> later Ceiling Act. That is, therefore, a case of reenactment. In the<lb/> reenacted statute there was a saving clause, namely, Section 15 of the<lb/> Rajasthan Act No.VIII of 1976. That indicated that earlier Ceiling Law,<lb/> namely, Act of 1955 was still on the statute book albeit for a limited<lb/> purpose. That is how paragraph 24 of Bansidhar&apos;s judgment (supra)<lb/> would read. Thus, the factual matrix was different. In the present case,<lb/> the Repeal Act destroys many provisions of the Principal Act. Sections 21<lb/> and 22 of the Principal Act are not saved and therefore, parimateria<lb/> provision like Section 20(2) cannot be held to be saved. Similarly all cases<lb/> which have been cited by the learned Advocate General on the law<lb/> enacting ceiling on agricultural lands are inapplicable because firstly<lb/> those Acts are not parimateria. Secondly, interpretation on the provisions<lb/> of those Acts was placed by the Honourable Supreme Court when the said<lb/> Acts were existing on the statute book and not repealed. That is why<lb/> these judgments cannot be cited as precedent for applicability of Section 6<lb/> of the General Clauses Act to the present case. Lastly, Mr.Naphade would<lb/> submit that the learned Advocate General was in error in placing reliance<lb/> on the decision of the Honourable Supreme Court in the case of Smt.Atia<lb/> Mohammadi Begum v/s State of U.P. reported in AIR 1993 SC 2465<lb/> because this decision is expressly dissented from in a later decision of the<lb/> Honourable Supreme Court in Her Highness Maharani Shantidevi P.<lb/> Gaikwad vs. Savjibhai Haribhai Patel and Others reported in (2001) 5 SCC<lb/> 101. It is overruled. Thus, if ChapterIII of the Principal Act is the heart of<lb/> the said law and its applicability is ruled out completely and not<lb/> temporarily as urged, then, the said ChapterIII does not survive repeal of<lb/> the Principal Act. For these reasons the Reference must be answered in<lb/> terms urged by the Petitioners.<lb/> 44<lb/> For properly appreciating the rival contentions a reference<lb/> firstly to the Principal Act and thereafter, the Repeal Act is necessary. In<lb/> AIR 1979 SC 1415 (Union of India v/s Valluri Basavaiah Chouwdhary),<lb/> the Honourable Supreme Court outlined the object and purpose of the<lb/> Principal Act in the following words:<lb/> &quot;6.<lb/> The primary object and the purpose of the Urban<lb/> Land (Ceiling and Regulation) Act, 1976, &apos;the Act&apos;, as<lb/> the long title and the preamble show, is to provide for<lb/> the imposition of a ceiling on vacant land in urban<lb/> agglomerations, for the acquisition of such land in<lb/> excess of the ceiling limit, to regulate the construction<lb/> of buildings on such land and for matters connected<lb/> therewith, with a view to preventing the<lb/> concentration of urban land in the hands of a few<lb/> persons and speculation and profiteering therein, and<lb/> with a view to bringing about an equitable<lb/> distribution of land in urban agglomerations to<lb/> subserve the common good, in furtherance of the<lb/> directive principles of Art.39(b) and (c).&quot;<lb/> 45<lb/> ChapterI of the Principal Act contains preliminary<lb/> provisions. Firstly, by Section 1 short title, application and<lb/> commencement is set out and by virtue of subsection (2) thereof the<lb/> Principal Act becomes applicable to the State of Maharashtra in the first</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>provision, namely, Section 5 sets out as to what are the consequences on<lb/> such vacant land being transferred at any time during the period<lb/> commencing on the appointed day and ending with the commencement<lb/> of the Principal Act. Then, Section 6 requires the persons holding vacant<lb/> land in excess of ceiling limit to file a statement. Section 6 of the Principal<lb/> Act reads as under:<lb/> &quot;6.<lb/> Persons holding vacant land in excess of ceiling limit<lb/> to file statement:<lb/> (1)<lb/> Every person holding vacant land in excess of the<lb/> ceiling limit at the commencement of this Act shall,<lb/> within such period as may be prescribed, file a<lb/> statement before the competent authority having<lb/> jurisdiction specifying the location, extent, value and<lb/> such other particulars as may be prescribed of all<lb/> vacant lands and of any other land on which there is<lb/> a building, whether or not with a dwelling unit<lb/> therein, held by him (including the nature of his<lb/> right, title or interest therein) and also specifying the<lb/> vacant lands within the ceiling limit which he desires<lb/> to retain:<lb/> Provided that in relation to any State to which this<lb/> Act applies in the first instance, the provisions of this<lb/> subsection shall have effect as if for the words &quot;Every<lb/> person holding vacant land in excess of the ceiling<lb/> limit and the commencement of this Act&quot;, the words,<lb/> figures and letters &quot;Every person who held vacant<lb/> land in excess of the ceiling limit on or after the 17th<lb/> day of February, 1975 and before the commencement<lb/> of this Act and every person holding vacant land in<lb/> excess of the ceiling limit at such commencement&quot; had<lb/> been substituted.<lb/> Explanation. -In this section, &quot;commencement of this Act&quot;<lb/> means, -<lb/>(i)<lb/> the date on which this Act comes into force in<lb/> any State;<lb/> (ii) where any land, not being vacant land,<lb/> situated in a State in which this Act is in force has<lb/> become vacant land by any reason whatsoever, the<lb/> date on which such land becomes vacant land;<lb/> (iii) where any notification has been issued under<lb/> clause (n) of section 2 in respect of any area in a<lb/> State in which this Act is in force; the date of<lb/> publication of such notification.<lb/> (2)<lb/> If the competent authority is of opinion that -<lb/>(a) in any State to which this Act applies in the<lb/> first instance, any person held on or after the 17th<lb/> day of February, 1975 and before the commencement<lb/> of this Act or holds at such commencement; or<lb/> (b) in any State which adopts this Act under clause<lb/> (1) of Article 252 of the Constitution, any person<lb/> holds at the commencement of this Act,<lb/> vacant land in excess of the ceiling limit, then,<lb/> notwithstanding anything contained in subsection<lb/> (1), it may serve a notice upon such person requiring<lb/> him to file, within such period as may be specified in<lb/> the notice, the statement referred to in subsection<lb/> (1).<lb/> (3)<lb/> The competent authority may, if it is satisfied that it<lb/> is necessary so to do, extend the date for filing the<lb/> statement under this section by such further period or<lb/> periods as it may think fit; so, however, that the<lb/> period or the aggregate of the periods of such<lb/> extension shall not exceed three months.<lb/> (4)<lb/> The statement under this section shall be filed, -<lb/>(a) in the case of an individual, by the individual<lb/> himself; where the individual is absent from India, by<lb/> the Individual concerned or by some person duly<lb/> authorised by him in this behalf; and where the<lb/> individual is mentally incapacitated from attending<lb/> to his affairs, by his guardian or any other person<lb/> competent to act on his behalf;<lb/> (b) in the case of a family, by the husband or wife<lb/> and where the husband or wife is absent from India<lb/> or is mentally incapacitated from attending to his or<lb/> her affairs, by the husband or wife who is not so<lb/> absent or mentally incapacitated and where both the<lb/> husband and the wife are absent from India or are<lb/> mentally incapacitated from attending to their<lb/> affairs, by any other person competent to act on<lb/> behalf of the husband or wife or both;<lb/> (c) in the case of a company, by the principal<lb/> officer thereof;<lb/> (d) in the case of a firm, by any partner thereof;<lb/> (e) in the case of any other association, by any<lb/> member of the association or the principal officer<lb/> thereof; and<lb/> (f)<lb/> in the case of any other person, by that person<lb/> or by a </table>
 
            <head>person competent to act on his behalf.<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>Explanation. -For the purposes of this subsection, &quot;principal<lb/> officer&quot;, -<lb/>(i)<lb/> in relation to a company, means the secretary,<lb/> manager or managingdirector of the company;<lb/> (ii) in relation to any association, means the<lb/> secretary, treasurer, manager or agent of the<lb/> association,</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>3)<lb/> At any time after the publication of the notification<lb/> under subsection (1), the competent authority may,<lb/> by notification published in the Official Gazette of the<lb/> State concerned, declare that the excess vacant land<lb/> referred to in the notification published under sub<lb/> section (1) shall, with effect from such date as may be<lb/> specified in the declaration, be deemed to have been<lb/> acquired by the State Government and upon the<lb/> publication of such declaration, such land shall be<lb/> deemed to have vested absolutely in the State<lb/> Government free from all encumbrances with effect<lb/> from the date so specified.<lb/> (4)<lb/> During the period commencing on the date of<lb/> publication of the notification under subsection (1)<lb/> and ending with the date specified in the declaration<lb/> made under subsection (3) -<lb/>(i)<lb/> no person shall transfer by way of sale,<lb/> mortgage, gift, lease or otherwise any excess vacant<lb/> land (including any part thereof) specified in the<lb/> notification aforesaid and any such transfer made in<lb/> contravention of this provision shall be deemed to be<lb/> null and void; and<lb/> (ii) no person shall alter or cause to be altered the<lb/> use of such excess vacant land.<lb/> (5)<lb/> Where any vacant land is vested in the State<lb/> Government under subsection (3), the competent<lb/> authority may, by notice in writing, order any person<lb/> who may be in possession of it to surrender or deliver<lb/> possession thereof to the State Government or to any<lb/> person duly authorised by the State Government in<lb/> this behalf within thirty days of the service of the<lb/> notice.<lb/> (6)<lb/> If any person refuses or fails to comply with an order<lb/> made under subsection (5), the competent authority<lb/> may take possession of the vacant land or cause it to<lb/> be given to the concerned State Government or to any<lb/> person duly authorised by such State Government in<lb/> this behalf and may for that purpose use such force as<lb/> may be necessary.<lb/> Explanation. -In this section, in subsection (1) of section 11<lb/> and in sections 14 and 23, &quot;State Government&quot;, in<lb/> relation to -<lb/>(a) any vacant land owned by the Central<lb/> Government, means the Central Government;<lb/> (b) any vacant land owned by any State<lb/> Government and situated in a Union territory or<lb/> within the local limits of a cantonment declared as<lb/> such under section 3 of the Cantonments Act, 1924,<lb/> (2 of 1924), means that State Government.&quot;<lb/> 47<lb/> A bare perusal thereof would indicate that it is providing for<lb/> acquisition of vacant land in excess of ceiling limit. Sections 11 to 14<lb/> create a mechanism for the purpose of payment of amount for vacant<lb/> lands acquired in terms of Section 10. By Section 15 there is a ceiling<lb/> limit on future acquisition by inheritance, bequest or by sale in execution<lb/> of decrees, etc. Then, there are other consequences which are to be found<lb/> when the Principal Act is adopted subsequently by any State. Then the<lb/> persons can file the statement and in relation to such State within the<lb/> time specified by Section 16. By Section 17 the power is given to enter<lb/> upon any vacant land. By Section 18 there are penalties provided for<lb/> concealment etc. of particulars or furnishing inaccurate particulars of<lb/> *57*<lb/> FULL.BENCH.JUDGMENT.sxw<lb/> vacant land. Section 19 states that the Chapter will not apply to certain<lb/> vacant lands and those are specified in subsection (1) of Section 19. By<lb/> subsection (2) of Section 19 the intent of the legislature is further<lb/> clarified inasmuch as there is distinction between the Chapter not<lb/> applying to certain vacant lands and exemption to vacant lands from the<lb/> provisions of the Chapter. By subsection (2) of Section 19 it is clarified<lb/> that the provisions of subsection (1) of Section 19 shall not be construed<lb/> as granting any exemption in favour of any person other than an<lb/> authority, institution or organization specified in subsection (1). Such<lb/> persons may be possessing any vacant land which is owned by such<lb/> authority, institution or organization. In other words, the Chapter is not<lb/> applicable to vacant lands which are owned by an authority, institution or<lb/> organization. Similarly, if any such authority, institution or organization<lb/> possesses any vacant land belonging to a person, then, that person/<lb/> owner does not derive any benefit or advantage merely because the<lb/> Chapter is not applicable since the vacant land is in possession of the<lb/> authority, institution or organization. By Section 20 the power to exempt<lb/> is conferred. Section 20 is reproduced herein below:<lb/> &quot;20. Power to exempt:<lb/> (1)<lb/> Notwithstanding anything contained in any of the<lb/> foregoing provisions of this Chapter. -<lb/>(a) where any person holds vacant land in excess of<lb/> the ceiling limit and the State Government is satisfied,<lb/> either on its own motion or otherwise, that, having<lb/> regard to the location of such land, the purpose for<lb/> which such land is being or is proposed to be used and<lb/> such other relevant factors as the circumstances of the<lb/> case may require, it is necessary or expedient in the<lb/> public interest so to do, that Government may, by<lb/> order, exempt, subject to such conditions, if any, as<lb/> may be specified in the order, such vacant land from<lb/> the provisions of this Chapter.<lb/> (b) where any person holds vacant land in excess of<lb/> *58*<lb/> the ceiling limit and the State Government, either on<lb/> its own motion or otherwise, is satisfied that the<lb/> application of the provisions of this Chapter would<lb/> cause undue hardship to such person, that<lb/> Government may by order, exempt subject to such<lb/> conditions, if any, as may be specified in the order,<lb/> such vacant land from the provisions of this Chapter:<lb/> Provided that no order under this clause shall be made unless<lb/> the reasons for doing so are recorded in writing.<lb/> (2)<lb/> If at any time the State Government is satisfied that<lb/> any of the conditions subject to which any exemption<lb/> under clause (a) or clause (b) of subsection (1) is<lb/> granted is not complied with by any person, it shall<lb/> be competent for the State Government to withdraw,<lb/> by order, such exemption after giving a reasonable<lb/> opportunity to such person for making a<lb/> representation against the proposed withdrawal and<lb/> thereupon the provisions of this Chapter shall apply<lb/> accordingly.&quot;<lb/> 48<lb/> A bare perusal of Section 20 would indicate that the power<lb/> thereunder is conferred in the State. The State can exempt the vacant<lb/> land in excess of ceiling limit from the provisions of the ChapterIII if it is<lb/> satisfied in terms of clause (a) or (b) of subsection (1) that the<lb/> exemption is required because of the location of land, the purpose for<lb/> which such land is being used or proposed to be used and such other<lb/> relevant factors as the circumstances of the case may require and that it is<lb/> necessary and expedient in the public interest so to do. By clause (b) of<lb/> subsection (1) of Section 20 to relieve undue hardship to a person</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>.<lb/> An Act to repeal the Urban Land (Ceiling and<lb/> Regulation) Act, 1976.<lb/> BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fiftieth Year of the<lb/> Republic of India as follows: -<lb/>1.<lb/> Short title and application commencement: -<lb/>(1) This Act may be called the Urban Land (Ceiling<lb/> and Regulation) Repeal Act, 1999.<lb/> (2) It applies in the first instance to the whole of<lb/> the States of Haryana and Punjab and to all the<lb/> Union territories; and it shall apply to such other<lb/> State which adopts this Act by resolution passed in<lb/> that behalf under clause (2) of article 252 of the<lb/> Constitution.<lb/> (3) It shall be deemed to have come into force in<lb/> the States of Haryana and Punjab and in all the<lb/> Union territories on the 11th day of January, 1999<lb/> and in any other State which adopts this Act under<lb/> clause (2) of article 252 of the Constitution on the<lb/> date of such adoption; and the reference to repeal of<lb/> the Urban Land (Ceiling and Regulation) Act, 1976<lb/> shall, in relation to any State or Union territory,<lb/> mean the date on which this Act comes into force in<lb/> such State or Union territory.<lb/> 2.<lb/> Repeal of Act 33 of 1976: -The Urban Land (Ceiling<lb/> and Regulation) Act, 1976 (hereinafter referred to as<lb/> the principal Act) is hereby repealed.<lb/> 3.<lb/> Savings: -<lb/>(1) The repeal of the principal Act shall not affect<lb/> (a) the vesting of any vacant land under<lb/> subsection (3) of section 10, possession of which has<lb/> been taken over by the State Government or any<lb/> person duly authorised by the State Government in<lb/> this behalf or by the competent authority;<lb/> (b) the validity of any order granting<lb/> exemption under subsection (1) of section 20 or any<lb/> action taken thereunder, notwithstanding any<lb/> judgment of any court to the contrary;<lb/> (c) any payment made to the State<lb/> Government as a condition for granting exemption<lb/> under subsection (1) of section 20.<lb/> (2) Where-<lb/>(a) any land is deemed to have vested in the<lb/> State Government under subsection (3) of section 10<lb/> of the principal Act but possession of which has not<lb/> been taken over by the State Government or any<lb/> person duly authorised by the State Government in<lb/> this behalf or by the competent authority; and<lb/> (b) any amount has been paid by the State<lb/> Government with respect </table>
 
            <head>to such land,<lb/> then, such land shall not be restored unless the<lb/> amount paid, if any, has been refunded to the State<lb/> Government.</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>They are not surplusage or superfluous or inserted as and by<lb/> way of abundant caution. The law in this regard is very clear and in the<lb/> words of the Honourable Mr. Justice Patanjali Shastri, Chief Justice of<lb/> India (as His Lordship then was) in the case of Aswini Kumar Ghose v/s<lb/> Arabinda Bose reported in AIR 1952 SC 369, &quot;it is not a sound principle<lb/> of construction to brush aside words in a statute as being inapposite<lb/> surplusage, if they can have appropriate application in circumstances<lb/> conceivably within the contemplation of the statute.&quot; The Honourable<lb/> Supreme Court has also held that it is incumbent on the court to avoid a<lb/> construction, if reasonably permissible on the language, which would<lb/> render a part of the statute devoid of any meaning or application. In other<lb/> decision reported in AIR 1961 SC 1170 (J.K.Cotton Spinning &amp; Weaving<lb/> Mills Co. Ltd. v/s State of U.P.), it is held that &quot;To harmonise is not to<lb/> destroy. The courts always presume that the Legislature inserted every<lb/> part thereof for a purpose and the legislative intention is that every part<lb/> of the statute should have effect&quot; (see para 7 at page 1174). The<lb/> Legislature is deemed not to waste its words or to say anything in vain.<lb/> Hence, it is not possible to easily attribute to the Legislature that a<lb/> provision has been made or the words have been inserted just as a matter<lb/> of caution or to chart a safe course. If the vesting of the land of which<lb/> possession has been taken is saved and repeal of the Principal Act was not<lb/> to affect it, then, nothing more was required to be stated or saved as the<lb/> law has taken its course. If vesting of the vacant land under Section<lb/> 10(3), possession of which has been taken over by the State alone, is to<lb/> be saved, then, making further provisions and incorporating them in the<lb/> Repeal Act was unnecessary.<lb/> 52<lb/> The above aspect becomes clear if we peruse the statement of<lb/> objects and reasons to the Repeal Bill, 1999. That reads as under:<lb/> &quot;Statement of Objects and Reasons:<lb/> The Urban Land (Ceiling and Regulation) Act, 1976<lb/> was passed with a laudable social objective. The main<lb/> purpose was to prevent concentration of urban land<lb/> in a few hands and to provide affordable housing to<lb/> the Economically Weaker Sections. It has on the<lb/> contrary pushed up land prices, practically brought<lb/> the housing industry to a stop and provided<lb/> opportunities for corruption. There is a widespread<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>demand for removing this irritant to land assembly<lb/> and construction activity. During the implementation<lb/> of the Urban Land (Ceiling and Regulation) Act,<lb/> 1976, there have been a spate of litigations giving rise<lb/> to serious hurdles in taking over possession of land,<lb/> by the State Governments. Public opinion is nearly<lb/> unanimous that the Act has failed to achieve its<lb/> objectives as expected.<lb/> 2.<lb/> Parliament has no power to repeal or amend the Act<lb/> unless resolutions are passed by two or more State<lb/> Legislatures as required under clause (2) of Article<lb/> 252. The Legislatures of Haryana and Punjab have<lb/> passed resolutions empowering Parliament to repeal<lb/> the Act in those States. The Act stands repealed in<lb/> those States and in the Union territories immediately<lb/> after promulgation of the repeal Ordinance and<lb/> subsequently if State Legislatures adopt this Repeal<lb/> Act by resolution, then the Urban Land (Ceiling and<lb/> Regulation) Act, 1976 will stand repealed in those<lb/> States, from the date of its adoption.</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>limit once it vests in the State. Precisely such an argument was canvassed<lb/> before the Honourable Supreme Court and rejected in the case of Special<lb/> Officer &amp; Competent Authority, Urban Land Ceilings, Hyderabad v/s P.S. Rao<lb/> reported in AIR 2000 SC 843 (see paragraphs 6 to 10).<lb/> 60<lb/> Therefore, once the power of exemption can be exercised<lb/> after the excess vacant land has vested in the State, then, equally the<lb/> power to withdraw the exemption can also be exercised in case of such<lb/> vacant land.<lb/> 61<lb/> In the case of Smt.Darothi Clare Parreira v/s State of<lb/> Maharashtra reported in AIR 1996 SC 2553 this is what is held by the<lb/> Honourable Supreme Court:<lb/> &quot;5. Having considered the respective contentions, the<lb/> question that arises for consideration is : Whether<lb/> publication of the notification under Section 10(3) of<lb/> the Act in the Gazette is in accordance with law? No<lb/> doubt, this question was not squarely put in issue before<lb/> the High Court in the manner in which Shri Naik and<lb/> Shri Bobde have posed before us.</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>The<lb/> applicability of ChapterIII in relation to such lands is, thus, ruled out and<lb/> so long as the exemption order is in force. If the order of exemption is<lb/> withdrawn the ChapterIII becomes applicable and all consequences<lb/> would follow.<lb/> 66<lb/> We must at once note that way back in the year 1990 in the<lb/> decision in the case of M/s Shantistar Builders v/s Narayan Khimalal<lb/> Totame reported in AIR 1990 SC 630, a Three Judge Bench of the<lb/> Honourable Supreme Court had framed the guidelines so as to enable<lb/> construction over the exempted lands covered under Section 20 of the<lb/> Principal Act. That is to ensure compliance with the constitutional<lb/> mandate of shelter and guaranteed vide Article 21 of the Constitution of<lb/> India. In that decision, the Honourable Supreme Court held as under:<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>&quot;5.<lb/> Both Subsections 20 and 21 contain provisions that<lb/> if Government or the competent authority, as the case<lb/> may be, is satisfied that any of the conditions subject<lb/> to which exemption was granted is not complied with,<lb/> it shall be competent for it to withdraw the order<lb/> under Section 20 or declare such land to be excess<lb/> land under Section 21 and bring it within the<lb/> mischief of the statute.<lb/> 6.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>In the instant case on January 11, 1978, on the basis<lb/> of an application made on 24th October, 1987, the<lb/> State Government made an order of exemption, the<lb/> salient portions of which are extracted for<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>convenience:<lb/> GOVERNMENT OF MAHARASHTRA<lb/> NO. HWE1077/XXXV<lb/> GENERAL ADMINISTRATION DEPARTMENT,<lb/> MANTRALAYA, BOMBAY400032.<lb/> 11TH JANUARY, 1978.<lb/> ORDER<lb/> WHEREAS (1) Shri Kumarpal Vadilal Shah (2)<lb/> Shri Navinchandra Vadilal Shah (3) Smt.<lb/> Champaben w/o Vadilal Shah (4) Shri Vasantlal<lb/> Vadilal Shah (5) Shri Babulal Vadilal Shah (6) Smt.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>Pushpa Mangaldas Shah (7) Smt. Nirmala Hiralal<lb/> Shah (8) Smt. Shakuntala Tansukhlal Parekh and<lb/> (9) Smt. Madhuabala Vadilal Shah (persons at Sr.<lb/> Nos.2 to 9 by their Constituted Attorney Shri<lb/> Kumarpal Vadilal Shah), 26, Suneel Shopping center,<lb/> Opp. Navrang Talkies, Andheri (West), Bombay<lb/> 400058, hold vacant lands in excess of the Ceiling<lb/> Limit in the Greater Bombay Urban Agglomeration,<lb/> details of which are given in the Schedule &apos;A&apos; herein:<lb/> AND WHEREAS the said persons have applied<lb/> for exemption under Section 20 of the Urban Land<lb/> (C.&amp; R. ) Act, (33 of 1976).</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <figDesc>.A.<lb/> 11) If at any time, the State Government is satisfied<lb/> that there is a breach of any of the condition<lb/> mentioned in this Order, it shall be competent for the<lb/> State Government by order to withdraw the<lb/> exemption from the date specified in the Order:<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>7.<lb/> ….....<lb/> 8.<lb/> ….....<lb/> 9.<lb/> Basic needs of man have traditionally been accepted<lb/> to be threefood, clothing and shelter. The right to life<lb/> is guaranteed in any civilized society. That would take<lb/> within its sweep the right to food, the right to<lb/> clothing, the right to decent environment and a<lb/> reasonable accommodation to live in. The difference<lb/> between the need of an animal and a human being<lb/> for shelter has to be kept in view. For the animal it is<lb/> the bare protection of the body; for a human being it<lb/> has to be a suitable accommodation which would<lb/> allow him to grow in every aspect physical, mental<lb/> and intellectual. The Constitution aims at ensuring<lb/> fuller development of every child. That would be<lb/> possible only if the child is in a proper home. It is not<lb/> necessary that every citizen must be ensured of living<lb/> in a well built comfortable house but a reasonable<lb/> home particularly for people in India can even be<lb/> mudbuilt thatched house or a mud built fireproof<lb/> accommodation.<lb/> 10.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>With the increase of population and the shift of the<lb/> rural masses to urban areas over the decades the<lb/> ratio of poor people without houses in the urban<lb/> areas has rapidly increased. This is a feature which<lb/> has become more perceptible after independence.<lb/> Apart from the fact that people in search of work<lb/> move to urban agglomerations, availability of<lb/> amenities and living conveniences also attract people<lb/> to move from rural areas to cities. Industrialisation is<lb/> equally responsible for concentration of population<lb/> around industries. These are feature which are<lb/> mainly responsible for increase in the homeless urban<lb/> population. Millions of people today live on the<lb/> pavements of different cities of India and a greater<lb/> number live animal like existence in jhuggis.<lb/> 11.<lb/> The Planning Commission took note of this situation<lb/> and was struck by the fact that there was no<lb/> corresponding rise in accommodation with the growth<lb/> of population and the shift of the rural people to the<lb/> cities. The growing realisation of this disparity led to<lb/> the passing of the Act and acquisition of vacant sites<lb/> for purposes of housing. Considerable attention has<lb/> been given in recent years to increasing<lb/> accommodation though whatever has been done is<lb/> not at all adequate. The quick growth of urban<lb/> population overshadows all attempts of increasing<lb/> accommodation. Sections 20 and 21 of the Act vest<lb/> power in the State Governments to exempt vacant<lb/> sites from vesting under the Act for purposes of being<lb/> taken over if housing schemes are undertaken by<lb/> owners of vacant urban lands. Section 21 specifically<lb/> emphasis upon weaker sections of the people. That<lb/> term finds place in Article 46 of the Constitution and<lb/> Section 21 uses the same language. &apos;Weaker sections&apos;<lb/> have, however, not been defined either in the<lb/> Constitution or in the Act itself. An attempt was made<lb/> in the Constitution Assembly to provide a definition<lb/> but was given up. Attempts have thereafter been<lb/> made from time to time to provide such definition but<lb/> on account of controversies which arise once the<lb/> exercise is undertaken, there has been no success. A<lb/> suggestion for introducing economic criterion for<lb/> explaining the term was made in the approach to the<lb/> Seventh Five Year Plan (19851990) brought out by<lb/> the Planning Commission and approved by the<lb/> National Development Council and the Union<lb/> Government. A lot of controversy was raised in<lb/> Parliament and the attempt, was dropped. In the<lb/> absence of a definition perhaps a proper guideline<lb/> could be indicated but no serious attention has been<lb/> devoted to this aspect.<lb/> 12.<lb/> Members of the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled<lb/> Tribes have ordinarily been accepted as belonging to<lb/> the weaker section. Attempt to bring in the test of<lb/> economic means has often been tried but no guideline<lb/> has been evolved. Undoubtedly, apart from the<lb/> members of the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled<lb/> Tribes, there would be millions of other citizens who<lb/> would also belong to the weaker sections. The<lb/> Constitution maker intended all citizens of India<lb/> belonging to the weaker sections to be benefited when<lb/> Article 46 was incorporated in the Constitution.<lb/> Parliament in adopting the same language in Section<lb/> 21 of the Act also intended people of all weaker<lb/> sections to have the advantage. It is, therefore,<lb/> appropriate that the Central Government should<lb/> come forward with an appropriate guideline to<lb/> indicate who would be included within weaker<lb/> sections of the society.<lb/> 13.<lb/> In recent years on account of erosion of the value of<lb/> the rupee, rampant prevalence of black money and<lb/> dearth of urban land, the value of such land has gone<lb/> up skyhigh. It has become impossible for any<lb/> member of the weaker sections to have residential<lb/> accommodation anywhere and much less in urban<lb/> areas. Since a reasonable residence is an<lb/> indispensable necessity for fulfilling the Constitutional<lb/> goal in the matter of development of man and should<lb/> be taken as included in &apos;life&apos; in Article 21, greater<lb/> social control is called for and exemptions granted<lb/> under Sections 20 and 21 should have to be<lb/> appropriately monitored to have the fullest benefit of<lb/> the beneficial legislation. We, therefore, command to<lb/> the Central Government to prescribe appropriate<lb/> guidelines laying down the true scope of the term<lb/> &apos;weaker sections of the society&apos; so that everyone<lb/> charged with administering the statute would find it<lb/> convenient to implement the same.<lb/> 14.</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>&quot;<lb/> 16.<lb/> After this preamble, 16 paragraphs in what has been<lb/> named as the Code and a copy of this Code is<lb/> appended to the judgment as annexure for<lb/> convenience indicate the guidelines.<lb/> 17.<lb/> We are of the view that allotment shall be on the<lb/> basis of &apos;one family one flat&apos; and the family shall<lb/> include husband, wife and dependent children. A<lb/> family which has one flat in any urban<lb/> agglomeration within the State shall not be entitled<lb/> to allotment or acquisition by transfer of a flat under<lb/> this Code.<lb/> 18.<lb/> Government nominees contemplated under the Code<lb/> must belong to weaker sections of the society and<lb/> shall also be subjected to the rule of one family one<lb/> flat. The number of Government nominees should not<lb/> exceed 5% of the total accommodation available in<lb/> any scheme.<lb/> 19.<lb/> Every builder shall maintain a register of applicants<lb/> chronologically registering them on the basis of the<lb/> date of receipt of the applications. The register should<lb/> be uptodate and available for inspection by the<lb/> authorities. As and when an application is received by<lb/> the builder an appropriate receipt acknowledging<lb/> acceptance of such application shall be issued to the<lb/> applicant and in such receipt, the number in the<lb/> Application Register shall be clearly indicated.<lb/> Simultaneously, a copy of the application with its<lb/> number shall be sent by the builder to the Committee<lb/> for its record.<lb/> 20.<lb/> As a working guideline we direct that a &apos;means test&apos;<lb/> for identifying &apos;weaker sections of the society shall be<lb/> adopted and for the present income of the family of<lb/> the applicant must not exceed Rs. 18,000/ (eighteen<lb/> thousand) to come within the meaning of the term to<lb/> qualify for allotment. The applicant shall be called<lb/> upon to satisfy the Committee about the limit of<lb/> income and the present prescription of Rs. 18,000/<lb/> may be varied from time to time by the State<lb/> Government taking into consideration the fall of the<lb/> value of the rupee, general improvement in the<lb/> income of the people now within the annual income<lb/> limit of Rs. 18,000/ and other relevant factors. It<lb/> shall be open to the State Government to prescribe<lb/> appropriate guideline in the matter of identifying the<lb/> &apos;weaker sections of the society&apos;.<lb/> 21.<lb/> <note>&apos;Competent authority&apos; has been defined in Section<lb/> 2(9) of the Act. From the Code it appears that he is<lb/> an officer subordinate to the Collector of the District<lb/> so far as the State of Maharashtra is concerned as an<lb/> appeal is contemplated from his orders to the<lb/> Collector. The duties and responsibilities and powers<lb/> vested in the competent authority under the Code are<lb/> wide and considerable. We are of the opinion<lb/> (without in any way casting any aspersion) that it<lb/> would be difficult for the competent authority to<lb/> exercise efficiently and to the satisfaction of everyone<lb/> the duties cast upon him under the Code. In the<lb/> matter of implementation of the scheme and with a<lb/> view to providing satisfactory execution thereof and<lb/> fulfilling the laudable purpose stipulated under the<lb/> Act and undertaken by the scheme, it is necessary that<lb/> there should be a committee in respect of the schemes<lb/> in every urban agglomeration for weaker sections<lb/> sanctioned under Sections 20 and 21 of the Act for<lb/> overseeing the implementation of every scheme,<lb/> particularly in the matter of due compliance of the<lb/> conditions under which exemption is granted, timely<lb/> construction of the flats, appropriate advertisement as<lb/> contemplated, registration of the applications in<lb/> response to advertisements in a systematic manner,<lb/> appropriate allotment of flats including priorities on<lb/> the basis of registration, ensuring legitimate charges<lb/> only being demanded and monitoring strict<lb/> compliance to avoid underhand dealing or any unjust<lb/> treatment. It should be handled by the competent<lb/> authority in a committee consisting of himself, a<lb/> judicial officer not below the rank of an Additional<lb/> District Judge and a Government engineer not below<lb/> the rank of Superintending Engineer. In the<lb/> committee, the judicial officer shall function as the<lb/> Chairman.<lb/> 22.<lb/> This Committee shall have powers to scrutinise all<lb/> relevant documents and give appropriate directions to<lb/> the builders and applicants keeping the requirements<lb/> of the schemes and the Code in view. To the extent we<lb/> have indicated the powers conferred on the competent<lb/> authority in terms of the State Code shall stand<lb/> vested in the committee. The Bombay High Court<lb/> shall take steps to ensure that in respect of schemes in<lb/> every agglomeration undertaken and which the State<lb/> Government may in future undertake, the services of<lb/> an efficient judicial officer not below the rank of an<lb/> Additional District Judge on such terms as the State<lb/> Government and the High Court consider appropriate<lb/> shall be made available for discharging the duties<lb/> indicated and/or as may be provided. We would like<lb/> to impress upon every Committee that fulfilment of<lb/> the laudable purpose of the providing a home to the<lb/> poor homeless depends upon its commitment to the<lb/> goal and every effort should be made by it to ensure<lb/> that the builder does not succeed in frustrating the<lb/> purpose. The State Government shall suitably modify<lb/> its Code in the light of this judgment and recirculate<lb/> the same to all concerned within four weeks from<lb/> today.&quot;<lb/> 67<lb/> A further order in terms of the guidelines formulated above<lb/> has been passed by the Honourable Supreme Court in the year 1995 and<lb/> to be precise on 17.11.1995. That order is reported in (1996) 1 SCC 233<lb/> (Shantistar Builders v/s Narayan Khimalal Totame). Therefore, the Scheme<lb/> formulated by the Honourable Supreme Court is in place. This order reads<lb/> thus:<lb/> &quot;1.<lb/> This Court by its judgment in Shantistar Builders v.<lb/> Narayan Khimalal Totame, while disposing of the<lb/> matter directed in paragraphs 21 and 22 the State<lb/> Government to constitute a committee for monitoring<lb/> allotment of the houses to the weaker sections, as per<lb/> the scheme sanctioned while exempting the Urban<lb/> land under Section 21 of the Urban Land (Ceiling &amp;<lb/> Regulation) Act, 1976 (for short &quot;the Act&quot;). </note>
 
            <table>One of the<lb/> members of the committee suggested was Additional<lb/> District Judge. The Bombay High Court was requested<lb/> to ensure that an Additional District Judge be made<lb/> available for enforcing the schemes in every<lb/> agglomeration, so that the Committee constituted by<lb/> the State Government would effectively implement the<lb/> schemes. This Court also impressed upon every<lb/> Committee to ensure fulfilment of the laudable<lb/> purpose of providing a home to the poor homeless to<lb/> effectuate its commitment to the constitutional goal<lb/> and that every effort should be made by it to ensure<lb/> that the builder does not succeed in frustrating the<lb/> purpose. The State Government should suitably<lb/> modify its scheme in the light of the judgment<lb/> rendered in Shantistar Builders case and recirculate<lb/> the same to all concerned within four weeks from the<lb/> date of the judgment.<lb/> 2.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>The State had filed an affidavit on March 30, 1990,<lb/> seeking certain modification or clarifications of the<lb/> order. One of the modifications sought was that under<lb/> the Act, the Deputy Commissioner is the competent<lb/> authority and an appeal was provided under the Act,<lb/> except for Bombay and Pune, to the Additional<lb/> Commissioner. For Pune and Bombay, the<lb/> Commissioner would deal with the same. If the<lb/> Additional District Judge was to supervise the<lb/> functioning of the allotment as per the scheme<lb/> sanctioned under Section 21 of the Act, it would be<lb/> inconvenient to the appellate authority to consider the<lb/> scheme under the Act.<lb/> 3.</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>far as the State of Maharashtra is concerned that is 17.02.1976. In a Full<lb/> Bench decision of this Court reported in AIR 1984 Bombay 122<lb/> Prabhakar Narhar Pawar v/s State of Maharashtra, the Full Bench held as<lb/> under:</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>.......&quot;<lb/> 72<lb/> This decision in Prabhakar Pawar&apos;s case (supra) has been<lb/> specifically approved by the Honourable Supreme Court in the case of<lb/> State of Gujarat v/s Parshottamdas Ramdas Patel reported in AIR </note>
 
            <head>1988 SC<lb/> 220. </head>
 
            <figDesc>The arguments of the learned Senior Counsel appearing for the<lb/> Petitioners in this case overlook the fact that when there is ceiling placed<lb/> on holding of vacant lands and such lands which are vacant, but in excess<lb/> of ceiling limit vest in the State, then, it would be futile to urge that the<lb/> exemption confers an absolute right or privilege. If the exemption is a<lb/> privilege as is held in the case of Southern Petrochemical Industries<lb/> Company Limited v/s Electricity Inspector and E.T.I.O. reported in AIR<lb/> 2007 SC 1984 and it is further held by the Honourable Supreme Court<lb/> that the right of exemption with a valid notification gives the right to<lb/> approve the rates, it is vested right and the word &quot;privilege&quot; has wider<lb/> meaning, then, the right is, therefore, protected even after repeal of the<lb/> Principal Act. It goes without saying that if such right is conditional the<lb/> conditions attached are not wiped out or destroyed if the right or<lb/> privilege is saved. In this regard, the Honourable Supreme Court holds<lb/> that when such is the nature of the claim, then, the Court is obliged to<lb/> consider as to whether the intention of the Legislature is to the contrary<lb/> meaning thereby there is a different intention than what is spelled out by<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <note>Section 6 of the General Clauses Act. In that regard this is what the<lb/> Honourable Supreme Court has held:<lb/> &quot;108. We are also unable to agree with Mr. Andhyarujina<lb/> that exemption from tax is a mere concession<lb/> defeasible by Government and does not confer any<lb/> accrued right to the recipient. Right of exemption<lb/> with a valid notification issued gives rise to an<lb/> accrued right. It is a vested right. Such right had </note>
 
            <table>been<lb/> granted to them permanently. &apos;Permanence&apos; would<lb/> mean unless altered by statute.<lb/> 109. Thus, when a right is accrued or vested, the same can<lb/> be taken away only by reason of a statute and not<lb/> otherwise. Thus, a notification which was duly issued<lb/> would continue to govern unless the same is repealed.<lb/> 110. Mr.Andhyarujina, however, would submit that<lb/> reference to the words &quot;anything duly done&quot; should be<lb/> given a restrictive meaning. He referred to &quot;Statutory<lb/> Interpretation A Code&quot; by F.A.R. Bennion, Third<lb/> Edition, page 229, wherein it was stated:<lb/> &quot;Paragraph<lb/> (ii)<lb/> This<lb/> derives<lb/> from<lb/> Interpretation Act 1978 Section 16(1)(b). The<lb/> reference to &apos;anything duly done&apos; avoids the need for<lb/> procedural matters, such as the giving of notices, to<lb/> be done over again.<lb/> Example 89.3 The Interpretation Act 1978<lb/> Section preserved the effect of a noise nuisance notice<lb/> served under the Control of Pollution Act, 1974,<lb/> Section 58(1) before its repeal and replacement by<lb/> the Environmental Protection Act, 1990, Sections 162<lb/> and 164(2</table>

            <figDesc>) and Schedule 16 Pt. III.&quot;<lb/> 111. The treatment of the law, in our opinion, is not<lb/> exhaustive as different consequences are required to<lb/> be taken into consideration and applied having<lb/> regard to the nature of the statutory provision.<lb/> 112. Mr.Andhyarujina also relied upon Maxwell on the<lb/> Interpretation of Statutes, 12th edition, page 18,<lb/> wherein it was stated:<lb/> &quot;When an Act is repealed, any delegated<lb/> legislation made under the Act falls to the ground<lb/> with the statute unless it is expressly preserved. Where<lb/> the subordinate legislation is continued in force,<lb/> however, the general rule is that its scope and<lb/> construction are determined according to the repealed<lb/> Act under which it was made.</figDesc>

            <note>&quot;<lb/> 113. The statement of law therein does not militate against<lb/> our findings aforementioned. Construction would<lb/> vary from statute to statute.<lb/> 114. It is profitable to notice at this stage a decision of this<lb/> Court in M/s. Universal Imports Agency (supra). In<lb/> that case under the IndoFrench Agreement entered<lb/> into by and between the two nations on 1st<lb/> November, 1954, the entire Administration of French<lb/> Settlement vested in the Government of India. The<lb/> territory of Pondicherry, thus, became a free port<lb/> without any restriction in case of most imports.<lb/> However, by reason of a notification dated 30th<lb/> October, 1954, the importers in Pondicherry were<lb/> required to obtain validation of licences held by them<lb/> to import goods as petitioners thereof did not have<lb/> any merchandise imported by them stood confiscated.<lb/> 115. </note>
 
            <figDesc>Clause 6 of the Agreement reads, thus:<lb/> &quot;Unless otherwise specifically provided in the<lb/> Schedule, all laws in force in the French<lb/> Establishments<lb/> immediately<lb/> before<lb/> the<lb/> commencement of the Order, which correspond to<lb/> enactments specified in the Schedule, shall cease to<lb/> have effect, save as respect things done or omitted to<lb/> be done before such commencement.</figDesc>

            <note>&quot;<lb/> 116. Analyzing the said provision, this Court held:<lb/> &quot;...The words things done in para 6 must be<lb/> reasonably interpreted and, if so interpreted, they can</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>1955, The Rajasthan Tenancy Act 1955 was<lb/> enacted. By the Rajasthan Tenancy (Amendment) Act,<lb/> for the first time, provisions in Chapter IIIB<lb/> prescribing a ceilings on holdings of agricultural<lb/> lands got introduced into the &apos;1955 Act&apos;, This<lb/> amending Act of 1960 received Presidential assent on<lb/> 12th March 1960. The Chapter IIIB was, by an<lb/> appropriate notification, brought into force with<lb/> effect from 15th December, 1963. The notifieddate,<lb/> under the &apos;1955 Act&apos; as stated earlier, was 1.4.1966.<lb/> 10.<lb/> Section (6A) of the &apos;1955 Act&apos; defined &apos;Ceilingarea&apos;:<lb/> &quot;Ceiling area&quot; in relation to land held<lb/> anywhere throughout the State by a person in any<lb/> capacity whatsoever shall mean the maximum area of<lb/> land that may be fixed as ceiling area under Section C<lb/> in relation to such person:<lb/> 11.<lb/> Section B in Chapter IIIB provided:<lb/> 30B. DefinitionsFor the purposes of this<lb/> Chapter</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>1.1.1973, the Governor of the State of Rajasthan<lb/> promulgated The Rajasthan Imposition of Ceiling on<lb/> Agricultural Holdings Ordinance, 1973 under Article<lb/> 213 of the Constitution of India. The Ordinance<lb/> repealed the corresponding provisions relating to<lb/> ceiling on agricultural holdings contained in Section<lb/> and Chapter IIIB of the &apos;1955 Act&apos; except to the<lb/> extent indicated in the Second Proviso to Section and<lb/> Section of the said Ordinance. The Ordinance brought<lb/> in to existence a new concept of and standards for<lb/> the&quot; ceilingarea&quot;. Certain transfers made by the land<lb/> holders even during the operation of the old law were<lb/> recognised as valid transfers for purposes of<lb/> computation of ceiling area under the new<lb/> dispensation brought about by the Ordinance. This<lb/> Ordinance was replaced by the 1973 Act which was<lb/> made operative retrospectively from 1.1.1973 being<lb/> the date of promulgation of the Ordinance. Section of<lb/> the &apos;1973 Act&apos; repealed as did the predecessor<lb/> Ordinance, both the old law in Chapter IIIB of the<lb/> &apos;1955 Act&apos; and the earlier Ordinance for which it<lb/> substituted.<lb/> 13.<lb/> Section Section 4(1), Second Proviso and Section of<lb/> the 1973 Act require particular notice.<lb/> 14.<lb/> Section 3 provides :<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>&quot;3. Act to override other laws, contracts, etc.<lb/> The provisions of this Act shall have effect<lb/> notwithstanding anything inconsistent contained in<lb/> any other law for the time being in force, on any<lb/> custom, usage or contract or decree or order of a<lb/> court or other authority.<lb/> 15.</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>The High Court referred to<lb/> Section [2] inserted by Act No. 8 of 1976 and what,<lb/> according to it, necessarily flowed from it in support<lb/> of its conclusion, Section [2] inserted by Act NO. 8 of<lb/> 1976 runs thus:<lb/> 15(2) Without prejudice to any other remedy<lb/> that may be available to it under the Rajasthan<lb/> Tenancy</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>to be fixed under its repealed provisions,<lb/> then it must follow as a necessary corollary, that the<lb/> pending cases must be decided under the old law.<lb/> 26.<lb/> Sri Lodha, learned Counsel for the State of Rajasthan<lb/> submitted that the &apos;ceilingarea&apos; had to be fixed with<lb/> reference to the notified date i.e. 1,4.1966 by the<lb/> statutory standards prescribed under the Chapter III<lb/> B of the &apos;1955 Act&apos;. The two legislations are<lb/> complementary to each other and constitute two tier<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>provisions. So far as the cases that attracted and fell<lb/> within Chapter IIIB of 1955 Act, as on 1.4.1966,<lb/> would continue to be governed by that law as the<lb/> rights and obligations created by the said Chapter III<lb/> B amounted to create rights and incur liabilities. Sri<lb/> Lodha submitted that the view taken by the High<lb/> Court was unexceptionable.<lb/> 27.<lb/> On a careful consideration of the matter, we are<lb/> inclined to agree with the view taken by the High<lb/> Court on the point. The reliance placed by appellants&apos;<lb/> learned Counsel on the provisions of Section of 1973<lb/> Act as detracting from the tenability of the conclusion<lb/> reached by the High Court on the point is, in our<lb/> opinion, somewhat tenuous. The contention of the<lb/> learned<lb/> Counsel<lb/> is<lb/> that<lb/> the<lb/> expression<lb/> &quot;notwithstanding anything inconsistent contained in<lb/> any other law for the time being in force&quot; in Section<lb/> of the 1973 Act would exclude the operation of<lb/> Chapter IIIB of the &apos;1955 Act&apos; which, according to the<lb/> contention, even if kept alive would yet be a &apos;law for<lb/> the time being in force&apos; and, therefore, be excluded by<lb/> virtue of Section This contention has been negatived<lb/> by the High Court ...and in our opinion rightly ..by<lb/> placing reliance on the pronouncements of this Court<lb/> in Rao Shiv Bahadur Singh and Anr. v. The State of<lb/> Vindhya Pradesh and Chief Inspector of Mines v. K.C.</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>The<lb/> distinction between what is and what is not a right<lb/> <note>::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:39 :::<lb/> <note>*120*<lb/> preserved by Section 6 of the General Clauses Act, it is<lb/> said, is often one of great fineness. What is unaffected<lb/> by the repeal is a right &apos;acquired&apos; or &apos;accrued&apos; under<lb/> the repealed statute and not &quot;a mere hope or<lb/> expectation&quot; of acquiring a right or liberty to apply<lb/> for a right.<lb/> 31.<lb/> In Lalji Raja v. Firm Hansraj Nathuram this Court<lb/> dealing with the distinction between the &quot;abstract<lb/> rights&quot; and &quot;specificrights&quot; for the purpose of the<lb/> operation of Section 6 of General Clauses Act said:<lb/> (SCC p. 728, para 16)<lb/> That a provision to preserve the right accrued<lb/> under a repealed Act &apos;was not intended to preserve the<lb/> abstract rights conferred by the repealed Act...It only<lb/> applies to specific rights given to an individual upon<lb/> happening of one or the other of the events specified<lb/> in statute&apos; -<lb/>See Lord Atkin&apos;s observations in<lb/> Hamilton Gell v. White. The mere right, existed at the<lb/> date of repealing statute, to take advantage of<lb/> provisions of the statute repealed is not a &apos;right<lb/> accrued&apos; within the meaning of the usual saving<lb/> clausesee Abbot v. Minister for Lands and G. Ogden<lb/> Industries pty. Ltd. v. Lucas.<lb/> 32.<lb/> ….....<lb/> 33.<lb/> …....<lb/> 34.<lb/> The rights and obligations under this provision had<lb/> had to be determined with reference to the notified<lb/> date i.e. 1.4.1966. Referring to analogous provision<lb/> of the Maharashtra Agricultural Lands [Ceiling on<lb/> Holdings] Act, 1961, this Court in Raghunath v.<lb/> Maharashtra observed: (SCC p. 397, para 17)</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>There is no substance in contention<lb/> [b] either.&quot;<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>77<lb/> Mr.Naphade would urge that this judgment is distinguishable<lb/> because it pertains to a ceiling on agricultural lands. Secondly, the<lb/> judgment deals with a case where earlier law was repealed, but reenacted<lb/> in a different form. Yet the Legislature retained the earlier law, namely,<lb/> the Act of 1955. The factual matrix was, therefore, different. This<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>judgment would have no application to the point before us.<lb/> We are unable to agree with Mr.Naphade and for more than<lb/> one reason. The judgment of the Honourable Supreme Court and laying<lb/> down such principles cannot be brushed aside on a spacious plea that the<lb/> statute which was subject matter of the judgment was repealed, but<lb/> reenacted later. This is a judgment on Section 6 of the Rajasthan General<lb/> Clauses Act, 1955 and which is identical to Section 6 of the General<lb/> Clauses Act, 1897. Section 6 of the General Clauses Act, 1897 reads as<lb/> under:<lb/> &quot;6.<lb/> Effect of repeal: -Where this Act, or any [Central Act]<lb/> or Regulation made after the commencement of this<lb/> Act, repeals any enactment hitherto made or hereafter<lb/> to be made, then, unless a different intention appears,<lb/> the repeal shall not -<lb/>(a) revive anything not in force or existing at the<lb/> time at which the repeal takes effect; or<lb/> (b) affect the previous operation of any enactment<lb/> so repealed or anything duly done or suffered<lb/> thereunder; or<lb/> (c) affect any right, privilege, obligation or liability<lb/> acquired, accrued or incurred under any enactment so<lb/> repealed; or<lb/> (d) affect any penalty, forfeiture or punishment<lb/> incurred in respect of any offence committed against<lb/> any enactment so repealed; or<lb/> (e) affect any investigation, legal proceeding or<lb/> remedy in respect of any such right, privilege,<lb/> obligation, liability, penalty, forfeiture or punishment<lb/> as aforesaid;</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>Further in the case of Amadalavasa Cooperative Agricultural<lb/> and Industrial Society Limited v/s Union of India reported in AIR 1976 SC<lb/> 958 in the context of compulsory insurance scheme and whether that<lb/> survives with all attendant conditions upon repeal of the Principal Act,<lb/> namely, the Emergency Risks (Factories) Insurance Act, 1962 the<lb/> Honourable Supreme Court held as under:</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>usual and ordinary sense in which it is commonly employed it expresses<lb/> the state of being under obligation in law or in justice [see AIR 1959<lb/> Punjab 328 (First National Bank Limited v/s Seth Sant Lal)].<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>85<lb/> A Full Bench of Delhi High Court in the case of Mohd. Yaqub<lb/> v/s Union of India reported in AIR 1971 Delhi 45 followed the above<lb/> Punjab High Court&apos;s view and held that the liability is the state of being<lb/> bound or obliged in law or justice. In Black&apos;s Law Dictionary the word<lb/> &quot;liability&quot; is defined to mean &quot;the state of being bound or obliged in law<lb/> or justice to do, pay or make good something; legal responsibility&quot;. It is,<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>therefore, a word of widest import meaning an obligation or duty to do<lb/> something or to refrain from doing something. [see paras 13 to 16 of AIR<lb/> 1971 Delhi 45].<lb/> We cannot, therefore, be unmindful of the fact that the words<lb/> &quot;liability incurred&quot; have been construed as very general and<lb/> comprehensive and ordinarily taking both civil and criminal liability. [See<lb/> Kapur Chand Pokhraj v/s State of Bombay AIR 1958 SC 993].<lb/> 87<lb/> Such being the position in law we cannot accept<lb/> Mr.Naphade&apos;s contentions that the judgment of the Honourable Supreme<lb/> Court in the case of Bansidhar (supra) would not apply.<lb/> 88<lb/> We are further not in agreement with Mr.Naphade that<lb/> Bansidhar&apos;s case (supra) was confined to agricultural ceiling law and<lb/> reenactment thereof. Even with regard to the Principal Act before us it has<lb/> been held by our Court in Sadashiv Durgaji Ambhore v/s State of<lb/> Maharashtra reported in 1992 Mh.L.J. 1300 as under:<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>&quot;8.<lb/> Coming to the scheme of the U.L.C. Act it is crystal<lb/> clear that no person can retain vacant land in urban<lb/> area more than the prescribed ceiling limit. The excess<lb/> or better still the surplus land has to vest in the State.<lb/> There can thus be no question of escaping the<lb/> prohibition imposed by the statute, the validity of<lb/> which is already tested before. Therefore, once the<lb/> surplus land is determined by the Competent<lb/> Authority the original owner has no right over such<lb/> land and in due course those lands must vest in the<lb/> State.<lb/> 9.</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>into force in the State which it adopts upon passing of the resolution by<lb/> the House of that State will not mean that Section 6 of the General<lb/> Clauses Act does not apply. The applicability of Section 6 of the General<lb/> Clauses Act has to be seen qua the Repeal Act. Mr.Sridharan does not<lb/> dispute that it applies to the Repeal Act. His argument is that because of<lb/> adoption of the Repeal Act by resolution of the House of the State of<lb/> Maharashtra, Section 6 of the General Clauses Act will not apply. The<lb/> resolution merely adopts the Repeal Act made by the Parliament in the<lb/> State. If Section 6 of the General Clauses Act applies to the Repeal Act<lb/> and that is how its applicability is being tested, then, the argument of<lb/> Mr.Sridharan need not detain us.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>94<lb/> Reliance that Mr.Sridharan placed upon the judgment in the<lb/> case of Kolhapur Canesugar Works Limited v/s Union of India reported in<lb/> (2000) 2 SCC 536 is entirely misplaced. There, the Honourable Supreme<lb/> Court was concerned with a situation as to whether Section 6 of the<lb/> General Clauses Act, which is applicable to repeal of enactments by a<lb/> Central Act or Regulation, would apply in the case of either omission or<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>rule. The Constitution Bench held that this Section 6 cannot apply in case<lb/> of omission of a rule and the term regulation in Section 6 of the General<lb/> <note>::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:40 :::</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>Section 3 of this Validation Act. It is in that context that the observations<lb/> regarding a Validating Statute have been made. We do not see as to how<lb/> this judgment can have any application in the light of our conclusions<lb/> recorded hereinabove. This judgment is, therefore, clearly distinguishable.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>99<lb/> Equally, misplaced is the reliance on the judgment of the<lb/> Honourable Supreme Court in the case of Union of India v/s West Coast<lb/> Paper Mills Limited reported in 2004 (164) ELT 375 (SC). There, the<lb/> question was as to whether the appeal can be considered as continuation<lb/> of the suit. We do not find how this judgment can assist Mr.Sridharan in<lb/> his arguments on the Reference before us.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:40 :::<lb/> <note>*143*<lb/> <note>FULL.BENCH.JUDGMENT.sxw<lb/> 100<lb/> Once we have held that neither the power to exempt can be<lb/> said to be legislative nor can it be held that the Repeal Act saves the<lb/> subordinate legislation, then, no assistance can be derived from the<lb/> judgment in the case of Air India V/s Union of India reported in (1995) 4<lb/> SCC 734. Rather some of the observations therein and particularly<lb/> reference to Bennion on Statutory Interpretation in paragraph 7 of this<lb/> judgment would assist us and reinforce our above conclusions.<lb/> 101<lb/> We are not in agreement with Mr.Naphade that the power to<lb/> exempt conferred by Section 20 of the Principal Act is legislative in<lb/> nature. We are of the clear opinion that this power is QuasiJudicial in<lb/> nature. The nature of this power is to exempt the excess vacant lands. In<lb/> other words, they are vacant lands in excess of ceiling limit. They are<lb/> exempted from the provisions or applicability of ChapterIII on the<lb/> satisfaction reached and which is to be found in clause (a) and clause (b)<lb/> of subsection (1) of this provision. In a decision reported in AIR 1982<lb/> Madhya Pradesh 33 (Nandakishore v/s State of M.P.), the Division Bench<lb/> of Madhya Pradesh High Court held as under:<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>&quot;5.<lb/> …..... Clause (a) of Subsection (1) of Section 20 of<lb/> the Act empowers the State Government to exempt<lb/> any vacant land in public interest; whereas Clause (b)<lb/> thereof empowers the State Government to grant<lb/> exemption to any person who holds vacant land in<lb/> excess of the ceiling limit, where such exemption is<lb/> considered necessary to avoid undue hardship to such<lb/> person. The second schedule to the Act inter alia<lb/> prescribes Rs.10/ as courtfees stamp to be paid on<lb/> an application for exemption of vacant land under<lb/> Section 20 of the Act. The power to exempt so<lb/> conferred on the State Government carries with it an<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>obligation to exercise that power on a case being<lb/> made out for the purpose. Of course, the power to<lb/> exempt is exercisable by the State Government on its<lb/> own motion, but the same can be exercised otherwise<lb/> also. This is what flows from the use of the expression<lb/> &quot;either on its own motion or otherwise&quot; used in<lb/> Clauses</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>See<lb/> Jullius v. Lord Bishon of Oxford, ((187480) ALL ER<lb/> Rep. 43 (HL) at p.47. Viewed from this angle, it<lb/> appears that the provisions placed in Section 20(1)(b)<lb/> of the Act are for the benefit of holders and the power<lb/> conferred thereby is exercisable for their benefit for<lb/> averting undue hardship that would be caused to<lb/> them if the land in respect of which exemption is<lb/> claimed is not exempted from the operation of the Act.<lb/> Accordingly, on case being made out, exemption has<lb/> to be granted and the State Government cannot<lb/> withhold the exemption claimed. As such, the word<lb/> &quot;may&apos;&apos; cannot be construed in a manner to clothe the<lb/> State Government with arbitrary power to reject an<lb/> application for exemption, even if the conditions for<lb/> grant thereof stand made out.&quot;<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>102<lb/> This judgment has been followed by another Division Bench<lb/> of Gujarat High Court in AIR 1985 Gujarat 47 (Manilal Hiralal Doshi v/s<lb/> State of Gujarat). We are not concerned with other findings and<lb/> conclusions of the Division Bench of Gujarat High Court, but in paragraph<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>4 of this judgment the observations of the Madhya Pradesh High Court<lb/> are referred and followed and in paragraphs 3 and 5 this is what is held:<lb/> &quot;3.<lb/> <note>…....... The Government&apos;s satisfaction about granting<lb/> or not granting the exemption under that provision<lb/> obviously rests on objective facts. The factors which<lb/> are required to be taken into account by the<lb/> Government are (</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>103<lb/> The above quoted observations of the Division Bench of the<lb/> Gujarat High Court and prior thereto of the Madhya Pradesh High Court<lb/> have our respectful concurrence.<lb/> 104<lb/> Similar view has been taken by the learned Single Judge of<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>Karnataka High Court in the judgment reported in AIR 1987 Karnataka 5<lb/> (D.Ananthakrishna Bhat v/s Special Deputy Commissioner and Competent<lb/> <note>*150*<lb/> <note>FULL.BENCH.JUDGMENT.sxw<lb/> Authority, Mangalore). In paragraph 16 this is what is held:<lb/> &quot;16.<lb/> It is true that unlike subsection (2) of Section 20, in<lb/> clauses (a) and (b), there is no specific provision for<lb/> giving a reasonable opportunity to the person<lb/> concerned. But it seems to me from the language<lb/> employed therein and also in view of the object sought<lb/> to be achieved, it is to be regarded that acting upon<lb/> the principles of natural justice regarding hearing of<lb/> the claimant is necessary while deciding his claim for<lb/> exemption thereunder. Satisfaction of the State<lb/> Government contemplated under clauses (a) and (b)<lb/> of subsection (1) of Section 20 of the Act has to, be<lb/> with regard to the question of public interest or the<lb/> nature of hard ship, which would be caused to the<lb/> claimant. Having regard to these objects to be<lb/> achieved, it must be reasonable to hold that the<lb/> satisfaction envisaged has to be objective in its<lb/> character and cannot be merely subjective satisfaction<lb/> the touchstone for testing the validity or otherwise of<lb/> the satisfaction having been provided by the law. In<lb/> this view, the function of the State Government,<lb/> appears to me, is of a quasijudicial character. The<lb/> view I take gains support from a decision of the<lb/> Madhya Pradesh High Court in Nandakishore v.<lb/> State, AIR 1982 Madh. Pra. 33.&quot;<lb/> 105<lb/> The above observations have been followed in a Division<lb/> Bench judgment of this Court reported in 1988 Mh.L.J. 773 (Janardhan<lb/> Gadekar v/s Assistant Collector and Competent Authority). (see para 13).</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>113<lb/> Equally, Mr.Naphade&apos;s reliance upon the judgments of the<lb/> Honourable Supreme Court in the case of State of U.P. v/s Hari Ram<lb/> reported in (2013) 4 SCC 280, M/s Tata Coffee Limited v/s Government of<lb/> Andhra Pradesh in Writ </table>
 
            <head>Petition No.11929 of 2013 decided on<lb/> 22</head>

            <note>.07.2013 (Andhra Pradesh High Court) and Gajanan Kamlya Patil v/s<lb/> Additional Collector &amp; Competent Authority in Civil Appeal<lb/> No.2069/2014 decided on 14.02.2014 by the Honourable Supreme</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:40 :::</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>are against the<lb/> Public Policy and would affect the citizens who are the<lb/> original owners of the lands and were legally granted<lb/> exemption to hold vacant lands in excess of the ceiling<lb/> limit U/s. 20 of the Urban Land (Ceiling and<lb/> Regulation) Act, 1976 (hereinafter referred to as &quot;the<lb/> ULC Act&quot;, which has been repealed w.e.f. 29.11.2007<lb/> by the Government by adopting the Urban Land<lb/> (Ceiling And Regulation) Repeal Act, 1999<lb/> (hereinafter referred to as &quot;the Repeal Act&quot;). Though<lb/> the ULC Act has been repealed intentionally and<lb/> malafidely, Government has issued the aforesaid<lb/> resolutions which are impugned in this petition. As a<lb/> result, the Government, instead of ruling out<lb/> manipulation, is giving opportunity to the respondent<lb/> Nos. 2 and 3 to take arbitrary and malafide decision<lb/> so as to harass the original land owners/scheme<lb/> holders as well as a common man who has purchased<lb/> the flats in the said Scheme. It is submitted that, after<lb/> granting exemption to hold vacant land in excess of<lb/> the ceiling limit under section 20 of the ULC Act, the<lb/> land owners have to surrender certain portion of the<lb/> vacant land to the Government free of cost. The<lb/> Government, prior to adoption of Repeal Act, allowed<lb/> to utilize such </table>
 
            <figDesc>lands by the original land owners<lb/> under the provisions of section 23 of the said Act, if it<lb/> was not possible to use such a land for any public<lb/> purpose and was likely to be encroached. It is further<lb/> submitted that considering inability of Government to<lb/> protect the possession of said land, it was permissible<lb/> to the land owners to buyback such lands vide<lb/> Government Resolution No.ULC 10 (2004)/C<lb/> No.93/ULCA2 dated 14.07.2004. However, for no<lb/> cogent reason, Government has issued the impugned<lb/> Resolution dated 8.11.2007 which is primafacie<lb/> arbitrary, unjust and not in the public interest and<lb/> therefore, the same is liable to be quashed and set<lb/> aside. This decision of the Government is arbitrary<lb/> and that would give rise to the respondent Nos. 2 and<lb/> 3 to allot such lands (surrendered lands) to the men<lb/> of their choice. This has happened on a large scale, as<lb/> has been specifically observed and pointed out by the<lb/> &quot;JUSTICE BATTA COMMISSION&quot; and therefore,<lb/> revoking the earlier decision i.e. buyback of<lb/> surrendered land, again there would be accumulation<lb/> of huge lands with the respondent Nos. 2 and 3 and<lb/> there would be repetition of the malafide acts by the<lb/> respondent Nos. 2 and 3. As a result of which, the<lb/> main aim and object of the Special Act would be<lb/> defeated.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>4.<lb/> It is submitted by the learned counsel for the<lb/> petitioner that Government has issued a G.R. dated<lb/> 31.07.2006, however, the effect and operation of said<lb/> Government Resolution has been stayed by this Court<lb/> in Writ Petition No.4966 of 2006 by passing the<lb/> following orders:<lb/> Order dt.4.10.2006 :<lb/> &quot;Heard Mr. C.V.Kale, Adv. for the petitioner.<lb/> Notice returnable in three weeks.<lb/> Mr.Agrawal, AGP waives notice on behalf of<lb/> respondent nos. 1 to 3.</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>In the case in hand, we are concerned with Subclause<lb/> (b) of Section (3) of Repeal Act which contemplates that<lb/> repeal of the principal Act shall not affect validity of any<lb/> order granting exemption under subsection (1) of<lb/> Section 20 or any action taken thereunder, not<lb/> withstanding any judgment of any Court to the counter.<lb/> It is, therefore, evident that validity of order granting<lb/> exemption under subsection (1) of Section 20 of the ULC<lb/> Act though passed prior to Repeal Act came into force,<lb/> would continue in view of the said saving clause.<lb/> Similarly, any action taken by the State Government<lb/> under subsection (2) of Section 20 prior to the Repeal<lb/> Act came into force is also continued to be valid even<lb/> after the Repeal Act came into force. Perusal of<lb/> provisions of Section 3 (1)(b) makes it evident that<lb/> repeal of Principal Act shall not affect validity of any<lb/> order granting exemption under subsection (1) of<lb/> Section 20 or any action taken thereunder. Hence, to<lb/> grant exemption in respect of land which was in excess<lb/> of the ceiling limit as well as action, if any taken by the<lb/> State Government thereunder in view of Section 20 (1)<lb/> is saved. Similarly, any action taken by the State<lb/> Government against the scheme holder under subclause</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>Paragraph 7 of the judgment reads as under:<lb/> &quot;7.<lb/> With the assistance of the learned counsel appearing<lb/> for parties we have perused the Writ Petition and also<lb/> the Division Bench judgment. Facts in our case are not<lb/> disputed. There has been no step or action taken in<lb/> pursuance of the order of exemption passed in favour<lb/> of the petitioner. Thus, the scheme was not<lb/> implemented. If it was not implemented, then, the<lb/> Division Bench judgment in Vithabai&apos;s case takes the<lb/> view that the consequence of passing an order under<lb/> Section 20(1) results in exemption of surplus vacant<lb/> land from the provisions of the Act. However, on<lb/> withdrawal of the exemption under Section 20(2) of<lb/> the Urban Land Ceiling Act, that does not provide that<lb/> possession of surplus land would automatically or is<lb/> deemed to have been taken by the Competent<lb/> Authority. If the State of Maharashtra is required to<lb/> resort to provisions of Chapter III of Urban Land</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <figDesc>The above Petition is filed on behalf of the members of<lb/> the Petitioner Association. The members of the Petitioner<lb/> Association who are the builders and developers have<lb/> taken benefit of the schemes meant for the Economically<lb/> Weaker Section of the society under Section 20 of the<lb/> Urban Land (Ceiling and Regulation) Act, 1976<lb/> [hereinafter referred to as &quot;the said Act&quot; for short]. The<lb/> said Act was repealed by the Urban Land (Ceiling and<lb/> Regulation) Repeal Act, 1999 which came into force in<lb/> the State of Maharashtra on 29.11.2007. Since a large<lb/> number of schemes were sanctioned under Section 20 of<lb/> the said Act, the State Government, with a view to see<lb/> that the schemes are fully implemented, if partly<lb/> implemented, after the repeal of the said Act, issued a<lb/> letter dated 23.06.2008 to the SubRegistrar of<lb/> Assurances, Thane City directing him to ascertain at the<lb/> time when the scheme holder presents a document for<lb/> registration, whether the scheme holder has sought for<lb/> extension for implementation of the scheme or not; as<lb/> otherwise not to register the documents in question.<lb/> 2.<lb/> It is the said letter dated 23.06.2008, which is impugned<lb/> in the present Petition. The principal ground on which<lb/> the said letter is assailed is that such a condition cannot<lb/> be imposed by the Registering Authority and that the<lb/> registration cannot be refused on the said ground.<lb/> 3.</figDesc>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>The statement of objects and reasons contained in the bill is in the<lb/> following terms :<lb/> &quot;<lb/> The Urban Land (Ceiling and Regulation) Act, 1976<lb/> was passed with a laudable social objective. The main<lb/> purpose was to prevent concentration of urban land<lb/> in a few hands and to provide affordable housing to<lb/> the Economically Weaker Sections. It has on the<lb/> contrary pushed up land prices, practically brought<lb/> the housing industry to a stop and provided<lb/> opportunities for corruption. There is a widespread<lb/> demand for removing this irritant to land assembly<lb/> and construction activity. During the implementation<lb/> of the Urban Land (Ceiling and Regulation) Act,<lb/> 1976, there have been a spate of litigations giving rise<lb/> to serious hurdles in taking over possession of land,<lb/> by the State Governments. Public opinion is nearly<lb/> unanimous that the Act has failed to achieve its<lb/> objectives as expected.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>2.<lb/> Parliament has no power to repeal or amend the Act<lb/> unless resolutions are passed by two or more State<lb/> Legislatures as required under clause (2) of Article<lb/> 252. The Legislatures of Haryana and Punjab have<lb/> passed resolutions empowering Parliament to repeal<lb/> the Act in those States. The Act stands repealed in<lb/> those States and in the Union territories immediately<lb/> after promulgation of the repeal Ordinance and<lb/> subsequently if State Legislatures adopt this Repeal<lb/> Act by resolution, then the Urban Land (Ceiling and<lb/> Regulation) Act, 1976 will stand repealed in those<lb/> States, from the date of its adoption.<lb/> 3.<lb/> The Urban Land (Ceiling and Regulation) Repeal Bill,<lb/> 1998 was examined by the Standing Committee on<lb/> Urban and Rural Development. The Committee felt<lb/> that the land which is yet to be put to use for the<lb/> original purposes stated in the Act, under possession<lb/> of the Government should not be restored to previous<lb/> owners as such restoration may lead to avoidable<lb/> discrimination. The Committee also suggested that the<lb/> repeal Bill should contain a provision for abatement<lb/> of proceedings in </table>
 
            <figDesc>the different courts. Keeping in view<lb/> the recommendations of the Committee, this Bill is<lb/> being introduced to replace the Urban Land (Ceiling<lb/> and Regulation) Repeal Ordinance, 1999 (Ord.5 of<lb/> 1999) notified on 11.01.1999 so that the State<lb/> Governments would be free to have their own<lb/> legislation commensurate with their needs and<lb/> experiences. Till this Act is repealed, States have no<lb/> power to legislate on this subject.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <note>4.<lb/> The proposed repeal, along with some other incentives<lb/> and simplification of administrative procedures, is<lb/> expected to revive the stagnant housing industry. The<lb/> repeal will facilitate construction of dwelling units<lb/> both in the public and private sector and help<lb/> achievement of targets contemplated under National<lb/> Agenda for Governance. The repeal will not, however,<lb/> affect vesting of any vacant land under subsection<lb/> (3) of Section 10 of the Urban Land (Ceiling and<lb/> Regulation) Act, 1976 the possession of which has<lb/> been taken over by the State Governments. It will not<lb/> affect payments made to the State Governments for<lb/> exemptions. The exemptions granted under Section 20<lb/> of the Act will continue to be operative. The amounts<lb/> paid out by the State Governments will become<lb/> refundable before restoration of the land to the<lb/> former owners.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>5.<lb/> The Bill also seeks to facilitate land assembly and a<lb/> flexible regime for administering urban land to suit<lb/> the varying local conditions based on State level<lb/> legislations or requirements.&quot;<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>The bill was passed by the Parliament and the Repeal Act was enacted.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>The Repeal Act contains the following provisions :<lb/> &quot;1.<lb/> Short title and application commencement: -<lb/>(1) This Act may be called the Urban Land (Ceiling<lb/> and Regulation) Repeal Act, 1999.<lb/> (2)<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>It applies in the first instance to the whole of the<lb/> States of Haryana and Punjab and to all the Union<lb/> territories; and it shall apply to such other State<lb/> which adopts this Act by resolution passed in that<lb/> behalf under clause (2) of article 252 of the<lb/> Constitution.<lb/> (3) It shall be deemed to have come into force in<lb/> the States of Haryana and Punjab and in all the<lb/> Union territories on the 11th day of January, 1999<lb/> and in any other State which adopts this Act under<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <note>clause (2) of article 252 of the Constitution on the<lb/> date of such adoption; and the reference to repeal of<lb/> the Urban Land (Ceiling and Regulation) Act, 1976<lb/> shall, in relation to any State or Union territory,<lb/> mean the date on which this Act comes into force in<lb/> such State or Union territory.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>2.<lb/> Repeal of Act 33 of 1976: -The Urban Land (Ceiling<lb/> and Regulation) Act, 1976 (hereinafter referred to as<lb/> the principal Act) is hereby repealed.<lb/> 3.<lb/> Savings: -<lb/>(1) The repeal of the principal Act shall not affect<lb/> (a) the vesting of any vacant land under<lb/> subsection (3) of section 10, possession of which has<lb/> been taken over by the State Government or any<lb/> person duly authorised by the State Government in<lb/> this behalf or by the competent authority;<lb/> (b) the validity of any order granting<lb/> exemption under subsection (1) of section 20 or any<lb/> action taken thereunder, notwithstanding any<lb/> judgment of any court to the contrary;<lb/> (c) any payment made to the State<lb/> Government as a condition for granting exemption<lb/> under subsection (1) of section 20.</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>of 1976);<lb/> And Whereas, consequent upon the<lb/> resolutions passed by the Houses of the Legislatures of<lb/> the States of Haryana and Punjab, under article<lb/> 252(2) of the Constitution, that the Urban Land<lb/> (Ceiling and Regulation) Act, 1976, in its application<lb/> to those States, be repealed by Parliament by law, the<lb/> Parliament has enacted the Urban Land (Ceiling and<lb/> Regulation) Repeal Act, 1999 (Act No. 15 of 1999);<lb/> And Whereas, subsection (2) of section<lb/> 1 of the Urban Land (Ceiling and Regulation) Repeal<lb/> Act, 1999, provides that the said Act shall apply to<lb/> such other State which adopts the said Act by<lb/> resolution passed in that behalf under clause (2) of<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>::: Uploaded on -11/09/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:51:40 :::<lb/> <note>*197*<lb/> article 252 of the Constitution;<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>And Whereas, the Government of<lb/> Maharashtra is of the opinion that the Urban Land<lb/> (Ceiling and Regulation) Act, 1976 should be<lb/> repealed, in its application to the State of<lb/> Maharashtra, so that land in urban area may be<lb/> available for housing;<lb/> Now, therefore, in pursuance of clause<lb/> (2) of article 252 of the Constitution of India, the<lb/> Maharashtra Legislative Assembly hereby resolves<lb/> that the Urban Land (Ceiling and Regulation) Repeal<lb/> Act, 1999, passed by the Parliament be adopted for<lb/> this State.&quot;<lb/> Accordingly, the Repeal Act was brought into force in the<lb/> State of Maharashtra on 29 November 2007.</figDesc>
		</figure>



    </text>
</tei>

