<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_b307e7b0dff6faf6df150163723a584c.pdf"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">


        <figure>

            POINTS<lb/> (1)<lb/> Whether the prosecution<lb/> has<lb/> established that accused No.I being the<lb/> Executive Director of Syndicate Bank,<lb/> entered into criminal conspiracy with<lb/> accused No.2 who was the Managing<lb/> Director of the non-government non<lb/> banking financial company viz. M/s Fair<lb/> Growth Investments Ltd. (FGIL) with the<lb/> object<lb/> of<lb/> illegally<lb/> and<lb/> dishonestly<lb/> committing criminal breach of trust of the<lb/> funds placed in the Portfolio Management<lb/> Scheme (PMS) of the Syndicate Bank by a<lb/> Government of India Undertaking viz. Oil<lb/> Industry Development Board (OIDB) and<lb/> thereby committed an offence punishable<lb/> under section 120B red with section 409<lb/> FINDINGS<lb/> In the<lb/> negative<lb/> of the Indian Penal Code by violating<lb/> specific directions given by the OIDB and<lb/> the guidelines given by the Reserve Bank<lb/> of India?<lb/> (2)<lb/> Whether the prosecution has<lb/> established that in </content>
 
            <figDesc>pursuance of the said<lb/> conspiracy, accused No. l used his official<lb/> position to persuade OIDB to place m<lb/> Portfolio Management Scheme (PMS) of<lb/> Syndicate Bank an amount of Rs 132.22<lb/> crores through several remittances of<lb/> various amounts during the period from<lb/> 2.4.1992 to 30.5.1992 in violation of the<lb/> directions given by OIDB and whether the<lb/> prosecution has proved that the accused<lb/> No. I invested in the said Company<lb/> through accused No.2 an amount of Rs<lb/> 93, 17, 77,925 through five remittances<lb/> during the period 07 /05/1992 to<lb/> 29/06/1992 in order to enable accused<lb/> No.2 to make wrongful gains and thereby<lb/> committed an offence under section 409<lb/> of the Indian Penal Code?</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            conspiracy, accused No.I has a motive or<lb/> reward for causing the wrongful gcnn to<lb/> accused No.2<lb/> and/or<lb/> his<lb/> Company<lb/> obtained 62000 shares </content>
 
            <figDesc>in his name and in<lb/> the name of his family members from the<lb/> promoters&apos; quota of FGIL and it&apos;s sister<lb/> concern the Fairgrowth Financial Services<lb/> Ltd and committed an offence punishable<lb/> under section 13(1) (d) read with section<lb/> 13(2) and section 7 of the Prevention of<lb/> Corruption Act, 1988?<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> (4)<lb/> Whether the prosecution has<lb/> established<lb/> that<lb/> the<lb/> accused<lb/> No.2<lb/> instigated and abetted </content>
 
            <figDesc>accused No.1 in<lb/> obtaining the said 62000 shares by way of<lb/> motive/reward for enabling him to make<lb/> the aforesaid wrongful<lb/> gain of Rs<lb/> 93, 17, 77, 925/ -and thereby committed an<lb/> offence punishable under section 12 of<lb/> the Prevention of Corruption Act.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> </content>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>return of 18.25o/o on its investments.<lb/> OIDB, through vanous<lb/> remittances, sent an amount of rs 132.22 crores to the Syndicate Bank,<lb/> Kasturba Gandhi Marg Branch, New Delhi. This amount, in tum, was<lb/> sent to the FIM Department of the Syndicate Bank at Bombay, who, in<lb/> tum, invested these amounts in shares of Private Companies. The<lb/> remittances were sent by OIDB between the period from 02/04/1992</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::</content>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>accused No.1 to accused No.2, 62000 shares were transferred in the<lb/> name of accused No.1 from the promoters&apos; quota of Mis Fair Growth<lb/> Investments Ltd. (FGIL) and its sister concern M/s Fairgrowth<lb/> Financial Services Ltd. and, accordingly, a complaint was lodged on<lb/> 02/06/ 1993 by Shri V. Sethumadhavan, Chief Vigilance Officer,<lb/> Syndicate Bank, Head Office, Manipal with the Central Bureau of<lb/> Investigation, Mumabi under section 120B read •with section 420 of<lb/> the Indian Penal Code and under section 13(2) read with section<lb/> 13(1)(d) of the Prevention of Corruption •Act, 1988 against Shri R.<lb/> Sundaresan, the then Divisional Manager, Syndicate Bank, FIM<lb/> Division, Bombay and Directors and Office bearers of M/s Fair Growth<lb/> Investments Ltd. (FGIL) and its sister concern M/s. Fair Growth<lb/> Financial Services Ltd. (FGFSL)<lb/> 10. On 24/07 /1997, a charge-sheet was filed by the Central Bureau<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> of Investigation, Bank Securities &amp; Fraud Cell, Bombay in the Special<lb/> Court constituted under the Special Courts (Trial of Offences Relating<lb/> to Transactions in Securities) Act, 1992 at Bombay against Shri R.S.<lb/> Pai, the then Executive Director, Syndicate Bank, the accused No.1 and<lb/> Shri<lb/> K. R. N. Shenoy, Managing Director of M/s Fair Growth<lb/> Investments Ltd., the accused No.2<lb/> and the charge-sheet was<lb/> registered as Special Case No.3 of 1997 in the Special Court at<lb/> Bombay.<lb/> 11. Both the accused filed discharge applications and during the<lb/> course of hearing of these discharge applications, the Counsel for the<lb/> prosecution thought it necessary to file additional documents and<lb/> additional statements in addition to the charge-sheet which was<lb/> already filed. Accordingly CBI filed Misc. Application No.338 of 2000<lb/> under section 173 of the Code of Criminal Procedure on 26/07 /2000,<lb/> seeking permission of the Court to place on record (i) list of 15<lb/> additional witnesses and their respective statements recorded under<lb/> section 161 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, (ii) list of all the 67<lb/> persons whose statements were recorded under section 161 of the<lb/> Code of Criminal Procedure, (iii) list of all search/seizure receipt<lb/> memos under which all documents have been seized by CBI and (iv)<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> additional list of </content>
 
            <figDesc>documents with the CBI on which reliance was placed<lb/> by CBI.<lb/> This application was rejected by the Special Court on<lb/> 26/07 /2000.<lb/> 12. CBI preferred an appeal in the Apex Court against the said order<lb/> and the appeal was allowed by the Apex Court on 03/04/2002 and the<lb/> order passed by the Special Court was set aside and the permission was<lb/> granted to CBI for production of additional documents. Thereafter,<lb/> again, discharge applications filed by the accused were heard and<lb/> were dismissed. Charge was framed against the accused, after they<lb/> pleaded not guilty to the offence with which they were charged.<lb/> Prosecution, in support of its case, examined 16 witnesses and brought<lb/> on record number of documents.<lb/> 13. After having gone through the oral and documentary evidence<lb/> which is brought on record, in my view, the prosecution has not<lb/> established that accused No.1 committed an offence punishable under<lb/> section 120B read with section 409 of the Indian Pen a l Code or has<lb/> committed an offence punishable under section 13(1)(d) read with<lb/> section 13(2) read with section 7 of the Prevention of Corruption Act,<lb/> 1988. Prosecution also has not established that the accused No.2 has<lb/> aided or abetted accused No. l for commission of the offence<lb/> punishable under section 409 of the Indian Penal code or for the<lb/> offence punishable under section 13(1)(d) read with section 13(2)<lb/> read with section 7 of the Prevention of Corruption Act, 1988.<lb/> Prosecution has not established that accused Nos. 1 and 2 had entered<lb/> into criminal conspiracy of diverting funds remitted by OIDB to the<lb/> Private Company of accused No.2 in oder to cause wrongful gain to<lb/> accused No.2 and wrongful loss to OIDB.<lb/> 14. I have come to the above conclusion for the following reasons.<lb/> 15. The first point which falls for consideration is : whether the<lb/> prosecution has established that accused No.1 and accused No.2 had<lb/> entered into conspiracy to misappropriate the funds which were sent<lb/> by OIDB?<lb/> 16. In the present case, admitted position is that the funds which .<lb/> were remitted by OIDB were sent directly to Syndicate Bank, Delhi<lb/> Branch and, thereafter, Delhi Branch of Syndicate Bank had sent these<lb/> • amounts to FIM Branch of the Syndicate Bank at Bombay and,<lb/> thereafter, Syndicate Bank, Bombay Branch, had remitted these<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> amounts to accused No.2 for the purpose of investing it in the<lb/> Companies. Prosecution has not been in a position to establish any<lb/> direct link with accused No. l who was the Executive Director of<lb/> Syndicate Bank and was stationed at Manipal, Kamataka State where<lb/> the Syndicate Bank has its Head Office. Neither the witnesses who<lb/> were examined from OIDB nor the witnesses who have been examined<lb/> from the Syndicate Bank have stated that. these funds were given to<lb/> accused No.2 on the instructions of accused No. l. On the contrary,<lb/> there is a documentary evidence on record to indicate that OIDB<lb/> Officers had, in tum, stated in their letter that they had no concern<lb/> with the PIM Branch of the Syndicate Bank at Bombay and that they<lb/> were concerned directly with the Delhi Branch of the Syndicate Bank<lb/> since the remittances were made through the Delhi Branch of the<lb/> Syndicate Bank.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            17.<lb/> In order to </content>
 
            <figDesc>establish the offence of conspiracy, prosecution has to<lb/> bring on record either direct or indirect evidence for the purpose of<lb/> establishing that there was meeting of minds on the part of the accused<lb/> to commit an illegal act by illegal means. It is normally not possible to<lb/> get direct evidence to establish the offence of criminal conspiracy and,<lb/> in large number of cases, prosecution has established criminal<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> conspiracy on the basis of circumstantial evidence. Law in respect of<lb/> criminal conspiracy has been laid down in several judgments of the<lb/> Apex Court and this Court. In the recent judgment in the case of Ram<lb/> Narayan Popli Vs. CBI reported in (2003) 3 SCC 641, arising out of<lb/> Special Courts (Trial of Offences Relating to Transactions in Securities)<lb/> Act, 1992 the Apex Court has made the following observations.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            comm1ss10n<lb/> of<lb/> the<lb/> crime<lb/> of<lb/> criminal<lb/> conspiracy. It </content>
 
            <figDesc>has to be shown that all means<lb/> adopted and illegal acts done were in<lb/> furtherance of the object of conspiracy<lb/> hatched.<lb/> The circumstances relied for the<lb/> purposes of drawing an inference should be<lb/> prior in time than the actual commission of<lb/> the offence in furtherance of the alleged<lb/> conspiracy.<lb/> 34 7.<lb/> Privacy and secrecy are more<lb/> characteristics of a conspiracy, than of a loud<lb/> discussion in an elevated place open to public</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>these two persons pursued by their acts<lb/> the same object, often by the same<lb/> means, one performing one part of an<lb/> act, and the other another part of the<lb/> same act, so as to complete it, with a<lb/> view to the attainment of the object<lb/> which they were pursuing , you will be<lb/> at liberty to draw the conclusion that<lb/> they have been engaged in a conspiracy<lb/> to effect that object. The question you<lb/> have to ask yourselves is, &apos; had they this<lb/> common design, and did they pursue it<lb/> by these common means -the design<lb/> being unlawful?&quot;<lb/> 351.<lb/> As noted above, the essential<lb/> ingredient of the offence of criminal<lb/> conspiracy is the agreement to commit<lb/> an offence.<lb/> In a case where the<lb/> agreement is for accomplishment of an<lb/> act which they itself constitutes an<lb/> offence, then in that event no overt act<lb/> is necessazy to be proved by the<lb/> prosecution because in such a situation,<lb/> criminal conspiracy is established by<lb/> proving such an agreement. Where the<lb/> conspiracy alleged is with regard to<lb/> commission of a serious crime of the<lb/> nature as contemplated in Section 120-B<lb/> read with the proviso to sub-section (2)<lb/> of section 120-A, then in that event<lb/> mere proof of an agreement between<lb/> the accused for commission of such a<lb/> crime alone is enough to bring about a<lb/> conviction under Section 120-B and the<lb/> proof of any overt act by the accused or<lb/> by any one of them would not be<lb/> necessary.<lb/> The provisions, in such a<lb/> situation, do not require that each and<lb/> every person who is a party to the<lb/> conspiracy must do some overt act<lb/> towards the fulfilment of the object of<lb/> conspiracy, the essential ingredient<lb/> being<lb/> an<lb/> agreement between<lb/> the<lb/> conspirators to commit the crime and if<lb/> these requirements and ingredients are<lb/> established, the act would fall within the<lb/> trappings of the provisions contained in<lb/> Section 120-B (See: Suresh Chandra<lb/> Bahri v. State of Bihar [1995 Supp (1)<lb/> sec soJ<lb/> 352. The conspiracies are not hatched<lb/> in the open, by their nature, they are<lb/> secretly planned, they can be proved<lb/> even by circumstantial evidence, the<lb/> lack of direct evidence relating to<lb/> conspiracy has no consequence. (See :<lb/> E.K. Chandrasenan v. State of Kerala<lb/> [(1995) 2 sec 99])<lb/> 353. In Kehar Singh v. State (Delhi<lb/> Admn.) [(1988) 3 sec 609] (AIR at p.<lb/> 1954), this Court observed: (SCC pp.<lb/> 732-33, para 275).<lb/> &quot;275.<lb/> Generally, a conspiracy is<lb/> hatched in secrecy and it may be<lb/> difficult to adduce direct evidence of<lb/> the same. The prosecution will often<lb/> rely on evidence of acts of various<lb/> parties to inf er that they were done in<lb/> reference to their common intention.<lb/> The prosecution will also more often<lb/> rely upon circumstantial evidence.<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> The conspiracy can be undoubtedly<lb/> proved by such evidence direct or<lb/> circumstantial.<lb/> But he court must<lb/> enquire whether the two persons are<lb/> independently pursing the same end<lb/> or they have come together to the<lb/> pursuit of unlawful object.<lb/> The<lb/> former<lb/> does<lb/> not<lb/> render<lb/> them<lb/> conspirators, but </content>
 
            <figDesc>the latter does. It is,<lb/> however, essential that the offence of<lb/> conspiracy requires some<lb/> kind of<lb/> physical fanifestation of agreement.<lb/> The express agreement, however,<lb/> need not be proved.<lb/> Nor actual<lb/> meeting of two persons is necessary.<lb/> Nor it is necessary to prove the actual<lb/> words of communication.<lb/> The<lb/> evidence as to tansm1ss1on of<lb/> thoughts sharing the unlawful design<lb/> may be sufficient.&quot;<lb/> &quot;Conspiracy can be proved by<lb/> circumstances and other materials.&quot;<lb/> (See: State of Bihar v. Paramhans<lb/> Yadav [1986 Pat LJR 688 (HC) )<lb/> : [T]o establish a charge of<lb/> conspiracy<lb/> knowledge<lb/> about<lb/> indulgence in either an illegal act or a<lb/> legal act by illegal<lb/> means is</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            354.<lb/> It<lb/> was noticed that Section<lb/> 120-A and 120-B IPC have brought<lb/> the law of conspiracy in India in line<lb/> with the English law by making an<lb/> overt<lb/> act<lb/> inessential<lb/> when<lb/> the<lb/> conspiracy<lb/> is<lb/> to<lb/> commit<lb/> any<lb/> punishable<lb/> offence.<lb/> The<lb/> most<lb/> important ingredient of the offence<lb/> being the agreement between two or<lb/> more persons to do an illegal act. In<lb/> a case where criminal conspiracy is<lb/> alleged, the court must inquire<lb/> whether<lb/> the<lb/> two<lb/> persons<lb/> are<lb/> independently pursuing the same end<lb/> or they have come together to pursue<lb/> the unlawful object. The former does<lb/> not render them conspirators but the<lb/> latter does.<lb/> For the offence of<lb/> conspiracy, some kind of physical<lb/> manifestation<lb/> of<lb/> agreement<lb/> 1s<lb/> required to be established.<lb/> The<lb/> express agreement need not be<lb/> proved.<lb/> The<lb/> evidence<lb/> as<lb/> to<lb/> transmission of thoughts sharing the<lb/> unlawful act is not sufficient.<lb/> A<lb/> conspiracy is a continuing offence<lb/> which continues to subsist till it is<lb/> executed or rescinded or frustrated by &apos;<lb/> choice of necessity.<lb/> During its<lb/> subsistence, whenever any one of the<lb/> conspirators does an act or series of<lb/> acts, he would be held guilty under<lb/> Section 120-B of the Indian Penal<lb/> Code.<lb/> 355.<lb/> I may usefully </content>
 
            <figDesc>refer to Ajay<lb/> Aggarwal v. Union of India, [(1993) 3<lb/> SCC 609]. It was held : (SCC p.617,<lb/> para 8-9)<lb/> •<lb/> &quot;8. . .... It is not necessary that each<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> conspirator must lmow all the details<lb/> of the scheme nor be a participant at<lb/> every stage. It is necessary that they<lb/> should agree for design or object of<lb/> the<lb/> conspiracy.<lb/> Conspiracy<lb/> is<lb/> conceived as having three elements:<lb/> (1) agreement; (2) between two or<lb/> more<lb/> persons<lb/> by<lb/> whom<lb/> the<lb/> agreement is effected</content>

            <figDesc>; and (3) a<lb/> criminal object, which may be either<lb/> the ultimate aim of the agreement, or<lb/> may constitute means, or one of the<lb/> means by which that aim is to be<lb/> accomplished.<lb/> It is immaterial<lb/> whether this is found in the ultimate<lb/> objects. The common law definition<lb/> of &apos; criminal conspiracy&apos; was stated<lb/> first by Lord Denman in Jones case<lb/> [ R. v. Jones, 1832 B &amp; Ad 345] that<lb/> an indictment for conspiracy must<lb/> &apos; charge a conspiracy to do an<lb/> unlawful act by unlawful means&apos; and<lb/> was elaborated by Willies, J. on<lb/> behalf of the Judges while referring<lb/> the question to the House of Lords in<lb/> Mulcahy v. R [(1868) 3 HL 306] and<lb/> the House of Lords in unanimous<lb/> decision reiterated in<lb/> Quinn v.<lb/> Leathern (1901 AC 495]:<lb/> enforced, if lawful: and punishable if<lb/> for a criminal object, or for the use of<lb/> criminal means.&apos;<lb/> 9. This Court in E.G. Barsay v. State<lb/> of Bombay [AIR 1961 SC 1762] held:</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>&quot; [See<lb/> State of Kerala v. P. Sugathan [(2000)<lb/> 8 SCC 203] (SCC p. 212, para 14)]&quot;<lb/> 18. Keeping in view the aforesaid principle laid down by the Apex</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>were remitted from the Delhi Branch of the Syndicate Bank to FIM<lb/> Branch of Syndicate Bank at Bombay. However, surprisingly, charges<lb/> against the said Shri R. Sundaresan were dropped when the charge<lb/> sheet was filed and this person who was named as accused was, later<lb/> on, examined as a witness by the prosecution.<lb/> No explanation has<lb/> been given by the prosecution as to why and for what reason the<lb/> Investigating Officer felt that it was not necessary to make the said R.<lb/> Sundaresan as an accused and in his place accused No.1 -R.S. Pai who<lb/> was stationed at Manipal, Kamataka State, was made an accused in<lb/> this case. When a query was made by this Court whether there was<lb/> any direct or indirect evidence against accused No.1 for the purpose of<lb/> proving that accused Nos. 1 and 2 conspired together, Mr. V.G.<lb/> Pradhan, the learned Special Public Prosecutor, very candidly stated<lb/> that no such documentary or oral evidence is available which could<lb/> establish that accused No.1 -R.S. Pai had entered into conspiracy with<lb/> accused No.2 -K. R. N. Shenoy. Prosecution has examined in all 16<lb/> witnesses.<lb/> 19.<lb/> P.W. 1 -V.P. Chugh, at the relevant time, was working as an<lb/> accountant in OIDB. It is pertinent to note that questions were asked<lb/> by Mr. Pradhan, the learned Special Public Prosecutor, to this witness<lb/> without declaring the said witness as hostile. Thereafter, after the<lb/> witness was cross-examined by the Counsel appearing for accused Nos.<lb/> 1 and 2, permission was sought by Mr. V.G. Pradhan, the learned<lb/> Special Public Prosecutor appearing for CBI to re-examine this witness.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>examination which was taken by Mr. V.G. Pradhan, Special Public<lb/> Prosecutor for CBI.<lb/> P.W. 2 -Arvind Kaushal was working as Financial Adviser and<lb/> Chief Accounts Officer for a period from October, 1991 to May, 1992.<lb/> P. W. 1 was also working in the same Department and he was<lb/> subordinate to P. W. 2.<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> P.W 3 -R. Sundaresan was working as Divisional Manager of<lb/> FIM Division Branch of Syndicate Bank at Bombay. A complaint was<lb/> lodged against him by Shri V. Sethumadhavan of the Vigilance Branch<lb/> of the Syndicate Bank. However, his name was dropped and in his<lb/> place the name of R.S. Pai was included and R. Sundaresan was<lb/> examined as the witness on behalf of the prosecution.<lb/> P.W. 4 -E.R. Seshadri was working as Deputy General Manager<lb/> of Syndicate Bank at Delhi Zonal Office.<lb/> P. W 5 -R. Kalyanasundaram was working in the Syndicate Bank<lb/> in its Funds and Investment Management Department (FIM) during<lb/> the relevant period.<lb/> P.W 6 -Shreyas Morakhia and P.W. 7 -Sharad Jamnadas Shah<lb/> were carrying on business in the Stock Exchange at the relevant time.<lb/> However, they did not support the prosecution case.<lb/> P.W. 8 -Ameet Dalal was a stock broker at Bombay Stock<lb/> Exchange at the relevant time. He has brought on record the contract<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> note signed by him at Exhibit-119.<lb/> P.W. 9 -M. Damodaran was a Joint Secretary, Ministry of<lb/> Finance at the relevant time and he had given sanction to prosecute<lb/> accused No.I.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>Thereafter, OIDB issued a clarification to its earlier letters by adding<lb/> the word &quot;etc.&quot; to directions contained in six letters. Prosecution has<lb/> proved remittances which have been made by OIDB between<lb/> 02/04/ 1992 and 30/05/ 1992 in favour of Syndicate Bank, Kasturba<lb/> Gandhi Marg Branch, New Delhi.<lb/> Prosecution has also proved<lb/> remittances of. the amount from Syndicate Bank, Kasturba Gandhi<lb/> Marg Branch, New Delhi to the FIM Branch of Syndicate Bank, Fort,<lb/> Bombay through interbank advice notes. Prosecution also has proved<lb/> that this amount was used for the purpose of purchasing shares in the<lb/> open market and these shares were purchased in the name of OIDB.<lb/> The brokers in the Stock Exchange who have been examined have<lb/> identified the contract notes for the purchase of shares out of the said<lb/> amount remitted to FIM Branch of the Syndicate Bank, Fort, Bombay.<lb/> The evidence on record and particularly the evidence of P.W. 1 -V.P.<lb/> Chugh and P.W 2 -Arvind Kaushal, on close scrutiny, clearly indicates<lb/> that the officials of OIDB had tried to salvage the position of their<lb/> investment in PMS activity by writing various letters to Delhi Branch of<lb/> the Syndicate Bank, seeking their explanation about investments made<lb/> by Syndicate Bank, after the amount was remitted by OIDB to<lb/> Syndicate Bank, Delhi Branch. Though the prosecution has brought on<lb/> record documents to prove the remittances from OIDB to the Delhi<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> Branch of the Syndicate Bank and from Delhi Branch of the Syndicate<lb/> Bank to FIM Branch of the Syndicate Bank, Fort, Bombay, it has not<lb/> been in a position to establish the manner in which the accused No. l<lb/> who was the Executive Director of the Syndicate Bank and who was<lb/> stationed at Manipal, Kamataka State is involved in the entire episode<lb/> of investment of the funds sent by OIDB in various shares in the capital<lb/> market. Though an an attempt has been made by the prosecution by<lb/> examining P.W. 3 -R. Sundaresan and other witnesses from the<lb/> Syndicate Bank to suggest that it was under the oral instructions of<lb/> R.S. Pai -accused No. l that the said investments were made in the<lb/> capital market, there is no documentary evidence on record and except<lb/> the bare words of P.W. 3, there is no vital evidence to indicate<lb/> involvement of accused No.I in the entire episode. P.W 3 -R.<lb/> Sundaresan has stated in his evi dence that he had met R. S. Pai in<lb/> Hongkong and on the request made by him to R. S. Pai, he was<lb/> brought to FIM Branch of Syndicate Bank, Fort, Bombay. Prosecution<lb/> has further brought on record statements of witnesses working in the<lb/> Syndicate Bank. In March, 1992 a meeting was conveyed by R.S. Pai -<lb/>accused No. l in which he has stated that the profitability of the Bank<lb/> had to be increased and suggested that for that purpose PMS should be<lb/> increased and efforts should be made for the purpose of mobilization<lb/> of fu nds from various Companies so that these could be invested in<lb/> PMS services and, as a result, higher margin of profit could be earned<lb/> through PMS activities. P.W. 3 -R. Sundaresan has stated that he had<lb/> orally directed him to engage accused No.2 for the purpose of<lb/> investment of moneys collected from his customers in the capital<lb/> market instruments. Though P.W. 3 has tried to suggest that it was at<lb/> the behest of accused No. l these investments were made, his testimony<lb/> has not been supported by the other witnesses who were examined<lb/> through the Syndicate Bank who have stated in their evidence that a<lb/> Committee was formed and FIM Branch of the Syndicate Bank, Fort,<lb/> Bombay would decide the amounts which would be invested in the<lb/> capital market. The time and the scrips and other particulars would be<lb/> decided by the said Committee. Admittedly, accused No.1 -R.S. Pai<lb/> was not the member of this Committee. There is, therefore, a clear<lb/> contradiction in the evidence of P.W. 3 -R. Sundaresan and other<lb/> witnesses from the Syndicate Bank. Though P.W. 3 -R. Sundaresan<lb/> has stated that they had acted as per the oral instructions of accused<lb/> No.1 -R.S. Pai, the other witnesses have stated that decision to make<lb/> investments was made by the Committee consisting of four members of<lb/> which P.W. 3 was one of the members. Further, the evidence which is<lb/> brought on record also clearly indicates that the funds of the OIDB<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> were entrusted to the Kasturba Gandhi Marg Branch of the Syndicate<lb/> Bank at New Delhi, which, in tum, had entrusted these amounts to the<lb/> FIM Branch of the Syndicate Bank, Fort, Bombay. There is thus no<lb/> evidence on record to show that the funds of OIDB were entrusted to<lb/> R.S. Pai who was stationed at Manipal, Kamataka State or that the<lb/> funds were routed through the Head Office to the Bombay Office. On<lb/> the contrary, when the letter was written by FIM Branch of the<lb/> Syndicate Bank, Fort, Bombay to OIDB, a reply was sent by the off icials<lb/> of OIDB stating that they were not concerned with the FIM Division of<lb/> the Syndicate Bank, Fort, Bombay as they had dealt only with the<lb/> Kasturba Gandhi Marg Branch of the Syndicate Bank at New Delhi.<lb/> This clearly indicates that there was no entrustment of funds to<lb/> accused No.l and, therefore the principal ingredient for the offence<lb/> punishable under section 409 is clearly absent as the entrustment of<lb/> funds by the OIDB to accused No.1 has not been establish ed. Further,<lb/> though accused No.2 has been charged for the offence of conspiracy of<lb/> committing criminal breach of trust, the documentary evidence on<lb/> record indicates that the amounts which were remitted by the Kasturba<lb/> Gandhi Marg Branch of the Syndicate Bank at New Delhi to the FIM<lb/> Division of the Syndicate Bank, Fort, Bombay were not invested in the<lb/> Companies owned by accused No.2 and the amount of Rs 93 crores<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> was invested in shares in the capital market which were purchased in<lb/> the name of OIDB. This indicates that there was actual purchase of<lb/> shares in favour of OIDB and the transaction in question was not an<lb/> ostensible purchase or sale transaction of shares.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            23.<lb/> P.W</content>

            <figDesc>. 1 -V.P. Chugh has deposed that the Oil Industry<lb/> Development Board was constituted under the Oil Industry<lb/> Development Act, 1974. The Government levied cess under section 15<lb/> of the said Act. P.W. 2 -Arvind Kaushal has stated that OIDB was<lb/> constituted under the statute and, therefore, was an autonomous body<lb/> and the Government levied cess on oil and the proceeds were credited<lb/> to the consolidated funds of India and, therefore, from time to time,<lb/> the amounts were transferred to its statutory organizations. The funds<lb/> which were given to OIDB from the consolidated funds were spent on<lb/> research and development and the funds were also given to various oil<lb/> sector companies for the purpose of development. P.W. 1 has fu rther<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> stated that over and above giving loans to the approved Companies,<lb/> OIDB still had surplus funds at its disposal and these funds were<lb/> deposited with the Nationalized Banks only and some amounts were<lb/> invested in Saving Bank Accounts kept in Fixed Deposits and for a<lb/> short time in Government Securities. He has stated that during the<lb/> period from October, 1991 to May, 1992, OIDB had accounts with the<lb/> Indian Overseas Bank, State Bank of India and number of other<lb/> Nationalized Banks. P.W. 2 -Arvind Kaushal has further stated in his<lb/> evidence that the guidelines were laid down regarding the manner in<lb/> which these surplus funds were to be utilized or invested by the OIDB.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>deposition on pages Nos. 29 and 30 of the notes of ev idence as under:-<lb/>&quot;During the rele vant pe riod, surplus funds<lb/> were deployed in the Syndicate Bank. Dur ing<lb/> this period, the investment were not made in<lb/> one bul k amount but were made in different<lb/> installments. Roughly, I could say that in four<lb/> to five installment investment was made. It is<lb/> possible that it could be more or less<lb/> installments. The OIDB dealt with the ban ks<lb/> only through their offices and branches in New<lb/> Delhi.<lb/> The mode of investment in these<lb/> branches in New Delhi was that either the<lb/> represe ntative of the bank would come to the<lb/> board and collect the cheque or the officer of<lb/> the board would come to the board and collect<lb/> the cheque or the officer of the board would<lb/> go to the bank and deliver the cheque and<lb/> letter.<lb/> The covering letter which was sent<lb/> alongwith the cheque gave specific directions<lb/> to the bank regarding amount to be invested,<lb/> securities, the peri od of investment and lastly<lb/> the manner of deployment of those funds.&quot;<lb/> 24.<lb/> In this context, in entire evidence of P.W. 1 and P .W. 2, no<lb/> reference at all has bee n made to accused No.1 -R.S. Pai. It has never<lb/> been stated by both the witnesses that the funds were entrusted to R.S.<lb/> Pai or that he had, on telephone or orally made any commit me nt for<lb/> fixed return of the investments made by OIDB with the Syndicate<lb/> Bank. On the contrary, the letter which is written by the Syndicate<lb/> Bank clearl y indicates that they had offered tentative interest rates and<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> --------------------<lb/>�<lb/> �<lb/> �<lb/> 46<lb/> no firm </content>
 
            <figDesc>commitment was made by them. The only evidence which is<lb/> sought to be brought on record against accused No.I -R.S. Pai is the<lb/> statement of P.W. 5 -R. Kalyanasundaram who has stated that R. S.<lb/> Pai -accused No.l and K. R. N. Shenoy -accused No.2 were known to<lb/> each othe r and both had worked together in Syndicate Bank and that<lb/> K. R. N. Shenoy -accused No.2 has re signed as Assistant General<lb/> Manager in Syndicate Bank and, thereafter, joine d the FGIL. The<lb/> accused Nos. 1 and 2 have not disbursed the remittance s which were<lb/> made by OIDB to the Delhi Branch of the Syndicate Bank or further<lb/> remittances made by Delhi Branch of Syndicate Bank to the FIM<lb/> Division of Syndicate Bank, Fort, Bombay. Only other evidence which<lb/> is brought on record against accused No. I is through. the evidence of<lb/> P.W. 4 -E.R. Seshadri, P.W. S -R. Kalyansundaram, P.W. 3 -R.<lb/> Sundaresan, Divisional Manager of Sy ndicate Bank at Bombay. P.W. 3<lb/> -R. Sundaresan has stated in his deposition on page 55 of the notes of<lb/> evidence as under: -<lb/>&quot;I say that the head office of the Syndicate<lb/> Bank is at Manipal, Kamataka. I say that<lb/> Shri R.S. Pai was operating from the he ad<lb/> office at Mani pal. I say that Mr. Shenoy<lb/> was working at Bombay.&quot;<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> ------------------------• � �<lb/> �<lb/> -<lb/>-<lb/>47<lb/> Similarly P.</content>

            <figDesc>W. 4 -E.R. Sheshadri has stated in his deposition on page<lb/> 94 of the notes of evidence as under: -<lb/>&quot;I say that I know Shri R.S. Pai. He was<lb/> Executive Director in the Syndicate Bank<lb/> and was posted at Mani pal.,<lb/> ,<lb/> And P.W. 5 -R. Kalyanasundaram has stated in his deposition on page<lb/> No.109 of the notes of evidence as under:-<lb/>&quot;I say that at that time Shri R.S. Pai was an<lb/> Executive Director of the Syndicate Bank. I<lb/> say that Shri R.S. Pai&apos;s office was situated<lb/> at Manipal, South Kamataka.&quot;<lb/> Further, P.W. 3 -R. Sundaresan in his evidence has stated that he had<lb/> met accused No.1 -R.S. Pai when he visited Hongkong and he had<lb/> stated that R.S. Pai expressed his concern about the deteriorating<lb/> condition of the Bank. P. W. 3 in his deposition on page Nos. 51 and<lb/> 52 of the notes of evidence has stated as under: -<lb/>&quot;I say that I have met R.S. Pai in Hongkong<lb/> when he had come there in a capacity as<lb/> Chairman of the Board of Directors in the<lb/> year 1991. In Syndicate Bank, he was a<lb/> Executive Director.<lb/> During this period<lb/> when Mr. Pai visited Hongkong, we did<lb/> discuss about the financial health of<lb/> Syndicate Bank.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> so<lb/> Bank. He</content>

            <figDesc>, therefore, suggested that the<lb/> Bank had Investment Department which<lb/> had ability to invest surplus funds of their<lb/> bank. Similarly, Investment Department<lb/> was also in a position to invest surplus<lb/> funds of the Syndicate Bank. I say that<lb/> expectation of Shri R.S. Pai as Head of the<lb/> organization was that all the branches and<lb/> Zonal Offices should generate good profits<lb/> for the Bank.<lb/> I say that about 20<lb/> members were present at the said<lb/> meeting.&quot;<lb/> 25. From the aforesaid evidence, apart from bare words of P.W. 3 -<lb/>R. Sundaresan that he was acting on the oral instructions of R.S. Pai,<lb/> there is no other evidence on record to suggest that R.S. Pai -accused<lb/> No. l was monitoring the entire transaction. The entire evidence of<lb/> these witnesses, as stated hereinabove, does not even remotely connect<lb/> the accused No.1 with the investments made by OIDB with the Delhi<lb/> Branch of the Syndicate Bank nor with the investments made by FIM<lb/> Branch of the Syndicate Bank, Fort, Bombay. On the other hand, the<lb/> entire correspondence with the OIDB has been made either through<lb/> the Delhi Branch of Syndicate Bank or by Shri R. Sundaresan as<lb/> Divisional Manager of Syndicate Bank, FIM Branch, Fort, Bombay. It</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::</content>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>3. All the correspondence is made and directions<lb/> have been given by P.W. 3 under his signature. There is absolutely no<lb/> evidence to show that he was under direct control of ac• cused No.I -<lb/>R.S. Pai, except his bare word that he was acting under his<lb/> instructions. His evidence has not been corroborated by any other<lb/> witness or by any qocumentary evidence on record. Prosecution also<lb/> •<lb/> has not been in a position to give any plausible explanation as to why<lb/> the prosecution chose to drop him as an accused and examined him as<lb/> a witness on behalf of the prosecution. Evidence of P.W. 2 -Arvind<lb/> Kaushal also indicates that all the correspondence was made by him<lb/> after the scam was broke out and the letters written by him appear to<lb/> be an afterthought to salvage the damage caused to OIDB. It has come<lb/> on record that the first remittance which was made by OIDB was<lb/> without entering into any formal document between the OlDB and the<lb/> Syndicate Bank and it is only on the basis of offer letters which were<lb/> sent by either party, OIDB is trying to make out a case that it had<lb/> remitted the amount for investing it only in Government Securities,<lb/> though the first remittance of Rs 20 crores (approx) was made even<lb/> without giving any intimation to the Kasturba Gandhi Marg Branch of<lb/> the Syndicate Bank at New Delhi. To that extent, therefore, evidence<lb/> of P.W. 2 -Arvind Kaushal also does not establish any nexus between<lb/> the accused Nos. 1 and 2 and the remittances which were made by the<lb/> Officials of the OIDB.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> accused. For </content>
 
            <figDesc>that purpose, it is necessary to see the chronology of<lb/> events. I have already stated that from 02/04/1992 to 30/05/1992<lb/> various remittances were made by the OIDB in the Kasturba Gandhi<lb/> Marg Branch of the Syndicate Bank at New Delhi for an amount of<lb/> Rs 93,17,77,925/-and this amount, in tum, was invested by accused<lb/> No.I and the said amount was remitted to accused No.2 through five<lb/> remittances of various amounts during the period 07 /05/1992 to<lb/> 29/06/1992. Now, it will have to be seen the manner in which the<lb/> amounts were paid and the correspondence between the parties before<lb/> and after the remittances were made in order to appreciate the rival<lb/> contentions.<lb/> 28. According to the prosecution, a meeting was arranged by accused<lb/> No.1 in March, 1992 wherein he has urged all his Executives to<lb/> mobilize funds from individual clients, so that these funds could be<lb/> invested in the PMS services. At this stage, it would be relevant to take<lb/> into consideration the RBI guidelines which have been issued. The<lb/> Reserve Bank of India issued guidelines which have been brought on<lb/> record at Exhibit-14. The said circular was communicated to the<lb/> Chairman/Chief Executive of all Scheduled, Commercial Banks. All<lb/> this was in relation to Portfolio Management Scheme on behalf of<lb/> clients. In para 2 of the said guidelines, it has been stated as under:-</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            (ii)<lb/> Banks have been accepting funds for<lb/> portfolio<lb/> management<lb/> and<lb/> instead<lb/> of<lb/> managing such funds themselves, placed<lb/> such<lb/> funds<lb/> with<lb/> other<lb/> banks<lb/> for<lb/> management.<lb/> (iii)<lb/> Banks have been deploying portfolio<lb/> funds in call money market and bills market.<lb/> (iv)<lb/> Banks have not been maintaining<lb/> client-wise </content>
 
            <figDesc>records of funds accepted for<lb/> portfolio management and investments made<lb/> thereagainst. They have been using portfolio<lb/> funds for their own purposes. They have also<lb/> been mixing their own investments with<lb/> those of their clients.&quot;<lb/> It was under these circumstances, the Reserve Bank of India issued<lb/> guidelines to Banks. Clause (iv) of para 3 of the said guidelines is as<lb/> follows :-<lb/>&quot;3.<lb/> It has, therefore, been considered<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> necessary to issue further guidelines to<lb/> banks on this matter. Portfolio management<lb/> services (PMS) may be provided by<lb/> banks/their subsidiaries to their clients<lb/> henceforth, subject strictly to the following<lb/> revised guidelines :<lb/> (i) .................................................... .</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>( v) ................................................... .<lb/> (vi) ............................ ......................... .</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            (&quot; )<lb/> ))<lb/> Vll ..</content>

            <figDesc>.................................................. .</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>made by the Bank to invest these . funds in the PMS. It would be<lb/> relevant, therefore, to see exactly what was the offer made by the<lb/> Syndicate Bank. The relevant portion of the said letter at Exhibit-7,<lb/> reads as under.<lb/> &quot;Dear Sir &apos;<lb/> Re : Investment of your funds with us<lb/> under Portfolio Management Scheme.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>18.250/o p. a. [Emphasis supplied]<lb/> Such funds placed with us by you will be managed by us as<lb/> per the guidelines issued by R.Bl/SEBI in the matter.&quot;<lb/> 30. At this juncture, it would also be relevant to consider another<lb/> guideline which was issued by the R.Bl in its guidelines at Exhibit-14<lb/> ln clause (ii) of para 3 of Exhibit-14, it is stated as under:-<lb/>&quot;3 (ii)<lb/> &apos;PMS&apos; should be in the nature<lb/> of investment<lb/> consultancy /management, for a fee, entirely at the<lb/> customer&apos;s risk, without guaranteeing, either directly or<lb/> indirectly, a pre-determined return.<lb/> The bank should<lb/> charge a definite fee for the services rendered independent<lb/> of the return to the client.&quot;<lb/> From the letter which is referred to at Exhibit-7, it is clear that the<lb/> Assistant Manager of the Kasturba Gandhi Marg Branch of the<lb/> Syndicate Bank, New Delhi had clearly stated that the yield was<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> indicative only to the extent of 18.25°/o . This is relevant because in the<lb/> subsequent correspondence between the OIDB Officials and the Bank,<lb/> much emphasis has been laid by the prosecution on these letters to<lb/> indicate that the Syndicate Bank had promised and assured OIDB that<lb/> it would give them the assured returns. The above letter at Exhibit-7<lb/> which is written prior in point of time to the first investment which is<lb/> made, clearly states that the only indicative yield of the interest has<lb/> been mentioned. Officials of the OIDB, therefore, were clearly aware<lb/> that what was the promise given by the Syndicate Bank and i.e only<lb/> the indicative yield of the investments which were made in the PMS.<lb/> The subsequent correspondence between the Officials of the OIDB with<lb/> the Syndicate Bank clearly is after the scam broke out and as I would<lb/> presently point out, obviously, this was in order to save their own skin<lb/> from the possible fa llout of the investments made at their behest with<lb/> the Syndicate Bank. The documents which I am presently dealing with<lb/> clearly suggest that the Officials of the OIDB were aware that the<lb/> investments were being made in PMS and that the yield would only an<lb/> indicative yield.<lb/> However, the subsequent correspondence which<lb/> strangely has begun after 21/4/1992 clearly suggests that the Officials<lb/> of the OIDB have tried to put a wool over their eyes or atleast suggest<lb/> that they were not aware that the investments were made in the PMS<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> which clearly was meant for investments which were essentially to be<lb/> made in the capital market instruments as indicated hereinabove in the<lb/> RBI guidelines. Syndicate Bank also had in the letter written to the<lb/> F.A &amp; C.A.0. of OIDB, New Delhi i.e. P.W. 1 dated 16/04/ 1992 given<lb/> details of PMS. This has become necessaiy to point out the details<lb/> which have been given by the Deputy General Manager, New Delhi<lb/> Branch of the Syndicate Bank. In this letter which is at Exhibit-15,<lb/> categorically, the following information was given:-<lb/></figDesc>

            <lb/>&quot; Dear Sir,<lb/> Re : Portfolio Manage ment Scheme<lb/> We bring to your kind notice that we have a<lb/> well equipped Merchant Banking Division<lb/> offering<lb/> amongst<lb/> others,<lb/> PORTF OLIO<lb/> MANAGEMENT SERVICES, </content>
 
            <figDesc>as per the Reserve<lb/> Bank of India guidelines:<lb/> These services are extended by us on the<lb/> fo llowing lines:</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>&quot; [Emphasis<lb/> supplied]<lb/> This letter has been received by OIDB and there is a stamp of<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> ---------------<lb/>-<lb/>--<lb/>63<lb/> acknowledgment and the </content>
 
            <figDesc>letter has been received on the same day and<lb/> F .A &amp; C.A.O. of OIDB has put his initials acknowledging receipt of this<lb/> letter. This letter assumes importance for two reasons. Later on, the<lb/> Officials of OIDB in their correspondence fe igned ignorance about the<lb/> invesnnents which were made by the Syndicate Bank in the capital<lb/> market instruments and have stated that specific directions were given<lb/> by the OIDB to invest their funds only in Government Securities. It is<lb/> imponant to note that when the first remittance was sent on<lb/> 03/04/1992, the said amount was remitted to the Delhi Branch of the<lb/> Syndicate Bank even before the formal agreement was executed<lb/> between the parties and after receipt of this letter at Exhibit-IS.<lb/> Therefore, there is no manner of doubt that the Syndicate Bank clearly<lb/> indicated that the funds which were invested in PMS were meant to be<lb/> invested in capital market instruments and that the risk was entirely of<lb/> the constituents and 1°/o &quot;Back-end,, service charges would be paid to<lb/> the Bank. The subsequent correspondence reveals that P.W. 2 has<lb/> produced one of the letters wherein he has expressed his surprise as to<lb/> how an amount of Rs 33 lacs (approximately) was charged as service<lb/> fee by the Syndicate Bank. The subsequent correspondence, therefore,<lb/> is clearly contrary to what the Syndicate Bank had clearly informed the<lb/> F.A. &amp; C.A.O. of OIDB, New Delhi. I shall refer to the said letter at<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> later stage. The stand taken by the OIDB, therefore, is clearly contrary<lb/> to the documents which are on record. In fact, the documents which<lb/> have been brought on record clearly falsifies the case of the<lb/> prosecution. It is surprising as to how the CBI did not make any<lb/> investigation in respect of Officials of OIDB who were equally<lb/> responsible for making these investments with the Syndicate Bank<lb/> when they were fully aware about the nature of the inve stments and<lb/> the indicative yield of the said investments as also the risk involved in<lb/> making these investments under PMS. The correspondence clearly</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>15 </head>
 
            <figDesc>and 16 who were Investigating Officers shows the manner in which<lb/> the investigation had been earned out. It clearly reveals that an<lb/> attempt has been made to protect the Officials of the OIDB and to let<lb/> go the persons who were directly responsible for the entire episode. A<lb/> complaint was filed by Shri V. Sethumadhavan who was the Chief<lb/> Vigilance Officer against Shri R. Sundaresan. No explanation has been<lb/> given as to why no case was filed against him and later on he was<lb/> examined as prosecution witness.<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> ._ __<lb/> --<lb/>---<lb/>-<lb/>•-<lb/>65<lb/> 31. In </content>
 
            <figDesc>the backdrop of these documents, now it has to be seen as to<lb/> how the Officials of OIDB have later on tried to give twist to the entire<lb/> episode which was obviously meant for the purpose of saving their<lb/> own skin. After this letter at Exhibit-15 was received by F.A. &amp; C.A.0.<lb/> of the OIDB, New Delhi and acknowledgment to that effect was given<lb/> it is thereafter he addressed a letter • to the Chief Manager of the<lb/> Syndicate Bank dated 21/4/1992 which is at Exhibit-5. P.W. 1 in this<lb/> letter states as under:-<lb/>&quot;We have parked funds to the extent of Rs<lb/> 20.09 crores with you as per acknowledgment<lb/> received from your bank vide your letter<lb/> No.216, DZO DGMS F-20,92 dated 18.4.92 for<lb/> their proper management under &apos;Portfo lio<lb/> Investment&apos;.<lb/> Your<lb/> acknowledgment<lb/> of<lb/> deployment of our funds in Govt. Securities,<lb/> Units of UTI and Public Sector Bonds, Safe<lb/> Custody of securities giving return as contained<lb/> in<lb/> your<lb/> letter<lb/> No. 788/9005/92,<lb/> dated<lb/> 25/26.3.1992 is awaited which may please be<lb/> expedited.&quot; [Emphasis supplied]<lb/> Since the reference is made to the letter dated 25/03/ 1992, it has to<lb/> be seen what was mentioned in the said letter which is at Exhibit-6<lb/> dated 25/03/1992. It is stated by the Divisional Manager of the New<lb/> Delhi Branch of the Syndicate Bank that yield on the investment made<lb/> by the OIDB would not be less that 18.250/o . P.W. 1, therefore, does<lb/> not make any reference to the letter received by him dated<lb/> 16/04/1992 in which details of the PMS was given. He, however,<lb/> makes a reference to letter dated 25/26.03.1992. P.W. 1, therefore<lb/> fe igned ignorance about receipt of the letter dated 16/04/ 1992. This<lb/> clearly indicates that though P.W. 1 -V.P. Chugh was very well aware<lb/> that the funds parked with the Syndicate Bank were to be deployed<lb/> under PMS with all its attending risk involved, he . fe igned ignorance<lb/> about this letter and makes a stray reference to the letter dated<lb/> 25/26.03.1992. It has to be noted that the letter dated 25/26.03.1992<lb/> has been written with reference to the letter written by the Assistant<lb/> General Manager of the Syndicate Bank to the OIDB dated<lb/> 21/03/1992. The said letter appears to be a confirmation of what is<lb/> stated in letter dated 21/03/1992. In this context, therefore, it will be<lb/> necessary to see the relevant contents of the said letter which is at<lb/> Exhibit-6 dated 25/26.03.1992 which read as under:-<lb/>&quot;Further to our letter of offer vide ref.<lb/> No.PMS/269/5037 /HKS/92 dated 21.3. 1992,<lb/> this is to confirm that the yield on your<lb/> investment would be not less than 18.25°/o p.a.<lb/> on the investment made by you with our Bank<lb/> upto Rs 140 crores (Rupees One hundred forty<lb/> crores) for one year.&quot;<lb/> This letter, therefore, was in addition to what was mentioned in<lb/> Exhibit-7. In the letter at Exhibit-7 dated 21/03/1992, it has been<lb/> clearly mentioned that the indicative yield of 18.25% 1 per annum<lb/> would be available on the funds placed with the Syndicate Bank. A<lb/> reference also has been made to the guidelines issued by RBl/SEBI in<lb/> the said letter. P.W. 1, instead of making reference to letter dated<lb/> 21/03/1992 at Exhibit-7 and further letter which was written dated<lb/> 16/04/1992 at Exhibit-15 giving complete details of PMS, chooses to<lb/> make a reference only to letter dated 25/26.3.1992 at Exhibit-6. This<lb/> clearly shows the dishonesty on the part of the prosecution witnesses</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>15 and 16 why<lb/> no investigation was made at the OIDB end though they had an ample<lb/> opportunity to do so.<lb/> On the other • hand, though the entire<lb/> documentary evidence dearly suggests that the correspondence was<lb/> essentially between the OIDB&apos;s officials and the Officers of New Delhi<lb/> Branch of the Syndicate Bank and the FIM Branch of the Syndicate<lb/> Bank, Fon, Bombay, further investigation has not been made after<lb/> these documents were made available • to the prosecution.<lb/> 33. The subsequent correspondence reveals that P.W. 1 in his<lb/> subsequent correspondence has maintained his stand that the funds in<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> ----<lb/>-----<lb/>--<lb/>-<lb/>..<lb/> 69<lb/> the PMS were </content>
 
            <figDesc>to be invested in Government Securities. Letter dated<lb/> 29/04/1992 at Exhibit-8 is written by P.W. 1 -V.P. Chugh to the Chief<lb/> Manager, Syndicate Bank, Bhagwan Das Ro ad, New Delhi records that<lb/> fo ur cheques, all dated 29/04/1992 drawn on State Bank of India, K.G.<lb/> Marg, New Delhi were sent for deployment under Portfolio<lb/> Management Scheme with effect from 29/04/1992 @ 19.51°/o . The<lb/> amount of the said cheques was Rs 81,68,50,924.65. It is interesting<lb/> to note that in para 3 of this letter he has stated as under:-<lb/>&quot;3. The funds have been parked with you for<lb/> their proper management as &quot;Portfolio<lb/> Investment&quot; in Government Securities Units of<lb/> UTI &amp; Public Sector Bonds in accordance with<lb/> RBI guidelines.&quot;</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>3 -R. Sundaresan, Divisional Manager of the Syndicate Bank. In the<lb/> letter at Exhibit-19 dated 18/06/1993, S.K. Pujari has informed the<lb/> Divisional Manager as under:-<lb/>&quot;Sub: Investment of funds under P.M.S<lb/> Ref : Your letter No.1212/FIM/PMS/93, dated<lb/> June 7, 1993.<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> • •-<lb/>•-<lb/>70<lb/> Sir,<lb/> The Oil Industry </content>
 
            <figDesc>Development Board has<lb/> made no investment with your branch. Whatever<lb/> investments the Board has made these have been<lb/> made with the Bank&apos;s office/branch located at New<lb/> Delhi. Therefore, no cognizance can be taken of<lb/> your above mentioned communication. You are<lb/> advised to take up the matter with the DGM,<lb/> Syndicate Bank, New Delhi and your headquarters<lb/> at Manipal.&quot;<lb/> The second letter is dated 03/06/ 1992 written by P.W. 1 -V.P. Chugh<lb/> to the Assistant General Manager of the Syndicate Bank which is at<lb/> Exhibit-24 in which he has stated that the Bombay Office in its letter<lb/> dated12/05/1992 has sent an acknowledgment regarding receipt of<lb/> funds amounting to Rs 61.43 crores from OIDB through your K.G.<lb/> Branch Office for placement in Portfolio Management. He has stated<lb/> that since the entire funds of Rs 198.38 crores have been given to Delhi<lb/> Office only, there was no occasion for Bombay Office to write the said<lb/> letter.<lb/> Again, P.W. 1 wrote a letter which is at Exhibit-26 dated<lb/> 03/08/1992 in which he has made a reference to the letter dated July<lb/> 18, 1992 from the Bombay Office regarding confirmation of investment<lb/> of funds. In para 2 of the said letter dated 3/8/ 1992 at Exhibit-26, he<lb/> has mentioned as under:-<lb/>&quot;Your Bombay Office vide its letter dated<lb/> July 1 8, 1992 has sent confirmation regarding<lb/> investment of funds and holding securitie s. This<lb/> is inexplicable since the funds have been placed<lb/> with your bank on the basis of offe r rece ive d<lb/> from your office.&quot;<lb/> So, on the one hand, OIDB has later on taken a sta nd that it was not<lb/> concerned with any othe r Office and that it had deploye d the funds<lb/> on ly with the K.G. Marg Branch of the Syndicate Bank, New Delhi. No<lb/> refe rence was made to any communication made by accused No.l -<lb/>R.S. Pai. This clearly establishes that the funds were entrusted by<lb/> OIDB even according to P.W. 1 and P.W. 2 with the Delhi Branch of<lb/> the Syndicate Bank and not eve n with the FIM Branch of the Syndicate<lb/> Bank, Fort, Bombay, much less with R.S. Pai who was the Executive<lb/> Director and who was stationed at Manipal, Karna taka.<lb/> The<lb/> correspondence also indicates that though Officials of OIDB were very<lb/> well aware about the lette r dated 16/04/1992 at Exhibit-15 and the<lb/> other letter dated 21/4/1992, they had fe igned ignorance about the<lb/> same and in their letters have stated that the funds were deployed for<lb/> the purpose of investment in Government Securities on ly and the<lb/> Syndicate Bank Officers at Delhi Branch had assured them of fixed<lb/> returns of ab ove 18°/o and, later on, in the subsequent correspondence,<lb/> they have maintaine d that the fund were deployed for investment at<lb/> 19.SlO /o per annum. This is clearly contrary to the correspondence<lb/> between the Assistant General Manager, Syndicate Bank and the OIDB.<lb/> In the letter dated 27 /04/ 1992 at Exhibit-17, the Assistant General<lb/> manager of the Syndicate Bank has again stated that the indicative<lb/> yield on the investment under PMS was 19.51°/0 per annum. The said<lb/> letter at Exhibit-17 reads as under:-<lb/>&quot;Further to our earlier letter to you on the<lb/> subject offering an in dicative yi eld of 18.50°/o<lb/> for<lb/> your<lb/> investment<lb/> under<lb/> Portfolio<lb/> Management Scheme with us we are now<lb/> pleased to offer you an indicative yield of<lb/> 19.51 % (Nineteen point five one percent<lb/> p.a.)&quot; [Emphasis supplied]<lb/> and yet P.W. 1 in his letter which is written two days after the letter at<lb/> Exhibit-17, states that the investment of Rs 81,68,50,924.65 under<lb/> PMS has been made with effect from 29/04/1992 @ 19.Slo/ o . All this<lb/> correspondence clearly reveals that on the one hand officials of the<lb/> OIDB were very well aware of the risk which was involved in investing<lb/> their surplus funds in PMS and, on the other hand, for the purpose of<lb/> creating record in its office, in the correspondence they have shown<lb/> audacity of stating that the funds were to be given for deployment in<lb/> Government Securities for a assured sum of interest, though in each<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> -••<lb/> -<lb/>--<lb/>::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> letter sent by </content>
 
            <figDesc>the Officers of the Delhi Branch of the Syndicate Bank,<lb/> they were at pains to point out that the yield was only an indicative<lb/> yield. Apart from this , it is evident that neither P.W. 1 -V.P. Chugh<lb/> nor P.W. 2 -Arvind Kaushal have made any reference to either Mr. R.S.<lb/> Pai -accused No. l or Mr. K. R. N. Shenoy -accused No.2. Therefore,<lb/> entrustment of funds with accused No. I has not at all been established.<lb/> A boogie has been raised by the Officials of the OIDB that they were<lb/> not aware that their surplus funds were being invested in PMS under<lb/> their own risk , though they were specifically informed by the Officers<lb/> of the Delhi Branch of the Syndicate Bank and the CBI has turned a<lb/> blind eye towards the OIDB Officials which is reflected from the<lb/> evidence of P.W. 15 and 16 who were the Investigating Officers who<lb/> have clearly stated in their cross-examination that though involvement<lb/> of OIDB Officials also appears to be eminent from these documents, no<lb/> investigation was made by the CBI on that front. The attempt made by<lb/> the OIDB Officials to play hide-and-seek at the same time is reflected<lb/> from the following letter which is at Exhibit-9 and this letter is written<lb/> by Mr. S.K. Pujari.<lb/> Mr. S.K. Puj ari writes a letter to the Chief<lb/> Manager, Syndicate Bank in which he states as under:-<lb/></figDesc>

            <lb/>::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> no connection between </content>
 
            <figDesc>the investment of funds by the OIDB either<lb/> with accused No. l or accused No.2. Therefore, point Nos. 1 and 2 are<lb/> answered in the negative.<lb/> 34.<lb/> Prosecution has also proved the remittances of money from<lb/> Delhi Branch of the Syndicate Bank to its Bombay Branch through<lb/> inter-bank credit advise note since these documents are not disputed.<lb/> Even if the said documents are accepted, as I have indicated earlier,<lb/> nothing turns on the said documents of transf�r of money from the<lb/> Syndicate Bank, New Delhi Branch to the FIM Branch of the Syndicate<lb/> Bank at Fort, Bombay and the further amount which has been sent to<lb/> FGIL. An attempt has been made by the prosecution to show that<lb/> accused No.1 knew accused No.2 while he was working in the<lb/> Syndicate Bank and further an attempt is made to show that P.W. 3 -R<lb/> Sundaresan was brought from Hongkong to the FIM Branch of the<lb/> Syndicate Bank at Fort, Bombay.<lb/> It is also said by some of the<lb/> witnesses that because Mr. Prabhu did not agree with Mr R.S. Pai -<lb/>accused No.l, he was suddenly transferred and in his place Mr. R.<lb/> Sundaresan was posted as Divisional Manager. It is the further case of<lb/> prosecution and it is so stated by P.W. 3 and P.W. 5 that on account of<lb/> suggestion made by R.S. Pai -accused No.1 that accused No.2 was<lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> appointed for the purpose of making investments in the capital market<lb/> instruments. The second limb of the prosecution case therefore is that<lb/> Mr. R.S. Pai had persuaded OIDB Officials to invest its money in<lb/> Syndicate Bank and, on the other hand, the said money was siphoned<lb/> off in favour of FGIL and it&apos;s sister concern the Fairgrowth Financial<lb/> Services Ltd since the said company of which accused No.2 was a<lb/> Managing Director was under liquidity crunch and, therefore, accused</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>to OIDB and wrongful gain to accused No.2.<lb/> Later on, when the<lb/> charge-sheet was filed, a charge of cheating was dropped. No charges<lb/> were levelled against P.W. 3 -R. Sundaresan who was named as an<lb/> accused in the original complaint and the charge was levelled against<lb/> accused No.1 -R.S. Pai for the substantive offence of criminal breach<lb/> of trust under section 409 of the Indian Penal Code and conspiracy<lb/> along with the offence under the Prevention of Corruption Act.<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> Though, it </content>
 
            <figDesc>has been charged that the entire amount was transferred in<lb/> the name of Company of accused No.2, it is a matter of record that the<lb/> actual shares to the tune of Rs 93 crores approximately were purchased<lb/> in the name of OIDB. The decision to make investment was taken by<lb/> the Committee of four persons in which accused No.1 was not a<lb/> member and, on the other hand, P.W. 3 -R. Sundaresan was the<lb/> member of the Committee alongwith three other persons. This falsifies<lb/> the case of the prosecution that the investments were made in FGIL<lb/> and its sister concern the Fairgrowth Financial Services Ltd of which<lb/> the accused No.2 was the Managing Director at the instance of Mr. R.S.<lb/> Pai -accused No.1. This decision was taken by the Committee of fo ur<lb/> persons which decided the date and the manner which the investments<lb/> were to be made.<lb/> This clearly indicates that the transaction of<lb/> investment in shares from the PMS of the client was not an ostensible<lb/> share transaction but was an actual share transaction. It is interesting<lb/> to note that the prosecution has not stated whether actual loss was<lb/> caused to the OIDB as a result of investment made. No such complaint<lb/> has been made either by V. Sethumadhavan who lodged a complaint or<lb/> by Officials of OIDB that the said funds of Rs 132.22 crores which were<lb/> deployed were lost or not repaid. Prosecution ought to have produced<lb/> the said fact on record as• to what happened thereafter in order to<lb/> _j<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> l<lb/> 78<lb/> make the record </content>
 
            <figDesc>straight.<lb/> Obvious inference therefore has to be<lb/> drawn. It is a matter of record that the entire amount was repaid to<lb/> OIDB alongwith interest and, as such, no loss was caused to the OIDB.<lb/> None of the witnesses who was examined from the Syndicate Bank<lb/> stated that any loss was caused to the Syndicate Bank. Prosecution,<lb/> therefore, has miserably failed in establishing the charge of criminal<lb/> conspiracy to commit an offence of criminal breach of trust by accused<lb/> No.l and accused No.2 or the substantive charge of criminal breach of<lb/> trust against accused No.1 Accordingly, point Nos. 1 and 2 are<lb/> answered in the negative.<lb/> 36.<lb/> So far as 3rd and 4th charge is concerned, prosecution has not<lb/> proved that 62000 shares from the promoters&apos; quota of FGIL and its<lb/> sister concern M/s Fair Growth Financial Services Ltd were transferred<lb/> in the name of accused No.1 or in the name of his family members.<lb/> The 3rd and 4th charge read as under:-<lb/>&quot;THIRDLY,<lb/> that in pursuance to the said<lb/> conspiracy you Accused No.l, as a motive<lb/> and/ or reward for causing the aforesaid<lb/> wrongful gain to accused No.2 and/or his said<lb/> company, dishonestly obtained in your name<lb/> and in the name of your fa mily members of<lb/> 62,000 shares from promoters&apos; quota of the<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> L<lb/> 79<lb/> FGIL and its </content>
 
            <figDesc>sister concern the Fairgrowth<lb/> Financial Services Ltd., and you have thereby<lb/> committed offences punishable under sections<lb/> 13(1) (d) read with section 13(2) and section 7<lb/> of the Prevention of Corruption Act, 1988.&quot;<lb/> &quot;FOURTHLY, that you Accused No.2 instigated<lb/> and abetted accused No.1 in obtaining the said<lb/> 62000 shares by way of motive/reward for<lb/> enabling you and/or your said company to<lb/> make the aforesaid wrongful gain of Rs<lb/> 93,17,77,925/-<lb/>and<lb/> you<lb/> have<lb/> thereby<lb/> committed an offence punishable under section<lb/> 12, Prevention of Conuption Act, 1988.&quot;<lb/> 37.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> the prosecution. </content>
 
            <figDesc>Prosecution witness viz Investigating Officer who had<lb/> produced these documents in the search conducted as per search<lb/> warrant dated 05/04/ 1994, did not identify the signatures and<lb/> handwriting of the said persons who prepared the documents and, as a<lb/> result, though the search warrant was brought on record alongwith<lb/> these documents, the relevant documents were not proved and,<lb/> therefore, are not the part of the record. Prosecution, therefore, is not<lb/> in a position to establish that these shares which were seized pursuant<lb/> to the search warrant which was issued were, in fact, transferred in the<lb/> name of accused No. I or his family members. That being the position,<lb/> the 3rd and 4 th charge has not been established by the prosecution and<lb/> the accused Nos. 1 and 2, therefore, have to be acquitted of the said<lb/> charge which is levelled against them. It has to be noted here that,<lb/> though ample opportunity was given to the prosecution to examine the<lb/> said witness, in spite of diligent efforts being made by the prosecution,<lb/> they were unable to examine the said witness. Points Nos. 3 and 4</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::<lb/> shares of FGIL </content>
 
            <figDesc>were transferred in favour of accused No.1 and the<lb/> members of his family as a motive or reward and, therefore, I have<lb/> already held that point Nos. 3 and 4 have not been proved by the<lb/> prosecution.</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <figDesc>In the result, both the accused are acquitted of the offences<lb/> with which they were charged. Their bails bonds stand cancelled.<lb/> (V.M. KANADE)<lb/> </figDesc>

            <lb/> ::: Uploaded on -13/11/2014<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:17 :::</content>
        </figure>



    </text>
</tei>

