<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<head>
			CORAM:
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE C. HARI SHANKAR
			<lb />
			J U D G E M E N T
			<lb />
			%
			<lb />
			17.09.2020
			<lb />
		</head>

		<p>
			1.
			<lb />
			This appeal, under Section 37(2)(b) of the Arbitration and
			<lb />
			Conciliation Act, 1996 (hereinafter referred to as &quot;the 1996 Act&quot;),
			<lb />
			assails the direction, in para 3.28 of order, dated 18 th February, 2020,
			<lb />
			passed by the learned Sole Arbitrator, to the appellants to furnish
			<lb />
			suitable security, equivalent to the sums involved, to the learned
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal. Vide subsequent order dated 14 th May, 2020, the
			<lb />
			learned Sole Arbitrator has clarified that the security would be
			<lb />
			furnished within a period of four weeks, to the satisfaction of the
			<lb />
			learned Sole Arbitrator.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			With consent of parties, who have been heard over several days,
			<lb />
			this judgement disposes of the appeal of the appellant.
			<lb />
			Facts
			<lb />
			Undisputed Facts
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			Anand Gupta, Rajesh Gupta and Dinesh Gupta are brothers,
			<lb />
			Anand Gupta being elder to Rajesh Gupta, who is elder to Dinesh
			<lb />
			Gupta. Dinesh Gupta is Appellant No. 1, and Anand Gupta is
			<lb />
			Respondent No. 1, in these proceedings. Rajesh Gupta has not been
			<lb />
			impleaded as a party.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			Dinesh Gupta, Anand Gupta and Rajesh Gupta headed three
			<lb />
			groups of a joint family, referred to, in the impugned order, by the
			<lb />
			acronyms &apos;DGG&apos;, &apos;AGG&apos; and &apos;RGG&apos;, respectively. A fourth group,
			<lb />
			namely the Bechu Singh Group (&apos;BSG&apos;) was also a party before the
			<lb />
			learned Sole Arbitrator. For ease of reference, this judgement uses the
			<lb />
			same acronyms.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			The appellants, in this appeal, are Dinesh Gupta, his wife
			<lb />
			Shivani Gupta and his son Shreyansh Gupta, as Appellants No. 1, 3
			<lb />
			and 2, and the various Companies constituting part of DGG, as
			<lb />
			Appellants No. 4 to 19. Respondents No. 2, 3 and 4 are the son, wife
			<lb />
			and daughter of Respondent No. 1 Anand Gupta, Respondent No. 5 is
			<lb />
			the HUF of the respondents and Respondents Nos. 6 to 12 are
			<lb />
			Companies which, together with Respondents Nos. 1 to 5, constitute
			<lb />
			AGG.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			Before the learned Sole Arbitrator, DGG was the claimant, and
			<lb />
			RGG, AGG and BSG were the respondents.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			Dinesh Gupta, Anand Gupta and Rajesh Gupta were, at one
			<lb />
			point of time, doing construction and real estate business (hereinafter
			<lb />
			referred to as &quot;the family business&quot;) together, under the name &quot;M/s
			<lb />
			BDR Builders and Developers Pvt Ltd&quot; (hereinafter referred to as
			<lb />
			&quot;BDR&quot;). In 1992, Anand Gupta and his family members separated
			<lb />
			from the family business which, thereafter, was continued by DGG
			<lb />
			and RGG.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			Disputes arose, in August 2017, between Dinesh Gupta and
			<lb />
			Rajesh Gupta. With the intervention of Anand Gupta, two Family
			<lb />
			Settlement deeds, dated 2 nd December, 2017 and 9 th December, 2017,
			<lb />
			were executed between DGG and RGG, and was signed, on their
			<lb />
			behalf, by Dinesh Gupta and Rajesh Gupta. The agreement dated 9 th
			<lb />
			December, 2017 -which, apparently, set out the terms of settlement -
			<lb />
			read thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			&quot;SETTLEMENT BETWEEN RAJESH GUPTA &amp;
			<lb />
			ASSOCIATES AND DINESH GUPTA &amp; ASSOCIATES
			<lb />
			This
		</p>

		<p>
			settlement is made at New Delhi on 9 th day of
			<lb />
			December, 2017.
			<lb />
			The terms of the settlement are as under: -
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			1.
			<lb />
			The list of BDR Group companies/entities
			<lb />
			which shall vest in Dinesh Gupta &amp; Associates is
			<lb />
			annexed herewith as Annexure-A.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			2.
			<lb />
			The list of BDR Group companies/entities
			<lb />
			which shall vest in Rajesh Gupta &amp; Associates is
			<lb />
			annexed herewith as Annexure-B.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			3.
			<lb />
			The list of properties which shall be transferred
			<lb />
			to Dinesh Gupta by the Companies vested in Rajesh
			<lb />
			Gupta and by Rajesh Gupta and Associates is annexed
			<lb />
			herewith as Annexure-C.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			4.
			<lb />
			The list of properties which shall be transferred
			<lb />
			to Rajesh Gupta by the Companies
			vested in Dinesh
			<lb />
			Gupta and by Dinesh Gupta and Associates is annexed
			<lb />
			herewith as Annexure-D.
			<lb />
		</item>


		<item>
			5.
			<lb />
			The list of actionable claims (only if received)
			<lb />
			which shall vest in Dinesh Gupta &amp; shall be
			<lb />
			transferred to Dinesh Gupta by the Companies vested
			<lb />
			in Rajesh Gupta and by Rajesh Gupta and Associates
			<lb />
			is annexed herewith as Annexure-E.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			6.
			<lb />
			The list of actionable claims (only if received)
			<lb />
			which shall vest in Rajesh Gupta &amp; shall be transferred
			<lb />
			to Rajesh Gupta by the Companies vested in Dinesh
			<lb />
			Gupta and by Dinesh Gupta and Associates is annexed
			<lb />
			herewith as Annexure-F.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			7.
			<lb />
			The list of liabilities (only if paid) which shall
			<lb />
			be borne by Dinesh Gupta though shown as
			<lb />
			outstanding in the Companies vested in Rajesh Gupta
			<lb />
			and in Rajesh Gupta and Associates is Annexed
			<lb />
			herewith as Annexure-G.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			8.
			<lb />
			The above said settlement is binding on the
			<lb />
			parties, on companies/entities vested in the parties as
			<lb />
			well as family members and associates of the parties.
			<lb />
			None of the parties shall challenge the terms of the
			<lb />
			settlement in any court, authority etc.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			9.
			<lb />
			The cross holdings shall be mutually transferred
			<lb />
			between the parties on the basis of vesting of
			<lb />
			companies as detailed above and in a manner and at
			<lb />
			valuations which will lead to the entire capital
			<lb />
			distributed 50:50 between both groups detailed as
			<lb />
			above A and B.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			10.
			<lb />
			The parties agreed that the tax will be borne
			<lb />
			respectively by the respective parties as per Annexure-
			<lb />
			A &amp; B. However, taxes pertaining to claims as per
			<lb />
			Annexure E &amp; F as list as per Annexure H shall be
			<lb />
			borne by the respective beneficiary.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			11.
			<lb />
			The parties shall cooperate with each other to
			<lb />
			implement the terms of this settlement.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			12.
			<lb />
			That more than 100 Crores worth of actionable
			<lb />
			claims were held in excess
			<lb />
			by Dinesh Group which is
			<lb />
			to be reimbursed to Rajesh Group if received. Specific
			<lb />
			irrevocable resolutions of companies will be given to
			<lb />
			recover the actionable claims by Dinesh Group.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(Sd/-)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Rajesh Gupta
			<lb />
			(for self &amp; on behalf of his associates and entities
			<lb />
			vested in him)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(Sd/-)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Dinesh Gupta
			<lb />
			(for self &amp; on behalf of his associates and entities
			<lb />
			vested in him)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Witnesses:-
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			Shashank Gupta
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			2.
			<lb />
			Shreyans Gupta&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			9.
			<lb />
			In line with the aforesaid Family Settlements (as the petitioners
			<lb />
			would aver), AGG
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			resigned from M/s Renu Farms Pvt. Ltd. (hereinafter
			<lb />
			referred to as &quot;Renu Farms&quot;), which fell to the share of RGG,
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii) resigned from M/s Renu Promoters Pvt. Ltd. (hereinafter
			<lb />
			referred to as &quot;Renu Promoters&quot;), which fell to the share of
			<lb />
			DGG,
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) transferred shareholdings, in nine companies, to RGG,
			<lb />
			without consideration,
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iv) transferred shareholdings, in six companies, to DGG,
			<lb />
			without consideration, and
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(v) liquidated investments, held by AGG in Kotak Mahindra
			<lb />
			Mutual Funds, ICICI Prudential Mutual Funds and Edelweiss
			<lb />
			Mutual Funds (hereinafter referred to, collectively, as &quot;the
			<lb />
			Mutual Funds&quot;), and credited the amounts obtained thereby, in
			<lb />
			the accounts of Anand Gupta (HUF) and Sanchit Gupta (son of
			<lb />
			Anand Gupta), totalling ₹ 19,89,34,500.88, out of which an
			<lb />
			amount of ₹ 19,55,00,000/-was credited into the accounts of
			<lb />
			DGG.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			10. DGG would aver that the aforesaid amount of ₹ 19,55,00,000/-
			<lb />
			was &quot;gifted&quot;, by AGG to DGG. AGG denies this contention, as the
			<lb />
			facts recited hereinafter would disclose.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			11. Consequent on the aforesaid Family Settlements, Rajesh Gupta
			<lb />
			resigned from seventeen Companies which fell to the lot of DGG, and
			<lb />
			transferred shares in four companies to DGG; DGG, likewise,
			<lb />
			resigned from twenty six companies which fell to the lot of RGG, and
			<lb />
			transferred shares in thirteen companies to RGG. These facts,
			<lb />
			however, are not particularly relevant, for the purposes of the present
			<lb />
			appeal.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			12. Thereafter, contends DGG, both RGG and AGG resiled from
			<lb />
			their commitments under the aforesaid Family Settlements, qua DGG.
			<lb />
			The actions of RGG, in this regard, do not seriously impact these
			<lb />
			proceedings, as the present lis is between DGG and AGG; however,
			<lb />
			reference, thereto, is necessary, in order to complete the factual
			<lb />
			recital.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			13. Acts of Rajesh Gupta/RGG, leading to CS (OS) 51/2018
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			13.1 As a sequel to earlier communications, between Rajesh Gupta
			<lb />
			and Dinesh Gupta, the former wrote, to the latter, on 10 th January,
			<lb />
			2018, alleging that Dinesh Gupta was illegally trying to encash mutual
			<lb />
			funds of BDR, which, as per the Family Settlements, were vested in
			<lb />
			Rajesh Gupta. Resultantly, it was alleged that Dinesh Gupta was
			<lb />
			liable to reimburse, to Rajesh Gupta, an amount of ₹ 22,44,85,000/-.
			<lb />
			Dinesh Gupta was also called upon to furnish resolutions for pursuing
			<lb />
			actionable claims of companies, which vested in RGG. The
			<lb />
			communication also requested that a reputed accounting/auditing firm
			<lb />
			(the names of KPMG and PricewaterhouseCoopers (PwC) were
			<lb />
			suggested), be appointed to resolve the disputes between RGG and
			<lb />
			DGG.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			13.2 DGG responded, on 12 th January, 2018, asserting that the
			<lb />
			Mutual Funds in issue were in the personal name of Dinesh Gupta,
			<lb />
			and that Rajesh Gupta was merely the second holder therein. It was
			<lb />
			further asserted that the investments, in the said Mutual Funds, had
			<lb />
			been made by Dinesh Gupta from his personal savings. DGG,
			<lb />
			therefore, denied any monetary liability towards RGG, but assented to
			<lb />
			the appointment of KPMG, to settle the disputes between RGG and
			<lb />
			DGG.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			13.3 On 19 th January, 2018, RGG sent requisitions, under Section 100
			<lb />
			of the Companies Act, 2013 (hereinafter referred to as &quot;the
			<lb />
			Companies Act&quot;) to the Board of Directors (hereinafter referred to as
			<lb />
			&quot;BOD&quot;) of BDR, for removal of Dinesh Gupta and Shreyansh Gupta
			<lb />
			from the Board of Directors of BDR, alleging that, by their acts, they
			<lb />
			had forfeited the right to continue as Directors, by virtue of Section
			<lb />
			169 of the Companies Act. The requisition requested that an Extra
			<lb />
			Ordinary General Meeting (EGM) of the BOD be called, for the said
			<lb />
			purpose. Similar requisitions, in respect of M/s. Able Management
			<lb />
			Consultants Pvt. Ltd., M/s. Verma Finvest Pvt. Ltd., and M/s. Nishit
			<lb />
			Capinvest Pvt. Ltd. (hereinafter referred to as &quot;Nishit&quot;), were issued
			<lb />
			by RGG on 24 th January, 2018, 25 th January, 2018 and 29 th January,
			<lb />
			2018. Admittedly, BDR, Cable Management Consultants Pvt. Ltd.,
			<lb />
			Verma Finvest Pvt. Ltd. and Nishit were companies which came to
			<lb />
			the share of DGG, under the Family Settlements.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			13.4 The above acts of RGG/Rajesh Gupta led to the filing, by
			<lb />
			Dinesh Gupta, of CS (OS) 51/2018 (Dinesh Gupta &amp; Ors. v. Rajesh
			<lb />
			Gupta &amp; Ors.), before this Court, praying for a permanent injunction,
			<lb />
			restraining Rajesh Gupta/RGG from acting in contravention of the
			<lb />
			Family Settlements dated 2 nd December, 2017 and 9 th December,
			<lb />
			2017, or interfering with the rights of DGG thereunder, and for
			<lb />
			appointment of KPMG, or any other reputed firm, to effectuate the
			<lb />
			said Family Settlements.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			13.5 Holding that DGG had managed to establish a prima facie case
			<lb />
			in its favour, a learned Single Judge of this Court, vide order dated 7 th
			<lb />
			February, 2018, in CS (OS) 51/2018, restrained RGG from giving
			<lb />
			effect to the notices dated 19 th January, 2018, 24 th January, 2018, 25 th
			<lb />
			January, 2018 and 29 th January, 2018, till the next date of hearing.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			14. Acts of Anand Gupta/AGG, leading to CS (OS) 100/2018
			<lb />
			14.1 On 22 nd February, 2018, Anand Gupta (HUF) and Sanchit
			<lb />
			Gupta, son of Anand Gupta, wrote to Shreyansh Gupta, alleging that
			<lb />
			the transfer of ₹ 19.55 crores, earned by liquidation of the investments
			<lb />
			made by AGG in Mutual Funds, to the account of DGG, had been
			<lb />
			effected without the consent of AGG and was, therefore, fraudulent.
			<lb />
			It was alleged that AGG had given signed blank cheques to Shreyansh
			<lb />
			Gupta, in good faith, so that the moneys, resulting from the liquidation
			<lb />
			of the Mutual Funds, could be invested in appropriate securities.
			<lb />
			Instead, it was alleged, Shreyansh Gupta, on behalf of DGG, had
			<lb />
			transferred the said moneys into the personal account of DGG,
			<lb />
			thereby misappropriating the said amount. The communication,
			<lb />
			therefore, required the said amount to be transferred back to AGG.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			14.2 On 12 th February, 2018, Anand Gupta wrote to BDR, Dinesh
			<lb />
			Gupta and Shreyansh Gupta, requiring them to repay, to Anand
			<lb />
			Gupta, a loan of ₹ 77,48,870/-, advanced by Anand Gupta, for
			<lb />
			investment in real estate projects and repayable on demand. The
			<lb />
			notice was predicated on the allegation that Dinesh Gupta and
			<lb />
			Shreyansh Gupta had committed various frauds, with which the
			<lb />
			present petition is not really concerned.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			14.3 On 16 February, 2018, Sanchit Gupta issued a requisition,
			<lb />
			under Section 100 (2) of the Companies Act, in respect of Renu
			<lb />
			Promoters. Sanchit Gupta asserted his authority to issue the said
			<lb />
			requisition, as he held 50% of the total paid-up equity share capital in
			<lb />
			Renu Promoters. Alleging that Dinesh Gupta had mismanaged the
			<lb />
			affairs of Renu Promoters and had, thereby, rendered himself
			<lb />
			incapable of continuing as Director of the said Company and liable to
			<lb />
			be removed under Section 169 of the Companies Act, the requisition
			<lb />
			sought convening of an EGM for the said purpose.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			14.4 On 23 rd February, 2018, AGG wrote to Dinesh Gupta and
			<lb />
			Shreyansh Gupta, with respect to the shareholding of AGG in BDR.
			<lb />
			It was asserted, in the said communication, that AGG had never
			<lb />
			transferred, of its own volition, its shares in BDR to DGG. Rather,
			<lb />
			the notice asserted that AGG had agreed to sell its shares in BDR to
			<lb />
			DGG @ ₹ 200/-per equity share and that, for this purpose, AGG had
			<lb />
			affixed signatures on Blank Delivery Instruction Slips, which were
			<lb />
			handed over, to Dinesh Gupta, with the understanding that the slips
			<lb />
			would be used to transfer the shares to DGG only after DGG paid, for
			<lb />
			such transfer, at the rate of ₹ 200/-per share. The slips, it was
			<lb />
			alleged, had been misused, by DGG, to fraudulently transfer the
			<lb />
			shares in its favour. As such, the notice called on DGG to pay, to
			<lb />
			AGG, consideration for such transfer, at the rate of ₹ 200/-per share,
			<lb />
			and not to deal with the said shares till such payment was made.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			14.5 These acts, of AGG, were challenged, by DGG, before this
			<lb />
			Court, by way of CS (OS) 100/2018 (Dinesh Gupta &amp; Ors. v. Anand
			<lb />
			Gupta &amp; Ors.).
			<lb />
			Judgement dated 16 th November, 2018 in IAs, under Order XXXIX,
			<lb />
			preferred in CS (OS) 51/2018 and CS (OS) 100/2018, and orders
			<lb />
			passed in FAO (OS) 6/2019 and FAO (OS) 18/2019, filed thereagainst
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			15. The interlocutory applications, preferred under Order XXXIX
			<lb />
			of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (CPC), for stay -IA 1854/2018
			<lb />
			in CS (OS) 51/2018 (Dinesh Gupta &amp; Ors. v. Rajesh Gupta &amp; Ors.)
			<lb />
			and IA 3238/2018 in CS (OS) 100/2018 (Dinesh Gupta &amp; Ors. v.
			<lb />
			Anand Gupta &amp; Ors.) were disposed of, along with IA 3241/2018 in
			<lb />
			CS (OS) 101/2018 (Dinesh Gupta &amp; Ors. v. Bechu Singh &amp; Ors.),
			<lb />
			vide judgement dated 16 th November, 2018, in the following terms
			<lb />
			(vide paras 53 and 54 of the judgement):
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;53. Accordingly, in the interest of family amity and unity
			<lb />
			and to uphold the family settlement, I confirm the interim
			<lb />
			order passed by this Court dated 7.2.2018 in CS (OS)
			<lb />
			51/2018. Similarly, in IA No 3238/2018 in CS (OS)
			<lb />
			100/2018, I pass an interim order restraining the defendants
			<lb />
			from giving effect to the notice dated 16.02.2018 issued under
			<lb />
			Section 100 of the Companies Act. An interim order was also
			<lb />
			passed against the defendants restraining them from giving
			<lb />
			effect to the notice/communication dated 12.02.2018,
			<lb />
			22.02.2018 and 23.02.2018. As far as IA No. 3241/2018 in
			<lb />
			CS (OS) 101/2018 is concerned, an interim order was passed
			<lb />
			restraining defendant No. 2 from giving effect to the notice
			<lb />
			dated 16.02.2018 issued under Section 100 of the Companies
			<lb />
			Act.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			54.
			<lb />
			However, the above interim order shall continue to
			<lb />
			operate during pendency of the accompanying suit provided
			<lb />
			the plaintiff does the following acts within six weeks from
			<lb />
			today: -
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			He will pay to Mr. Rajesh Gupta a sum of Rs.
			<lb />
			11.28 crores plus Rs.5.28 crores which he is seeking to
			<lb />
			withhold on his own interpretation of the family
			<lb />
			settlement. This amount would be in lieu of the
			<lb />
			redemption of mutual funds held by BDR Developers
			<lb />
			and Builders Private Limited. This would also be
			<lb />
			subject to further orders that may be passed by the
			<lb />
			court.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii)
			<lb />
			The plaintiff will ensure resolution of the Board
			<lb />
			of Directors of the companies vested in Dinesh Gupta
			<lb />
			Group be given in favour of Mr. Rajesh Gupta to
			<lb />
			contest/pursue the case of actionable claims pertaining
			<lb />
			to the said companies/actionable claims have been
			<lb />
			given to the Rajesh Gupta Group. This is subject to
			<lb />
			further orders the court may pass.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) Plaintiff will also pass a resolution of the Board
			<lb />
			of Directors in favour of Rajesh Gupta of Companies
			<lb />
			which have fallen to his share for the purpose of
			<lb />
			pursuing litigation with respect to immovable
			<lb />
			properties which are vested in the Rajesh Gupta
			<lb />
			Group. This is subject to further orders that the court
			<lb />
			may pass.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iv) Mr. Rajesh Gupta will place on record accounts
			<lb />
			of any amounts which are recovered by him in the
			<lb />
			course of adjudication of proceedings regarding
			<lb />
			actionable claims/immovable properties.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(v)
			<lb />
			All the companies which are listed in the family
			<lb />
			settlement will ensure that the quarterly statement of
			<lb />
			accounts are regularly provided to the two main
			<lb />
			parties, namely, Mr. Dinesh Gupta and Mr. Rajesh
			<lb />
			Gupta respectively.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			16. The above order, dated 16 th November, 2018, was carried, in
			<lb />
			appeal, both by Dinesh Gupta and Anand Gupta, vide FAO (OS)
			<lb />
			6/2019 (Dinesh Gupta &amp; Ors. v. Rajesh Gupta &amp; Ors.) and FAO
			<lb />
			(OS) 18/2019 (Anand Gupta &amp; Ors. v. Dinesh Gupta &amp; Ors.).
			<lb />
			While issuing notice, in FAO (OS) 6/2019, the Division Bench of this
			<lb />
			Court, on 14 th January, 2019, stayed, till the next date of hearing,
			<lb />
			directions (i) and (iv) in para 54 of the judgement, dated 16 th
			<lb />
			November, 2018 supra, of the learned Single Judge.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			17. Finally, vide order dated 18 th March, 2019, the Division Bench
			<lb />
			disposed of the aforesaid FAO (OS) 6/2019 and FAO (OS) 18/2019,
			<lb />
			by consent, as the parties agreed to reference of the dispute, between
			<lb />
			them, to the arbitration of Hon&apos;ble Mr. Justice A. K. Sikri (retd.).
			<lb />
			All three suits, which were before the learned Single Judge, were
			<lb />
			referred to the learned Sole Arbitrator. The operative paragraphs of
			<lb />
			the order, dated 18 th March, 2019, merit reproduction, thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;Accordingly, the disputes in all three suits are referred to the
			<lb />
			Sole Arbitration of Mr. Justice A. K. Sikri (Retd. Judge,
			<lb />
			Supreme Court), for decision on merits.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Parties are also agreeable that the interim arrangement
			<lb />
			ordered by the learned Single Judge in the impugned order
			<lb />
			dated 16.11.2018, as modified by the Division Bench in its
			<lb />
			order dated 14.1.2019 in FAO (OS) No. 6/2019 be continued,
			<lb />
			and the present appeal is i.e. FAO (OS) No. 6/2019 and FAO
			<lb />
			(OS) No. 18/2019 and Cross Objections [No. 5947/2019 in
			<lb />
			FAO (OS) No. 6/2019] be also placed before learned
			<lb />
			Arbitrator to be treated as the applications under Section 17
			<lb />
			of the Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996, for decision.
			<lb />
			Parties are further agreeable that they may move further
			<lb />
			application, if any, under Section 17 of the Arbitration and
			<lb />
			Conciliation Act, 1996 before the learned Arbitrator. Ordered
			<lb />
			accordingly.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The learned Arbitrator shall be free to pass orders under
			<lb />
			Section 17 of the Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996 after
			<lb />
			hearing the parties, uninfluenced either by the impugned
			<lb />
			order dated 16.11.2018 passed by a learned Single Judge, or
			<lb />
			by the order dated 14.1.2019 passed by the Division Bench.
			<lb />
			The impugned order dated 16.11.2018 passed by the learned
			<lb />
			Single Judge and the order dated 14.1.2019 shall merge in the
			<lb />
			orders that may be passed by the Ld. Arbitrator.&quot;
			<lb />
			Proceedings before the learned Sole Arbitrator, and the passing of the
			<lb />
			impugned Order dated 18 th February, 2020
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			18. Before the learned Sole Arbitrator, Anand Gupta/AGG filed
			<lb />
			two counter-claims.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			19. Counter-claim by Anand Gupta/AGG related to Mutual Funds,
			<lb />
			claiming a total of ₹ 19,55,00,000/-:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			19.1 This counter claim (hereinafter referred to as &quot;the Mutual
			<lb />
			Funds counter-claim&quot;, for the sake of convenience) was
			<lb />
			preferred by Anand Gupta (HUF) and Sanchit Gupta,
			<lb />
			representing, in essence, the interests of AGG. It was
			<lb />
			contended, in the counter-claim, that, on 30 th November, 2017
			<lb />
			and 4 th December, 2017, the counter-claimants liquidated part
			<lb />
			of their investments in their Mutual Funds, and credited the
			<lb />
			amounts in their respective bank accounts. Thereafter, signed
			<lb />
			blank cheques were stated to have been handed over, to
			<lb />
			Shreyansh Gupta, for investing the amounts in appropriate
			<lb />
			equity Mutual Funds, which, purportedly, was a practice that
			<lb />
			had been adopted on earlier occasions as well. It was alleged
			<lb />
			that Shreyansh Gupta, taking advantage of the family
			<lb />
			relationship, and without the consent of the counter-claimants,
			<lb />
			fraudulently transferred, to his own account, ₹ 19,55,00,000/-,
			<lb />
			using the said blank cheques. Of the said amount, ₹
			<lb />
			15,25,00,000/-was stated to have been misappropriated from
			<lb />
			Anand Gupta (HUF), and ₹ 4,30,00,000/-from Sanchit Gupta.
			<lb />
			Emphasising the fact that the counter-claimants (being the
			<lb />
			respondents in the present proceedings) were not party to any
			<lb />
			family settlement between DGG and RGG, and refuting the
			<lb />
			assertion, by DGG, that ₹ 19,55,00,000/-had been &quot;gifted&quot;, to
			<lb />
			DGG by AGG, the counter-claimants asserted their right to
			<lb />
			recovery of the said amount of ₹ 19,55,00,000/-, with interest.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			19.2 The counter-claim, therefore, prayed that Shreyansh
			<lb />
			Gupta be directed to pay ₹ 15,25,00,000/-and ₹ 4,30,00,000/-,
			<lb />
			respectively, to Sanchit Gupta and Anand Gupta, with interest
			<lb />
			@ 18% p.a.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			20. Counter-claim by Anand Gupta/AGG relating to 26,86,190
			<lb />
			shares of BDR:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			20.1 This counter-claim, by Anand Gupta, Sanchit Gupta,
			<lb />
			Meena Gupta (wife of Anand Gupta) and Aashna Gupta
			<lb />
			(daughter of Anand Gupta) (referred to, hereinafter, for the sake
			<lb />
			of convenience, as the &quot;BDR Shares counter-claim&quot;), alleged
			<lb />
			fraudulent and illegal transfer of 26,86,190 shares of BDR, held
			<lb />
			by the counter-claimants, by DGG, to its DEMAT account. It
			<lb />
			was asserted, in the counter-claim, that, by oral agreement,
			<lb />
			DGG was obligated to pay ₹ 53,72,38,000/-, to the counter-
			<lb />
			claimants, against transfer of 26,86,190 equity shares of BDR.
			<lb />
			On the said assurance, the counter-claimants claimed to have
			<lb />
			signed and executed blank Delivery Instruction Slips, which
			<lb />
			were expected to be used, by DGG, for transferring the shares
			<lb />
			only after the consideration, for such transfer, at the rate of ₹
			<lb />
			200/-per equity share, was paid by it. In violation of the said
			<lb />
			understanding, the counter-claimants alleged that DGG had
			<lb />
			fraudulently transferred the aforesaid 26,86,190 equity shares of
			<lb />
			BDR, to its DEMAT account, without paying the agreed
			<lb />
			consideration therefor. Emphasising the fact that they were not
			<lb />
			party to the purported Family Settlements between DGG and
			<lb />
			RGG, the counter-claimants asserted their right to be paid the
			<lb />
			agreed consideration, for transfer of the aforesaid equity shares
			<lb />
			of BDR, along with interest.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			20.2 The counter-claim, therefore, prayed that DGG be
			<lb />
			directed to pay ₹ 19,02,74,000/-to Anand Gupta, ₹
			<lb />
			21,07,24,000/-to Sanchit Gupta, ₹ 4,81,20,000/-to Meena
			<lb />
			Gupta and ₹ 8,81,20,000/-to Aashna Gupta, along with interest
			<lb />
			@ 18% p.a.
			<lb />
			Fresh applications, under Section 17, preferred before the learned Sole
			<lb />
			Arbitrator
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			21. Four fresh applications, under Section 17 of the 1996 Act, were
			<lb />
			preferred, before the learned Sole Arbitrator. Of these, one was
			<lb />
			preferred by DGG and three were preferred by AGG.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			22. Fresh application, under Section 17, preferred before the
			<lb />
			learned Sole Arbitrator by DGG, seeking implementation of the
			<lb />
			Family Settlements:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			22.1 Alleging that, while it had itself implemented the covenants of
			<lb />
			the Family Settlements &quot;to an extent of more than eighty percent&quot;,
			<lb />
			RGG had implemented the said covenants only to the extent of thirty
			<lb />
			percent, and that the acts of AGG, prejudicial to the interests of DGG,
			<lb />
			were provoked by RGG, an application, under Section 17 of the 1996
			<lb />
			Act, was moved, before the learned Sole Arbitrator, by DGG.
			<lb />
			Reference was invited to the orders, passed by the learned Single
			<lb />
			Judge, as well as by the Division Bench, cited supra. DGG expressed
			<lb />
			discomfiture at the fact that the shares, transferred by DGG to RGG,
			<lb />
			were being used by RGG for, inter alia, issuing notices under Section
			<lb />
			100 of the Companies Act and filing proceedings before the NCLT. It
			<lb />
			was further contended that Mutual Funds, held by Dinesh Gupta in his
			<lb />
			personal name, were being blocked by Rajesh Gupta on the ground
			<lb />
			that he was the nominee therein. Owing to these obstructions, it was
			<lb />
			pointed out that Dinesh Gupta had not been able to withdraw any of
			<lb />
			the Mutual Funds which, even as per the Family Settlements,
			<lb />
			devolved on DGG.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			22.2 DGG also advanced various reasons, to dispute the allegations
			<lb />
			of AGG, regarding fraudulent transfer of shares into the DEMAT
			<lb />
			account of DGG. It was pointed out that the complete exit of AGG,
			<lb />
			from Renu Farms and Renu Promoters, was manifest even by the
			<lb />
			alteration of the authorised signatories of the said Bank accounts.
			<lb />
			Further, DGG pointed out that AGG had never set up any claim, in
			<lb />
			any Court of law, challenging the documents of transfer, and the
			<lb />
			limitation for such challenge had also expired. In view of the
			<lb />
			submissions, it was prayed, in the application, that
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			the order, dated 16 th November, 2018, passed by the
			<lb />
			learned Single Judge in CS (OS) 101/2018, be continued during
			<lb />
			the pendency of the arbitral proceedings,
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii) RGG be directed to deposit, before the learned Sole
			<lb />
			Arbitrator, all shares held by him in Companies/entities which
			<lb />
			came to the share of DGG, under the Family Settlement dated
			<lb />
			9 th December, 2017,
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) RGG be directed to remove the objection in respect of
			<lb />
			encashment of the Mutual Funds in favour of DGG, and
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iv) RGG be directed to provide authorisation to DGG for
			<lb />
			commencement/prosecution of any actionable claims pertaining
			<lb />
			to the shares of DGG, in Companies which went to RGG under
			<lb />
			the Family Settlement.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			23. Three applications, under Section 17, preferred before the
			<lb />
			learned Sole Arbitrator by AGG/Sanchit Gupta:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			23.1 On 12 th April, 2019, AGG/the members thereof, filed three
			<lb />
			applications, under Section 17, before the learned Sole Arbitrator. For
			<lb />
			the sake of convenience, they would be referred to, hereinafter, as the
			<lb />
			first, second and third Section 17 applications, respectively.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			23.2 The first Section 17 application was filed by Sanchit Gupta,
			<lb />
			purportedly for protection of the rights and interests of shareholders in
			<lb />
			Renu Promoters, against the acts of Dinesh Gupta and Shreyansh
			<lb />
			Gupta, in their capacity as Directors in the said Company. The
			<lb />
			application alleged that Dinesh Gupta and Shreyansh Gupta were &quot;not
			<lb />
			handling the issue efficiently with the tenant of the property&quot; of Renu
			<lb />
			Promoters, located at W-12, Greater Kailash Part II, New Delhi. Even
			<lb />
			while judgement was reserved, by the learned Single Judge in CS
			<lb />
			(OS) 100/2018, it was alleged that Dinesh Gupta and Shreyansh
			<lb />
			Gupta had sold the said property, vide Sale Deed dated 18 th May,
			<lb />
			2018, for ₹ 10,50,00,000/-.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			23.3 Pointing out that AGG was not a party to the Family
			<lb />
			Settlements between DGG and RGG, and that the said Family
			<lb />
			Settlements had also been disputed by RGG on various grounds, the
			<lb />
			application asserted that, in issuing notices under Section 100 of the
			<lb />
			Companies Act, for convening of the EGM, Sanchit Gupta was
			<lb />
			merely exercising his statutory rights, in view of the fact that Dinesh
			<lb />
			Gupta was acting against the interests of Renu Promoters. In the
			<lb />
			circumstances, the application prayed that
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			Dinesh Gupta, Shreyansh Gupta and Renu Promoters be
			<lb />
			directed to maintain status quo, in relation to the immovable
			<lb />
			assets of Renu Promoters, as well as in relation to its
			<lb />
			shareholdings, and that
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii) Dinesh Gupta and Shreyansh Gupta be restrained from
			<lb />
			taking any decision in their capacity as Directors in Renu
			<lb />
			Promoters, or from utilising any money received on behalf of
			<lb />
			Renu Promoters.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			23.4 The second Section 17 application, by Sanchit Gupta and
			<lb />
			Anand Gupta HUF, sought restraint, against Shreyansh Gupta, in
			<lb />
			respect of M/s. C. R. Farms Pvt Ltd (hereinafter referred to as &quot;C.R.
			<lb />
			Farms&quot;). The prayer was premised on the alleged entitlement, of
			<lb />
			AGG, to recover ₹ 19.55 crores from Shreyansh Gupta. As the share
			<lb />
			capital of CR Farms had been acquired by utilisating of part of the
			<lb />
			alleged fraudulent transferred amount of ₹ 19.55 crores, the
			<lb />
			application sought restraint, against Shreyansh Gupta, from
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			alienating the said equity shares,
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii) creating any charge, encumbrance or third party rights on
			<lb />
			the said equity shares,
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) enjoying any benefits, including exercising of voting
			<lb />
			rights, accruing to Shreyansh Gupta from holding of the said
			<lb />
			shares, and
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iv) transferring/liquidating any mutual funds, acquired from
			<lb />
			the allegedly fraudulently transferred amount,
			<lb />
			till the amount of ₹ 19.55 crores was repaid to Anand Gupta HUF and
			<lb />
			Sanchit Gupta.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			23.5 The impugned direction was issued in this application.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			23.6 The third Section 17 application was filed by Anand Gupta,
			<lb />
			Sanchit Gupta, Meena Gupta and Aashna Gupta, for restraining
			<lb />
			Dinesh Gupta and Shreyansh Gupta from alienating 26,86,190 shares
			<lb />
			of BDR. It was alleged, in the application, that, by oral agreement,
			<lb />
			the applicants had agreed to transfer 26,86,190 equity shares of BDR
			<lb />
			to Dinesh Gupta and Shreyansh Gupta, on condition of payment, by
			<lb />
			the latter, of ₹ 53,72,38,000/-. Acting on the basis of the said
			<lb />
			purported oral agreement, the applicants claimed to have executed
			<lb />
			blank Delivery Instruction Slips, which were to be used by Dinesh
			<lb />
			Gupta and Shreyansh Gupta, for transfer of the said shares to DGG,
			<lb />
			only after payment of consideration, therefor, @ ₹ 200/-per equity
			<lb />
			share. In violation of the said oral agreement, the application alleged
			<lb />
			that Dinesh Gupta and Shreyansh Gupta had fraudulently transferred
			<lb />
			26,86,190 shares, of BDR, to their DEMAT Account. The applicants,
			<lb />
			therefore, claimed that they were entitled to consideration, for the said
			<lb />
			transfer, amounting to ₹ 53,72,38,000/-. The application, therefore,
			<lb />
			sought a restraint, against Dinesh Gupta and Shreyansh Gupta, from
			<lb />
			alienating the aforesaid 26,86,190 equity shares of BDR, or from
			<lb />
			creating any third party rights in respect thereof.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			24. As a result, the learned Sole Arbitrator had, before him, seven
			<lb />
			applications, under Section 17 of the 1996 Act -the three Civil Suits
			<lb />
			filed before the learned Single Judge, i.e. CS (OS) 51/2018, CS (OS)
			<lb />
			100/2018 and CS (OS) 101/2018, one fresh application filed by
			<lb />
			Dinesh Gupta and three fresh applications filed by AGG/its members.
			<lb />
			Besides these, applications had also been preferred, under Section 17,
			<lb />
			by RGG and by Bechu Singh, with which we need not concern
			<lb />
			ourselves.
			<lb />
			The impugned Order
			<lb />
			25. Though the grievance of the petitioner is with respect to a
			<lb />
			limited direction in the impugned Order, it is necessary to examine
			<lb />
			how the learned Sole Arbitrator has proceeded, while deciding the
			<lb />
			aforesaid applications, under Section 17, preferred by DGG and
			<lb />
			AGG/their respective members.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			26. The learned Sole Arbitrator has observed, at the outset, that the
			<lb />
			execution of the Family Settlement dated 2 nd December, 2017 and 9 th
			<lb />
			December, 2017, was undisputed, and that it was also an admitted
			<lb />
			position that, even prior to the recording of the said Family
			<lb />
			Settlements, DGG, RGG and even AGG were taking actions to
			<lb />
			detangle their rights in various Companies, in terms thereof.
			<lb />
			Disputes, however, persisted, with respect to implementation of the
			<lb />
			Settlement Agreement qua actionable claims, to be pursued by one, or
			<lb />
			the other, faction, with respect to Companies which fell to the share of
			<lb />
			that faction, though they remained with the other. The learned Sole
			<lb />
			Arbitrator placed reliance on the decisions in Kale v Deputy Director
			<lb />
			of Consolidation 1 , S. Shanmugham Pillai v. K. Shanmugham Pillai 2
			<lb />
			and Hari Shankar Singhania v. Gaur Hari Singhania 3 , to hold that
			<lb />
			arrangements in family settlements were sacrosanct, and commanded
			<lb />
			implicit compliance.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			27. Proceeding, thereafter, to the applications filed by DGG and
			<lb />
			AGG, or their members, under Section 17, the learned Sole Arbitrator
			<lb />
			has, on the application of DGG, continued the order, dated 16 th
			<lb />
			1 (1976) 3 SCC 119
			<lb />
			2 (1973) 2 SCC 312
			<lb />
			3 (2006) 4 SCC 658
			<lb />
			November, 2018, of the learned Single Judge, as his own order, in the
			<lb />
			arbitral proceedings. No grievance, with this decision, has been
			<lb />
			expressed by either side.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			28. The learned Sole Arbitrator has, thereafter, proceeded to advert
			<lb />
			to the three applications, under Section 17, preferred by AGG, or its
			<lb />
			members.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			29. Apropos the first Section 17 application, filed by Sanchit Gupta
			<lb />
			on 12 th April, 2019, for a direction, to DGG and Shreyans Gupta to
			<lb />
			maintain status quo in relation to the immovable assets of BDR and
			<lb />
			Nimit Builders Pvt. Ltd., the learned Sole Arbitrator has noticed that
			<lb />
			these Companies fell to the share of DGG, under the Family
			<lb />
			Settlements. Though AGG was not a signatory thereto, DGG, it has
			<lb />
			been noticed, had contended that the Family Settlements had the
			<lb />
			blessings of Anand Gupta/AGG, who/which had acted on the basis
			<lb />
			thereof, by transferring shares, held by it in Companies which had
			<lb />
			fallen to the share of DGG under the Family Settlements, to DGG, and
			<lb />
			also by remitting, to the accounts of the members of DGG, amounts
			<lb />
			realised by encashment of various mutual funds. Observing that these
			<lb />
			actions were in tune with the covenants of the Family Settlements, the
			<lb />
			learned Sole Arbitrator has found that a prima facie case existed, in
			<lb />
			favour of DGG.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			30. The learned Sole Arbitrator has, thereafter, referred to the
			<lb />
			decisions of the Supreme Court in Narendra Kante v. Anuradha
			<lb />
			Kante 4 and M. S. Madhusoodanan v. Kerala Kaumudi (P) Ltd 5 , as
			<lb />
			well as of this Court in Satya Pal Gupta v. Sudhir Kumar Gupta 6 , to
			<lb />
			observe that family settlements were enforceable even against non-
			<lb />
			signatories thereto. As BDR and Nishit fell, under the Family
			<lb />
			Settlements, to the share of DGG, the learned Sole Arbitrator held that
			<lb />
			it was not appropriate to restrain DGG from dealing with the said
			<lb />
			Companies, especially as they were in the business of real estate, and
			<lb />
			any direction, to them, to maintain status quo in respect of the
			<lb />
			immovable assets of BDR and Nishit would stifle their business. It
			<lb />
			was noticed that the said assets were the stock-in-trade of BDR and
			<lb />
			Nishit. Even so, DGG was directed to maintain status quo in respect
			<lb />
			of those immovable assets which constituted part of its capital assets,
			<lb />
			and were not part of its stock-in-trade.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			31. Adverting to the second and third applications, under Section
			<lb />
			17 of the 1996 Act, preferred by AGG/its members, the learned Sole
			<lb />
			Arbitrator held thus (in para 3.28 of the impugned Order, the
			<lb />
			concluding sentence of which constitutes the subject matter of
			<lb />
			challenge herein):
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;In the other two applications filed by members of AGG, they
			<lb />
			are seeking restitution of the amounts which they have
			<lb />
			remitted. For the reasons given above, such a relief cannot be
			<lb />
			granted at this stage as it needs determination as to whether
			<lb />
			the payments were made by AGG of (sic to?) DGG
			<lb />
			voluntarily pursuant to the Family Settlements or they are
			<lb />
			fraudulently secured by DGG as contended by AGG in these
			<lb />
			applications. At the same time, in order to secure the interest
			<lb />
			of AGG, in the event AGG ultimately succeeds, it would be
			<lb />
			4 (2010) 2 SCC 77
			<lb />
			5 (2004) 9 SCC 204
			<lb />
			6 2016 SCC OnLine Del 2502
			<lb />
			appropriate to direct DGG to furnish suitable (security)
			<lb />
			equivalent to the sums involved, to the Tribunal.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			(It may be mentioned, here, that the word &quot;security&quot;, as parenthesized
			<lb />
			in the concluding sentence of the afore-extracted para, does not figure
			<lb />
			in the paragraph, as contained in the copy of the impugned Order,
			<lb />
			filed by the petitioner. However, the subsequent clarificatory order,
			<lb />
			passed by the learned Sole Arbitrator on 14 th May, 2020, indicates that
			<lb />
			DGG was directed to furnish security.)
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			32. DGG claims, in this appeal, to be aggrieved by the direction to
			<lb />
			it, as contained in the italicised sentence from the afore-extracted para
			<lb />
			3.28 of the impugned Order passed by the learned Sole Arbitrator, to
			<lb />
			furnish security equivalent to the sums involved. This direction,
			<lb />
			contends DGG -as vocalized, on its behalf, by Mr. Rajeev Nayar,
			<lb />
			learned Senior Counsel -was completely unjustified, as well as
			<lb />
			unsustainable in law. It is, therefore, prayed that the said direction be
			<lb />
			quashed and set aside.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			33. DGG, RGG and AGG, thereafter, moved an application, before
			<lb />
			the learned Sole Arbitrator, for clarification of the impugned order,
			<lb />
			dated 18 th February, 2020, in certain respects. All these applications
			<lb />
			were disposed of, by the learned Sole Arbitrator, vide a common order
			<lb />
			dated 14 th May, 2020. Dealing with the clarifications sought by DGG,
			<lb />
			the learned Sole Arbitrator observed, inter alia, that
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			the direction for maintenance of status quo, by DGG, in
			<lb />
			respect of the capital assets of BDR and Nishit, related to the
			<lb />
			assets of Renu Promoters,
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii) in addition to continuation, of the order, dated 16 th
			<lb />
			November, 2018 supra, passed by the learned Single Judge, the
			<lb />
			orders of restraint, passed by the learned Single Judge, in
			<lb />
			respect of the notices, under Section 100 of the Companies Act,
			<lb />
			dated 12 th February, 2018, 22 nd February, 2018 and 23 rd
			<lb />
			February, 2018, were also continued, and
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) the prayer for &quot;clarification&quot;, of the direction, to DGG, to
			<lb />
			transfer the shares of Nishit by Renu Gupta to BDR, amounted
			<lb />
			to seeking a review of the impugned order, which was not
			<lb />
			permissible.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			Apropos the clarifications sought by AGG, the learned Sole Arbitrator
			<lb />
			only addressed the submission that, qua the impugned direction to
			<lb />
			DGG to furnish security, no time period had been stipulated. The
			<lb />
			learned Sole Arbitrator clarified that security was required to be
			<lb />
			furnished, by DGG, as directed in the impugned para 3.28 of the order
			<lb />
			dated 18 th February, 2020, within four weeks, to the satisfaction of the
			<lb />
			learned Sole Arbitrator.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			34. The findings of the learned Sole Arbitrator, qua the
			<lb />
			clarifications sought by RGG, are not relevant for the purposes of the
			<lb />
			present petition, and are not, therefore, being adverted to.
			<lb />
			Rival Contentions
			<lb />
			35. Mr. Rajiv Nayar, on behalf of the appellant, advances the
			<lb />
			following submissions, to assail the impugned direction, in para 3.28
			<lb />
			of the order dated 18 th February, 2020, of the learned Sole Arbitrator:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			No prayer, for directing furnishing of security, by DGG,
			<lb />
			had been made by AGG, in any of its applications, under
			<lb />
			Section 17. The prayer was only for restraint, against DGG,
			<lb />
			from dealing with the shares held by DGG in C.R. Farms and
			<lb />
			with the shares of BDR. No prayer, for restitution of any
			<lb />
			amount, was contained in the applications. The impugned
			<lb />
			direction, for furnishing of security, proceeded on the premise
			<lb />
			that AGG had sought restitution/refund, of the amount of ₹
			<lb />
			19.55 crores. As such, the learned Sole Arbitrator had
			<lb />
			exceeded his jurisdiction in granting a relief, unclaimed by
			<lb />
			AGG. Reliance is placed, for this purpose, on the judgements
			<lb />
			of this Court in Tata Advanced Systems Ltd v. Texcell
			<lb />
			Information Systems Ltd 7 , Captain Guman Singh &amp; Sons v.
			<lb />
			Indian Oil Corporation 8 and NHPC Ltd v. HCC Ltd 9 .
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii) Having observed, in para 3.26 of the impugned Order
			<lb />
			dated 18 th February, 2020, that a prima facie case existed in
			<lb />
			favour of DGG, the learned Sole Arbitrator erred in directing
			<lb />
			furnishing of security, by DGG, in favour of AGG.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) The direction for furnishing of security was also vitiated
			<lb />
			by non-compliance, in the facts of the case, with the ingredients
			<lb />
			7 MANU/DE/1061/2020
			<lb />
			8 2016 SCC Online Del 983
			<lb />
			9 2018 IX AD (Delhi) 1
			<lb />
			of Order XXXVIII Rule 5 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908
			<lb />
			(CPC), which were not even pleaded by AGG. The learned
			<lb />
			Sole Arbitrator could not, therefore, have directed furnishing of
			<lb />
			security, by DGG, merely on the basis of an unascertained
			<lb />
			counter-claim. Reliance has been placed, for this proposition,
			<lb />
			on the judgements of the Supreme Court in State Bank of
			<lb />
			India v. Ericsson India Pvt Ltd 10 and of this Court in C.V. Rao
			<lb />
			and Krishnapatnam Port Co. Ltd. v.
			<lb />
			Strategic Port
			<lb />
			Investments KPC Ltd 11 , Lanco Infratech Ltd. v. Hindustan
			<lb />
			Construction Co Ltd 12 , Goodwill Non-Woven (P) Ltd v. Xcoal
			<lb />
			Energy and Resources LLC 13 and BMW India Private Limited
			<lb />
			v. Libra Automotives Pvt Ltd 14 .
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iv) Even if it were to be presumed that the learned Sole
			<lb />
			Arbitrator has the power to &quot;mould&quot; the reliefs prayed for, such
			<lb />
			moulding had to be informed by reasons, to be contained in the
			<lb />
			order. Relief, not sought in the application under Section 17,
			<lb />
			and not pressed even during arguments before the learned Sole
			<lb />
			Arbitrator, could not have been granted. Least of all could the
			<lb />
			learned Sole Arbitrator have directed furnishing of security, by
			<lb />
			DGG, without putting DGG, in the first instance, on notice in
			<lb />
			that regard. Reliance was placed, in this context, on the
			<lb />
			judgements of the Supreme Court in Om Prakash Gupta v.
			<lb />
			Ranbir B. Goyal 15 (which, according to Mr. Nayar, set out the
			<lb />
			10 (2018) 16 SCC 617
			<lb />
			11 218 (2015) DLT 200 (DB)
			<lb />
			12 234 (2016) DLT 175
			<lb />
			13 2020 SCC Online Del 631
			<lb />
			14 2019 (5) Arb LR 118 (Del)
			<lb />
			15 (2002) 2 SCC 256
			<lb />
			circumstances in which relief could be moulded, none of which
			<lb />
			were satisfied in the present case) and Seshambal v. Chelur
			<lb />
			Corporation Chelur Building 16 .
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(v) No finding of the existence of a prima facie case, in
			<lb />
			favour of AGG, had been returned by the learned Sole
			<lb />
			Arbitrator. Nor has the learned Sole Arbitrator addressed the
			<lb />
			concerns of balance of convenience and irreparable loss, which,
			<lb />
			in conjunction with the existence of a prima facie case,
			<lb />
			constituted the troika for grant of interim relief. Mr. Nayar
			<lb />
			relied, in this context, on the judgement of this Court in
			<lb />
			Intertoll ICS Cecons O &amp; M Co. Pvt Ltd v. N.H.A.I. 17 .
			<lb />
			(vi) AGG was acting with clear dishonesty, as it was
			<lb />
			challenging the actions, taken by it in favour of DGG, without
			<lb />
			challenging similar actions, taken by it in favour of RGG.
			<lb />
			(vii) The liability for security had entirely been fastened on
			<lb />
			DGG, whereas the liability of AGG, if any, would fall on the
			<lb />
			entire estate shared between DGG and RGG.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			36. Responding to the submissions of Mr. Nayar, it was contended,
			<lb />
			by Mr. Sudhir Nandrajog, learned Senior Counsel for AGG, thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			AGG was neither a party, nor a signatory, to the Family
			<lb />
			Settlement dated 2 nd December, 2017 and 9 December, 2017.
			<lb />
			In fact, it had been conceded by DGG, in CS (OS) 51/2018, that
			<lb />
			16 (2010) 3 SCC 470
			<lb />
			17 ILR (2013) II Del 1018
			<lb />
			&quot;all objections, rights and obligations of the third branch i.e.
			<lb />
			Anand Gupta Group stood satisfied and settled prior to the
			<lb />
			execution of the Family Settlement&quot;, thus obviating the
			<lb />
			necessity of including the Anand Gupta Group in the Family
			<lb />
			Settlement.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii) The business of AGG was not interconnected, in any
			<lb />
			manner, with that of DGG. There was no reason, therefore, for
			<lb />
			AGG to be part of any settlement between DGG and RGG.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) The Family Settlements did not address the claims of
			<lb />
			AGG, and limited themselves to settling the estate of DGG and
			<lb />
			RGG. Such a &quot;partial&quot; Family Settlement, excluding the rights
			<lb />
			and claims of other groups, which had legitimate interests, was
			<lb />
			impermissible and unenforceable. There was no inter-se
			<lb />
			Family Settlement between DGG, RGG and AGG.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iv) Having asserted, in CS (OS) 51/2018, (as noted
			<lb />
			hereinabove) that all rights and obligations of AGG stood
			<lb />
			satisfied and settled prior to the execution of the Family
			<lb />
			Settlements, DGG was seeking to contend, now, that AGG had
			<lb />
			obligations under the Family Settlements.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(v) Apropos the submission, of Mr. Nayar, that the learned
			<lb />
			Sole Arbitrator had erred in granting a relief, not sought or
			<lb />
			claimed by AGG, it was contended that a plain reading of the
			<lb />
			impugned Order revealed that the learned Sole Arbitrator had,
			<lb />
			in fact, rejected the relief, sought by AGG, and had granted a
			<lb />
			lesser relief, in the form of furnishing of security. The power of
			<lb />
			the learned Sole Arbitrator, to do so, was unexceptionable. Mr.
			<lb />
			Nandrajog drew my attention, in this context, to the prayers of
			<lb />
			AGG, in the applications, preferred by it under Section 17. It
			<lb />
			was also submitted, in this context, that, in fact, the property at
			<lb />
			C.R. Farms had been purchased by DGG using the monies
			<lb />
			realised by liquidation of the Mutual Funds, in which AGG had
			<lb />
			invested.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(vi) Besides, even on facts, it was submitted that, as the order,
			<lb />
			dated 18 th March, 2019, of the Division Bench in FAO (OS)
			<lb />
			6/2019 and FAO (OS) 18/2019, directed the said appeals to be
			<lb />
			treated as applications under Section 17, it could not be said
			<lb />
			that the learned Sole Arbitrator had exceeded his jurisdiction in
			<lb />
			directing furnishing of security by DGG. My attention was
			<lb />
			invited, in this context, to the reliefs sought in the appeals
			<lb />
			which, according to Mr. Nandrajog, were in excess of mere
			<lb />
			furnishing of security.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(vii) The reliefs claimed by AGG, in its counter claims, was
			<lb />
			also relevant. The amounts claimed by AGG were in excess of
			<lb />
			₹ 70 crores.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(viii) Para 3.27 of the impugned Order clearly noted the
			<lb />
			contentions of the parties, and gave reasons for not granting the
			<lb />
			larger relief claimed by AGG. The status quo, as directed to be
			<lb />
			maintained by DGG, was also restricted to its capital assets, and
			<lb />
			did not extend to its stock-in-trade. This direction was not
			<lb />
			assailed by DGG. AGG had, in fact, sought restitution. The
			<lb />
			learned Sole Arbitrator held that, while it was not possible to
			<lb />
			grant restitution as claimed, it was equitable to direct furnishing
			<lb />
			of security by DGG. In so directing, the learned Sole Arbitrator
			<lb />
			clearly acted within the confines of the jurisdiction, vested in
			<lb />
			him by clauses (b) and (e) of Section 17 (2) of the 1996 Act.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ix) The direction for furnishing of securities effectively
			<lb />
			balanced the equities between the parties. No occasion, for
			<lb />
			interference therewith, therefore, existed. In this context, my
			<lb />
			attention was invited to the fact that the learned Sole Arbitrator
			<lb />
			had stayed all the recovery notices, issued by AGG.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(x) The reliance, by the appellant, on Order XXXVIII Rule 5
			<lb />
			of the CPC, was misplaced. Section 17 of the 1996 Act was a
			<lb />
			complete code in itself. In view of Section 19 of the 1996 Act,
			<lb />
			the CPC did not apply. The restrictions, which influenced
			<lb />
			exercise of jurisdiction under Order XXXVIII Rule 5 of the
			<lb />
			CPC, were not incorporated, either expressly or by necessary
			<lb />
			implication, into Section 17.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(xi) Besides, the invocation of Order XXXVIII Rule 5 was,
			<lb />
			even otherwise, misconceived on facts, as the learned Sole
			<lb />
			Arbitrator had not directed attachment, but only furnishing of
			<lb />
			security.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(xii) Though DGG, RGG and AGG had all applied for
			<lb />
			clarification of the impugned Order dated 18 th February, 2020,
			<lb />
			no clarification, of the direction to furnish security, was sought
			<lb />
			by the appellant. The balance of convenience was also,
			<lb />
			therefore, against the appellant.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(xiii) It was not open to DGG to rely on the Family
			<lb />
			Settlements, as the validity and scope thereof, were yet to be
			<lb />
			decided by the learned Sole Arbitrator. My attention was
			<lb />
			invited, in this context, to the &quot;Proposed Points of
			<lb />
			Determination&quot;, as submitted by the appellant to the learned
			<lb />
			Sole Arbitrator, Points 4 and 7, whereof, read thus:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;4.
			<lb />
			Where the Anand Gupta Group (&apos;AGG&apos;) can be
			<lb />
			allowed to resile from the transactions made by it prior
			<lb />
			to and after the execution of the Family Settlement
			<lb />
			dated 02.12.2017 and 09.12.2017 on the basis that he
			<lb />
			was not a signatory to the said Family Settlements?
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			7.
			<lb />
			Whether RGG, DGG, AGG, BSE deserved to
			<lb />
			be directed to comply with the terms of the Family
			<lb />
			Settlement in a manner that valuations which leads to
			<lb />
			the entire capital distributed 50:50 amongst RGG and
			<lb />
			DGG and accordingly be directed to not employ others
			<lb />
			to destroy the letter and spirit of such terms of the
			<lb />
			Family Settlement dated 02.12.2017 and 09.12.2017?&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(xiv) There was nothing to indicate that the claim of ₹ 19.55
			<lb />
			crores, by AGG, was part of the Family Settlement. Nor was
			<lb />
			there any evidence to indicate that the said amount had been
			<lb />
			gifted by AGG to DGG. The appellant, too, had not averred
			<lb />
			that this amount was shown as gift, in its Tax Returns.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(xv) Inasmuch as the issue of whether AGG was, or was not,
			<lb />
			part of the Family Settlement, and was bound by the terms
			<lb />
			thereof, was yet to be determined, the direction, to DGG, to
			<lb />
			furnish security, was equitable, and did not call for interference.
			<lb />
			If, ultimately, the learned Sole Arbitrator was to reach the
			<lb />
			opinion that the Family Settlements were binding, AGG would
			<lb />
			be left high and dry.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(xvi) The reliance, by the appellant, on Sections 91 and 92 of
			<lb />
			the Evidence Act, was misplaced, as these provisions applied
			<lb />
			only where a person sought to lead evidence contrary to the
			<lb />
			document to which he was a signatory. No such occasion arose
			<lb />
			in the present case.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(xvii) The impugned Order had been passed at a preliminary
			<lb />
			stage, and could not be said to suffer from any such perversity,
			<lb />
			as would justify interference, by this Court.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			37. Arguing in rejoinder, Mr. Nayar re-emphasised the fact that,
			<lb />
			having held, in para 3.28 of the impugned Order dated 18 th February,
			<lb />
			2020, that no relief, for restitution of the amounts, as claimed by
			<lb />
			AGG, could be granted, the learned Sole Arbitrator signally erred in
			<lb />
			directing furnishing of security by the appellant. Mr. Nayar
			<lb />
			emphasised, further, that the contentions, advanced by Mr. Nandrajog,
			<lb />
			did not constitute the basis for the impugned direction, of the learned
			<lb />
			Sole Arbitrator. He submitted that the direction to furnish security, if
			<lb />
			issued under Section 17 of the 1996 Act, had necessarily to conform
			<lb />
			to the discipline of Order XXXVIII Rule 5, sub-rule (4) whereof
			<lb />
			rendered void any order for attachment, passed in violation of sub-rule
			<lb />
			(1). Mr. Nayar submitted that the emphasis, by Mr. Nandrajog, on the
			<lb />
			impugned direction being equitable in nature, was misguided, as the
			<lb />
			learned Sole Arbitrator was not empowered to act on the basis of
			<lb />
			equity. There was, Mr. Nayar re-emphasised, no prayer, for
			<lb />
			furnishing of security, made by AGG at any stage of the proceedings,
			<lb />
			including the appeals, against the order of the learned Single Judge,
			<lb />
			which had been converted, by this Court, into applications under
			<lb />
			Section 17 of the 1996 Act.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>

				Analysis
			</p>
		<p>

			<lb />
			Scope of interference under Section 37
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			38. Before proceeding to examine the submissions of learned
			<lb />
			Senior Counsel, as advanced before me, it would be appropriate to
			<lb />
			address, in the first instance, the scope and ambit of Section 37 of the
			<lb />
			1996 Act, especially apropos the jurisdiction, of this Court, to
			<lb />
			interfere with interlocutory orders passed by the learned Arbitrator
			<lb />
			under Section 17.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			39. Section 37, on its plain reading, provides for an appeal against
			<lb />
			certain orders. The provision does not define the scope and extent of
			<lb />
			the said jurisdiction of the High Court, in the matter of entertaining
			<lb />
			and disposing of the appeal. Nor is there any other provision, in the
			<lb />
			1996 Act, which enlightens on this aspect. For ready reference,
			<lb />
			Section 37 may be reproduced, thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;Section 37. Appealable orders.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(1) Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for
			<lb />
			the time being in force, an appeal shall lie from the following
			<lb />
			orders (and from no others) to the Court authorised by law to
			<lb />
			hear appeals from original decrees of the Court passing the
			<lb />
			order, namely : --
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a) refusing to refer the parties to arbitration under
			<lb />
			section 8;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b) granting or refusing to grant any measure under
			<lb />
			section 9;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(c) setting aside or refusing to set aside an arbitral
			<lb />
			award under section 34.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(2) Appeal shall also lie to a court from an order of the
			<lb />
			arbitral tribunal--
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a) accepting the plea referred to in sub-section (2) or
			<lb />
			sub-section (3) of section 16; or
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b) granting or refusing to grant an interim measure
			<lb />
			under section 17.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(3) No second appeal shall lie from an order passed in appeal
			<lb />
			under this section, but nothing in this section shall affect or
			<lb />
			take away any right to appeal to the Supreme Court.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			40. Oftentimes, the question arises as to whether the jurisdiction of
			<lb />
			the High Court, under Section 37, is subject to the same
			<lb />
			circumscriptions as formed by its jurisdiction under Section 34. Mr.
			<lb />
			Nayar had submitted, before me, that it would be folly to restrict the
			<lb />
			jurisdiction of the High Court, under Section 37, by the principles
			<lb />
			which apply to Section 34. He had sought to emphasise that the
			<lb />
			jurisdiction vested in the Court by Section 37 was appellate, unlike
			<lb />
			Section 34. Appellate jurisdiction, by its very nature, Mr. Nayar had
			<lb />
			sought to submit, is wider than the jurisdiction which applies to
			<lb />
			consideration of objections against an arbitral award. Appellate
			<lb />
			jurisdiction encompasses, within its fold, the power to review findings
			<lb />
			of fact and, in fact, the appellate court is, jurisprudentially, an
			<lb />
			extension of the original court, the appeal being a continuation of the
			<lb />
			original proceedings. As such, Mr. Nayar had sought to submit, the
			<lb />
			High Court, exercising appellate jurisdiction under Section 37, should
			<lb />
			not feel restricted by the constraints which govern its jurisdiction
			<lb />
			under Section 34.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			41. Empirically viewed, Mr. Nayar&apos;s submissions appear attractive.
			<lb />
			There is, undoubtedly, qualitatively, a distinction between appellate
			<lb />
			jurisdiction and &quot;judicial review jurisdiction&quot;. Appellate jurisdiction,
			<lb />
			equally, is classically regarded as an extension of original jurisdiction,
			<lb />
			the appellate proceedings being an extension of the original
			<lb />
			proceedings. The appellate court is, therefore, ordinarily, empowered
			<lb />
			to re-appreciate findings of fact entered by the original court. That the
			<lb />
			jurisdiction of the appellate court is much wider than the jurisdiction
			<lb />
			of a Court exercising judicial review, of any other kind, is also,
			<lb />
			classically, well settled.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			42. Legal principles are, however, in every instance, required to be
			<lb />
			applied to the factual scenario, in which their application is invited.
			<lb />
			While, therefore, appreciating the jurisdiction of the High Court,
			<lb />
			under Section 37 of the 1996 Act, we are required to be aware of the
			<lb />
			fact that the order, interference with which is being invited, was
			<lb />
			passed by an arbitrator, or arbitral tribunal. The sanctity attached to
			<lb />
			arbitral awards, especially in the context of the 1996 Act -which is
			<lb />
			based on the UNCITRAL model -has, therefore, necessarily to be
			<lb />
			borne in mind, while exercising jurisdiction over the decision of the
			<lb />
			arbitrator, whether in the form of a final award, or an interim award
			<lb />
			under Section 17.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			43. In the opinion of this Court, another important, and peculiar,
			<lb />
			feature of the 1996 Act, which must necessarily inform the approach
			<lb />
			of the High Court, is that the 1996 Act provides for an appeal against
			<lb />
			interlocutory orders, whereas the final award is not amenable to any
			<lb />
			appeal, but only to objections under Section 34. If the submission of
			<lb />
			Mr. Nayar, as advanced, were to be accepted, it would imply that the
			<lb />
			jurisdiction of the Court, over the interlocutory decision of the
			<lb />
			arbitrator, would be much wider than the jurisdiction against the final
			<lb />
			award. Though, jurisprudentially, perhaps, such a position may not be
			<lb />
			objectionable, it does appear incongruous, and opposed to the well
			<lb />
			settled principle that the scope of interference with interim orders, is,
			<lb />
			ordinarily, much more restricted than the scope of interference with
			<lb />
			the final judgement.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			44. Here, yet another peculiar dispensation, in the 1996 Act,
			<lb />
			apropos the scope of interference with the decision of the arbitrator,
			<lb />
			manifests itself. The proviso to Section 36 (3) ordains that the Court,
			<lb />
			while considering an application for grant of stay of a final arbitral
			<lb />
			award for payment of money, shall &quot;have due regard to the provisions
			<lb />
			for grant of stay of a decree under the provisions of the Code of Civil
			<lb />
			Procedure, 1908&quot;. By reference, therefore, Order 41 Rule 5 of the
			<lb />
			CPC, which deals with stay, by the appellate court, of original
			<lb />
			decrees, stands incorporated into Section 36(3) of the 1996 Act.
			<lb />
			Though, therefore, the final arbitral award is not made amenable to
			<lb />
			appeal, by the 1996 Act, any prayer for stay of the arbitral award, that
			<lb />
			accompanies objections under Section 34, is required to be examined
			<lb />
			in the light of the provisions, in the CPC, governing stay of original
			<lb />
			decrees, in exercise of appellate jurisdiction. Though, for the
			<lb />
			purposes of this judgement, it is not necessary to psychoanalyse the
			<lb />
			legislative intent in providing for such a peculiar dispensation, the fact
			<lb />
			that applications for stay of final arbitral awards, are required to be
			<lb />
			considered on the basis of the principles governing stay, by appellate
			<lb />
			courts, under Order 41 Rule 5 of the CPC, indicate, to an extent, that
			<lb />
			the principles of Order 41 are also required to be borne in mind, while
			<lb />
			exercising appellate jurisdiction, under Section 37.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			45. The 1996 Act is, preambularly, a fallout of the United Nation&apos;s
			<lb />
			Commission on International Trade Law (UNCITRAL), adopted in
			<lb />
			1995 as the Model Law on International Commercial Arbitration. The
			<lb />
			Statement of Objects and Reasons, preceding the 1996 Act, stipulates,
			<lb />
			in paras 2 to 5 thereof, as under, in this respect:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			The United Nations Commission on International
			<lb />
			Trade Law (UNCITRAL) adopted in 1985 the Model Law on
			<lb />
			International Commercial Arbitration. The General Assembly
			<lb />
			of the United Nations has recommended that all countries
			<lb />
			give due consideration to the said Model Law, in view of the
			<lb />
			desirability of uniformity of the law of arbitral procedures and
			<lb />
			the specific needs of international commercial arbitration
			<lb />
			practise. The UNCITRAL also adopted in 1980 a set of
			<lb />
			Conciliation Rules. The General Assembly of the United
			<lb />
			Nations has recommended the use of these Rules in cases
			<lb />
			where the disputes arise in the context of international
			<lb />
			commercial relations and the parties seek amicable settlement
			<lb />
			of the disputes by recourse to conciliation. An important
			<lb />
			feature of the UNCITRAL Model Law and Rules is that they
			<lb />
			have harmonized concepts on arbitration and conciliation of
			<lb />
			different legal systems of the world and thus contains
			<lb />
			provisions which are designed for universal applications.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			3.
			<lb />
			Though the said UNCITRAL Model Law and Rules
			<lb />
			are intended to deal with International Commercial
			<lb />
			Arbitration and Conciliation, they could, with appropriate
			<lb />
			modifications, serve as a model for legislation on domestic
			<lb />
			arbitration and conciliation. The present Bill seeks to
			<lb />
			consolidate and amend the law relating to domestic
			<lb />
			arbitration, international commercial arbitration, enforcement
			<lb />
			of foreign arbitral awards and to define the law relating to
			<lb />
			conciliation, taking into account the said UNCITRAL Model
			<lb />
			Law and Rules.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			4.
			<lb />
			The main objectives of the Bill are as under:-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			a. to comprehensively cover international and
			<lb />
			commercial arbitration and conciliation as also
			<lb />
			domestic arbitration and conciliation;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			b. to make provision for an arbitral procedure which is
			<lb />
			fair, efficient and capable of meeting the needs of the
			<lb />
			specific arbitration;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			c. to provide that the arbitral tribunal gives reasons for its
			<lb />
			arbitral award;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			d. to ensure that the arbitral tribunal remains within the
			<lb />
			limits of its jurisdiction;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			e. to minimize the supervisory role of the courts in the
			<lb />
			arbitral process;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			f. to permit an arbitral tribunal to use mediation,
			<lb />
			conciliation or other procedure during the arbitral
			<lb />
			proceedings to encourage settlement of disputes;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			g. to provide that every final arbitral award is enforced in
			<lb />
			the same manner as if it were a decree of the court;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			h. to provide a settlement agreement reached by the
			<lb />
			parties as a result of conciliation proceedings will have
			<lb />
			the same status and effect as an arbitral award on
			<lb />
			agreed terms on the substance of the dispute rendered
			<lb />
			by an arbitral tribunal; and
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			i. to provide that, for purposes of enforcement of foreign
			<lb />
			awards, every arbitral award made in a country to
			<lb />
			which one of the two international Conventions
			<lb />
			relating to foreign arbitral awards to which India is a
			<lb />
			party applies, will be treated as a foreign awards.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			5.
			<lb />
			The Bill seeks to achieve the above objects.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			46. The Supreme Court has, in Chloro Controls (I) Ltd v. Severn
			<lb />
			Trent Water Purification Inc. 18 , held that the legislative intent and
			<lb />
			essence of the 1996 Act &quot;is to bring domestic as well as international
			<lb />
			commercial arbitration in consonance with the UNCITRAL Model
			<lb />
			Rules, the New York Convention and Geneva Convention&quot;. The
			<lb />
			afore-extracted passages, from the Statements of Object and Reasons
			<lb />
			of the 1996 Act has, necessarily, to guide the Court, while interpreting
			<lb />
			the provisions thereof. While on the point, it may be noted that, in
			<lb />
			Bharat Sewa Sansthan v. U. P. Electronics Corporation Ltd 19 , the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court has clearly held the &quot;main objective of the (1996)
			<lb />
			Act&quot; as being &quot;to make provision for an arbitral procedure which is
			<lb />
			fair, efficient and capable of meeting the needs of the specific
			<lb />
			arbitration and to minimise the supervisory role of courts in the
			<lb />
			arbitral process and to permit an arbitral Tribunal to use mediation,
			<lb />
			the conciliation or other procedures during the arbitral proceedings in
			<lb />
			settlement of disputes, etc.&quot;
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			47. There can be no gainsaying the proposition, therefore, that,
			<lb />
			while exercising any kind of jurisdiction, over arbitral orders, or
			<lb />
			arbitral awards, whether interim or final, or with the arbitral process
			<lb />
			itself, the Court is required to maintain an extremely circumspect
			<lb />
			approach. It is always required to be borne, in mind, that arbitration is
			<lb />
			intended to be an avenue for &quot;alternative dispute resolution&quot;, and not a
			<lb />
			means to multiply, or foster, further disputes. Where, therefore, the
			<lb />
			arbitrator resolves the dispute, that resolution is entitled to due respect
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			18 (2013) 1 SCC 641
			<lb />
			19 AIR 2007 SC 2961 : (2007) 7 SCC 737
			<lb />
			and, save and except for the reasons explicitly set out in the body of
			<lb />
			the 1996 Act, is, ordinarily, immune from judicial interference.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			48. Interestingly, while examining, in Snehadeep Structures (P)
			<lb />
			Ltd v. Maharashtra Small Scale Industries Development
			<lb />
			Corporation Ltd 20 , the scope of the expression &quot;appeal&quot; as employed
			<lb />
			in Section 7 of the Interest on Delayed Payments to Small Scale and
			<lb />
			Ancillary Undertakings Act, 1993, the Supreme Court held that , &quot;if
			<lb />
			… the meaning of &quot;appeal&quot; is ambiguous, the interpretation that
			<lb />
			advances the object and purpose of the legislation, shall be accepted.&quot;
			<lb />
			Purposive interpretation, as has been noticed in Shailesh Dhairyawan
			<lb />
			v. Mohan Balkrishna Lulla 21 and Richa Mishra v. State of
			<lb />
			Chhattisgarh 22 , has, over time, replaced the principle of &quot;plain
			<lb />
			reading&quot; as the golden rule, for interpreting statutory instruments.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			49. In my opinion, this principle has to guide, strongly, the
			<lb />
			approach of this Court, while dealing with a challenge such as the
			<lb />
			present, which is directed against an order which, at an interlocutory
			<lb />
			stage, merely directing furnishing of security, by one of the parties to
			<lb />
			the dispute. The power, of the learned Sole Arbitrator, to direct
			<lb />
			furnishing of security, is not under question; indeed, in view of sub-
			<lb />
			clause (b) of Section 17 (1) (ii) of the 1996 Act, it cannot. The
			<lb />
			arbitrator is, under the said sub-clause, entirely within his jurisdiction
			<lb />
			in securing the amount in dispute in the arbitration. Whether, in
			<lb />
			exercising such jurisdiction, the arbitrator has acted in accordance
			<lb />
			20 (2010) 3 SCC 34
			<lb />
			21 (2016) 3 SCC 619
			<lb />
			22 (2016) 4 SCC 179
			<lb />
			with law, or not, can, of course, always be questioned. While
			<lb />
			examining such a challenge, however, the Court has to be mindful of
			<lb />
			its limitations, in interfering with the decision of the arbitrator,
			<lb />
			especially a decision taken at the discretionary level, and at an
			<lb />
			interlocutory stage.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			50. One may also refer, in this context, to Section 5 of the 1996
			<lb />
			Act, which reads as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;
		</p>

		<item>
			5.
			<lb />
			Extent of judicial intervention. -Notwithstanding
			<lb />
			anything contained in any other law for the time being in
			<lb />
			force, in matters covered by this Part, no judicial authority
			<lb />
			shall intervene except where so provided in this Part.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			It is, no doubt, possible to argue that the intent, of Section 5, is to
			<lb />
			restrict judicial intervention, with arbitral proceedings, and orders
			<lb />
			passed therein, to the avenues for such interference, as provided by
			<lb />
			Part I of the 1996 Act, and not to restrict the scope of the Sections and
			<lb />
			the provisions contained in Part I. Perhaps. Section 5 remains,
			<lb />
			however, a clear pointer to the legislative intent, permeating the 1996
			<lb />
			Act, that judicial interference, with arbitral proceedings, is to be kept
			<lb />
			at a minimum. Significantly, in Venture Global Engineering v.
			<lb />
			Satyam Computer Services Ltd 23 , it was opined that the scheme of the
			<lb />
			1996 Act was &quot;such that the general provisions of Part I, including
			<lb />
			Section 5, will apply to all Chapters or Parts of the Act&quot;. In State of
			<lb />
			Kerala v. Somdatt Builders Ltd 24 , a Division Bench of the Kerala
			<lb />
			High Court held that the jurisdiction of the Court, under Section 37 of
			<lb />
			23 (2008) 4 SCC 190
			<lb />
			24 2012 (3) Arb LR 151 (Ker) (DB)
			<lb />
			the 1996 Act, was also required to be interpreted in the light of the
			<lb />
			legislative policy contained in Section 5. I entirely agree.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			51. The principle of least intervention by courts was held, in
			<lb />
			Enercon (India) Ltd v. Enercon Gmbh 25 , to be well-recognised in
			<lb />
			arbitration jurisprudence, in almost all jurisdictions. In a similar vein,
			<lb />
			earlier in point of time, the Supreme Court held, in P. Anand
			<lb />
			Gajapathi Raju v. P. V. G. Raju 26 , that Section 5 &quot;brings out clearly
			<lb />
			the object of the new Act, namely, that of encouraging resolution of
			<lb />
			disputes expeditiously and less expensively and when there is an
			<lb />
			arbitration agreement, the court&apos;s intervention should be minimal.&quot;
			<lb />
			Likewise, albeit in the context of Section 34, it was held, in
			<lb />
			McDermott International Inc. v. Burn Standard Co. Ltd 27 , thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;The 1996 Act makes provision for the supervisory role of
			<lb />
			courts, for the review of the arbitral award only to ensure
			<lb />
			fairness. Intervention of the court is envisaged in few
			<lb />
			circumstances only, like, in case of fraud or bias by the
			<lb />
			arbitrators, violation of natural justice, etc. the court cannot
			<lb />
			correct errors of the arbitrators. It can only quash the award
			<lb />
			leaving the parties free to begin the arbitration again if it is
			<lb />
			desired. So, the scheme of the provision aims at keeping the
			<lb />
			supervisory role of the court at minimum level and this can be
			<lb />
			justified as the parties to the agreement make a conscious
			<lb />
			decision to exclude the court&apos;s jurisdiction by opting for
			<lb />
			arbitration as they prefer the expediency and finality offered
			<lb />
			by it.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			Though the above exposition of the law is in the context of Section
			<lb />
			34, the principles enunciated therein embody the general philosophy
			<lb />
			underlying the 1996 Act. The italicised words, towards the
			<lb />
			25 (2014) 5 SCC 1
			<lb />
			26 (2000) 4 SCC 539
			<lb />
			27 (2006) 11 SCC 181
			<lb />
			conclusion of the paragraph, especially, would apply, with equal
			<lb />
			force, to challenges to interlocutory orders of arbitral tribunals, under
			<lb />
			Section 37, as they would, to challenges to the final award, under
			<lb />
			Section 34.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			52. Section 37 is, in a sense, a somewhat peculiar provision as,
			<lb />
			against the decision of the arbitrator, it provides for a first appeal, as
			<lb />
			well as a second appeal, to the High Court. Sub-section (1) provides
			<lb />
			for an appeal, to the High Court, from the decision of the Section 34
			<lb />
			Court, before which the final award has, in the first instance, been
			<lb />
			tested. Sub-section (2), on the other hand, provides for a first appeal,
			<lb />
			against interlocutory orders of the arbitral tribunal under Section 16
			<lb />
			or Section 17. There is, necessarily, a qualitative difference between
			<lb />
			these two challenges, though both would lie to the High Court. The
			<lb />
			challenge under Section 37(1), which is directed against a final award
			<lb />
			of the arbitrator/arbitral tribunal, is akin to a second appeal, as was
			<lb />
			observed by this Court in M.T.N.L. v. Fujitshu India Pvt Ltd 28 . The
			<lb />
			challenge under Section 37(2), on the other hand, is directed against
			<lb />
			the decision of the arbitral tribunal and has therefore, in my opinion,
			<lb />
			necessarily to conform to the discipline enforced by Section 5. It
			<lb />
			would, therefore, be improper for a Court to treat an appeal, under
			<lb />
			Section 37 (2) of the 1996 Act, as akin to an appeal under the CPC, or
			<lb />
			as understood in ordinary -or extraordinary -civil law. An appeal
			<lb />
			against an order by an arbitrator, or by an arbitral tribunal, is an
			<lb />
			appeal sui generis, and interference, by the Court, in such appeals, has
			<lb />
			to be necessarily cautious and circumspect.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			28 2015 (2) Arb LR 332 (Delhi)
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			53. This position would stand especially underscored where the
			<lb />
			order, under challenge, is discretionary in nature. Orders of
			<lb />
			arbitrators, or Arbitral Tribunals, which are amenable to appeal, under
			<lb />
			Section 37(2), have, statutorily, to have been issued either under
			<lb />
			Section 16(2) or (3) or under Section 17. Section 16(2) and 16(3),
			<lb />
			essentially, deal with rulings on the jurisdiction and authority of the
			<lb />
			arbitral tribunal, to arbitrate. Any order, passed under either, or both,
			<lb />
			of these provisions has, therefore, necessarily to partake of a purely
			<lb />
			legal character. Such an order would not, ordinarily, be discretionary
			<lb />
			in nature.
			<lb />
			Section 17(1), and applicability of Order XXXIX, CPC, thereto
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			54.
			<lb />
			As against this, orders which are appealable under Section
			<lb />
			37(2)(b) are orders granting, or refusing to grant, interim measures
			<lb />
			under Section 17. Section 17(1), for its part, reads thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;17. Interim measures ordered by arbitral tribunal. -
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(1)
			<lb />
			A party may, during the arbitral proceedings,
			<lb />
			apply to the arbitral tribunal -
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			for the appointment of a guardian for
			<lb />
			minor or person of unsound mind for the
			<lb />
			purposes of arbitral proceedings; or
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii)
			<lb />
			for an interim measure of protection in
			<lb />
			respect of any of the following matters, namely:
			<lb />
			-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a)
			<lb />
			the preservation, interim custody
			<lb />
			or sale of any goods which are the
			<lb />
			subject-matter
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			arbitration
			<lb />
			agreement;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b)
			<lb />
			securing the amount in dispute in
			<lb />
			the arbitration;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(c)
			<lb />
			the detention, preservation or
			<lb />
			inspection of any property or thing which
			<lb />
			is the subject-matter of the dispute in
			<lb />
			arbitration, or as to which any question
			<lb />
			may arise therein and authorizing for any
			<lb />
			of the aforesaid purposes any person to
			<lb />
			enter upon any land or building in the
			<lb />
			possession of any party, authorizing any
			<lb />
			samples to be taken, or any observation
			<lb />
			to be made, or experiment to be tried,
			<lb />
			which may be necessary or expedient for
			<lb />
			the purpose of obtaining full information
			<lb />
			or evidence;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(d)
			<lb />
			interim
			<lb />
			injunction
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			appointment of a receiver;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(e)
			<lb />
			such other interim measure of
			<lb />
			protection as may appear to the arbitral
			<lb />
			tribunal to be just and convenient,
			<lb />
			and the arbitral tribunal shall have the same
			<lb />
			power for making orders, as the court has for
			<lb />
			the purpose of, and in relation to, any
			<lb />
			proceedings before it.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			55. The concluding caveat, in Section 17 (1), makes it abundantly
			<lb />
			clear that the power of an arbitrator, to grant interim measures, under
			<lb />
			Section 17(1), is analogous and equivalent to the power of a Court, to
			<lb />
			pass such orders. Section 9 of the 1996 Act grants co-equal
			<lb />
			jurisdiction, worded in identical terms, on the Court, to pass interim
			<lb />
			orders, concluding with a parallel caveat, to the effect that &quot;the Court
			<lb />
			shall have the same power for making orders as it has for the purpose
			<lb />
			of, and in relation to, any proceedings before it&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			56. The scope and ambit of Section 9, especially in the light of this
			<lb />
			concluding caveat, was examined by the Supreme Court in Arvind
			<lb />
			Constructions Co. (P) Ltd v. Kalinga Mining Corporation 29 and
			<lb />
			Adhunik Steels Ltd v. Orissa Manganese and Minerals (P) Ltd 30 . In
			<lb />
			Arvind Constructions Co. (P) Ltd 29 , it was held thus (in para 15 of the
			<lb />
			report):
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;The argument that the power under Section 9 of the Act is
			<lb />
			independent of the Specific Relief Act or that the restrictions
			<lb />
			placed by the Specific Relief Act cannot control the exercise
			<lb />
			of power under Section 9 of the Act cannot prima facie be
			<lb />
			accepted.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			reliance
			<lb />
			placed
			<lb />
			on Firm
			<lb />
			Ashok
			<lb />
			Traders v. Gurumukh Das Saluja, (2004) 3 SCC 155 in that
			<lb />
			behalf does not also help much, since this Court in that case
			<lb />
			did not answer that question finally but prima facie felt that
			<lb />
			the objection based on Section 69(3) of the Partnership Act
			<lb />
			may not stand in the way of a party to an arbitration
			<lb />
			agreement moving the court under Section 9 of the Act. The
			<lb />
			power under Section 9 is conferred on the District Court. No
			<lb />
			special procedure is prescribed by the Act in that behalf. It is
			<lb />
			also clarified that the court entertaining an application under
			<lb />
			Section 9 of the Act shall have the same power for making
			<lb />
			orders as it has for the purpose and in relation to any
			<lb />
			proceedings before it. Prima facie, it appears that the general
			<lb />
			rules that governed the court while considering the grant of
			<lb />
			an interim injunction at the threshold are attracted even while
			<lb />
			dealing with an application under Section 9 of the Act. There
			<lb />
			is also the principle that when a power is conferred under a
			<lb />
			special statute and it is conferred on an ordinary court of the
			<lb />
			land, without laying down any special condition for exercise
			<lb />
			of that power, the general rules of procedure of that court
			<lb />
			would apply. The Act does not prima facie purport to keep
			<lb />
			out the provisions of the Specific Relief Act from
			<lb />
			consideration. … we may indicate that we are prima facie
			<lb />
			29 (2007) 6 SCC 798
			<lb />
			30 (2007) 7 SCC 125
			<lb />
			inclined to the view that exercise of power under Section 9 of
			<lb />
			the Act must be based on well-recognized principles
			<lb />
			governing the grant of interim injunctions and other orders of
			<lb />
			interim protection or the appointment of a Receiver.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			In Adhunik Steels Ltd 30 , P.K. Balasubramanyan, J. (who had also
			<lb />
			authored Arvind Constructions Co. (P) Ltd 29 ), after a somewhat
			<lb />
			longer and more detailed discussion, reiterated the position that &quot;it
			<lb />
			would not be correct to say that the power under Section 9 of the Act
			<lb />
			is totally independent of the well known principles governing the
			<lb />
			grant of interim injunction that generally governed the courts in this
			<lb />
			connection&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			57. The principles governing Order XXXIX of the CPC have,
			<lb />
			therefore, also to guide the Court, while granting interim protection
			<lb />
			under Section 9(1), or the arbitrator, while granting such protection
			<lb />
			under Section 17(1), of the 1996 Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			58. Applicability of Order XXXVIII Rule 5, CPC, to Section
			<lb />
			9(1)(ii)(b), and Section 17(1)(ii)(b) of the 1996 Act
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			58.1 On the applicability, to Section 9(1)(ii)(b), or Section
			<lb />
			17(1)(ii)(b), of Order XXXVIII Rule 5, CPC, reliance was placed, by
			<lb />
			Mr. Nandrajog, on the judgement of a learned Single Judge of this
			<lb />
			Court in Steel Authority of India Ltd v. AMCI PTY Ltd 31 , to contend
			<lb />
			that Order XXXVIII Rule 5 of the CPC has no applicability to
			<lb />
			31 (2011) 3 Arb LR 502
			<lb />
			proceedings under the 1996 Act, specifically to the exercise of
			<lb />
			jurisdiction under Section 17.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			58.2 Undoubtedly, Steel Authority of India Ltd 31 says so. That
			<lb />
			position has, however, altered, subsequently, with the judgement, of a
			<lb />
			Division Bench of this Court in Ajay Singh v. Kal Airways Pvt Ltd 32 ,
			<lb />
			paras 25 to 28 of which read thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;25. The first question which the court addresses is the one
			<lb />
			adverted to by the appellant, that principles underlying Order
			<lb />
			XXXVIII, Rule 5 CPC have to be kept in mind, while making
			<lb />
			an interim order, in a given case, directing security by one
			<lb />
			party. Indian Telephone Industries v. Siemens Public
			<lb />
			Communication, (2002) 5 SCC 510 is an authority of the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court, which tells the courts that though there is no
			<lb />
			textual basis in the Arbitration Act, linking it with provisions
			<lb />
			of the CPC, nevertheless, the principles underlying exercise
			<lb />
			of power by courts -in the CPC -are to be kept in mind,
			<lb />
			while making orders under Section 9. In Arvind
			<lb />
			Constructions v. Kalinga Mining Corporation (2007) 6 SCC
			<lb />
			798, the court held as follows:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;The power under Section 9 is conferred on the
			<lb />
			District Court. No special procedure is prescribed by
			<lb />
			the Act in that behalf. It is also clarified that the Court
			<lb />
			entertaining an application under Section 9 of the Act
			<lb />
			shall have the same power for making orders as it has
			<lb />
			for the purpose and in relation to any proceedings
			<lb />
			before it. Prima facie, it appears that the general rules
			<lb />
			that governed the court while considering the grant of
			<lb />
			an interim injunction at the threshold are attracted even
			<lb />
			while dealing with an application under Section 9 of
			<lb />
			the Act. There is also the principle that when a power
			<lb />
			is conferred under a special statute and it is conferred
			<lb />
			on an ordinary court of the land, without laying down
			<lb />
			any special condition for exercise of that power, the
			<lb />
			general rules of procedure of that court would apply.
			<lb />
			The Act does not prima facie purport to keep out the
			<lb />
			provisions of the Specific Relief Act from
			<lb />
			consideration. No doubt, a view that exercise of power
			<lb />
			under Section 9 of the Act is not controlled by the
			<lb />
			Specific Relief Act has been taken by the Madhya
			<lb />
			Pradesh High Court. The power under Section 9 of the
			<lb />
			Act is not controlled by Order XVIII Rule 5 of the
			<lb />
			Code of Civil Procedure is a view taken by the High
			<lb />
			Court of Bombay. But, how far these decisions are
			<lb />
			correct, requires to be considered in an appropriate
			<lb />
			case. Suffice it to say that on the basis of the
			<lb />
			submissions made in this case, we are not inclined to
			<lb />
			answer that question finally. But, we may indicate that
			<lb />
			we are prima facie inclined to the view that exercise of
			<lb />
			power under Section 9 of the Act must be based on
			<lb />
			well recognized principles governing the grant of
			<lb />
			interim injunctions and other orders of interim
			<lb />
			protection or the appointment of a receiver.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			26.
			<lb />
			Interestingly, in a previous decision, Firm Ashok
			<lb />
			Traders v. Gurumukh Das Saluja (2004) 3 SCC 155, the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court observed that:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;13. ..The Relief sought for in an application under
			<lb />
			Section 9 of the A&amp;C Act is neither in a suit nor a
			<lb />
			right arising from a contract. The right arising from the
			<lb />
			partnership deed or conferred by the Partnership Act is
			<lb />
			being enforced in the Arbitral Tribunal; the court
			<lb />
			under Section 9 is only formulating interim measures
			<lb />
			so as to protect the right under adjudication before the
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal from being frustrated…..&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			27.
			<lb />
			Though apparently, there seem to be two divergent
			<lb />
			strands of thought, in judicial thinking, this court is of the
			<lb />
			opinion that the matter is one of the weight to be given to the
			<lb />
			materials on record, a fact dependent exercise, rather than of
			<lb />
			principle. That Section 9 grants wide powers to the courts in
			<lb />
			fashioning an appropriate interim order, is apparent from its
			<lb />
			text. Nevertheless, what the authorities stress is that the
			<lb />
			exercise of such power should be principled, premised on
			<lb />
			some known guidelines -therefore, the analogy of Orders 38
			<lb />
			and 39. Equally, the court should not find itself unduly bound
			<lb />
			by the text of those provisions rather it is to follow the
			<lb />
			underlying principles. In this regard, the observations of Lord
			<lb />
			Hoffman in Films Rover International Ltd. v. Cannon Film
			<lb />
			Sales Ltd. (1986) 3 All ER 772 are fitting:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;But I think it is important in this area to distinguish
			<lb />
			between fundamental principles and what are
			<lb />
			sometimes described as &apos;guidelines&apos;, i.e. useful
			<lb />
			generalizations about the way to deal with the normal
			<lb />
			run of cases falling within a particular category. The
			<lb />
			principal dilemma about the grant of interlocutory
			<lb />
			injunctions, whether prohibitory or mandatory, is that
			<lb />
			there is by definition a risk that the court may make the
			<lb />
			&apos;wrong&apos; decision, in the sense of granting an
			<lb />
			injunction to a party who fails to establish his right at
			<lb />
			the trial (or would fail if there was a trial) or
			<lb />
			alternatively, in failing to grant an injunction to a
			<lb />
			party who succeeds (or would succeed) at trial. A
			<lb />
			fundamental principle is therefore that the court
			<lb />
			should take whichever course appears to carry the
			<lb />
			lower risk of injustice if it should turn out to have been
			<lb />
			&apos;wrong&apos; in the sense I have described. The guidelines
			<lb />
			for the grant of both kinds of interlocutory injunctions
			<lb />
			are derived from this principle.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			28.
			<lb />
			It was observed later, in the same judgment that:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;The question of substance is whether the granting of
			<lb />
			the injunction would carry that higher risk of injustice
			<lb />
			which is normally associated with the grant of a
			<lb />
			mandatory injunction. The second point is that in cases
			<lb />
			in which there can be no dispute about the use of the
			<lb />
			term &apos;mandatory&apos; to describe the injunction, the same
			<lb />
			question of substance will determine whether the case
			<lb />
			is &apos;normal&apos; and therefore within the guideline or
			<lb />
			&apos;exceptional&apos; and therefore requiring special treatment.
			<lb />
			If it appears to the court that, exceptionally, the case is
			<lb />
			one in which withholding a mandatory interlocutory
			<lb />
			injunction would in fact carry a greater risk of injustice
			<lb />
			than granting it even though the court does not feel a
			<lb />
			&apos;high degree of assurance&apos; about the plaintiff&apos;s chances
			<lb />
			of establishing his right, there cannot be any rational
			<lb />
			basis for withholding the injunction.&quot; &quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			58.3 The Special Leave Petition, preferred against Ajay Singh 32 , was
			<lb />
			dismissed, by the Supreme Court on 28 th July, 2017, albeit without
			<lb />
			going into merits, as the order was interlocutory in nature.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			58.4 Steel authority of India Ltd 31 and Ajay Singh 32 were, however,
			<lb />
			both decisions which arose under Section 17 of the 1996 Act, as it
			<lb />
			stood prior to its amendment, with effect from 23 rd October, 2015.
			<lb />
			Lanco Infratech 12 , rendered by a learned Single Judge of this Court,
			<lb />
			however, seriously doubts the applicability of Order XXXVIII Rule 5
			<lb />
			of the CPC, to cases arising under Section 17 of the 1996 Act, after its
			<lb />
			amendment with effect from 23 rd October, 2015. The controversy, in
			<lb />
			that case, arose under the pre-amended Section 17, and paras 12, 14
			<lb />
			and 35 of the report are of stellar significance, in the context of the
			<lb />
			issue of applicability of Order XXXVIII Rule 5 of the CPC. They
			<lb />
			read thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;12. The above submissions have been considered. The
			<lb />
			submissions revolve around the scope of the powers under
			<lb />
			Section 17 of the Act as it stood prior to the amendment by
			<lb />
			the Arbitration and Conciliation (Amendment) Act, 2015 with
			<lb />
			effect from 23 rd October 2015. The unamended Section 17
			<lb />
			reads thus:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;17. Interim measures ordered by arbitral
			<lb />
			tribunal. -
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(1)
			<lb />
			Unless otherwise agreed by the parties,
			<lb />
			the arbitral tribunal may, at the request of a
			<lb />
			party, order a party to take any interim measure
			<lb />
			of protection as the arbitral tribunal may
			<lb />
			consider necessary in respect of the subject-
			<lb />
			matter of the dispute.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(2)
			<lb />
			The arbitral tribunal may require a party
			<lb />
			to provide appropriate security in connection
			<lb />
			with a measure ordered under sub-section (1).&quot;
			<lb />
			*****
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			14.
			<lb />
			It will straightway be seen that while under the
			<lb />
			unamended Section 17 of the Act, there was no specific power
			<lb />
			for the AT to order interim measures to secure the amount in
			<lb />
			dispute, that power has been expressly provided under the
			<lb />
			amended Section 17(1)(ii)(b) of the Act. The other important
			<lb />
			change is in Section 17(2) which states that the interim order
			<lb />
			passed by the AT would be enforceable as if it were an order
			<lb />
			of a Court under the CPC. This makes it explicit that the
			<lb />
			purpose of these changes was to bring the powers of the AT
			<lb />
			under Section 17 of the Act on par with that of the Court
			<lb />
			under Section 9 of the Act. In the amended forms both Section
			<lb />
			9 and Section 17 read alike. This is therefore a significant
			<lb />
			change and not one, as contended by counsel for HCCL, one
			<lb />
			that is clarificatory of an implicit legal position. This
			<lb />
			distinction is necessary to be kept in mind because both
			<lb />
			parties here do not dispute that the application filed by HCCL
			<lb />
			before the AT was governed by Section 17 of the Act as it
			<lb />
			stood prior to its amendment. It is also significant that the
			<lb />
			decisions cited by both parties seek to interpret Section 17 as
			<lb />
			it stood prior to its amendment.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			*****
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			35.
			<lb />
			It is also clear from the impugned order that the AT
			<lb />
			failed to come to any conclusion even prima facie that Lanco
			<lb />
			was about to dispose of or remove whole or part of its assets
			<lb />
			from the local limits of the AT which was one of the
			<lb />
			contentions warranting exercise of power under Order
			<lb />
			XXXVIII Rule 5 CPC the underlying principle of which, as
			<lb />
			explained in the decisions examined hereinbefore, apply to
			<lb />
			Section 17 of the Act as it stood prior to the amendment with
			<lb />
			effect from 23 rd October, 2015.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			58.5 The Special Leave Petition, preferred by M/s Hindustan
			<lb />
			Construction Co. Ltd against the aforesaid judgement of the learned
			<lb />
			Single Judge in Lanco Infratech 12 was dismissed, by the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court, on 30 th January, 2017, holding that &quot;no ground for interference
			<lb />
			(was) made out&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			58.6 The resultant legal position is that, while the applicability of
			<lb />
			Order XXXVIII Rule 5, CPC, to the amended Section 17(1)(ii)(b) of
			<lb />
			the 1996 Act, may be seriously questionable, even under the pre-
			<lb />
			amended Section 17, the provisions of Order XXXVIII Rule 5 of the
			<lb />
			CPC cannot, bodily, be incorporated into the provision, though the
			<lb />
			principles governing the exercise of jurisdiction under Order
			<lb />
			XXXVIII Rule 5 are required to inform such exercise of jurisdiction.
			<lb />
			Either which way, therefore, while exercising jurisdiction under
			<lb />
			Section 17(1)(ii)(b), the arbitrator is not strictly bound by the confines
			<lb />
			of Order XXXVIII Rule 5 of the CPC, but is also proscribed from
			<lb />
			acting in a manner completely opposed thereto. A middling approach
			<lb />
			is, therefore, required, without treating Order XXXVIII Rule 5 as
			<lb />
			entirely inapplicable to Section 17(1)(ii)(b) (as Mr. Nandrajog would
			<lb />
			contend), or as applicable with all its vigour and vitality (as Mr. Nayar
			<lb />
			would contend).
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			59. Having said that, it is indisputable that the exercise of
			<lb />
			jurisdiction, by the arbitrator, under Section 17, is fundamentally
			<lb />
			discretionary in nature -as contrasted with Section 16(2) and (3).
			<lb />
			Judicial interference, with the exercise of discretionary power, is,
			<lb />
			classically, limited, and is even more circumscribed, where the
			<lb />
			authority exercising discretion is itself a judicial authority -as
			<lb />
			opposed to a purely administrative or executive functionary. (One
			<lb />
			uses the expression &quot;judicial authority&quot;, here, to denote the nature -
			<lb />
			rather than the status -of the jurisdiction exercised by the Arbitrator,
			<lb />
			it having been settled, by the Supreme Court, in M.D., Army Welfare
			<lb />
			Housing Organisation v. Sumangal Services (P) Ltd 33 , that an
			<lb />
			arbitrator is not a &quot;Court&quot;, and does not exercises judicial functions.)
			<lb />
			Discretionary orders passed by arbitral tribunals have, therefore, to be
			<lb />
			handled with kid gloves, and protected from injury by any over-
			<lb />
			zealous administration, by the court, of the law as it perceives it to be.
			<lb />
			If anything, therefore, the jurisdiction of the Court, under Section
			<lb />
			37(2)(b), is even more limited than the jurisdiction that it exercises
			<lb />
			under Section 37(2)(a) or, for that matter, under Section 34. The
			<lb />
			discretionary jurisdiction, as exercised by the arbitrator, merits
			<lb />
			interference, under Section 37(2)(b), therefore, only where such
			<lb />
			exercise is palpably arbitrary or unconscionable.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			60. This position is additionally underscored, where the order of the
			<lb />
			arbitrator is relatable to Section 17(1)(ii)(b) or (e), and directs
			<lb />
			furnishing of security. Direction, to litigating parties, to furnish
			<lb />
			security, is a purely discretionary exercise, intended to balance the
			<lb />
			equities. The scope of interference, in appeal, with a discretionary
			<lb />
			order passed by a judicial forum, stands authoritatively delineated in
			<lb />
			the following passages, from Wander Ltd v. Antox India P Ltd 34 :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;13. On a consideration of the matter, we are afraid, the
			<lb />
			appellate bench fell into error on two important propositions.
			<lb />
			The first is a misdirection in regard to the very scope and
			<lb />
			nature of the appeals before it and the limitations on the
			<lb />
			powers of the appellate court to substitute its own discretion
			<lb />
			in an appeal preferred against a discretionary order. The
			<lb />
			second pertains to the infirmities in the ratiocination as to the
			<lb />
			33 (2004) 9 SCC 619
			<lb />
			34 1990 Supp SCC 727
			<lb />
			quality of Antox&apos;s alleged user of the trademark on which the
			<lb />
			passing-off action is founded. We shall deal with these two
			<lb />
			separately.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			14.
			<lb />
			The appeals before the Division Bench were against
			<lb />
			the exercise of discretion by the Single Judge. In such
			<lb />
			appeals, the appellate court will not interfere with the exercise
			<lb />
			of discretion of the court of first instance and substitute its
			<lb />
			own discretion except where the discretion has been shown to
			<lb />
			have been exercised arbitrarily, or capriciously or perversely
			<lb />
			or where the court had ignored the settled principles of law
			<lb />
			regulating grant or refusal of interlocutory injunctions. An
			<lb />
			appeal against exercise of discretion is said to be an appeal on
			<lb />
			principle. Appellate court will not reassess the material and
			<lb />
			seek to reach a conclusion different from the one reached by
			<lb />
			the court below if the one reached by that court was
			<lb />
			reasonably possible on the material. The appellate court
			<lb />
			would normally not be justified in interfering with the
			<lb />
			exercise of discretion under appeal solely on the ground that
			<lb />
			if it had considered the matter at the trial stage it would have
			<lb />
			come to a contrary conclusion. If the discretion has been
			<lb />
			exercised by the trial court reasonably and in a judicial
			<lb />
			manner the fact
			<lb />
			that the appellate court would have taken a
			<lb />
			different view may not justify interference with the trial
			<lb />
			court&apos;s exercise of discretion. After referring to these
			<lb />
			principles Gajendragadkar, J. in Printers (Mysore) Private
			<lb />
			Ltd. v. Pothan Joseph, (1960) 3 SCR 713 : AIR 1960 SC
			<lb />
			1156:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			&quot;... These principles are well established, but as has
			<lb />
			been observed by Viscount Simon in Charles Osenton
			<lb />
			&amp; Co. v. Jhanaton, 1942 AC 130 &apos;...the law as to the
			<lb />
			reversal by a court of appeal of an order made by a
			<lb />
			judge below in the exercise of his discretion is well
			<lb />
			established, and any difficulty that arises is due only to
			<lb />
			the application of well settled principles in an
			<lb />
			individual case&apos;.&quot;
			<lb />
			The appellate judgment does not seem to defer to this
			<lb />
			principle.&quot;
			<lb />
			That this principle applies to exercise of appellate jurisdiction, over
			<lb />
			discretionary interlocutory orders, passed by arbitrators, under Section
			<lb />
			17 of the 1996 Act, has been reiterated, by this Court, in several
			<lb />
			decisions, including Bakshi Speedways v. Hindustan Petroleum
			<lb />
			Corporation 35 , EMAAR MGF Land Ltd v. Kakade British Realities
			<lb />
			Pvt Ltd 36 , Reliance Communications Ltd v. Bharti Infratel Ltd 37 ,
			<lb />
			Ascot Hotels and Resorts Pvt Ltd v. Connaught Plaza Restaurants
			<lb />
			Pvt Ltd 38 and Green Infra Wind Energy Ltd v. Regen Powertech Pvt
			<lb />
			Ltd 39 .
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			61. I proceed to apply the above principles to the facts at hand, and
			<lb />
			the rival contentions advanced by learned Senior Counsel before me.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			62. Re. Submission that the learned Sole Arbitrator exceeded his
			<lb />
			jurisdiction by granting relief in excess of that sought by the
			<lb />
			respondents
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			62.1 In order to appreciate this submission, it is necessary, in the
			<lb />
			first instance, to set out the reliefs sought by AGG, in its applications
			<lb />
			under Section 17, which stand adjudicated by the impugned order.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			62.2 The order, dated 18 th March, 2019, of the Division Bench of
			<lb />
			this Court in FAO (OS) 6/2019 and FAO (OS) 18/2019, directed that
			<lb />
			the said appeals be treated as applications under Section 17.
			<lb />
			Additionally, parties were granted liberty to file fresh applications,
			<lb />
			under Section 17, before the learned Sole Arbitrator. Acting on the
			<lb />
			liberty thus granted, AGG filed three fresh applications, under Section
			<lb />
			35 2009 (162) DLT 638
			<lb />
			36 2013 (138) DRJ 507
			<lb />
			37 2018 SCC OnLine Del 6564
			<lb />
			38 2018 (249) DRJ 329
			<lb />
			39 2018 SCC OnLine Del 8273
			<lb />
			17, before the learned Sole Arbitrator. In all, therefore, there were
			<lb />
			four applications, under Section 17, of AGG, before the learned Sole
			<lb />
			Arbitrator, i.e. FAO (OS) 18/2019 and the three fresh applications.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			62.3 The prayer clauses, in FAO (OS) 18/2019, and in the three fresh
			<lb />
			applications filed by AGG before the learned Sole Arbitrator, may be
			<lb />
			reproduced, to the extent relevant, thus:
			<lb />
			FAO (OS) 18/2019
			<lb />
			&quot;It is, therefore, most respectfully prayed that this Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Court may kindly be pleased to allow the present Appeal: -
			<lb />
			a.
			<lb />
			Set aside the Impugned order dated November
			<lb />
			16, 2018 passed in IA No 3238 of 2018 th in CS (OS)
			<lb />
			No. 100 of 2018 to the extent that the Appellants were
			<lb />
			restrained
			<lb />
			from
			<lb />
			giving
			<lb />
			effect
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			notices/communications dated February 16, 2018,
			<lb />
			February 12, 2018, February 22, 2018 and February
			<lb />
			23, 2018;
			<lb />
			b.
			<lb />
			Fix a date of meeting of shareholders of Renu
			<lb />
			Promoters Pvt. Ltd. (Respondent No. 12) in pursuance
			<lb />
			of and as contemplated in the notice/communication
			<lb />
			dated February 16, 2018 in accordance with the
			<lb />
			provisions of the Companies Act, 2013.&quot;
			<lb />
			The First Section 17 application
			<lb />
			&quot;It is, therefore, most respectfully prayed that Ld. Arbitrator
			<lb />
			may kindly be pleased to allow the present Application and: -
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			i.
			<lb />
			Direct Claimant Nos. 1, 2 and 12 to maintain
			<lb />
			status quo in relation to its immovable assets and not
			<lb />
			to create any charge, encumbrance and/or third-party
			<lb />
			rights in relation to the said immovable assets.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			ii.
			<lb />
			Direct Claimant No 1, 2 and 12 to maintain
			<lb />
			status quo in relation to the shareholding of Claimant
			<lb />
			No. 12.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			iii.
			<lb />
			Restrained the Claimant Nos. 1 and 2 from
			<lb />
			taking any decision in the capacity of being the
			<lb />
			Director during the pendency of the present
			<lb />
			proceedings and further, restrained the Claimant No. 1
			<lb />
			and 2 from interfering in the day to day operations and
			<lb />
			working of the Claimant No. 12.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			iv.
			<lb />
			Direct the Claimant Nos. 1 and 2 not to utilize
			<lb />
			any money received on behalf of the Claimant No.
			<lb />
			12.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Claimant No. 1 and Claimant No. 2 were Dinesh Gupta and
			<lb />
			Shreyansh Gupta, and Claimant No. 12 was Renu Promoters.)
			<lb />
			The Second Section 17 application
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;It is, therefore, most respectfully prayed that Ld. Arbitrator
			<lb />
			may kindly be pleased to allow the present Application and: -
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			a.
			<lb />
			Restrain the Claimant No. 2 from alienating
			<lb />
			equity shares held in C.R. Farms Pvt. Ltd. having its
			<lb />
			registered office at C-43, LGF Jangpura Extension
			<lb />
			New Delhi South Delhi-110014, by the Claimant No.
			<lb />
			2, until the Rs. 19,55,00,000 (Rupees Nineteen Crores
			<lb />
			and Fifty-five Lakhs only) is paid by the Claimant No.
			<lb />
			2 to the Counter-Claimant Nos. 2 and 5;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			b.
			<lb />
			Restrain Claimant No. 2 from creating any
			<lb />
			charge, encumbrance or any other third-party rights
			<lb />
			over the above-mentioned equity shares held in C.R.
			<lb />
			Farms Pvt. Ltd. having its registered office at C-43,
			<lb />
			LGF Jangpura Extension New Delhi South Delhi-
			<lb />
			110014, by the Claimant No. 2 until the Rs.
			<lb />
			19,55,00,000 (Rupees Nineteen Crores and Fifty-five
			<lb />
			Lakhs only) is paid by the Claimant No. 2 to the
			<lb />
			Counter-Claimant Nos. 2 and 5;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			c.
			<lb />
			Restrain Claimant No. 2 from enjoying any
			<lb />
			benefit(s) including exercising of voting rights
			<lb />
			accruing to the Claimant No. 2 out of the shares held
			<lb />
			in C. R. Farms Pvt. Ltd. until the Rs. 19,55,00,000
			<lb />
			(Rupees Nineteen Crores and Fifty-five Lakhs only) is
			<lb />
			paid by the Claimant No. 2 to the Counter-Claimant
			<lb />
			Nos. 2 and 5.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			d.
			<lb />
			Restrain
			<lb />
			Claimant
			<lb />
			No.
			<lb />
			2
			<lb />
			from
			<lb />
			transferring/liquidating any mutual fund(s) which has
			<lb />
			been acquired from the fraudulently transferred
			<lb />
			amount until the Rs. 19,55,00,000 (Rupees Nineteen
			<lb />
			Crores and Fifty-five Lakhs only) is paid by the
			<lb />
			Claimant No. 2 to the Counter-Claimant Nos. 2 and 5.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Claimant No. 2 and 5 were Shreyansh Gupta and Dinesh
			<lb />
			Gupta, and Counter-Claimants Nos. 2 and 5 were Anand
			<lb />
			Gupta and M/s. Anand Gupta HUF, respectively.)
			<lb />
			The Third Section 17 application
			<lb />
			&quot;It is therefore, most respectfully prayed that the Ld.
			<lb />
			Arbitrator may be pleased to: -
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			a.
			<lb />
			Restrain the Claimants from alienating the
			<lb />
			26,86,190 (Twenty-Six Lakh Eighty-Six Thousand
			<lb />
			One Hundred And Ninety) equity shares of BDR,
			<lb />
			which
			<lb />
			were
			<lb />
			held
			<lb />
			by
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Counter-
			<lb />
			Claimants/Respondent Nos. 1 to 4 and were illegally
			<lb />
			and fraudulently transferred by the Claimant Nos. 1
			<lb />
			and 2, in their favor, until the consideration of Rs.
			<lb />
			53,72,38,000/-(Rupees Fifty-Three Crores Seventy
			<lb />
			Two Lakhs Thirty Eight Thousand only) is paid by the
			<lb />
			Claimant Nos. 1 and 2 to the Counter-
			<lb />
			Claimants/Respondent Nos. 1 to 4, for such transfer of
			<lb />
			shares, as explained above;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			b.
			<lb />
			Restrain the Claimants from creating any
			<lb />
			charge, encumbrance or any other third-party rights
			<lb />
			over the above mentioned 26,86,190 (Twenty-Six
			<lb />
			Lakh Eighty-Six Thousand One Hundred And Ninety)
			<lb />
			equity shares of BDR, until the consideration of Rs.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			53,72,38,000/-(Rupees Fifty-Three Crores Seventy
			<lb />
			Two Lakhs Thirty Eight Thousand only), for transfer
			<lb />
			of the said shares has been paid by the Claimant Nos. 1
			<lb />
			and 2 to the Counter-Claimants/Respondents Nos. 1 to
			<lb />
			4.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			62.4 On these three applications, the learned Sole Arbitrator has
			<lb />
			ruled, thus (in para 3.27 and 3.28 of the impugned Order):
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;3.27 Having regard to the aforesaid, and when the
			<lb />
			companies have gone to DGG, it may not be appropriate to
			<lb />
			restrain Claimants 1, 2 and 12 from dealing with the
			<lb />
			properties of BDR and Nishit. The two companies are in the
			<lb />
			business of real estate and directing the companies to
			<lb />
			maintain status quo in respect of immovable assets would
			<lb />
			amount to stifling their business. Therefore, these immovable
			<lb />
			properties which are stock-in-trade of the two companies,
			<lb />
			cannot be subject to such restrictions. At the same time,
			<lb />
			Claimants 1, 2 and 12 are directed to maintain status quo in
			<lb />
			respect of those immovable assets which are the capital assets
			<lb />
			of the two companies and do not form part of stock-in-trade.
			<lb />
			Relief only to this extent can be given in this application.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			3.28 In the other two applications filed by members of
			<lb />
			AGG, they are seeking restitution of the amounts which they
			<lb />
			have remitted. For the reasons given above, such a relief
			<lb />
			cannot be granted at this stage as it needs determination as to
			<lb />
			whether the payments were made by AGG of DGG
			<lb />
			voluntarily pursuant to the Family Settlements or they are
			<lb />
			fraudulently secured by DGG as contended by AGG in these
			<lb />
			applications. At the same time, in order to secure the interest
			<lb />
			of the AGG, in the event AGG ultimately succeeds, it would
			<lb />
			be appropriate to direct DGG to furnish suitable equivalent to
			<lb />
			the sums involved, to the Tribunal.&quot;
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			62.5 The notices, dated 12 th February, 2018, 16 th February, 2018,
			<lb />
			22 nd February, 2018 and 23 rd February, 2018, issued by AGG/its
			<lb />
			members, alleged (i) misconduct, on the part of Dinesh Gupta and
			<lb />
			Shreyansh Gupta, in the affairs of BDR, (ii) mismanagement in the
			<lb />
			affairs of Renu Promoters, (iii) fraudulent transfer of shares, held by
			<lb />
			AGG in BDR, to the DEMAT Account of DGG, and (iv) fraudulent
			<lb />
			misappropriation, by DGG, of the amounts earned by liquidation of
			<lb />
			Mutual Funds, held by AGG. Premised on these allegations, AGG
			<lb />
			sought, vide the said notices/communications, (i) repayment, by DGG,
			<lb />
			of the loans advanced by AGG and lying in the accounts of BDR,
			<lb />
			totaling ₹ 81,31,725/-, (ii) convening of an EGM of Renu Promoters,
			<lb />
			to remove Dinesh Gupta and Shivani Gupta from the Directorship of
			<lb />
			the said Company, (iii) repayment, to AGG, of ₹ 19,55,00,000/-,
			<lb />
			earned by liquidation of the Mutual Funds held by AGG and,
			<lb />
			allegedly, fraudulently misappropriated by Dinesh Gupta and
			<lb />
			Shreyans Gupta and (iv) payment, by DGG, of ₹ 53,72,38,000/-, as
			<lb />
			the price for 26,86,190 equity shares of BDR, held by AGG/its
			<lb />
			members and, allegedly, fraudulently transferred by DGG to its
			<lb />
			DEMAT Account. The response of DGG, to these claims, was that
			<lb />
			the shares, held in BDR by AGG, as well as the monies earned by
			<lb />
			liquidation of the Mutual Funds held by AGG, had, voluntarily and
			<lb />
			without consideration, being transferred, and gifted, by AGG to DGG,
			<lb />
			as sequelae to the Family Settlements dated 2 nd December, 2017 and
			<lb />
			9 th December, 2017. Mr. Nandrajog, representing AGG, emphatically
			<lb />
			contended that it was preposterous to imagine that AGG would, willy-
			<lb />
			nilly and without any consideration whatsoever, relinquish such huge
			<lb />
			amounts on investments, in favor of DGG. He also pointed out that
			<lb />
			AGG was, in fact, not even a party to the Family Settlements.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			62.6 The learned Single Judge had, vide his order dated 16 th
			<lb />
			November, 2018, stayed the operation of the aforesaid notices, dated
			<lb />
			12 th February, 2018, 16 th February, 2018, 22 nd February, 2018 and 23 rd
			<lb />
			February, 2018, issued by AGG. AGG had, in FAO (OS) 18/2019,
			<lb />
			challenged the said order of stay. FAO (OS) 18/2019 was converted
			<lb />
			into an application under Section 17 of the 1996 Act, to be decided by
			<lb />
			the learned Sole Arbitrator. The learned Sole Arbitrator was,
			<lb />
			therefore, seized the of the issue of whether to continue the interim
			<lb />
			order, dated 16 th November, 2018, of the learned Single Judge,
			<lb />
			thereby continuing the injunction against operation of the notices
			<lb />
			dated 12 th February, 2018, 16 February, 2018, 22 nd February, 2018
			<lb />
			and 23 rd February, 2018, or vacate the injunctions, as sought by AGG.
			<lb />
			The learned Sole Arbitrator chose to continue the said orders, thereby
			<lb />
			rendering the notices, as well as the actions proposed therein, by
			<lb />
			AGG, inoperative during the currency of the arbitral proceedings.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			62.7 AGG, in its first Section 17 application, alleged
			<lb />
			mismanagement, by Dinesh Gupta and Shreyansh Gupta, of the affairs
			<lb />
			of Renu Promoters and, therefore, sought that they be directed to
			<lb />
			maintain status quo, in relation to the immovable assets of Renu
			<lb />
			promoters and its shareholdings, and be restrained from taking any
			<lb />
			decision, in their capacity as Directors in Renu Promoters. The
			<lb />
			second Section 17 application alleged illegal acquisition of the share
			<lb />
			capital of C.R. Farms, by DGG, using the ₹ 19.55 crores received by
			<lb />
			liquidation of the Mutual Funds held by AGG. The third Section 17
			<lb />
			application, similarly, alleged illegal misappropriation, by DGG, of
			<lb />
			26,86,190 equity shares of BDR, and consequent liability, by DGG,
			<lb />
			towards AGG, of ₹ 53,72,38,000/-. AGG, therefore, sought a
			<lb />
			restraint, against DGG, from alienating the equity shares in BDR, held
			<lb />
			by AGG and allegedly misappropriated by DGG, as well as payment
			<lb />
			of the amount of ₹ 53,72,38,000/-, accompanied by an order of
			<lb />
			restraint, against DGG, from alienating the aforesaid 26,86,190 equity
			<lb />
			shares of BDR.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			62.8 The learned Sole Arbitrator did not grant any of the reliefs, as
			<lb />
			sought by AGG, opining that, as DGG was engaged in the real estate
			<lb />
			business, grant of the said reliefs would result in severe financial
			<lb />
			hardship to it. No restraint, on DGG dealing with the affairs of any of
			<lb />
			these Companies, was, therefore, imposed by the learned Sole
			<lb />
			Arbitrator. Neither was any direction issued, to pay, or repay, any
			<lb />
			amount to AGG, as sought by it. All that the learned Sole Arbitrator
			<lb />
			did, in the circumstances, was, having rejected the prayers of AGG,
			<lb />
			and continued the interlocutory injunction, on the notices issued by
			<lb />
			AGG, as granted by the learned Single Judge in his order dated 16 th
			<lb />
			November, 2018, to secure the claim of AGG, directed DGG to
			<lb />
			furnish Bank Guarantee for the said amount.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			62.9 There is substance in the submission, of Mr. Nandrajog, that the
			<lb />
			concluding sentence, in para 3.28 of the impugned Order dated 18 th
			<lb />
			February, 2020, cannot be torn out of its context, and subjected to
			<lb />
			independent microscopic analysis. As is correctly pointed out, the
			<lb />
			learned Sole Arbitrator did not decide, by the said Order, a single
			<lb />
			application, or even a group of applications filed by AGG under
			<lb />
			Section 17, alone, but disposed of all the applications, under Section
			<lb />
			17, pending before him, whether filed by AGG, DGG or RGG. The
			<lb />
			rationale and raison d&apos;etre, for the decision of the learned Sole
			<lb />
			Arbitrator has, therefore, to be discerned by a holistic appreciation of
			<lb />
			the impugned Order, and not by an isolated, or insulated, reading of
			<lb />
			the last sentence in para 3.28, with which DGG claims to be
			<lb />
			aggrieved. It is clear that the learned Sole Arbitrator has not directed
			<lb />
			furnishing of security, equivalent to the disputed amount, as his mere
			<lb />
			ipse dixit, but has arrived at the said decision by a careful process of
			<lb />
			ratiocination, keeping the competing interests of the claims of the
			<lb />
			claimants and the respondents, as well as their legitimate business
			<lb />
			concerns and considerations, in mind.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			62.10 The discussion, hereinabove, has already made it apparent that
			<lb />
			the principles behind Orders XXXVIII and XXXIX of the CPC are
			<lb />
			required to guide the exercise of jurisdiction under Section 9, or
			<lb />
			Section 17 of the 1996 Act, though the provisions themselves are not
			<lb />
			to be regarded as having been bodily incorporated into Sections 9 or
			<lb />
			17. Ultimately, the prevailing consideration, applying the law laid
			<lb />
			down in Ajay Singh 32 is the doing of complete and substantial justice
			<lb />
			between the parties. Where it appears, on the face of it, that the
			<lb />
			impugned direction is loaded in favor of one party and that, therefore,
			<lb />
			the direction cannot be sustained as balancing the equities between the
			<lb />
			litigants before the Arbitral Tribunal, interference on the other hand,
			<lb />
			the Court may legitimately interfere therewith. Where, however, the
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal has balanced the equities, given the fact that the
			<lb />
			jurisdiction, conferred on the Tribunal by Section 17 is fundamentally
			<lb />
			discretionary in nature, the Court has, necessarily, to be slow to
			<lb />
			interfere, lest the autonomy of the arbitral process be imperiled. In
			<lb />
			my view, the restraint, to be exercised by Courts in interfering with
			<lb />
			the decision of the arbitrator, has to extend to not seeking to
			<lb />
			substitute, for the exercise of discretion by the arbitrator, what may
			<lb />
			seem, to the Court, to be a &quot;more appropriate&quot; manner of such
			<lb />
			exercise. In other words, even if the Court were to feel that the
			<lb />
			equities could have been better balanced, by some arrangement other
			<lb />
			than that which has appealed to the discretion of the Arbitral Tribunal,
			<lb />
			that would not constitute a legitimate basis, for interfering with the
			<lb />
			exercise of such
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			62.11 The impugned Order of the learned Sole Arbitrator does not
			<lb />
			grant any interlocutory mandatory injunction. Nor has the learned
			<lb />
			Sole Arbitrator secured, stricto sensu, the amount, or property, in
			<lb />
			dispute in the arbitral proceedings, by directing deposit, thereof, by
			<lb />
			the appellant/DGG. He has merely directed furnishing of a Bank
			<lb />
			Guarantee, after an examination of the competing stands of the parties
			<lb />
			before him, to ensure that the balancing claims are secured. Directing
			<lb />
			securing of the amount involved in the arbitration, is a power
			<lb />
			statutorily invested in the learned Sole Arbitrator, by Section
			<lb />
			17(1)(ii)(b). No excess of jurisdiction can, therefore, be imputed to
			<lb />
			the learned Sole Arbitrator, in directing furnishing of security by
			<lb />
			DGG. No want of proper application of mind can be imputed to the
			<lb />
			learned Sole Arbitrator, in so directing. The submission, of Mr.
			<lb />
			Nayar, that, in so directing, the learned Sole Arbitrator has granted
			<lb />
			relief in excess of that sought by AGG is also, in the facts, clearly
			<lb />
			misguided, as the impugned direction has been issued after balancing
			<lb />
			the rival claims of both parties.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			62.12 The judgements, on which Mr. Nayar sought to place reliance,
			<lb />
			to support his submission that the learned Sole Arbitrator had erred in
			<lb />
			awarding relief in excess of that sought by AGG, do not really
			<lb />
			advance his case. Tata Advanced Systems Ltd 7 did not notice the
			<lb />
			judgement of the Division Bench of this Court in Ajay Singh 32 ;
			<lb />
			besides, there was no application, under Section 17, before the
			<lb />
			arbitrator in that case, and there is a specific finding, by the learned
			<lb />
			Single Judge, to the effect that the direction, for furnishing of Bank
			<lb />
			Guarantee, was not preceded by any reasoning. Captain Guman
			<lb />
			Singh 8 , too, does not help Mr. Nayar, as it merely reiterates the
			<lb />
			principle that a Court cannot grant relief, not sought by the parties
			<lb />
			before it. In the present case, as I have observed, the learned Sole
			<lb />
			Arbitrator was well within his jurisdiction in directing DGG to furnish
			<lb />
			security, of the amount in dispute. Besides, the direction to furnish
			<lb />
			security was an attempt to balance the equities, rejecting the greater
			<lb />
			relief, sought by AGG. The facts in the present case, therefore, are
			<lb />
			peculiar to that extent, and cannot be analogised to those in Captain
			<lb />
			Guman Singh 8 . NHPC Ltd 9 involved a situation in which the Arbitral
			<lb />
			Tribunal was found to have granted an interim measure of protection,
			<lb />
			travelling beyond the confines of the subject matter of the dispute
			<lb />
			before it. In the present case, it has not even been contended, by
			<lb />
			DGG, that the amount, in respect of which Bank Guarantee has been
			<lb />
			directed to be furnished by the learned Sole Arbitrator, was not the
			<lb />
			subject matter of the dispute before him.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			63. Re. Submission that, having found that a prima facie case
			<lb />
			existed in favour of DGG, the learned Sole Arbitrator could not have
			<lb />
			granted interim relief to AGG, by directing furnishing of security by
			<lb />
			DGG:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			63.1 Mr. Nayar relies on the observation, in para 3.26 of the
			<lb />
			impugned Order, that DGG has made out a prima facie case. The
			<lb />
			reliance is, in my opinion, out of place. Following on the said
			<lb />
			observation, the learned Sole Arbitrator proceeded to reject the prayer,
			<lb />
			of AGG, for a direction, to DGG not to deal with the properties of
			<lb />
			BDR and Nishit, limiting the relief, in that regard, to maintenance of
			<lb />
			status quo in relation to immovable assets constituting the capital
			<lb />
			assets of the said two companies. The learned Sole Arbitrator,
			<lb />
			thereby, acted on the basis of his finding that DGG had made out a
			<lb />
			prima facie case. The direction, to DGG, to furnish security, for the
			<lb />
			amount in dispute in the arbitral proceedings, does not militate, in any
			<lb />
			manner, against the said finding. At the cost of repetition, it must be
			<lb />
			emphasised that the circumstances, and rationale, behind the said
			<lb />
			direction, are required to be appreciated. Para-3.28 of the impugned
			<lb />
			Order, though brief, is sufficiently evocative in that regard. The
			<lb />
			learned Sole Arbitrator has, initially, noted that, in the Section 17
			<lb />
			applications filed by it, AGG had sought restitution of the amounts
			<lb />
			remitted by it -which, according to AGG, were unlawfully and
			<lb />
			illegally appropriated, by DGG, into its accounts. The learned Sole
			<lb />
			Arbitrator, thereafter, goes on to observe that, &quot;for the reasons given
			<lb />
			above&quot;, such a relief could not be granted at that stage. The
			<lb />
			&quot;reasons&quot;, to which the learned Sole Arbitrator refers, clearly
			<lb />
			encompass the entire recital prior to the said decision, in the course of
			<lb />
			which the learned Sole Arbitrator has examined, in detail, the facts of
			<lb />
			the case, and has comprehensively analysed the competing equities,
			<lb />
			and the claims of the parties before him. The dispute was still at large
			<lb />
			before the learned Sole Arbitrator, and it would have been entirely
			<lb />
			inappropriate, for the learned Sole Arbitrator, at that stage, to opine,
			<lb />
			one way or the other, thereon, with any modicum of finality. The
			<lb />
			learned Sole Arbitrator, therefore, correctly observes that it needed
			<lb />
			determination &quot;as to whether the payments were made by AGG (to)
			<lb />
			DGG voluntarily pursuant to the Family Settlements or they are
			<lb />
			fraudulently secured by DGG as contended by AGG in these
			<lb />
			applications&quot;. Even so, while rejecting the relief sought by AGG, the
			<lb />
			learned Sole Arbitrator has, acting within the confines of the
			<lb />
			jurisdiction vested in him by Section 17(1)(ii)(b), deemed it
			<lb />
			appropriate to secure the amount in dispute.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			63.2 Even on facts, the learned Sole Arbitrator was justified in so
			<lb />
			directing. The impugned Order does contain factual justification for
			<lb />
			the direction. The allegation, of AGG, was that their shares, are held
			<lb />
			by it in BDR, and the monies realised by liquidation of the Mutual
			<lb />
			Funds, which undisputedly belongs to AGG, had fraudulently been
			<lb />
			appropriated, by DGG, into its accounts. DGG does not contend,
			<lb />
			either before the learned Sole Arbitrator, or before this Court, that
			<lb />
			there existed any written document, evidencing intention, on the part
			<lb />
			of AGG, to relinquish, gratis, the entire amount of ₹ 19.55 crores,
			<lb />
			earned by liquidation of the Mutual Funds, or the 26,86,190 shares of
			<lb />
			BDR, which, in the price of ₹ 53,72,38,000/-. In the absence of any
			<lb />
			such written document, or registered Gift Deed, the submission of
			<lb />
			AGG, that these amounts had illegally been appropriated, by DGG,
			<lb />
			i.e. by Dinesh Gupta and Shreyansh Gupta, to enrich itself,
			<lb />
			undoubtedly deserves consideration. It certainly cannot be regarded
			<lb />
			as moonshine. If, therefore, the learned Sole Arbitrator deemed it
			<lb />
			appropriate to secure the amount in question, that direction adequately
			<lb />
			balanced the rival claims. No injunction, as sought by AGG against
			<lb />
			DGG, was granted. Neither was any direction issued, to DGG, not to
			<lb />
			deal with the finances of Renu Promoters, C.R. Farms or BDR. No
			<lb />
			direction, to secure the amounts credited to the accounts of DGG,
			<lb />
			without any consideration having been paid to AGG therefor, was
			<lb />
			issued. In the circumstances, I am of the opinion that DGG really has
			<lb />
			no cause to complain against the direction to furnish security, which,
			<lb />
			as the learned Sole Arbitrator himself observes, was &quot;in order to
			<lb />
			secure the interest of AGG, in the event AGG ultimately succeeds&quot;.
			<lb />
			This is precisely what Section 17(1)(ii)(b) contemplates.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			63.3 The amounts/shares in question having shifted base, from the
			<lb />
			accounts of AGG to those of DGG, without a farthing by way of
			<lb />
			consideration, and with no written document, evidencing intent, on the
			<lb />
			part of AGG, to such transfer gratis, no exception can be taken to the
			<lb />
			decision, of the learned Sole Arbitrator, to secure the amounts, to
			<lb />
			protect the interests of AGG and, thereby, balance the equities.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			64. Re. Order XXXVIII Rule 5, CPC
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			64.1 This judgement has, adequately, dealt with Order XXXVIII
			<lb />
			Rule 5, CPC, in the backdrop of the impugned direction, hereinabove.
			<lb />
			Mr. Nayar has, however, placed reliance on several decisions, and, in
			<lb />
			fairness to him, it would be appropriate to examine the import thereof.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			64.2 State Bank of India v. Ericsson India Pvt Ltd 10 is a short order,
			<lb />
			of the Supreme Court, which dealt with the challenge to the direction,
			<lb />
			of the Arbitral Tribunal, restraining the claimant&apos;s from alienating,
			<lb />
			encumbering or transferring its assets without permission of the
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal. As such, the order in question was injunctive in
			<lb />
			nature, unlike the present case, where injunction has specifically been
			<lb />
			refused. This, even by itself, the said decision entirely
			<lb />
			inapplicable to the facts of this case. It is further observed, in the said
			<lb />
			order, that the Arbitral Tribunal merely cited balance of convenience
			<lb />
			and irreparable injury, as a ground for the injunction. Further, the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court observes that &quot;the Arbitral Tribunal has no jurisdiction
			<lb />
			to affect the rights and remedies of the third party secured creditors in
			<lb />
			the course of determining disputes pending before it&quot;, as the claim of
			<lb />
			the appellants, before the Supreme Court, was that they were not even
			<lb />
			parties before the arbitrator. The order does not disclose that any
			<lb />
			direction, furnishing security, had been passed by the Arbitral
			<lb />
			Tribunal in that case. As such, the reliance, by Mr. Nayar, on the
			<lb />
			observation, in the concluding para 5 of the order, that the decision of
			<lb />
			the Arbitral Tribunal &quot;does not comply with the mandate of Rules 5
			<lb />
			and 10 of Order XXXVIII CPC&quot;, torn out of context, is completely
			<lb />
			misplaced.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			64.3 In C. V. Rao 11 , the Division Bench of this Court was, again,
			<lb />
			dealing with an injunctive direction, by the learned Single Judge,
			<lb />
			under Section 9, restraining the appellant from dealing with its assets.
			<lb />
			The learned Single Judge restrained the appellants from &quot;availing any
			<lb />
			additional debt without the specific consent of the respondent No. 1
			<lb />
			and also (restrained) them from selling/transferring/alienating their
			<lb />
			interest in any of the properties&quot; (from para 47 of the report). At the
			<lb />
			cost of repetition, no such injunction has been in the present
			<lb />
			case; rather, the learned Sole Arbitrator has specifically rejected the
			<lb />
			prayer for such injunction, as advanced by AGG.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			64.4 The Division Bench noted that the learned Single Judge had, in
			<lb />
			granting an injunction, proceeded on &quot;the prima facie satisfaction that
			<lb />
			the respondent No. 1 is entitled to realise the put consideration&quot;. In
			<lb />
			this context, it was held, in para 55 of the report, that &quot;even if a prima
			<lb />
			facie case is made out by the respondent No. 1 as to the claim for put
			<lb />
			amount, the same will not entitle them to seek an interim measure of
			<lb />
			protection by restraining the appellants from dealing with their assets
			<lb />
			unless it is also established that the appellants are intending to defeat
			<lb />
			the right of the respondent No. 1 to enforce the arbitral award&quot;. In
			<lb />
			these circumstances, the Division Bench opined that the learned
			<lb />
			Single Judge erred in issuing orders of prohibitory injunction. The
			<lb />
			order of the learned Single Judge, which was under challenge before
			<lb />
			the Division Bench in C. V. Rao 11 , and the impugned direction, as
			<lb />
			issued by the learned Sole Arbitrator are, therefore, as alike as chalk
			<lb />
			and cheese.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			64.5 Before parting with the point, I deem it appropriate to observe
			<lb />
			that reliance, in a case such as the present, with precedents dealing
			<lb />
			with orders of interlocutory prohibitory injunctions, would be entirely
			<lb />
			misguided. Interim prohibitory injunctions, as a category of relief, are
			<lb />
			a specie sui generis. They follow a strict regimen, chalked out, by the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court, in a series of authorities, including Deoraj v. State of
			<lb />
			Maharashtra 40 , Dorab Cawasji Warden v. Coomi Sorab Warden 41
			<lb />
			and Hammad Ahmed v. Abdul Majeed 42 . As the present dispute does
			<lb />
			not involve any order of prohibitory injunction, I do not deem it
			<lb />
			necessary to burden this judgement with the law on the point; suffice
			<lb />
			it to state that judgements, involving challenges to orders of interim
			<lb />
			prohibitory injunction, whether under Section 17, or under Section 9,
			<lb />
			of the 1996 Act, may not be of much relevance, while examining a
			<lb />
			challenge to an order directing furnishing of security by way of Bank
			<lb />
			Guarantee.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			65.
			<lb />
			Lanco Infratech 12 is completely inapplicable, as it did with the
			<lb />
			pre-amended Section 17. In fact, the learned Single Judge of this
			<lb />
			Court, while deciding the petition, has clarified, or more than one
			<lb />
			point, that he was adjudicating the matter in the context of the pre-
			<lb />
			amended Section 17, and that &quot;the underlying principle&quot; behind Order
			<lb />
			XXXVIII Rule 5 of the CPC &quot;apply to Section 17 of the Act as it
			<lb />
			stood prior to the amendment with effect from 23 rd October, 2015&quot;. It
			<lb />
			has also been observed, in the said decision, that &quot;while under the
			<lb />
			unamended Section 17 of the Act, there was no specific power for the
			<lb />
			AT to order interim measures to secure the amount in dispute, that
			<lb />
			power has been expressly provided under the amended Section
			<lb />
			17(1)(ii)(b) of the Act&quot;. The amendment of Section 17, w.e.f. 23 rd
			<lb />
			October, 2015, it was observed, was intended &quot;to bring the powers of
			<lb />
			the AT under Section 17 of the Act on par with that of the Court under
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			40 (2004) 4 SCC 697
			<lb />
			41 (1990) 2 SCC 117
			<lb />
			42 (2019) 14 SCC 1
			<lb />
			Section 9 of the Act&quot;. This change, held the learned Single Judge,
			<lb />
			was &quot;significant&quot;, and not merely &quot;clarificatory of an implicit legal
			<lb />
			position&quot;. This judgement, therefore, rather than supporting the
			<lb />
			petitioner, would throw up the issue of whether, in respect of arbitral
			<lb />
			proceedings which were governed by the amended Section 17, Order
			<lb />
			XXXVIII Rule 5 of the CPC would apply at all.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			66. Goodwill Non-Woven (P) Ltd 13 arose, not under Section 17, but
			<lb />
			under Section 9 of the 1996 Act. Pre-arbitral interim directions were
			<lb />
			sought, and para-56 of the judgement reveals that the primary ground,
			<lb />
			urged by the petitioner (in that case) was that, in view of the COVID-
			<lb />
			2019 pandemic, it was unable to meet the timelines for invoking
			<lb />
			arbitration, and apprehended that, in the interregnum, the respondent
			<lb />
			would attempt to obstruct satisfaction of a decree which might be
			<lb />
			awarded in the petitioner&apos;s favour. No doubt, there is an observation,
			<lb />
			in para-55 of the judgement, that, &quot;for grant of the relief as prayed for
			<lb />
			by the petitioner, the petitioner has to show that; (a) it has a prima
			<lb />
			facie case and balance of convenience in its favour and shall succeed
			<lb />
			in the arbitration proceedings and (b) that the respondent is acting in a
			<lb />
			manner as to defeat the realisation of the future award that may
			<lb />
			ultimately be passed&quot;. Besides the fact that the said decision does not
			<lb />
			consider Lanco Infratech 12 , or the difference, if any, which the
			<lb />
			amendment to Section 17, would make to the applicability of Order
			<lb />
			XXXVIII Rule 5, CPC, thereto (no such case having, apparently, been
			<lb />
			urged before the learned Single Judge, before whom Lanco
			<lb />
			Infratech 12 was not cited by either party), the facts, before the learned
			<lb />
			Single Judge in that case are so markedly different from those in the
			<lb />
			present, as to render the decision in Goodwill Non-Woven (P) Ltd 13
			<lb />
			an extremely unsafe precedent, while examining the present
			<lb />
			controversy.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			67. Enunciations of the law, in judicial precedents, are not to be
			<lb />
			equated with the Ten Commandments handed down to Moses, or
			<lb />
			even, on a more terrestrial note, the theorems of Euclid, but have to be
			<lb />
			understood in the backdrop of the fact-situation which presented itself
			<lb />
			before the Court, and the precise controversy, with which the Court
			<lb />
			was seized. 43 In the present case, no parallel, whatsoever, can be
			<lb />
			drawn with the facts which presented themselves before this Court in
			<lb />
			Goodwill Non-Woven (P) Ltd 13 . Here, the precise case of AGG was
			<lb />
			that DGG had, in a fraudulent manner, misappropriated, to its own
			<lb />
			unjust advantage, ₹ 19.55 crores, resulting from liquidation of the
			<lb />
			Mutual Funds of AGG, as well as 26,86,190 with the shares of BDR,
			<lb />
			valued at ₹ 53,72,38,000/-. As such, the allegation of AGG was that
			<lb />
			DGG had not only failed to abide by the oral agreement between
			<lb />
			AGG and DVD, on the basis whereof blank Delivery Instruction
			<lb />
			Slips, qua the 26,86,190 shares of BDR, and blank cheques, qua the
			<lb />
			amount of ₹ 19.55 crores, realised by liquidation of the Mutual Funds,
			<lb />
			had been provided by AGG to DGG, but that it had used the said
			<lb />
			blank Delivery Instruction Slips and blank cheques to misappropriate,
			<lb />
			to its own advantage, the shares of BDR, as well as the amount of ₹
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			19.55 crores. It was further alleged that, using the said monies, DGG
			<lb />
			had invested in other corporate concerns as well. These allegations
			<lb />
			have been noticed by the learned Sole Arbitrator, and taken into
			<lb />
			43 U.O.I v. Major Bahadur Singh (2006) 1 SCC 368 ; BGS SGS Soma JV v. NHPC Ltd. (2020) 4 SCC
			<lb />
			234
			<lb />
			account, before issuing the impugned direction. Once that is so, it no
			<lb />
			longer lies within the province of the jurisdiction of this Court, acting
			<lb />
			under Section 37 of the 1996 Act, to examine, further, whether these
			<lb />
			circumstances were sufficient to warrant the direction to furnish
			<lb />
			security. Sufficiency of the grounds on which the learned Sole
			<lb />
			Arbitrator acted, especially where such action was in exercise of
			<lb />
			discretion statutorily conferred on him, cannot be tested by this Court,
			<lb />
			as any such exercise would amount to an attempt to substitute, for the
			<lb />
			discretion exercised by the learned Sole Arbitrator, its own discretion.
			<lb />
			This is an exercise which has been proscribed, time and time again, by
			<lb />
			several judicial authorities, too numerous to mention.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			68. No such occasion arose, before this Court, in Goodwill Non-
			<lb />
			Woven (P) Ltd 13 , and the reliance, by Mr. Nayar, on the said decision,
			<lb />
			therefore, fails to impress.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			69. BMW India Private Limited 14 , similarly, was a case which
			<lb />
			arose under Section 9 of the 1996 Act. This decision is, in para-29 of
			<lb />
			the report (in SCC OnLine), observed that, while the Court should not
			<lb />
			ignore the principles all the well-known guidelines, governing Order
			<lb />
			38 Rule 5 of the CPC, while exercising jurisdiction under Section
			<lb />
			9(1)(ii)(b), it should not be unduly bound by the text thereof.
			<lb />
			Observing, further, that an order for securing the amount, prior to an
			<lb />
			arbitral award, was comparable to the nature of relief provided under
			<lb />
			Order 38 Rule 5, the learned Single Judge of this Court has, in the said
			<lb />
			decision, observed that, before directing furnishing of security, the
			<lb />
			Court is required to be satisfied regarding the existence of a prima
			<lb />
			facie case in favour of the applicant, and the possibility of the
			<lb />
			opposite party defeating the realisation of the future award that may
			<lb />
			ultimately be passed, were such security not directed. Direction for
			<lb />
			furnishing of security cannot, in the opinion of this Court in the said
			<lb />
			case, be passed mechanically, and has to be informed by the
			<lb />
			&quot;underlying basis of Order 38 Rule 5, CPC&quot;. Having thus observed,
			<lb />
			the learned Single Judge has proceeded to note that the sole argument,
			<lb />
			on the basis of which the prayer for security, in the said case, was
			<lb />
			premised, was that the respondent was in financial distress. The
			<lb />
			learned Single Judge observed that the question of whether, in fact,
			<lb />
			such &quot;financial distress&quot; existed, or not, was a disputed question of
			<lb />
			fact, which could not be adjudicated under Section 9. This sole
			<lb />
			ground, therefore, held the learned Single Judge, was insufficient to
			<lb />
			sustain a prayer for directing furnishing of security, by the opposite
			<lb />
			party. In the present case, the learned Sole Arbitrator was exercising
			<lb />
			jurisdiction, not under Section 9, but under Section 17. That apart, as
			<lb />
			the discussion hereinabove amply reveals, the learned Sole Arbitrator
			<lb />
			as set out, in detail, the facts of the case, which disclosed that the
			<lb />
			amount of ₹ 19.55 crores, realised by liquidation of the Mutual Funds
			<lb />
			of the AGG, as well as the 26,86,190 shares of BDR, held by AGG,
			<lb />
			had been appropriated, by DGG, to its bank account, and to its
			<lb />
			DEMAT Account, respectively, without any consideration having
			<lb />
			been paid to AGG therefor. Further, AGG had alleged that part of the
			<lb />
			said amount had also been invested in certain other corporate
			<lb />
			enterprises. This, therefore, is clearly not the case in which the
			<lb />
			prayer, for furnishing of security, was made, solely on the ground of
			<lb />
			financial distress of the opposite party. The learned Sole Arbitrator
			<lb />
			has, keeping all these facts in mind, felt that it was necessary to secure
			<lb />
			the claim of AGG, by directing furnishing of security, and, within the
			<lb />
			confines of the appellate jurisdiction of this Court under Section 37, I
			<lb />
			am of the opinion that no occasion arises, to interfere. The decision in
			<lb />
			BMW India Private Limited 14 , too, cannot, therefore, assist the
			<lb />
			appellant.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			70. Mr. Nayar also advanced submissions on the power, of the
			<lb />
			learned Sole Arbitrator, to mould reliefs. I do not deem it necessary
			<lb />
			to traverse that terrain, as Section 17(1)(ii)(b) clearly empowered the
			<lb />
			learned Sole Arbitrator to secure the amount in dispute in the
			<lb />
			arbitration. There is, therefore, no gainsaying the fact that, in
			<lb />
			directing as he did, the learned Sole Arbitrator committed no
			<lb />
			jurisdictional error. The learned Sole Arbitrator referred to the
			<lb />
			&quot;reasons given above&quot;, as constituting, inter alia, the basis for this
			<lb />
			decision. Having, for the said reasons, rejected the relief sought by
			<lb />
			AGG, which was undoubtedly much more drastic, the learned Sole
			<lb />
			Arbitrator restricted his order to a direction, to DGG, to secure the
			<lb />
			amount in dispute, by furnishing suitable security. A holistic reading
			<lb />
			of the order reveals that the balance of convenience was kept in mind,
			<lb />
			while passing the impugned direction. No patent illegality can, in my
			<lb />
			view, be discerned, in the impugned decision.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			Conclusion
			<lb />
			71. This Court, while exercising appellate jurisdiction, under
			<lb />
			Section 37 (2) of the 1996 Act, over the interim order of the learned
			<lb />
			Sole Arbitrator, is not expected, or even required, to delve deep into
			<lb />
			the facts of the case. Nor is it expected to substitute its own
			<lb />
			discretion, for the discretion of the learned Sole Arbitrator. If the
			<lb />
			exercise of discretion, by the learned Sole Arbitrator, suffers from
			<lb />
			patent illegality, or is otherwise unconscionable in law or on facts,
			<lb />
			interference may be justified; never otherwise.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			72. Judicial intervention, with arbitral proceedings, has necessarily
			<lb />
			to be reduced to a bare minimum, under the 1996 Act. Applying this
			<lb />
			salutary principle, I am of the opinion that, were this Court to set
			<lb />
			aside, or even modify, the direction, of the learned Sole Arbitrator, to
			<lb />
			DGG, to furnish security for the amount in dispute in the arbitration -
			<lb />
			which, clearly, is within the province of the jurisdiction of the learned
			<lb />
			Sole Arbitrator, conferred by Section 17(1)(ii)(b) -it would do
			<lb />
			violence to the entire ethos of the 1996 Act, and would militate
			<lb />
			against the avowed objective of the legislation itself.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			73. In my view, any interlocutory order, by the arbitrator, under
			<lb />
			Section 17, to furnish security, if preceded by adequate examination
			<lb />
			and appreciation of the facts, and the rival stands of the parties, should
			<lb />
			remain impervious to judicial interference. The Court is required to
			<lb />
			adopt a holistic, and comprehensive, view in such cases. Any attempt,
			<lb />
			by the Court, to vivisect, microscopically, the order of the arbitrator,
			<lb />
			to find flaws, would be entirely inappropriate. So long as the decision
			<lb />
			is informed by adequate application of mind, it should be allowed to
			<lb />
			prevail, especially as it is in the nature of an interlocutory direction,
			<lb />
			and is always subject to the final award, to be passed in the arbitral
			<lb />
			proceedings.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			74. For all these reasons, I am of the opinion that no occasion
			<lb />
			arises, for this Court to interfere with the impugned direction, in para
			<lb />
			3.28 of the Order supra, dated 18 th February, 2020, of the learned Sole
			<lb />
			Arbitrator to DGG, to furnish suitable security, equivalent to the
			<lb />
			amount involved in the dispute. This Court, therefore, upholds the
			<lb />
			said direction.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			75. It is clarified that observations in this judgement are prima facie
			<lb />
			in nature, and do not intend to represent any final expression of
			<lb />
			opinion on any of the issues of which the learned Sole Arbitrator is in
			<lb />
			seisin, including the validity of the Family Settlements, the nature of
			<lb />
			the acquisition, by DGG, of the 26,86,190 shares of BDR and their
			<lb />
			transfer into the DEMAT account of DGG, the transfer of ₹ 19.55
			<lb />
			crores into the account of DGG, or, indeed, any other aspect
			<lb />
			whatsoever. The learned Sole Arbitrator shall, while arbitrating on
			<lb />
			the issues before him, proceed entirely uninfluenced by any
			<lb />
			observation contained in this judgement. This Court is, in the present
			<lb />
			case, essentially concerned with whether a case for interference, with
			<lb />
			the impugned direction of the learned Sole Arbitrator, has, within the
			<lb />
			confines of Section 37 of the 1996 Act, been made out or not, and has,
			<lb />
			for the reasons adduced hereinbefore, answered the issue in the
			<lb />
			negative.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			76. The appeal is, accordingly, dismissed, albeit with no orders as
			<lb />
			to costs.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			77. Pending applications, if any, stand disposed of accordingly.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			C. HARI SHANKAR, J.
			<lb />
			SEPTEMBER 17, 2020
			<lb />
			HJ
		</p>


	</text>
</tei>