<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">

		<head>
			CORAM : A.S.CHANDURKAR and SMT. M.S.JAWALKAR, JJ.
			<lb />
			ARGUMENTS WERE HEARD ON 08.03.2022.
			<lb />
			JUDGMENT IS PRONOUNCED ON 17.03.2022
			<lb />
			WP.4588.2019 WITH CONNECTED WPs.(J)
			<lb />
			4/13
			<lb />
			ORAL JUDGMENT (Per A.S.CHANDURKAR, J.)
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			Rule. Rule made returnable forthwith and heard the learned counsel
			<lb />
			for the parties.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			The question that arises in this batch of writ petitions is whether
			<lb />
			grant of short term permit for minor minerals under Rule 59 of the
			<lb />
			Maharashtra Minor Mineral Extraction (Development and Regulation) Rules,
			<lb />
			2013 (for short, the Rules of 2013) ought to be preceded by holding public
			<lb />
			auction or whether such short term permit can be granted on the basis of an
			<lb />
			application made to the Competent Authority ?
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			Each petitioner claims to hold permission to operate stone crushers.
			<lb />
			The petitioners were informed by the Additional Collector that in view of
			<lb />
			Government Resolution dated 23.01.2019 grant of short term permit would be
			<lb />
			permissible only through e-auction. For that reason, the request made by the
			<lb />
			petitioners for grant of short term permit came to be refused. Being aggrieved
			<lb />
			by the issuance of such communication the petitioners have challenged the
			<lb />
			orders passed in that regard and further seek a direction that the respondents
			<lb />
			be directed to issue short term permit for extraction of minor minerals to the
			<lb />
			petitioners.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			Shri Shantanu Khedkar, learned Counsel alongwith S/Shri V.B.Bhise
			<lb />
			and R.D.Dhande, learned counsel for the petitioners submitted that the
			<lb />
			Additional Collector by misconstruing the provisions of Rule 59 of the Rules of
			<lb />
			2013 alongwith Government Resolution dated 23.01.2019 has refused to grant
			<lb />
			short term permit for excavation of minor minerals. Inviting attention to the
			<lb />
			provisions of Rule 2(s) which defines &quot;quarry license or lease&quot; and Rule 2(t)
			<lb />
			which defines &quot;quarry permit&quot;, it was submitted that the Rules of 2013 make a
			<lb />
			distinction between quarry license or lease and quarry permit. Rule 9 of the
			<lb />
			Rules of 2013 prescribes the mode of granting quarry lease and under sub-rule
			<lb />
			(1) the Competent Authority can grant quarry lease either on receipt of an
			<lb />
			application or by way of public auction. Inviting attention to Rule 59 it was
			<lb />
			submitted that for grant of short term permit to extract any minor mineral it
			<lb />
			was necessary only to make an application to the Competent Authority and the
			<lb />
			said Rule did not provide for conducting any auction in that regard. It was
			<lb />
			further submitted that on 12.01.2018 the Revenue and Forest Department
			<lb />
			issued Notification seeking to amend the Rules of 2013. Rule 9 as existing was
			<lb />
			substituted making it obligatory on the part of the Competent Authority to
			<lb />
			grant quarry lease by way of public auction. While introducing such
			<lb />
			amendment the provisions of Rule 59 of the Rules of 2013 were not so
			<lb />
			amended and hence there was no basis for the Additional Collector to hold that
			<lb />
			grant of short term permit was also to be through public auction. On a plain
			<lb />
			reading of Rule 9 as amended and Rule 59, it was submitted that there was no
			<lb />
			reason to hold that grant of short term permit was to be through public auction.
			<lb />
			Rule 59 began with the use of a non obstante clause and therefore there was no
			<lb />
			occasion to apply the provisions of Rule 9 while granting short term permit for
			<lb />
			excavation of minor minerals. The learned counsel referred to the decision
			<lb />
			Laxmi Devi vs. State of Bihar and others (2015) 10 SCC 241. It was thus
			<lb />
			submitted that the impugned orders passed by the Additional Collector were
			<lb />
			liable to be set aside and the application for grant of short term permit ought to
			<lb />
			be considered in the light of Rule 59 of the Rules of 2013.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			Ms. N. P. Mehta, learned Assistant Government Pleader for the
			<lb />
			respondents opposed the aforesaid submissions. She submitted that under
			<lb />
			Section 15 of the Mines and Mineral (Development and Regulation) Act, 1957
			<lb />
			(for short, the Act of 1957) the State Government was empowered to make
			<lb />
			Rules in respect of minor mineral. The Rules of 2013 were accordingly framed.
			<lb />
			As per Rule 9 a quarry lease could be granted after holding public auction. The
			<lb />
			same modality was to be followed for grant of short term quarry permit.
			<lb />
			Inviting attention to Government Resolution dated 23.01.2019 it was submitted
			<lb />
			that the manner in which such public auction was to be held was stipulated.
			<lb />
			On a plain reading of the said Government Resolution it was clear that the
			<lb />
			Additional Collector did not commit any error when he observed that short
			<lb />
			term quarry permit could be granted only after holding a public auction. It was
			<lb />
			thus submitted that the writ petitions were liable to be dismissed.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			We have heard the learned counsel for the parties at length and we
			<lb />
			have given due consideration to their respective submissions. For answering
			<lb />
			the question as framed hereinabove it would be necessary to first refer to the
			<lb />
			relevant statutory provisions holding the field.
			<lb />
			Under Section 15(1) of the Act of 1957 the State Government is
			<lb />
			empowered to make Rules for regulating grant of quarry lease, minor lease or
			<lb />
			other mineral concessions in respect of minor mineral. In exercise of that
			<lb />
			power the Rules of 2013 have been framed. Rules 2(s) and 2(t) read as under:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;2(s) Quarry license of lease means a license granted under
			<lb />
			these rules wherein a licensee is required to pay fixed annual
			<lb />
			license fee exclusive or inclusive of royalty, as the case may
			<lb />
			be.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;2(t) : Quarry permit means a permit granted under
			<lb />
			Chapter-IV of these rules to extract and remove any minor
			<lb />
			mineral in specified quantities and specified time.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			Chapter II lays down the procedure for grant of quarry lease. Rule 9 prescribes
			<lb />
			mode of granting quarry lease. That rule as substituted by Notification dated
			<lb />
			12.01.2018 reads as under :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;9. Mode of granting quarry lease : (1) Subject to the
			<lb />
			provisions of these rules, mineral concessions for quarry
			<lb />
			lease on any land vested in the Government or any public
			<lb />
			authority may be granted by the Competent Authority by
			<lb />
			way of public auction.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Provided that, grant of quarry lease on a private land
			<lb />
			in the name of the occupant or holder of such private land
			<lb />
			shall be exempted from auction process and may be
			<lb />
			granted to such occupant or holder upon his application.
			<lb />
			However where the occupant or holder of a private land is
			<lb />
			desirous of leasing his land to another person for
			<lb />
			quarrying, such occupant or holder shall give his written
			<lb />
			consent in that regard to the Collector who shall then put
			<lb />
			quarrying rights in such land to auction for specified
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			period in which case, the amount realized in auction shall
			<lb />
			be credited to the Government and the amount of surface
			<lb />
			rent as decided by the Government from time to time, will
			<lb />
			be given to the land holder:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Provided further that, the practice of granting quarry
			<lb />
			lease or permit upon application shall be continued in
			<lb />
			case of Kumbhar and Vadar families which wish to do
			<lb />
			such mining for pursuing their traditional business :
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Provided further that, the provisions of this rule,
			<lb />
			shall not apply to any case where prospecting licence or
			<lb />
			mining lease had been granted but mining lease deed
			<lb />
			could not be executed before the date of publication of the
			<lb />
			Government of India Gazette notification No.F. No.5/ 1/
			<lb />
			2015-M.M., dated 10 th February 2015 declaring 31 major
			<lb />
			minerals as minor minerals.
			<lb />
			Explanation 1-for the Purposes of this rules,
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&apos;Public Authority&quot; means any authority or body or
			<lb />
			institution of self-government established or constituted,-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a) by or under the Constitution of India;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b) by any law made by the Parliament;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(c) by any law made by the State Legislature:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			by notification issued or order made by the
			<lb />
			appropriate Government, and includes any body owned,
			<lb />
			controlled or substantially financed by the Central
			<lb />
			Government or the State.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Explanation 2-for the Purpose of this rule.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;Surface rent&quot; means rent, payable by the lessee for the
			<lb />
			surface area, leased to him for the purpose of mining, at
			<lb />
			the rates prescribed by the Government.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(2) A quarry lease may be granted for quarry operation
			<lb />
			on the condition of payment of lease money including
			<lb />
			royalty, dead rent, surface rent, water rates payable to the
			<lb />
			Government and under such quarry lease, the lessee shall
			<lb />
			have the right of quarrying and disposing of the extracted
			<lb />
			minor minerals.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(3)
			<lb />
			Procedure and terms and conditions for public
			<lb />
			auction of quarry lease shall be such as the Government
			<lb />
			may, by an order, specify, from time to time.&quot;.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			Rule 11 pertains to an application for seeking quarry lease and Rule 15 refers
			<lb />
			to disposal of the application for quarry lease. Chapter III comprises of Rules
			<lb />
			46 to 57 and it prescribes terms and conditions of quarry lease. Chapter IV
			<lb />
			pertains to grant of quarry permits for minor minerals and Rule 59, with which
			<lb />
			we are concerned, reads as under :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;59. Grant of short term permits for minor minerals.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(1) Not-withstanding anything contained in the foregoing
			<lb />
			rules, the Competent Officer, on an application made to
			<lb />
			him may grant a quarry permit to any person to extract or
			<lb />
			remove from any specified land within the limits of his
			<lb />
			jurisdiction any minor mineral not exceeding in quantity as
			<lb />
			mentioned under any one permit on payment of advance
			<lb />
			royalties [at the rate specified in Schedule I] and on such
			<lb />
			rents and fees assessable for such extraction:
			<lb />
			Provided that, no permits shall be granted in case of any
			<lb />
			specified minor mineral without prior approval of the
			<lb />
			Director.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(2) The Competent Officer shall grant permit for specific
			<lb />
			time and specific volume.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>(</item>

		<item>
			3)
			<lb />
			The Competent Officer may refuse to grant such
			<lb />
			permit for reasons to be recorded in writing.&quot;
			<lb />
			Chapter V prescribes grant of concession by way of public auction. Under Rule
			<lb />
			68 minor minerals can be disposed by way of public auction and under Rule 70
			<lb />
			sand from nalah, river beds and creeks can be disposed of by way of public
			<lb />
			auction. The Rules also comprise of various forms. Form B is an application
			<lb />
			for quarry lease, Form C is an application of renewal for quarry lease and Form
			<lb />
			P is an application for quarry permit.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			From the aforesaid provisions it becomes instantly clear that
			<lb />
			reference to grant by way of public auction can be found in Rules 9(1), 68(1)
			<lb />
			and 70. Rule 59 merely refers to an application to be made to the Competent
			<lb />
			Officer for grant of quarry permit. On a plain reading of the aforesaid Rules, it
			<lb />
			is obvious that the procedure for grant of quarry lease under Rule 9 as
			<lb />
			amended is distinct from the procedure for grant of short term permit under
			<lb />
			Rule 59. The Forms prescribed under the Rules of 2013 are also distinct.
			<lb />
			Moreover, Rule 59(1) states that &quot;notwithstanding anything contained in the
			<lb />
			foregoing rules,…….&quot; Rule 59 (1) thus is intended to operate notwithstanding
			<lb />
			anything contained in the foregoing rules including Rule 9. It is also pertinent
			<lb />
			to observe that by Notification dated 12.01.2018, the Rules of 2013 were
			<lb />
			amended. While existing Rule 9 was substituted, the earlier provision in Rule
			<lb />
			9(1) of making an application for grant of quarry lease has been done away
			<lb />
			with. After amendment, quarry lease can be granted by the Competent
			<lb />
			Authority only by way of public auction. Rule 59 however has not been
			<lb />
			amended and it continues to operate in its earlier form. Thus after amendment
			<lb />
			the distinction between Rule 9(1) and Rule 59(1) becomes more obvious and it
			<lb />
			is thus clear that it was not the intention of the State that short term permit for
			<lb />
			minor minerals should be granted by way of public auction. The mode of
			<lb />
			granting such permit on an application made has been retained.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			Much emphasis was sought to be placed on the Government
			<lb />
			Resolution dated 23.01.2019. A complete reading of this Government
			<lb />
			Resolution indicates that it lays down the procedure for conduct of auctions for
			<lb />
			grant of quarry lease under Rule 9 of the Rules of 2013. In the entire
			<lb />
			Government Resolution reference can be found only to the modality prescribed
			<lb />
			by Rule 9 and other ancillary Rules in that regard. There is no reference
			<lb />
			whatsoever to Rule 59 which empowers grant of short term permits. In the
			<lb />
			absence of any provision in Rule 59(1) to grant short term quarry permit by
			<lb />
			holding public auction, the same cannot be imported by referring to
			<lb />
			Government Resolution dated 23.01.2019. In any event, that Government
			<lb />
			Resolution specifically refers to Rule 9 of the Rules of 2013 and there is total
			<lb />
			absence of any reference to Rule 59 of the Rules of 2013. It is thus clear that
			<lb />
			the modality for grant of quarry lease under Rule 9 has been prescribed only to
			<lb />
			be by way of public auction while grant of short term permit is only by way of
			<lb />
			making an application to the Competent Authority. The question as framed is
			<lb />
			answered accordingly.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			Having found that short term quarry permit under Rule 59(1) of the
			<lb />
			Rules of 2013 can be granted on an application being made to the Competent
			<lb />
			Authority, we find that the application made by the petitioners herein are not
			<lb />
			in accordance with Form P. Rule 61(1) of the Rules of 2013 prescribes the
			<lb />
			nature of application to be made for grant of quarry permits and therefore if
			<lb />
			the petitioners seek quarry permit they would be required to apply as per the
			<lb />
			provisions of Rule 61(1) of the Rules of 2013 and Form P thereof. However
			<lb />
			rejection of the application as made by the petitioners is for the reason that
			<lb />
			grant of quarry permits has to be as per public auction which reason has been
			<lb />
			found to be incorrect. Incidentally, we may observe that holding of public
			<lb />
			auction would always be preferable than any grant being made on the basis of
			<lb />
			an application. However, for that purpose there ought to be some statutory
			<lb />
			provision in that regard which is however absent in Rule 59 of the Rules of
			<lb />
			2013.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			10.
			<lb />
			Accordingly, the following order is passed :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(1)
			<lb />
			It is held that grant of quarry permits under Rule 59(1) would be
			<lb />
			pursuant to application made in Form P to the Competent Authority and not by
			<lb />
			public auction since there is no such requirement in Rule 59 of the Rules of
			<lb />
			2013. Government Resolution dated 23.01.2019 is not applicable to grant of
			<lb />
			quarry permits under Rule 59 of the Rules of 2013.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(2)
			<lb />
			The impugned orders refusing to grant short term quarry permit by
			<lb />
			stating that the same can be granted only by way of public auction are set
			<lb />
			aside.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(3)
			<lb />
			If the petitioners desire to seek grant of quarry permit under Rule
			<lb />
			59(1) of the Rules of 2013, they are free to make such application under Rule
			<lb />
			61(1) and Form P as prescribed. If such application is made the Competent
			<lb />
			Authority shall decide the same in accordance with law and in the light of the
			<lb />
			observations made hereinabove.
			<lb />
			Rule is made absolute in aforesaid terms with no order as to costs.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(SMT. M.S.JAWALKAR,J.)
			<lb />
			(A.S.CHANDURKAR, J.)
			<lb />
			Andurkar..
		</p>


	</text>
</tei>