<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="358c2215280a80b31e2c37509d227d83"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>

	1<lb/>
	<byline>
	<affiliation>IN THE HIGH COURT OF JUDICATURE AT BOMBAY<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>NAGPUR BENCH, NAGPUR.<lb/> WRIT PETITION NO. 934/94, 967/92, 1179/93, 3085/93, 1784/92,<lb/> 1034/95, 1512/2000, 1136/93, 2322/92, 822/99, 1070/2000 &amp;<lb/> 5145/07.<lb/></address>

	(1)<lb/>
	<reference>WRIT PETITION NO. 934 OF 1994.<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">Friends Cooperative Housing Society<lb/> Limited, Nagpur, duly registered<lb/> under the Maharashtra Cooperative<lb/> Societies Act, 1960, bearing Registration<lb/> No. HSG/NGP/123 of 1962, having<lb/></note>

	its registered office at 41, Tatya Tope<lb/> Nagar, Nagpur-15, through its<lb/> Secretary.<lb/> ....<lb/> PETITIONER.<lb/> ....Versus....<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">1. The Nagpur Improvement Trust, through<lb/> its Chairman, Civil Lines, Nagpur,<lb/></note>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2. The State of Maharashtra, through its<lb/> Secretary, Department of Urban<lb/> Land Development, Mantralaya Annexe,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bombay-32,<lb/> 3.</address>

	<note type="copyright">Matru Seva Sangh, a society registered<lb/> under the Bombay Public Trusts Act,<lb/> having its registered office at Sitabuldi,<lb/> Nagpur, through its Secretary,<lb/></note>

	<reference>4. Sati Mata Shikshan Sanstha, through<lb/> its Secretary, 11, Vyankatesh Nagar,<lb/> Khamla Road, Nagpur-25.<lb/> ....<lb/> RESPONDENTS.<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:43 ::: 2<lb/> Mr. Uday Dastane, Counsel for petitioner,<lb/> Mr. A.S. Fulzele, A.G.P. for respondent no.2,<lb/> Mr. S.K. Mishra, Counsel for respondent no.1,<lb/> Mr. S.S. Joshi, Counsel for respondent no.3.<lb/> Mr. S.D. Deshpande, Counsel for respondent no.4.<lb/></reference>

	(2)<lb/>
	<reference>WRIT PETITION NO. 967 OF 1992.<lb/></reference>

	PETITIONERS:<lb/> 1.
	<keyword>Dharampeth Grihanirman Sahakari Sanstha,<lb/> bearing Registration No.1041/55, 89-C,<lb/> Ramnagar, Nagpur-10, through its Secretary -<lb/>Shri Gangadhar s/o Narayan Morone, aged 61<lb/> years, Occu: Pensioner, r/o 117, Abhyankar<lb/> Nagar, Nagpur.<lb/> 2. Citizen Uplift Society,<lb/> 23, Gawande Lay-out, Khamla Road,<lb/> Nagpur-15, by its Secretary, Shri Ramrao<lb/> Wankhede.<lb/></keyword>

	: VERSUS :<lb/>
	<keyword>RESPONDENTS: 1. The Nagpur Improvement Trust,<lb/> through its Chairman, Kings way, Sadar<lb/> Nagpur-1.<lb/></keyword>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2. Bhartiya Adim Jati Sewak Sangh,<lb/> through Secretary Shri M.N.More,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Yogabhyasi Mandal, Ramnagar, Nagpur-10.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3. National Centre for Rural Development,<lb/> through Managing Director Shri Ram Kale,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>253<lb/> Shivaji Nagar, Nagpur-10.<lb/></address>

	INTERVENORS:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Deendayal Nagar Semutkarsha Sanstha Ltd.,<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	through its Secretary, Registered Office at<lb/>
	<byline>
	<affiliation>29-Dharampeth Layout, Deendayal Nagar,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Nagpur-22.<lb/></address>

	<idno>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:43 ::: 3<lb/></idno>

	<reference>Mr.R.S.Parsodkar,Advocate for the petitioners.<lb/> Mr.S.K.Mishra, Advocate for N.I.T.<lb/> Shri S.W.Ghate, Advocate for the intervenor.<lb/></reference>

	(3)<lb/>
	<reference>WRIT PETITION NO.1179 OF 1993.<lb/></reference>

	PETITIONER:<lb/>
	<keyword>Saraswati Cooperative Housing Society Ltd.<lb/> bearing registration No.1796/60, through<lb/> its Secretary, Shri H.B. Chikerur, aged about 74<lb/> years, Occupation : Retired from Service,<lb/> R/o 57-58, Deendayal Nagar, Nagpur.<lb/></keyword>

	: VERSUS :<lb/>
	<keyword>RESPONDENTS: 1. The Nagpur Improvement Trust, through its<lb/> Chairman, near Liberty Cinema Sadar,<lb/> Nagpur.<lb/> 2. Halba Koshti Housing Society, through its<lb/> Executive Member Shri Asai,<lb/> Civil Lines, Nagpur.<lb/> INTERVENOR :<lb/> Dnyan Vidnyan Vardhini, 185, NIT Layout,<lb/> Trimurti Nagar, Ring Road, Nagpur, through<lb/> its General Secretary Smt. Preeti P. Siras.<lb/> Mr.R.S.Parsodkar,Advocate for the petitioner.<lb/> Mr.S.K.Mishra, Advocate for N.I.T./respondent no.1.<lb/> Shri Ambilwade, Adv. for respondent no.2.<lb/> Shri D.L.Dharmadhikari, Adv. for the Intervenor.<lb/></keyword>

	(4)<lb/>
	<reference>WRIT PETITION NO.3085 OF 1998.<lb/></reference>

	PETITIONER:<lb/>
	<keyword>Telecom Engineering Cooperative<lb/> Housing Society Ltd., through its<lb/> Secretary Shri G.V.Sohoni, 71, Telecom<lb/> Amenity Hall, Telecom Nagar, Nagpur.<lb/></keyword>

	: VERSUS :<lb/>
	<keyword>RESPONDENTS: 1. The Nagpur Improvement Trust,<lb/> through its Chairman, Near<lb/> Liberty Cinema, Sadar,Nagpur.<lb/></keyword>

	:::
	<reference>Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:43 ::: 4<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">2. The Corporation of the City of Nagpur through<lb/> the Municipal Commissioner, Civil Lines,<lb/> Nagpur.<lb/> 3. Vidarbha Cricket Association,<lb/> through its Secretary, Nagpur.<lb/></note>

	<reference>Mr.A.M.Ghare, Advocate for the petitioner.<lb/> Mr.S.K.Mishra, Advocate for respondent no.1.<lb/> Mr.R.S.Parsodkar, Advocate for respondent no.2.<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">(5)<lb/> WRIT PETITION NO. 1784/1992<lb/></note>

	<reference>The Rani Laxmi Nagar Nagrik Sabha,<lb/> Regd. No. 567, Laxmi Nagar, Nagpur,<lb/> through its President.<lb/></reference>

	.....PETITIONER<lb/> ...V E R S U S...<lb/>
	<keyword>1. The Nagpur Improvement Trust,<lb/> through its Chairman.<lb/> 2. The Scientific Cooperative Housing<lb/> Society, Rani Laxmi Nagar, Nagpur,<lb/> through its Secretary.<lb/> .....RESPONDENTS<lb/> Mr. M. M. Agnihotri, Advocate for the petitioner.<lb/> Mr. S. K. Mishra, Advocate for respondent no. 1.<lb/> Mr. P. T. Trivedi, Advocate for respondent no.2.<lb/></keyword>

	(6)<lb/> WRIT PETITION NO.
	<date>1034/1995<lb/></date>

	1. Keshao s/o Pandurang Shivankar,<lb/> aged about 53 years, r/o Plot No. 16,<lb/>
	<byline>
	<affiliation>Gawande Colony, Chhatrapati Nagar,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Nagpur.<lb/></address>

	2. Prabhakar Krishnarao Patrikar,<lb/> aged about 60 years, r/o plot No. 11-A,<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:43 :::
	<byline>
	<affiliation>5<lb/> Pendse Layout,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Wardha Road, Nagpur.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3. Narayanrao Jagobaji Gawande Public<lb/> Trust, through its Secretary, Shri Madhukar<lb/> Pandurang Gawande, r/o Gayatri Nagar,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>South Ambazari Road, Nagpur.<lb/></address>

	.....PETITIONERS<lb/> ...V E R S U S...<lb/>
	<byline>
	<affiliation>1. State of Maharashtra, through its<lb/> Secretary, Urban Development,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Mantralaya, Bombay-32.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2. Nagpur Improvement Trust,<lb/> through its Chairman, Station Road,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Sadar, Nagpur.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3. Santaji Mahavidyalaya through its<lb/> Chairman Govindrao Wanjari,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Wardha Road, Nagpur.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4. Shri Govindrao Wanjari,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>President, Santaji Mahavidyalaya,<lb/> Wardha Road, Nagpur.<lb/></address>

	.....RESPONDENTS<lb/> Mr. Anand Parchure, Advocate for the petitioner.<lb/>
	<reference>Mrs. K.S. Joshi, A.G.P. for respondent no. 1.<lb/> Mr. R. P. Joshi, Advocate for respondent no.2.<lb/> Mr. S. P. Dharmadhikari, Advocate for respondent nos. 3 and 4.<lb/> (7)<lb/> WRIT PETITION NO.1512 OF 2000.<lb/></reference>

	PETITIONER:<lb/>
	<reference>Janta Co-operative Housing Society Ltd.,<lb/> Nagpur, duly registered under the Maharashtra<lb/> Cooperative Societies Act, 1960, bearing<lb/> Registration No.HSG/NGP/952 of 1955, having<lb/> its registered office at 374, Shankar Nagar,<lb/> Nagpur-15 through its Secretary.<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:43 :::</reference>

	6<lb/> : VERSUS :<lb/>
	<keyword>RESPONDENTS: 1. The Nagpur Improvement Trust,<lb/> through its Chairman, Civil Lines, Nagpur.<lb/></keyword>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2. The State of Maharashtra,<lb/> through its Secretary, Department of Union<lb/> Land Development,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Mantralaya, Annexe,<lb/> Mumbai 400032.<lb/></address>

	<note type="copyright">3. The Nagpur Municipal Corporation, Nagpur,<lb/> through its Municipal Commissioner.<lb/></note>

	<reference>Mr.U.Dastane, Advocate for the petitioner.<lb/> Mr.S.K.Mishra, Advocate for respondent no.1.<lb/> Mrs. K.S. Joshi, A.G.P. for respondent no.2.<lb/> (8)<lb/> WRIT PETITION NO. 1136 OF 1993.<lb/></reference>

	PETITIONER:<lb/>
	<reference>Shri Gajanan Cooperative Housing<lb/> Society Ltd., Wardha Road, Nagpur through<lb/> its Secretary Shri J.G.Padnis, Plot No.53,<lb/></reference>

	<address>Gajanan Nagar, Wardha Road, Nagpur.<lb/></address>

	: VERSUS :<lb/>
	<keyword>RESPONDENTS: 1. The Nagpur Improvement Trust,<lb/> through its Chairman, Kingsway,Nagpur.<lb/> 2. Kanya Kubjya Vaishya (Halwai)<lb/> Hitkarni Sangh, through their President,<lb/></keyword>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>C/o Anant Gupta Bhandar, Nalsaheb Chowk,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bhandara Road, Nagpur<lb/></address>

	<reference>Mr.V.S.Kukday, Advocate for the petitioner.<lb/> Mr.S.K.Mishra, Advocate for respondent no.1.<lb/> Mr. Shyam D. Dewani, Advocate for respondent no.2.<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:43 ::: 7<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>(9)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<reference>WRIT PETITION NO.2322 OF 1992.<lb/></reference>

	PETITIONER:<lb/>
	<keyword>Bhanudas s/o Pancham Varade,<lb/> aged about 70 years, Occu: Nil, residents<lb/> of Untkhana Dahipura Layout, near<lb/> Baidyanath Chowk, Varade Bhavan, Nagpur.<lb/></keyword>

	: VERSUS :<lb/>
	<keyword>RESPONDENTS: 1. State of Maharashtra through its<lb/> Secretary, Urban Development Department,<lb/> Mantralaya, Bombay -32.<lb/> 2. The Nagpur Improvement Trust,<lb/> through its Chairman, Station Road, Sadar,<lb/> Nagpur.<lb/> 3. The Divisional Officer,<lb/> C.S.E.S., Nagpur Improvement Trust, Nagpur.<lb/> 4. Asit Multi-purpose Association,<lb/> Registered No.31 N/75, through its President<lb/> Shri Shyam Bhagat, Untkhana, Nagpur.<lb/> Mr.Anand Parchure, Advocate for the petitioner.<lb/> Mrs. K.S. Joshi, A.G.P. for respondent no.1,<lb/> Mr.S.K.Mishra, Advocate for respondents no.2 and 3.<lb/> Mr.Z.A.Haq Advocate for respondent no.4.<lb/> (10)<lb/> WRIT PETITION NO. 822 OF 1999<lb/> P. M. G. Office Staff Cooperative<lb/> Housing Society Limited,<lb/> Madhav Nagar, Nagpur-through<lb/> its President, Madhav Nagar<lb/> Nagpur.<lb/> PETITIONER.</keyword>

	VERSUS<lb/> :::
	<reference>Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:43 ::: 8<lb/></reference>

	1.
	<keyword>Nagpur Improvement Trust,<lb/> through its Chairman, Near<lb/> Liberty Cinema Building, Sadar,<lb/> Nagpur.<lb/> 2. Vidarbha Cricket Association,<lb/> Opp. I. B. M. Building, Sadar,<lb/> Nagpur through its President.<lb/> RESPONDENTS.<lb/> Shri A. R. Patil, Counsel for the petitioner.<lb/> Shri S. K. Mishra, Counsel for respondent No. 1.<lb/> Shri A. S. Jaiswal, Counsel for respondent No. 2.<lb/> (11)<lb/> WRIT PETITION NO. 1070 OF 2000<lb/> Friends Cooperative Housing<lb/> Society Ltd. Nagpur, duly registered<lb/> under the Maharashtra Cooperative<lb/> Societies Act, 1960, bearing<lb/> Registration No. HSG/NGP/123 of<lb/> 1962, having its registered office at<lb/> 41, Tatya Tope Nagar, Nagpur-15,<lb/> through its Secretary.<lb/> PETITIONER. VERSUS<lb/> 1. The Nagpur Improvement Trust,<lb/> through its Chairman, Civil<lb/> Lines, Nagpur.<lb/></keyword>

	2. The State of Maharashtra,<lb/> through its Secretary,<lb/>
	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Urban Land<lb/> Development, Mantralaya,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Annexe, Mumbai-32.<lb/></address>

	3. The Nagpur Municipal<lb/> Corporation, Nagpur,<lb/> :::
	<reference>Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:43 :::</reference>

	9<lb/>
	<keyword>through its Municipal<lb/> Commissioner.<lb/> RESPONDENTS.<lb/> Shri. U. S. Dastane, Counsel for the petitioner.<lb/> Mr. A.S. Fulzele, A.G.P. for respondent no.2,<lb/> Shri S.K. Mishra, Counsel for respondent No.1.<lb/> (12)<lb/> WRIT PETITION NO. 5145 OF 2007.<lb/> The Greater Nagpur Cooperative<lb/> Development and Housing Society<lb/> Limited, having its Head Office at<lb/> 51, Alhad Jyoti Apartment, Ramkrishna<lb/> Nagar, Khamla, Nagpur-25, through<lb/> its President Chandrashekhar K.<lb/> Najpande, R/o Ramkrishna Nagar,<lb/> Khamla, Nagpur-25.<lb/> ....<lb/> PETITIONER.<lb/> ....Versus....<lb/> 1. State of Maharashtra, through its<lb/> Secretary to the Urban Development<lb/> Departments, Mantralaya, Mumbai-32,<lb/> 2. Nagpur Improvement Trust, through<lb/> its Secretary, having its office at<lb/> Kingsway, Sadar, Nagpur,<lb/> 3. The Corporation of the City of Nagpur,<lb/> through its Commissioner, having its<lb/> Office at Civil Lines, Nagpur,<lb/> 4. Sneh Manila Vikas Sanstha, through<lb/> its Secretary, Nagpur.<lb/> ....<lb/> RESPONDENTS.<lb/></keyword>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Mr. Anand Parchure,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Advocate for the petitioner,<lb/>
	<reference>Mrs. K.S. Joshi, A.G.P. for respondent no.1,<lb/> Mr. S.K. Mishra, Counsel for respondent no.2,<lb/> Mr. S.V. Manohar, Counsel for respondent no.4.<lb/> ::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:43 :::<lb/></reference>

	<div type="abstract">allotment has been made. Therefore, there cannot be any fault, which<lb/> can be found out with the allotment being made in favour of the<lb/> allottees, who have applied in consonance to the advertisement and<lb/> fulfilled the terms and conditions of the agreement. NIT has allotted the<lb/> public utility land to following institutions; which are : Maharashtra<lb/></div>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Rashtrabhasha Sabha, Nagpur,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Hostel for Women, South Indian<lb/> Educational Society, Deaf and Dumb&apos;s School, Indian Medical<lb/> Association, Institutions like Nagrik Sahakari Rugnalaya,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kusumtai<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Wankhede Hall, Shri Guru Raghvendra Swami Bhajan Mandal, Maharana<lb/> Pratap Smuruti Mandir Sanstha, Matru Sewa Sangh, Shashkiya<lb/> Chitrakala Mahavidyalaya,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Chaitanya International Hospital,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>L.A.D.<lb/> College, Vidarbha Bridge Association, Kalakunj, Yogabhayasi Mandal,<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Rani Laxmibai Jhansichi Smarak Samiti, Bhagwad Pad Sabha, Bhratru<lb/> Mandal, Yogabhasi Mandal, Karnatak Sangh, Ved Dharma Shastra<lb/> Papipalan Sabha, Satchikitsa Prasarak Mandal, Mahila Sewa Samaj,<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Nagendra Digambar Jain Samaj, Khaire Kumbhi Samaj, Sewadal<lb/> Education Society, Shri Sant Tukaram Gyan Mandir, Nagpur Houses of<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Mary Immanulate, Bhartiya Bhasha Dnyan Mandir, Dr. Hedgewar Smarak<lb/> Samiti, Sant Gulab Baba Sewa Ashram, Gayatri Parivar Trust,<lb/> Keshaonagar Sanskrutik Mandir, Stree Shikshan Prasarak Mandal,<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:43 :::
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
