<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>IN THE HIGH COURT OF JUDICATURE AT BOMBAY, <lb/>NAGPUR BENCH, NAGPUR <lb/>Criminal Application No.2424 of 2008 <lb/>In <lb/>Criminal Appeal No.390 of 2008, <lb/>Criminal Application No.2425 of 2008 <lb/>In <lb/>Criminal Appeal No.391 of 2008, <lb/>Criminal Application No.2426 of 2008 <lb/>In <lb/>Criminal Appeal No.392 of 2008, <lb/>Criminal Application No.2428 of 2008 <lb/>In <lb/>Criminal Appeal No.393 of 2008, <lb/>Criminal Application No.2427 of 2008 <lb/>In <lb/>Criminal Appeal No.399 of 2008, <lb/>Criminal Appeal No.390 of 2008, <lb/>Criminal Appeal No.391 of 2008, <lb/>Criminal Appeal No.392 of 2008, <lb/>Criminal Appeal No.393 of 2008, <lb/>And <lb/>Criminal Appeal No.399 of 2008 <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/>2 <lb/>Criminal Application No.2424 of 2008 <lb/>In <lb/>Criminal Appeal No.390 of 2008 <lb/>M/s. Jinraj Paper Udyog, <lb/>2/26, Ansari Road, Delhi, <lb/>Office also at Jejani Sadan, <lb/>Itwari Bhaji Mandi, Nagpur, <lb/>through its Proprietor, <lb/>Jinraj s/o Ramkisan Jain. <lb/>... Applicant <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. M/s. Dinesh Associates, <lb/>Proprietorship Concern, <lb/>3796/2, Gali Lohe Wali, <lb/>Behind Namkeen Shop, <lb/>Charkhewalan, Chawari Bazar, <lb/>Delhi-110 006. <lb/>2. Dinesh s/o Gopichand Gupta, <lb/>Proprietor of M/s. Dinesh Associates, <lb/>R/o D-145, &quot;Priyadarshini Vihar&quot;, <lb/>Opp. Lovely Public School, <lb/>Shahadara, Delhi. <lb/>...Respondent/ <lb/>Accused <lb/>Criminal Application No.2425 of 2008 <lb/>In <lb/>Criminal Appeal No.391 of 2008 <lb/>M/s. Jinraj Paper Udyog, <lb/>2/26, Ansari Road, Delhi, <lb/>Office also at Jejani Sadan, <lb/>Itwari Bhaji Mandi, Nagpur, <lb/>through its Proprietor, <lb/>Jinraj s/o Ramkisan Jain. <lb/>... Applicant <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<front>Versus <lb/>1. M/s. Dinesh Associates, <lb/>Proprietorship Concern, <lb/>3796/2, Gali Lohe Wali, <lb/>Behind Namkeen Shop, <lb/>Charkhewalan, Chawari Bazar, <lb/>Delhi-110 006. <lb/>2. Dinesh s/o Gopichand Gupta, <lb/>Proprietor of M/s. Dinesh Associates, <lb/>R/o D-145, &quot;Priyadarshini Vihar&quot;, <lb/>Opp. Lovely Public School, <lb/>Shahadara, Delhi. <lb/>...Respondent/ <lb/>Accused <lb/>Criminal Application No.2426 of 2008 <lb/>In <lb/>Criminal Appeal No.392 of 2008 <lb/>M/s. Jinraj Paper Udyog, <lb/>2/26, Ansari Road, Delhi, <lb/>Office also at Jejani Sadan, <lb/>Itwari Bhaji Mandi, Nagpur, <lb/>through its Proprietor, <lb/>Jinraj s/o Ramkisan Jain. <lb/>... Applicant <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. M/s. Dinesh Associates, <lb/>Proprietorship Concern, <lb/>3796/2, Gali Lohe Wali, <lb/>Behind Namkeen Shop, <lb/>Charkhewalan, Chawari Bazar, <lb/>Delhi-110 006. <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<front>2. Dinesh s/o Gopichand Gupta, <lb/>Proprietor of M/s. Dinesh Associates, <lb/>R/o D-145, &quot;Priyadarshini Vihar&quot;, <lb/>Opp. Lovely Public School, <lb/>Shahadara, Delhi. <lb/>...Respondent/ <lb/>Accused <lb/>Criminal Application No.2428 of 2008 <lb/>In <lb/>Criminal Appeal No.393 of 2008 <lb/>M/s. Jinraj Paper Udyog, <lb/>2/26, Ansari Road, Delhi, <lb/>Office also at Jejani Sadan, <lb/>Itwari Bhaji Mandi, Nagpur, <lb/>through its Proprietor, <lb/>Jinraj s/o Ramkisan Jain. <lb/>... Applicant <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. M/s. Dinesh Associates, <lb/>Proprietorship Concern, <lb/>3796/2, Gali Lohe Wali, <lb/>Behind Namkeen Shop, <lb/>Charkhewalan, Chawari Bazar, <lb/>Delhi-110 006. <lb/>2. Dinesh s/o Gopichand Gupta, <lb/>Proprietor of M/s. Dinesh Associates, <lb/>R/o D-145, &quot;Priyadarshini Vihar&quot;, <lb/>Opp. Lovely Public School, <lb/>Shahadara, Delhi. <lb/>...Respondent/ <lb/>Accused <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/>5 <lb/>Criminal Application No.2427 of 2008 <lb/>In <lb/>Criminal Appeal No.399 of 2008 <lb/>M/s. Jinraj Paper Udyog, <lb/>2/26, Ansari Road, Delhi, <lb/>Office also at Jejani Sadan, <lb/>Itwari Bhaji Mandi, Nagpur, <lb/>through its Proprietor, <lb/>Jinraj s/o Ramkisan Jain. <lb/>... Applicant <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. M/s. Dinesh Associates, <lb/>Proprietorship Concern, <lb/>3796/2, Gali Lohe Wali, <lb/>Behind Namkeen Shop, <lb/>Charkhewalan, Chawari Bazar, <lb/>Delhi-110 006. <lb/>2. Dinesh s/o Gopichand Gupta, <lb/>Proprietor of M/s. Dinesh Associates, <lb/>R/o D-145, &quot;Priyadarshini Vihar&quot;, <lb/>Opp. Lovely Public School, <lb/>Shahadara, Delhi. <lb/>...Respondent/ <lb/>Accused <lb/>Criminal Appeal No.390 of 2008 <lb/>M/s. Jinraj Paper Udyog, <lb/>2/26, Ansari Road, Delhi, <lb/>Office also at Jejani Sadan, <lb/>Itwari Bhaji Mandi, Nagpur, <lb/>through its Proprietor, <lb/>Jinraj s/o Ramkisan Jain. <lb/>... Appellant <lb/>Versus <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></front>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<front>1. M/s. Dinesh Associates, <lb/>Proprietorship Concern, <lb/>3796/2, Gali Lohe Wali, <lb/>Behind Namkeen Shop, <lb/>Charkhewalan, Chawari Bazar, <lb/>Delhi-110 006. <lb/>2. Dinesh s/o Gopichand Gupta, <lb/>Proprietor of M/s. Dinesh Associates, <lb/>R/o D-145, &quot;Priyadarshini Vihar&quot;, <lb/>Opp. Lovely Public School, <lb/>Shahadara, Delhi. <lb/>...Respondent/ <lb/>Accused <lb/>Criminal Appeal No.391 of 2008 <lb/>M/s. Jinraj Paper Udyog, <lb/>2/26, Ansari Road, Delhi, <lb/>Office also at Jejani Sadan, <lb/>Itwari Bhaji Mandi, Nagpur, <lb/>through its Proprietor, <lb/>Jinraj s/o Ramkisan Jain. <lb/>... Appellant <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. M/s. Dinesh Associates, <lb/>Proprietorship Concern, <lb/>3796/2, Gali Lohe Wali, <lb/>Behind Namkeen Shop, <lb/>Charkhewalan, Chawari Bazar, <lb/>Delhi-110 006. <lb/>2. Dinesh s/o Gopichand Gupta, <lb/>Proprietor of M/s. Dinesh Associates, <lb/>R/o D-145, &quot;Priyadarshini Vihar&quot;, <lb/>Opp. Lovely Public School, <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<front>Shahadara, Delhi. <lb/>...Respondent/ <lb/>Accused <lb/>Criminal Appeal No.392 of 2008 <lb/>M/s. Jinraj Paper Udyog, <lb/>2/26, Ansari Road, Delhi, <lb/>Office also at Jejani Sadan, <lb/>Itwari Bhaji Mandi, Nagpur, <lb/>through its Proprietor, <lb/>Jinraj s/o Ramkisan Jain. <lb/>... Appellant <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. M/s. Dinesh Associates, <lb/>Proprietorship Concern, <lb/>3796/2, Gali Lohe Wali, <lb/>Behind Namkeen Shop, <lb/>Charkhewalan, Chawari Bazar, <lb/>Delhi-110 006. <lb/>2. Dinesh s/o Gopichand Gupta, <lb/>Proprietor of M/s. Dinesh Associates, <lb/>R/o D-145, &quot;Priyadarshini Vihar&quot;, <lb/>Opp. Lovely Public School, <lb/>Shahadara, Delhi. <lb/>...Respondent/ <lb/>Accused <lb/>Criminal Appeal No.393 of 2008 <lb/>M/s. Jinraj Paper Udyog, <lb/>2/26, Ansari Road, Delhi, <lb/>Office also at Jejani Sadan, <lb/>Itwari Bhaji Mandi, Nagpur, <lb/>through its Proprietor, <lb/>Jinraj s/o Ramkisan Jain. <lb/>... Appellant <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<front>Versus <lb/>1. M/s. Dinesh Associates, <lb/>Proprietorship Concern, <lb/>3796/2, Gali Lohe Wali, <lb/>Behind Namkeen Shop, <lb/>Charkhewalan, Chawari Bazar, <lb/>Delhi-110 006. <lb/>2. Dinesh s/o Gopichand Gupta, <lb/>Proprietor of M/s. Dinesh Associates, <lb/>R/o D-145, &quot;Priyadarshini Vihar&quot;, <lb/>Opp. Lovely Public School, <lb/>Shahadara, Delhi. <lb/>...Respondent/ <lb/>Accused <lb/>Criminal Appeal No.399 of 2008 <lb/>M/s. Jinraj Paper Udyog, <lb/>2/26, Ansari Road, Delhi, <lb/>Office also at Jejani Sadan, <lb/>Itwari Bhaji Mandi, Nagpur, <lb/>through its Proprietor, <lb/>Jinraj s/o Ramkisan Jain. <lb/>... Appellant <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. M/s. Dinesh Associates, <lb/>Proprietorship Concern, <lb/>3796/2, Gali Lohe Wali, <lb/>Behind Namkeen Shop, <lb/>Charkhewalan, Chawari Bazar, <lb/>Delhi-110 006. <lb/>2. Dinesh s/o Gopichand Gupta, <lb/>Proprietor of M/s. Dinesh Associates, <lb/>::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/>9 <lb/>R/o D-145, &quot;Priyadarshini Vihar&quot;, <lb/>Opp. Lovely Public School, <lb/>Shahadara, Delhi. <lb/>...Respondent/ <lb/>Accused <lb/>Shri R.P. Joshi, Advocate for Applicant/Appellant. <lb/>S/Shri Anand.S. Joshi, and Shri D.M. Gabhane, Advocates for Respondent. <lb/></front>

			<body>Coram : R.C. Chavan, J. <lb/>Date of Reserving the Judgment : 23-10-2008 <lb/>Date of Pronouncing the Judgment : 10-11-2008 <lb/>JUDGMENT : <lb/>Criminal Application Nos.2424, 2425, 2426, 2427 and 2428 of 2008 <lb/>By these applications under Section 378(4) of the Code of <lb/>Criminal Procedure Code original complainant seeks leave to file appeals <lb/>against the judgments of acquittal rendered by the learned Judicial <lb/>Magistrate First Class, Nagpur in five Summary Criminal Cases relating to <lb/>office punishable under Section 138 of the Negotiable Instruments Act. <lb/>When the applications and appeals were first listed, notice of final disposal <lb/>was directed to be issued. Thereafter R &amp; P too was called and has been <lb/>received. In view of this, leave to file appeals granted. The applications are <lb/>allowed. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<front>Criminal Appeal Nos.390, 391, 392, 393 and 399 of 2008 <lb/></front>

			<body>1. <lb/>These five appeals are directed against the judgments of <lb/>acquittal rendered by the learned Judicial Magistrate First Class, Nagpur in <lb/>five criminal complaints in respect of offences punishable under Section 138 <lb/>of the Negotiable Instruments Act. <lb/>2. <lb/>Facts which occasioned filing of those complaints are <lb/>identical. There is substantially no dispute about facts which are material <lb/>for deciding these appeals. Between 24-5-2002 and 24-3-2003, the <lb/>complainant supplied paper worth Rs.20,38,357/-to accused No.1, whose <lb/>proprietor is accused No.2. Both the complainant and accused ordinarily do <lb/>their business at Delhi and paper was supplied at Delhi. Five cheques of <lb/>Rs.60,000/-each, drawn on Indian Overseas Bank, Delhi were delivered by <lb/>the accused to complainant towards these dues. These cheques were lodged <lb/>by the complainant for collection with his bank in Nagpur, where he claims <lb/>to have an office. The bank on which the cheques were drawn, i.e. Indian <lb/>Overseas Bank, Delhi, intimated to the complainant&apos;s bankers that the <lb/>cheques were dishonoured, and the said bank, in turn, sent intimation of <lb/>dishonour to complainant. The complainant sent notices of demand from <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>his Nagpur office to the accused, which were duly received by them. As the <lb/>accused failed to pay, the complainant filed five complaint cases before the <lb/>learned Judicial Magistrate First Class, Nagpur on 3-2-2004. <lb/>3. <lb/>Upon issuance of process, accused appeared, pleaded not <lb/>guilty, but did not raise any question about jurisdiction of the Courts at <lb/>Nagpur to entertain the complaints. Complainant tendered affidavits in <lb/>evidence on 26-7-2006 in these cases and was cross-examined. <lb/>4. <lb/>On 4-9-2006, this Court (in fact, I) delivered a judgment in <lb/>Ahuja S/o Nandkishore Dongre Vs. State of Maharashtra and another, <lb/>reported at 2006 ALL MR (Cri) 3357, in respect of jurisdiction in cases of <lb/>offence punishable under Section 138 of the Negotiable Instruments Act, <lb/>holding that presentation of a cheque contemplated its presentation to the <lb/>drawee bank. This judgment is reportedly challenged before the Hon&apos;ble <lb/>Supreme Court by filing a Special Leave Petition on 2-2-2007 in which the <lb/>Apex Court is stated to have issued notice. <lb/>5. <lb/>On 13-11-2007, the accused filed his own affidavits, and <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>examined himself in defence. By judgment dated 2-5-2008, the learned <lb/>Magistrate proceeded to acquit the accused in all the five cases relying on <lb/>my judgment in Ahuja Nandkishore Dongre&apos;s case. <lb/>6. <lb/>The learned counsel for the appellant fairly concedes that <lb/>the entire transaction had in fact taken place in Delhi. However, he states <lb/>that since such cases take a longer time for decision in Courts in Delhi, his <lb/>client chose to lodge the cheques for collection with a bank at Nagpur and <lb/>also issued a notice from an office located at Nagpur in a business <lb/>associate&apos;s premises, so that he could lodge a complaint in Nagpur Courts, <lb/>where adjudication is comparatively faster. According to him, if law <lb/>permitted this course, there was nothing wrong in choosing a forum. <lb/>7. <lb/>His learned adversary submitted that in fact complainant <lb/>does not have any office in Nagpur. No registration under the Shops and <lb/>Establishments Act or other document is produced to show that there is such <lb/>an office. He was informed that even the account in bank at Nagpur, in <lb/>which the cheques were lodged, was opened just a day before the cheques <lb/>were actually lodged, though, no document to that effect is produced. The <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>learned counsel for the respondent further submitted that in face of my <lb/>judgment in Ahuja Nandkishore Dongre&apos;s case, which was binding on the <lb/>learned Magistrate, the Magistrate could not have decided the case <lb/>differently. <lb/>8. <lb/>In this factual context, the rival contentions would have to <lb/>be examined. The learned counsel for the appellant is correct in contending <lb/>that if the learned Magistrate held that he had no jurisdiction, the only <lb/>course open to him was to return the complaint under Section 201 of the <lb/>Code of Criminal Procedure for presentation to proper Court. In fact, such <lb/>is the direction in Ahuja Nandkishore Dongre&apos;s case. Therefore, acquittal of <lb/>respondent by a Court professing lack of jurisdiction is unsustainable. <lb/>9. <lb/>The learned counsel for the appellant next submitted that <lb/>the judgment in <lb/>Ahuja Nandkishore Dongre&apos;s case was delivered <lb/>on 4-9-2006, long after the complaints were filed on 3-2-2004. No <lb/>objection had been raised to the jurisdiction of the Court till practically the <lb/>trial was over and, therefore, such objection could not have entertained by <lb/>the learned Magistrate. He submitted that in Ahuja Nandkishore Dongre&apos;s <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>case, the accused had filed an application taking objection to jurisdiction of <lb/>the Court immediately after process was issued and had approached this <lb/>Court under Section 482 of the Code of Criminal Procedure upon rejection <lb/>of his application. Such were not the facts in this bunch of cases. <lb/>Therefore, the judgment in <lb/>Ahuja Nandkishore Dongre&apos;s case was <lb/>inapplicable. He pointed out that Section 462 of the Code of Criminal <lb/>Procedure even leaves undisturbed judgments rendered by Courts which <lb/>lacked territorial jurisdiction, unless it appears that such error has in fact <lb/>occasioned a failure of justice. Here, according to the learned counsel for <lb/>the appellant, far from there being any failure of justice, there is not even <lb/>any prejudice shown to have been caused. He submitted that it was unfair <lb/>on the part of the accused to participate in the trial without a demur and <lb/>take advantage of a judgment which came much after the case was filed. <lb/>10. <lb/>The learned counsel for the respondent submitted that law <lb/>has not changed on account of judgment in Ahuja Nandkishore Dongre&apos;s <lb/>case, which merely explained the ratio of judgment in the case of K. <lb/>Bhaskaran Vs. Sankaran Vaidhyan Balan, reported at 1999 ALL MR (Cri) <lb/>1845 (S.C.). In any case, a judgment, declaratory of law, would apply even <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>on the date the appellant filed criminal complaints before the learned <lb/>Magistrate. Further, according to the learned counsel, occasions for an <lb/>accused to disclose his stand would arise first, only in course of cross-<lb/>examination of complainant, which the accused had done by eliciting in the <lb/>cross-examination that the lis had no causal connection with the forum. He <lb/>further submitted that accused could undoubtedly have followed the course <lb/>chosen by Ahuja Dongre, namely, applying for objecting to jurisdiction, but, <lb/>failure to do so has no consequences, since accused was under no duty or <lb/>obligation to follow only that course. <lb/>11. <lb/>The learned counsel for the respondent submitted that in <lb/>fact proper stage for raising jurisdictional question is the trial itself and this <lb/>Court had discouraged application under Section 482 of the Code of <lb/>Criminal Procedure for quashing a complaint on account of lack of <lb/>jurisdiction in A. Chinnaswami Vs. M/s. Bilakchand Gyanchand Company, <lb/>reported at 1998(3) Bom.C.R. 120. In that case too, jurisdiction of Court of <lb/>Judicial Magistrate First Class, Chopada was invoked because cheques were <lb/>&quot;presented&quot; at Chopada branch of State Bank of India, though the <lb/>transaction had allegedly taken place at Coimbatore. In this context, this <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>Court observed that the question of jurisdiction is a mixed question of fact <lb/>and law and that the learned Magistrate would have to record evidence with <lb/>respect to the fact as to the place where the transaction took place. In view <lb/>of this, it has to be held that the accused in the present case had raised the <lb/>objection at a proper stage. <lb/>12. <lb/>It is indeed correct that accused was not obliged to raise an <lb/>objection by specifically making an application and had sufficiently <lb/>indicated his stance at appropriate stage. Therefore, the learned Magistrate <lb/>was right in not shutting out this defence of the accused and rightly took it <lb/>into account. <lb/>13. <lb/>As for the argument based upon Section 462 of the Code of <lb/>Criminal Procedure, the learned counsel for the respondent submitted, and <lb/>rightly in my view, that a distinction has to be drawn in the case of one who <lb/>allows a judgment to be delivered without demur, and one, who raises the <lb/>defence at a stage of trial when he is obliged to do so. Therefore, the <lb/>contention that if a judgment could not be questioned, proceedings at trial <lb/>too were beyond reproach is fallacious. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>14. <lb/>The learned counsel for the appellant relied on judgment of <lb/>Supreme Court in State of M.P. Vs. Bhooraji and others, reported at (2001) 7 <lb/>SCC 679, where the Court held that a trial held before a competent Court <lb/>would not be vitiated by a procedural lapse. The High Court of Madhya <lb/>Pradesh in Meerabai Vs. Bhujbal Singh, reported at 1995 Cri LJ 2376 (MP), <lb/>had held that cases under the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes <lb/>(Prevention of Atrocities) Act needed to be committed to the Special Court <lb/>of Session. This was overruled by a Full Bench of the same Court, which <lb/>held that the Special Court could directly take cognizance without <lb/>commitment. This in turn was overruled by the Apex Court in Gangula <lb/>Ashok Vs. State of A.P., reported in (2000) 2 SCC 504, making commitment <lb/>necessary. Bhooraji&apos;s case was tried by appropriate Court, but without its <lb/>having been committed. The High Court ordered a fresh trial. On appeal, <lb/>the Supreme Court set aside the judgment, observing as under in para 21: <lb/>&quot;21. <lb/>The expression &quot;a court of competent jurisdiction&quot; <lb/>envisaged in Section 465 is to denote a validly constituted <lb/>court conferred with jurisdiction to try the offence or offences. <lb/>Such a court will not get denuded of its competence to try the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>case on account of any procedural lapse and the competence <lb/>would remain unaffected by the non-compliance with the <lb/>procedural requirement. The inability to take cognizance of <lb/>an offence without a committal order does not mean that a <lb/>duly constituted court became an incompetent court for all <lb/>purposes. If an objection was raised in that court at the <lb/>earliest occasion on the ground that the case should have been <lb/>committed by a Magistrate, the same specified court has to <lb/>exercise a jurisdiction either for sending the records to a <lb/>Magistrate for adopting committal proceedings or return the <lb/>police report to the Public Prosecutor or the police for <lb/>presentation before the Magistrate. Even this could be done <lb/>only because the court has competence to deal with the case. <lb/>Sometimes that court may have to hear arguments to decide <lb/>that preliminary issue. Hence the argument advanced by the <lb/>learned counsel on the strength of the aforesaid decisions is of <lb/>no avail.&quot; <lb/>15. <lb/>It may be seen that in Bhooraji&apos;s case, it was not that the <lb/>Court which tried the offenders had no jurisdiction. Upon commitment, the <lb/>case would have been tried by the same Court. Such is not the present case. <lb/>Here, the question whether Court at Nagpur has jurisdiction is very much in <lb/>issue. The question here is not of procedural lapse, but of the very <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>competence of the Court to take cognizance for want of jurisdiction. The <lb/>question here is not connected with procedural error covered by Section 465 <lb/>of the Code of Criminal Procedure, dealing with irregular proceedings, and <lb/>so Bhooraji&apos;s case has no application, as rightly contended by the learned <lb/>counsel for the respondent. <lb/>16. <lb/>In this view of the matter, it would be necessary to examine <lb/>whether the learned Judicial Magistrate, First Class, was right in concluding <lb/>that he lacked jurisdiction. The learned counsel for the respondent <lb/>submitted that in the face of judgment of this Court in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case, <lb/>the learned Magistrate could not have held otherwise and, therefore, the <lb/>judgment is unassailable. <lb/>17. <lb/>The learned counsel for the appellant submitted that <lb/>judgment in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case is itself rendered per incuriam and it was <lb/>impermissible for this Court to &quot;distinguish&quot; the ratio of judgment of the <lb/>Apex Court in K. Bhaskaran Vs. Sankaran Vaidhyan Balan, reported at <lb/>(1999) 7 SCC 510=AIR 1999 SC 3762. Therefore, according to the learned <lb/>counsel, the judgment in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case need not have been applied <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>and in any case, may not be applied, since it cannot stand with judgments of <lb/>Supreme Court on which the learned counsel sought to rely. <lb/>18. <lb/>Before going into the question whether Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case <lb/>was decided per incuriam, it would be useful to recount as to what was <lb/>decided by the Hon&apos;ble Apex Court in the case of K. Bhaskaran and how this <lb/>judgment was considered in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case. The material part of <lb/>observations of the Apex Court on the question of jurisdiction, contained in <lb/>paras 14 to 16 of the judgment as reported at AIR 1999 SC 3762 may be <lb/>usefully reproduced as under : <lb/>&quot;14. <lb/>The offence under Section 138 of the Act can be <lb/>completed only with the con-catenation of a number of acts. <lb/>Following are the acts which are components of the said <lb/>offence : (1) Drawing of the cheque, (2) Presentation of the <lb/>cheque to the bank, (3) Returning the cheque unpaid by the <lb/>drawee bank, (4) Giving notice in writing to the drawer of the <lb/>cheque demanding payment of the cheque amount, (5) failure <lb/>of the drawer to make payment within 15 days of the receipt <lb/>of the notice.&quot; <lb/>&quot;15. <lb/>It is not necessary that all the above five acts should <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>have been perpetrated at the same locality. It is possible that <lb/>each of those five acts could be done at 5 different localities. <lb/>But concatenation of all the above five is a sine qua non for <lb/>the completion of the offence under Section 138 of the Act. In <lb/>this context a reference to Section 178(d) of the Code is useful. <lb/>It is extracted below : <lb/>&quot;Where the offence consists of several acts done in <lb/>different local areas, it may be inquired into or tried by a <lb/>Court having jurisdiction over any of such local areas.&quot; <lb/>&quot;16. <lb/>Thus it is clear, if the five different acts were done in <lb/>five different localities any one of the Courts exercising <lb/>jurisdiction in one of the five local areas can become the place <lb/>of trial for the offence under Section 138 of the Act. In other <lb/>words, the complainant can choose any one of those Courts <lb/>having jurisdiction over any one of the local areas within the <lb/>territorial limits of which any one of those five acts was done. <lb/>As the amplitude stands so widened and so expansive it is an <lb/>idle exercise to raise jurisdictional question regarding the <lb/>offence under Section 138 of the Act.&quot; <lb/>The above observations were considered in paras 14, 15, 17 to 19, 22 and <lb/>23 in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case as under : <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>&quot;14. <lb/>In Bhaskaran&apos;s case, as a matter of fact, it was held <lb/>as proved that cheques in question have been issued at the <lb/>shop of P.W.3 within territorial limits of trial Court&apos;s <lb/>jurisdiction. The five ingredients enumerated by the Court in <lb/>paragraph 14 of the judgment would undisputedly attract the <lb/>provisions of Clause (d) of Section 178 of the Code of <lb/>Criminal Procedure, since it can be said that the offence <lb/>punishable under Section 138 of the Negotiable Instruments <lb/>Act consists of the five acts, enumerated in paragraph 14 of the <lb/>judgment. It may be seen that clauses (2) and (3) in <lb/>paragraph 14 of the judgment refer to presentation of &quot;the <lb/>cheque&quot; to &quot;the Bank&quot; and returning the cheque unpaid by <lb/>&quot;the drawee Bank&quot;. A reference to Section 138 of the <lb/>Negotiable Instruments Act, would also show that the section <lb/>begins, with reference to &quot;a banker&quot; and then goes on to refer <lb/>to &quot;the banker&quot;...... &quot;is returned by the bank&quot;, ...... &quot;by an <lb/>agreement made with that bank&quot;...... &quot;the cheque has been <lb/>presented to the bank within thirty days from information by <lb/>him to the bank&quot; etc. Thus, the reference to presentation of <lb/>the cheque or return of the cheque dishonoured is in relation <lb/>to the bank on which the cheque is drawn. Considering the <lb/>usage of indefinite articles &quot;a&quot; and &quot;an&quot; and definite article <lb/>&quot;the&quot; it would not be permissible to hold that reference to the <lb/>bank extends to any bank where the cheque is presented, or <lb/>any bank from which holder in due course eventually gets <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>information of dishonour. This is amply made clear by the <lb/>Apex Court by prefixing the words &quot;bank&quot; and &quot;drawee bank&quot; <lb/>in items (1) and (2) in paragraph 14 of the judgment with <lb/>definite article &quot;the&quot;.&quot; <lb/>&quot;15. <lb/>The Apex Court must have chosen to prefix the word <lb/>&quot;bank&quot; by definite article &quot;the&quot; in order to avoid the confusion <lb/>and problems that would be created by using indefinite article <lb/>&quot;a&quot;. A cheque is negotiable instrument and by appropriate <lb/>endorsement and delivery it can be negotiated. If instead of <lb/>the Courts at the place where the bank on which the cheque <lb/>was drawn, the Courts at the place where the cheque was <lb/>presented were to have jurisdiction, drawers of the cheque <lb/>would be exposed to an unforeseen risk. When a person issues <lb/>a cheque to another, he intends to make payment to that <lb/>another, for a consideration which he has received at the bank <lb/>on which the cheque is drawn. That other, may, in turn, <lb/>negotiate the cheque in favour of third person for a liability <lb/>which that other may have to discharge towards such third <lb/>person. The drawer of the cheque cannot be said to have <lb/>foreseen that, by such negotiation, his cheque would land at <lb/>place far away from the place at which it was meant to be <lb/>paid, making him liable to be hauled up in a Court at a place <lb/>where the cheque was presented by the holder in due course. <lb/>Therefore, with utmost humility and with great respect to the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>observations made by Andhra Pradesh High Court, it is <lb/>difficult to deduce the ratio elicited by the Andhra Pradesh <lb/>High Court, from the observations of the Supreme Court from <lb/>K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case. It must be held that the observations in <lb/>Bhaskaran&apos;s case do not support such a view of law.&quot; <lb/>&quot;17. <lb/>While creating an offence punishable under Section <lb/>138 of the Negotiable Instruments Act, the parliament has not <lb/>changed the whole scheme of the Act. Under Section 6 of the <lb/>Act, a cheque is still defined at a bill of exchange, drawn on a <lb/>specified banker. The &quot;drawee&quot; is the person directed to pay <lb/>under Section 7, and Section 61 requires that a bill of <lb/>exchange has to be presented to &quot;the drawee&quot; (&amp; not to any <lb/>banker), and if the bill is directed to a drawee at a particular <lb/>place, it must be presented at that place. Section 72 makes the <lb/>requirement in respect of a cheque clear and lays down as <lb/>under : <lb/>&quot;72. Presentment of cheque to charge drawer :--<lb/>(Subject to the provisions of Section 84) a cheque must, in <lb/>order to charge the drawer, be presented at the bank upon <lb/>which if is drawn before the relation between the drawer and <lb/>his banker has been altered to the prejudice of the drawer.&quot; <lb/>Since all these provisions are left intact a cheque has <lb/>to be presented to the drawee bank at the place mentioned on <lb/>the cheque.&quot; <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>&quot;19. <lb/>The choice of definite article &quot;the&quot; by the Apex Court <lb/>in items (1) and (2) in paragraph 14 of Bhaskaran&apos;s judgment <lb/>merely gives effect to these statutory requirements.&quot; <lb/>&quot;22. <lb/>The words in paragraph 16 of the judgment <lb/>regarding widened amplitude have to be read in this <lb/>background. The Apex Court must not be understood to have <lb/>held that question of jurisdiction in a proceeding for offence <lb/>punishable under Section 138 of N.I. Act is utterly irrelevant, <lb/>or that there is absolutely no restriction on the choice of place <lb/>of suing. These observations have to be read in the context of <lb/>what is held in paragraph 14 and therefore the amplitude <lb/>must be taken to have widened to the extent indicated in <lb/>paragraph 14.&quot; <lb/>&quot;23. <lb/>Same holds good about observations in paragraph <lb/>12 of Bhaskaran&apos;s judgment in respect of the word &quot;ordinarily&quot; <lb/>appearing in Section 177, Cr.P.C. The Apex Court must be <lb/>understood to have held that ordinarily the place of suing <lb/>must have a nexus to the lis, but upon making out a case for <lb/>deviating from this rule, action could be initiated even at some <lb/>other place. It is not the word &quot;Ordinarily&quot; gives an unbridled <lb/>freedom to a complainant to choose his forum for hauling up <lb/>an accused.&quot; <lb/>(Emphasis supplied) <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>It may thus be seen that this Court had neither <lb/>&quot;distinguished&quot; judgment of the Apex Court in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case, nor had <lb/>held that any part of the observations were not applicable. At the cost of <lb/>repetition, it may be useful to re-state as to how the judgment in K. <lb/>Bhaskaran&apos;s case was understood by this Court. <lb/>19. <lb/>In K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case, the Apex Court held that <lb/>&quot;presentation of the cheque to the bank&quot; was a component of the said <lb/>offence. In Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case too, this dictum is followed. The Hon&apos;ble <lb/>Apex Court had chosen the word &quot;presentation&quot; and had also added article <lb/>&quot;the&quot; before the word &quot;bank&quot;. In para 17 of the judgment in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s <lb/>case quoted above, the scheme of the Negotiable Instruments Act is <lb/>considered and what amounts to &quot;presentation&quot; is discussed. It is impossible <lb/>to even contend that the Hon&apos;ble Apex Court would have in contemplation <lb/>some meaning of the word &quot;presentation&quot; different than one warranted by <lb/>the provisions of the Negotiable Instruments Act. <lb/>20. <lb/>When a payee of a cheque lodges (and not &quot;presents&quot;) a <lb/>cheque to his banker for collection, his banker, as his agent, &quot;presents&quot; it to <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>the drawee bank. Question of dishonour would arise only after it is <lb/>&quot;presented&quot; to the drawee bank. If colloquially people believe that they <lb/>&quot;present&quot; a cheque drawn on a different bank to their banker, it does neither <lb/>alter law nor banking practice. Therefore, the signifance of article &quot;the&quot; <lb/>prefixed by the Apex Court to the word &quot;bank&quot; was emphasized. <lb/>21. <lb/>The fourth component enumerated in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case, <lb/>namely, &quot;(4) Giving notice in writing to the drawer of the cheque demanding <lb/>payment of the cheque amount&quot;, had been applied and it was observed in <lb/>para 27 of the judgment in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case that since payment was <lb/>demanded to be made to the client, whose address in the notice showed that <lb/>he was residing outside the jurisdiction of the concerned Court, the Court <lb/>had no jurisdiction. The other three components were not attracted to the <lb/>facts of that case. <lb/>22. <lb/>As to the following observations in para 16 in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s <lb/>case, &quot;As the amplitude stands so widened and so expansive it is an idle <lb/>exercise to raise jurisdictional question regarding offence under Section 138 <lb/>of the Act&quot;, in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case in para 22 quoted above, it has been held <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>that the observations must be read in the context of five components of the <lb/>offence enumerated in para 14 of K. Bhaskaran&apos;s judgment. To contend <lb/>that jurisdictional question has become irrelevant and that irrespective of <lb/>the fact that none of the five components occurred within the jurisdiction of <lb/>a Court, it could entertain a complaint, would amount to reading sentences <lb/>out of context. <lb/>23. <lb/>That in spite of &quot;wide amplitude&quot;, jurisdictional question is <lb/>still relevant is clear from a later judgment of the Hon&apos;ble Apex Court in <lb/>Mosaraf Hossain Khan Vs. Bhagheeratha Engg. Ltd. and others, reported at <lb/>AIR 2006 SC 1288= (2006) 3 SCC 658. Complainant in that case had filed <lb/>complaints in the Court of Chief Judicial Magistrate, Birbhum at Suri in <lb/>respect of several cheques that had been dishonoured. The respondent <lb/>(accused Company) had undertaken work of construction of major bridges <lb/>in West Bengal. The complainant was supplying crushed stone aggregates. <lb/>In respect of the amount outstanding towards supply of raw material, the <lb/>accused Company had issued post-dated cheques from the registered office <lb/>of the Company in Kerala. The cheques were deposited by the complainant <lb/>with Mayurakhi Gramin Bank, Suri Branch and were returned by the banker <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body>stating &quot;full cover not received&quot;. Upon service of notice of demand, a part <lb/>of the sum was paid, leaving a big balance. The Chief Judicial Magistrate <lb/>issued process on the complaints and summonses were served at Kolabhat, <lb/>Midnapore, West Bengal. Instead of appearing before the Chief Judicial <lb/>Magistrate, the accused filed a writ petition before the High Court of Kerala <lb/>for quashing the complaints. The accused Company contended that since <lb/>the cheques were issued from registered office of the Company in Kerala, a <lb/>part of cause of action arose within the State of Kerala. <lb/>24. <lb/>The High Court of Kerala entertained the petition and <lb/>granted interim reliefs. After considering the question of jurisdiction of the <lb/>High Court to entertain in such a petition, the Apex Court also considered <lb/>the question as to which Magisterial Court would have jurisdiction to <lb/>entertain the complaints. After considering decision in OM Hemrajani Vs. <lb/>State of U.P. and another, reported at (2005) 1 SCC 617, about jurisdiction <lb/>in cases of offences committed abroad, the Apex Court held as under : <lb/>&quot;31. <lb/>A bare perusal of the complaint petition would <lb/>clearly go to show that according to the complainant the entire <lb/>cause of action arose within the jurisdiction of the District <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<body>Court of Birbhum and in that view of the matter it is that <lb/>court which will have jurisdiction to take cognisance of the <lb/>offence. In fact the jurisdiction of the Court of CJM, Birbhum, <lb/>Suri, is not in question. It is not contended that the <lb/>complainant had suppressed material fact and which if not <lb/>disclosed would have demonstrated that the offence was <lb/>committed outside the jurisdiction of the said court. Even if <lb/>Section 178 of the Code of Criminal Procedure is attracted, the <lb/>Court of the Chief Judicial Magistrate, Birbhum will alone <lb/>have jurisdiction in the matter.&quot; <lb/>&quot;32. <lb/>Sending of cheques from Erakulam or the <lb/>respondents having an office at that place did not form an <lb/>integral part of &quot;cause of action&quot; for which the complaint <lb/>petition was filed by the appellant and cognisance of the <lb/>offence under Section 138 of the Negotiable Instruments Act, <lb/>1881 was taken by the Chief Judicial Magistrate, Suri. We <lb/>may moreover notice that the situs of the accused wherefor <lb/>jurisdiction of a court can be invoked and which is an <lb/>exception to the aforementioned provisions as contained in <lb/>Section 188 of the Code of Criminal Procedure recently came <lb/>up for consideration by this Court in Om Hemrajani v. State of <lb/>U.P. It was held that the said provisions may be interpreted <lb/>widely. The law was laid down in the following terms: (SCC <lb/>pp. 621-22, paras 8-9) <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body>&quot;8. <lb/>Section 177 postulates that ordinarily <lb/>offence shall be inquired into and tried by a court <lb/>within whose local jurisdiction it was committed. <lb/>Section 178, inter alia, deals with situations when it <lb/>is uncertain in which of several local areas an offence <lb/>is committed or partly committed in one area and <lb/>partly in another. The section provides that the <lb/>offence can be inquired into or tried by a court <lb/>having jurisdiction over any of the local areas <lb/>mentioned therein. ...&quot; <lb/>9. ... <lb/>&quot;33. <lb/>In this case, the averments made in the writ petition <lb/>filed by the respondent herein even if given face value and <lb/>taken to be correct in their entirety would not confer any <lb/>jurisdiction upon the Kerala High Court. The agreement was <lb/>entered into within the jurisdiction of the Calcutta High <lb/>Court. The project for which the supply of stone chips and <lb/>transportation was being carried out was also within the State <lb/>of West Bengal. Payments were obviously required to be made <lb/>within the jurisdiction of the said Court where either the <lb/>contract had been entered into or where payment was to be <lb/>made&quot; <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<body>&quot;34. <lb/>The appellant did not deny or dispute any of the <lb/>averments made in the complaint petition. In the writ <lb/>petition it merely wanted some time to make the payment. It <lb/>is now well known that the object of the provision of Section <lb/>138 of the Act is that for proper and smooth functioning of <lb/>business transaction in particular, use of cheques as <lb/>negotiable instruments would primarily depend upon the <lb/>integrity and honesty of the parties. It was noticed that <lb/>cheques used to be issued as a device inter alia for defrauding <lb/>the creditors and stalling the payments. It was also noticed in <lb/>a number of decisions of this Court that dishonour of a cheque <lb/>by the bank causes incalculable loss, injury and inconvenience <lb/>to the payee and the entire credibility of the business <lb/>transactions within and outside the country suffers a serious <lb/>setback. It was also found that the remedy available in a civil <lb/>court is a long-drawn process and an unscrupulous drawer <lb/>normally takes various pleas to defeat the genuine claim of the <lb/>payee.&quot; <lb/>&quot;35. <lb/>In Prem Chand Vijay Kumar v. Yashpal Singh <lb/>[(2005) 4 SCC 417] we may, however, notice that it was held <lb/>that for securing conviction under the Negotiable Instruments <lb/>Act, 1881 the facts which are required to be proved are: (SCC <lb/>p. 423, para 10) <lb/>&quot;10. (a) that the cheque was drawn for payment of <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body>an amount of money for discharge of a debt/liability and the <lb/>cheque was dishonoured; <lb/>(b) that the cheque was presented within the <lb/>prescribed period; <lb/>(c) <lb/>that the payee made a demand for payment of <lb/>the money by giving a notice in writing to the drawer within <lb/>the stipulated period; and <lb/>(d) that the drawer failed to make the payment <lb/>within 15 days of the receipt of the notice.&quot; <lb/>&quot;36. <lb/>For the purpose of proving the aforementioned <lb/>ingredients of the offence under Section 138 of the Act, the <lb/>complainant appellant was required to prove the facts <lb/>constituting the cause of action therefor none of which arose <lb/>within the jurisdiction of the Kerala High Court. It is apt to <lb/>mention that in Prem Chand Vijay Kumar this Court held that <lb/>cause of action within the meaning of Section 142(b) of the <lb/>Act can arise only once.&quot; <lb/>The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court then allowed the appeal, setting aside orders by <lb/>the Kerala High Court. Had the question of jurisdiction become irrelevant <lb/>the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court would not have said so. It may be recalled that <lb/>the Supreme Court not only held that Courts at Birbhum, Suri had <lb/>jurisdiction (because in any case some part of cause of action arose there), <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<body>but held that the entire cause of action arose within the jurisdiction of <lb/>District Court of Birbhum, in spite of the fact that cheques were allegedly <lb/>issued from Kerala. It ruled that sending cheques from Ernakulam did not <lb/>form an integral part of cause of action. Para 33 of the judgment quoted <lb/>above is decisive of what would be crucial in determining jurisdiction in <lb/>such cases. <lb/>25. <lb/>It is true that the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court had not <lb/>considered judgment in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case while making these <lb/>observations. But it would be impermissible to even suggest that the Apex <lb/>Court had not considered if &quot;drawing of the cheque&quot;, enumerated as the first <lb/>component in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case, had a bearing on the question of <lb/>jurisdiction in cases under Section 138 of the Negotiable Instruments Act or <lb/>not. In fact, this aspect was considered and yet the Court held that it was <lb/>not an integral part of cause of action. <lb/>26. <lb/>In Premchand Vijay Kumar Vs. Yashpal Singh, reported at <lb/>2005(4) Mh.L.J. 100, which had been referred to in Mosaraf Hossain&apos;s case, <lb/>the question was not of jurisdiction, but that of cause of action to file a <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body>complaint of offence punishable under Section 138 of the Negotiable <lb/>Instrument Act. In that case, a notice making demand was made first <lb/>on 17-2-1995. Cheque was presented again on 6-7-1995 and after it was <lb/>dishonoured fresh notice of demand was sent on 24-7-1995 and, therefore, <lb/>complaint was filed. In this context, the Court held as under in paras 9 <lb/>and 10. <lb/>&quot;9. <lb/>In a generic and wide sense (as in section 20 of the <lb/>Civil Procedure Code, 1908 (in short &apos;CPC&apos;) &quot;cause of action&quot; <lb/>means every fact which it is necessary to establish to support a <lb/>right or obtain a judgment. Viewed in that context, the <lb/>following facts are required to be proved to successfully <lb/>prosecute the drawer for an offence under Section 138 of the <lb/>Act : <lb/>(a) <lb/>that the cheque was drawn for payment of an <lb/>amount of money for discharge of a debt/liability <lb/>and the cheque was dishonoured; <lb/>(b) <lb/>that the cheque was presented within the prescribed <lb/>period; <lb/>(c) <lb/>that the payee made a demand for payment of the <lb/>money by giving a notice in writing to the drawer <lb/>within the stipulated period; and <lb/>(d) <lb/>that the drawer failed to make the payment within <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<body>15 days of the receipt of the notice.&quot; <lb/>&quot;10. <lb/>Proceeding on the basis of the generic meaning of the <lb/>term cause of action, certainly each of the above facts would <lb/>constitute a part of the cause of action but clause (b) of section <lb/>142 gives it a restrictive meaning, in that, it refers to only one <lb/>fact which will give rise to the cause of action and that is the <lb/>failure to make the payment within 15 days from the date of <lb/>the receipt of the notice. A combined reading of sections 138 <lb/>and 142 makes it clear that cause of action is to be reckoned <lb/>accordingly. The combined reading of the above two sections <lb/>of the Act leaves no room for doubt that cause of action within <lb/>the meaning of section 142(c) arises -and can arise -only <lb/>once.&quot; <lb/>This is the observation which was referred to by the Apex Court in Mosaraf <lb/>Hossain&apos;s case. <lb/>27. <lb/>Judgment in Mosaraf Hossain Khan&apos;s case, in my humble <lb/>view, would show that :-<lb/>(1) Jurisdictional question is very much relevant in cases <lb/>under Section 138 of the Negotiable Instruments Act. <lb/>(2) Place where transaction took place and where <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<body>payment was intended to be made would be an <lb/>important relevant consideration in deciding <lb/>jurisdictional issue, and <lb/>(3) Place where the cheque in question was issued in itself <lb/>is not decisive (and as a corollary, each of the five <lb/>components enumerated in K. Bhaskaran, taken <lb/>individually though relevant, may not be decisive of <lb/>the matter) <lb/>28. <lb/>The last aspect in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s judgment, which has <lb/>been discussed in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case is about the observations about the <lb/>word &quot;ordinarily&quot; appearing in Section 177 of the Code of Criminal <lb/>Procedure. It cannot be contended that use of word &quot;Ordinarily&quot; enables a <lb/>party to approach any criminal Court anywhere irrespective of whether it <lb/>has any nexus to the lis or to the parties. <lb/>29. <lb/>This takes me to the questions whether it was impermissible <lb/>for this Court to take such a course and whether the judgment is rendered <lb/>per incuriam. Both the learned counsel for the parties painstakingly took me <lb/>through all the relevant judgments on which they could lay hands on the <lb/>question of &quot;precedent&quot;, &quot;stare decisis&quot;, &quot;ratio decidendi&quot; and &quot;obiter dicta&quot;. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<body>It is settled legal position that even obiter dicta of the Supreme Court are <lb/>binding on all the Courts in India, in the absence of a direct pronouncement <lb/>on the subject by the Supreme Court, as held in para 26 of the judgment in <lb/>para 26 of the judgment in Oriental Insurance Vs. Meena Variyal, reported at <lb/>2007(5) SCC 428. As the foregoing enumeration would show, it is clear that <lb/>dicta of the Hon&apos;ble Apex Court in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case have been followed. <lb/>If the judgment in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case gives an impression that law laid <lb/>down by the Hon&apos;ble Apex Court has not been followed in letter and spirit, it <lb/>may only be an regrettable lapse in articulation. The attempt, in fact, was to <lb/>discern correctly as to what the Apex Court had ruled in order to accurately <lb/>apply it to the facts of the said case. <lb/>30. <lb/>In Emkay Exports, Mumbai and another Vs. Madhusudan <lb/>Shrikrishna, reported at 2008(4) Mh.L.J. 843, on which the learned counsel <lb/>for the respondent placed reliance, a Full Bench of this Court, speaking <lb/>through the Hon&apos;ble the Chief Justice, considered the concepts of precedent, <lb/>ratio, stare decisis in the following erudite words : <lb/>&quot;6. <lb/>The concept of precedent has attained important <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<body>role in administration of justice in the modern times. The case <lb/>before the Court should be decided in accordance with law and <lb/>the doctrines. The mind of the Court should be clearly <lb/>reflecting on the material in issue with regard to the facts of <lb/>the case. The reason and spirit of case make law and not the <lb/>letter of a particular precedent. Halsbury&apos;s &quot;The Laws of <lb/>England&quot;, explained the word &quot;ratio decidendi&quot; as &quot;It may be <lb/>laid down as a general rule that that part alone of a decision <lb/>by a Court of Law is binding upon Courts of coordinate <lb/>jurisdiction and inferior Courts which consists of the <lb/>enunciation of the reason or principle upon which the question <lb/>before the Court has really been determined. This underlying <lb/>principle which forms the only authoritative element of a <lb/>precedent is often termed the ratio decidendi.&quot; It is by the <lb/>choice of material facts that the Court create law. The law so <lb/>created would be a good precedent for similar subsequent cases <lb/>unless it falls within the exceptions hereinafter indicated.&quot; <lb/>&quot;7. <lb/>The doctrine of precedent relates to following of <lb/>previous decisions within its limitations. It introduces the <lb/>concept of finality and adherence to the previous decisions and <lb/>while attaining it, it creates consistency in application of law. <lb/>The later judgment should be similar to the earlier judgment, <lb/>which on material facts are the same. Finding ratio decidendi <lb/>is not a mechanical process but an art which one gradually <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>40 <lb/></page>

			<body>acquires through practice. What is really involved in finding <lb/>the ratio decidendi of a case is the process of abstraction. <lb/>Ratio decidendi is a term used in contrast to obiter dictum <lb/>which is not necessarily binding in law. According to Sir John <lb/>Salmond, &quot;a precedent is a judicial decision, which contains in <lb/>itself a principle. <lb/>The only principle which forms its <lb/>authoritative element is often termed the &apos;ratio decidendi&apos;. The <lb/>concrete decision is binding between the parties to it, but it is <lb/>the abstract ratio decidendi which alone has the force of law <lb/>as regards the world at large&quot;. According to Austin, the <lb/>general reasons or principles of judicial decisions abstracted <lb/>from peculiarities of the case are commonly styled by writers <lb/>on jurisprudence as &apos;ratio decidendi&apos;.&quot; <lb/>&quot;10 <lb/>The Hon&apos;ble Apex Court further observed that a <lb/>caution need to be taken while applying the principle of <lb/>judicial precedents as decision of the Court and its <lb/>observations must be read in context in which they appear. In <lb/>a judgment discussion is meant to explain and not to define. <lb/>In this regard, reference can be made to the case of Haryana <lb/>Financial Corporation and anr. vs. M/s. Jagdamba Oil Mills <lb/>and anr., J.T. 2002(1) SC 484.&quot; <lb/>&quot;12. <lb/>In order to apply a judgment as a precedent, the <lb/>relevant laws and earlier judgment should be brought to the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>41 <lb/></page>

			<body>notice of the Court and they should be correctly applied. Mere <lb/>observations in a previous judgment may not be binding on a <lb/>subsequent Bench if they are not truly applicable to the facts <lb/>and controversies in a subsequent case as per settled principle <lb/>of &quot;ratio decidendi&quot;. ...&quot; <lb/>&quot;13. <lb/>In the case of Commissioner of Customs (Fort) vs. <lb/>Toyota Kirloskar Motor (P) Ltd., (2007) 5 SCC 371, the <lb/>Supreme Court stated the law relating to precedents and held <lb/>that a decision, as is well known, is an authority for what it <lb/>decides and not what can logically be deduced therefrom. The <lb/>ratio of a decision must be culled out from the facts involved <lb/>in a given case and need not be an authority in generality <lb/>without reference to the reasons, discussions and facts of the <lb/>case.&quot; <lb/>&quot;15. <lb/>Furthermore, ratio decidendi of a judgment has to <lb/>be found out only on reading the entire judgment. The ratio <lb/>of the judgment is what is set out in the judgment itself. <lb/>Answer to the question necessarily would have to be read in <lb/>the context what is set out in the judgment and not in <lb/>isolation. In case of any doubt as regards any observations, <lb/>reasons or principles, the other part of the judgment must be <lb/>looked into. By reading a line here and there from the <lb/>judgment, one cannot find out the entire ratio decidendi of the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>42 <lb/></page>

			<body>judgment. The reasoning could be deciphered upon reading <lb/>the judgment in its entirety and then applying these principles <lb/>to the subsequent cases. (Reference : (i) Union of India vs. <lb/>Godfrey Philips India Ltd., AIR 1996 SC 806, (ii) Union of <lb/>India vs. Dhanwanti Devi, (1996) 6 SCC 44, (iii) State of <lb/>Tripura vs. Tripura Bar Association, AIR 1999 SC 1494 and <lb/>(iv) Islamic Academy of Education vs. State of Karnatake, <lb/>(2003) 6 SCC 697).&quot; <lb/>(Emphasis Supplied) <lb/>31. <lb/>In Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case, an attempt to read the observations <lb/>in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case in the context of applicable law has been made and, <lb/>therefore, it is not possible to accept the submission that the judgment is per <lb/>incuriam. <lb/>32. <lb/>The learned counsel for the appellant submitted that <lb/>interpreting a judgment of the Supreme Court is itself impermissible and for <lb/>this purpose cited judgment of the Supreme Court in G.K. Dudani and others <lb/>Vs. S.D. Sharma and others, reported at AIR 1986 SC 1455. In that case, a <lb/>Division Bench of Gujarat High Court had sought to interpret the words <lb/>&quot;promotees regularly appointed&quot; in a judgment of Supreme Court in N.K. <lb/>Chauhan v. State of Gujarat, reported at AIR 1977 SC 251. The Supreme <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>43 <lb/></page>

			<body>Court observed as under in para 19 : <lb/>&quot;19. <lb/>Even apart from the question of res judicata, the <lb/>Division Bench was not right in its approach to Chauhan&apos;s <lb/>Case. The interpretation placed by the Division Bench upon <lb/>the words &quot;promotees regularly appointed&quot; in direction (d) in <lb/>Chauhan&apos;s case was wholly erroneous. Under the guise of <lb/>interpreting the judgment in that case, the Division Bench of <lb/>the High Court virtually sat in appeal over the judgment of <lb/>this Court and modified it. The High Court ought to have <lb/>taken the words in that judgment in the sense in which they <lb/>were used and ought to have applied them to the facts before it <lb/>instead of trying to put words in the mouth of this Court. ...&quot; <lb/>It is not clear as to how the judgment could be an authority for the <lb/>proposition that a High Court cannot attribute to the words in an Apex <lb/>Court judgment, meaning assigned in the relevant enactment. True, High <lb/>Court should not put words in the mouth of the Apex Court. But if an <lb/>attempt is made to put a strained meaning on words in a judgment without <lb/>considering the context, a High Court would be duty bound to repel such <lb/>attempt and read the words in the context of the relevant enactment. This <lb/>is what was done in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>44 <lb/></page>

			<body>33. <lb/>In Ballabhdas Mathuradas Lakhani and others Vs. <lb/>Municipal Committee, Malkapur, reported at AIR 1970 SC 1002, the Supreme <lb/>Court held that its earlier decision on the question of validity of levy of tax <lb/>by Municipality was binding on the High Court and the High Court could <lb/>not ignore it because they thought that relevant provisions were not brought <lb/>to the notice of the Supreme Court. Such is not the present case. <lb/>34. <lb/>The learned counsel for the appellant next relied on a <lb/>judgment of High Court of Rajasthan in M/s. Bhanwar Lal Brij Gopal and etc. <lb/>etc. v. State of Rajasthan and others, reported at AIR 1983 Rajasthan 104, to <lb/>contend that even if same aspect of a matter was not considered by the Apex <lb/>Court, it would not enable a High Court to re-agitate the issue. In that case, <lb/>validity of a notification dated 23-5-1981 was challenged before the High <lb/>Court, when the very same notification had been held valid by the Apex <lb/>Court in a judgment in Surajmal Kailash Chand Vs. Union of India, reported <lb/>at AIR 1982 SC 130. The Court made the following observations in para 22 : <lb/>&quot;22. <lb/>This raises a serious question as to what would be <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>45 <lb/></page>

			<body>the effect of the decision of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court, more <lb/>so when the same Notification being declared valid by the <lb/>Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court and the High Court has declared <lb/>invalid on the same day. Undoubtedly Art. 141 makes it <lb/>explicit and beyond doubt that the law laid down by the <lb/>Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court is to be obeyed by all concerned. <lb/>Even otherwise so far as the High Court is concerned the <lb/>Supreme Court is of a superior jurisdiction and law laid down <lb/>by the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court is binding, even if Article 41 <lb/>and Article 144 would not be there.&quot; <lb/>It then quoted from a judgment of Supreme Court in Ambica Prasad Mishra <lb/>Vs. State of U.P., reported at AIR 1980 SC 1762, in para 23 as under : <lb/>&quot;23. ... The answer to this problem need not be given by me <lb/>but in Ambica Prasad Mishra v. State of U.P. (AIR 1980 SC <lb/>1762), the Supreme Court have taken pains to answer what <lb/>would be the effect of raising additional points or such points <lb/>later. It was observed as under :--<lb/>&quot;Constitution of India, art. 141--<lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>46 <lb/></page>

			<body>reconsideration of binding precedent -when permissible. <lb/>Every new discovery or argumentative novelty cannot undo or <lb/>compel reconsideration of a binding precedent. <lb/>It is <lb/>fundamental that the nation&apos;s constitution is not kept in <lb/>constant uncertainty by judicial review every season because it <lb/>paralyses, by perennial suspense, all legislative and <lb/>administrative action, on vital issues deterred by the brooding <lb/>threat of forensic blow-up. This, if permitted, may well be a <lb/>kind of judicial destabilisation of State action too dangerous <lb/>to be indulged in save where national crisis of great moment <lb/>to the life, liberty and safety of this country and its millions <lb/>are at stake, or the basic direction of the nation itself is in <lb/>peril of a shake-up. <lb/>It is wise to remember that fatal flaws silenced by earlier <lb/>rulings cannot survive after death because a decision does not <lb/>lose its authority &quot;merely because it was badly argued, <lb/>inadequately considered and fallaciously &quot;reasoned&quot; &apos;&apos; <lb/>35. <lb/>The judgment in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case does not even hint that <lb/>K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case was badly argued, inadequately considered or <lb/>fallaciously reasoned. Far from this, K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case, being the first <lb/>authoritative pronouncement, which not only comprehensively considered <lb/>all aspects but also ruled in expression aptly chosen for defining the five <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>47 <lb/></page>

			<body>components, in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case, it is followed strictly. Ahuja Dongre&apos;s <lb/>case merely repels an attempt to put colloquial or loose meaning on the <lb/>expression used in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case. <lb/>36. <lb/>Same holds good about reliance by the learned counsel for <lb/>the appellant on the judgment of the Supreme Court in Suganthi Suresh <lb/>Kumar v. Jagdeeshan, reported at (2002) 2 SCC 420, where the Supreme <lb/>Court had disapproved High Courts overruling decisions of the Apex Court <lb/>on the ground that it had laid down the legal position without considering <lb/>any other point. This objection cannot be raised in respect of judgment in <lb/>Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case since the Supreme Court in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case chose to <lb/>use the expression &quot;presented&quot; and &quot;the bank&quot; and the Supreme Court did <lb/>not rule that depositing the cheque with drawer&apos;s bank was also a relevant <lb/>component. Judicial discipline to abide by the declaration of law by the <lb/>Supreme Court is the foremost consideration for a High Court, as held in <lb/>Suga Ram alias Chhugaram Vs. State of Rajasthan and others, reported at <lb/>(2006) 8 SCC 641, and judgment in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case strictly follows K. <lb/>Bhaskaran&apos;s case. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>48 <lb/></page>

			<body>37. <lb/>It is not clear as to why the learned counsel for the appellant <lb/>chose to cite judgment in Smt. Kausalya Devi Bogra and others Vs. Land <lb/>Acquisition Officer, Aurangabad and another, reported at (1984) 2 SCC 324. <lb/>In that case, while allowing earlier appeals by judgment dated 23-3-1979, <lb/>the Supreme Court had directed the High Court to re-hear the appeals in the <lb/>light of directions given. Yet the High Court observed that they had not <lb/>heard the parties on merits at all and re-confirmed the view taken by earlier <lb/>Division Bench, which had been expressly set aside by the Supreme Court. <lb/>In this context, the Supreme Court held as under : <lb/>&quot;5. <lb/>Having read the judgment of the High Court and <lb/>considering the manner in which the first appeals have been <lb/>disposed of, we have no doubts in our mind that the High <lb/>Court exceeded its jurisdiction in dealing with the first appeals. <lb/>This Court in exercise of appellate powers vested in it under <lb/>Article 136 (sic Article 133) of the Constitution had set aside <lb/>the Bench decision of the High Court delivered in 1971 and <lb/>that judgment for all intents and purposes had become non-<lb/>existent. The present Division Bench of the High Court was <lb/>not entitled, by any process known to law, to resurrect that <lb/>judgment into life.&quot; <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>49 <lb/></page>

			<body>The judgment would have applied only if this Court in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case <lb/>had come to express any doubts over the observations of the Supreme Court <lb/>in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case. On the contrary, this Court merely warded off an <lb/>attempt to put a gloss over the words in the judgment, which was necessary <lb/>to avoid stretching the ratio therein to an illogical extreme. <lb/>38. <lb/>Since in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case this Court had not taken a view <lb/>contrary to that of any co-ordinate Bench or Bench of a higher strength, <lb/>there was no occasion to make a reference. Hence, ratio in Sundarjas <lb/>Kanyalal Bhatija and others v. Collector, Thane, Maharashtra and others, <lb/>reported at (1989) 3 SCC 396, on which the learned counsel for the <lb/>appellant relied, would not be attracted. <lb/>39. <lb/>Repeated reliance on the judgments to show that the <lb/>observations in the judgments of the Supreme Court cannot be disregarded <lb/>cannot lead to an inference that factually there has been any such disregard. <lb/>The position that an earlier decision of the Supreme Court cannot be <lb/>overruled by even a co-equal bench of that Court reported in (1995) 4 SCC <lb/>96 (Indian Oil Corporation Ltd. Vs. Municipal Corporation and another), <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>50 <lb/></page>

			<body>referred to by the learned counsel for the appellant is so clear that an <lb/>authority was really not necessary. <lb/>40. <lb/>To recapitulate :-<lb/>(1) <lb/>The judgment in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case does not contain even a <lb/>whisper that K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case was decided without considering any <lb/>provision of law or any legal aspect. <lb/>(2) <lb/>On the contrary, the judgment in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case enforces in <lb/>letter and spirit the observations of the Supreme Court in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s <lb/>case, by reading the expression used contextually, and refusing to read the <lb/>explanatory expression out of context, as is required to be done (Para 10 of <lb/>Full Bench judgment in Emkay Exports, Mumbai and another Vs. <lb/>Madhusudan Shrikrishna -2008(4) Mh.L.J. 843). <lb/>(3) <lb/>What is now being attempted by the appellants is to put an <lb/>unwarranted colloquial meaning on the expression used, stretching the ratio <lb/>of K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case to illogical extent, and then alleging deviation in <lb/>Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case from such strained interpretation put on the judgment <lb/>which is not proper. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>51 <lb/></page>

			<body>41. <lb/>The learned counsel for the appellant next submitted that in <lb/>Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case, this Court had suggested that principally the Court <lb/>within whose jurisdiction cheque was issued would have jurisdiction, and <lb/>that such a conclusion runs counter to the judgment of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme <lb/>Court in Mosaraf Hossain Khan&apos;s case. It has to be humbly pointed out that <lb/>in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case, the question was about place of presentation, since <lb/>the concerned Court was sought to be clothed with jurisdiction on the <lb/>foundation that the cheque was allegedly presented within such jurisdiction. <lb/>It was pointed out that the cheque was merely lodged in payee&apos;s bank and it <lb/>was eventually presented to the bank on which it was drawn, which was <lb/>outside the jurisdiction of the said Court. <lb/>42. <lb/>While the place where the cheque is issued and the place <lb/>where the cheque is presented (i.e. place where drawee bank is situated) <lb/>may in a given case be the same, as held in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case, these places <lb/>could be different. Drawer of a cheque may not necessarily draw a cheque <lb/>at the place where the drawee bank is situated and issue it. He may as well <lb/>draw it at his place/payee&apos;s place, etc. In a metro, such places could be in a <lb/>different jurisdictions, though in the same city. If jurisdiction is excluded by <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>52 <lb/></page>

			<body>applying observations in Mosaraf Hossain&apos;s case, and holding that one <lb/>component, namely place of issuance of cheque is not relevant, it does not <lb/>automatically exclude jurisdiction if the second component of presentation <lb/>and dishonour have occurred at the same place where cheque was issued. <lb/>Therefore, Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case is not in conflict with Mosaraf Hossain&apos;s case, <lb/>and so it cannot be said that Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case is rendered per incuriam. <lb/>There is yet another component of the place where payment was intended <lb/>to be made, which place could be different from the place where cheque <lb/>was issued or delivered. To find out where the payment was to be made, <lb/>one has to simply took at the cheque to find out where the drawee bank is <lb/>situated. Had the cheque been honoured, which could have been the place <lb/>where payment could be said to have been made to the payee? --obviously <lb/>the drawee bank, since there the account of drawer would be debited and <lb/>amount transmitted to the payee&apos;s agent -his bank -for being credited to <lb/>his account. Such inference about intended place of payment could, <lb/>however, be rebutted by tendering evidence to show that payment was to <lb/>be made elsewhere. <lb/>43. <lb/>The learned counsel for the appellant submitted that a <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>53 <lb/></page>

			<body>Special Leave Petition is already filed before the Supreme Court challenging <lb/>judgment in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case. Also another Hon&apos;ble Single Judge has <lb/>referred the matter to a larger Bench. He submitted that the appeals could <lb/>be kept pending till the Special Leave Petition or reference to larger Bench <lb/>are decided, and that the appellant would not mind waiting for the decision <lb/>of the lis. He drew my attention to an order of the Supreme Court in Umesh <lb/>Korga Bhandari Vs. Mahanagar Telephone Nigam Ltd. and another, reported <lb/>at (2005) 13 SCC 691, to suggest such a course. In that case, the Supreme <lb/>Court observed that since decision in Bangalore Water Supply Board&apos;s case <lb/>had been referred in 2005 to a larger Bench in State of U.P. Vs. Jai Bir Singh, <lb/>it would be appropriate to await the decision of larger Bench. <lb/>44. <lb/>This submission could have been made when the matters <lb/>first came up before Hon&apos;ble Shri Justice A.H. Joshi for admission <lb/>on 4-9-2008, when notice of final disposal was issued. After a matter is <lb/>heard at length, no useful purpose would be served by keeping it pending, <lb/>since there is no way to know when the Special Leave Petition or the <lb/>reference to larger Bench would be decided, as Courts have other pressing <lb/>work as well. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>54 <lb/></page>

			<body>45. <lb/>In Criminal Writ Petition No.7 of 2008 before the High <lb/>Court of Bombay at Goa, by an order dated 7-2-2008, an Hon&apos;ble Single <lb/>Judge referred the matter to a larger Bench. Copy of that order was made <lb/>available by the Registry, in order to enable me to ascertain as to what part <lb/>of judgment in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case was found to be incorrect. In para 2, the <lb/>Hon&apos;ble Single Judge observes as under : <lb/>&quot;2. <lb/>I have perused both the decisions delivered by the <lb/>learned Single Judges of this Court. In Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case, <lb/>the learned Single Judge has held that a cheque as a <lb/>negotiable instrument is statutorily required to be discharged <lb/>at the place mentioned therein and a reference is made in that <lb/>regard to Section 72 of the Negotiable Instruments Act. <lb/>Referring to the decision of the Apex Court in K. Bhasaran v. <lb/>Sankaran Vaidhyan Balan, reported in AIR 1999 SC 3762, <lb/>it was held that in K. Bhasaran&apos;s case as a matter of fact it <lb/>was held as proved that the cheques in question had been <lb/>issued at the shop of P.W.3 with the territorial limits of the <lb/>trial Court&apos;s jurisdiction. Having so observed, it was further <lb/>held by the learned Single Judge that the five ingredients <lb/>enumerated by the Court in para 14 of the Judgment would <lb/>undisputedly attract the provisions of clause (d) of Section 178 <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>55 <lb/></page>

			<body>of the Code of Criminal Procedure, since it could not be said <lb/>that the offence punishable under Section 138 of the <lb/>Negotiable Instruments Act consists of the five acts, <lb/>enumerated in paragraph 14 of the judgment.&quot; <lb/>(Emphasis supplied) <lb/>The learned Single Judge then paraphrases interpretation put by me on the <lb/>expressions &quot;presented&quot; and &quot;the drawee bank&quot;. In para 3, the Hon&apos;ble <lb/>Judge quotes from K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case, and in paras 5 and 6 observes as to <lb/>what the Apex Court has held in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case. The sentence in para 6 <lb/>wherein the Hon&apos;ble Judge refers to judgment in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case reads <lb/>as under : <lb/>&quot;... The decision of the Apex Court therefore is very clear to the <lb/>effect that the jurisdiction for initiating action under Section <lb/>138 of the Negotiable Instruments Act is not restricted to the <lb/>place where the drawee bank is situated and, hence, in my <lb/>considered opinion, and with utmost respect to the learned <lb/>Judge in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case, the view therein is directly <lb/>contrary to the law laid down by the Apex Court in K. <lb/>Bhaskaran&apos;s case.&quot; <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>56 <lb/></page>

			<body>The portion underlined in para 2 of the order would show that the Hon&apos;ble <lb/>Single Judge correctly concluded that it was held in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case that <lb/>the five ingredients enumerated by the Court in para 14 of the judgment <lb/>would undisputedly attract the provisions of clause (d) of Section 178 of the <lb/>Code of Criminal Procedure. But reading by the Hon&apos;ble Single Judge of the <lb/>remaining part of same sentence in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case is, however different <lb/>from that in the report of the judgment at 2006(6) All Bom R 201, which the <lb/>Hon&apos;ble Single Judge had referred to (as may be seen from para 1 of his <lb/>order). The sentence in para 14 of the judgment in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case <lb/>reads as under : <lb/>&quot;The five ingredients enumerated by the Court in paragraph <lb/>14 of the judgment would undisputedly attract the oprovisions <lb/>of Clause (d) of Section 178 of the Code of Criminal <lb/>Procedure, since it can be said that the offence punishable <lb/>under Section 138 of the Negotiable Instruments Act consists <lb/>of the five acts, enumerated in paragraph 14 of the judgment.&quot; <lb/>It seems that ingenious advocacy led to reading &quot;not&quot;, when it did not exist <lb/>in the sentence referred to. And it made a world of difference. The <lb/>sentence quoted above should be enough to dispel the notion that it was <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>57 <lb/></page>

			<body>sought to be suggested in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case that jurisdiction is restricted <lb/>to the place where drawee bank is situated. It should also have been noted <lb/>that component (4), giving of notice, was discussed in paras 25 to 27 of the <lb/>judgment in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case, and as a fact it was held that notice was <lb/>issued demanding payment for the payee residing in adjacent district, <lb/>outside the jurisdiction of the Court concerned. <lb/>46. <lb/>The learned counsel for the appellant next submitted that <lb/>even the High Court of Jammu and Kashmir in Sunil Somnath Ghumare Vs. <lb/>FIL Industries and another, reported at 2007(4) Crimes 566 (J&amp;K), relied on <lb/>K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case, had held that Court in Srinagar (J&amp;K) had jurisdiction <lb/>to try a case of dishonour of a cheque drawn on a bank at Kopergaon <lb/>(Maharashtra) as the cheque was presented by complainant to his bank at <lb/>Srinagar. It was not urged before the High Court of Jammu and Kashmir <lb/>that lodging a cheque for collection did not amount to its presentation. <lb/>Secondly, the signifance or article &quot;the&quot; prefixed to word &quot;bank&quot; in the <lb/>second component of K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case enumeration was also not argued, <lb/>and, therefore, there is no pronouncement on this aspect. Had the High <lb/>Court of Jammu and Kashmir considered these aspects and taken a <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>58 <lb/></page>

			<body>different view, that could have been examined in order to find out if the <lb/>logic in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case was wrong. Hence, this judgment is unhelpful <lb/>to the appellant. <lb/>47. <lb/>The learned counsel for the appellant next submitted that <lb/>the Supreme Court had held in Harbans Lal Vs. State of Haryana and <lb/>another, reported at 1999 ALL MR (Cri) 390, that when gold was <lb/>transported from Pakistan to a place near Bahadurgarh in Haryana, each of <lb/>the Courts, through whose jurisdiction the contraband passed, would have <lb/>jurisdiction to try offence punishable under the Customs Act. Therefore, <lb/>according to him, when notice demanding payment has been issued from <lb/>Nagpur, jurisdiction of Nagpur Court could not be excluded. As regards <lb/>significance of service of notice, apart from K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case, the learned <lb/>counsel also relied on judgment of the Supreme Court in M/s. Sarav <lb/>Investment &amp; Financial Consultants Pvt. Ltd. &amp; Anr. Vs. Llyods Register of <lb/>Shipping Indian Office Staff Provident Fund &amp; Anr., reported at <lb/>2008 ALL MR (Cri) 300 (S.C.). There was no question of jurisdiction <lb/>involved. The question was about service of notice by hand delivery, which <lb/>the High Court had held to be sufficient. The Supreme Court, allowing the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>59 <lb/></page>

			<body>appeal, and setting aside the judgment of the High Court, after quoting <lb/>from K. Bhaskaran, observed in paras 16 and 19 as under : <lb/>&quot;16. <lb/>Section 138 of the Act contains a penal provision. <lb/>It is a special statute. It creates a vicarious liability. Even the <lb/>burden of proof to some extent is on the accused. Having <lb/>regard to the purport of the said provision as also in view of <lb/>the fact that it provides for a severe penalty, the provision <lb/>warrants a strict construction. Proviso appended to Section <lb/>138 contains a non-obstante clause. It provides that nothing <lb/>contained in the main provision shall apply unless the <lb/>requirements prescribed therein are complied with. Service of <lb/>notice is one of the statutory requirements for initiation of a <lb/>criminal proceeding. Such notice is required to be given <lb/>within 30 days of the receipt of the information by the <lb/>complainant from the bank regarding the cheque as unpaid. <lb/>Clause (c) provides that the holder of the cheque must be <lb/>given an opportunity to pay the amount in question within 15 <lb/>days of the receipt of the said notice. Complaint Petition, <lb/>thus, can be filed for commission of an offence by a drawee of <lb/>a cheque only 15 days after service of the notice. What are the <lb/>requirements of service of a notice is no longer res-integra in <lb/>view of the recent decision of this Court in C.C. Alavi Haji Vs. <lb/>Palapetty Muhammed &amp; Anr. [JT 2007(7) SC 498 : 2007 <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>60 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">ALL MR (Cri) 2044 (S.C.)].&quot; <lb/>&quot;19. <lb/>In K. Bhaskaran Vs. Sankaran Vaidhyan Balan <lb/>and Anr. [(1999)7 SCC 510 : 1999(4) ALL MR 452 (S.C.) <lb/>: 1999 ALL MR (Cri) 1845 (S.C.)], importance of service of <lb/>notice has been pointed out stating :-<lb/>&quot;19. <lb/>In Black&apos;s Law Dictionary &apos;giving of notice&apos; is <lb/>distinguished from &apos;receiving of the notice&apos; (vide p.621) : <lb/>&apos;A person notifies or gives notice to another by taking such <lb/>steps as may be reasonably required to inform the other in <lb/>the ordinary course, whether or not such other actually <lb/>comes to know of it&apos;. A person &apos;receives&apos; a notice when it is <lb/>duly delivered to him or at the place of his business. <lb/>21. <lb/>If a strict interpretation is given that the drawer <lb/>should have actually received the notice for the period of <lb/>15 days to start running no matter that the payee sent the <lb/>notice on the correct address, a trickster cheque drawer <lb/>would get the premium to avoid receiving the notice by <lb/>different strategies and he could escape from the legal <lb/>consequences of Section 138 of the Act. It must be borne <lb/>in mind that the court should not adopt an interpretation <lb/>which helps a dishonest evader and clips an honest payee <lb/>as that would defeat the very legislative measure. <lb/>22. <lb/>In Maxwell&apos;s Interpretation of Statutes, the <lb/>learned author has emphasized that &apos;provisions relating to <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>61 <lb/></page>

			<body>giving of notice often receive liberal interpretation&apos; (vide <lb/>p.99 of the 12 th Ed.). The context envisaged in Section <lb/>138 of the act invites a liberal interpretation for the <lb/>person who has the statutory obligation to give notice <lb/>because he is presumed to be the loser in the transaction <lb/>and it is for his interest the very provision is made by the <lb/>legislature. The words in clause (b) of the proviso to <lb/>Section 138 of the Act show that the payee has the <lb/>statutory obligation to &apos;make a demand&apos; by giving notice. <lb/>The thrust in the clause is one the need to &apos;make a <lb/>demand&apos;. It is only the mode for making such demand <lb/>which the legislature has prescribed. A payee can send the <lb/>notice for doing his part for giving the notice. Once it is <lb/>dispatched his part is over and the next depends on what <lb/>the sendee does.&quot; <lb/>This question too had never been in doubt, and the law laid down in <lb/>K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case in this behalf had in fact been applied even in Ahuja <lb/>Dongre&apos;s case. <lb/>48. <lb/>The learned counsel for the respondent, however, submitted <lb/>that the question of giving notice had also been considered by this Court in <lb/>M/s. Yashomala Engineering Pvt. Ltd. and others Vs. Tata SSL Ltd. and <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>62 <lb/></page>

			<body>another, reported at 1998 Cri.L.J. 4350. The following observations in paras <lb/>13 and 14 may have a bearing on the issue. <lb/>&quot;13. <lb/>The learned Advocate for the petitioner has strongly <lb/>urged that if notice is held to be an integral part of offence it <lb/>would give an unnecessary handle to the payee of the cheque <lb/>to institute complaint in any part of the country where it <lb/>happens to be an offence. Firstly, this is not possible because if <lb/>one turns to that Section again and reads definition of the <lb/>word &quot;payee&quot; as contained in Section 7 of the said Act, <lb/>payment is to be made to the payee as defined. He is none else <lb/>but the person named in the instrument to whom or to whose <lb/>order, the money is by the instrument directed to be paid.&quot; <lb/>&quot;14. <lb/>In the event of payee being a company, when the <lb/>money is to be paid to the person named in the instrument, <lb/>payment to the company would be sufficient compliance of the <lb/>proviso. This would necessarily mean that the institution of <lb/>complaint will be restricted to the place where the registered <lb/>office of the company is situated. If this be the consequence of <lb/>the provision of Section 138 read with its proviso, it could well <lb/>be and that could not be a ground for interpreting the Section <lb/>and to restrict the jurisdiction of the Court only where the <lb/>cheque was issued and where it was returned unpaid.&quot; <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>63 <lb/></page>

			<body>The learned counsel submitted that mere despatch of notice from a <lb/>non-existant office at Nagpur would not do and since complainant&apos;s <lb/>(payee&apos;s) registered office is at Delhi, demand for payment must be <lb/>construed to have been made from Delhi. What the law prescribes is not <lb/>mere &quot;posting&quot; of a notice or quoting an address on the notice. What is <lb/>prescribed is &quot;giving&quot; of notice by the payee and, therefore, whatever may <lb/>be the address quoted or wherever notice is posted, the place of giving <lb/>notice would be the place where the payee ordinarily resides or works for <lb/>gain. <lb/>49. <lb/>Incidentally, by judgment dated 5-7-2006, i.e. a little before <lb/>Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case was decided, a learned Single Judge of this Court had <lb/>considered the significance of place from where notice of demand was <lb/>issued. This judgment in Laxmi Travels, Nagpur Vs. G.E. Countrywide <lb/>Consumer and another, reported at 2006(5) AIR Bom R 316 (in September <lb/>2006 issue), was not available to me while deciding Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case. In <lb/>that case, the facts were as under : <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>64 <lb/></page>

			<body>&quot;2. <lb/>The basic transaction between the parties took place <lb/>at Nagpur. The parties are residing at Nagpur. The cheques <lb/>are also presented at Canara Bank at Nagpur. As it was <lb/>bounced, the endorsement also made by the Canara Bank at <lb/>Nagpur. However, the complainant had issued notice of <lb/>demand from Aurangabad and as there was no compliance of <lb/>the same, the present complaint has been filed at <lb/>Aurangabad.&quot; <lb/>The learned Single Judge then considered the contentions based upon <lb/>pronouncement in K. Bhaskaran, M/s. Prem Chand Vijaykumar Vs. Yashpal <lb/>Singh, and Mosaraf Hossain Khan, and concluded in para 7 as under : <lb/>&quot;7. <lb/>The contention as raised by the learned counsel in <lb/>favour of complainant that the above judgment of the Apex <lb/>Court in K. Bhaskaran (AIR 1999 SC 3762) (supra) supports <lb/>his case to this extent that giving of notice in writing to the <lb/>drawer of the cheque demanding payment of the cheque <lb/>amount and failure of the drawer to make payment within 15 <lb/>days from the notice gives cause of action only at Aurangabad. <lb/>This contention has no force. The Apex Court, nowhere dealt <lb/>with this aspect. What has been decided by the Apex Court in <lb/>K. Bhaskaran and M/s. Prem Chand (supra) refers to the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>65 <lb/></page>

			<body>basic ingredients which are necessary for an offence under <lb/>S.138 of the Act. There is no dispute about this that all these <lb/>ingredients are necessary. We are concerned with the cause of <lb/>action in the present matters. The demand notice is a must. <lb/>But a place of issuance of notice and no payment thereafter <lb/>cannot sufficient to file complaint under S.138 of N.I. Act. <lb/>The notice was though sent from Aurangabad, but received at <lb/>Nagpur. The party failed to make the payment as per notice. <lb/>Therefore, issuance of notice from Aurangabad itself cannot <lb/>give cause of action to file complaint at Aurangabad. The <lb/>object of issuing notice as observed by the Apex Court in <lb/>Rajneesh Aggarwal v. Amit J. Bhalla, reported in (2001) 1 <lb/>SCC 631 : (AIR 2001 SC 518) is as under : <lb/>&quot;Mere dishonour of a cheque would not raise to a cause of <lb/>action unless the payee makes a demand in writing to the <lb/>drawer of the cheque for the payment and the drawer fails to <lb/>make the payment of the said amount of money to the payee. <lb/>The object of issuing notice indicating the factum of dishonour <lb/>of the cheques is to give an opportunity to the drawer to make <lb/>the payment within 15 days, so that it will not be necessary <lb/>for the payee to proceed against in any criminal action, even <lb/>though the bank dishonoured the cheques.&quot; <lb/>The learned Single Judge then allowed the petition and dismissed the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>66 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">complaint. <lb/>50. <lb/>The learned counsel for the respondent also relied on a <lb/>judgment of High Court of Kerala in Harihara Puthra Sharma Vs. State of <lb/>Kerala and another, reported at 2007(1) DCR 440, where a learned Single <lb/>Judge of the Kerala High Court considered the directions of the Apex Court <lb/>in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case, as regards issuance of notice. The cheque in that <lb/>case had issued, presented and dishonoured within the limits of <lb/>jurisdiction of Judicial Magistrate First Class, Adoor. Demand for payment <lb/>was made by the complainant&apos;s counsel from his office at Pathnamthitta <lb/>and so the complainant was filed at Pathanamthitta. In this factual context, <lb/>the learned Single observed as under : <lb/>&quot; 12. <lb/>Undoubtedly, introduction of Chapter XVII in the <lb/>Act has brought in a laudable and welcome change as far as <lb/>efficacy of banking transactions is concerned. But at the same <lb/>time, the havoc that can be created by unscrupulous money <lb/>lenders and other elements who may try to misuse the penal <lb/>provisions to harass innocent and gullible persons who happen <lb/>to issue cheques in the court of honest and bonafide <lb/>transactions has also to be borne in mind. If unbridled <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>67 <lb/></page>

			<body>discretion is given to the complainants to choose the forum of <lb/>litigation, it may create judicial havoc, to say the least.&quot; <lb/>&quot;13. <lb/>As mentioned earlier, instances galore where <lb/>unscrupulous money lenders have misused the blank cheques <lb/>extracted by them from their borrowers by inserting inflated <lb/>amounts, claiming conscionable and unbelievable rates of <lb/>interest. If the drawee of a cheque who is bent upon harassing <lb/>his borrower is permitted to select the forum of his choice, a <lb/>situation may arise where a complainant living in <lb/>Trivandrum, at the southern end of the State will choose to file <lb/>a complaint before the Court at Kasaragod situated at the <lb/>northern extremity, after issuing a demand notice through a <lb/>counsel at Kasaragod, though the entire transaction between <lb/>the complainant and the accused had taken place at <lb/>Trivandrum. It may be true that the complainant may also <lb/>have to appear before the Court at Kasaragod in that <lb/>eventuality. But in a case where the complainant is aware <lb/>that the accused may not be in a position to undertake such <lb/>frequent journeys from the southern most part of the State to <lb/>the northern end, it may not be improbable that such an <lb/>ingenious method would not be adopted by a complainant.The <lb/>above instance may be hypothetical, but it may not be entirely <lb/>improbable or impossible at all.&quot; <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>68 <lb/></page>

			<body>&quot;16. <lb/>It is true that in Bhaskaran&apos;s case (supra), their <lb/>Lordships of the Supreme Court had held that &quot;the offence <lb/>under Section 138 of the Act can be completed only with the <lb/>concatenation&quot; of the following acts &quot; <lb/>(1) Drawing of the cheque. <lb/>(2) Returning the cheque unpaid by the drawee bank. <lb/>(4) Giving notice in writing to the drawer of the cheque <lb/>demanding payment of the cheque amount. <lb/>(5) Failure of the drawer to make payment within 15 <lb/>days of their receipt of the notice. <lb/>The court observed that it is not necessary that all the <lb/>five acts should have been perpetrated at the same locality. <lb/>While noticing the possibility that each of the five acts <lb/>mentioned above could be done at five different localities, the <lb/>court held that &quot;any one of the courts exercising jurisdiction in <lb/>one of the give local areas can become the place of trial for the <lb/>offence under Section 138 of the Act.&quot; The Court went on to <lb/>hold further that &quot;the complainant can choose any one of <lb/>those courts having jurisdiction over any one of the local areas <lb/>within the territorial limits of which any one of those five acts <lb/>was done.&quot; &apos;&apos; <lb/>&quot;17. <lb/>Learned counsel for the complainant has laid heavy <lb/>emphasis on the above observation made by the Apex Court, in <lb/>support of his case. But in the above decision, the factual <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>69 <lb/></page>

			<body>situation was totally different from the one available in the <lb/>case on hand. In that case, the trial Court had held that it <lb/>had no territorial jurisdiction to try the case since the cheque <lb/>was dishonoured by the Branch Office of the Bank situated in <lb/>a different district. But all other acts like drawing of the <lb/>cheque, its presentation for encashment, its return after <lb/>dishonour, and issuance of demand notice etc. had taken place <lb/>within the territorial limits of the trial court at Adoor. The <lb/>cheque was presented before the branch of the Syndicate Bank <lb/>at Kayamkulam and it was returned due to insufficiency of <lb/>funds in the accountof the accused. Apart from the above sole <lb/>act of presentation of the cheque before a branch outside the <lb/>jurisdiction of the trial court, all other acts as noticed by the <lb/>Supreme Court had, occurred within the territorial limits of <lb/>the trial court itself. Their Lordships had, in the above facts <lb/>and circumstances of the case, held that the trial Court was <lb/>not justified in refusing to exercise jurisdiction and deal with <lb/>the case in accordance with law.&quot; <lb/>&quot;19. <lb/>I have referred to the above observations of the <lb/>Apex Court to emphasis the fact that any one of the 5 <lb/>conditions enumerated by their Lordships in Bhaskaran&apos;s <lb/>case may not by itself invariably clinch the issue while <lb/>deciding the question of jurisdiction. That question has to <lb/>be decided keeping in view the entire sequence of events <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>70 <lb/></page>

			<body>starting from issuance of the cheque in the ultimate <lb/>culmination of refusal to pay.&quot; <lb/>&quot;21. <lb/>Having regard to the entire facts and <lb/>circumstances of the case on hand, I am satisfied that the <lb/>complainant is not entitled to institute the complaint <lb/>before the court at Pathanamthitta. since the major part <lb/>of the transaction like issuance of the cheque, its <lb/>presentation and dishonour, having taken place at Adoor, <lb/>it may not be just or proper to allow the complainant to <lb/>prosecute the petitioner/accused before the Chief Judicial <lb/>Magistrate&apos;s Court at Pathanamthitta solely for the reason <lb/>that the complainant had engaged a counsel at <lb/>Pathanamthitta to issue the statutory demand notice. In <lb/>my view, the method adopted by the complainant is clear <lb/>intended to harass the petitioner. <lb/>This cannot be <lb/>permitted. <lb/>51. <lb/>Thus just as in Ahuja Dongre&apos;s case, notice by a lawyer from <lb/>a different jurisdiction was held not enough to clothe the Court at that place <lb/>with jurisdiction to try the offence. <lb/>52. <lb/>What emerges from all these judgments, and more <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>71 <lb/></page>

			<body>particularly, K. Bhaskaran and Mosaraf Hossain&apos;s cases, could be summed up <lb/>as under (in spite of risks inherent in such summing up ) : <lb/>1. <lb/>Jurisdiction to file a case of offence punishable under Section 138 <lb/>of the Negotiable Instrument Act is not restricted only to the Court <lb/>within whose jurisdiction the drawee bank is situated and where <lb/>cheque is actually dishonoured upon presentation, though a <lb/>complaint could be filed even at such place as payment was <lb/>intended to be made there. <lb/>2. <lb/>Five components of the offence enumerated in the judgment in K. <lb/>Bhaskaran would be relevant for considering the question of <lb/>jurisdiction. <lb/>3. <lb/>Mere issuance of cheque may not be enough to confer <lb/>jurisdiction to the Court within whose jurisdiction the cheque was <lb/>issued. <lb/>4. <lb/>More pertinent, or decisive component would be the place, where <lb/>the transaction leading to debt or creation of legally enforceable <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>72 <lb/></page>

			<body>liability, for discharge whereof a cheque is issued, or, where <lb/>payment was to be made. <lb/>5. <lb/>Drawing a cheque on a particular bank would indicate intention to <lb/>make payment at the place where such bank is situated and <lb/>acceptance of such cheque by payee would indicate his consent to <lb/>receive payment at such place. <lb/>6. <lb/>Since &quot;the payee&quot; is required to issue a notice demanding <lb/>payment, such place of giving notice would be where, if payee is a <lb/>company (or other registered establishment) it has a registered <lb/>office, and in other cases, normally, where the payee ordinarily <lb/>resides or works for gain, and not any place from where the payee <lb/>may choose to despatch a notice. <lb/>53. <lb/>The facts of these cases, which may now be examined with <lb/>reference to the above conclusions, are as under : <lb/>1. <lb/>Both the parties have their shops/offices in Delhi. <lb/>2. <lb/>The transactions which gave rise to the liability took place at <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>73 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Delhi. <lb/>3. <lb/>The cheques were issued/delivered at Delhi. <lb/>4. <lb/>They were drawn on a bank at Delhi and accepted by the <lb/>complainant. <lb/>5. <lb/>They were presented to the bank at Delhi through payee&apos;s bank at <lb/>Nagpur and were returned unpaid by the bank at Delhi. <lb/>6. <lb/>The complainant does not have any registered office of Nagpur. <lb/>7. <lb/>Notices of demand were issued showing address at the premises of <lb/>a business associate at Nagpur, when the complainant has office at <lb/>Delhi. <lb/>54. <lb/>It is thus clear that the complainant had taken the detour of <lb/>lodging cheques for clearing at a Nagpur bank and issued notices of demand <lb/>showing address of a business associate in Nagpur only in order to have his <lb/>lis tried at Nagpur, and admittedly so, since, according to the learned <lb/>counsel for the appellant, the cases could not have been speedily disposed of <lb/>at Delhi. The learned counsel for the appellant submitted that choosing a <lb/>forum, which is convenient, is not impermissible and so the complainant <lb/>was justified in filing complaint in the Court at Nagpur. He submitted that <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>74 <lb/></page>

			<body>there is nothing wrong about pre-trial harassment of the accused, and that it <lb/>is nowhere held that such pre-trial harassment would be a criterion to <lb/>decide jurisdictional issues. <lb/>55. <lb/>The learned counsel for the appellant submitted that <lb/>criminal law cannot be over concerned about the rights of accused alone, <lb/>and victim&apos;s convenience and rights too are equally important. There can be <lb/>no doubt that a victim cannot be subjected to harassment for the sake of <lb/>securing justice. However, it does not follow that law sanctifies harassment <lb/>of the accused, even before he is adjudged guilty. His being required to <lb/>participate at trial is not in fact harassment, but an opportunity to defend <lb/>himself. His participation at trial, held ordinarily at a place where he ought <lb/>to be tried, cannot amount to harassment. But if he is dragged to a forum <lb/>with which lis has no concern, it would amount to either pre-conviction <lb/>punishment or a tactic of arm-twisting, which cannot be encouraged. <lb/>56. <lb/>The learned counsel for the appellant referred to the <lb/>following observations of the Supreme Court in Mosaraf Hossain&apos;s case in <lb/>para 35 of the judgment reported at AIR 2006 SC 1288. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>75 <lb/></page>

			<body>&quot;35. <lb/>The appellant did not deny or dispute any of the <lb/>averments made in the complaint petition. In the writ petition <lb/>it merely wanted some time to make the payment. It is now <lb/>well known that the object of the provision of Section 138 of <lb/>the Act is that for proper and smooth functioning of business <lb/>transaction in particular, use of cheques as negotiable <lb/>instruments would primarily depend upon the integrity and <lb/>honesty of the parties. It was noticed that cheques used to be <lb/>issued as a device inter alia for defrauding the creditors and <lb/>stalling the payments. It was also noticed in a number of <lb/>decisions of this Court that dishonour of a cheque by the bank <lb/>causes incalculable loss, injury and inconvenience to the payee <lb/>and the entire credibility of the business transactions within <lb/>and outside the country suffers a serious setback. It was also <lb/>found that the remedy available in a civil court is a long <lb/>drawn process and an unscrupulous drawer normally takes <lb/>various pleas to defeat the genuine claim of the payee.&quot; <lb/>He submitted that bearing this object in view, an interpretation which <lb/>supports the cause of payee has to be preferred. According to the learned <lb/>counsel, a trader may have transactions with several others across the <lb/>country and may receive payment for goods supplied at his business place in <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>76 <lb/></page>

			<body>form of cheques which may be drawn on banks at several places. If he was <lb/>to be required to file cases at such places, he would be rather shuttling from <lb/>one court at one place to another than being in his shop. The learned <lb/>counsel submitted that this was not contemplated. <lb/>57. <lb/>It is not clear as to how this argument factually favours the <lb/>complainant. The complainant had to simply file cases in Delhi where he <lb/>was supposed to be paid for goods sold by him. He has chosen to file cases <lb/>in Nagpur for no rhyme or reason, except that Courts here would be able to <lb/>deliver speedy justice. The concerns of traders aired by the learned counsel <lb/>are in fact addressed by the Apex Court in para 34 of the judgment in <lb/>Mosaraf Hossain&apos;s case by observing to the effect that jurisdiction would vest <lb/>in the Court within whose territorial jurisdiction payment was to be made. <lb/>58. <lb/>While in K. Bhaskaran&apos;s case, five components are <lb/>enumerated, the wordings of Section 138 of the Negotiable Instruments Act <lb/>would underline that the cheque is but a means of fulfilling the more basic <lb/>obligation -namely, &quot;for the discharge, in whole or in part, of any debt or <lb/>other liability&quot;. Therefore, the place where the debt or other liability was <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>77 <lb/></page>

			<body>required to be discharged is of crucial importance in deciding jurisdictional <lb/>issue, as is held in Mosaraf Hossain&apos;s case. This should answer the <lb/>appellant&apos;s apprehensions about difficulties of businessmen in realising <lb/>outstation cheques for goods sold. <lb/>59. <lb/>It has to be borne in mind that once a superior Court sets a <lb/>precedent by allowing place of trial to be changed on such considerations, <lb/>the place could as well be deliberately chosen so as to cause maximum <lb/>inconvenience and harassment. Today, a Delhi trial is being sought to be <lb/>shifted to Nagpur because trials here are speedy. Tomorrow, money <lb/>lenders/financers may set up offices in remote areas where Courts have little <lb/>work only in order to drag opponents to such Courts to coerce a settlement. <lb/>While laying down a legal principle all the possible implications would have <lb/>to be borne in mind. Substantive law is so drafted that no crook escapes <lb/>punishment. But procedural law has to be so crafted that no innocent <lb/>person is victimised, or made to surrender to fait accompli, upon being worn <lb/>out by visits to Courts. In view of all this, no fault can be found with the <lb/>learned Magistrate&apos;s conclusion that the Courts at Nagpur lacked jurisdiction <lb/>to try the case. However, the learned Magistrate could not have recorded <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>78 <lb/></page>

			<body>acquittal of the accused. He should have directed return of complaints for <lb/>being filed in appropriate Court. <lb/>60. <lb/>The learned counsel for the appellant submitted that while <lb/>ordering such return of complaints, the Courts at Delhi to whom the <lb/>complaints would be presented may be directed to proceed on the basis of <lb/>evidence already tendered and a de novo trial should not be ordered as held <lb/>in State of M.P. Vs. Bhooraji and others, reported at (2001) 7 SCC 679 <lb/>(already discussed). There is no question of this Court ordering de novo <lb/>trials, since these are summary criminal cases, evidence (excluding <lb/>affidavits) is in form of notes taken by the Magistrate, and it may not be <lb/>possible for the Magistrate at Delhi to proceed on those notes. However, <lb/>this aspect is best left open for the parties and the concerned Court to be <lb/>worked out in a manner which will ensure avoiding loss of scarce judicial <lb/>time. <lb/>61. <lb/>In view of the foregoing discussion, all these appeals are <lb/>partly allowed. The impugned judgments and acquittal of the respondent <lb/>are set aside and the complaints along with evidence recorded are directed <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: <lb/></note>

			<page>79 <lb/></page>

			<body>to be returned under Section 201 of the Code of Criminal Procedure Code <lb/>for being presented to proper Court. <lb/>JUDGE <lb/>Lanjewar <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -18/03/2022 19:40:04 ::: </note>


	</text>
</tei>
