<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<item>1.<lb/> This group of writ petitions (enumerated in the Schedule<lb/> appended with the present order, which be treated an integral part<lb/> of this order) lay challenge to separate transfer order(s) issued on<lb/> one<lb/> day<lb/> i.e.<lb/> 29.09.2019<lb/> by<lb/> the<lb/> Additional<lb/> Director<lb/></item>

			<item>(Administration), Medical &amp; Health Services, Rajasthan Jaipur.<lb/></item>

			<p>2.<lb/> The essence of petitioners&apos; contention is that the respondent<lb/> State, more particularly the Department of Medical &amp; Health<lb/> Service, has no authority to transfer the petitioners, whose<lb/> services are governed by the Rajasthan Panchayati Raj<lb/> (Transferred Activities) Rules, 2011 (hereinafter after referred to<lb/> as &quot;the Rules of 2011&quot;). For the sake of convenience and clarity,<lb/> the relevant facts from Kiran Kumari&apos;s case (SB Civil Writ Petition<lb/> No.14964/2019) are taken into consideration.<lb/></p>

			<p>2.1 It may be noted that the State Government issued a<lb/> circular/order dated 02.10.2010, whereby Sub-Centres, Primary<lb/> Health Centres (PHC) and Community Health Centres (CHC)<lb/> situated in various rural areas of Medical &amp; Health Department,<lb/> including their staff were transferred to the Panachati Raj<lb/> Institutions.<lb/></p>

			<p>2.2 According to such decision of the State, services of all such<lb/> employees (including the petitioners) were ordered to be governed<lb/> by the Rules of 2011. Consequently, their parent department<lb/> remains Medical &amp; Health Department, but their other incidence of<lb/> service, including transfer are governed by the Rules of 2011.<lb/></p>

			<p>2.3 Petitioner was afforded appointment on the post of Auxiliary<lb/> Nurse Midwifery (ANM) on 29.01.2016.<lb/> (3 of 16)<lb/> [CW-14964/2019]<lb/></p>

			<p>2.4 The present bunch of writ petitions includes those persons<lb/> who have been transferred from one District to another and one<lb/> Panchayat Samiti to another Panchayat Samit, so also one Gram<lb/> Panchayat to other.<lb/></p>

			<p>2.5 By way of the order dated 29.09.2019, respondent No.2 has<lb/> transferred the petitioner -Kiran Kumari from Community Health<lb/> Center Rajgarh, Churu to Sub-Center, Bhawta, Kuchaman City,<lb/> Nagaur -from one district to another.<lb/></p>

			<p>3.<lb/> Mr. Vikas Bijarnia, learned counsel leading the arguments in<lb/> this group of matters, at the outset submitted that after transfer<lb/> of petitioner&apos;s services to the Panchayati Raj Department,<lb/> petitioners&apos; transfer can be made only in accordance with Rule 8 of<lb/> the Rules of 2011, which reads thus :-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;8. Transfer.-Transfer of such transferred<lb/> employees shall be made under the transfer policy<lb/> and directions issued by the State Government from<lb/> time to time, by :-<lb/></item>

			<item>(i) the Administration and Establishment<lb/> Committee of the Panchayat Samiti concerned<lb/> within the same Panchayat Samit.<lb/></item>

			<item>(ii) the District Establishment Committee of the<lb/> Zila Parishad concerned from one Panchayat<lb/> Samiti to another Panchayat Samiti within the<lb/> same District.<lb/></item>

			<item>(iii) the department Concerned from one district<lb/> to another district with the consent of the<lb/> Panchayati Raj Department.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<item>4.<lb/> Having read the provisions of Rule 8 of the Rules of 2011,<lb/> learned counsel contended that transfer of an employee, from one<lb/> Gram Panchayat to another, can be effected by the Administration<lb/> (4 of 16)<lb/></item>

			<item>[CW-14964/2019]<lb/></item>

			<p>and Establishment Committee of Panchayat Samiti concerned; in<lb/> case of transfer from one Panchayat Samiti to another, it can be<lb/> done by District Establishment Committee of the Zila Parishad<lb/> concerned and in case of inter district transfer, the same can be<lb/> done by the department concerned i.e. Medical &amp; Health<lb/> Department, of course with the consent of Panchayati Raj<lb/> Department.<lb/></p>

			<p>5.<lb/> Learned counsel contended that as per the mandate of Rule<lb/> 8 of the Rules of 2011, transfer of an ANM or any employee for<lb/> that matter, governed by the Rules of 2011, in the contingencies<lb/> mentioned in (i) and (ii) of Rule 8 can be effected by the<lb/> Panchayati Raj Department and in the third contingency i.e. in<lb/> case of inter-district transfer, the same can be done by Medical &amp;<lb/> Health Department, subject of course to consent of the Panchayati<lb/> Raj Department.<lb/></p>

			<p>6.<lb/> Inviting Court&apos;s attention towards transfer order, Mr. Bijarnia<lb/> pointed out that the same has been done by the Medical &amp; Health<lb/> Department and thus, petitioner&apos;s transfer from District Churu to<lb/> Nagaur, which otherwise is governed by Rule 8 (iii) of the Rules of<lb/> 2011, is illegal and deserves to be quashed as no consent of<lb/> Panchayati Raj Department has been obtained.<lb/></p>

			<p>7.<lb/> In a bid to lend support to his argument aforesaid, learned<lb/> counsel placed reliance on a series of judgments, more<lb/> particularly, judgment dated 14.11.2017 rendered in SB Civil Writ<lb/> Petition No.11862/2017 (Samleta Vs. State of Raj. &amp; Ors.);<lb/> Division Bench judgment dated 11.10.2018 in DB Special Appeal<lb/> Writ No.736/2018 (State of Raj. &amp; Ors. Vs. Samleta) -affirming<lb/> the Single Bench decision; judgment dated 28.05.2019 rendered<lb/> in SB Civil Writ Petition No.6917/2019 (Harish Chandra Katara Vs.<lb/></p>

			<p>(5 of 16)<lb/> [CW-14964/2019]<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.); judgment dated 12.11.2018 rendered in SB<lb/> Civil Writ Petition No.16963/2018 (Smt. Bimla Devi Vs. State of<lb/> Raj. &amp; Ors.).<lb/></p>

			<p>8.<lb/> Navigating the Court through the judgments aforesaid,<lb/> learned counsel submitted that it has been consistent view of this<lb/> Court, that transfer of ANMs or any such employee governed by<lb/> the Rules of 2011, cannot be made by the parent department,<lb/> without the prior consent of the Panchayati Raj Department in<lb/> case of inter district transfer and in case of transfer within district,<lb/> it can be done only by the District Establishment Committee or<lb/> Administration and Establishment Committee, as the case may be.<lb/></p>

			<p>9.<lb/> Mr. K.S. Rajpurohit, learned Additional Advocate General<lb/> assisted by Mr. Shreyansh Mehta defending the impugned transfer<lb/> order(s) issued by the State Government placed before the Court<lb/> an order dated 16.06.2018 issued by the State Government,<lb/> whereby an in-principle decision has been taken that in case of<lb/> transfer, the consent of Panchayati Raj Department will not be<lb/> necessary. It was also argued that while taking such decision, a<lb/> general consent has been taken from the Panchayati Raj<lb/> Department in relation to all the transfers governed by Rule 8 of<lb/> the Rules of 2011, hence, no separate consent of the Panchayati<lb/> Raj Department is necessary in case of inter-district transfers.<lb/></p>

			<p>10. It was further argued that in light of the said decision of the<lb/> State Government, it is no more necessary that transfer should be<lb/> effected by Administration &amp; Establishment Committee or District<lb/> Establishment Committee of the Panchayati Raj Department in<lb/> case of transfers within the district.<lb/></p>

			<p>11. Learned Additional Advocate General pointed out that the<lb/> order dated 16.06.2018 passed by the Chief Secretary, though in<lb/> (6 of 16)<lb/> [CW-14964/2019]<lb/> his administrative capacity has the equal effect, if not more to<lb/> Rule 8 in view of the power given to the State Government in the<lb/> body of Rule 8 of the Rules of 2011, permitting the State<lb/> Government to issue directions and guidelines.<lb/></p>

			<p>12. He zealously read opening words of Rule 8, particularly the<lb/> expression &quot;… … … under the transfer policy and directions issued<lb/> by the State Government from time to time, …&quot;, and argued that<lb/> the order dated 16.06.2018 fills the gap between the rules and in<lb/> light of what has been provided in the order dated 16.06.2018, all<lb/> the transfers made by the State, subject matter of instant writ<lb/> petitions are valid and in accordance with law.<lb/></p>

			<p>13. Having argued so, learned counsel for the respondents<lb/> submitted that the transfers in question have been made in public<lb/> interest and looking to the administrative exigencies, as it is the<lb/> Medical and Health Department, who is otherwise held responsible<lb/> or accountable for deficiency or lack of medical facilities and it is<lb/> the parent medical department, which can ascertain and adjudge<lb/> requirement or suitability of a particular employee. Resting his<lb/> arguments, he urged that since the transfers impugned were done<lb/> in public interest, interference with such orders be avoided,<lb/> keeping the public interest and public health as a paramount.<lb/> 14. Heard.<lb/></p>

			<p>15. A bare reading of Rule 8 of the Rules of 2011 leaves no room<lb/> for ambiguity that transfer of the employees, whose services have<lb/> been transferred to Panchayati Raj institution can be made by an<lb/> authority who is authorized to transfer such employee, as has<lb/> been clearly defined rather prescribed in the Rule 8 itself, viz. (i)<lb/> in case of transfer within Panchayat Samiti -Administration and<lb/> Establishment Committee of Panchayat Samiti, (ii) in case of<lb/> (7 of 16)<lb/> [CW-14964/2019]<lb/> transfer from one Panchayat Samiti to another Panchayat Samiti<lb/> within the same District -District Establishment Committee of the<lb/> Zila Parishad and (iii) in case of transfer from one District to<lb/> another or inter district transfer -department concerned with<lb/> consent of Panchayati Raj Department.<lb/></p>

			<p>16. This Court is unable to accept the argument advanced by<lb/> learned counsel for the respondents that by virtue of order dated<lb/> 16.06.2018, the State Government has given an in-principle<lb/> consent for transfer and has permitted transfers by the Medical &amp;<lb/> Health Department in case of intra Panchayat Samiti and inter<lb/> Panchayat Samiti also.<lb/></p>

			<p>17. Rules of 2011 have been framed under Article 309 of the<lb/> Constitution and they have statutory force. Any order or circular,<lb/> may it be passed by the Chief Secretary, cannot alter, obliterate or<lb/> override the provisions contained in the Rules. This Court hardly<lb/> finds any substance in the arguments of learned Additional<lb/> Advocate General that since the State legislature or rule making<lb/> authority cannot amend the Rules every of and on, as and when<lb/> required, executive order passed by the State Government can do<lb/> the same and such administrative order can be issued in public<lb/> interest and to meet the exigencies.<lb/></p>

			<p>18. All the judgments cited by learned counsel for the petitioners<lb/> right from the judgment dated 14.11.2017 in case of Samleta<lb/> (supra) till the judgment dated 28.05.2019 in case of Harish<lb/> Chandra Katara (supra), have consistently held that Rule 8 of the<lb/> Rules of 2011 is sacrosanct and the State Government cannot<lb/> transfer its staff/employee dehors the provisions contained in Rule<lb/> 8 of the Rules of 2011. Relevant portions of the judgments<lb/> aforesaid are being reproduced hereunder :-<lb/>(8 of 16)<lb/> [CW-14964/2019]<lb/></p>

			<p>(i) (Samleta Vs. State of Rajasthan &amp; Ors.) :<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;3. concededly no such consent was taken. I note<lb/> that vide order dated 20.09.2017 it was directed that<lb/> joining of duties by the petitioner pursuant to impugned<lb/> transfer order dated 15.09.2017 at the place where she<lb/> has been transferred shall be subject to the decision of the<lb/> writ petition.<lb/></p>

			<p>4. The respondents have not been able to show to<lb/> the Court as to why consent of the PanchayatiDepartment<lb/> is not warranted.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii) (State of Raj. &amp; Ors. Vs. Samleta) :<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;Sub-rule (ii) of Rule 8 of the Rajasthan Panchayati<lb/> Raj (Transfer Activities) Rules, 2011 clearly postulates that<lb/> when a person is transferred from one District to another,<lb/> there is a prerequisite condition of obtaining prior consent<lb/> of Panchayati Raj Department. In the present case, the<lb/> respondent is an employee of the Panchayati Raj<lb/> Institution and she has been transferred from one district<lb/> to another. Admittedly, no consent as per Rule 8 of the<lb/> Rules of 2011 was obtained from the Panchayati Raj<lb/> Department and therefore, her transfer is bad and in<lb/> violation of the provisions of Rule 8 of the Rules of 2011.<lb/> Even in the cases of transfer of surplus employees,<lb/> consent has to be obtained from the Panchayati Raj<lb/> Department.<lb/> In view of the above observations, we are not<lb/> inclined to interfere in the order passed by the learned<lb/> Single Judge.<lb/> The appeal is, therefore, dismissed.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>(iii) (Smt. Bimla Devi Vs. State of Raj. &amp; Ors.) :<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;Sh. S.K. Gupta Additional Advocate General<lb/> appearing for the respondents submits that in each &amp;<lb/> every matter consent as required under Rule 8 of the<lb/> Rules, 2011 is not necessary and submits that a circular<lb/> (9 of 16)<lb/></item>

			<p>[CW-14964/2019]<lb/> dated 16.06.2018 was issued in this regard by the<lb/> Panchayati Raj Department.<lb/> After hearing counsel for the parties, the contention<lb/> advanced by the counsel for the petitioners holds<lb/> substance for the reasons; firstly according to Rule 8 of<lb/> the Rules, 2011 the consent is necessary to be obtained as<lb/> required from the Panchayati Raj. Department; secondly a<lb/> bare perusal of the order/circular dated 16.6.2018 clearly<lb/> shows that it holds that for transfer of an employee the<lb/> consent of the Panchayati Raj Department is not necessary<lb/> which is violative of Rule 8 of the Rules, 2011.<lb/> In that view of the matter, the writ petitions filed by<lb/> the petitioners deserve acceptance and the transfer orders<lb/> impugned herein deserve to be set aside.<lb/> Accordingly, the writ petitions are allowed and the<lb/> respective transfer orders impugned in the present<lb/> petitions are set aside. However, the respondent-State is<lb/> at liberty to pass order of transfer afresh, if exigency of<lb/> service so require, only after strict compliance of Rule 8 of<lb/> the Rules, 2011. Copy of the order be separately placed in<lb/> each file.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>(iv) (Harish Chandra Katara Vs. State of Raj. &amp;<lb/> Ors.) :<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;Learned counsel appearing for the respondent<lb/> department placed reliance on the order dated 16.06.2018<lb/> (Annex.9 in SBCWP No.7212/2019), purportedly directing<lb/> under Rule 8 and ordering that the required consent of the<lb/> Panchayati Raj Department would not be required and<lb/> therefore, the plea raised by the petitioners in this regard<lb/> has no substance.<lb/> Learned counsel for the petitioners in SBCWP<lb/> No.7212/2019 submits that the circular dated 16.06.2018<lb/> relied on by the respondents being contrary to the express<lb/> provisions of Rule 8, the transfer orders without requisite<lb/> consent under Rule 8 has been set aside in Smt. Bimla<lb/> (10 of 16)<lb/> [CW-14964/2019]<lb/> Devi v. State of Rajasthan &amp; Ors. ; SB Civil Writ Petition<lb/> No.16963/2018, decided on 12.11.2018 at Jaipur Bench.<lb/> … … …<lb/> … … …<lb/> In view of the express provision of Rule 8 as well as<lb/> the judgment in the case of Bimla Devi (supra), wherein<lb/> the circular sought to be relied on by the respondents has<lb/> been taken into consideration, the action of the<lb/> respondents in effecting transfers of the petitioners in<lb/> SBCWP Nos.4214/2019 and 7212/2019 cannot be<lb/> sustained.<lb/> The order dated 08.03.2019 (Annex.2 in<lb/> SBCWP No.4214/2019) and order dated 08.03.2019<lb/> (Annex.8 in SBCWP No.7212/2019), qua the petitioners<lb/> are quashed and set aside.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>19. State&apos;s endeavour to justify, rather defend impugned<lb/> order(s) by submitting that these transfers have been made in<lb/> public interest and that too by the Medical &amp; Health Department,<lb/> which is the best suited to ascertain the suitability of an employee<lb/> considering the ground realities, also does not cut any ice.<lb/></p>

			<p>20. It is settled preposition of law that if a statute or rule<lb/> provides something to be done in a particular manner, such act is<lb/> required to be done only as mandated by such rule. In the<lb/> present case, Rule 8 is not only the fountain head of power to<lb/> transfer but also a dividing line or road-map setting out clearly the<lb/> authority and manner in which the transfers are to be effected.<lb/></p>

			<p>21. This Court has no hesitation in holding that transfer of<lb/> petitioners governed by the Rules of 2011 can be done only by the<lb/> authorities/committees mentioned in clause (i), (ii) and (iii) of<lb/> Rule 8 of the Rules of 2011. No authority or officer, howsoever<lb/> high he may be placed in the bureaucratic hierarchy, can transfer<lb/> an employee governed by the Rules of 2011, in violation of Rule 8.<lb/> (11 of 16)<lb/> [CW-14964/2019]<lb/></p>

			<p>22. Argument of respondents that by virtue of order dated<lb/> 16.06.2018 passed by the Chief Secretary, the Medical &amp; Health<lb/> Department has been authorized to transfer the employees of<lb/> Panchayati Raj Department is untenable. In considered opinion of<lb/> this Court, any executive order cannot over-take or take place of<lb/> substantive Rules.<lb/></p>

			<p>23. In unqualified opinion of this Court, the Rules of 2011 framed<lb/> by the State Government under Article 309 of the Constitution are<lb/> paramount. Much relied expression in Rule 8 &quot;… … … under the<lb/> transfer policy and directions issued by the State Government … …<lb/> …&quot; are only to supplement the Rule. State&apos;s attempt to give a<lb/> complete go by to the Rules in the garb of such expression is<lb/> unsustainable.<lb/></p>

			<p>24. The State Government can frame policy or issue directions<lb/> only on those aspects, in relation to which, the Rules are silent.<lb/> Any executive order of the State Government, which is contrary to<lb/> the express provision of the Rules cannot get sanction of the<lb/> Court. Such orders will have to concede, on all aspects wherever<lb/> they come in conflict with the statutory Rules.<lb/></p>

			<p>25. The order of the State Government dated 16.06.2018, if read<lb/> carefully reveals that all the stipulations contained in order dated<lb/> 16.06.2018 are contrary to express provisions contained in Rule 8.<lb/></p>

			<item>(i) Para (v) requires the consent of parent Department i.e. Medical<lb/> &amp; Health Department in cases of transfer under Rule 8(i) and 8(ii);<lb/> the same clearly falls foul to Rule 8 (i) and 8 (ii);<lb/></item>

			<item>(ii) (c) seeks to ratify such transfers affected, that too cannot be<lb/> done -an act which is void ab-initio cannot be ratified and that<lb/> too by the authority which has usurped the powers;<lb/></item>

			<item>(iii) and direction given in (l) in relation to inter-district transfers.<lb/></item>

			<item>(12 of 16)<lb/></item>

			<item>[CW-14964/2019]<lb/></item>

			<p>26. The order dated 16.06.2018 at best be read or construed to<lb/> be a prior rather tacit approval of the Panchayati Raj Department.<lb/> But in the opinion of this Court, even that is impermissible and<lb/> unsustainable because Rule 8(iii) postulates consent of Panchayati<lb/> Raj Department; whereas part (l) of the order goes on to say that<lb/> in case of inter-district transfers, parent Department will not be<lb/> required to take consent of Panchayati Raj Department.<lb/></p>

			<p>27. In considered opinion of this Court, stipulation given in part<lb/> (l) of the order does violence with what is contained in para (iii)<lb/> of Rule 8 and it is in direct conflict with Rule 8(iii) of the Rules of<lb/> 2011.<lb/></p>

			<p>28. The order dated 16.06.2018 issued by the Chief Secretary of<lb/> the State does not go along with Rule 8 of the Rules of 2011 and<lb/> thus, the same cannot be allowed to endure. Though there is no<lb/> specific challenge to said order, but since it has been relied upon<lb/> by the State as a shield to protect the order of transfers, the<lb/> Government order dated 16.06.2018 is hereby quashed.<lb/></p>

			<p>29. As a natural corollary, the impugned transfer orders (dated<lb/> 29.09.2019) issued by the Additional Director (Administration),<lb/> Medical &amp; Health Department, Rajasthan Jaipur are also quashed;<lb/> writ petitions are allowed.<lb/></p>

			<p>30. It is informed that the petitioners involved in the present<lb/> bunch of writ petitions are protected by way of interim order(s)<lb/> passed by this Court, the interim order(s) passed in these writ<lb/> petitions, consequent to petitions being allowed, are made<lb/> absolute.<lb/></p>

			<p>31. At the request of learned Additional Advocate General, the<lb/> orders of transfer dated 29.09.2019 shall be treated to have been<lb/> cancelled only qua these petitioners or who are protected by<lb/> (13 of 16)<lb/> [CW-14964/2019]<lb/> interim orders already passed.<lb/> Whosoever has/have joined<lb/> pursuant to the transfer order dated 29.09.2019, at the new place<lb/> of positing, shall not be entitled for relief and they shall not be<lb/> disturbed.<lb/></p>

			<p>32. Needless to observe that if State in administrative exigencies<lb/> wishes to transfer these petitioners, the same be done, needless<lb/> to say, strictly in accordance with Rule 8 of the Rules of 2011.<lb/></p>

			<p>33. Registry is directed to keep photostat copy of this order in<lb/> each file, mentioned in the Schedule.<lb/></p>

			<p>34. All interlocutory applications, including stay petitions stand<lb/> disposed of.<lb/></p>

			<item>(DINESH MEHTA),J<lb/></item>

			<item>17-ArunV/-<lb/>SCHEDULE<lb/> S.No.<lb/> Civil Writ Petition No.<lb/> Petitioner(s)<lb/> Respondents<lb/> 1.<lb/> SB Civil Writ Petition No.14896/2019 Kiran Devi<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>2.<lb/> SB Civil Writ Petition No.14915/2019 Meera<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>3.<lb/> SB Civil Writ Petition No.14922/2019 Deepak Verma<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>4.<lb/> SB Civil Writ Petition No.15148/2019 Bimla Devi<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>5.<lb/> SB Civil Writ Petition No.15155/2019 Sohani Vishnoi<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>6.<lb/> SB Civil Writ Petition No.15157/2019 Giriraj Kumar<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>7.<lb/> SB Civil Writ Petition No.15160/2019 Vanita Saad<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>8.<lb/> SB Civil Writ Petition No.15181/2019 Durga Shankar Meena<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>9.<lb/> SB Civil Writ Petition No.15187/2019 Anil Kumar<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>10. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15199/2019 Devi Singh<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>11. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15246/2019 Sunil Kumar Ahari<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>12. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15311/2019 Mohan Lal<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>13. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15325/2019 Nirmala Kumari<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>14. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15332/2019 Sunita<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>15. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15354/2019 Smt. Sharmila<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>16. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15360/2019 Manjula Patel<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>17. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15365/2019 Rakesh Yadav<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>18. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15373/2019 Rekha Malawat<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>19. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15376/2019 Simmi Meena<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>20. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15377/2019 Ranjeet Kour<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>21. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15386/2019 Mahesh Kumar Benda<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>22. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15388/2019 Baljeet Kaur<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>23. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15393/2019 Roshani Devi<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>24. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15404/2019 Kamla<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>25. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15479/2019 Bhawani Shankar<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>26. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15557/2019 Kamla<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>27. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15566/2019 Rajkumar Dubey<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>28. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15568/2019 Ram Kanya<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>29. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15569/2019 Pramod Kumari<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>30. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15575/2019 Suman<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>31. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15582/2019 Sulochana Jyani<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>32. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15594/2019 Sahnila<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>33. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15601/2019 Smt. Pinki<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>34. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15610/2019 Suman<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>35. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15613/2019 Sulochana<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>36. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15615/2019 Dr. Kailash Prajapat<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>37. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15697/2019 Savita Chouhan<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>38. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15698/2019 Dr. Gyanendra Joshi<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>39. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15711/2019 Rajbala<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>40. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15720/2019 Om Prakash Kumhar<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>41. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15722/2019 Geeta<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>42. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15727/2019 Mohan Lal Sonal<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>43. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15736/2019 Rajveer Singh<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>44. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15742/2019 Girija Chaturvedi<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>45. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15743/2019 Kaushlya Choudhary<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>46. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15745/2019 Nootan Kumar Bairwa<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>47. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15754/2019 Sushma<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>48. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15760/2019 Smt. Premlata Sargara<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>(15 of 16)<lb/></item>

			<item>[CW-14964/2019]<lb/></item>

			<item>49. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15776/2019 Mohan Lal Kachhwaha<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>50. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15802/2019 Rajesh Kumari<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>51. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15857/2019 Saleem Mohammed<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>52. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15872/2019 Satveer Kaur<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>53. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15876/2019 Tarawati<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>54. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15883/2019 Rajender Kumar Arora<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>55. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15935/2019 Annamma Joseph<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>56. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15969/2019 Khema Ram Bhakar<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>57. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15988/2019 Manish Kumar Sharma<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>58. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15995/2019 Raghu Bhagwan<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>59. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16006/2019 Kaushalya<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>60. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16009/2019 Sushila Devi<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>61. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16013/2019 Smt. Alka Devi<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>62. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16018/2019 Anju Devi<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>63. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16062/2019 Jointa Ram Choudhary<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>64. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16080/2019 Anita<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>65. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16081/2019 Annamma K A<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>66. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16082/2019 Dr. Ravi Nagar<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>67. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16097/2019 Rosamma John<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>68. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16107/2019 Mohini<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>69. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16113/2019 Rajesh<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>70. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16114/2019 Palwinder Kaur<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>71. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16119/2019 Manju Dhanka<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>72. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16130/2019 Saroj<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>73. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16195/2019 Bhanwar Lal Choudhary<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>74. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16197/2019 Kailash Salvi<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>75. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16199/2019 Dr. PushpendraNath Vyas State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>76. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16292/2019 Bhaskar Choudhary<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>77. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16304/2019 Saroj<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>78. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16307/2019 Dinesh Kumar<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>79. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16319/2019 Mota Ram Choudhary<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>80. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16320/2019 Geeta Devi Choudhary<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>81. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16351/2019 Fareed Khan<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>82. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16597/2019 Vandana Sehgal<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>83. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16603/2019 Nand Lal Verma<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>84. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16608/2019 Narpat Singh<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>85. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16722/2019 Kuldeep Singh<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>86. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16793/2019 Saraswati Patel<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>87. SB Civil Writ Petition No.17024/2019 Smt. Jamna Maru<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>88. SB Civil Writ Petition No.17359/2019 Ranju Ahir<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>89. SB Civil Writ Petition No.17527/2019 Mani Lal Pargi<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>90. SB Civil Writ Petition No.17680/2019 Heera Lal Dodiyar<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>91. SB Civil Writ Petition No.17757/2019 Dr. Joya Rizwan<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>92. SB Civil Writ Petition No.18263/2019 Shobha Borana<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>93. SB Civil Writ Petition No.18414/2019 Parsee<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>94. SB Civil Writ Petition No.100/2020<lb/> Manoj<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>95. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15366/2019 Karni Singh Shekhwat<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>96. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15574/2019 Madanlal<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>97. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15757/2019 Manju Sheela<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>98. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15766/2019 Bhateri Devi<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>99. SB Civil Writ Petition No.15853/2019 Dr. Deepak Gogra<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>100. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16541/2019 Yaswant Singh<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>(16 of 16)<lb/></item>

			<item>[CW-14964/2019]<lb/></item>

			<item>101. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16588/2019 Smt. Neelam<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>102. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16593/2019 Kirana<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>103. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16598/2019 Jasvinder Singh<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>104. SB Civil Writ Petition No.16872/2019 Saroj Bala<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>105. SB Civil Writ Petition No.17066/2019 Dhara Singh Meena<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>106. SB Civil Writ Petition No.17472/2019 Ram Niwas Meena<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>107. SB Civil Writ Petition No.17566/2019 Manju Pargi<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>108. SB Civil Writ Petition No.17594/2019 Jitendra Jetawat<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>109. SB Civil Writ Petition No.18114/2019 Meghraj<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>110. SB Civil Writ Petition No.18873/2019 Mukesh Mehta<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>111. SB Civil Writ Petition No.17422/2019 Sangeeta Pargi<lb/> State of Raj. &amp; Ors.</item>


	</text>
</tei>
