<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<head>Judgment<lb/> Reportable :<lb/></head>

			<item>19/03/2020<lb/></item>

			<p>1. The present group of writ petitions involves challenge to the<lb/> result of the written examination conducted by Rajasthan Public<lb/> Service Commission (hereinafter referred to as &quot;the RPSC&quot; or &quot;the<lb/> Commission&quot;) pursuant to the advertisement dated 28.03.2018<lb/> issued for recruitment of Headmasters in Secondary Education.<lb/></p>

			<p>2. The petitioners having failed to secure berth in the select list,<lb/> allege that because of the wrong assessment of the questions and<lb/> answers, they lagged behind. According to them, the answers of<lb/> some of the questions ought to have been, what they claim to be<lb/> correct and some of the questions deserve deletion. Grievance<lb/> has been raised in relation to host of questions -their improper<lb/> framing; difference in Hindi and English version of the questions;<lb/> so also regarding correctness of the answers.<lb/></p>

			<p>3. Before embarking upon the journey of adjudicating answers to<lb/> the questions and correctness of the questions themselves, this<lb/> Court deems it appropriate to sail through the judgments, which<lb/> were cited by rival counsel at Bar.<lb/></p>

			<p>4. Learned counsel for the petitioners cited judgment dated<lb/> 12.03.2019 rendered in the case of Bhundaram Vs. State (D.B.<lb/> Civil Special Appeal No.922/2018); judgment dated<lb/> 03.01.2020 rendered in the case of Vinod Kumar Vs. State of<lb/> Rajasthan (S.B. Civil Writ Petition No.12077/2019) and<lb/> judgment dated 16.04.2018 in Rameshwari Kumari Vs. State<lb/> of Rajasthan (S.B. Civil Writ Petition No.3083/2018), in a<lb/> bid to show that this court has been interfering in matters relating<lb/> to challenge to the questions and their respective answers.<lb/></p>

			<p>5. As against this, Mr. Tarun Joshi, learned counsel appearing for<lb/> the Commission, informed that upon declaration of the result,<lb/> objections were invited; all the objections were laid before a<lb/> Committee of Experts, constituted by the Commission; and said<lb/> committee after thorough deliberation and consideration of<lb/> relevant material, has given its opinion and the Commission has<lb/> proceeded strictly in accordance with the recommendation of the<lb/> experts.<lb/></p>

			<p>6. While informing that the questions under consideration are<lb/> from varied subjects, he opined that the Court should not act as<lb/> an expert and enter and traverse in an unfamiliar terrain. To<lb/> buttress such stand, learned counsel relied upon a rather recent<lb/> decision of Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court in the case of Uttar<lb/> Pradeh Public Service Commission Vs. Rahul Singh and Anr.<lb/> [(2018) 7 SCC 254].<lb/></p>

			<p>7. So far as the judgments cited by the petitioners are<lb/> concerned, they are indicative of the fact that the Courts have<lb/> been indulgent in such cases; whereas the judgment of Hon&apos;ble<lb/> the Apex Court, which was cited by Mr. Joshi, in the case of Uttar<lb/> Pradesh Public Service Commission Vs. Rahul Singh (supra); lays<lb/> down the parameters within which the Court can interfere.<lb/></p>

			<p>8. The relevant extract of the judgment of Hon&apos;ble the Supreme<lb/> Court is being reproduced hereunder:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;8. What is the extent and power of the Court<lb/> to interfere in matters of academic nature has<lb/> been the subject matter of a number of cases.<lb/> We shall deal with the two main cases cited<lb/> before us.<lb/></item>

			<item>9. In Kanpur University v. Samir Gupta, this<lb/> Court was dealing with a case relating to the<lb/> Combined Pre Medical Test. Admittedly, the<lb/> examination setter himself had provided the<lb/> key answers and there were no committees to<lb/> moderate or verify the correctness of the key<lb/> answers provided by the examiner. This Court<lb/> upheld the view of the Allahabad High Court<lb/> that the students had proved that 3 of the key<lb/> answers were wrong. Following observations<lb/> of the Court are pertinent:-<lb/></item>

			<item>16...........We agree that the key<lb/> answer should be assumed to be<lb/> correct unless it is proved to be<lb/> wrong and that it should not be<lb/> held to be wrong by an inferential<lb/> process of reasoning or by a<lb/> process of rationalization. It must<lb/> be clearly demonstrated to be<lb/> wrong, that is to say, it must be<lb/> such as no reasonable body of men<lb/> well-versed in the particular subject<lb/> would regard as correct. The Court<lb/> gave further directions but we are<lb/> concerned mainly with one that the<lb/> State Government should devise a<lb/> system for moderating the key<lb/> answers furnished by the paper<lb/> setters.<lb/></item>

			<p>10. In Ran Vijay Singh and Others vs. State<lb/> of Uttar Pradesh and Others, this Court<lb/> after referring to a catena of judicial<lb/> pronouncements summarized the legal<lb/> position in the following terms:-<lb/></p>

			<item>30. The law on the subject is<lb/> therefore, quite clear and we only<lb/> propose<lb/> to<lb/> highlight<lb/> a<lb/> few<lb/> significant conclusions. They are:<lb/></item>

			<item>30.1. If a statute, Rule or<lb/> Regulation<lb/> governing<lb/> an<lb/> examination<lb/> permits<lb/> the<lb/> re-<lb/>evaluation of an answer sheet or<lb/> scrutiny of an answer sheet as a<lb/> matter of right, then the authority<lb/> conducting the examination may<lb/> permit it;<lb/></item>

			<item>30.2. If a statute, Rule or<lb/> Regulation<lb/> governing<lb/> an<lb/> examination does not permit re-<lb/>evaluation or scrutiny of an answer<lb/> sheet (as distinct from prohibiting<lb/> it) then the court may permit re-<lb/>evaluation or scrutiny only if it is<lb/> demonstrated very clearly, without<lb/> any inferential process of reasoning<lb/> or by a process of rationalisation<lb/> and only in rare or exceptional<lb/> cases that a material error has<lb/> been committed;<lb/></item>

			<p>30.3. The court should not at all re-<lb/>evaluate or scrutinise the answer<lb/> sheets of a candidate it has no<lb/> expertise in the matter and<lb/> academic matters are best left to<lb/> academics;<lb/></p>

			<p>30.4. The court should presume the<lb/> correctness of the key answers and<lb/> proceed on that assumption; and<lb/></p>

			<item>30.5. In the event of a doubt, the<lb/> benefit<lb/> should<lb/> go<lb/> to<lb/> the<lb/> examination authority rather than<lb/> to the candidate.<lb/></item>

			<item>11. We may also refer to the following<lb/> observations in Paras 31 and 32 which show<lb/> why the Constitutional Courts must exercise<lb/> restraint in such matters:<lb/></item>

			<item>31. On our part we may add that<lb/> sympathy or compassion does not<lb/> play any role in the matter of<lb/> directing or not directing re-<lb/>evaluation of an answer sheet. If an<lb/> error<lb/> is<lb/> committed<lb/> by<lb/> the<lb/> examination authority, the complete<lb/> body of candidates suffers. The<lb/> entire examination process does not<lb/> deserve to be derailed only because<lb/> some candidates are disappointed<lb/> or dissatisfied or perceive some<lb/> injustice having been caused to<lb/> them by an erroneous question or<lb/> an erroneous answer. All candidates<lb/> suffer equally, though some might<lb/> suffer more but that cannot be<lb/> helped since mathematical precision<lb/> is not always possible. This Court<lb/> has shown one way out of an<lb/> impasse exclude the suspect or<lb/> offending question.<lb/></item>

			<item>32. It is rather unfortunate that<lb/> despite several decisions of this<lb/> Court, some of which have been<lb/> discussed<lb/> above,<lb/> there<lb/> is<lb/> interference by the courts in the<lb/> result of examinations. This places<lb/> the examination authorities in an<lb/> unenviable position where they are<lb/> under<lb/> scrutiny<lb/> and<lb/> not<lb/> the<lb/> candidates. Additionally, a massive<lb/> and<lb/> sometimes<lb/> prolonged<lb/> examination<lb/> exercise<lb/> concludes<lb/> with an air of uncertainty. While<lb/> there is no doubt that candidates<lb/> put in a tremendous effort in<lb/> preparing for an examination, it<lb/> must not be forgotten that even the<lb/> examination authorities put in<lb/> equally great efforts to successfully<lb/> conduct<lb/> an<lb/> examination.<lb/> The<lb/> enormity of the task might reveal<lb/> some lapse at a later stage, but the<lb/> court must consider the internal<lb/> checks and balances put in place by<lb/> the examination authorities before<lb/> interfering with the efforts put in by<lb/> the<lb/> candidates<lb/> who<lb/> have<lb/> successfully participated in the<lb/> examination and the examination<lb/> authorities. The present appeals are<lb/> a<lb/> classic<lb/> example<lb/> of<lb/> the<lb/> consequence of such interference<lb/> where there is no finality to the<lb/> result of the examinations even<lb/> after a lapse of eight years. Apart<lb/> from the examination authorities<lb/> even the candidates are left<lb/> wondering about the certainty or<lb/> otherwise of the result of the<lb/> examination whether they have<lb/> passed or not; whether their result<lb/> will be approved or disapproved by<lb/> the court; whether they will get<lb/> admission in a college or university<lb/> or not; and whether they will get<lb/> recruited or not. This unsatisfactory<lb/> situation<lb/> does<lb/> not<lb/> work<lb/> to<lb/> anybody&apos;s advantage and such a<lb/> state of uncertainty results in<lb/> confusion being worse confounded.<lb/> The overall and larger impact of all<lb/> this is that public interest suffers.<lb/></item>

			<item>12. The law is well settled that the onus is<lb/> on the candidate to not only demonstrate<lb/> that the key answer is incorrect but also<lb/> that it is a glaring mistake which is totally<lb/> apparent and no inferential process or<lb/> reasoning is required to show that the key<lb/> answer is wrong. The Constitutional Courts<lb/> must exercise great restraint in such<lb/> matters and should be reluctant to entertain<lb/> a plea challenging the correctness of the key<lb/> answers. In Kanpur University case (supra),<lb/> the Court recommended a system of:-(1)<lb/> moderation; (2) avoiding ambiguity in the<lb/> questions; (3) prompt decisions be taken to<lb/> exclude suspected questions and no marks<lb/> be assigned to such questions.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>9. Having gone through the above judgment and some other<lb/> judgments of the Apex court, this Court is of the opinion that a<lb/> writ Court cannot become a super-expert or Appellate Authority<lb/> over the experts. In exercise of its power of judicial review, a writ<lb/> Court can only examine as to whether the question itself as<lb/> framed was wrongly framed and/or in a given case interfere if the<lb/> answer is so erroneous that no person having acquaintance with<lb/> the subject would endorse it.<lb/></p>

			<p>10. During the course of hearing, learned counsel for the RPSC<lb/> placed for perusal of the Court, experts&apos; evaluation of answer key,<lb/> titled as &quot;Expert Validation of Answer Key&quot;. More often than not,<lb/> the Court found that the opinion of the experts justifies the name/<lb/> nomenclature given to such evaluation -they try to vindicate or<lb/> validate the answer given by the Commission. In the considered<lb/> opinion of this Court, the experts while deciding the objections<lb/> should act dispassionately and independently. They should at<lb/> least give brief reasons for holding a particular view, while taking<lb/> support of relevant material.<lb/> As the ensuing discussion will<lb/> reveal, instead of quoting excerpts or reproducing relevant book/<lb/> material, the experts have simply enclosed photocopies of the<lb/> book, even when it does not contain a direct answer.<lb/></p>

			<p>11. True it is that a candidate cannot use the writ jurisdiction as<lb/> an appeal in disguise over the experts&apos; opinion. But taking cue<lb/> from the established principles of judicial review, this Court feels<lb/> that of late it has become imperative for the Courts to be satisfied<lb/> at least about the decision making process of the experts, if not<lb/> the outcome. The Court may or may not pronounce upon the<lb/> ultimate decision of the experts, but it can certainly examine as to<lb/> whether the experts have relied upon the relevant material or not;<lb/> Court can also see as to whether on the basis of the material so<lb/> relied by the experts, no other view was possible. The Court<lb/> needs to be satisfied that the experts have given brief reasons for<lb/> taking a particular view. In case, the Court finds that the material<lb/> relied and reasoning given by the experts is not acceptable to a<lb/> man of reasonable prudence, it will not keep its hands tied.<lb/></p>

			<p>12. For the purpose of enabling the Court to have a proper judicial<lb/> review, it is expected from the expert committee to bear in mind<lb/> the following:-<lb/></p>

			<p>(i) In case the answer to a question is direct and is<lb/> not dependent upon reasoning or analysis, the<lb/> experts may avoid giving reasons. In such cases, a<lb/> reference to relevant material is imperative.<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii) In case where the answer to a particular<lb/> question is not direct -it is to be deduced or the<lb/> same is subservient to reasoning, the experts<lb/> should give brief reasons for holding such opinion,<lb/> while enclosing the authentic book/relevant<lb/> material, which they have relied upon.<lb/></p>

			<p>(iii) The experts are supposed to rely upon<lb/> authentic material and direct evidence so far as<lb/> practicable instead of referring to the text books<lb/> prescribed for the schools/colleges.<lb/></p>

			<p>(iv) If a question relates to work/report of some<lb/> Scientist, Economist, survey etc. they should<lb/> invariably refer to the original work, rather than<lb/> referring to the text books or some other author&apos;s<lb/> interpretation or reproduction of such work.<lb/></p>

			<p>13. Hence, while abstaining from being an Appellate Authority<lb/> over the experts, this Court proceeds to pronounce upon the<lb/> arguments advanced, being guided by the principles laid down in<lb/> this regard and bearing in mind, what has been deduced in<lb/> preceding paragraphs (10 to 13). The questions are being taken<lb/> one after another:-<lb/></p>

			<p>PAPER -I :<lb/></p>

			<p>14. Q. 13 -The Royal cavalry of Shivaji was called-<lb/>(1) Bargir<lb/> (2) Risala<lb/> (3) Siladar<lb/> (4) Dabeer<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (1) Bargir<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : (1) Bargir<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : To be deleted<lb/></p>

			<p>15. Learned counsel for the petitioners claims that the correct<lb/> answer is &quot;Paga&quot;, which is not provided in the options. Hence, the<lb/> question is liable to be deleted.<lb/></p>

			<p>16. In support of his contention aforesaid, Mr. Vishnoi, learned<lb/> counsel for the petitioner invited Court&apos;s attention towards a book<lb/> -&quot;Hkkjr dk jktuhfrd ,oa lka Ldfrd bfrgkl&quot;, published by Rajasthan Hindu<lb/> Granth Academy and submitted that as per the said book, there<lb/> were 45,000 ikxk (&quot;kkgh ?kq Mlokj). He contended that &quot;kkgh v&quot;o ls uk and<lb/> &quot;kkgh ?kq Mlokj are synonymous and as &quot;ikxk&quot; was not an option given<lb/> in the paper, the question No.13 was required to be deleted, while<lb/> asserting that &quot;Bargir&quot; is not the correct answer.<lb/></p>

			<p>17. Mr. Tarun Joshi, per contra, invited Court&apos;s attention towards a<lb/> book known as e/;dkyhu Hkkjr edited by Mr. Harish Chandra and<lb/> submitted that as per the said book &quot;Bargir&quot; is the correct answer,<lb/> as has been given by the Commission.<lb/></p>

			<p>18. It will not be out of place to reproduce, what has been relied<lb/> upon by Mr. Joshi, which reads thus:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;f&quot;kokth us viuh ,d LFkk;h ls uk cukbZ Fkh vkS j o&apos;kkZ dky<lb/> ds nkS jku ls fudks a dks ogkW a jgus dk LFkku Hkh miyC/k<lb/> djk;k tkrk jgk FkkA f&quot;kokth dh eR;q ds le; mudh<lb/> ls uk es a 30 ls 40 gtkj fu;fer vkS j LFkk;h :i ls<lb/> fu;q Dr ?kq Mlokj] ,d yk[k inkfr vkS j 1260 gkFkh Fks A<lb/> muds rks i[kkus ds la ca /k es a Bhd&amp;Bhd tkudkjh miyC/k<lb/> ugha gS fda rq bruk Kkr gS fd mUgks us lw jr vkS j vU;<lb/> LFkkuks a ij vkdz e.k djrs le; rks i[kkus dk mi;ks x fd;k<lb/> FkkA<lb/> Ukkxfjd iz &quot;kklu dh HkkW a fr gh lS U;&amp;iz &quot;kklu es a Hkh leq fpr<lb/> Js f.k;kW a cuh gq bZ Fkha A ?kq Mlokj ls uk es a nks Js f.k;kW a Fkh] (d)<lb/> ckjxhj os ?kq Mlokj lS fud Fks ftUgs a jkT; dh vks j ls ?kks Ms<lb/> vkS j &quot;kL= fn, tkrs Fks ( [k ) flYgnkj ftUgs a O;oLFkk vki<lb/> djuh iMrh FkhA ?kq Mlokj ls uk dh lcls Nks Vh bdkbZ es a<lb/> 25 toku gks rs Fks ] ftuds mij ,d goynkj gks rk FkkA<lb/> ikW a p goynkjks a dk ,d tq eyk gks rk Fkk] ftlds mij ,d<lb/> tq eyknkj gks rk FkkA nl tq eyknkjks a dh ,d gtkjh gks rh<lb/> Fkh vkS j ikW a p ,d gtkfj;ks a ds mij ,d ia pgtkjh gks rk<lb/> FkkA og ljuks cr ds va rxZ r vkrk FkkA iz R;s d 25 Vq dfM;ks a<lb/> ds fy, jkT; dh vks j ls ,d ukfod vkS j ,d fHk&quot;rh fn;k<lb/> tkrk FkkA<lb/></item>

			<item>19. Upon comparison of the material relied upon by rival counsel,<lb/> it emerges that the petitioner has referred to book namely &quot;Hkkjr dk<lb/> jktuhfrd ,oa lka Ldfrd bfrgkl&quot;, published by Rajasthan Hindi Granth<lb/> Academy, which clearly contains a stipulation that there were forty<lb/> five thousand ikxk (&quot;kkgh ?kq Mlokj), as against this a perusal of above<lb/> part of the book relied upon by the Commission is not even<lb/> indicative of the answer to the question set by the examiner.<lb/></item>

			<item>20. A reading of the above paragraph from the book, which has<lb/> been heavily relied upon by the Commission, shows that it does<lb/> not bring to fore as to what was the Royal Cavalry or &quot;kkgh ?kq Mlokj<lb/> called. Even going by the above excerpted part, what can be<lb/> inferred is that there were two types of soldiers riding horses :<lb/></item>

			<item>(i) Bargirs who were provided horses by the State and (ii) Silhdars<lb/> who were supposed to arrange them at their own. It is not<lb/> suggestive of the name by which Royal Cavalry of Shivaji was<lb/> called.<lb/></item>

			<p>21. This Court is not satisfied with the material placed by<lb/> the Commission in support of the stand that the Option (1)<lb/> is the correct answer to question No.13. The answer key<lb/> qua question No.13 is, therefore, set aside; the matter is<lb/> referred back to Expert Committee, to be constituted by the<lb/> Commission, which will go through relevant material,<lb/> including the book relied upon by the rival parties.<lb/></p>

			<p>22. Q.22 When did Swami Vivekanand establish Ram Krishna<lb/> Math at Belur-<lb/>(1) 1909<lb/> (2) 1881<lb/> (3) 1897<lb/> (4) 1901<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (3) 1897<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : Question was deleted<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : (3) 1897<lb/></p>

			<p>23. Learned counsel for the petitioners submitted that the answer<lb/> given by the RPSC in first answer key &quot;Option (3) 1897&quot;, is<lb/> correct, which fact is evident from the History book of Secondary<lb/> Education prescribed for Rajasthan State Open School. However,<lb/> the RPSC deleted the aforesaid question.<lb/></p>

			<p>24. As per the expert opinion, none of the options given qua this<lb/> question were correct. Inviting Court&apos;s attention towards the<lb/> expert opinion, it was pointed out that establishment of<lb/> Ramkrishna Math was a continuous process and the same started<lb/> in April 1898, whereas in 1897 Ramkrishna Mission was<lb/> established.<lb/></p>

			<p>25. Upon consideration of the material relied upon by the<lb/> petitioner, particularly page No.178 of the paper-book, what<lb/> transpires is that in 1897 Swami Vivekananda established<lb/> Ramkrishna Mission and constructed Belur Math.<lb/></p>

			<p>26. The experts have noted that the process establishing &apos;Math&apos;<lb/> began in the year 1898. Though, the experts have made reference<lb/> of Biography of Swami Vivekananda (page No.1041) and<lb/> Biography of Sister Nevedita (page No.10) but they are also<lb/> suggestive and not concrete. The experts have also given the<lb/> information available on official website namely belurmath.org.<lb/></p>

			<p>27. The decision of the experts, based on the information<lb/> available on official website of &apos;Math&apos; cannot be faulted with. What<lb/> has been relied upon by petitioner relates to Ramkrishna Mission<lb/> and not &apos;Math&apos;. Petitioners have failed to distinguish between<lb/> Ramkrishna Mission and Ramkrishna Math.<lb/></p>

			<p>28. As an upshot of above discussion, this Court does not find any<lb/> error in the stand of the Commission.<lb/></p>

			<p>29. The challenge to the answer key qua this question fails.<lb/> The Commission&apos;s decision to delete Question No.22 of<lb/> Paper-I is, therefore, affirmed.<lb/></p>

			<p>30. Q.37-The moderate leader of the congress who served as a<lb/> member of Indian Public Service Commission during 1912-1915<lb/> was -<lb/>(1) Gopal Krishna Gokhale<lb/> (2) Dada Bhai Noroji<lb/> (3) Surendra Nath Banerjee<lb/> (4) Firojshah Mehta<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (1) Gopal Krishna Gokhale<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : (1) Gopal Krishna Gokhale<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : To be deleted.<lb/></p>

			<p>31. Learned counsel for the petitioners submitted that the RPSC<lb/> has given option No. (1) for the aforesaid question in both the<lb/> answer keys published by it, which is not correct because no<lb/> commission in the name of Indian Public Service Commission ever<lb/> existed more particularly during the aforesaid period. It was<lb/> asserted that it was &quot;Royal Commission in the Public Services&quot;,<lb/> while relying upon a book of Political Science of Class-XIth.<lb/> Learned counsel contended that the RPSC ought to have deleted<lb/> this question.<lb/></p>

			<p>32. Mr. Joshi invited Court&apos;s attention towards the photostat copy<lb/> of a notification dated 30.01.1922 and submitted that Gopal<lb/> Krishna Gokhle was a Member of &quot;Royal Commission on the Public<lb/> Services in India&quot;.<lb/> He invited Court&apos;s attention towards the<lb/> expert&apos;s opinion, who has relied upon a book known as &quot;vk/kq fud<lb/> Hkkjr&quot; written by Yashpal Grover to show that Gopal Krishna Gokhle<lb/> was member of Indian Public Service Commission. A reliance was<lb/> also placed upon Encyclopedia &quot;Britanica&quot;, which contains an<lb/> information about Gopal Krishna Gokhle and that Shri Gokhle was<lb/> Member of India Public Service Commission between 1912-15.<lb/></p>

			<p>33. The essence of the question is clear -the paper setter wanted<lb/> to elicit name of moderate Congress Leader, who was a member of<lb/> India Public Service Commission. May be, the Indian Public<lb/> Service Commission had not come into existence during 1912-15<lb/> and its name was &quot;Royal Commission in the Public Services&quot;, as<lb/> claimed by the petitioners. But then, this question should not<lb/> create confusion in the mind of the candidates, merely because of<lb/> wrong name.<lb/> No other person out of the available options<lb/> remained member of Royal Commission in the Public Services or<lb/> Indian Public Service Commission during the period 1912-15.<lb/> Going by the thrust of the question, this Court is satisfied that the<lb/> petitioners have created an uncalled for confusion about the<lb/> question under the cloak of so called error that too in the name of<lb/> Public Service Commission, which is inconsequential having regard<lb/> to the tenor of the question.<lb/></p>

			<p>34. This Court, hardly finds any substance in the challenge<lb/> to this question. Challenge fails. Option (1) i.e. Gopal<lb/> Krishna Gokhale, declared by the Commission is affirmed.<lb/></p>

			<p>35. Q.65-In which of the following women -literacy rate (Census<lb/> 2011) is lowest in the country?<lb/></p>

			<p>(1) Rajasthan<lb/> (2) Bihar<lb/> (3) Uttar Pradesh<lb/> (4) Nagaland<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (1) Rajasthan<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : (2) Bihar<lb/> Claim by the petitioner<lb/> : (1) Rajasthan<lb/> 36. An argument was advanced by Mr. Inderjeet Yadav in relation<lb/> to question No.65, which deals with Women Literacy rate (Census<lb/> 2011). A perusal of the pleadings of the petitioner shows that it<lb/> has not been pleaded as to how answer given by RPSC qua<lb/> question No.65 is wrong.<lb/></p>

			<p>37. It is rather disturbing that it is only in prayer No.(ii) (Writ<lb/> Petition No.17294/2019), the petitioner has made a prayer that<lb/> question No.65 be deleted. The petitioner has placed Annex.23<lb/> along with the memo of writ petition, but without making any<lb/> reference. Though, during the course of submission, learned<lb/> counsel had invited Court&apos;s attention towards Annex.23, but the<lb/> writ petition is absolutely silent about Annex.23. Not even a<lb/> whisper about Annex.23 is found in the entire memo of writ<lb/> petition, running into 15 pages.<lb/></p>

			<p>38. Be that as it may, relying upon photostat copies of the Text-<lb/>Book of Geography Class-XII, Mr. Yadav contended that correct<lb/> answer is Rajasthan with 52.70%. The experts have relied upon<lb/> census published by Government of India and Data Book.<lb/></p>

			<p>39. The Court itself has surfed through the official website i.e.<lb/> census2011.co.in and found that Bihar has lowest Female literacy<lb/> rate (51.50%) and Rajasthan is just ahead with 52.12%, as per<lb/> the Census of 2011.<lb/></p>

			<p>40. Petitioners&apos; challenge is based upon a book, which<lb/> cannot be given more weightage than the figures of census<lb/> itself. Challenge fails. Option (2) i.e. Bihar given by the<lb/> Commission, which is based upon the official website of<lb/> Census -2011 is affirmed.<lb/></p>

			<p>41. Q.69-According to Tendulkar&apos;s Estimates (2009) what<lb/> percentage of Indian population is living below poverty line?<lb/> (1) 20.18%<lb/> (2) 25.20%<lb/> (3) 30.1%<lb/> (4) 37.2%<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (4) 37.2%<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : (4) 37.2%<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : To be deleted<lb/></p>

			<p>42. Mr. Mahaveer Bishnoi, learned counsel for the petitioners<lb/> submitted that the RPSC has given option No. (4) for the aforesaid<lb/> question in both the answer keys published by it. According to the<lb/> petitioners, as per Tendulkar&apos;s Estimates (2009), total 29.8% of<lb/> Indian population was living below poverty line, which fact is<lb/> fortified from Economic Book of Class-XI, prescribed by the Board<lb/> of Secondary Education Rajasthan, Ajmer (Annex-18 and 19).<lb/> Since option of 29.8% was not given in the question paper, the<lb/> petitioners urged that this question is required to be deleted.<lb/></p>

			<p>43. Mr. Kunal Vishnoi, learned counsel for another petitioner<lb/> invited Court&apos;s attention towards the press release of the<lb/> Government of India and submitted that as per such release, the<lb/> poverty estimates are 29.8%.<lb/></p>

			<p>44. Mr. Jangid echoed the same voice while relying upon certain<lb/> books, such as book of economics published by Rajasthan Rajya<lb/> Pathya Pustak Mandal and the book of economics recognized by<lb/> National Council of Educational Research and Training (NCERT).<lb/></p>

			<p>45. Mr. Joshi, learned counsel for the respondent-Commission, on<lb/> the other hand, submitted that the petitioners have not properly<lb/> understood the question. He relied upon the expert&apos;s opinion in<lb/> this regard and submitted that experts have opined the correct<lb/> answer to be Option No.(4), i.e. 37.2%.<lb/></p>

			<p>46. He navigated the Court through the material relied upon by<lb/> the experts, particularly poverty estimates 2011-12, published by<lb/> Government of India Planning Commission -2013, and submitted<lb/> that as per the poverty estimates given by the Planning<lb/> Commission, poverty ratio for such period was 37.2%.<lb/></p>

			<p>47. Upon perusal of the material placed by the Commission, this<lb/> Court finds that percentage 37.2 has been shown as poverty ratio,<lb/> but that is against year 2004-05. A perusal of the documents<lb/> relied upon by Mr. Tarun Joshi shows that 37.2% has been shown<lb/> to be poverty ratio for year 2004-05.<lb/></p>

			<p>48. The Court, not being a subject expert, cannot pronounce upon<lb/> correctness of the answer, yet, on the basis of material placed by<lb/> the Commission vis-à-vis the material placed by the petitioners,<lb/> can well ascertain whose stand is more logical. The Commission<lb/> has not been able to prove by any documentary evidence that as<lb/> per the Tendulkar&apos;s Estimate (2009), what is the percentage of<lb/> indian population, which is living below poverty line, let alone the<lb/> percentage (37.2) claimed by it. The petitioners have been able<lb/> to satisfy that the answer given by the RPSC i.e. 37.2% is not<lb/> beyond the pale of doubt.<lb/></p>

			<p>49. During the Course of hearing, copy of the report dated<lb/> 27.11.2009, forwarded by Suresh D. Tendulkar has been placed<lb/> for perusal of the Court. According to Annexure.A of the report,<lb/> final poverty lines and poverty head count ratio for 2004-05 of<lb/> India, has been shown to be 37.2%.<lb/></p>

			<p>50. The question under consideration does not speak of estimates<lb/> for the year 2009-10, as a matter of fact, it required the<lb/> candidates to answer as to what is the percentage of persons<lb/> below poverty line as per Tendulkar&apos;s Report (2009).<lb/></p>

			<p>51. A perusal of the Tendulkar&apos;s Report reveals that it contains<lb/> Annexure.B, which provides &quot;Poverty Estimates and Poverty Lines<lb/> for 1993-94&quot; as against Annexure.A, which contains a heading<lb/> &quot;Final Poverty Lines and Poverty Heading Count Ratio for 2004-<lb/>05&quot;.<lb/></p>

			<p>52. This Court is not at all satisfied by the stand taken by the<lb/> Commission based on Annexure-A to the Report, as the same<lb/> gives out final poverty lines and poverty head count ratio for<lb/> 2004-05; whereas the question was in relation to percentage of<lb/> Indian population living below poverty line as per Tendulkar&apos;s<lb/> Estimates (2009).<lb/></p>

			<p>53. The question was very specific and the experts were required<lb/> to directly refer to the report of Tendulkar. It is a matter of<lb/> concern that the experts have not even referred to Tendulkar&apos;s<lb/> Report, which is evident from a look at the copy of the expert<lb/> validation of answer key, provided by the Commission for perusal<lb/> of the Court. It will be apt to reproduce what has been noted by<lb/> the Expert Committee while validating (literally) question No.69:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;Question No.69 -(4)<lb/> Source -Press note of Poverty<lb/> Estimate 2011-12, Government of<lb/> India, Planning Commission 2013<lb/> (copy attached). It is within syllabus<lb/> (proof attached).&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>54. Even going by the press note on poverty estimates relied<lb/> upon by the experts and placed for perusal of the Court, this court<lb/> finds that para No.9 shows otherwise. Relevant parts of para No.9<lb/> is reproduced hereunder:-<lb/></p>

			<item>9. xxx xxx xxx. It was 50.1% in rural<lb/> areas, 31.8% in urban areas and<lb/> 45.3% for the country as a whole in<lb/> 1993-94. In 2011-12, India had 270<lb/> million persons below the Tendulkar<lb/> Poverty Line as compared to 407<lb/> million in 2004-05, that is reduction of<lb/> 137 million persons over the seven year<lb/> period.<lb/></item>

			<p>55. In considered opinion of this Court, the experts were required<lb/> to look into Tendulkar&apos;s Report, which has been placed for perusal<lb/> by learned counsel Mr. Joshi.<lb/></p>

			<p>56. That apart, the Court fails to comprehend as to why the<lb/> experts have picked up figure &apos;37.2&apos; given against 2004-05 in<lb/> Column No.3 Row No.2 of the Table and not &apos;21.9&apos; given in Column<lb/> No.3 Row No.3, against year 2011-12. Generally speaking, in the<lb/> year 2009, figures of 2004-05 cannot be said to be estimates, but<lb/> figures of 2011-12 can be estimates.<lb/></p>

			<p>57. Be that as it may, having regard to the discrepancy<lb/> noticed, the question is referred to the Expert Committee to<lb/> be constituted by the Commission, which will give its<lb/> opinion making specific reference to Tendulkar&apos;s Report.<lb/></p>

			<p>58. Q.80-When Rajasthan Govt. approved first forest policy?<lb/></p>

			<item>(1) September 2011<lb/></item>

			<item>(2) August 2010<lb/></item>

			<item>(3) March 2011<lb/></item>

			<item>(4) February 2010<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (4) February 2010<lb/> Revised result<lb/> : (4) February 2010<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : To be deleted.<lb/></item>

			<p>59. Learned counsel argued that topic of Forest and other related<lb/> topics are not provided in the syllabus of the examination.<lb/></p>

			<p>60. Mr. Joshi, learned counsel for the respondent Commission<lb/> submitted that the topic is duly covered in the syllabus under the<lb/> subject &quot;Land Use&quot;.<lb/></p>

			<p>61. This Court is satisfied with the stand of the Commission<lb/> that forest policy is a part of land use; the question is not<lb/> out of course. No interference is, thus, called for.<lb/></p>

			<p>62. Q.96-Which one of the following statements about Rajasthan<lb/> is not correct?<lb/></p>

			<item>(1) Its East-West extent is more than North-South extent.<lb/></item>

			<item>(2) Its East-West extent is less than North -South extent.<lb/></item>

			<item>(3) Its total land boundary is less 6000 km.<lb/></item>

			<item>(4) Its latitudinal extent is more than 7 o latitudes.<lb/></item>

			<p>Answer given by the RPSC : (2) Its East -West extent is less than<lb/> North -South extent.<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : Question was deleted<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : (2) Its East -West extent is less than<lb/> North -South extent.<lb/></p>

			<p>63. Learned counsel for the petitioners pointed out that the RPSC<lb/> has given option No. (2) for the aforesaid question at the first<lb/> instance, whereafter this question was deleted. Petitioners<lb/> contention has been that the correct answer is &quot;option No. (2)&quot;<lb/> and there was no reason to delete the question. In support of his<lb/> argument that correct answer is (2), he relied upon the book of<lb/> Geography of Rajasthan published by the Rajasthan Hindi Granth<lb/> Academy (Annex.20).<lb/></p>

			<p>64. Mr. Joshi, learned counsel appearing for the respondent<lb/> Commission submitted that the experts have directed to delete<lb/> the question, as the word &quot;than&quot; is missing in English version.<lb/></p>

			<p>65. Justifying the stand of the RPSC/experts, learned counsel<lb/> submitted that omission of expression &quot;than&quot; in option (3) has<lb/> resulted in vagueness in its meaning and thus, the question was<lb/> rightly deleted.<lb/></p>

			<p>66. This Court is of the opinion that an option has to be<lb/> contextually understood in the backdrop of the corresponding<lb/> question. The question No.96 specifically asked that which of the<lb/> given options was not correct. Option (3) even without the use of<lb/> expression &quot;than&quot; was able to convey the meaning reasonably.<lb/> True it is, that a typographical error has crept in, but such<lb/> innocuous error did not warrant the question to be deleted.<lb/></p>

			<p>67. Given the fact that Rajasthan&apos;s total perimeter or land<lb/> boundary is 5920 kms., a candidate appearing in the examination<lb/> (even without use of word &apos;than&apos;) would find that the statement<lb/> given in option No.3 was correct. If all the four options are<lb/> compared, one would easily discern that option (2) i.e. &apos;east-west<lb/> extent is less than north south extent&apos; was the only incorrect<lb/> statement and thus option No.2 was the correct answer.<lb/></p>

			<p>68. In considered opinion of this Court, the RPSC has committed<lb/> error in deleting the question, merely because of omission of the<lb/> word &quot;than&quot; in option (3). Even if one does not look at the Hindi<lb/> version of the question, the import of the option can well be<lb/> gathered.<lb/> The omission at least does not alter the soul or<lb/> substance of the question.<lb/></p>

			<p>69. As per this Court, inadvertent slips or typographical error,<lb/> which do not change the character or substance of the<lb/> question/answer, should not entail deletion of the question, as has<lb/> been done by the Commission in the instant case.<lb/></p>

			<p>70. Petitioners&apos; challenge to the revised answer key,<lb/> therefore, succeeds. Deletion of question No.96 is,<lb/> therefore, set aside.<lb/></p>

			<p>71. Q.101-The census year with lowest sex-ratio in Rajasthan<lb/> between year 1901 to 2011 is -<lb/>(1) 1901<lb/> (2) 1921<lb/> (3) 1991<lb/> (4) 2011<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (2) 1921<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : (2) 1921<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : To be deleted.<lb/></p>

			<p>72. Learned counsel for the petitioners submitted that the RPSC<lb/> has given option No. (2) for the aforesaid question in both the<lb/> answer keys published by it. It is claimed that in Syllabus, only<lb/> Census of 2011 is mentioned, thus question was out of syllabus. It<lb/> was also argued that the question suggests the census year with<lb/> lowest sex ratio in Rajasthan between year 1901 to 2011, but in<lb/> the year 1921, the State of Rajasthan was not even formed,<lb/> hence, the question itself was wrong. Prayer was to delete this<lb/> question, pertaining to a subject, which was not covered by the<lb/> syllabus.<lb/></p>

			<p>73. Responding to objection raised by the petitioner that this<lb/> question is out of syllabus as the syllabus only mentions Census-<lb/>2011, Mr. Joshi, learned counsel for the respondent-Commission<lb/> submitted that the question No.101 does not relate to census; the<lb/> question is from a chapter relating to demographic characteristics.<lb/> Taking the Court through the syllabus, he submitted that &apos;sex<lb/> ratio&apos; is a part of demographic study.<lb/></p>

			<p>74. Having heard learned counsel for the parties and going<lb/> through the syllabus, this Court is of the considered opinion<lb/> that sex ratio is a part of demographic characteristics. It<lb/> cannot be said that the same is out of syllabus. The<lb/> objection fails. Hence, option (2) i.e. 1921 given by the<lb/> Commission is affirmed.<lb/></p>

			<p>75. Q.114-In Odisha and Andhra Pradesh shifting agriculture is<lb/> known as -<lb/>(1) Penda<lb/> (2) Podu<lb/> (3) Onam<lb/> (4) Jhoom<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (2) Podu<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : (2) Podu<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : To be deleted<lb/></p>

			<p>76. Learned counsel for the petitioners submitted that the RPSC<lb/> has given option No. (2) for the aforesaid question in both the<lb/> answer keys published by it, but as per the authentic books and<lb/> proofs, more than one options are correct, thus, the question was<lb/> required to be deleted by the RPSC.<lb/> (Samkalin Bharat-2,<lb/> Geography Book of Class-X).<lb/></p>

			<p>77. A perusal of the expert opinion placed by the Commission<lb/> reveals that objection relating to Question No.114 has been<lb/> rejected by the expert inter alia observing that the question is<lb/> within syllabus.<lb/></p>

			<p>78. The objection regarding Question No.114, as raised by the<lb/> petitioners, does not relate to syllabus, but the same assails the<lb/> adjudication by the Commission on its merit, whereas the expert<lb/> committee of Commission seems to have decided the objection<lb/> only on the allegation that the same is out of syllabus.<lb/></p>

			<p>79. Though Mr. Joshi tried to satisfy the Court that option No.2 is<lb/> the correct answer, while taking the Court through photo copies of<lb/> various books, however, since the expert committee itself has not<lb/> dealt with the objection in the manner raised by the petitioners,<lb/> this Court leaves it to be determined by the expert, instead of<lb/> deciding the challenge as an expert.<lb/></p>

			<p>80. The matter is, therefore, referred to expert committee<lb/> to be constituted by the Commission, which will give the<lb/> correct answer to this question.<lb/></p>

			<p>81. Q.115-Which one of the following crops in India is estimated<lb/> to have decreased production during 2017-18 over the year 2016-<lb/>17?<lb/></p>

			<p>(1) Rice<lb/> (2) Cotton<lb/> (3) Wheat<lb/> (4) Sugarcane<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (3) Wheat<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : (3) Wheat<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : To be deleted<lb/></p>

			<p>82. Learned counsel for the petitioners submitted that the RPSC<lb/> has given option No. (3) for the aforesaid question in both the<lb/> answer keys published by it. It was asserted that production of<lb/> none of the crops witnessed decrease in the relevant year as per<lb/> the estimates given by Agriculture, Cooperative and Farmer<lb/> Welfare Department, Government of India.<lb/> According to the<lb/> petitioners the options were wrong (source -report of year 2018-<lb/>19 issued by the Agriculture Department, Government of India,<lb/> Annex.22) hence, the question was to be deleted by the RPSC.<lb/></p>

			<p>83. Joining the issue on this question, Mr. Joshi, while reading<lb/> question, pointed out that the question was about estimate and<lb/> not advanced estimates. He invited Court&apos;s attention towards<lb/> proof relied upon by the experts (as on 28.08.2018), more<lb/> particularly towards the last four columns (2016-17 &amp; 2017-18)<lb/> and submitted that the production of wheat, which was 98.51<lb/> million tons as per final estimates of 2016-17, has decreased to<lb/> 97.50 as per the estimates of 2017-18.<lb/></p>

			<p>84. Mr. Joshi further relied upon a print-out/photostat copy of<lb/> some document (source whereof has not been given) and pointed<lb/> out that there was a reduction of production of wheat. It will not<lb/> be out of place to reproduce the part, which was relied upon by<lb/> Mr. Joshi.<lb/> &quot;</p>

			<p>5.-Production of wheat estimated at<lb/> 97.11 million of tons is lower by 1.40<lb/> million tons&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>85. Petitioners have placed on record annual report for year 2018-<lb/>19, published by Agricultural Cooperative and Farmers&apos; Welfare<lb/> Department, which shows that production of none of the crops has<lb/> decreased in the year 2017-18. As against this, the Commission<lb/> has placed on record figures of agricultural statistics published by<lb/> Directorate of Economics and Statistics Department of Agriculture.<lb/></p>

			<p>86. A careful reading of the documents produced by the<lb/> Commission shows that the table provides fourth advanced<lb/> estimates of production of food-grains for 2017-18.<lb/></p>

			<p>87. It will not be out of place to reproduce relevant part of the<lb/> document placed by the Commission, which reads thus:-<lb/>Crop<lb/> 2016-17<lb/> 2017-18<lb/> Wheat 4 th<lb/> Advanced<lb/> Estimates<lb/> Final<lb/> Estimates<lb/> Targets<lb/> 4 th<lb/> Advanced<lb/> Estimates<lb/> 98.38<lb/> 98.51<lb/> 97.50<lb/> 99.70<lb/></p>

			<p>88. Upon comparing the above figures, this Court is not in a<lb/> position to discern as to how the Commission claims that<lb/> production of wheat estimated to have decreased during 2017-18<lb/> over the year 2016-17.<lb/></p>

			<p>89. Faced with such situation, the Court tried to find answer in the<lb/> experts&apos; opinion for this question, but is surprised, if not shocked<lb/> to see the adjudication made by the experts. It is deemed<lb/> necessary to reproduce, what has been reported by the Experts<lb/> qua question No.115:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;115. Answer (3) -objection over-ruled.<lb/> (Proof attached)&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>90. It is to be noted that not only about question No.115, even<lb/> qua questions No.112 &amp; 114, the body of experts have given its<lb/> opinion rather verdict in the same cryptic manner. The experts<lb/> are supposed to give their opinion with reasoning and proofs. The<lb/> experts have decided the objection in less than one line, as if they<lb/> are solving the paper themselves.<lb/> Decision of objection<lb/> presupposes dealing with the objection with reasons.<lb/></p>

			<p>91. Mr. Joshi has placed the above referred material given by the<lb/> experts as a proof. The proofs furnished by the Commission do not<lb/> give any direct answer to the question. The Experts were at least<lb/> required to dilate upon as to how option (3) is the correct answer<lb/> to question No.115.<lb/></p>

			<p>92. Upon perusal of the proof submitted by the Commission to<lb/> show that the figures have reduced from 98.50% to 97.50%, this<lb/> Court finds that figure 98.51 is given under heading &quot;Final<lb/> Estimates for year 2016-17&quot; whereas 97.50% is given under<lb/> headings &quot;Targets for year 2017-18&quot;.<lb/></p>

			<p>93. If that be so and figures mentioned in the Columns 17 and 18<lb/> of the table are to be compared, this Court finds that even qua<lb/> rice, the figures have reduced from 109.70 to 108.50 and so is the<lb/> position, vis-à-vis sugar-cane, which has reduced from 3060.69 to<lb/> 3550, if one compares the figures mentioned in column No.17 and<lb/> 18 of the table.<lb/></p>

			<p>94. The question is, therefore, referred to expert committee<lb/> to be constituted by the Commission.<lb/></p>

			<p>95. Q.125-Which one of the following is not an area of<lb/> Mediterranean type of climate?<lb/></p>

			<p>(1) Central California<lb/> (2) Northern New Zealand<lb/> (3) Central Chile<lb/> (4) Southern tip of Africa<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (2) Northern New Zealand<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : (2) Northern New Zealand<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : To be deleted<lb/> 96. Learned counsel for the petitioners submitted that the RPSC<lb/> has given option No. (2) for the aforesaid question in both the<lb/> answer keys published by it. It was argued by the petitioners that<lb/> a candidate was required to point out which of the following is not<lb/> an area of Mediterranean type of climate, but all the places given<lb/> in the options witness Mediterranean climate, as is evident from<lb/> book of NCERT for Class-XI and book of Physical Geography<lb/> published by Rajasthan Hindi Granth Academy. According to the<lb/> petitioner, since all the options were correct, the question was<lb/> required to be deleted by the RPSC.<lb/></p>

			<p>97. Responding to petitioners&apos; argument, Mr. Joshi relied upon<lb/> photo copy of book (Page No.531 of book), written by Mr. Savindra<lb/> Singh and submitted that Mediterranean regions include California,<lb/> South-Western tip of Africa, South Australia and South-west<lb/> Australia,<lb/> whereas<lb/> New<lb/> Zealand<lb/> does<lb/> not<lb/> experience<lb/> Mediterranean climate.<lb/></p>

			<p>98. A perusal of the material placed by the petitioners shows that<lb/> one book, namely, Physical Geography, published by Dr.L.N.<lb/> Upadhyay, shows that south-west part of Australia and Northern<lb/> part of New Zealand experience Mediterranean climate. No other<lb/> book has been placed by the petitioners showing that New<lb/> Zealand experience Mediterranean climate.<lb/></p>

			<p>99. In absence of any substantial or relevant material<lb/> evincing the stand of the expert to be erroneous, this Court<lb/> is inclined to go with the view of the experts.<lb/> The<lb/> challenge to question No.125, therefore, fails. Option (2)<lb/> i.e. Northern New Zealand given by the Commission is<lb/> affirmed.<lb/></p>

			<item>100. Q.126 -Which vitamin helps in healing of wounds ?<lb/></item>

			<item>(1) Vitamin A<lb/></item>

			<item>(2) Vitamin B<lb/></item>

			<item>(3) Vitamin C<lb/></item>

			<item>(</item>

			<p>4) Vitamin D<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (4) Vitamin D<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : (3) Vitamin C<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : To be deleted<lb/> 101. Learned counsel for the petitioners submitted that the RPSC<lb/> has given option No. (4) for the aforesaid question in the first<lb/> answer key, thereafter, changed to option No.(3) in the revised<lb/> answer key published by it. Petitioners claim that as per authentic<lb/> books and proofs, all the options are correct, thus, the question<lb/> deserves to be deleted.<lb/></p>

			<p>102. In support of stand aforesaid, Mr. Jangid relied upon text-<lb/>book of Agricultural Science for Class XI, published by Board of<lb/> Secondary Education, Ajmer and submitted that Vitamin-A also<lb/> plays an important role in healing of the wound.<lb/></p>

			<p>103. Mr. Joshi, learned counsel appearing for the respondent-<lb/>Commission submitted that the experts have found option (3) -<lb/>Vitamin-C to be the correct option. He emphasised that in a<lb/> multiple-choice question, a candidate is required to give most<lb/> suitable option as the answer. Inviting Court&apos;s attention towards<lb/> various material, he submitted that it is the Vitamin-C, which is<lb/> primarily responsible for healing the wound.<lb/></p>

			<p>104. Mr. Jangid has relied upon a book of Agriculture Science,<lb/> which shows relevance of Vitamin &apos;A&apos; in healing of the wound.<lb/> Book written by an author on Agriculture Science cannot be<lb/> treated to be a magnacarta on the use of Vitamins.<lb/></p>

			<p>105. On the basis of material placed by the RPSC and based<lb/> on experts&apos; opinion, this Court holds that option (3), i.e.<lb/> Vitamin-C given by the RPSC is the most suitable answer.<lb/> The petitioners&apos; challenge to question No.126, therefore,<lb/> fails.<lb/></p>

			<p>106. Q.127-Who invented penicillin?<lb/> (1) Stephenson<lb/> (2) Dunlop<lb/> (3) Kove<lb/> (4) Alexander Fleming<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (4) Alexander Fleming<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : Question was deleted<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : (4) Alexander Fleming<lb/> 107. Learned counsel for the petitioners submitted that the RPSC<lb/> had given option No. (4) for the aforesaid question in the first<lb/> answer key, but deleted this question in the revised answer key.<lb/> Learned counsel contended that though option No. (4) as given by<lb/> the RPSC in the first answer key was correct, as is evident from<lb/> Science Book of Class-VI, published by Rajasthan Rajya<lb/> Pathyapustak Mandal, Jaipur (Annex.25), yet the RPSC has<lb/> deleted this question for no valid reason.<lb/></p>

			<p>108. Mr. Joshi, learned counsel appearing for the respondent-<lb/>Commission submitted that though option (4), namely, Alexander<lb/> Fleming is the correct answer, but the experts have deleted the<lb/> question as it was not covered by syllabus.<lb/></p>

			<p>109. Counsel for the petitioners argued that the Commission has<lb/> erred in deleting the question claiming it to be duly covered by<lb/> chapter &quot;Structure and Function of Cell and Biomolecules.&quot; Mr.<lb/> Kunal Vishnoi and Mr. Jangid, learned counsel appearing for<lb/> different petitioners, invited Court&apos;s attention towards the syllabus<lb/> and expanse of the subjects Structure and Functions of Cell and<lb/> Biomolecules to convince the Court that it is covered in the<lb/> syllabus.<lb/></p>

			<p>110. In the considered opinion of this Court, if the examining body<lb/> itself finds that a particular question is out of syllabus, the<lb/> interference of the Court has to be minimum.<lb/></p>

			<p>111. This Court is of the opinion that since the<lb/> RPSC/experts have found the question to be out of<lb/> syllabus, no interference is warranted.<lb/> Deletion of<lb/> Question No.127 by the Commission is, therefore, upheld.<lb/></p>

			<p>112. Q.131 -Mirage is an example of -<lb/>(1) Refraction<lb/> (2) Total internal reflection<lb/> (3) Deflection<lb/> (4) Diffraction<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (2) Total internal reflection<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : Question was deleted<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : (2) Total internal reflection<lb/></p>

			<p>113. Learned counsel for the petitioners submitted that the RPSC<lb/> has given option No. (2) for the aforesaid question in the first<lb/> answer key but later deleted this question in revised answer key.<lb/> Petitioners&apos; stand is that the correct option is (2) &quot;Total internal<lb/> reflection&quot;, which is fortified from perusal of Physics Text book of<lb/> Class-XII (Annex.26). The question was wrongly deleted, was the<lb/> petitioners&apos; contention.<lb/></p>

			<p>114. Mr. Joshi, learned counsel appearing for the Commission<lb/> submitted that the Commission has decided to delete the question<lb/> as two options, (1) and (2) are correct.<lb/></p>

			<p>115. Inviting Court&apos;s attention towards the experts&apos; opinion, he<lb/> submitted that the experts have referred to material, which evince<lb/> that Mirage is an example of refraction so also total internal<lb/> reflection.<lb/></p>

			<p>116. Mr. Jangid learned counsel for the petitioners, made an<lb/> ardent effort to satisfy the Court that if a student of Physics is<lb/> asked this question, he would definitely select option (2), i.e. total<lb/> internal reflection. He added that the experts are wrong in stating<lb/> that refraction is also a correct answer. According to Mr. Jangid,<lb/> Refraction is a phenomenon, which explains deviation of a ray,<lb/> whereas total internal reflection is the cause of illusion known as<lb/> mirage and option (2) is the only correct answer.<lb/></p>

			<p>117. Having heard learned counsel for the parties and after<lb/> carefully considering the question (Mirage is an example of), this<lb/> Court is of the opinion that total internal reflection is the more<lb/> correct answer. Had the question been Mirage is a result of,<lb/> perhaps option (1) &apos;refraction&apos; and (2) &apos;total internal reflection&apos;,<lb/> both would have been treated to be correct options, but when the<lb/> question is so specific, then a student is supposed to give the<lb/> most suitable answer, which in the present case is, total internal<lb/> reflection.<lb/></p>

			<p>118. It will not be out of place to reproduce the opinion of the<lb/> experts, which reads thus:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;Options (1) and (2) are correct. Total internal<lb/> reflection is a special case of refraction. Aso<lb/> deflection is also involved in almost all<lb/> geometric phenomenon. Multiple options are<lb/> correct. Question No.141 may be deleted.<lb/> Reference: (1) Halliday Resnick Walker<lb/> Fundamentals of Physics (VI Edition, page<lb/> No.823)<lb/></item>

			<item>(2) Class XII Fundamental Physics by Dr. K.L.<lb/> Goswami.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>119. Neither the material referred by the experts nor does<lb/> the opinion of the experts show that which option is the<lb/> precise or more correct answer. The question is, thus,<lb/> referred to the expert committee to be constituted by the<lb/> RPSC.<lb/></p>

			<p>120. Q.137-Ohm&apos;s law is not applicable on which of the following?<lb/> (1) AC circuit<lb/> (2) Conductor<lb/> (3) Semi conductor<lb/> (4) On conductors when there is change in temperature<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (3) Semi conductor<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : Question was deleted<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : (3) Semi conductor<lb/> 121. Learned counsel for the petitioners submitted that the RPSC<lb/> has given option No. (3) for the aforesaid question in the first<lb/> answer key but question was deleted in revised answer key<lb/> published by it. The petitioners claimed that Option No. (3) is<lb/> correct option because Ohm&apos;s law is not applicable on semi<lb/> conductor. According to the petitioner, this question was wrongly<lb/> deleted.<lb/></p>

			<p>122. Mr. Joshi, learned counsel for the respondent-Commission<lb/> submitted that as per the experts both the options (3) and (4)<lb/> were correct, for which the experts opined to delete the question.<lb/></p>

			<p>123. This Court does not find it to be a case warranting<lb/> interference in the face of the opinion of the experts. The<lb/> petitioner has not been able to show much less satisfy that<lb/> option (3) is the only correct answer.<lb/> Challenge to<lb/> question No.137, therefore, fails. Deletion of this question<lb/> by the Commission is upheld.<lb/> 124. Q.139-The ore which is found in abundance in India is-<lb/>(1) Monazite<lb/> (2) Fluospar<lb/> (3) Bauxite<lb/> (4) Magnetite<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (1) Monazite<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : Question was deleted<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : (3) Bauxite<lb/></p>

			<p>125. It was argued by Mr. Kunal Vishnoi, learned counsel for the<lb/> petitioner that as per the report of Mining Department, issued in<lb/> 2017-18, Bauxite is found in abundance and thus, option (3) is the<lb/> correct answer.<lb/></p>

			<p>126. As against this, the Commission has found the question to be<lb/> incorrect. Mr. Joshi, learned counsel for the RPSC submitted that<lb/> expression &quot;abundance&quot; is a relative term and thus no specific<lb/> answer can be given to this question.<lb/></p>

			<p>127. This Court approves the stand of the RPSC that the<lb/> question as framed itself was incorrect. Abundance is a<lb/> relative expression. Out of four options, it cannot be said<lb/> that which of these ores is not found in abundance. All the<lb/> ores mentioned in the options are found in large quantity in<lb/> India. No interference is, therefore, called for. Deletion of<lb/> this question by the Commission is affirmed.<lb/> PAPER -II<lb/></p>

			<p>128. Q.35 -If x -2 is a factor of X3 + Kx2 -2x -24, then the<lb/> value of k is -<lb/>(1) 6<lb/> (2) 5<lb/> (3) 1<lb/> (4) -2<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (2) 5<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : Question was deleted<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : (2) 5<lb/></p>

			<p>129. Learned counsel for the petitioners submitted that the RPSC<lb/> has given option No. (2) for the aforesaid question in the first<lb/> answer key but thereafter deleted this question in the revised<lb/> answer key. Petitioners claimed that option No.(2) is the correct<lb/> answer, while solving the question given. Question was wrongly<lb/> deleted by the RPSC, has been the contention of learned counsel<lb/> for the petitioner.<lb/></p>

			<p>130. Mr. Joshi, learned counsel for the respondent-Commission<lb/> submitted that the question was deleted as it was out of syllabus.<lb/> Inviting Court&apos;s attention towards the syllabus, he pointed out that<lb/> only &quot;Pair of linear equations in two variables and quadratic<lb/> equations&quot; were given in the syllabus of Mathematics; whereas<lb/> due to inadvertence, the paper setter has given a question, other<lb/> than the one related to quadratic equations.<lb/></p>

			<p>131. As the question under dispute deals with the cubic value or<lb/> relates to X3, it cannot be said that it is a quadratic equation. The<lb/> Commission was right in deleting the question for following<lb/> reason:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;Equation is of degree 3 but in syllabus<lb/> only equation with highest degree 2 has<lb/> been provided.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>132. Challenge to question No.35, therefore, fails. Deletion<lb/> of this question by the Commission is affirmed.<lb/></p>

			<p>133. Q.57 -Which of the following audio-visual aid is most<lb/> effective according to the &apos;cone&apos; proposed by Edger Dale?<lb/> (1) Experiment<lb/> (2) Diagram<lb/> (3) Coloured Slide<lb/> (4) Motion picture<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (1) Experiment<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : (1) Experiment<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : (4) Motion Picture<lb/> 134. Mr. Kunal Bishnoi, learned counsel for the petitioner<lb/> submitted that the RPSC has given option No. (1) for the aforesaid<lb/> question in both the answer keys published by it. Petitioner<lb/> claimed that option (4) &quot;Motion Picture&quot; is most effective audio-<lb/>visual aid, as is evident from the book of Education Technique<lb/> edited by S.K. Mangal and Uma Mangal (Annex.28). Option (1)<lb/> &quot;Experiment&quot; is not mentioned under Edger Dale&apos;s Cone, as such<lb/> RPSC has given incorrect answer.<lb/></p>

			<p>135. Mr. Joshi, learned counsel for the respondent-Commission<lb/> invited Court&apos;s attention towards the material he has placed in<lb/> support of his stand and submitted that experts have opined thus<lb/> vis-à-vis question No.57:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;Question No.57-Answer 1. RPSC&apos;s answer -<lb/>Option (1), proof attached (Annex.6). f&quot;k{kk<lb/> rduhdh] ys [kd S.K. Mangal, pages Nos.38-39&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>136. True it is, that this Court is not expert to adjudicate upon the<lb/> correctness of the question. But, it can very conveniently be<lb/> concluded, as to whether the experts have relied upon correct<lb/> material or not. It can further be examined as to what can be<lb/> deduced from the material placed by the experts.<lb/></p>

			<p>137. RPSC has placed a cone diagram, being Edger Dale&apos;s Cone of<lb/> Experience. According to the diagram and the details placed by<lb/> the RPSC itself, it can be deciphered that out of the options given,<lb/> &quot;Motion Picture&quot; is the most effective tool.<lb/></p>

			<p>138. It is noteworthy that option (1), which has been held to be<lb/> correct option by the RPSC and experts viz. &quot;Experiment,&quot; is not<lb/> at all given in Edger Dale&apos;s Cone of Experience. Experiment may<lb/> be a form of real direct experience.<lb/></p>

			<p>139. Material placed by RPSC, relied upon by the experts,<lb/> including the book of Dr. S.K. Mangal do not clearly show that<lb/> experiment is also a variant of real direct experience. Experts&apos;<lb/> opinion is not supported by reasoning.<lb/></p>

			<p>140. The question is, therefore, referred to the Expert<lb/> Committee to be constituted by the RPSC with a direction<lb/> to give correct answer with brief explanation.<lb/></p>

			<p>141. Q.77 -What is given in &apos;Gargi Puraskar&apos; to the students<lb/> passing tenth (10 th ) Board examination?<lb/></p>

			<item>(1) A total sum of ₹ 6000 and a certificate<lb/></item>

			<item>(2) A total sum of ₹ 10000 and a certificate<lb/></item>

			<item>(3) A total sum of ₹ 25000 and a certificate<lb/></item>

			<item>(4) A total sum of ₹ 5000 and a certificate<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (1) A total sum of ₹6000 and a<lb/> certificate<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : Question was deleted<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : (1) A total sum of ₹6000 and a<lb/> certificate<lb/></item>

			<p>142. Learned counsel for the petitioners submitted that though<lb/> the RPSC had given option No. (1) for the aforesaid question in<lb/> the first answer key, but however deleted this question in the<lb/> revised key. Petitioners claimed that option (1) as per the first<lb/> answer key is the correct answer, as per monthly Shivira Patrika<lb/> for the month of August, 2018 (Annex.31). RPSC has wrongly<lb/> deleted this question, has been their contention.<lb/></p>

			<p>143. Mr. Joshi, learned counsel appearing for the respondent-<lb/>Commission submitted that the question itself was wrong<lb/> inasmuch as Gargi Puraskar is given to a girl candidate, who<lb/> having passed X Board examination continues her studies of Class<lb/> XI and XII.<lb/></p>

			<p>144. The Experts&apos; opinion suggests deletion of this question, which<lb/> reads thus:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;The question in itself is wrong. Hence it<lb/> may be deleted. The prize money is given<lb/> to girls when she continues to study in<lb/> Classes XI and XII.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>145. In support of the stand of the Commission/the Expert<lb/> Committee, Mr. Joshi took the Court through relevant material<lb/> placed by him and submitted that Gargi Award is given to a female<lb/> candidate who having secured 75% or more marks in her Board<lb/> examination, pursues her future studies for Class XI and XII. He<lb/> added that it is only during such time, (for two years) she is given<lb/> the prize and submitted that the question No.77 was incomplete,<lb/> as the same did not contain the requisite stipulation, particularly<lb/> continuance of study for a period of two years.<lb/></p>

			<p>146. In considered opinion of this Court, a perusal of the question<lb/> shows that the emphasis of the question is as to what is given in<lb/> Gargi Purarskar to the student passing Xth Board Examination; in<lb/> other words the examiner wanted to elicit the amount of award<lb/> given under Gargi Puraskar. The Commission&apos;s stand that the<lb/> expression &quot;Girl&quot; is absent in question No.77 and thus, the<lb/> question is incorrect, cannot be countenanced, more particularly<lb/> because the examiner has not asked as to &apos;who&apos; is given the Gargi<lb/> Purarskar.<lb/> The fact that the word &quot;Girl&quot; is absent in the<lb/> formulation of question hardly has any bearing on the<lb/> question/answer nor does its absence makes the question<lb/> incomplete or prone to confusion. The emphasis of the question is<lb/> on the quantum of amount of award, which is easily discernible<lb/> from other options given for the question.<lb/></p>

			<p>147. Opinion of the experts instead of being on the correctness of<lb/> the answer, is on the framing of the question. As a matter of fact,<lb/> experts&apos; opinion is/was not required to examine the correctness of<lb/> the question.<lb/></p>

			<p>148. This Court is of the firm view that the opinion of the experts<lb/> that question be deleted because the expression &quot;girl&quot; and further<lb/> stipulation &quot;she continues to study in class XI and XII&quot; were<lb/> absent, is untenable. Even in absence of these expressions, the<lb/> question which focuses on the quantum of award, is complete.<lb/> Thus, the answer originally given i.e. option (1) is the correct<lb/> answer.<lb/></p>

			<p>149. As a result thereof, the action of the respondents in<lb/> deleting question No.77 is set aside. The first answer, i.e.<lb/></p>

			<p>(1) is held to be correct answer.<lb/></p>

			<p>150. Q.87 -Child Care Leave for mothers has been announced for<lb/> those mothers who have children upto the maximum age of -<lb/>(1) 12 years<lb/> (2) 14 years<lb/> (3) 16 years<lb/> (4) 18 years<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (4) 18 years<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : Question was deleted<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : (4) 18 years<lb/> 151. Mr. Mahaveer Bishnoi, learned counsel for the petitioners<lb/> submitted that the RPSC has given option No. (4) for the aforesaid<lb/> question in the first answer key but thereafter deleted this<lb/> question. Asserting that option No. (4) is the correct answer, as<lb/> per notification dated 22.05.2018, issued by the Finance<lb/> Department, Government of Rajasthan, learned counsel argued<lb/> that RPSC has erred in deleting this question.<lb/></p>

			<p>152. It is noteworthy that while deleting the question, the RPSC<lb/> has opined thus:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;for<lb/> foHkkx<lb/> dh<lb/> vf/klw puk<lb/> la [;k<lb/> i-1(6)<lb/> F.D./Rules/2011 fnuka d 22-5-2018 ds }kjk Child<lb/> Care Leave dk iz ko/kku jktLFkku ls ok fu;e 1951 ds<lb/> fu;e 103C es lfEefyr fd;k x;k gS A bl fu;e es Child<lb/> dh ifjHkk&apos;kk fuEukuq lkj nh xbZ gS A<lb/></item>

			<item>(a) a child below the age of eighteen years or<lb/></item>

			<item>(b) a child upto the age of twenty two years<lb/> with a minimum disability of forty percent as<lb/> elaborated in the Ministry of Social Justice and<lb/> Empowerment Govt. of India, notification<lb/> number 16-18/97-N1. Dated 01.06.2001.<lb/></item>

			<p>iz &apos;uks a ds fodYiks a es s upto the maximum age of<lb/> (1) 12 years (2) 14 years (3) 16 years (4) 18<lb/> years fy[kk x;k gS A Child dh ifjHkk&apos;kk es a below 18<lb/> years gh gS A vr% iz &quot;u dh Hkk&apos;kk lgh ugha gks us ds dkj.k<lb/> iz &quot;u dk fodYi xyr gS A&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>153. According to the experts, the language of the question was<lb/> not correct, hence, the question deserved to be deleted, while<lb/> observing thus:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;Child dh ifjHkk&apos;kk es a below 18 years gh g S A vr% iz &quot;u<lb/> dh Hkk&apos;kk lgh ugha gks us ds dkj.k iz &quot;u dk fodYi xyr gS A&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>154. Explaining the stand of the experts, Mr. Joshi submitted that<lb/> the question contains the expression &quot;upto the maximum age of&quot;;<lb/> whereas Rule 103C of the Rules, published vide notification dated<lb/> 22.05.2018 uses the expression &quot;Child below the age of 18 years&quot;.<lb/></p>

			<p>155. In considered opinion of this Court, the experts clearly got<lb/> confused and misdirected. There is practically no difference<lb/> between the expression &quot;upto the maximum age&quot; and &quot;child below<lb/> the age of&quot;.<lb/></p>

			<p>156. Though sub-rule (b) of Rule 103 has not been a reason to<lb/> delete, but it may be clarified that yet sub-rule (b) of Rule 103 is<lb/> applicable in exceptional cases, namely, &quot;a child having disability<lb/> of minimum 40%&quot;. Since the age of 22 years is an exception and<lb/> having regard to the fact that 22 years is not an option provided,<lb/> the answer earlier given by the RPSC (4) 18 years is held to be<lb/> correct answer.<lb/></p>

			<p>157. The action of the respondents in deleting the question<lb/> is, therefore, clearly illegal. It is held that correct answer<lb/> is option No.(4).<lb/></p>

			<p>158. Q.89 -Bills for Travelling allowance other than fixed or<lb/> permanent allowance shall be prepared and presented in system<lb/> Generated New form. This order is effective from the following<lb/> date -<lb/></p>

			<item>(1) 01/01/2016<lb/></item>

			<item>(2) 01/10/2017<lb/></item>

			<item>(3) 01/01/2017<lb/></item>

			<item>(4) 01/01/2018<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (1) 01/01/2016<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : (1) 01/01/2016<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : To be deleted.<lb/></item>

			<p>159. Learned counsel for the petitioners submitted that the RPSC<lb/> has given option No. (1) for the aforesaid question in both the<lb/> answer keys, but as per the circular dated 04.08.2017 (Annex.33)<lb/> issued by the Finance Department, Government of Rajasthan, with<lb/> effect from 15.09.2017, the Bills for travelling allowance other<lb/> than fixed or permanent allowance are required to be prepared<lb/> and presented in system Generated New form. According to the<lb/> petitioners, since &apos;15.09.2017&apos; has not been given as an option,<lb/> question No.89 was required to be deleted.<lb/></p>

			<p>160. Asserting that RPSC was right, Mr. Joshi relied upon Circular<lb/> dated 04.10.2016, while placing the same for perusal of the Court<lb/> and submitted that system generated new Form No.65 has been<lb/> made effective from 01.01.2017.<lb/> 161. After considering the rival contentions and the Circular<lb/> dated 04.10.2016, this Court finds that the stand of the<lb/> RPSC is correct.<lb/> Challenge to this question is<lb/> unsustainable. Option (1) i.e. 01/01/2016 given by the<lb/> Commission is affirmed.<lb/></p>

			<p>162. Q.90 -The date of birth, once entered in the service<lb/> book/service Roll can be changed with period permission of-<lb/>(1) Head of office<lb/> (2) Head of Department<lb/> (3) Controlling officer<lb/> (4) Finance Department<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (4) Finance Department<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : Question was deleted<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : (4) Finance Department<lb/> 163. Learned counsel for the petitioners submitted that the RPSC<lb/> has given option (4) for the aforesaid question in the first answer<lb/> key but thereafter deleted this question. Petitioners claimed that<lb/> correct option is (4) as per the notification dated 21.02.2012<lb/> issued by the Finance Department, Government of Rajasthan,<lb/> thus, the Commission has wrongly deleted this question.<lb/></p>

			<p>164. Mr. Joshi, learned counsel for the respondent-Commission<lb/> submitted that there was a typing mistake in the question<lb/> inasmuch as, in place of word &quot;prior&quot;, the word &quot;period&quot; has been<lb/> printed,<lb/> which<lb/> conveys<lb/> no<lb/> meaning.<lb/> As<lb/> such,<lb/> the<lb/> Commission/Experts deleted the question.<lb/></p>

			<p>165. I have carefully read the question No.90 and compared<lb/> the same with its Hindi version. The Commission was<lb/> justified in deleting the question, given the fact that as per<lb/> the Note appended to the question paper, English version<lb/> was to be accepted in case of discrepancy. As the English<lb/> version of the question No.90 itself was erroneous, the<lb/> commission was justified in deleting the question. The<lb/> challenge to this question therefore, fails. Deletion of<lb/> question No.90 by the Commission is affirmed.<lb/></p>

			<p>166. Q. 102: A child who is 10 years old and has never gone to<lb/> school before is eligible to be admitted in which class?<lb/> (1) One<lb/> (2) Three<lb/> (3) Four<lb/> (4) Five<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (4) Five<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : (4) Five<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : (3) Four<lb/> 167. Learned Counsel for the petitioners submits that as per the<lb/> authentic books option No.(3) is correct.<lb/></p>

			<p>168. Learned counsel appearing for the respondent-Commission,<lb/> inviting Court&apos;s attention towards Section 4 of the Right to<lb/> Education Act,2009, submitted that the child of six years of age is<lb/> required to be admitted in I Standard and thus, at the age of 10<lb/> years, he is to be given admission in V Standard.<lb/></p>

			<p>169. Mr. Jangid, learned counsel invited Court&apos;s attention towards<lb/> Section 4 of the Right to Education Act and read Question No.30<lb/> and its answer. The same is being reproduced hereinbelow:-<lb/></p>

			<item>Q. 30 What does &apos;age appropriate class&apos; mean?<lb/></item>

			<item>It means giving admission in a class where the<lb/> child would normally be if she had joined school<lb/> from Class I at six years of age. So if a child is 11<lb/> years old and has never been to school, she or he<lb/> will be admitted to Class V, but shall be given<lb/> special education to reach the level in a time frame<lb/> of three months to two years [Model Rule 3(1)].<lb/></item>

			<p>170. Before going through the contents of above quoted<lb/> paragraph, this Court deems it necessary to record its displeasure<lb/> about the anxiety of the petitioners -they just rely upon and<lb/> insist upon the Court to blindly follow and base its judgment on an<lb/> opinion, source, authenticity and authority whereof is unknown.<lb/> The Courts of Law can be guided only by the statutory provisions<lb/> or binding precedents. Such random question -answer picked<lb/> from net or website are absolutely worthless before the Courts.<lb/></p>

			<p>171. Be that as it may. Going by above para, Mr. Jangid argued<lb/> that as a 11 year old child is to be admitted in Class V, a 10 year<lb/> old is to be given admission in Class IV. This Court cannot, but<lb/> refrain from recording its concern about the wisdom of the author<lb/> -it is beyond common sense and fails simple mathematics. Even<lb/> going by this para, if a six year old child is to get admission in<lb/> Class I, then by simple mathematics a ten year old will go to Class<lb/> V (6-I, 7-II, 8-III, 9-IV, 10-V). The quoted paragraph, petitioners&apos;<lb/> argument and challenge to this question defies logic and simple<lb/> arithmetic.<lb/></p>

			<p>172. The answer of the RPSC is correct. Challenge to<lb/> question No.102 fails.<lb/></p>

			<p>173. Q.103: Who is the runner-up of Wimbledon Gentlemen&apos;s<lb/> singles&quot;<lb/></p>

			<item>(1) Novak Djokovic<lb/></item>

			<item>(2) Pete Sampras<lb/></item>

			<item>(3) Roger Federer<lb/></item>

			<item>(4) Kevin Anderson<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (4) Kevin Anderson<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : Question was deleted<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : (4) Kevin Anderson<lb/></item>

			<p>174. Learned counsel for the petitioners claims that as per the<lb/> authentic books option No. 4 is correct answer, whereas RPSC has<lb/> deleted the question.<lb/></p>

			<p>175. As against the contention raised by the petitioners, learned<lb/> counsel for RPSC invited Court&apos;s attention towards framing of the<lb/> question; he read the question No.103 and pointed out that year<lb/> 2018 was omitted to be printed, therefore, going by the Note<lb/> No.10, the question was deleted.<lb/></p>

			<p>176. A simple look at question No.103 goes to show that year<lb/> &apos;2018&apos; has not been mentioned, whereas in Hindi version, year<lb/> 2018 has been mentioned.<lb/></p>

			<p>177. In view of the apparent omission, RPSC was justified<lb/> in deleting the question -as the question became open<lb/> ended, in absence of year of championship. The challenge<lb/> to this question, therefore, fails.<lb/></p>

			<p>178. Q. 118 -Which one of the following countries received $ 39<lb/> Million for Maritime Security from the U.S.?<lb/></p>

			<p>(1) Bangladesh<lb/> (2) India<lb/> (3) Pakistan<lb/> (4) Srilanka<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (4) Srilanka<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : (4) Srilanka<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : To be deleted<lb/> 179. Learned counsel for the petitioners submitted that the RPSC<lb/> has given option No. (4) for the aforesaid question in both the<lb/> answer keys, but considering the fact that in Hindi version of<lb/> question paper, &quot;Maritice Security&quot; (eS jh VkbZ l) is mentioned in place<lb/> of &quot;Maritime Security&quot;, the question was required to be deleted.<lb/></p>

			<p>180. Inviting Court&apos;s attention towards Hindi Version vis-à-vis<lb/> English version, Mr. Joshi submitted that as per Note appended to<lb/> the question paper, English version was to be accepted. He added<lb/> that it is true that Hindi version, the word &quot;eS jh VkbZ l&quot; in place of<lb/> &quot;eS jh Vkbe&quot; has been printed, such inadvertent error was to be<lb/> omitted, as the English version of the question was correctly<lb/> typed.<lb/></p>

			<p>181. A comparison of Hindi version and English version of<lb/> the question reveals that there is a typographical error in<lb/> Hindi version of question No.118, but as per Note 10 of the<lb/> question paper, English version is to be accepted. Since<lb/> English version of the question is correct, the petitioner&apos;s<lb/> contention that the question needs to be deleted, cannot be<lb/> accepted. Contention rejected. Option (4) i.e. Srilanka<lb/> given by the Commission is affirmed.<lb/></p>

			<p>182. Q. 120: Consumer Protection Act was enforced in-<lb/>(1) 1984<lb/> (2) 1982<lb/> (3) 1986<lb/> (4) 1989<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (3) 1986<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : (3) 1986<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : To be deleted<lb/></p>

			<p>183. Mr. Bhaleria, learned counsel for the petitioners argued that<lb/> as per the authentic books, the Act was enforced in 1987. As<lb/> correct answer is not given in the options, the question was<lb/> required to be deleted.<lb/></p>

			<p>184. With respect to question No.120, the experts opined thus:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;;?kfi iz &quot;u es iw Nk x;k vf/kfu;e 1986 es a ykxq<lb/> gw vk gS ] rFkkfi bl vf/kfu;e dks replace dj u;k<lb/> vf/kfu;e cukus dk fo/ks ;d fn-05-01-2018 dks<lb/> yks dlHkk es a iw u%LFkkfir fd;k x;k gS A rnũq lkj ;g<lb/> eq )k current affairs es a lekfgr gS A<lb/> vr,o OS ,oa AOW dh vkifRr;ka vLohdk;Z gS A&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>185. A perusal of the note quoted above suggests that the experts<lb/> have decided the objection treating the same to be out of<lb/> syllabus. The correctness of the answer has not been examined at<lb/> all.<lb/></p>

			<p>186. Having regard to the arguments advanced by Mr. J.S.<lb/> Bhaleria, learned counsel in SBCWP No.16733/2019, (Ajay Bhadu<lb/> Vs. State), the Court proceeded to examine the correctness of the<lb/> question by itself. In the process of elucidating correct answer,<lb/> the Court asked Mr. Joshi, learned counsel for the Commission to<lb/> give correct answer, while making relevant material (Book,<lb/> Notification etc.) available to him.<lb/></p>

			<p>187. On reading of sub-section (2) of Section 1 of the Consumer<lb/> Protection Act, 1986 and the gazette notification No.SO-390(E)<lb/> dated 15.04.1987, Mr. Joshi submitted that it can be said with<lb/> certitude that the Act of 1986 came into force w.e.f. 15.04.1987.<lb/></p>

			<p>188. &apos;1987&apos; has not at all been given as an option qua<lb/> question No.120; its options are thus, erroneous. Question<lb/> No.120, is, thus, liable to be deleted. Ordered accordingly.<lb/></p>

			<p>189. Q. 122 -&apos;Agricultural shot&apos; is associated with-<lb/>(1) Hockey<lb/> (2) Cricket<lb/> (3) Baseball<lb/> (4) Chess<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (2) Cricket<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : (2) Cricket<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : To be deleted<lb/> 190. Learned counsel for the petitioners informed that the RPSC<lb/> has given option No. (2) for the aforesaid question in both the<lb/> answer keys published by it. Petitioners contention is that the<lb/> question relates to vocabulary of sports and sports or sports<lb/> vocabulary is not given in the syllabus, hence, the question being<lb/> out of syllabus, deserves to be deleted.<lb/></p>

			<p>191. Responding to petitioners&apos; argument that &quot;Agricultural Shot&quot;<lb/> is a term/vocabulary relating to sports is out of the syllabus, Mr.<lb/> Joshi submitted that the this question is from &apos;current events&apos;.<lb/></p>

			<p>192. In this regard, he invited Court&apos;s attention towards the<lb/> experts&apos; opinion and submitted that &quot;Agricultural Shot&quot; is<lb/> commonly used expression in cricket and thus, it is covered in<lb/> current events.<lb/></p>

			<p>193. Before adjudicating the dispute, this Court deems it<lb/> appropriate to first reproduce what experts have said about this<lb/> question:-<lb/>&quot;Agricultural shot fdz ds V ls la ca f/kr ,d yks d iz pfyr<lb/> &quot;kCn gS ] tks Hkkjr dh lgHkkfxrk okys eS pks a ds nkS jku ppkZ es a<lb/> vo&quot;; jgrk gS A vr% ;g ikB;dz e es a mYys f[r &apos;current<lb/> events&apos; es lekfgr gS A vr% OS dh vkifRr vLohdk;Z gS A&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>194. This Court is not at all convinced with the views of the<lb/> experts. Even if an expression is commonly used in the cricket<lb/> matches, it cannot be said that it is a part of a current event.<lb/> Current event is a one time incident, having happened in recent<lb/> past. The experts have not given any detail, as to when or during<lb/> which event, (which had happened currently), such shot was<lb/> played or came into prominence. True it is, that agricultural shot is<lb/> a shot known in cricket, but merely because it might have been<lb/> heard during recent cricket matches, it cannot be said that the<lb/> same is covered in current events.<lb/></p>

			<p>195. Objection raised by the petitioners qua this question is<lb/> sustained. It is surprising to note that when it comes to<lb/> Penicillin, RPSC opines it to be out of syllabus, but with<lb/> respect to agricultural shot it says that it is included in<lb/> current events -without even mentioning that when such<lb/> shot was played recently. RPSC&apos;s stand that it is within<lb/> syllabus is rejected. Consequently, question No.122 is<lb/> ordered to be deleted.<lb/></p>

			<p>196. Q. 125 -Recently Hima Das won a gold medal. The sports<lb/> event in which she won was-<lb/>(1) Asian Games-2018<lb/> (2) World Atheletics Championship-2018<lb/> (3) World Junior Atheletics Championship-2018<lb/> (4) Commonwealth Games-2018.<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (3) World Junior Atheletics<lb/> Championship-2018<lb/> Revised Result<lb/> : Deleted<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : (3) World Junior Atheletics<lb/> Championship-2018<lb/> 197. Learned counsel for the petitioners argued that correct option<lb/> is option No.(3), as the participation in the Asian Games was as a<lb/> team and not individually. According to the petitioner the deletion<lb/> was improper.<lb/></p>

			<p>198. Mr. Joshi, learned counsel for the Commission submitted that<lb/> Hima Das won gold medal in Asian Games-2018 so also in World<lb/> Junior Athletics Championship-2018. According to Commission,<lb/> since options Nos.1 and 3 both were correct, it was thought<lb/> appropriate to delete the question.<lb/></p>

			<p>199. It is really a sorry state of affairs that RPSC has relied upon a<lb/> news item with the heading &quot;Asian Game Gold Medalist Hima Das<lb/> says that she did not expect to be nominated for the Arjuna Award<lb/> this year&quot; to establish that she won a Gold Medal in Asian Games.<lb/> The experts ought to have traced the news of her winning Gold<lb/> Medal itself or should have referred to the information lying in the<lb/> website. Experts are supposed to act and perform as experts -<lb/>they have been novice on most of the occasions.<lb/></p>

			<p>200. In considered opinion of this Court, such news item cannot<lb/> be treated to be an evidence in support of the fact that Hima Das<lb/> is an Asian Games gold medalist. True it is, that Hima Das was<lb/> part of the team which won a Gold medal for India in Asian Games<lb/> 2018 (Women&apos;s 4x400 meter relay race).<lb/></p>

			<p>201. Upon surfing through the record, it is clear that so far Asian<lb/> Games-2018 is concerned, the telly shows that Hima Das was part<lb/> of two teams, which fetched Gold medals for India-she was a<lb/> member of mixed as well as women&apos;s team taking part in 4x400<lb/> meter relay race. That way, she helped India win two Gold<lb/> medals. But since the question is specific -&apos;a gold medal&apos; and<lb/> also because a medal won by a team cannot be attributed to one<lb/> player alone, in considered opinion of this Court, option (3) -<lb/>&apos;World Junior Athletics&apos; is the correct answer as option No.(1) does<lb/> not fit-in qua the question asked.<lb/></p>

			<p>202. Even if option No.1 is to be treated correct, then, more<lb/> correct answer is (3) -World Junior Athletics Championship-2018,<lb/> in which she begged Gold in 400 meter race.<lb/></p>

			<p>203. As an upshot of the discussion foregoing, this Court is<lb/> of the opinion that option (3) is the most suitable option<lb/> and RPSC has erred in deleting the question. RPSC is<lb/> directed to revise the result while treating option No.(3) to<lb/> be correct answer.<lb/></p>

			<item>204. Q. 126: Consider the following statements about &apos;Ayushman<lb/> Bharat Scheme&apos;-<lb/></item>

			<item>(i) It is also known as National Health Protection Mission<lb/></item>

			<item>(ii) The scheme provides the benefit cover of 2 lakh per family per<lb/> year<lb/></item>

			<item>(iii) The scheme will launch on 25 September 2018<lb/> Which of the above statements/statements are incorrect?<lb/></item>

			<item>(1) only (i)<lb/></item>

			<p>(2) only (ii)<lb/> (3) (ii) &amp; (iii)<lb/> (4) only (iii)<lb/> Answer given by the RPSC : (2) only (ii)<lb/> Revised answer key<lb/> : (2) only (ii)<lb/> Claim by the petitioners<lb/> : (3) (ii) &amp; (iii)<lb/> 205. Learned counsel for the petitioners claims that correct option<lb/> is option No.(3).<lb/></p>

			<p>206. Mr. Joshi, learned counsel for the Commission submitted that<lb/> the date of examination was 02.09.2018, whereas the change in<lb/> the coverage amount was made on 18.09.2018, after the date of<lb/> examination. He argued that as on the date of examination,<lb/> option No.(2) given by the RPSC was correct.<lb/></p>

			<p>207. The petitioners have relied upon the material/event, which<lb/> has come into being after the date of examination.<lb/></p>

			<p>208. In considered opinion of this Court, the answer to a question<lb/> has to be examined as per the fact(s) prevailing on the date of<lb/> examination, i.e. 02.09.2018. This Court is satisfied with the<lb/> reasons given by the experts duly explained by Mr. Joshi.<lb/></p>

			<p>209. Challenge to question No.126 fails; Option (2) i.e. only<lb/> (ii) given by the Commission is, therefore, affirmed.<lb/></p>

			<p>210. It is to be noted that challenge to many questions has been<lb/> led by the petitioners, however, during the submissions, challenge<lb/> to many of the questions was dropped, the adjudication is,<lb/> therefore, confined to the questions, which were pressed before<lb/> the Court.<lb/></p>

			<p>211. During the course of hearing, learned counsel appearing for<lb/> the Commission has said that not only the final result has been<lb/> declared, list of selected candidates has already been forwarded to<lb/> the State Government and thus, if any interference is made, the<lb/> same be confined to petitioners involved in the present writ<lb/> petitions.<lb/></p>

			<p>212. Having dealt with the contentions of rival parties and<lb/> adjudicated upon the challenge raised to each of the questions,<lb/> this Court finds itself on the cross-road. Dwelling on the request<lb/> of the RPSC to confine the adjudication made herein qua the<lb/> petitioners only, this Court is of the firm view that the present<lb/> adjudication cannot be confined to the petitioners alone.<lb/></p>

			<p>213. The reasons are not far to seek and the same are set out<lb/> hereinfra.<lb/></p>

			<p>214. It is to be noted that out of 300 questions in all, 29 questions<lb/> were impugned in these writ petitions. Doubting the correctness<lb/> of 12 questions, this Court has modified the answer or has<lb/> referred the questions to the Expert Committee. As the instances<lb/> of errors/omissions are such large in number (4%), restricting the<lb/> adjudication to the petitioners would be giving undue advantage<lb/> to the candidates, who had given wrong answers. Hence, if the<lb/> result is to be revised, it is required to be reviewed/revised for all.<lb/> The candidates cannot be made to suffer on account of fault or<lb/> folly of the Paper Setter, Proof Reader, Printer, Experts and the<lb/> Commission itself.<lb/></p>

			<p>215. In view of the aforesaid, these writ petitions are allowed; the<lb/> merit list and the select list (if any) is hereby quashed; the RPSC<lb/> is directed to recheck all the answer scripts in tendam with the<lb/> adjudication made qua each of the question under consideration.<lb/></p>

			<p>216. For the sake of convenience, particulars of questions and<lb/> corresponding answers/directions, which need to be revisited have<lb/> been cataloged in the Schedule appended with the present<lb/> judgment.<lb/> The revision of result shall be subject to the<lb/> following :-<lb/></p>

			<item>(i)<lb/> The Commission shall immediately constitute at least<lb/> two members Committee(s) of Experts for the questions,<lb/> which have been ordered to be referred to the Expert<lb/> Committee;<lb/></item>

			<item>(ii)<lb/> Questions belonging to different subjects may be<lb/> referred to different Committees;<lb/></item>

			<item>(iii)<lb/> The RPSC shall provide not only a copy of the judgment<lb/> instant but also copies of writ petition(s) to the members of<lb/> the Expert Committee so as to enable them to take into<lb/> account the challenge/contentions/arguments and material<lb/> relied upon by the petitioners;<lb/></item>

			<item>(iv)<lb/> The Experts are expected to go through the<lb/> observations made by this Court while dealing with the<lb/> questions referred to it, more particularly what has been said<lb/> in para No.12 of the judgment instant;<lb/></item>

			<item>(v)<lb/> The Expert Committee to submit its report qua the<lb/> questions referred latest by 15.04.2020;<lb/></item>

			<item>(vi)<lb/> Assimilating the answers suggested by the Expert<lb/> Committee and the adjudication made in the present<lb/> judgment, the RPSC will recheck the answer scripts of all the<lb/> candidates by 30.04.2020;<lb/></item>

			<item>(vii) The revised result/select list shall be forwarded to the<lb/> State Government latest by 15.05.2020 .<lb/></item>

			<p>217. While adjudicating the contentious questions, this Court finds<lb/> that out of 29 questions, six questions contained typographical<lb/> mistakes in the question papers, which have largely attributed to<lb/> revision of result and necessitated present litigation which was<lb/> otherwise avoidable.<lb/> A cost of Rs.1,00,000/-is, therefore,<lb/> imposed upon the Commission. The amount of cost be utilized in<lb/> the field of girls&apos; education.<lb/></p>

			<p>218. The cost aforesaid be deposited in the form of Demand Draft<lb/> payable to Rajasthan State Legal Services Authority, attached with<lb/> the Rajasthan High Court, Jodhpur on or before 15 th April, 2020.<lb/></p>

			<p>219. The Commission shall furnish a proof of such payment and<lb/> will be free to recover such cost from Printer(s)/Proof Reader(s)<lb/> concerned.<lb/></p>

			<p>220. The matter be placed before the Registrar (Judicial) on<lb/> 22.04.2020 for the purpose of ascertaining the factum of payment<lb/> of cost. In case, the amount of cost is not deposited, the matter<lb/> be laid before the Court on 27.04.2020 at 02.00 p.m.<lb/></p>

			<p>221. Secretary, Rajasthan State Legal Services Authority,<lb/> Rajasthan at Jodhpur be intimated about the order instant.<lb/></p>

			<p>222. Stay application(s) filed in each of the writ petition stands<lb/> disposed of.<lb/></p>

			<p>(DINESH MEHTA),J<lb/> ArunV/-<lb/>SCHEDULE TO JUDGMENT DATED 19.03.2020<lb/> PAPER-I<lb/> S.No.<lb/> Question No.<lb/> Adjudication<lb/> by Court<lb/> Conclusion<lb/> in para No.<lb/></p>

			<item>i.<lb/> Question No.13<lb/> Referred to the<lb/> Expert<lb/> Committee.<lb/></item>

			<item>21<lb/> ii.<lb/> Question No.22<lb/> Challenge fails.<lb/></item>

			<item>29<lb/> iii.<lb/> Question No.37<lb/> Challenge fails.<lb/></item>

			<item>iv.<lb/> Question No.65<lb/> Challenge fails.<lb/> 40<lb/> v.<lb/> Question No.69<lb/> Referred to the<lb/> Expert<lb/> Committee.<lb/> 57<lb/> vi.<lb/> Question No.80<lb/> No interference. 61<lb/> vii. Question No.96<lb/> Deletion<lb/> of<lb/> question No.96 is<lb/> set<lb/> aside.<lb/> Option No.2 is<lb/> restored.<lb/> 70<lb/> viii. Question No.101 Objection<lb/> rejected.<lb/></item>

			<p>74<lb/> ix.<lb/> Question No.114 Referred to the<lb/> Expert<lb/> Committee.<lb/></p>

			<p>80<lb/> x.<lb/> Question No.115 Referred to the<lb/> Expert<lb/> Committee.<lb/> 94<lb/> xi.<lb/> Question No.125 Challenge fails.<lb/> 99<lb/> xii. Question No.126 Challenge fails.<lb/> 105<lb/> xiii. Question No.127 Challenge fails.<lb/> 111<lb/> xiv. Question No.131 Referred to the<lb/> Expert<lb/> Committee.<lb/></p>

			<p>119<lb/> xv.<lb/> Question No.137 Challenge fails.<lb/> 123<lb/> xvi. Question No.139 No interference. 127<lb/></p>

			<p>PAPER-II<lb/> S.No.<lb/> Question<lb/> Adjudication by<lb/> Court<lb/> Conclusion in<lb/> para No.<lb/></p>

			<p>xvii.<lb/> Question No.35<lb/> Challenge fails.<lb/> 132<lb/></p>

			<item>xviii.<lb/> Question No.57<lb/> Referred to the<lb/> Expert<lb/> Committee.<lb/></item>

			<item>140<lb/> xix.<lb/> Question No.77<lb/> Deletion<lb/> of<lb/> question is set<lb/> aside;<lb/> Option<lb/> No.(1) is held to<lb/> be<lb/> correct<lb/> answer.<lb/> 149<lb/></item>

			<item>xx.<lb/> Question No.87<lb/> Deletion<lb/> of 157<lb/> question is set<lb/> aside. Option (4)<lb/> is held to be<lb/> correct answer.<lb/> xxi.<lb/> Question No.89<lb/> Challenge fails.<lb/> 161<lb/> xxii.<lb/> Question No.90<lb/> Challenge fails.<lb/></item>

			<item>165<lb/> xxiii.<lb/> Question No.102 Challenge fails.<lb/> 172<lb/> xxiv.<lb/> Question No.103 Challenge fails.<lb/></item>

			<item>177<lb/> xxv.<lb/> Question No.118 Challenge fails.<lb/> 181<lb/> xxvi.<lb/> Question No.120 Question<lb/> deserves to be<lb/> deleted.<lb/></item>

			<item>188<lb/> xxvii.<lb/> Question No.122 Question<lb/> deserves to be<lb/> deleted.<lb/> 195<lb/> xxviii. Question No.125 Deletion<lb/> of<lb/> question is set<lb/> aside.<lb/> Option<lb/></item>

			<item>(3) is held to be<lb/> correct answer.<lb/></item>

			<item>203<lb/> xxix.<lb/> Question No.126 Challenge fails.<lb/></item>

			<item>209</item>


	</text>
</tei>
