<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="R7"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>HIGH COURT of JUDICATURE FOR RAJASTHAN<lb/> AT JODHPUR<lb/> S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 15319/2021<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Hamendra Singh Chundawat S/o Raghunath Singh</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	, aged about<lb/> 42 Years, Resident of Village Bhundwas, District Rajsamand<lb/> (Rajasthan).<lb/> ----Petitioner Versus<lb/> 1.<lb/> State of
	<keyword>Rajasthan through the Secretary, Secondary<lb/> Education, Rajasthan, Jaipur (Rajasthan).<lb/> 2.<lb/> Joint Education Secretary, Education (Group II)<lb/> Department, Jaipur (Rajasthan).<lb/> 3.<lb/> Director, Secondary Education, Rajasthan, Bikaner<lb/> (Rajasthan).<lb/> 4.<lb/> Joint Director (Training), Secondary Education, Rajasthan,<lb/> Bikaner (Rajasthan).<lb/> 5.<lb/> District Education officer, Office of District Education<lb/> Officer Secondary (Headquarter), Rajsamand (Rajasthan).<lb/> 6.<lb/> District Education officer, Office of District Education<lb/></keyword>

	Officer Secondary (Headquarter), Karauli (Rajasthan).<lb/> ----Respondents<lb/> For Petitioner(s)<lb/> :
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Mr. Indrajeet Yadav.<lb/> Mr. O.P. Sangwa.<lb/> Mr. Bherulal Jat.<lb/> Mr. Abhijeet Sharma.<lb/> Mr. Rajendra Singh Rathore.<lb/> Mr. Kailash Jangid.<lb/> Mr. Mohan Singh Shekhawat.<lb/> Mr. Rajendra Singh Bhati.<lb/> Mr. Chandraveer Singh Shekhawat.<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	For Respondent(s)<lb/> :
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Mr. Hemant Choudhary, G.C.<lb/> Mr. Vishal Jangid, Dy. Govt. Counsel.<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE ARUN BHANSALI Order<lb/> 02/12/2021<lb/> The present bunch of writ petitions enlisted in the appended<lb/> Schedule, which shall be treated to be part and parcel of the order<lb/> instant, are decided by a common order.<lb/></div>

	(2 of 13)<lb/> [CW-15319/2021]
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
