<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<p>These writ petitions have been filed by the petitioners<lb/> aggrieved against the order dated 12.10.2021 passed by the<lb/> respondents pursuant to the directions given by this Court in<lb/> various writ petitions led by Sangeeta Patidar vs. The State of<lb/> Rajsthan &amp; Ors. : S.B.C.W.P. No.7730/2021 decided on<lb/> 10.08.2021.<lb/> The petitioners, aggrieved by allotment of the districts<lb/> pursuant to reshuffling by the respondents, approached this Court<lb/> by filing various writ petitions led by Sangeeta Patidar (supra). A<lb/> Coordinate Bench of this Court after hearing the parties and on<lb/> their request, inter-alia, passed the following orders: -<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;1. The present bunch of writ petitions enlisted<lb/> in the appended Schedule, which shall be treated to<lb/> be part and parcel of the order instant, are decided by<lb/> a common order.<lb/></item>

			<item>2.<lb/> These writ petitions have been preferred<lb/> by the petitioners, interalia, laying challenge to the<lb/> order of the allotment of District to the petitioners.<lb/></item>

			<item>3.<lb/> Learned counsel for the petitioners submit<lb/> that the issue involved in the present writ petitions is<lb/> squarely covered by the judgment of this Court dated<lb/></item>

			<item>16.10.2020, passed by Jaipur Bench of this Court in<lb/> bunch of writ petitions led by Reena Vs. State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.(S.B. Civil Writ Petition No.7617/2020).<lb/></item>

			<p>4.<lb/> Mr. Jangid, learned counsel for the<lb/> respondents does not dispute the aforesaid position of<lb/> facts and law.<lb/></p>

			<p>5.<lb/> The Jaipur Bench in its judgment in the<lb/> case of Reena (supra) has held thus:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;Keeping in view that the same principle<lb/> would be applied to the present selections,<lb/> this Court is satisfied that the directions<lb/> issued by the Coordinate Bench, at Principal<lb/> Seat, Jodhpur, as quoted in Para 35 of the<lb/> judgment (supra), would have full application<lb/> to all the candidates, who have appeared in<lb/> the selection process and have been selected<lb/> as Teacher Grade-II. This Court also notices<lb/> that the case of the petitioners is identical to<lb/> the case of those petitioners, who were before<lb/> the Court in the case of Nirmal Jat (supra).&quot;<lb/></item>

			<item>6.<lb/> Accordingly these writ petitions are<lb/> allowed.<lb/></item>

			<item>7.<lb/> The petitioners shall be free to make a<lb/> detailed representation to the concerned authority in<lb/> terms of the circular dated 25.09.2020, 30.09.2020<lb/></item>

			<item>(if any) and any other circular if prevailing presently.<lb/></item>

			<item>The representation be filed on or before 31.10.2021.<lb/></item>

			<item>8.<lb/> Till the petitioners&apos; representations are<lb/> decided as directed hereby, interim order passed in<lb/> the writ petitions shall continue.<lb/></item>

			<item>9.<lb/> All pending applications stand disposed of<lb/> accordingly.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>Pursuant to the order dated 10.08.2021 passed by the<lb/> Coordinate Bench , the respondents issued a communication dated<lb/> 12.10.2021 (Annex.7 to S.B.C.W.P. No.14988/2021) referring to<lb/> order passed by the Court and directed as under:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;vr% funs Z f&quot;kr fd;k tkrk gS fd ekuuh; U;k;ky; }kjk ikfjr<lb/> fu.kZ ;ks a ds dz e es a vkids dk;kZ y; Lrj ls fuEufyf[kr dk;Z okgh fd;k<lb/> tkuk lq fuf&quot;pr djkos a %&amp;<lb/></item>

			<item>1-&quot;kkjhfjd iz f&quot;k{k.k vuq ns &quot;kd xz s M kkk HkrhZ 2018 es a fj&quot;kQy ftyk<lb/> vkoa Vu<lb/> ds<lb/> lEcU/k<lb/> es a<lb/> dk;kZ y;<lb/> gktk<lb/> ds<lb/> i=ka d<lb/> f&quot;kfojk@ek/;@la LFkk@,Q&amp;1@12102@&quot;kk-f&quot;k-xz s M&amp;kkk@lh-Hk-&amp;2018@,u-<lb/>ts -@2021 fnuka d 11-06-2021 }kjk iz nRr fn&quot;kk&amp;funs Z &quot;kks a ds vuq lkj vkids<lb/> ftys es a &quot;kkjhfjd iz f&quot;k{k.k vuq ns &quot;kd xz s M kkk ds fjDr inks a dks fnuka d 14-10-<lb/>2021 rd foHkkxh; os clkbZ V ij iz nf&quot;kZ r djs a A<lb/></item>

			<item>2-fcUnq la [;k 01 es a iz nRr funs Z &quot;kks a ds dz e es a iz nf&quot;kZ r fjDr inks a es a<lb/> ls fdlh ij inLFkkiu pkgus okys ;kfpdkfFkZ ;ks a }kjk fnuka d 31-10-2020<lb/> rd vkids dk;kZ y; es a iz Lrq r leLr vH;kos nuks a dks fuEukuq lkj fuLrkfjr<lb/> fd;k tkos %&amp;<lb/> ➢ fj&quot;kQy ftyk vkoa Vu ds rgr uohu vkoa fVr ftys es a gh ¼vUr%<lb/> ftyk½ inLFkkiu LFkku es a ifjoZ ru pkgus okys ;kfpdkfFkZ ;ks a ds<lb/> vH;kos nuks a dks fj&quot;kQy ftyk vkoa Vu ds lEcU/k es a dk;kZ y; gktk<lb/> ds<lb/> i=ka d<lb/> f&quot;kfojk@ek/;@la LFkk@,Q&amp;1@12102@&quot;kk-f&quot;k-<lb/>xz s M&amp;kkk@lh-Hk-&amp;2018@,u-ts -@2021 fnuka d 11-06-2021 }kjk<lb/> iz nRr fn&quot;kk&amp;funs Z &quot;kks a ds vk/kkj ij inLFkkiu gs rq vH;fFk;ks a ds<lb/> ojh;rk dz e dk fu/kkZ j.k dj mDr ojh;rkuq lkj vH;kos nu dk<lb/> fuLrkj.k djs A<lb/></item>

			<p>➢ &quot;kkjhfjd iz f&quot;k{k.k vuq ns &quot;kd xz s M kkk HkrhZ 2018 es a fj&quot;kQy ftyk<lb/> vkoa Vu ds rgr uohu vkoa fVr ftys dh os clkbZ V ij iz nf&quot;kZ r<lb/> fjDr in ds LFkku ij iw oZ vkoa fVr@vU; ftys es a inLFkkiu<lb/> pkgus okys vH;fF;ks a ds vH;kos nuks a dks vLohdkj djrs gq ,<lb/> fuLrkfjr djs A<lb/> 3-leLr vH;kos nuks a dks fnuka d 10-11-2021 rd fuLrkfjr djds<lb/> ekuuh; U;k;ky; }kjk fofHkUu ;kfpdkvks a es a iw oZ es a ikfjr va rfje vkns &quot;k<lb/> dh ikyuk es a iw oZ vkoa fVr ftys ls dk;Z eq Dr ugha gks us okys dkfeZ dks a dks<lb/> fnuka d 12-11-2021 rd dk;Z eq Dr dj uohu vkoa fVr ftys es a dk;Z xz g.k<lb/> djok;k tkuk lq fuf&quot;pr djkos A&quot;<lb/> The petitioners are aggrieved of the second part of Point<lb/> No.2, wherein it has been indicated that P.T.I. Grade-III, who have<lb/> applied for previously allotted/other districts other than the<lb/> reshuffled districts allotted to them, their representations be<lb/> rejected.<lb/> It is submitted by the learned counsel for the petitioners that<lb/> the action of the respondents in confining the choice of petitioners<lb/> for allotment of districts pursuant to order passed by this Court in<lb/> the case of Sangeeta Patidar (supra) to the allotted district is<lb/> wholly incorrect; the respondents should have permitted the<lb/> petitioners to opt for any of the districts throughout the State and<lb/> as such, the action being contrary to the directions given by this<lb/> Court, the offending portion of the communication dated<lb/> 12.10.2021 deserves to be struck down.<lb/> Counsel for the petitioners, in the alternative, made<lb/> submissions that as the last date given in the case of Sangeeta<lb/> Patidar for making representation was 31.10.2021 and the<lb/> respondents had issued the communication dated 12.10.2021 and<lb/> petitioners were aggrieved of the stipulation made therein, some<lb/> of them could not make the representations by 31.10.2021 as per<lb/> communication dated 12.10.2021 and, therefore, they may be<lb/> granted one more opportunity to make representation in<lb/> consonance with communication dated 12.10.2021.<lb/> E-converso, learned counsel for the State submitted that the<lb/> order dated 12.10.2021 is in consonance with the directions given<lb/> by this Court in the case of Sangeeta Patidar (supra), inasmuch as<lb/> the said case was decided directing the respondents to follow the<lb/> judgment in the case of Nirmla Jat vs. State of Rajasthan &amp; Ors. :<lb/> S.B.C.W.P. No.5753/2020 decided on 14.09.2020. Once the<lb/> direction was to follow the directions issued in the case of Nirmla<lb/> Jat (supra), the communication dated 12.10.2021 issued is in<lb/> consonance with the directions contained therein, except for<lb/> change from division to district, inasmuch as cadre in the case of<lb/> Teacher Grade-II, which was the subject matter in the case of<lb/> Nirmla Jat (supra) was Division Wise, the cadre in the case of<lb/> P.T.I. Grade-III is District Wise and as such, the plea sought to be<lb/> raised by the petitioners being wholly baseless, the writ petitions<lb/> deserves to be dismissed.<lb/> Counsel for the respondents in peculiar circumstances of the<lb/> case do not object to the alternative prayer and submits that<lb/> representations, if any, should be filed within a period of ten days.<lb/> I have considered the submissions made by the counsel for<lb/> the parties and have perused the material available on record.<lb/> A perusal of the order passed in the case of Sangeeta Patidar<lb/> (supra) would reveal that said petitions were decided while<lb/> referring to order passed in Reena vs. State of Rajasthan &amp; Ors. :<lb/> S.B.C.W.P. No.7617/2020 decided on 16.10.2020 at Jaipur Bench.<lb/> The Bench at Jaipur in the case of Reena (supra) referred to<lb/> paragraph 35 of the judgment in the case of Nirmla Jat (supra)<lb/> and directed the respondents to follow the same directions. This<lb/> Court in the case of Nirmla Jat (supra) had, inter alia, directed as<lb/> under: -<lb/>&quot;34. There is yet another reason, for which this<lb/> Court does not deem it appropriate to direct the<lb/> respondents to undertake the exercise afresh.<lb/> Seniority of the teachers is reckoned Division Wise.<lb/> Now all the teachers have been allotted the division<lb/> according to their merit cum preference. When it<lb/> comes to posting, it has to be noted that they are<lb/> subject to intra division transfers, hence, posting at a<lb/> particular place cannot be claimed as a matter of right.<lb/> Posting is only a matter of convenience, which can be<lb/> addressed/redressed at a later point of time.<lb/></p>

			<p>35. Hence, considering the submission of the<lb/> State, as noticed in para No. 21 above and in view of<lb/> the<lb/> common<lb/> consensus<lb/> and<lb/> alternative<lb/> oral<lb/> submission of all the learned counsel for the respective<lb/> petitioners, this Court deems it appropriate and in the<lb/> interest of all the concerned, particularly the<lb/> candidates (who are not before this Court) to dispose<lb/> of all the writ petitions with following directions:-<lb/></p>

			<item>(i) The State shall publish latest subject-wise and<lb/> category-wise vacant position of each division on its<lb/> website, within a period of 15 days from today.<lb/></item>

			<item>(ii) All the petitioners herein may submit<lb/> representations to the Director, giving choice(s) qua<lb/> the vacant positions [out of their division(s)], so<lb/> published by the State. Representation(s) be furnished<lb/> within a period of four weeks from publication of such<lb/> list.<lb/></item>

			<item>(iii) The petitioners shall also be permitted to<lb/> request for mutual transfer within their division.<lb/></item>

			<item>(iv)<lb/> The Director/Joint Director shall decide<lb/> petitioners&apos; representations within a period of four<lb/> weeks thereafter, while trying to accommodate the<lb/> petitioners in accordance with the preference given by<lb/> them, of course, if the relevant law/guidelines so<lb/> permit.<lb/></item>

			<item>(v) In case, petitioners&apos; representations are<lb/> rejected, the respondents shall pass a reasoned order<lb/> under intimation to the concerned.<lb/></item>

			<item>(vi) The petitioners will be free to take up their<lb/> remedies against such orders, in accordance with law.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>It may be noticed here that the Bench in the case of Nirmla<lb/> Jat (supra) observed that seniority of the Teachers is reckoned<lb/> Division Wise, which in the case of P.T.I. Grade-III, which is<lb/> subject matter of the present writ petitions, is reckoned District<lb/> Wise. If the directions given in the case of Nirmla Jat (supra) are<lb/> read mutatis mutandis qua the present case, instead of &apos;Division&apos;,<lb/> &apos;District&apos; will have to be read and consequently, the directions as<lb/> given in the case of Nirmla Jat (supra) would inter alia read as<lb/> under: -<lb/></p>

			<item>(i) The State shall publish latest subject-wise and category-<lb/>wise vacant position of each District on its website, within a period<lb/> of 15 days from today.<lb/></item>

			<item>(ii) All the petitioners herein may submit representations to<lb/> the Director, giving choice(s) qua the vacant positions [out of their<lb/> district(s)], so published by the State. Representation(s) be<lb/> furnished within a period of four weeks from publication of such<lb/> list.<lb/></item>

			<item>(iii) The petitioners shall also be permitted to request for<lb/> mutual transfer within their district.<lb/></item>

			<p>The respondents in the communication dated 12.10.2021, as<lb/> quoted herein before, have required that in case of Intra-District<lb/> transfer within newly allotted districts, if representation has been<lb/> made, the same may be disposed of as per the merit of the<lb/> candidate(s) and qua the representations seeking Inter-District<lb/> Transfers, it was directed that the same be dismissed.<lb/> The communication dated 12.10.2021 is in consonance with<lb/> the directions given in the case of Nirmla Jat (supra), when the<lb/> same is read in context of the district, wherein the Court has<lb/> specifically<lb/> indicated<lb/> that<lb/> the<lb/> petitioners<lb/> may<lb/> submit<lb/> representation giving choice of any vacant position (out of their<lb/> district) so published by the State.<lb/> Once in the case of Nirmla Jat (supra), the choice was<lb/> restricted to Division, wherein the cadre was Division Wise, the<lb/> stipulation made in the communication dated 12.10.2021<lb/> restricting the choice within the district, in the present case,<lb/> where the cadre is District Wise, the same cannot be faulted on<lb/> any count.<lb/> In view of above fact situation, no case for interference in<lb/> the order dated 12.10.2021 is made out. The petitions have no<lb/> substance, they are therefore, dismissed.<lb/> In case the representations made by the petitioners are still<lb/> pending, the same may be decided expeditiously by the<lb/> respondents, preferably within a period of three weeks in<lb/> accordance with communication dated 12.10.2021.<lb/> The petitioners, who have not made any representation in<lb/> consonance with communication dated 12.10.2021, they may<lb/> make representation within a period of ten days from today i.e. by<lb/> 13.12.2021 and the respondents are directed to pass appropriate<lb/> orders thereon by 24.12.2021.<lb/></p>

			<p>(ARUN BHANSALI),J<lb/> 27, 108 to 214<lb/> &amp; 216 to 219-DJ/-<lb/>Schedule<lb/> S.No.<lb/> Item<lb/> No.<lb/> WRIT PETITION No(s).<lb/> PARTY NAME<lb/></p>

			<p>1.<lb/> 108<lb/> SBCWP No.14831/2021<lb/> Surendra Pal Singh<lb/> Sandhu<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></p>

			<item>2.<lb/> 109<lb/> SBCWP No.14835/2021<lb/> Jagdish Chandra<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>3.<lb/> 110<lb/> SBCWP No.14861/2021<lb/> Gursahab Singh<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>4.<lb/> 111<lb/> SBCWP No.14905/2021<lb/> Maya Devi<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>5.<lb/> 112<lb/> SBCWP No.14945/2021<lb/> Vinod Kumar Suman State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>6.<lb/> 113<lb/> SBCWP No.14963/2021<lb/> Ashok Kumar<lb/> Kumawat<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>7.<lb/> 114<lb/> SBCWP No.14964/2021<lb/> Meena Suman<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>8.<lb/> 115<lb/> SBCWP No.14965/2021<lb/> Kailash Chand Bheel State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>9.<lb/> 116<lb/> SBCWP No.14971/2021<lb/> Vinay Kulhari<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>10. 117<lb/> SBCWP No.14974/2021<lb/> Ram Ratan<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>11. 118<lb/> SBCWP No.14978/2021<lb/> Aman Deep Yadav<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>12. 119<lb/> SBCWP No.14982/2021<lb/> Sunil Chiraniya<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>13. 120<lb/> SBCWP No.14986/2021<lb/> Krishan Kumar<lb/> Choudhary<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>14. 121<lb/> SBCWP No.14987/2021<lb/> Dara Singh<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>15. 122<lb/> SBCWP No.14988/2021<lb/> Rakesh Kumar<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>16. 123<lb/> SBCWP No.14990/2021<lb/> Sushila Kumari<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>17. 124<lb/> SBCWP No.15029/2021<lb/> Raju Dhobi<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>18. 125<lb/> SBCWP No.15051/2021<lb/> Jagdish Jat<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>19. 126<lb/> SBCWP No.15055/2021<lb/> Vinod Kumar<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>20. 127<lb/> SBCWP No.15058/2021<lb/> Neetu Vaid<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>21. 128<lb/> SBCWP No.15074/2021<lb/> Pushpa Choudhary<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>22. 129<lb/> SBCWP No.15078/2021<lb/> Dharampal Barala<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>23. 130<lb/> SBCWP No.15086/2021<lb/> Bhagirath Suthar<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>24. 131<lb/> SBCWP No.15092/2021<lb/> Sanju Devi<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>25. 132<lb/> SBCWP No.15094/2021<lb/> Sushila Saini<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>26. 133<lb/> SBCWP No.15096/2021<lb/> Mukesh Meena<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>27. 134<lb/> SBCWP No.15097/2021<lb/> Saroj<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/></item>

			<item>(11 of 13)<lb/></item>

			<item>[CW-15319/2021]<lb/></item>

			<item>&amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>28. 135<lb/> SBCWP No.15103/2021<lb/> Manisha Kannojiya<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>29. 136<lb/> SBCWP No.15108/2021<lb/> Pranjal Rawal<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>30. 137<lb/> SBCWP No.15110/2021<lb/> Vinod Kumar Lochib<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>31. 138<lb/> SBCWP No.15111/2021<lb/> Pokar Ram<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>32. 139<lb/> SBCWP No.15112/2021<lb/> Shankar Lal Bana<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>33. 140<lb/> SBCWP No.15114/2021<lb/> Rajesh Swami<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>34. 141<lb/> SBCWP No.15140/2021<lb/> Girdhari Singh<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>35. 142<lb/> SBCWP No.15151/2021<lb/> Nandu Jat<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>36. 143<lb/> SBCWP No.15154/2021<lb/> Madan Lal<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>37. 144<lb/> SBCWP No.15159/2021<lb/> Virendra Meena<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>38. 145<lb/> SBCWP No.15176/2021<lb/> Dinesh<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>39. 146<lb/> SBCWP No.15178/2021<lb/> Hemraj Gurjar<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>40. 147<lb/> SBCWP No.15180/2021<lb/> Bacchu Singh Gurjar State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>41. 148<lb/> SBCWP No.15187/2021<lb/> Sarita Khedar<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>42. 149<lb/> SBCWP No.15192/2021<lb/> Vinita Choudhary<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>43. 150<lb/> SBCWP No.15218/2021<lb/> Vinod Kumar Sujawat State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>44. 151<lb/> SBCWP No.15221/2021<lb/> Pushpa Kumari Gadri State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>45. 152<lb/> SBCWP No.15223/2021<lb/> Shanker Lal Saini<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>46. 153<lb/> SBCWP No.15225/2021<lb/> Ramesh Chandra<lb/> Gurjar<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>47. 154<lb/> SBCWP No.15226/2021<lb/> Durga Devi<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>48. 155<lb/> SBCWP No.15237/2021<lb/> Jagmohan Singh<lb/> Gurjar<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>49. 156<lb/> SBCWP No.15252/2021<lb/> Chetan Rathore<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>50. 157<lb/> SBCWP No.15255/2021<lb/> Omprakash<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>51. 158<lb/> SBCWP No.15258/2021<lb/> Mukesh Kumar Jat<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>52. 159<lb/> SBCWP No.15259/2021<lb/> Kalpana Gurjar<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>53. 160<lb/> SBCWP No.15306/2021<lb/> Devi Singh Adha<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>54. 161<lb/> SBCWP No.15307/2021<lb/> Dinesh Kumar Jat<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>55. 162<lb/> SBCWP No.15344/2021<lb/> Lokesh Kumar<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>56. 163<lb/> SBCWP No.15347/2021<lb/> Nehpal Singh<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/></item>

			<item>(12 of 13)<lb/></item>

			<item>[CW-15319/2021]<lb/></item>

			<item>&amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>57. 164<lb/> SBCWP No.15348/2021<lb/> Shankar Lal Menaria State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>58. 165<lb/> SBCWP No.15353/2021<lb/> Magha Ram<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors.<lb/></item>

			<item>59. 166<lb/> SBCWP No.15360/2021<lb/> Mukesh Kumar Ahari State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/> 60. 167<lb/> SBCWP No.15369/2021<lb/> Urmila Yadav<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/> 61. 168<lb/> SBCWP No.15388/2021<lb/> Amrit Singh Parihar<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/> 62. 169<lb/> SBCWP No.15390/2021<lb/> Ganesh<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>63. 170<lb/> SBCWP No.15395/2021<lb/> Ajeet Godara<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>64. 171<lb/> SBCWP No.15396/2021<lb/> Daleep Kumar<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>65. 172<lb/> SBCWP No.15398/2021<lb/> Kamlendra Kumawat State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>66. 173<lb/> SBCWP No.15408/2021<lb/> Yadavinder<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>67. 174<lb/> SBCWP No.15409/2021<lb/> Eakbal Singh<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>68. 175<lb/> SBCWP No.15411/2021<lb/> Sanju Kumari Khati<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>69. 176<lb/> SBCWP No.15412/2021<lb/> Subodh Chaturvedi<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>70. 177<lb/> SBCWP No.15414/2021<lb/> Ankit Jat<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>71. 178<lb/> SBCWP No.15415/2021<lb/> Parvati<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>72. 179<lb/> SBCWP No.15428/2021<lb/> Oma Ram<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>73. 180<lb/> SBCWP No.15453/2021<lb/> Gambhir Singh Bhati State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>74. 181<lb/> SBCWP No.15487/2021<lb/> Neelu Charan<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>75. 182<lb/> SBCWP No.15542/2021<lb/> Ved Prakash<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>76. 183<lb/> SBCWP No.15543/2021<lb/> Prahlad Bairagi<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>77. 184<lb/> SBCWP No.15544/2021<lb/> Manpreet Singh<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>78. 185<lb/> SBCWP No.15614/2021<lb/> Sangeeta Parihar<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>79. 186<lb/> SBCWP No.15632/2021<lb/> Gaytri Vyas<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>80. 187<lb/> SBCWP No.15639/2021<lb/> Arun Kumar Gusar<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>81. 188<lb/> SBCWP No.15665/2021<lb/> Deepak Kumar<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>82. 189<lb/> SBCWP No.15677/2021<lb/> Anita Kumari Damor State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>83. 190<lb/> SBCWP No.15697/2021<lb/> Jagdeesh Meena<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>84. 191<lb/> SBCWP No.15701/2021<lb/> Pinky Rani Jaat<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>85. 192<lb/> SBCWP No.15703/2021<lb/> Sheela Meena<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/></item>

			<item>(13 of 13)<lb/></item>

			<item>[CW-15319/2021]<lb/></item>

			<item>&amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>86. 193<lb/> SBCWP No.15704/2021<lb/> Tophik Alam<lb/> Kayamkhani<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>87. 194<lb/> SBCWP No.15705/2021<lb/> Shankar Chanderiya<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>88. 195<lb/> SBCWP No.15706/2021<lb/> Santosh Gocher<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>89. 196<lb/> SBCWP No.15707/2021<lb/> Sampat Ram<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>90. 197<lb/> SBCWP No.15708/2021<lb/> Gajanand Palsania<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>91. 198<lb/> SBCWP No.15712/2021<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>92. 199<lb/> SBCWP No.15713/2021<lb/> Naresh Yadav<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>93. 200<lb/> SBCWP No.15736/2021<lb/> Rajesh Neniwal<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>94. 201<lb/> SBCWP No.15738/2021<lb/> Ashok Kumar Dabi<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>95. 202<lb/> SBCWP No.15769/2021<lb/> Vishawdeep Singh<lb/> Sekhon<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>96. 203<lb/> SBCWP No.15833/2021<lb/> Shilpa Sowara<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>97. 204<lb/> SBCWP No.15837/2021<lb/> Bhupendra Kumar<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>98. 205<lb/> SBCWP No.15842/2021<lb/> Anil Kumar<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>99. 206<lb/> SBCWP No.15922/2021<lb/> Rajkumar Fogawat<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<item>100. 207<lb/> SBCWP No.15933/2021<lb/> Surendra Kumar<lb/> Kanjar<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/> 101. 208<lb/> SBCWP No.15942/2021<lb/> Vikram Palsaniya<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/></item>

			<p>102. 209<lb/> SBCWP No.15948/2021<lb/> Bhagya Singh Gurjar State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/> 103. 210<lb/> SBCWP No.15997/2021<lb/> Mahaveer Prasad<lb/> Verma<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/> 104. 211<lb/> SBCWP No.16070/2021<lb/> Rajeshwar Singh<lb/> Rajawat<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/> 105. 212<lb/> SBCWP No.16226/2021<lb/> Ravindra Kumar<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/> 106. 213<lb/> SBCWP No.16316/2021<lb/> Soniya Burdak<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/> 107. 214<lb/> SBCWP No.16340/2021<lb/> Turna<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/> 108. 216<lb/> SBCWP No.15800/2021<lb/> Saroj Meena<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/> 109. 217<lb/> SBCWP No.15802/2021<lb/> Rekha Kumari<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/> 110. 218<lb/> SBCWP No.15828/2021<lb/> Anita Faleja<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors<lb/> 111. 219<lb/> SBCWP No.15838/2021<lb/> Usha Kumari Katara<lb/> State of Raj.<lb/> &amp; Ors</p>


	</text>
</tei>
