<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<page>
			1
			<lb />
		</page>

		<front>
			REPORTABLE
			<lb />
			IN THE SUPREME COURT OF INDIA
			<lb />
			CRIMINAL APPELLATE JURISDICTION
			<lb />
			CRIMINAL APPEAL NO.200 OF 2020
			<lb />
			(@ S.L.P.(CRIMINAL)No.4178 of 2019)
			<lb />
			UNION OF INDIA
			<lb />
			... APPELLANT(S)
			<lb />
			VERSUS
			<lb />
			ASHOK KUMAR SHARMA AND OTHERS
			<lb />
			... RESPONDENT(S)
			<lb />
		</front>

		<body>
			J U D G M E N T
			<lb />
			K.M. JOSEPH, J.
			<lb />
			1. What is the interplay between the provisions of the
			<lb />
			Code of Criminal Procedure (hereinafter referred to as
			<lb />
			&quot;CrPC&quot; for short) and the Drugs and Cosmetics Act, 1940
			<lb />
			(hereinafter referred to as &quot;the Act&quot; for short)? Whether
			<lb />
			in respect of offences falling under chapter IV of the Act,
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place='footnote'>
			Digitally signed by
			<lb />
			ASHA SUNDRIYAL
			<lb />
			Date: 2020.08.28
			<lb />
			19:27:16 IST
			<lb />
			Reason:
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			2
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			a FIR can be registered under Section 154 of the CrPC and
			<lb />
			the case investigated or whether Section 32 of the Act
			<lb />
			supplants the procedure for investigation of offences under
			<lb />
			CrPC and the taking of cognizance of an offence under
			<lb />
			Section 190 of the CrPC? Still further, can the Inspector
			<lb />
			under the Act, arrest a person in connection with an offence
			<lb />
			under Chapter IV of the Act.
			<lb />
			2. One Naushad Khan made an online complaint on 22.2.2018.
			<lb />
			The Commissioner (Food Protection and Drugs) directed
			<lb />
			enquiry and the Drug Inspector, Mau, U.P. along with two
			<lb />
			others conducted an inspection at the Sharda Narayan Clinic
			<lb />
			and Pharmacy and the respondent No.1 was directed to show
			<lb />
			papers in respect of medicines stored in the shop. The
			<lb />
			first respondent according to the appellant stated that he
			<lb />
			did not have any license though he was the owner of the
			<lb />
			medical store and that he had stored the medicines without
			<lb />
			proper license. Thereby, he has committed offence under
			<lb />
			Section 18 and 27 of the Act. On the basis of recovery made,
			<lb />
			an FIR came to be lodged on 22.6.2018 purporting to be under
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			3
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Section 18 (a)(i) and Section 27 of the Act.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			complainant it may be noted is none other than the Drugs
			<lb />
			Inspector. The respondent filed a writ petition for
			<lb />
			quashing the FIR and not to arrest him. The appellant,
			<lb />
			viz., the Union of India through the Secretary, Ministry
			<lb />
			of Health and Family Welfare was not made a party to the
			<lb />
			writ petition. The respondents in the writ petition were
			<lb />
			the Superintendent of Police, the Station House Officer and
			<lb />
			the Drugs Inspector, Mau in his personal capacity. This is
			<lb />
			apart from the State of U.P. which was made the first
			<lb />
			respondent. It is pointed out by the appellant that the
			<lb />
			High Court issued notice seeking presence of the appellant.
			<lb />
			The High Court by the impugned order had allowed the writ
			<lb />
			petition and quashed the FIR. In short, the reasoning of
			<lb />
			the High Court is that under the Act Section 32 must be
			<lb />
			scrupulously observed and it is the mechanism for
			<lb />
			prosecuting offences and there is no scope for registration
			<lb />
			of a FIR under CrPC.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			4
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			FINDINGS OF THE HIGH COURT
			<lb />
			3. The High Court referred to Section 32 of the Act and
			<lb />
			found that only an Inspector, a Gazetted Officer conferred
			<lb />
			with authority, a person aggrieved or recognized consumer
			<lb />
			organization is eligible to make a complaint. The court
			<lb />
			adverted to the other provisions of the Act including
			<lb />
			Sections 22, 23, 25 and 27 apart from Section 32 and found
			<lb />
			that the Act clearly lays down a complete code for the trial
			<lb />
			of offences committed in respect of Drugs and Cosmetics.
			<lb />
			The Act was a special Act enacted for the trial of offences
			<lb />
			committed under the Act.
			<lb />
			No other provision would be
			<lb />
			applicable as the Act had an overriding effect over all
			<lb />
			Acts. The provisions of the CrPC would not be applicable
			<lb />
			except as provided in the Act itself. Since the lodging
			<lb />
			of an FIR is under Section 154 of the CrPC, the said
			<lb />
			provision would not be invokable.
			<lb />
			It further held as
			<lb />
			follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;21. In this Act, the procedure for launching
			<lb />
			a prosecution has been clearly laid down
			<lb />
			saying that prosecution under this Act can be
			<lb />
			initiated only on a complaint made by an
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			5
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			authorized Inspector or other authorized
			<lb />
			persons defined under Section 32, who is
			<lb />
			supposed to follow the entire procedure as
			<lb />
			narrated above. By no stretch of imagination
			<lb />
			could the concerned Inspector have lodged an
			<lb />
			F.I.R. in this case and authorize the police
			<lb />
			to make investigation in this case.&quot;
			<lb />
			4. It was further held that the lodging of the FIR is
			<lb />
			absolutely barred and FIR deserved to be quashed. The
			<lb />
			court also directed the issue of notice to the Inspector
			<lb />
			who had gone to lodge the FIR, despite there being a special
			<lb />
			provision for launching the prosecution and explanation was
			<lb />
			sought. Still further it was directed as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;23. We, accordingly, allow this petition
			<lb />
			and quash the F.I.R. and simultaneously it is
			<lb />
			further directed that notice shall be issued
			<lb />
			to the concerned Inspector by the Competent
			<lb />
			Authority to show cause as to why he
			<lb />
			deliberately lodged an F.I.R. when there is
			<lb />
			specific provision for prosecuting the
			<lb />
			accused by lodging a complaint. The
			<lb />
			explanation and action taken against him,
			<lb />
			shall be forwarded to the Court by the
			<lb />
			Competent Authority within 8 weeks from today
			<lb />
			through Registrar General of this Court who
			<lb />
			shall place the same before us for perusal in
			<lb />
			our chambers as soon as the same is received
			<lb />
			by Registrar General. We further grant
			<lb />
			liberty to the respondent no. 4 to initiate
			<lb />
			criminal proceedings in accordance with the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			6
			<lb />
		</page>

		<front>
			procedure laid down under this Act forthwith
			<lb />
			against the petitioner.
			<lb />
			24. Registrar General to sent a certified
			<lb />
			copy of this order to Principal Secretary,
			<lb />
			Food Safety and
			<lb />
			Drug Administration,
			<lb />
			Government of U.P. for his necessary
			<lb />
			information and follow up action. It is
			<lb />
			further directed that Principal Secretary,
			<lb />
			Food Safety and
			<lb />
			Drug Administration,
			<lb />
			Government of U.P. shall notify such
			<lb />
			direction to all the D.Ms. of the State so
			<lb />
			that no such error recurs.&quot;
			<lb />
			5. We heard Ms. Pinky Anand, learned Additional Solicitor
			<lb />
			General appearing on behalf of the appellant. We also
			<lb />
			heard Shri S. Nagamuthu, learned Senior Counsel, whom we
			<lb />
			appointed as Amicus Curiae.
			<lb />
			SUBMISSIONS OF THE APPELLANT
			<lb />
			6. Ms. Pinky Anand, learned Additional Solicitor General
			<lb />
			would submit that the High Court was in error in holding
			<lb />
			that FIR under CrPC cannot be lodged in respect of the Act.
			<lb />
			She drew our attention to Section 36 AC of the Act.
			<lb />
			Thereunder, as we shall see in greater detail, certain
			<lb />
			offences under the Act have been declared to be cognizable
			<lb />
		</front>

		<page>
			7
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			offences. She would point out that once these offences are
			<lb />
			declared as cognizable offences it is inconceivable that
			<lb />
			a FIR cannot be lodged under the CrPC in regard to the same.
			<lb />
			She drew our attention to Section 4 and 5 of the CrPC. She
			<lb />
			contended that there is nothing in the Act which detracted
			<lb />
			from a FIR being registered in regard to offences under the
			<lb />
			Act. Regarding the consequences flowing from Section 32 of
			<lb />
			the Act, it is her contention that the High Court fell in
			<lb />
			error in ignoring Section 36AC of the Act. It is her
			<lb />
			complaint that the Act contemplated curbing of various
			<lb />
			highly undesirable activities posing a great threat to the
			<lb />
			health and the safety of citizens as can be gleaned from
			<lb />
			the grave offences which have been created under the Act.
			<lb />
			In fact, it is pointed out that many cases where
			<lb />
			investigation was carried out on the basis of FIR lodged
			<lb />
			under the Act will witness unmerited burial and offenders
			<lb />
			would go scot free if the impugned judgment of the High Court
			<lb />
			is allowed to stand. There is no bar under the Act to the
			<lb />
			registration of FIR under CrPC.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			8
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			7. Shri Nagamuthu, learned senior counsel submitted that
			<lb />
			having regard to the scheme of the Act and Section 32, in
			<lb />
			particular, the judgment of the High Court is only to be
			<lb />
			supported.
			<lb />
			He drew our attention to the following
			<lb />
			judgments:
			<lb />
			a. Jeewan Kumar Raut and another v. CBI 1 ;
			<lb />
			b. State (NCT of Delhi) v. Sanjay 2 .
			<lb />
			8. He also referred to the judgment of this Court in Kanwar
			<lb />
			Pal Singh v. State of Uttar Pradesh and another in Criminal
			<lb />
			Appeal No.1920 of 2019. He would submit that as far as
			<lb />
			offences falling within the ambit of Section 36AC are
			<lb />
			concerned, a FIR under Section 154 of the CrPC is not
			<lb />
			contemplated and cannot be registered. The mere fact that
			<lb />
			Section 36 AC of the Act declares certain offences under
			<lb />
			the Act cognizable would not mean that the scheme of Section
			<lb />
			32 of the Act can be jettisoned. He would point out that
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			1 (2009) 7 SCC 526
			<lb />
			2 (2014) 9 SCC 772
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			9
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			prosecution can be launched only in the manner provided
			<lb />
			under the Act in regard to offences under the Act covered
			<lb />
			by Section 32. The institution of the prosecution can be
			<lb />
			only at the instance of the persons named in the said
			<lb />
			section. He points out that Section 32 came to be amended
			<lb />
			at the same time as Section 36 AC was inserted. Nothing
			<lb />
			prevented the Legislature if it so desired to provide that
			<lb />
			the offences falling under Section 32 should be
			<lb />
			investigated in the manner provided under the provisions
			<lb />
			of the CRPC namely by lodging a FIR and after investigating
			<lb />
			the offences by filing a report within the meaning of
			<lb />
			Section 173 of the CrPC. The fact that such a procedure
			<lb />
			was not contemplated by the Legislature is clear from the
			<lb />
			fact that under the pre amended regime, three out of four
			<lb />
			categories mentioned in the present amended avtaar were
			<lb />
			already present and the amendment added only one more to
			<lb />
			the categories of persons who alone could institute the
			<lb />
			prosecution. In fact, as regards Section 36 AC declaring
			<lb />
			certain offences under the Act to be cognizable, he drew
			<lb />
			our attention to the second part of the first schedule of
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			10
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			the CrPC. He contended inter alia that even without the
			<lb />
			aid of Section 36 AC, the offences under Section 27(1)(a)
			<lb />
			and 27(1)(c) were cognizable having regard to the term of
			<lb />
			imprisonment provided as punishment for the same. Nothing
			<lb />
			turned on the offence being cognizable except apprehension
			<lb />
			of the offender without the aid of a warrant. He would
			<lb />
			submit that in regard to the offences embraced by Section
			<lb />
			32, an F.I.R. within the meaning of the CrPC is not
			<lb />
			contemplated but he was at pains to point out that this did
			<lb />
			not stand in the way of an F.I.R. being lodged if the
			<lb />
			offence constituted a distinct offence under any other law.
			<lb />
			In such a scenario, while the lodging of the F.I.R. in regard
			<lb />
			to the offences covered by Section 32 would be impermissible
			<lb />
			the Officer would be within his powers if he were to register
			<lb />
			an F.I.R. and proceed to investigate offences other than
			<lb />
			the offence falling under Section 32, should they be
			<lb />
			cognizable. In this case, he would submit that the offence
			<lb />
			alleged is under Section 27 (1)(b) of the Act which squarely
			<lb />
			fell within the four walls of Section 32. So, also Section
			<lb />
			18 prohibiting certain acts fell in Chapter IV of the Act,
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			11
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			thus, attracting Section 32. In regard to these offences,
			<lb />
			Section 32 constitutes a bar for the registration of an
			<lb />
			F.I.R. under CrPC and the investigation as an ordinary case.
			<lb />
			9. In reply to submission of learned Amicus Curiae,
			<lb />
			Ms. Pinky Anand, learned Additional Solicitor General, drew
			<lb />
			our attention to Section 36AC and reiterated that neither
			<lb />
			the CrPC nor the Act constitute a stumbling block to the
			<lb />
			lodging of an FIR. She also drew our attention to Section
			<lb />
			13 of the Act. It is pointed out that Section 13 falls under
			<lb />
			Chapter III. She contended that the Act contemplated a
			<lb />
			Special Court to deal with the offences under the Act. The
			<lb />
			procedure leading to the institution of the prosecution
			<lb />
			case must be governed by the provisions of the CrPC, runs
			<lb />
			her argument.
			<lb />
			ANALYSIS
			<lb />
			10. The Act purports to achieve the object of regulating
			<lb />
			the import, manufacture, distribution and sale of drugs and
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			12
			<lb />
		</page>

		<front>
			cosmetics. The word Drugs has been defined in Section 3(b).
			<lb />
			Section 3(e) defines Inspector:
			<lb />
			&quot;3 Definitions. -In this Act, unless there
			<lb />
			is anything repugnant in the subject or
			<lb />
			context,-
			<lb />
			(e) &quot;Inspector&quot; means-
			<lb />
			(i) in relation to Ayurvedic, Siddha or
			<lb />
			Unani drug, an Inspector appointed by the
			<lb />
			Central Government or a State Government
			<lb />
			under section 33G; and
			<lb />
			(ii) in relation to any other drug or
			<lb />
			cosmetic, an Inspector appointed by the
			<lb />
			Central Government or a State Government
			<lb />
			under section 21;
			<lb />
			11. Chapter III contains provisions which provide for
			<lb />
			deeming definitions of misbranded drugs, adulterated
			<lb />
			drugs, spurious drugs, misbranded cosmetics and spurious
			<lb />
			cosmetics for the purpose of Chapter III. Section 13
			<lb />
			provides for offences arising out of imports. Chapter IV
			<lb />
			falls under the chapter heading &quot;Manufacture, Sale and
			<lb />
			Distribution of Drugs and Cosmetics&quot;. Interestingly,
			<lb />
			misbranded drugs, adulterated drugs, spurious drugs,
			<lb />
		</front>

		<page>
			13
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			misbranded cosmetics and spurious cosmetics, adulterated
			<lb />
			cosmetics are defined by provisions found in Chapter IV for
			<lb />
			the purpose of Chapter IV. Section 18 contemplates that from
			<lb />
			such date as may be fixed by the State Government,
			<lb />
			manufacture for sale or distribution, or to sell, or stock
			<lb />
			or exhibit or offer for sale or distribution of drugs
			<lb />
			misbranded, adulterated, spurious drugs and cosmetics
			<lb />
			inter alia are prohibited. Section 21 reads as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;21. Inspectors.-
			<lb />
			(1) The Central Government or a State
			<lb />
			Government may by notification in the
			<lb />
			Official Gazette, appoint such persons as
			<lb />
			it thinks fit, having the prescribed
			<lb />
			qualifications, to be Inspectors for such
			<lb />
			areas as may be assigned to them by the
			<lb />
			Central
			<lb />
			Government
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			State
			<lb />
			Government, as the case may be.
			<lb />
			(2) The powers which may be exercised by an
			<lb />
			Inspector and the duties which may be
			<lb />
			performed by him, the drugs or [classes of
			<lb />
			drugs or cosmetics or classes of cosmetics]
			<lb />
			in relation to which and the conditions,
			<lb />
			limitations or restrictions subject to
			<lb />
			which, such powers and duties may be
			<lb />
			exercised or performed shall be such as may
			<lb />
			be prescribed.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			14
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			(3) No person who has any financial
			<lb />
			interest in the import, manufacture or sale
			<lb />
			of drugs or cosmetics shall be appointed to
			<lb />
			be an Inspector under this section.
			<lb />
			(4) Every Inspector shall be deemed to be
			<lb />
			a public servant within the meaning of
			<lb />
			section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of
			<lb />
			1860), and shall be officially subordinate
			<lb />
			to such authority, having the prescribed
			<lb />
			qualifications,]
			<lb />
			as
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Government
			<lb />
			appointing him may specify in this behalf.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			12. It is necessary to notice the rules relevant in this
			<lb />
			regard. Rule (49) deals with qualifications of Inspectors.
			<lb />
			It reads as follows: -
			<lb />
			&quot;49. Qualifications of Inspectors. -A person
			<lb />
			who is appointed an Inspector under the Act
			<lb />
			shall be a person who has a degree in Pharmacy
			<lb />
			or Pharmaceutical Sciences or Medicine with
			<lb />
			specialisation in Clinical Pharmacology or
			<lb />
			Microbiology from a University established
			<lb />
			in India by law: Provided that only those
			<lb />
			Inspectors-
			<lb />
			(i) who have not less than 18 months&apos;
			<lb />
			experience in the manufacture of at least one
			<lb />
			of the substances specified in Schedule C, or
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			15
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			(ii) who have not less than 18 months&apos;
			<lb />
			experience in testing of at least one of the
			<lb />
			substances in Schedule C in a laboratory
			<lb />
			approved for this purpose by the licensing
			<lb />
			authority, or
			<lb />
			(iii) who have gained experience of not less
			<lb />
			than three years in the inspection of firm
			<lb />
			manufacturing
			<lb />
			any
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			substances
			<lb />
			specified in Schedule C during the tenure of
			<lb />
			their services as Drugs Inspectors; shall be
			<lb />
			authorised to inspect the manufacture of the
			<lb />
			substances mentioned in Schedule C:
			<lb />
			Provided further that the requirement as
			<lb />
			to the academic qualification shall not apply
			<lb />
			to persons appointed as Inspectors on or
			<lb />
			before the 18th day of October, 1993.&quot;
			<lb />
			Rule (51) deals with duties of Inspectors in regard to
			<lb />
			sale. It reads as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;51. Duties of Inspectors of premises
			<lb />
			licensed
			<lb />
			for
			<lb />
			sale.-Subject
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			instructions of the controlling authority,
			<lb />
			it shall be the duty of an Inspector
			<lb />
			authorized to inspect premises licensed for
			<lb />
			the sale of drugs-
			<lb />
			(1) to inspect not less than once a year all
			<lb />
			establishments licensed for the sale of drugs
			<lb />
			within the area assigned to him;
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			16
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			(2) to satisfy himself that the conditions of
			<lb />
			the licences are being observed;
			<lb />
			(3) to procure and send for test or analysis,
			<lb />
			if necessary, imported packages which he has
			<lb />
			reason to suspect contain drugs being sold or
			<lb />
			stocked
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			exhibited
			<lb />
			for
			<lb />
			sale
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			contravention of the provisions of the Act or
			<lb />
			rules thereunder;
			<lb />
			(4) to investigate any complaint in writing
			<lb />
			which may be made to him;
			<lb />
			(5) to institute prosecutions in respect of
			<lb />
			breaches of the Act and rules thereunder;
			<lb />
			(6) to maintain a record of all inspections
			<lb />
			made and action taken by him in the
			<lb />
			performance of his duties, including the
			<lb />
			taking of samples and the seizure of stocks,
			<lb />
			and to submit copies of such record to the
			<lb />
			controlling authority;
			<lb />
			(7) to make such enquiries and inspections as
			<lb />
			may be necessary to detect the sale of drugs
			<lb />
			in contravention of the Act;
			<lb />
			(8) when so authorized by the State
			<lb />
			Government, to detain imported packages
			<lb />
			which he has reason to suspect contain drugs,
			<lb />
			the import of which is prohibited.&quot;
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			17
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Rule (52) deals with duties of Inspectors in regard to
			<lb />
			manufacturer. It reads as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;52. Duties of inspectors specially
			<lb />
			authorised to inspect the manufacture of
			<lb />
			drugs or cosmetics. -Subject to the
			<lb />
			instructions of the controlling authority it
			<lb />
			shall be the duty of an Inspector authorized
			<lb />
			to inspect the manufacture of drugs-
			<lb />
			(1) to inspect [not less than once a year],
			<lb />
			all premises licensed for manufacture of
			<lb />
			drugs or cosmetics within the area allotted
			<lb />
			to him to satisfy himself that the conditions
			<lb />
			of the licence and provisions of the Act and
			<lb />
			Rules thereunder are being observed;
			<lb />
			(2) in the case of establishments licensed to
			<lb />
			manufacture products specified in Schedules
			<lb />
			C and C (1) to inspect the plant and the
			<lb />
			process of manufacture, the means employed
			<lb />
			for standardizing and testing the drug, the
			<lb />
			methods and place of storage, the technical
			<lb />
			qualifications of the staff employed and all
			<lb />
			details of location, construction and
			<lb />
			administration of the establishment likely
			<lb />
			to affect the potency or purity of the
			<lb />
			product;
			<lb />
			(3) to send forthwith to the controlling
			<lb />
			authority after each inspection a detailed
			<lb />
			report indicating the conditions of the
			<lb />
			licence and provisions of the Act and rules
			<lb />
			thereunder which are being observed and the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			18
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			conditions and provisions, if any, which are
			<lb />
			not being observed;
			<lb />
			(4) to take samples of the drugs manufactured
			<lb />
			on the premises and send them for test or
			<lb />
			analysis in accordance with these Rules;
			<lb />
			(5) to institute prosecutions in respect of
			<lb />
			breaches of the Act and rules thereunder.&quot;
			<lb />
			Section 22 deals with the powers of the Inspector.
			<lb />
			reads as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;22. Powers of Inspectors.-(1) Subject to
			<lb />
			the provisions of section 23 and of any rules
			<lb />
			made by the Central Government in this
			<lb />
			behalf, an Inspector may, within the local
			<lb />
			limits of the area for which he is
			<lb />
			appointed,-&quot; (a) inspect,-&quot;
			<lb />
			(i) any premises wherein any drug or cosmetic
			<lb />
			is being manufactured and the means employed
			<lb />
			for standardising and testing the drug or
			<lb />
			cosmetic;
			<lb />
			(ii) any premises wherein any drug or
			<lb />
			cosmetic is being sold, or stocked or
			<lb />
			exhibited
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			offered
			<lb />
			for
			<lb />
			sale,
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			distributed;
			<lb />
			(b) take samples of any drug or cosmetic,-
			<lb />
			(i) which is being manufactured or being sold
			<lb />
			or is stocked or exhibited or offered for
			<lb />
			sale, or is being distributed;
			<lb />
			(ii) from any person who is in the course of
			<lb />
			conveying, delivering or preparing to
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			19
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			deliver such drug or cosmetic to a purchaser
			<lb />
			or a consignee;
			<lb />
			(c) at all reasonable times, with such
			<lb />
			assistance, if any, as he considers
			<lb />
			necessary,-
			<lb />
			(i) search any person, who, he has reason to
			<lb />
			believe, has secreted about his person, any
			<lb />
			drug or cosmetic in respect of which an
			<lb />
			offence under this Chapter has been, or is
			<lb />
			being, committed; or
			<lb />
			(ii) enter and search any place in which he
			<lb />
			has reason to believe that an offence under
			<lb />
			this Chapter has been, or is being,
			<lb />
			committed; or
			<lb />
			(iii) stop and search any vehicle, vessel or
			<lb />
			other conveyance which, he has reason to
			<lb />
			believe, is being used for carrying any drug
			<lb />
			or cosmetic in respect of which an offence
			<lb />
			under this Chapter has been, or is being,
			<lb />
			committed,
			<lb />
			and order in writing the person in possession
			<lb />
			of the drug or cosmetic in respect of which
			<lb />
			the offence has been, or is being, committed,
			<lb />
			not to dispose of any stock of such drug or
			<lb />
			cosmetic for a specified period not exceeding
			<lb />
			twenty days, or, unless the alleged offence
			<lb />
			is such that the defect may be removed by the
			<lb />
			possessor of the drug or cosmetic, seize the
			<lb />
			stock of such drug or cosmetic and any
			<lb />
			substance or article by means of which the
			<lb />
			offence has been, or is being, committed or
			<lb />
			which may be employed for the commission of
			<lb />
			such offence;
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			20
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			(cc) examine any record, register, document
			<lb />
			or any other material object found with any
			<lb />
			person, or in any place, vehicle, vessel or
			<lb />
			other conveyance referred to in clause (c),
			<lb />
			and seize the same if he has reason to believe
			<lb />
			that it may furnish evidence of the
			<lb />
			commission of an offence punishable under
			<lb />
			this Act or the Rules made thereunder;
			<lb />
			(cca) require any person to produce any
			<lb />
			record, register, or other document relating
			<lb />
			to the manufacture for sale or for
			<lb />
			distribution, stocking, exhibition for sale,
			<lb />
			offer for sale or distribution of any drug or
			<lb />
			cosmetic in respect of which he has reason to
			<lb />
			believe that an offence under this Chapter
			<lb />
			has been, or is being, committed;
			<lb />
			(d) exercise such other powers as may be
			<lb />
			necessary for carrying out the purposes of
			<lb />
			this Chapter or any rules made thereunder.
			<lb />
			22(2)The provisions of the Code of Criminal
			<lb />
			Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)] shall, so far as
			<lb />
			may be, apply to any search or seizure under
			<lb />
			this Chapter as they apply to any search or
			<lb />
			seizure made under the authority of a warrant
			<lb />
			issued under section 94 of the said Code.
			<lb />
			(2A) Every record, register or other document
			<lb />
			seized under clause (cc) or produced under
			<lb />
			clause (cca) shall be returned to the person,
			<lb />
			from whom they were seized or who produce the
			<lb />
			same, within a period of twenty days of the
			<lb />
			date of such seizure or production, as the
			<lb />
			case may be, after copies thereof or extracts
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			21
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			therefrom certified by that person, in such
			<lb />
			manner as may be prescribed, have been taken.
			<lb />
			(3)If any person wilfully obstructs an
			<lb />
			Inspector in the exercise of the powers
			<lb />
			conferred upon by or under this Chapter or
			<lb />
			refuses to produce any record, register or
			<lb />
			other document when so required under clause
			<lb />
			(cca) of sub-section (1), he shall be
			<lb />
			punishable with imprisonment which may
			<lb />
			extend to three years or with fine, or with
			<lb />
			both.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			13. Section 23 provides for the procedure to be followed
			<lb />
			by the Inspector. It includes the tendering of fair price
			<lb />
			when a sample is taken of a drug or cosmetic under the
			<lb />
			Chapter. There are various other provisions regarding the
			<lb />
			procedure to be followed by the Inspector which includes
			<lb />
			seizure of record/ register, documents or other material
			<lb />
			objects and the need to notify a judicial Magistrate [See
			<lb />
			Section 23(6)].
			<lb />
			14. Section 27 provides for penalty for manufacture, sale
			<lb />
			etc. of drug in contravention of Chapter IV. It reads as
			<lb />
			follows:
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			22
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			&quot;27. Penalty for manufacture, sale, etc., of
			<lb />
			drugs in contravention of this Chapter.-
			<lb />
			Whoever, himself or by any other person on his
			<lb />
			behalf, manufactures for sale or for
			<lb />
			distribution, or sells, or stocks or exhibits
			<lb />
			or offers for sale or distributes,-
			<lb />
			(a) any drug deemed to be adulterated under
			<lb />
			section
			<lb />
			17A
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			spurious
			<lb />
			under
			<lb />
			section 17B and which when used by any
			<lb />
			person for or in the diagnosis,
			<lb />
			treatment, mitigation, or prevention of
			<lb />
			any disease or disorder is likely to
			<lb />
			cause his death or is likely to cause
			<lb />
			such harm on his body as would amount to
			<lb />
			grievous hurt within the meaning of
			<lb />
			section 320 of the Indian Penal Code (45
			<lb />
			of 1860), solely on account of such drug
			<lb />
			being adulterated or spurious or not of
			<lb />
			standard quality, as the case may be,
			<lb />
			shall be punishable with imprisonment
			<lb />
			for a term which shall not be less than
			<lb />
			ten years but which may extend to
			<lb />
			imprisonment for life and shall also be
			<lb />
			liable to fine which shall not be less
			<lb />
			than ten lakh rupees or three times value
			<lb />
			of the drugs confiscated, whichever is
			<lb />
			more:
			<lb />
			Provided that the fine imposed on and
			<lb />
			released from, the person convicted
			<lb />
			under this clause shall be paid, by way
			<lb />
			of compensation, to the person who had
			<lb />
			used the adulterated or spurious drugs
			<lb />
			referred to in this clause:
			<lb />
			Provided further that where the use of
			<lb />
			the adulterated or spurious drugs
			<lb />
			referred to in this clause has caused the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			23
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			death of a person who used such drugs,
			<lb />
			the fine imposed on and realised from,
			<lb />
			the person convicted under this clause,
			<lb />
			shall be paid to the relative of the
			<lb />
			person who had died due to the use of the
			<lb />
			adulterated or spurious drugs referred
			<lb />
			to in this clause.
			<lb />
			Explanation.--For the purposes of the
			<lb />
			second
			<lb />
			proviso,
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			expression
			<lb />
			&quot;relative&quot; means--
			<lb />
			(i) spouse of the deceased person; or
			<lb />
			(ii) a minor legitimate son, and
			<lb />
			unmarried legitimate daughter and a
			<lb />
			widowed mother; or
			<lb />
			(iii) parent of the minor victim; or
			<lb />
			(iv) if wholly dependent on the earnings
			<lb />
			of the deceased person at the time of his
			<lb />
			death, a son or a daughter who has
			<lb />
			attained the age of eighteen years; or
			<lb />
			(v) any person, if wholly or in part,
			<lb />
			dependent on the earnings of the deceased
			<lb />
			person at the time of his death,--
			<lb />
			(a) the parent; or
			<lb />
			(b) a minor brother or an unmarried
			<lb />
			sister; or
			<lb />
			(c) a widowed daughter-in-law; or
			<lb />
			(d) a widowed sister; or
			<lb />
			(e) a minor child of a pre-deceased son;
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			24
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			(f) a minor child of a pre-deceased
			<lb />
			daughter where no parent of the child is
			<lb />
			alive; or
			<lb />
			(g) the paternal grandparent if no parent
			<lb />
			of the member is alive;]
			<lb />
			(b) any drug--
			<lb />
			(i) deemed to be adulterated under section
			<lb />
			17A, but not being a drug referred to in
			<lb />
			clause (a), or
			<lb />
			(ii) without a valid licence as required
			<lb />
			under clause (c) of section 18, shall be
			<lb />
			punishable with imprisonment for a term
			<lb />
			which shall not be less than three years but
			<lb />
			which may extend to five years and with fine
			<lb />
			which shall not be less than one lakh rupees
			<lb />
			or three times the value of the drugs
			<lb />
			confiscated, whichever is more:
			<lb />
			Provided that the Court may, for any
			<lb />
			adequate and special reasons to be recorded
			<lb />
			in the judgment, impose a sentence of
			<lb />
			imprisonment for a term of less than three
			<lb />
			years and of fine of less than one lakh
			<lb />
			rupees;
			<lb />
			(c)
			<lb />
			any drug deemed to be spurious under
			<lb />
			section 17B, but not being a drug
			<lb />
			referred to in clause (a) shall be
			<lb />
			punishable with imprisonment for a
			<lb />
			term which shall not less than seven
			<lb />
			years but which may extend to
			<lb />
			imprisonment for life and with fine
			<lb />
			which shall not be three lakh rupees
			<lb />
			or three times the value of the drugs
			<lb />
			confiscated, whichever is more:
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			25
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Provided that the Court may, for
			<lb />
			any adequate and special reasons, to
			<lb />
			be recorded in the judgment, impose a
			<lb />
			sentence of imprisonment for a term
			<lb />
			of 8 [less than seven years but not
			<lb />
			less than three years and of fine of
			<lb />
			less than one lakh rupees];
			<lb />
			(d)
			<lb />
			any drug, other than a drug referred
			<lb />
			to in clause (a) or clause (b) or
			<lb />
			clause (c), in contravention of any
			<lb />
			other provision of this Chapter or any
			<lb />
			rule made thereunder, shall be
			<lb />
			punishable with imprisonment for a
			<lb />
			term which shall not be less than one
			<lb />
			year but which may extend to two
			<lb />
			years and with fine which shall not be
			<lb />
			less than twenty thousand rupees:
			<lb />
			Provided that the Court may for
			<lb />
			any adequate and special reasons to be
			<lb />
			recorded in the judgment impose a
			<lb />
			sentence of imprisonment for a term of
			<lb />
			less than one year.&quot;
			<lb />
			15. Sections 27A, 28, 28A, 28B and 29 provide for other
			<lb />
			offences. Section 30 contemplates penalty in the case of
			<lb />
			subsequent offences. Section 31 deals with confiscation.
			<lb />
			Section 32 which is at the center stage of the controversy
			<lb />
			reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			26
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			&quot;32 Cognizance of offences. -(1) No
			<lb />
			prosecution under this Chapter shall be
			<lb />
			instituted except by-
			<lb />
			(a) an Inspector; or
			<lb />
			(b) any gazetted officer of the Central
			<lb />
			Government or a State Government authorised
			<lb />
			in writing in this behalf by the Central
			<lb />
			Government or a State Government by a general
			<lb />
			or special order made in this behalf by that
			<lb />
			Government; or
			<lb />
			(c) the person aggrieved; or
			<lb />
			(d) a
			<lb />
			recognised
			<lb />
			consumer
			<lb />
			association
			<lb />
			whether such person is a member of that
			<lb />
			association or not.
			<lb />
			(2) Save as otherwise provided in this Act,
			<lb />
			no court inferior to that of a Court of
			<lb />
			Session shall try an offence punishable under
			<lb />
			this Chapter.
			<lb />
			(3) Nothing contained in this Chapter shall
			<lb />
			be deemed to prevent any person from being
			<lb />
			prosecuted under any other law for any act or
			<lb />
			omission which constitutes an offence
			<lb />
			against this Chapter.&quot;
			<lb />
			Section 32B provides for compounding of certain
			<lb />
			offences.
			<lb />
			16. Chapter IV-A provides for &quot;Provisions relating to
			<lb />
			Ayurvedic, Siddha and Unani Drugs&quot;. It also contains
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			27
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			provisions for the purpose of Chapter IV-A dealing with
			<lb />
			deemed definitions of Misbranded drugs, Adulterated drugs,
			<lb />
			Spurious drugs and are created offences. Section 33G
			<lb />
			provides for appointment of Inspectors by the Central
			<lb />
			Government or the State Government. Section 33H makes the
			<lb />
			provision of Section 22,23,24 and 25 and the rules, if any,
			<lb />
			thereunder applicable in respect of Ayurvedic, Siddha and
			<lb />
			Unani drugs. Section 33M reads as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;33M. Cognizance of offences.-
			<lb />
			(1) No prosecution under this Chapter shall
			<lb />
			be instituted except by an Inspector [with
			<lb />
			the previous sanction of the authority
			<lb />
			specified under sub-section (4) of section
			<lb />
			33G.
			<lb />
			(2) No Court inferior to that [of a
			<lb />
			Metropolitan Magistrate or of a Judicial
			<lb />
			Magistrate of the first class] shall try an
			<lb />
			offence punishable under this Chapter.&quot;
			<lb />
			17. The last Chapter of the Act is Chapter V. It bears the
			<lb />
			Chapter heading &quot;Miscellaneous&quot;. Section 36 declares that
			<lb />
			any Metropolitan Magistrate or Judicial Magistrate of First
			<lb />
			Class may pass a sentence in excess of the powers under the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			28
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			CrPC. Section 36A provides that certain offences are to be
			<lb />
			tried summarily.
			<lb />
			18. Section 36AB provides for Special Courts. It declares
			<lb />
			that the Central Government or the State Government in
			<lb />
			consultation with the Chief Justice of the High Court,
			<lb />
			shall, for certain offences designate one or more Court of
			<lb />
			Sessions as a Special Court or Special Courts. Sub-section
			<lb />
			(2) provides that the Special Court may try an offence other
			<lb />
			than the offences covered by sub-section (1) which may be
			<lb />
			charged against the accused at the same trial. Section
			<lb />
			36AC around which much arguments were addressed reads as
			<lb />
			follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;36AC. Offences to be cognizable and
			<lb />
			non-bailable
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			certain
			<lb />
			cases.
			<lb />
			-
			<lb />
			(1) Notwithstanding anything contained in
			<lb />
			the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of
			<lb />
			1974),-
			<lb />
			(a) every offence, relating to adulterated
			<lb />
			or spurious drug and punishable under
			<lb />
			clauses (a) and (c) of sub-section (1) of
			<lb />
			section 13, clause (a) of sub-section (2) of
			<lb />
			section 13, sub-section (3) of section 22,
			<lb />
			clauses (a) and (c) of section 27, section
			<lb />
			28,
			<lb />
			section
			<lb />
			28A,
			<lb />
			section
			<lb />
			28B
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			29
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			sub-sections (1) and (2) of section 30 and
			<lb />
			other offences relating to adulterated
			<lb />
			drugs
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			spurious
			<lb />
			drugs,
			<lb />
			shall
			<lb />
			be
			<lb />
			cognizable.
			<lb />
			(b) no person accused, of an offence
			<lb />
			punishable under clauses (a) and (c) of
			<lb />
			sub-section (1) of section 13, clause (a) of
			<lb />
			sub-section (2) of section 13, sub-section
			<lb />
			(3) of section 22, clauses (a) and (c) of
			<lb />
			section 27, section 28, section 28A, section
			<lb />
			28B and sub-sections (1) and (2) of section
			<lb />
			30 and other offences relating to adulterated
			<lb />
			drugs or spurious drugs, shall be released on
			<lb />
			bail or on his own bond unless-
			<lb />
			(i) the Public Prosecutor has been given an
			<lb />
			opportunity to oppose the application for
			<lb />
			such release; and
			<lb />
			(ii) where the Public Prosecutor opposes the
			<lb />
			application, the Court is satisfied that
			<lb />
			there are reasonable grounds for believing
			<lb />
			that he is not guilty of such offence and that
			<lb />
			he is not likely to commit any offence while
			<lb />
			on bail:
			<lb />
			Provided that a person, who, is under the age
			<lb />
			of sixteen years, or is a woman or is sick or
			<lb />
			infirm, may be released on bail, if the
			<lb />
			Special Court so directs.
			<lb />
			(2) The limitation on granting of bail
			<lb />
			specified in clause (b) of sub-section (1) is
			<lb />
			in addition to the limitations under the Code
			<lb />
			of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) or any
			<lb />
			other law for the time being in force on
			<lb />
			granting of bail.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			30
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			(3) Nothing contained in this section shall
			<lb />
			be deemed to affect the special powers of the
			<lb />
			High Court regarding bail under section 439
			<lb />
			of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of
			<lb />
			1974) and the High Court may exercise such
			<lb />
			powers including the power under clause (b)
			<lb />
			of sub-section (1) of that section as if the
			<lb />
			reference to &quot;Magistrate&quot; in that section
			<lb />
			includes also a reference to a &quot;Special
			<lb />
			Court&quot; designated under section 36AB.&quot;
			<lb />
			Section 36AD also being relevant is referred to:
			<lb />
			&quot;36AD Application of Code of Criminal
			<lb />
			Procedure, 1973 to proceedings before
			<lb />
			Special Court. -
			<lb />
			(1) Save as otherwise provided in this Act,
			<lb />
			the provisions of the Code of Criminal
			<lb />
			Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) (including the
			<lb />
			provisions as to bails or bonds), shall apply
			<lb />
			to the proceedings before a Special Court and
			<lb />
			for the purposes of the said provisions, the
			<lb />
			Special Court shall be deemed to be a Court
			<lb />
			of Session and the person conducting the
			<lb />
			prosecution before the Special Court, shall
			<lb />
			be deemed to be a Public Prosecutor:
			<lb />
			Provided that the Central Government or the
			<lb />
			State Government may also appoint, for any
			<lb />
			case or class or group of cases, a Special
			<lb />
			Public Prosecutor.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			31
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			(2) A person shall not be qualified to be
			<lb />
			appointed as a Public Prosecutor or a Special
			<lb />
			Public Prosecutor under this section unless
			<lb />
			he has been in practice as an advocate for not
			<lb />
			less than seven years, under the Union or a
			<lb />
			State, requiring special knowledge of law.
			<lb />
			(3) Every person appointed as a Public
			<lb />
			Prosecutor or a Special Public Prosecutor
			<lb />
			under this section shall be deemed to be a
			<lb />
			Public Prosecutor within the meaning of
			<lb />
			clause (u) of section 2 of the Code of
			<lb />
			Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) and the
			<lb />
			provisions of that Code shall have effect
			<lb />
			accordingly.&quot;
			<lb />
			RELEVANT PROVISIONS OF THE CRPC
			<lb />
			19. Section 2(a) defines &quot;bailable offence&quot; as offence
			<lb />
			shown as such in the First Schedule, or which is made
			<lb />
			bailable under any other law for the time being in force.
			<lb />
			&quot;Non-bailable
			<lb />
			offence&quot;
			<lb />
			means
			<lb />
			any
			<lb />
			other
			<lb />
			offence.
			<lb />
			&apos;Cognizable offence&apos; is defined in Section 2(c). It reads
			<lb />
			as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;2(c) &quot; cognizable offence&quot; means an offence
			<lb />
			for which, and&quot; cognizable case&quot; means a case
			<lb />
			in which, a police officer may, in accordance
			<lb />
			with the First Schedule or under any other law
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			32
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			for the time being in force, arrest without
			<lb />
			warrant;&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			20. Section 2(d) defines &apos;complaint&apos;. It reads as
			<lb />
			follows:-
			<lb />
			&quot;2(d) &quot; complaint&quot; means any allegation made
			<lb />
			orally or in writing to a Magistrate, with a
			<lb />
			view to his taking action under this Code,
			<lb />
			that some person, whether known or unknown,
			<lb />
			has committed an offence, but does not
			<lb />
			include a police report.
			<lb />
			Explanation.-A report made by a police
			<lb />
			officer in a case which discloses, after
			<lb />
			investigation, the commission of a non-
			<lb />
			cognizable offence shall be deemed to be a
			<lb />
			complaint; and the police officer by whom
			<lb />
			such report is made shall be deemed to be the
			<lb />
			complainant;&quot;
			<lb />
			21. Section 2(h) defines investigation as
			<lb />
			follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;2(h)&quot;investigation&quot;
			<lb />
			includes
			<lb />
			all
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			proceedings under this Code for the
			<lb />
			collection of evidence conducted by a police
			<lb />
			officer or by any person (other than a
			<lb />
			Magistrate) who is authorised by a Magistrate
			<lb />
			in this behalf.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			33
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			22. &apos;Police report&apos; is defined in Section 2 (r) as meaning
			<lb />
			a report forwarded by a police officer to a Magistrate under
			<lb />
			sub-section (2) of Section 173. Sections 4 and 5 being
			<lb />
			relevant, we advert to the same.
			<lb />
			&quot;4. Trial of offences under the Indian Penal
			<lb />
			Code and other laws.-
			<lb />
			(1) All offences under the Indian Penal
			<lb />
			Code (45 of 1860 ) shall be investigated,
			<lb />
			inquired into, tried, and otherwise
			<lb />
			dealt with according to the provisions
			<lb />
			hereinafter contained.
			<lb />
			(2) All offences under any other law
			<lb />
			shall be investigated, inquired into,
			<lb />
			tried,
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			otherwise
			<lb />
			dealt
			<lb />
			with
			<lb />
			according to the same provisions, but
			<lb />
			subject to any enactment for the time
			<lb />
			being in force regulating the manner or
			<lb />
			place of investigating, inquiring into,
			<lb />
			trying or otherwise dealing with such
			<lb />
			offences.
			<lb />
			5. Saving.-Nothing contained in this Code
			<lb />
			shall, in the absence of a specific provision
			<lb />
			to the contrary, affect any special or local
			<lb />
			law for the time being in force, or any
			<lb />
			special jurisdiction or power conferred, or
			<lb />
			any special form of procedure prescribed, by
			<lb />
			any other law for the time being in force.&quot;
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			34
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			23. Chapter XII comes under the heading &apos;Information to the
			<lb />
			Police and their Powers to Investigate&apos;. Section 154 inter
			<lb />
			alia provides that every information relevant to the
			<lb />
			commission of a cognizable offence given orally to an
			<lb />
			officer in charge of a Police Station shall be reduced to
			<lb />
			writing by him or under his direction, and be read over to
			<lb />
			informant.
			<lb />
			Every such information whether given in
			<lb />
			writing or reduced to writing as aforesaid shall be signed
			<lb />
			by the person giving it. The substance of the same is to
			<lb />
			be entered in a book to be kept by such officer in such form
			<lb />
			as may be prescribed. Section 155 deals with information
			<lb />
			as to non-cognizable cases and the manner of investigation
			<lb />
			of such cases.
			<lb />
			No police officer can investigate a
			<lb />
			non-cognizable offence without the order of the Magistrate
			<lb />
			having power to try such case or commit such case for trial.
			<lb />
			Section 156 reads as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;156.
			<lb />
			Police
			<lb />
			officer&apos;s
			<lb />
			power
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			investigate cognizable case. -
			<lb />
			(1) Any officer in charge of a police station
			<lb />
			may, without the order of a Magistrate,
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			35
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			investigate any cognizable case which a Court
			<lb />
			having jurisdiction over the local area
			<lb />
			within the limits of such station would have
			<lb />
			power to inquire into or try under the
			<lb />
			provisions of Chapter XIII.
			<lb />
			(2) No proceeding of a police officer in any
			<lb />
			such case shall at any stage be called in
			<lb />
			question on the ground that the case was one
			<lb />
			which such officer was not empowered under
			<lb />
			this section to investigate.
			<lb />
			(3) Any Magistrate empowered under section
			<lb />
			190 may order such an investigation as
			<lb />
			above-mentioned&quot;.
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			24. Section 157 provides for Procedure for Investigation.
			<lb />
			The limitations for the use of the statement given under
			<lb />
			Section 161 are spelt out in Section 162. Section 173
			<lb />
			provides for the report to be given on completion of
			<lb />
			investigation.
			<lb />
			25. Chapter XIV deals with the &quot;Conditions requisite for
			<lb />
			Initiation of Proceedings&quot;. Section 190 reads as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;190.
			<lb />
			Cognizance
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			offences
			<lb />
			by
			<lb />
			Magistrates.-
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			36
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			(1) Subject to the provisions of this
			<lb />
			Chapter, any Magistrate of the first class,
			<lb />
			and any Magistrate of the second class
			<lb />
			specially empowered in this behalf under
			<lb />
			sub-section (2), may take cognizance of
			<lb />
			any offence-
			<lb />
			(a) upon receiving a complaint of facts
			<lb />
			which constitute such offence;
			<lb />
			(b) upon a police report of such facts;
			<lb />
			(c) upon information received from any
			<lb />
			person other than a police officer, or upon
			<lb />
			his own knowledge, that such offence has
			<lb />
			been committed.
			<lb />
			(2) The Chief Judicial Magistrate may
			<lb />
			empower any Magistrate of the second class
			<lb />
			to take cognizance under sub-section (1)
			<lb />
			of such offences as are within his
			<lb />
			competence to inquire into or try.&quot;
			<lb />
			26. Chapter XV deals with Complaints to Magistrates.
			<lb />
			Section 202 having been referred by the learned Amicus
			<lb />
			Curiae is extracted:
			<lb />
			&quot;202.
			<lb />
			Postponement
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			issue
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			process.-(1) Any Magistrate, on receipt of
			<lb />
			a complaint of an offence of which he is
			<lb />
			authorised to take cognizance or which has
			<lb />
			been made over to him under section 192,
			<lb />
			may, if he thinks fit, postpone the issue
			<lb />
			of process against the accused, and either
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			37
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			inquire into the case himself or direct an
			<lb />
			investigation to be made by a police
			<lb />
			officer or by such other person as he thinks
			<lb />
			fit, for the purpose of deciding whether or
			<lb />
			not there is sufficient ground for
			<lb />
			proceeding:
			<lb />
			Provided
			<lb />
			that
			<lb />
			no
			<lb />
			such
			<lb />
			direction for investigation shall be
			<lb />
			made,-
			<lb />
			(a) where it appears to the Magistrate that
			<lb />
			the offence complained of is triable
			<lb />
			exclusively by the Court of Session; or
			<lb />
			(b) where the complaint has not been made
			<lb />
			by a Court, unless the complainant and the
			<lb />
			witnesses present (if any) have been
			<lb />
			examined on oath under section 200.
			<lb />
			(2) In an inquiry under sub-section (1),
			<lb />
			the Magistrate may, if he thinks fit, take
			<lb />
			evidence of witnesses on oath:
			<lb />
			Provided that if it appears to the
			<lb />
			Magistrate that the offence complained of
			<lb />
			is triable exclusively by the Court of
			<lb />
			Session, he shall call upon the complainant
			<lb />
			to produce all his witnesses and examine
			<lb />
			them on oath.
			<lb />
			(3) If an investigation under sub-section
			<lb />
			(1) is made by a person not being a police
			<lb />
			officer,
			<lb />
			he
			<lb />
			shall
			<lb />
			have
			<lb />
			for
			<lb />
			that
			<lb />
			investigation all the powers conferred by
			<lb />
			this Code on an officer-in-charge of a
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			38
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			police station except the power to arrest
			<lb />
			without warrant.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			27. Chapter XVI comes under the chapter heading
			<lb />
			&quot;Commencement
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			Proceedings
			<lb />
			before
			<lb />
			Magistrates&quot;.
			<lb />
			Section 204 deals with &quot;Issue of Process&quot; in a case where
			<lb />
			the Magistrate taking cognizance is of the view that there
			<lb />
			is sufficient ground for proceeding in the matter. It may
			<lb />
			also be relevant to notice part II of the First Schedule
			<lb />
			to the CrPC. It must be remembered that cognizable offence
			<lb />
			has been defined in terms of the classification of the
			<lb />
			offences under the First Schedule. The first part of the
			<lb />
			First Schedule deals with offences under the Indian Penal
			<lb />
			Code.
			<lb />
			The second part, as it were, deals with
			<lb />
			classification of offences against other laws. It reads
			<lb />
			as follows:
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			40
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			in regard to offences under any law other than the IPC. The
			<lb />
			purport of Section 5 is this:
			<lb />
			If any special law or local law for the time
			<lb />
			being
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			force
			<lb />
			contemplates
			<lb />
			any
			<lb />
			special
			<lb />
			jurisdiction or power or any special form of
			<lb />
			procedure prescribed, unless there is something to
			<lb />
			the contrary, to be found, it is the provisions of
			<lb />
			the special law or the local law which would
			<lb />
			prevail.
			<lb />
			IMPACT OF SECTION 2 OF THE ACT
			<lb />
			29. We have noticed that Section 2 of the Act declares that
			<lb />
			the provisions of the Act shall be in addition to and not
			<lb />
			in derogation of the Dangerous Drugs Act 1930 and any other
			<lb />
			law for the time being in force. As far as Section (2) of
			<lb />
			the Act is concerned if the attempt of the appellant is to
			<lb />
			contend that it imports the provisions in CrPC which tends
			<lb />
			to overwhelm, in particular, any special procedure provided
			<lb />
			under the Act, we have no hesitation in repelling the same.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			41
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			The purport of Section 2 appears to be that Legislature
			<lb />
			intended to keep alive the provisions of the Dangerous Drugs
			<lb />
			Act, 1930. It would continue to hold sway despite the
			<lb />
			enactment of the Act. If there are any other provisions
			<lb />
			of cognate laws dealing with the subjects dealt with by the
			<lb />
			Act, the operation of those Acts was to be preserved. The
			<lb />
			Act does not provide for any express repeal of any
			<lb />
			enactment.
			<lb />
			Nothing further needs to be stated about
			<lb />
			Section 2 and we are of the view that it does not have any
			<lb />
			further repercussion on the issue at hand.
			<lb />
			SECTION 32 OF THE ACT
			<lb />
			30. Coming to Section 32 of the Act, as already noted by
			<lb />
			us it falls in chapter IV. Inspectors are appointed by the
			<lb />
			Central Government or the State Government from persons
			<lb />
			possessing prescribed qualifications under a notification.
			<lb />
			Section 21 contemplates prescribing under rules the powers
			<lb />
			which may be exercised by the Inspectors apart from the
			<lb />
			duties which may be performed by him inter alia.
			<lb />
			Section 22 of the Act provides for power of search by the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			42
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Inspectors. They have power to inspect any premise, take
			<lb />
			samples, powers of search, examine any record, register,
			<lb />
			material object and seize them. The Legislature has
			<lb />
			undoubtedly applied the provisions of the CrPC in regard
			<lb />
			to searches under the Act. Section 23 elaborately provides
			<lb />
			for procedure to be adopted by Inspectors.
			<lb />
			31. Section 32 falling under section heading &apos;Cognizance
			<lb />
			of offences&apos; declares, in unambiguous words, that
			<lb />
			prosecution, under Chapter IV, can be instituted only by
			<lb />
			(1) an Inspector (2)any gazetted officer of the Central
			<lb />
			Government or State Government authorised in writing by the
			<lb />
			respective Government by a general or special order made
			<lb />
			in this behalf by that Government (3) the person aggrieved
			<lb />
			(4) a recognised consumer association whether such person
			<lb />
			is a member of that association or not. Section 32 further
			<lb />
			proclaims that unless it is otherwise provided, no court
			<lb />
			inferior to a court of session shall try an offence
			<lb />
			punishable under Chapter IV. Section 32(3) makes it clear
			<lb />
			that nothing in chapter IV would stand in the way of the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			43
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			person being prosecuted against under any other law for any
			<lb />
			act or omission which constitutes an offence against this
			<lb />
			Chapter. Section 32 was substituted by Act 22 of 2008.
			<lb />
			Prior to the substitution it read as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;32 Cognizance of offences. -(1) No
			<lb />
			prosecution under this Chapter shall be
			<lb />
			instituted except by an Inspector or by the
			<lb />
			person aggrieved or by a recognised consumer
			<lb />
			association whether such person is a member of
			<lb />
			that association or not.
			<lb />
			(2) No court inferior to that of a Metropolitan
			<lb />
			Magistrate or of a Judicial Magistrate of the
			<lb />
			first class shall try an offence punishable
			<lb />
			under this Chapter.
			<lb />
			(3) Nothing contained in this Chapter shall be
			<lb />
			deemed to prevent any person from being
			<lb />
			prosecuted under any other law for any act or
			<lb />
			omission which constitutes an offence against
			<lb />
			this Chapter.&quot;
			<lb />
			32. It will be noticed at once that Section 190 of the CrPC
			<lb />
			also has a title &apos;Cognizance of Offence by Magistrate&apos;.
			<lb />
			Cognizance under Section 190 is contemplated in three
			<lb />
			different modes.
			<lb />
			They are -(1) complaints of facts
			<lb />
			constituting such offences, (2) police report of such
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			44
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			facts, (3) upon any information received from a person other
			<lb />
			than a Police Officer or upon a court being possessed of
			<lb />
			knowledge about the commission of the offence. In other
			<lb />
			words, where the court takes cognizance suo motu. A
			<lb />
			comparison between Section 32 of the Act and 190 of the CrPC
			<lb />
			dealing with cognizance of offences, makes it abundantly
			<lb />
			clear that the Law Giver has provided for distinct modes
			<lb />
			in regard to prosecuting of the offences under the general
			<lb />
			law, viz., the CrPC and the special provision, as contained
			<lb />
			in Section 32 of the Act.
			<lb />
			33. Section 193 of the CrPC reads as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;193. Cognizance of offences by Courts of
			<lb />
			Session. Except as otherwise expressly
			<lb />
			provided by this Code or by any other law
			<lb />
			for the time being in force, no Court of
			<lb />
			Session shall take cognizance of any
			<lb />
			offence as a Court of original jurisdiction
			<lb />
			unless the case has been committed to it by
			<lb />
			a Magistrate under this Code.&quot;
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			45
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			34. Section 195 prohibits the Court from taking any
			<lb />
			cognizance of the offences mentioned therein except on the
			<lb />
			complaint in writing by the persons named therein.
			<lb />
			35. Section 198A and Section 199 likewise permit the courts
			<lb />
			to take cognizance only upon the complaint made by the
			<lb />
			persons mentioned therein. Similarly, Section 199 taboos
			<lb />
			cognizance of offence of defamation except on the complaint
			<lb />
			made by some aggrieved person.
			<lb />
			36. Section 36AD of the Act applies the provisions of the
			<lb />
			CrPC except where it is otherwise provided in the Act in
			<lb />
			regard to the proceedings before the Special Court and the
			<lb />
			Special Court is deemed to be the Court of Sessions and the
			<lb />
			person conducting the prosecution is deemed to be the Public
			<lb />
			Prosecutor. No doubt, the proviso empowers the Central
			<lb />
			Government or the State Government to appoint for any case
			<lb />
			or class or group of cases, a Special Public Prosecutor.
			<lb />
			37. The Scheme of the Act must be borne in mind when Section
			<lb />
			32, which provides, inter alia, that an Inspector can set
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			46
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			the ball rolling, is considered. The Inspectors, under the
			<lb />
			Act, are to possess the prescribed qualifications. The
			<lb />
			qualifications bear a nexus with the performance of the
			<lb />
			specialised duties which are to be performed under the Act.
			<lb />
			Apparently, knowledge about the drugs and cosmetics goes
			<lb />
			a long way in equipping them to perform their multifarious
			<lb />
			functions. Section 22 clothing the Inspector with powers
			<lb />
			must also be viewed thus in the context of the legislative
			<lb />
			value judgment that a complaint is to be moved by the
			<lb />
			Inspector under the Act and not by a Police Officer under
			<lb />
			the CrPC. The Inspector is expected to inspect premises
			<lb />
			where drugs and cosmetics are being manufactured, sold,
			<lb />
			stocked, exhibited, offered for sale or distributed.
			<lb />
			Samples are to be taken at the points of manufacturing,
			<lb />
			selling, stocking and the points of delivery. He is expected
			<lb />
			also, where he has reason to believe that an offence under
			<lb />
			the Act has been committed, to search any person, enter any
			<lb />
			place, stop and search any vehicle, examine records, and
			<lb />
			documents and seize the same. Last but not the least,
			<lb />
			Section 22(1)(d) declares that he may exercise other powers
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			47
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			as may be necessary for carrying the purposes of Chapter
			<lb />
			IV or any Rules made thereunder. The elaborate procedure
			<lb />
			to be followed by the Inspectors is also provided by the
			<lb />
			law.
			<lb />
			38. Section 26 of the Drugs and Cosmetics Act, 1940, reads
			<lb />
			as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;26. Purchaser of drug or cosmetic
			<lb />
			enabled to obtain test or analysis.-Any
			<lb />
			person
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			any
			<lb />
			recognised
			<lb />
			consumer
			<lb />
			association, whether such person is a
			<lb />
			member of that association or not shall, on
			<lb />
			application in the prescribed manner and on
			<lb />
			payment of the prescribed fee, be entitled
			<lb />
			to submit for test or analysis to a
			<lb />
			Government Analyst any drug or cosmetic
			<lb />
			purchased by him or it and to receive a
			<lb />
			report of such test or analysis signed by
			<lb />
			the Government Analyst.
			<lb />
			Explanation.-For the purposes of this
			<lb />
			section and section 32, &quot;recognised
			<lb />
			consumer association&quot; means a voluntary
			<lb />
			consumer association registered under the
			<lb />
			Companies Act, 1956 or any other law for the
			<lb />
			time being in force.&quot;
			<lb />
			39. A perusal of the same would indicate the role which
			<lb />
			is assigned to any person and recognized consumer
			<lb />
			association within the meaning of Section 32. Section 26
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			48
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			of the Drugs and Cosmetics Act, 1940 declares that on the
			<lb />
			application, any person or any recognized consumer
			<lb />
			association, in the prescribed manner and on payment of
			<lb />
			prescribed fee, is entitled to submit for test or analysis,
			<lb />
			to a Government Analyst any drug or cosmetic purchased by
			<lb />
			the person or the association and to receive a report of
			<lb />
			such test or analysis signed by the Government Analyst.
			<lb />
			There can be no gainsaying that armed with a report which
			<lb />
			reveals the commission of an offence under Chapter IV of
			<lb />
			the Act, they can invoke Section 32 and prosecute the
			<lb />
			offender.
			<lb />
			40. Section 32 of the Act undoubtedly provides for taking
			<lb />
			cognizance of the offence by the court only at the instance
			<lb />
			of the four categories mentioned therein. They are: (a)
			<lb />
			Inspector under the Act; (b) Any Gazetted Officer empowered
			<lb />
			by the Central or the State Government; (c) Aggrieved
			<lb />
			person; and (d) Voluntary Association. It is clear that the
			<lb />
			Legislature has not included the Police Officer as a person
			<lb />
			who can move the court. Before the matter reaches the court,
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			49
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			under Section 190 of the CrPC, ordinarily starting with the
			<lb />
			lodging of the first information report leading to the
			<lb />
			registration
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			first
			<lb />
			information
			<lb />
			report,
			<lb />
			investigation is carried out culminating in a report under
			<lb />
			Section 173. The Police Report, in fact, is the Report
			<lb />
			submitted under Section 173 of the CrPC to the court. Under
			<lb />
			Section 190 of the CrPC, the court may take cognizance on
			<lb />
			the basis of the police report. Such a procedure is alien
			<lb />
			to Section 32 of the Act. In other words, it is not open
			<lb />
			to the Police Officer to submit a report under Section 173
			<lb />
			of the CrPC in regard to an offence under Chapter IV of the
			<lb />
			Act under Section 32. In regard to offences contemplated
			<lb />
			under Section 32(3), the Police Officer may have power as
			<lb />
			per the concerned provisions. Being a special enactment,
			<lb />
			the manner of dealing with the offences under the Act, would
			<lb />
			be governed by the provisions of the Act. It is to be noted
			<lb />
			that Section 32 declares that no court inferior to the Court
			<lb />
			of Sessions shall try offence punishable under Chapter IV.
			<lb />
			We have noticed that under Section 193 of the CrPC, no Court
			<lb />
			of Sessions can take cognizance of any offence as a Court
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			50
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			of Original Jurisdiction unless the case has been committed
			<lb />
			to it by a Magistrate under the CrPC. This is, undoubtedly,
			<lb />
			subject to the law providing expressly that that Court of
			<lb />
			Sessions may take cognizance of any offence as the Court
			<lb />
			of Original Jurisdiction. There is no provision in the Act
			<lb />
			which expressly authorises the special court which is the
			<lb />
			Court of Sessions to take cognizance of the offence under
			<lb />
			Chapter IV. This means that the provisions of Chapters XV
			<lb />
			and XVI of the CrPC must be followed in regard to even
			<lb />
			offences falling under Chapter IV of the Act. Starting with
			<lb />
			Section 200 of the Act dealing with taking of cognizance
			<lb />
			by a Magistrate on a complaint, including examination of
			<lb />
			the witnesses produced by the complainant, the dismissal
			<lb />
			of an unworthy complaint under Section 203 and following
			<lb />
			the procedure under Section 202 in the case of postponement
			<lb />
			of issue of process are all steps to be followed. It is true
			<lb />
			that when the complaint under Section 32 is filed either
			<lb />
			by the Inspector or by the Authorised Gazetted Officer being
			<lb />
			public servants under Section 200, the Magistrate is
			<lb />
			exempted from examining the complainant and witnesses.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			51
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			41. The learned Amicus Curiae, when queried about the
			<lb />
			procedure to be adopted when a complaint is lodged by
			<lb />
			persons falling in Section 32(C) and (d), viz., the
			<lb />
			aggrieved person or a voluntary association, it was
			<lb />
			submitted that the Magistrate can, under Section 202 of the
			<lb />
			CrPC, order an investigation by the Police Officer or any
			<lb />
			other person. A perusal of Section 202 would show that in
			<lb />
			regard to an offence falling under Chapter IV of the Act,
			<lb />
			being exclusively triable, by a Court of Sessions, the
			<lb />
			proviso to sub-Section (1) to Section 202 prohibits the
			<lb />
			direction for investigation under Section 202. The proviso
			<lb />
			to sub-Section (2) of Section 202 contemplates that when
			<lb />
			an offence is exclusively triable by the Court of Sessions,
			<lb />
			and the Magistrate proceeds under Section 202 of the CrPC,
			<lb />
			he is duty bound to call upon the complainant to produce
			<lb />
			all its witnesses and examine them on oath. Thus, the effect
			<lb />
			of the two provisions in sub-Sections (1) and (2),
			<lb />
			respectively, is as follows:
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			52
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			A Magistrate proceeding under Section 202 of the CrPC,
			<lb />
			is subjected to two conditions:
			<lb />
			a. Unlike in an ordinary case, meaning thereby, an
			<lb />
			offence which is not exclusively triable by a Court
			<lb />
			of Sessions, in a case where it is an offence
			<lb />
			exclusively triable by a Court of Sessions, the
			<lb />
			inquiry can be conducted only by a Magistrate
			<lb />
			himself. It is not open to him to cause an
			<lb />
			investigation be it by a Police Officer or any
			<lb />
			other person.
			<lb />
			b. In regard to the inquiry so conducted by him, he
			<lb />
			must call upon the complainant to produce all his
			<lb />
			witnesses and they must be examined not on the
			<lb />
			basis of any affidavit, and not without the support
			<lb />
			of an oath but the examination must be under an
			<lb />
			oath. It is to be remembered that under the
			<lb />
			provisions existing under the previous Code, an
			<lb />
			elaborate preliminary inquiry where even an
			<lb />
			accused had right of cross-examination of
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			53
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			witnesses, was contemplated at the hands of the
			<lb />
			Magistrate before the committal order was passed.
			<lb />
			This no longer survives after the amendment.
			<lb />
			42. Offences exclusively triable by a Court of Sessions are
			<lb />
			ordinarily pursued on the strength of a Police Report. The
			<lb />
			Police Officer examines witnesses under Section 161 of the
			<lb />
			CrPC, collects other evidence, arrives at a satisfaction
			<lb />
			that indeed a case is made out to arraign a person or persons
			<lb />
			and, accordingly, the charge-sheet is filed under Section
			<lb />
			173. Section 207 of the Code contemplates making available
			<lb />
			statements of all the witnesses examined among other
			<lb />
			documents to be made available to the accused as provided
			<lb />
			therein. This prepares the accused for the case he is likely
			<lb />
			to be called upon to meet in the Court of Sessions.
			<lb />
			43. As far as a complainant setting the criminal law in
			<lb />
			motion is concerned, what is contemplated is that by the
			<lb />
			mechanism of cognizance under Section 200 read with Section
			<lb />
			202, culminating in the issuance of summons or warrant under
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			54
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Section 204, there is material before the Magistrate and
			<lb />
			the court is assured that the case is not frivolous and
			<lb />
			wholly meritless going by a prima facie view undoubtedly
			<lb />
			as contemplated in law at that stage regarding the
			<lb />
			commission of a cognizance offence. Apart from this,
			<lb />
			reassuring aspect, as in a prosecution launched under
			<lb />
			Police Report, the accused in a trial by a Court of Sessions
			<lb />
			to which Court a case would stand committed under Section
			<lb />
			209, would also know beforehand the case he would have to
			<lb />
			meet having regard to the materials which weighed with the
			<lb />
			Magistrate and which is also made available to him under
			<lb />
			Section 208 of the Act. In such circumstances, we need not
			<lb />
			consider further the argument of the learned Amicus Curiae
			<lb />
			that a direction for investigation by the Magistrate under
			<lb />
			Section 202 would not be tabooed as the result of the
			<lb />
			investigation by the Police Officer pursuant to a direction
			<lb />
			would not amount to a report under Section 173. This is for
			<lb />
			the reason that being offences exclusively triable by the
			<lb />
			Court of Sessions, as noticed earlier, there is a bar
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			55
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			against the Magistrate directing investigation under
			<lb />
			Section 202 by the Police Officer or otherwise.
			<lb />
			44. The learned Amicus Curiae submitted that the
			<lb />
			registering of an FIR under Section 154 of the CrPC in regard
			<lb />
			to reference under Chapter IV of the Act is a futile
			<lb />
			exercise. It is his submission that the filing of the First
			<lb />
			Information Statement (FIS) (We notice his complaint that
			<lb />
			even courts refer to the FIS as the complaint whereas a
			<lb />
			complaint is what is contemplated under Section 190 of the
			<lb />
			CrPC which is filed before a court) constitutes information
			<lb />
			provided under Section 154 before a Station House Officer
			<lb />
			In-Charge of Police Station which activises the Officer and
			<lb />
			he investigates the matter with the object of filing a
			<lb />
			report under Section 173 which is also described as
			<lb />
			charge-sheet in a case where the Officer finds that an
			<lb />
			offence has been committed. It is named a final report where
			<lb />
			no basis is found for prosecution. On the strength of the
			<lb />
			same, he invites the court concerned to take cognizance.
			<lb />
			If under Section 32 of the Act, the Police Officer has no
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			56
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			authority to file a report, he questions the actions of the
			<lb />
			Police Officer as one which is bound to die a natural death.
			<lb />
			He would submit that declaring certain offences under
			<lb />
			Section 36AC cognisable, is only to empower the arrest of
			<lb />
			the accused.
			<lb />
			45. It may be noticed at this juncture, that the Act does
			<lb />
			contemplate arrest. Section 36AC clearly declares that
			<lb />
			certain offences are non-bailable. Section 36AC(b)
			<lb />
			proclaims that no person accused of the offences mentioned
			<lb />
			therein shall be released on bail or on his own bond unless
			<lb />
			the Public Prosecutor has been given an opportunity to
			<lb />
			oppose the application of such release and where the Public
			<lb />
			Prosecutor opposes, the court is satisfied that there are
			<lb />
			reasonable ground for believing that he is not guilty of
			<lb />
			such offence and that he is not likely to commit any offence
			<lb />
			while on bail. This limitation on the grant of bail is in
			<lb />
			addition to the limitations under the CrPC or and under any
			<lb />
			other law for the time being in force on grant of bail. The
			<lb />
			special powers, however, of the High Court regarding the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			57
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			grant of bail under Section 439 of the CrPC, is preserved
			<lb />
			as found therein.
			<lb />
			46. The argument of Ms. Pinky Anand, learned Additional
			<lb />
			Solicitor General is that having regard to the fact that
			<lb />
			certain offences under Section 36AC have been declared
			<lb />
			cognizable, the powers of the police under the CrPC
			<lb />
			including the duty to register a FIR under Section 154
			<lb />
			cannot be obviated. The only prohibition is against the
			<lb />
			Police Officer lodging the charge sheet. There can be no
			<lb />
			taboo on the Police Officer registering the FIR and even
			<lb />
			conducting the investigation. This brings up another issue,
			<lb />
			who is the person who can arrest a person accused of an
			<lb />
			offence in Chapter IV of the Act? Is it open to a Police
			<lb />
			Officer acting under the CrPC to arrest such person? Is the
			<lb />
			Inspector under the Act empowered to arrest a person accused
			<lb />
			of an offence under Chapter IV of the Act? Before we deal
			<lb />
			with this aspect, we may look at how this Court spoke in
			<lb />
			the past in the matter of taking cognizance among other
			<lb />
			aspects.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			58
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			A LOOK AT HOW THIS COURT SPOKE IN THE PAST
			<lb />
			47. In Jeewan Kumar Raut and another v. Central Bureau of
			<lb />
			Investigation 3 , the case arose under the Transplantation of
			<lb />
			Human Organs Act, 1994 (TOHO Act). Section 22 of this Act
			<lb />
			reads as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;22. Cognizance of offence.-
			<lb />
			(1) No court shall take cognizance of an
			<lb />
			offence under this Act except on a complaint
			<lb />
			made by-
			<lb />
			(a) the Appropriate Authority concerned, or
			<lb />
			any officer authorised in this behalf by the
			<lb />
			Central Government or the State Government
			<lb />
			or, as the case may be, the Appropriate
			<lb />
			Authority; or
			<lb />
			(b) a person who has given notice of not less
			<lb />
			than sixty days, in such manner as may be
			<lb />
			prescribed, to the Appropriate Authority
			<lb />
			concerned, of the alleged offence and of his
			<lb />
			intention to make a complaint to the court.
			<lb />
			(2) No court
			<lb />
			other
			<lb />
			than that of a
			<lb />
			Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial
			<lb />
			Magistrate of the first class shall try any
			<lb />
			offence punishable under this Act.
			<lb />
			(3) Where a complaint has been made under
			<lb />
			clause (b) of sub-section (1), the court may,
			<lb />
			on demand by such person, direct the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			3 (2009) 7 SCC 526
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			59
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Appropriate Authority to make available
			<lb />
			copies of the relevant records in its
			<lb />
			possession to such person.&quot;
			<lb />
			48. The appellants were Medical Practitioners. An FIR was
			<lb />
			registered against them under Section 420 of the IPC and
			<lb />
			Sections 18 and 19 of the TOHO Act at the Police Station.
			<lb />
			The investigation was transferred to the CBI, respondent
			<lb />
			in the case. The CBI registered another FIR which included
			<lb />
			Sections 18 and 19 of the TOHO Act. Appellant no.2 was
			<lb />
			arrested and produced before the Magistrate. Appellant no.1
			<lb />
			surrendered. The respondent filed a complaint under Section
			<lb />
			22 of TOHO Act pointing out that the period of 90 days from
			<lb />
			the detention expired on 07.05.2008, Appellant no.2 filed
			<lb />
			an application for grant of bail within the meaning of
			<lb />
			Section 167(2) of the CrPC. It was, while considering the
			<lb />
			same, this Court held, inter alia, as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;19. TOHO is a special Act. It deals with
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			subjects mentioned
			<lb />
			therein, viz.
			<lb />
			offences relating to removal of human organs,
			<lb />
			etc. Having regard to the importance of the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			60
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			subject only, enactment of the said
			<lb />
			regulatory statute was imperative.
			<lb />
			20. TOHO provides for appointment of an
			<lb />
			appropriate authority to deal with the
			<lb />
			matters specified in sub-section (3) of
			<lb />
			Section 13 thereof. By reason of the
			<lb />
			aforementioned provision, an appropriate
			<lb />
			authority has specifically been authorised
			<lb />
			inter alia to investigate any complaint of
			<lb />
			the breach of any of the provisions of TOHO
			<lb />
			or any of the rules made thereunder and take
			<lb />
			appropriate
			<lb />
			action.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			appropriate
			<lb />
			authority, subject to exceptions provided
			<lb />
			for in TOHO, thus, is only authorised to
			<lb />
			investigate cases of breach of any of the
			<lb />
			provisions
			<lb />
			thereof,
			<lb />
			whether
			<lb />
			penal
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			otherwise.
			<lb />
			21. Ordinarily, any person can set the
			<lb />
			criminal law in motion. Parliament and the
			<lb />
			State Legislatures, however, keeping in view
			<lb />
			the sensitivity and/or importance of the
			<lb />
			subject, have carved out specific areas where
			<lb />
			violations of any of the provisions of a
			<lb />
			special statute like TOHO can be dealt with
			<lb />
			only by the authorities specified therein.
			<lb />
			The FIR lodged before the officer in charge
			<lb />
			of Gurgaon Police Station was by way of
			<lb />
			information.
			<lb />
			It
			<lb />
			disclosed
			<lb />
			not
			<lb />
			only
			<lb />
			commission of an offence under TOHO but also
			<lb />
			under various provisions of the Penal Code.
			<lb />
			The officer in charge of the police station,
			<lb />
			however,
			<lb />
			was
			<lb />
			not
			<lb />
			authorised
			<lb />
			by
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			61
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			appropriate Government to deal with the
			<lb />
			matter in relation to TOHO; but, the
			<lb />
			respondent was. In that view of the matter,
			<lb />
			the investigation of the said complaint was
			<lb />
			handed over to it.
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			23. TOHO being a special Act and the matter
			<lb />
			relating to dealing with offences thereunder
			<lb />
			having been regulated by reason of the
			<lb />
			provisions thereof, there cannot be any
			<lb />
			manner of doubt whatsoever that the same
			<lb />
			shall prevail over the provisions of the
			<lb />
			Code. The investigation in terms of Section
			<lb />
			13(3)(iv) of TOHO, thus, must be conducted by
			<lb />
			an authorised officer. Nobody else could do
			<lb />
			it. For the aforementioned reasons, the
			<lb />
			officer in charge of Gurgaon Police Station
			<lb />
			had no other option but to hand over the
			<lb />
			investigation to the appropriate authority.
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			25. Section 22 of TOHO prohibits taking of
			<lb />
			cognizance except on a complaint made by an
			<lb />
			appropriate authority or the person who had
			<lb />
			made a complaint earlier to it as laid down
			<lb />
			therein. The respondent, although, has all
			<lb />
			the powers of an investigating agency, it
			<lb />
			expressly has been statutorily prohibited
			<lb />
			from filing a police report. It could file a
			<lb />
			complaint petition only as an appropriate
			<lb />
			authority so as to comply with the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			62
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			requirements contained in Section 22 of TOHO.
			<lb />
			If by reason of the provisions of TOHO, filing
			<lb />
			of a police report by necessary implication
			<lb />
			is necessarily forbidden, the question of its
			<lb />
			submitting a report in terms of sub-section
			<lb />
			(2) of Section 173 of the Code did not and
			<lb />
			could not arise. In other words, if no police
			<lb />
			report could be filed, sub-section (2) of
			<lb />
			Section 167 of the Code was not attracted.
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			28. To put it differently, upon completion
			<lb />
			of the investigation, an authorised officer
			<lb />
			could only file a complaint and not a police
			<lb />
			report, as a specific bar has been created by
			<lb />
			Parliament. In that view of the matter, the
			<lb />
			police report being not a complaint and vice
			<lb />
			versa, it was obligatory on the part of the
			<lb />
			respondent to choose the said method invoking
			<lb />
			the jurisdiction of the Magistrate concerned
			<lb />
			for taking cognizance of the offence only in
			<lb />
			the manner laid down therein and not by any
			<lb />
			other mode. The procedure laid down in TOHO,
			<lb />
			thus, would permit the respondent to file a
			<lb />
			complaint and not a report which course of
			<lb />
			action could have been taken recourse to but
			<lb />
			for the special provisions contained in
			<lb />
			Section 22 of TOHO.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			63
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			49. We may also notice the hope expressed by the Court for
			<lb />
			Parliamentary intervention expressing doubt about the
			<lb />
			absence of power to arrest with the Officer who is
			<lb />
			authorised to carry out the investigation:
			<lb />
			&quot;37. In the present case, however, the
			<lb />
			respondent having specially been empowered
			<lb />
			both under the 1946 Act as also under the Code
			<lb />
			to carry out investigation and file a
			<lb />
			charge-sheet is precluded from doing so only
			<lb />
			by reason of Section 22 of TOHO. It is
			<lb />
			doubtful as to whether in the event of
			<lb />
			authorisation of an officer of the Department
			<lb />
			to carry out investigation on a complaint
			<lb />
			made by a third party, he would be entitled
			<lb />
			to arrest the accused and carry on
			<lb />
			investigation as if he is a police officer.
			<lb />
			We
			<lb />
			hope
			<lb />
			that
			<lb />
			Parliament
			<lb />
			would
			<lb />
			take
			<lb />
			appropriate measures to suitably amend the
			<lb />
			law in the near future.&quot;
			<lb />
			50. In Jamiruddin
			<lb />
			Ansari
			<lb />
			v.
			<lb />
			Central
			<lb />
			Bureau
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			Investigation and another 4 , the case arose under the
			<lb />
			Maharashtra Control of Organized Crime Act, 1999 (MCOCA).
			<lb />
			A private complaint was filed against certain accused
			<lb />
			persons by a person. The Special Judge ordered the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			4 (2009) 6 SCC 316
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			64
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Commissioner of Police to investigate into the complaint
			<lb />
			under Section 156(3) of the CrPC. The State took the stand
			<lb />
			in a Writ Petition challenging the said order that in view
			<lb />
			of Sections 23(2) of the MCOCA sans previous sanction as
			<lb />
			contemplated therein, the Court could not take cognizance.
			<lb />
			It is necessary to advert to Sections 9 and 23 of the said
			<lb />
			Act. Sections (9) inter alia and 23 of MCOCA reads as
			<lb />
			follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;9. Procedure and powers of Special
			<lb />
			Court.-(1) A Special Court may take
			<lb />
			cognizance of any offence without the accused
			<lb />
			being committed to it for trial, upon
			<lb />
			receiving a complaint of facts which
			<lb />
			constitute such offence or upon a police
			<lb />
			report of such facts.
			<lb />
			(2)-(3)***
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			&quot;23. Cognizance of, and investigation
			<lb />
			into,
			<lb />
			an
			<lb />
			offence.-(1)
			<lb />
			Notwithstanding
			<lb />
			anything contained in the Code,-
			<lb />
			(a)
			<lb />
			no
			<lb />
			information
			<lb />
			about
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			commission of an offence of organised
			<lb />
			crime under this Act, shall be recorded
			<lb />
			by a police officer without the prior
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			65
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			approval of the police officer not below
			<lb />
			the rank of the Deputy Inspector General
			<lb />
			of Police;
			<lb />
			(b) no investigation of an offence
			<lb />
			under the provisions of this Act shall
			<lb />
			be carried out by a police officer below
			<lb />
			the rank of the Deputy Superintendent of
			<lb />
			Police.
			<lb />
			(2) No Special Court shall take cognizance of
			<lb />
			any offence under this Act without the
			<lb />
			previous sanction of the police officer not
			<lb />
			below the rank of Additional Director General
			<lb />
			of Police.&quot;
			<lb />
			51. The Full Bench which was constituted to hear the
			<lb />
			matter, by a majority, took the view that a private
			<lb />
			complaint under Section 9, was not trammelled by the
			<lb />
			requirement under Section 23. This Court held, inter alia,
			<lb />
			as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;67. We are also inclined to hold that in view
			<lb />
			of the provisions of Section 25 of MCOCA, the
			<lb />
			provisions of the said Act would have an
			<lb />
			overriding effect over the provisions of the
			<lb />
			Criminal Procedure Code and the learned
			<lb />
			Special Judge would not, therefore, be
			<lb />
			entitled to invoke the provisions of Section
			<lb />
			156(3) CrPC for ordering a special inquiry on
			<lb />
			a private complaint and taking cognizance
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			66
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			thereupon, without traversing the route
			<lb />
			indicated in Section 23 of MCOCA. In other
			<lb />
			words, even on a private complaint about the
			<lb />
			commission of an offence of organised crime
			<lb />
			under MCOCA cognizance cannot be taken by the
			<lb />
			Special Judge without due compliance with
			<lb />
			sub-section (1) of Section 23, which starts
			<lb />
			with a non obstante clause.
			<lb />
			68. As indicated hereinabove, the provisions
			<lb />
			of Section 23 are the safeguards provided
			<lb />
			against the invocation of the provisions of
			<lb />
			the Act which are extremely stringent and far
			<lb />
			removed from the provisions of the general
			<lb />
			criminal law. If, as submitted on behalf of
			<lb />
			some of the respondents, it is accepted that
			<lb />
			a private complaint under Section 9(1) is not
			<lb />
			subject to the rigours of Section 23, then the
			<lb />
			very purpose of introducing such safeguards
			<lb />
			lose their very raison d&apos;tre. At the same
			<lb />
			time, since the filing of a private complaint
			<lb />
			is also contemplated under Section 9(1)
			<lb />
			of MCOCA, for it to be entertained it has also
			<lb />
			to be subject to the rigours of Section 23.
			<lb />
			Accordingly, in view of the bar imposed under
			<lb />
			sub-section (2) of Section 23 of the Act, the
			<lb />
			learned Special Judge is precluded from
			<lb />
			taking cognizance on a private complaint upon
			<lb />
			a separate inquiry under Section 156(3) CrPC.
			<lb />
			The bar of Section 23(2) continues to remain
			<lb />
			in respect of complaints, either of a private
			<lb />
			nature or on a police report.&quot;
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			67
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			52. Thereafter, the Court proceeded to harmonise the
			<lb />
			provisions by holding as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;69. In order to give a harmonious
			<lb />
			construction to the provisions of Section
			<lb />
			9(1) and Section 23 of MCOCA, upon receipt of
			<lb />
			such private complaint the learned Special
			<lb />
			Judge has to forward the same to the officer
			<lb />
			indicated in clause (a) of sub-section (1) of
			<lb />
			Section 23 to have an inquiry conducted into
			<lb />
			the complaint by a police officer indicated
			<lb />
			in clause (b) of sub-section (1) and only
			<lb />
			thereafter take cognizance of the offence
			<lb />
			complained of, if sanction is accorded to the
			<lb />
			Special Court to take cognizance of such
			<lb />
			offence under sub-section (2) of Section 23.&quot;
			<lb />
			53. It is pertinent to notice that in the said enactment,
			<lb />
			under Section 23, there was a taboo against recording of
			<lb />
			any information under the Act without the prior approval
			<lb />
			of the Police Officer not below the rank of the Deputy
			<lb />
			Inspector General of Police. This must be understood as
			<lb />
			supplanting the provisions of Section 154 of the CrPC to
			<lb />
			the extent that the modification was spelt out. Not only
			<lb />
			could the information not be so recorded without the prior
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			68
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			approval, investigation also cannot be carried out except
			<lb />
			by a Police Officer of the rank of Deputy Superintendent
			<lb />
			of Police and above. This is apart from the prohibition
			<lb />
			against taking cognizance of an offence under the said Act
			<lb />
			without the previous sanction of the Police Officer not
			<lb />
			below the rank of Additional Director General of Police.
			<lb />
			54. The decision of this Court in H.N. Rishbud and Inder
			<lb />
			Singh v. State of Delhi, ETC. 5 dealt with a case under the
			<lb />
			Prevention of Corruption Act, 1947. Investigation in the
			<lb />
			said case was undertaken by an Officer without
			<lb />
			authorisation by the Magistrate under Section 5(4) of the
			<lb />
			Prevention of Corruption Act, 1947. Cognizance was taken
			<lb />
			and the trial went on. The accused thereupon pointed out
			<lb />
			the flaw in the investigation. It is in the said
			<lb />
			circumstances, this Court proceeded to deal with what is
			<lb />
			investigation, inter alia:
			<lb />
			&quot;8.  Thus, under the Code investigation
			<lb />
			consists generally of the following steps:
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			5 AIR 1955 SC 196
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			69
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			(1) Proceeding to the spot, (2) Ascertainment
			<lb />
			of the facts and circumstances of the case,
			<lb />
			(3) Discovery and arrest of the suspected
			<lb />
			offender,
			<lb />
			(4)
			<lb />
			Collection
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			evidence
			<lb />
			relating to the commission of the offence
			<lb />
			which may consist of (a) the examination of
			<lb />
			various persons (including the accused) and
			<lb />
			the reduction of their statements into
			<lb />
			writing, if the officer thinks fit, (b) the
			<lb />
			search of places or seizure of things
			<lb />
			considered necessary for the investigation
			<lb />
			and to be produced at the trial, and (5)
			<lb />
			Formation of the opinion as to whether on the
			<lb />
			material collected there is a case to place
			<lb />
			the accused before a Magistrate for trial and
			<lb />
			if so taking the necessary steps for the same
			<lb />
			by the filing of a charge-sheet under Section
			<lb />
			173. &quot;
			<lb />
			55. No doubt, the Court went on to take the view that the
			<lb />
			invalidity of the investigation, if brought to the
			<lb />
			knowledge of the Court at a sufficiently early stage,
			<lb />
			remedial steps may be taken to get the illegality cured.
			<lb />
			However, it was found that if cognizance is taken on a Police
			<lb />
			Report vitiated by the breach of a mandatory provision
			<lb />
			relating to investigation, the result of the trial cannot
			<lb />
			be affected unless it has resulted in a miscarriage of
			<lb />
			justice. It is pertinent to note that the Court made the
			<lb />
			following observations as well:
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			70
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			&quot;9.  Here we are not concerned with the
			<lb />
			effect of the breach of a mandatory provision
			<lb />
			regulating the competence or procedure of the
			<lb />
			Court as regards cognizance or trial. It is
			<lb />
			only with reference to such a breach that the
			<lb />
			question as to whether it constitutes an
			<lb />
			illegality vitiating the proceedings or a
			<lb />
			mere irregularity arises.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			56. In Institute of Chartered Accountants of India v. Vimal
			<lb />
			Kumar Surana and another 6 , the matter arose under the
			<lb />
			Chartered Accounts Act, 1949. The respondent, who had
			<lb />
			passed the examination of Chartered Accountant but was not
			<lb />
			a member of the appellant-Institute, was sought to be
			<lb />
			prosecuted on the basis that he had represented before the
			<lb />
			Tax Authorities on the basis of the Power of Attorney or
			<lb />
			as Legal Representative and was submitting documents by
			<lb />
			preparing forged seals. The Authorised Representative of
			<lb />
			the appellant-Institute submitted a complaint to the Police
			<lb />
			Officer. After investigation, the Police filed a challan
			<lb />
			of offences under the IPC and Sections 24 and 26 of the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			71
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Chartered Accountants Act. The same was successfully
			<lb />
			questioned by the respondent on the basis that it fell foul
			<lb />
			of the mandate of Section 28 of the Chartered Accounts Act.
			<lb />
			57. Section 28 of the Chartered Accountants Act, 1949 reads
			<lb />
			as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;28. Sanction to prosecute
			<lb />
			No person shall be prosecuted under this
			<lb />
			Act except on a complaint made by or under the
			<lb />
			order of the Council or of the Central
			<lb />
			Government.&quot;
			<lb />
			58. This Court went on to notice the line of decisions
			<lb />
			rendered by this Court which permitted prosecution of
			<lb />
			distinct offences by way of dealing with the argument based
			<lb />
			on prohibition against prosecution and punishment for the
			<lb />
			same offence flowing from Article 20(2) of the Constitution
			<lb />
			of India. We notice paragraphs 20,21 and 41 of Vimal Kumar
			<lb />
			Surana and another (supra):
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place='footnote'>
			6 (2011) 1 SCC 534
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			72
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			&quot;20. In other words, if the particular act
			<lb />
			of a member of the Institute or a non-member
			<lb />
			or a company results in contravention of the
			<lb />
			provisions contained in Section 24 or
			<lb />
			sub-section (1) of Sections 24-A, 25 or 26 and
			<lb />
			such act also amounts to criminal misconduct
			<lb />
			which is defined as an offence under IPC, then
			<lb />
			a complaint can be filed by or under the order
			<lb />
			of the Council or of the Central Government
			<lb />
			under Section 28, which may ultimately result
			<lb />
			in imposition of the punishment prescribed
			<lb />
			under Section 24 or sub-section (2) of
			<lb />
			Sections 24-A, 25 or 26 and such member or
			<lb />
			non-member or company can also be prosecuted
			<lb />
			for any identified offence under IPC.
			<lb />
			21. The object underlying the prohibition
			<lb />
			contained in Section 28 is to protect the
			<lb />
			persons engaged in profession of Chartered
			<lb />
			Accountants against false and untenable
			<lb />
			complaints from dissatisfied litigants and
			<lb />
			others. However, there is nothing in the
			<lb />
			language of the provisions contained in
			<lb />
			Chapter VII from which it can be inferred that
			<lb />
			Parliament wanted to confer immunity upon the
			<lb />
			members and non-members from prosecution and
			<lb />
			punishment if the action of such member or
			<lb />
			non-member amounts to an offence under IPC or
			<lb />
			any other law.
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			41. It is also apposite to mention that
			<lb />
			except the provision contained in Section 28
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			73
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			against the prosecution of a person, who is
			<lb />
			alleged to have acted in contravention of
			<lb />
			sub-section (1) of Sections 24, 24-A, 25 or
			<lb />
			26 otherwise then on a complaint made by or
			<lb />
			under the order of the Council or the Central
			<lb />
			Government, the Act does not specify the
			<lb />
			procedure to be followed for punishing such
			<lb />
			person. In the absence of any such provision,
			<lb />
			the procedure prescribed in CrPC has to be
			<lb />
			followed for inquiry, investigation and
			<lb />
			trial of the complaint which may be filed for
			<lb />
			contravention of any of the provisions
			<lb />
			contained
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			Chapter
			<lb />
			VII
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Act-Section 4 CrPC.&quot;
			<lb />
			59. In State (NCT of Delhi) v. Sanjay, ETC., ETC. 7 , the
			<lb />
			matter arose under the Mines and Minerals Development and
			<lb />
			Regulation Act, 1957 (MMDR Act) as also under Sections 378
			<lb />
			and 379 of the IPC and the question which arose for decision
			<lb />
			was whether the provisions of Sections 21 and 22, apart from
			<lb />
			other provisions of the MMDR Act, operated as a bar to
			<lb />
			prosecution for offences under Section 379/114 and other
			<lb />
			provisions of the IPC. Section 21 of the said Act prescribes
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place='footnote'>
			7 (2014) 9 SCC 772
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			74
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			various penalties. Section 22 deals with cognizance of
			<lb />
			offences and it reads as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;22.Cognizance of offences.-No court
			<lb />
			shall take cognizance of any offence
			<lb />
			punishable under this Act or any Rules made
			<lb />
			thereunder except upon complaint in writing
			<lb />
			made by a person authorised in this behalf by
			<lb />
			the Central Government or the State
			<lb />
			Government.&quot;
			<lb />
			60. The Court was dealing with appeals from judgments of
			<lb />
			High Courts of Delhi and Gujarat. The registration of the
			<lb />
			cases was challenged on the basis of Section 22 of the MMDR
			<lb />
			Act. Paragraphs 8, 9, 10 and 11 reveals the questions which
			<lb />
			arose and how it came to be dealt with by the High Court:
			<lb />
			&quot;8. Criminal Appeal No. 499 of 2011, as
			<lb />
			stated above, arose out of the order
			<lb />
			[Sanjay v. State, (2009) 109 DRJ 594] passed
			<lb />
			by the Delhi High Court. The Delhi High Court
			<lb />
			formulated three issues for consideration:
			<lb />
			(1) Whether the police could have
			<lb />
			registered an FIR in the case;
			<lb />
			(2) Whether a cognizance can be taken by
			<lb />
			the Magistrate concerned on the basis of
			<lb />
			police report; and
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			75
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			(3) Whether a case of theft was made out
			<lb />
			for permitting registration of an FIR
			<lb />
			under Sections 379/411 of the Penal Code.
			<lb />
			9. The Delhi High Court after referring
			<lb />
			various provisions on the MMDR Act vis--vis
			<lb />
			the Code of Criminal Procedure disposed of
			<lb />
			the application directing the respondent to
			<lb />
			amend the FIR, which was registered, by
			<lb />
			converting the offence mentioned therein
			<lb />
			under Sections 379/411/120-B/34 IPC to
			<lb />
			Section 21 of the MMDR Act. The High Court in
			<lb />
			para 18 of the impugned order held as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;18. In view of the aforesaid and taking
			<lb />
			into
			<lb />
			consideration
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			provisions
			<lb />
			contained under Section 21(6) of the said
			<lb />
			Act I hold that:
			<lb />
			(i) The offence under the said Act
			<lb />
			being cognizable offence, the police
			<lb />
			could have registered an FIR in this
			<lb />
			case;
			<lb />
			(ii) However, so far as taking
			<lb />
			cognizance of an offence under the said
			<lb />
			Act is concerned, it can be taken by the
			<lb />
			Magistrate only on the basis of a
			<lb />
			complaint filed by an authorised
			<lb />
			officer, which may be filed along with
			<lb />
			the police report;
			<lb />
			(iii) Since the offence of mining of
			<lb />
			sand without permission is punishable
			<lb />
			under Section 21 of the said Act, the
			<lb />
			question of the said offence being an
			<lb />
			offence under Section 379 IPC does not
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			76
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			arise because the said Act makes illegal
			<lb />
			mining as an offence only when there is
			<lb />
			no permit/licence for such extraction
			<lb />
			and a complaint in this regard is filed
			<lb />
			by an authorised officer.&quot;
			<lb />
			10. On the other hand the Gujarat High
			<lb />
			Court formulated the following questions for
			<lb />
			consideration:
			<lb />
			(1) Whether Section 22 of the Act would
			<lb />
			debar even lodging an FIR before the police
			<lb />
			with respect to the offences punishable
			<lb />
			under the said Act and the Rules made
			<lb />
			thereunder?
			<lb />
			(2) In case such FIRs are not debarred
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			police
			<lb />
			are
			<lb />
			permitted
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			investigate, can the Magistrate concerned
			<lb />
			take cognizance of the offences on a police
			<lb />
			report?
			<lb />
			(3) What would be the effect on the
			<lb />
			offences punishable under the Penal Code
			<lb />
			in view of the provisions contained in the
			<lb />
			Act?
			<lb />
			11. The Gujarat High Court came to the
			<lb />
			following conclusion:
			<lb />
			(i) The offence under the said Act being
			<lb />
			cognizable offence, the police could have
			<lb />
			registered an FIR in this case;
			<lb />
			(ii)
			<lb />
			However,
			<lb />
			so
			<lb />
			far
			<lb />
			as
			<lb />
			taking
			<lb />
			cognizance of offence under the said Act
			<lb />
			is concerned, it can be taken by the
			<lb />
			Magistrate only on the basis of a complaint
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			77
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			filed by an authorised officer, which may
			<lb />
			be filed along with the police report;
			<lb />
			(iii) Since the offence of mining of sand
			<lb />
			without permission is punishable under
			<lb />
			Section 21 of the said Act, the question
			<lb />
			of said offence being an offence under
			<lb />
			Section 379 IPC does not arise because the
			<lb />
			said Act makes illegal mining as an offence
			<lb />
			only when there is no permit/licence for
			<lb />
			such extraction and a complaint in this
			<lb />
			regard is filed by an authorised officer.&quot;
			<lb />
			61. The Gujarat High Court also held that Section 22 did
			<lb />
			not prohibit registering an FIR by the Police in regard to
			<lb />
			offence under the MMDR Act and the Rules thereunder.
			<lb />
			However, it was not open to the Magistrate to take
			<lb />
			cognizance. This Court, after referring to the decisions
			<lb />
			in Sanjay, ETC., ETC. (supra), held as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;69. Considering
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			principles
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			interpretation and the wordings used in
			<lb />
			Section 22, in our considered opinion, the
			<lb />
			provision is not a complete and absolute bar
			<lb />
			for taking action by the police for illegal
			<lb />
			and dishonestly committing theft of minerals
			<lb />
			including sand from the riverbed. The Court
			<lb />
			shall take judicial notice of the fact that
			<lb />
			over the years rivers in India have been
			<lb />
			affected by the alarming rate of unrestricted
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			78
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			sand mining which is damaging the ecosystem
			<lb />
			of the rivers and safety of bridges. It also
			<lb />
			weakens
			<lb />
			riverbeds,
			<lb />
			fish
			<lb />
			breeding
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			destroys the natural habitat of many
			<lb />
			organisms. If these illegal activities are
			<lb />
			not stopped by the State and the police
			<lb />
			authorities of the State, it will cause
			<lb />
			serious
			<lb />
			repercussions
			<lb />
			as
			<lb />
			mentioned
			<lb />
			hereinabove. It will not only change the
			<lb />
			river hydrology but also will deplete the
			<lb />
			groundwater levels.
			<lb />
			70. There cannot be any dispute with
			<lb />
			regard to restrictions imposed under the MMDR
			<lb />
			Act and remedy provided therein. In any case,
			<lb />
			where there is a mining activity by any person
			<lb />
			in contravention of the provisions of Section
			<lb />
			4 and other sections of the Act, the officer
			<lb />
			empowered and authorised under the Act shall
			<lb />
			exercise all the powers including making a
			<lb />
			complaint
			<lb />
			before
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Jurisdictional
			<lb />
			Magistrate. It is also not in dispute that the
			<lb />
			Magistrate shall in such cases take
			<lb />
			cognizance on the basis of the complaint
			<lb />
			filed before it by a duly authorised officer.
			<lb />
			In case of breach and violation of Section 4
			<lb />
			and other provisions of the Act, the police
			<lb />
			officer cannot insist the Magistrate for
			<lb />
			taking cognizance under the Act on the basis
			<lb />
			of the record submitted by the police
			<lb />
			alleging contravention of the said Act. In
			<lb />
			other words, the prohibition contained in
			<lb />
			Section 22 of the Act against prosecution of
			<lb />
			a person except on a complaint made by the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			79
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			officer is attracted only when such person is
			<lb />
			sought to be prosecuted for contravention of
			<lb />
			Section 4 of the Act and not for any act or
			<lb />
			omission which constitutes an offence under
			<lb />
			the Penal Code.
			<lb />
			71. However, there may be a situation
			<lb />
			where a person without any lease or licence
			<lb />
			or any authority enters into river and
			<lb />
			extracts sand, gravel and other minerals and
			<lb />
			remove or transport those minerals in a
			<lb />
			clandestine manner with an intent to remove
			<lb />
			dishonestly
			<lb />
			those
			<lb />
			minerals
			<lb />
			from
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			possession of the State, is liable to be
			<lb />
			punished for committing such offence under
			<lb />
			Sections 378 and 379 of the Penal Code.
			<lb />
			72. From a close reading of the provisions
			<lb />
			of the MMDR Act and the offence defined under
			<lb />
			Section 378 IPC, it is manifest that the
			<lb />
			ingredients constituting the offence are
			<lb />
			different. The contravention of terms and
			<lb />
			conditions of mining lease or doing mining
			<lb />
			activity in violation of Section 4 of the Act
			<lb />
			is an offence punishable under Section 21 of
			<lb />
			the MMDR Act, whereas dishonestly removing
			<lb />
			sand, gravel and other minerals from the
			<lb />
			river, which is the property of the State, out
			<lb />
			of the State&apos;s possession without the
			<lb />
			consent, constitute an offence of theft.
			<lb />
			Hence,
			<lb />
			merely
			<lb />
			because
			<lb />
			initiation
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			proceeding for commission of an offence under
			<lb />
			the MMDR Act on the basis of complaint cannot
			<lb />
			and shall not debar the police from taking
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			80
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			action against persons for committing theft
			<lb />
			of sand and minerals in the manner mentioned
			<lb />
			above by exercising power under the Code of
			<lb />
			Criminal Procedure and submit a report before
			<lb />
			the Magistrate for taking cognizance against
			<lb />
			such persons. In other words, in a case where
			<lb />
			there is a theft of sand and gravel from the
			<lb />
			government land, the police can register a
			<lb />
			case, investigate the same and submit a final
			<lb />
			report under Section 173 CrPC before a
			<lb />
			Magistrate having jurisdiction for the
			<lb />
			purpose of taking cognizance as provided in
			<lb />
			Section 190(1)(d) of the Code of Criminal
			<lb />
			Procedure.
			<lb />
			73. After
			<lb />
			giving
			<lb />
			our
			<lb />
			thoughtful
			<lb />
			consideration in the matter, in the light of
			<lb />
			the relevant provisions of the Act vis--vis
			<lb />
			the Code of Criminal Procedure and the Penal
			<lb />
			Code, we are of the definite opinion that the
			<lb />
			ingredients constituting the offence under
			<lb />
			the MMDR Act and the ingredients of
			<lb />
			dishonestly removing sand and gravel from the
			<lb />
			riverbeds without consent, which is the
			<lb />
			property of the State, is a distinct offence
			<lb />
			under IPC. Hence, for the commission of
			<lb />
			offence under Section 378 IPC, on receipt of
			<lb />
			the police report, the Magistrate having
			<lb />
			jurisdiction can take cognizance of the said
			<lb />
			offence without awaiting the receipt of
			<lb />
			complaint that may be filed by the authorised
			<lb />
			officer for taking cognizance in respect of
			<lb />
			violation of various provisions of the MMDR
			<lb />
			Act. Consequently, the contrary view taken by
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			81
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			the different High Courts cannot be sustained
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			law
			<lb />
			and,
			<lb />
			therefore,
			<lb />
			overruled.
			<lb />
			Consequently, these criminal appeals are
			<lb />
			disposed of with a direction to the
			<lb />
			Magistrates
			<lb />
			concerned
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			proceed
			<lb />
			accordingly.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			62. Chapter XII of the CrPC carries the chapter heading
			<lb />
			&quot;Information to the Police and their Powers to
			<lb />
			Investigate&quot;. The Chapter starts off with Section 154
			<lb />
			carrying Section heading &quot;Information in cognizable
			<lb />
			cases&quot;. It declares that every information relating to a
			<lb />
			cognizable offence given to an officer in charge of the
			<lb />
			police station, if given orally, is to be reduced to writing
			<lb />
			and whether given in writing or reduced to writing it is
			<lb />
			to be signed by the informant. The key elements of Section
			<lb />
			154 CrPC can be noticed. Information in relation to a
			<lb />
			cognizable offence reaching the officer in charge of a
			<lb />
			police station which is ordinarily understood as first
			<lb />
			information statement concerning cognizable offences sets
			<lb />
			the ball rolling so far as the police officer, in charge
			<lb />
			of a police station is concerned. The next provision to
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			82
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			notice in the Chapter is Section 156. It provides that any
			<lb />
			officer in charge of a police station may without the order
			<lb />
			from a Magistrate investigate any cognizable offence within
			<lb />
			which a court, having jurisdiction over a local area within
			<lb />
			the limits of such station, would have the power to enquire
			<lb />
			into or try under the provisions of Chapter XIII. In fact,
			<lb />
			Section 177 of the CrPC, which is the first Section in
			<lb />
			Chapter XIII dealing with jurisdiction of Criminal Courts
			<lb />
			Inquiries and Trial, proclaims that every offence shall
			<lb />
			ordinarily be enquired into and tried by a court within
			<lb />
			whose jurisdiction, the offence was committed. Thus,
			<lb />
			ordinarily, it is the Police Officer, within whose
			<lb />
			jurisdiction the cognizable offence is committed, would
			<lb />
			have the jurisdiction to investigate that offence. Section
			<lb />
			178 onwards provide for the exceptions to Section 177 and
			<lb />
			we need not probe this matter further. Sub-section (2)
			<lb />
			declares the proceedings of police officer in a case of
			<lb />
			cognizable offence shall not in any stage be called in
			<lb />
			question on the ground that the case was one which he was
			<lb />
			not empowered to investigate under the provision. Lastly,
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			83
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			sub-section (3) provides that any Magistrate who is
			<lb />
			empowered under Section 190 may order such an investigation
			<lb />
			which the officer is to undertake under sub-section (1).
			<lb />
			It is next relevant to notice Section 157 CrPC:
			<lb />
			&quot;157.
			<lb />
			Procedure
			<lb />
			for
			<lb />
			investigation
			<lb />
			preliminary
			<lb />
			inquiry.(1) If,
			<lb />
			from
			<lb />
			information received or otherwise, an
			<lb />
			officer in charge of a police station has
			<lb />
			reason to suspect the commission of an
			<lb />
			offence which he is empowered under section
			<lb />
			156 to investigate, he shall forthwith send
			<lb />
			a report of the same to a Magistrate empowered
			<lb />
			to take cognizance of such offence upon a
			<lb />
			police report and shall proceed in person, or
			<lb />
			shall depute one of his subordinate officers
			<lb />
			not being below such rank as the State
			<lb />
			Government may, by general or special order,
			<lb />
			prescribe in this behalf, to proceed, to the
			<lb />
			spot,
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			investigate
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			facts
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			circumstances of the case, and, if necessary,
			<lb />
			to take measures for the discovery and arrest
			<lb />
			of the offender; Provided that-
			<lb />
			(a) when
			<lb />
			information
			<lb />
			as
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			commission of any such offence is
			<lb />
			given against any person by name and
			<lb />
			the case is not of a serious nature,
			<lb />
			the officer in charge of a police
			<lb />
			station need not proceed in person
			<lb />
			or depute a subordinate officer to
			<lb />
			make an investigation on the spot;
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			84
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			(b) if it appears to the officer in
			<lb />
			charge of a police station that
			<lb />
			there is no sufficient ground for
			<lb />
			entering on an investigation, he
			<lb />
			shall not investigate the case.
			<lb />
			(2) In each of the cases mentioned in clauses
			<lb />
			(a) and (b) of the proviso to sub-section (1),
			<lb />
			the officer in charge of the police station
			<lb />
			shall state in his report his reasons for not
			<lb />
			fully complying with the requirements of that
			<lb />
			sub-section, and, in the case mentioned in
			<lb />
			clause (b) of the said proviso, the officer
			<lb />
			shall also forthwith notify to the informant,
			<lb />
			if any, in such manner as may be prescribed
			<lb />
			by the State Government, the fact that he will
			<lb />
			not investigate the case or cause it to be
			<lb />
			investigated.&quot;
			<lb />
			63. It comes under the section heading &apos;Procedure for
			<lb />
			investigation&apos;. The body of the Section can be split-up
			<lb />
			into the following parts -(i) An officer in charge of a
			<lb />
			police station may from information received have reason
			<lb />
			to suspect the commission of an offence. He may also have
			<lb />
			reason to suspect the commission of cognizable offence not
			<lb />
			on the basis of any information but otherwise. (ii) As far
			<lb />
			as information is concerned, it is clearly relatable to the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			85
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			information which has been provided to him within the
			<lb />
			meaning of Section 154. Cases where he acts on his own
			<lb />
			knowledge would be covered by the expression otherwise.
			<lb />
			(iii) The offences must be an offence which he is empowered
			<lb />
			under Section 156 to investigate. We have noticed that a
			<lb />
			police officer is empowered to investigate a cognizable
			<lb />
			offence without an order of the Magistrate. As far as
			<lb />
			non-cognizable offence is concerned, he cannot investigate
			<lb />
			such offence without the order of the Magistrate having
			<lb />
			power to try or commit the case for trial. (iv) However,
			<lb />
			a police officer who undertakes to investigate the matter
			<lb />
			is obliged to forthwith send a report of the same to the
			<lb />
			Magistrate empowered to take cognizance of an offence upon
			<lb />
			a police report. It is at once relevant to notice in the
			<lb />
			facts of this case that this indispensable element is not
			<lb />
			present. This is for the reason that under Section 32 of
			<lb />
			the Act, a Magistrate is not competent to take cognizance
			<lb />
			of the offences under Chapter IV of the Act upon a police
			<lb />
			report. At this juncture, we may notice Section 158 CrPC.
			<lb />
			It speaks about the manner of sending the report to the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			86
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Magistrate under Section 157. It is a matter governed by
			<lb />
			a general or special order issued by the State Government.
			<lb />
			Quite clearly even Section 158 cannot apply in the case of
			<lb />
			a cognizable offence falling under Chapter IV of the Act
			<lb />
			for the reasons which we have adverted to. Section 159
			<lb />
			enables the Magistrate on receiving such report to direct
			<lb />
			investigation or if he thinks fit at once to proceed or
			<lb />
			depute any Magistrate subordinate to him to proceed, to hold
			<lb />
			a preliminary inquiry or otherwise to dispose of the case
			<lb />
			in the manner provided in the Code. It is clear that the
			<lb />
			purpose of Section 157 is to hold the police officer
			<lb />
			accountable to keep informed the Magistrate. It acts as an
			<lb />
			assurance that the reports are not tampered, and that the
			<lb />
			rights of the accused are sought to be secured. The purport
			<lb />
			of Section 159 is also to enable the Magistrate to exercise
			<lb />
			control over the investigation. All these aspects are
			<lb />
			irrelevant and out of bounds both for the police officer
			<lb />
			and the Magistrate in respect of an offence falling under
			<lb />
			chapter IV of the Act.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			87
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			64. Section 160 refers to investigation under the Chapter,
			<lb />
			viz., Chapter XII. Section 161 speaks about the examination
			<lb />
			of witnesses and how the statements are to be reduced to
			<lb />
			writing. Again, Section 161 speaks about an investigation
			<lb />
			carried out under Chapter XII. The use to which statements
			<lb />
			under Section 161 can be put and the limitation on the same
			<lb />
			are spelt out in Section 162 CrPC.
			<lb />
			Reverting back to
			<lb />
			Section 157, we have taken note of the requirement about
			<lb />
			the police officer reporting to the Magistrate about the
			<lb />
			reason to suspect entertained by the police officer about
			<lb />
			the commission of a cognizable offence on which the
			<lb />
			Magistrate is to take cognizance on a report.
			<lb />
			Be it
			<lb />
			remembered that the Magistrate can take cognizance under
			<lb />
			Section 190 of the CrPC on a complaint, a police report or
			<lb />
			information received from any person other than a police
			<lb />
			officer or otherwise. Section 157 appears to contemplate
			<lb />
			information received under Section 154 or knowledge gained
			<lb />
			otherwise about the commission of a cognizance offence
			<lb />
			clothing the police officer with the power to investigate
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			88
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			leading to the sending of the report to the Magistrate being
			<lb />
			confined to cases where officer intends to send the police
			<lb />
			report which has been defined as the report under Section
			<lb />
			173 of the CrPC. In regard to taking cognizance under
			<lb />
			Section 32 of the Act, it is unambiguously clear that there
			<lb />
			is no place for a police report within the meaning of Section
			<lb />
			173 of the CrPC in regard to offences falling under Chapter
			<lb />
			IV of the Act. Section 157 contemplates that the Officer
			<lb />
			proceeding either by himself or through his subordinate
			<lb />
			Officer to investigate the facts and circumstances, and if
			<lb />
			necessary, to take measures for the discovery and the arrest
			<lb />
			of the offender. But on reading the provisions, we gather
			<lb />
			the unmistakable impression that the law giver has
			<lb />
			empowered the police officer to investigate in the case of
			<lb />
			a cognizable offence without any order of the Magistrate
			<lb />
			where he ultimately in an appropriate case wishes the Court
			<lb />
			to take cognizance based on the material he gathers and
			<lb />
			transmits a police report. If this impression of ours is
			<lb />
			not flawed, an inevitable corollary would be that in the
			<lb />
			case of offence under Chapter IV of the Act though it be
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			89
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			cognizable, a police officer would not have the power to
			<lb />
			investigate the matter. Section 169 speaks about the duty
			<lb />
			to release a person in custody if it is found on
			<lb />
			investigation that there is no sufficient evidence or
			<lb />
			reasonable ground of suspicion to justify forwarding such
			<lb />
			person to the Magistrate. Section 170 deals with cases
			<lb />
			where an officer conducting investigation finds sufficient
			<lb />
			evidence or reasonable ground and the accused is forwarded
			<lb />
			to the Magistrate empowered to take cognizance of the
			<lb />
			offence upon a report. Again, the cardinal requirement for
			<lb />
			the officer to invoke Section 170 is availability of power
			<lb />
			with the Magistrate to take cognizance upon a police report.
			<lb />
			This key requirement is absent in the case of an offence
			<lb />
			falling under Chapter IV of the Act. The link therefore
			<lb />
			snaps. Section 173 speaks about the report on completion
			<lb />
			of the investigation for the police officer. Section 173
			<lb />
			(5) is to be read with Section 170, that is to say, in a
			<lb />
			case where there is sufficient material for prosecuting the
			<lb />
			concerned person, the documents and the statements of
			<lb />
			witnesses are to be forwarded to the Magistrate as provided
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			90
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			therein. We have already noted Section 190 of the CrPC.
			<lb />
			Sections 154, 156, 157, 158, 159, 160, 161, 170 and 173 are
			<lb />
			part of a scheme of provisions geared to empower and require
			<lb />
			investigation of cognisable offences which are to culminate
			<lb />
			in a police report within the meaning of Section 190(b) of
			<lb />
			the CrPC.
			<lb />
			However, what is applicable in respect of
			<lb />
			offences under Chapter IV of the Act is not 190 of the CrPC
			<lb />
			but Section 32 of the Act which does not permit cognizance
			<lb />
			being taken on a police report. The entire exercise of a
			<lb />
			police officer proceeding on a basis of a FIR becomes
			<lb />
			futile.
			<lb />
			It is not contemplated in law. It therefore
			<lb />
			becomes unauthorised.
			<lb />
			IMPACT OF LALITA KUMARI V. GOVERNMENT OF UTTAR PRADESH AND
			<lb />
			OTHERS 8
			<lb />
			65. In the said case, a Constitution Bench of this Court
			<lb />
			has held that registration of an FIR is mandatory under
			<lb />
			Section 154 of the CrPC, if the information discloses
			<lb />
			commission of a cognizable offence and no preliminary
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place='footnote'>
			8 (2014) 2 SCC 1
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			91
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			inquiry is permissible in such a situation. It was further
			<lb />
			held that a preliminary inquiry may be conducted only to
			<lb />
			ascertain whether a cognizable offence is disclosed or not,
			<lb />
			if the information received does not disclose a cognizable
			<lb />
			offence but indicates the need for such an inquiry. The
			<lb />
			Court has also indicated certain cases where a preliminary
			<lb />
			inquiry may be conducted, depending on the facts and
			<lb />
			circumstances of each case. They include matrimonial
			<lb />
			disputes, commercial offences and cases where there is
			<lb />
			abnormal delay/latches. This Court also held that the
			<lb />
			aforesaid were not exhaustive of all conditions which may
			<lb />
			warrant a preliminary inquiry.
			<lb />
			66. We would think that this Court was not, in the said
			<lb />
			case, considering a case under the Act or cases similar to
			<lb />
			those under the Act, and we would think that having regard
			<lb />
			to the discussion which we have made and on a conspectus
			<lb />
			of the provisions of the CrPC and Section 32 of the Act,
			<lb />
			the principle laid down in Lalita Kumari (supra) is not
			<lb />
			attracted when an information is made before a Police
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			92
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Officer making out the commission of an offence under
			<lb />
			Chapter IV of the Act mandating a registration of a FIR under
			<lb />
			Section 154 of the CrPC.
			<lb />
			DUTY OF POLICE OFFICER UNDER SECTION 154 OF THE CRPC
			<lb />
			IRRESPECTIVE OF IMPACT OF TERRITORIAL JURISDICTION
			<lb />
			67. In State of A.P. v. Punati Ramulu and others 9 , the
			<lb />
			Police Constable had refused to record the complaint on the
			<lb />
			ground that the said Police Station had no territorial
			<lb />
			jurisdiction over the place of crime. It was held as
			<lb />
			follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;4.  It was certainly a dereliction of
			<lb />
			duty on the part of the constable because any
			<lb />
			lack of territorial jurisdiction, could not
			<lb />
			have prevented the constable from recording
			<lb />
			information about the cognizable offence and
			<lb />
			forwarding the same to the police station
			<lb />
			having jurisdiction over the area in which
			<lb />
			the crime was said to have been committed.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			9 AIR 1993 SC 2644
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			93
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			68. In Satvinder Kaur v. State (Govt. of NCT of Delhi) and
			<lb />
			another 10 , this Court held, inter alia, as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;10. It
			<lb />
			is
			<lb />
			true
			<lb />
			that
			<lb />
			territorial
			<lb />
			jurisdiction also is prescribed under
			<lb />
			sub-section (1) to the extent that the
			<lb />
			officer can investigate any cognizable case
			<lb />
			which a court having jurisdiction over the
			<lb />
			local area within the limits of such police
			<lb />
			station would have power to enquire into or
			<lb />
			try under the provisions of Chapter XIII.
			<lb />
			However, sub-section (2) makes the position
			<lb />
			clear by providing that no proceeding of a
			<lb />
			police officer in any such case shall at any
			<lb />
			stage be called in question on the ground that
			<lb />
			the case was one which such officer was not
			<lb />
			empowered
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			investigate.
			<lb />
			After
			<lb />
			investigation is completed, the result of
			<lb />
			such investigation is required to be
			<lb />
			submitted as provided under Sections 168, 169
			<lb />
			and 170. Section 170 specifically provides
			<lb />
			that if, upon an investigation, it appears to
			<lb />
			the officer in charge of the police station
			<lb />
			that there is sufficient evidence or
			<lb />
			reasonable ground of suspicion to justify the
			<lb />
			forwarding of the accused to a Magistrate,
			<lb />
			such officer shall forward the accused under
			<lb />
			custody to a Magistrate empowered to take
			<lb />
			cognizance of the offence upon a police
			<lb />
			report and to try the accused or commit for
			<lb />
			trial. Further, if the investigating officer
			<lb />
			arrives at the conclusion that the crime was
			<lb />
			not
			<lb />
			committed
			<lb />
			within the
			<lb />
			territorial
			<lb />
			jurisdiction of the police station, then FIR
			<lb />
			can be forwarded to the police station having
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			10 AIR 1999 SC 3596
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			94
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			jurisdiction over the area in which the crime
			<lb />
			is committed. But this would not mean that in
			<lb />
			a case which requires investigation, the
			<lb />
			police officer can refuse to record the FIR
			<lb />
			and/or investigate it.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			69. This was a case where the FIR had been quashed by the
			<lb />
			High Court under Section 482 CrPC on the ground that the
			<lb />
			Police Officer at Delhi was not having territorial
			<lb />
			jurisdiction. It was a case under Section 498A of the IPC.
			<lb />
			This Court set aside the judgment of the High Court quashing
			<lb />
			the FIR, also taking note of Section 156(2) of the IPC.
			<lb />
			70. There is practice of registering an FIR as a Zero FIR,
			<lb />
			when the Police Station at which FIR is registered, does
			<lb />
			not have territorial jurisdiction, and then, it is made over
			<lb />
			to the Police Station which has jurisdiction in the matter.
			<lb />
			Could it, therefore, be said that when information is given
			<lb />
			to a Police Officer, within the meaning of Section 154 of
			<lb />
			the CrPC, in relation to the commission of a cognizable
			<lb />
			offence under Chapter IV of the Act, the Police Officer must
			<lb />
			register a FIR and then make it over to the Inspector.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			95
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			71. It is to be noted that the duty to register FIR, when
			<lb />
			information is received about a cognizable offence falling
			<lb />
			under Chapter IV of the Act, it is clear from the very
			<lb />
			inception that a Police Officer has no jurisdiction to
			<lb />
			investigate the offence. It is not a case of absence of
			<lb />
			territorial jurisdiction. No doubt, if it is a case of
			<lb />
			another Police Officer being empowered to investigate the
			<lb />
			offence in terms of powers under CrPC, the law is, as laid
			<lb />
			down, that there is the obligation to register an FIR and
			<lb />
			then make it over to the Police Station which has
			<lb />
			jurisdiction. In fact, a conflict, when in the context of
			<lb />
			Sections 178 to 185 of the CrPC, which constitute exceptions
			<lb />
			to the general principle laid down in Section 177 of the
			<lb />
			CrPC, the High Court is to decide the dispute, as is provided
			<lb />
			in Section 186 of the CrPC. If an information is relatable
			<lb />
			only to cognizable offences under Chapter IV of the Act,
			<lb />
			we would think that the Police Officer would be out of bounds
			<lb />
			and he has no role to play in the investigation as neither
			<lb />
			he nor any other Police Officer has any role to play in the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			96
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			investigation. His duty lies in referring the complainant
			<lb />
			to the concerned Drugs Inspector. If he is in receipt of
			<lb />
			information about an offence under Chapter IV of the Act,
			<lb />
			he must promptly notify the concerned Drugs Inspector.
			<lb />
			POWER TO ARREST UNDER THE ACT
			<lb />
			72. One of the reliefs which is sought by the first
			<lb />
			respondent-writ petitioner was a direction not to arrest
			<lb />
			him. The Act does not expressly confer upon the Inspector
			<lb />
			the power to arrest. This brings up the issue, therefore,
			<lb />
			of the person empowered to arrest.
			<lb />
			73. Perusal of Section 36AC of the Act makes it clear that
			<lb />
			arrest is contemplated under the Act. Conditions have been
			<lb />
			imposed for grant of bail as enacted in Section 36AC which
			<lb />
			we have already referred. If the Inspector under the Act
			<lb />
			has no authority to carry out the arrest, there cannot be
			<lb />
			a situation where arrest is in the contemplation of the law
			<lb />
			giver and yet there is no person who can effectuate that
			<lb />
			arrest.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			97
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			74. The further question which would therefore arise is,
			<lb />
			the impact of finding that arrest can be effected by a police
			<lb />
			officer in respect of a cognizable offence under Chapter
			<lb />
			IV of the Act on the need to register an FIR under Section
			<lb />
			154. We have already noticed that under Section 157 of the
			<lb />
			Act making a report to the Magistrate who can take
			<lb />
			cognizance of a police report renders the provision as such
			<lb />
			inapplicable under Chapter IV of the Act.
			<lb />
			75. The question would arise if investigation is not
			<lb />
			permissible for a police officer under Section 157 and that
			<lb />
			he cannot give a report under the said provision, can he
			<lb />
			be empowered to carry out the arrest? Is the scheme of
			<lb />
			arrest under Section 41 of the Act interlinked with the
			<lb />
			power of arrest under Section 157? We heard the learned
			<lb />
			Counsel for the petitioner and the learned Amicus Curiae
			<lb />
			on this point and have considered their Written Submissions
			<lb />
			as well.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			98
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			PROVISIONS AS TO ARREST IN THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA -
			<lb />
			ARTICLE 22(1) AND ARTICLE 22(2).
			<lb />
			76. Article 22(1) and Article 22(2) of the Constitution of
			<lb />
			India, reads as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;22. Protection against arrest and detention
			<lb />
			in certain cases
			<lb />
			(1) No person who is arrested shall be
			<lb />
			detained in custody without being informed,
			<lb />
			as soon as may be, of the grounds for such
			<lb />
			arrest nor shall he be denied the right to
			<lb />
			consult, and to be defended by, a legal
			<lb />
			practitioner of his choice
			<lb />
			(2) Every person who is arrested and
			<lb />
			detained in custody shall be produced before
			<lb />
			the nearest magistrate within a period of
			<lb />
			twenty four hours of such arrest excluding
			<lb />
			the time necessary for the journey from the
			<lb />
			place of arrest to the court of the
			<lb />
			magistrate and no such person shall be
			<lb />
			detained in custody beyond the said period
			<lb />
			without the authority of a magistrate.&quot;
			<lb />
			77. At this juncture, it is necessary to notice the
			<lb />
			judgment of this Court in D.K. Basu v. State of West
			<lb />
			Bengal 11 . In the said case, this Court issued various
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place='footnote'>
			11 (1997) 1 SCC 416
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			99
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			directions in regard to safeguards to be observed in the
			<lb />
			matter of effecting arrest. They are found in paragraph-35
			<lb />
			and read as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;35. We,
			<lb />
			therefore,
			<lb />
			consider
			<lb />
			it
			<lb />
			appropriate
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			issue
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			following requirements to be followed in all
			<lb />
			cases of arrest or detention till legal
			<lb />
			provisions
			<lb />
			are
			<lb />
			made
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			that
			<lb />
			behalf
			<lb />
			as preventive measures:
			<lb />
			(1) The police personnel carrying out
			<lb />
			the arrest and handling the interrogation
			<lb />
			of the arrestee should bear accurate,
			<lb />
			visible and clear identification and name
			<lb />
			tags
			<lb />
			with
			<lb />
			their
			<lb />
			designations.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			particulars of all such police personnel
			<lb />
			who handle interrogation of the arrestee
			<lb />
			must be recorded in a register.
			<lb />
			(2) That the police officer carrying out
			<lb />
			the arrest of the arrestee shall prepare
			<lb />
			a memo of arrest at the time of arrest and
			<lb />
			such memo shall be attested by at least one
			<lb />
			witness, who may either be a member of the
			<lb />
			family of the arrestee or a respectable
			<lb />
			person of the locality from where the
			<lb />
			arrest is made. It shall also be
			<lb />
			countersigned by the arrestee and shall
			<lb />
			contain the time and date of arrest.
			<lb />
			(3) A person who has been arrested or
			<lb />
			detained and is being held in custody in
			<lb />
			a police station or interrogation centre
			<lb />
			or other lock-up, shall be entitled to have
			<lb />
			one friend or relative or other person
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			100
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			known to him or having interest in his
			<lb />
			welfare being informed, as soon as
			<lb />
			practicable, that he has been arrested and
			<lb />
			is being detained at the particular place,
			<lb />
			unless the attesting witness of the memo
			<lb />
			of arrest is himself such a friend or a
			<lb />
			relative of the arrestee.
			<lb />
			(4) The time, place of arrest and venue
			<lb />
			of custody of an arrestee must be notified
			<lb />
			by the police where the next friend or
			<lb />
			relative of the arrestee lives outside the
			<lb />
			district or town through the Legal Aid
			<lb />
			Organisation in the District and the
			<lb />
			police station of the area concerned
			<lb />
			telegraphically within a period of 8 to 12
			<lb />
			hours after the arrest.
			<lb />
			(5) The person arrested must be made
			<lb />
			aware of this right to have someone
			<lb />
			informed of his arrest or detention as soon
			<lb />
			as he is put under arrest or is detained.
			<lb />
			(6) An entry must be made in the diary
			<lb />
			at the place of detention regarding the
			<lb />
			arrest of the person which shall also
			<lb />
			disclose the name of the next friend of the
			<lb />
			person who has been informed of the arrest
			<lb />
			and the names and particulars of the police
			<lb />
			officials in whose custody the arrestee
			<lb />
			is.
			<lb />
			(7) The arrestee should, where he so
			<lb />
			requests, be also examined at the time of
			<lb />
			his arrest and major and minor injuries,
			<lb />
			if any present on his/her body, must be
			<lb />
			recorded at that time. The &quot;Inspection
			<lb />
			Memo&quot; must be signed both by the arrestee
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			101
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			and the police officer effecting the
			<lb />
			arrest and its copy provided to the
			<lb />
			arrestee.
			<lb />
			(8) The arrestee should be subjected to
			<lb />
			medical examination by a trained doctor
			<lb />
			every 48 hours during his detention in
			<lb />
			custody by a doctor on the panel of
			<lb />
			approved doctors appointed by Director,
			<lb />
			Health Services of the State or Union
			<lb />
			Territory concerned. Director, Health
			<lb />
			Services should prepare such a panel for
			<lb />
			all tehsils and districts as well.
			<lb />
			(9) Copies of all the documents
			<lb />
			including the memo of arrest, referred to
			<lb />
			above, should be sent to the Illaqa
			<lb />
			Magistrate for his record.
			<lb />
			(10) The arrestee may be permitted to
			<lb />
			meet his lawyer during interrogation,
			<lb />
			though not throughout the interrogation.
			<lb />
			(11) A police control room should be
			<lb />
			provided at all district and State
			<lb />
			headquarters, where information regarding
			<lb />
			the arrest and the place of custody of the
			<lb />
			arrestee shall be communicated by the
			<lb />
			officer causing the arrest, within 12
			<lb />
			hours of effecting the arrest and at the
			<lb />
			police control room it should be displayed
			<lb />
			on a conspicuous notice board.&quot;
			<lb />
			78. We may observe what this Court laid down in
			<lb />
			paragraphs-36 and 37:
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			102
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			&quot;36. Failure to comply with the requirements
			<lb />
			hereinabove
			<lb />
			mentioned
			<lb />
			shall
			<lb />
			apart
			<lb />
			from
			<lb />
			rendering the official concerned liable for
			<lb />
			departmental action, also render him liable to
			<lb />
			be punished for contempt of court and the
			<lb />
			proceedings for contempt of court may be
			<lb />
			instituted in any High Court of the country,
			<lb />
			having territorial jurisdiction over the
			<lb />
			matter.
			<lb />
			37. The requirements, referred to above flow
			<lb />
			from Articles 21 and 22(1) of the Constitution
			<lb />
			and need to be strictly followed. These would
			<lb />
			apply
			<lb />
			with
			<lb />
			equal
			<lb />
			force
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			other
			<lb />
			governmental agencies also to which a reference
			<lb />
			has been made earlier.&quot;
			<lb />
			79. When this Court laid down in paragraph-37 that the
			<lb />
			requirements laid down by this Court would apply with equal
			<lb />
			force to other governmental agencies, to which reference
			<lb />
			was made earlier, the Court had in mind the following
			<lb />
			statements in paragraph-30 of the Judgment:
			<lb />
			&quot;30. Apart from the police, there are
			<lb />
			several other governmental authorities also
			<lb />
			like Directorate of Revenue Intelligence,
			<lb />
			Directorate of Enforcement, Coastal Guard,
			<lb />
			Central Reserve Police Force (CRPF), Border
			<lb />
			Security Force (BSF), the Central Industrial
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			103
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Security Force (CISF), the State Armed
			<lb />
			Police, Intelligence Agencies like the
			<lb />
			Intelligence Bureau, RAW, Central Bureau of
			<lb />
			Investigation (CBI), CID, Traffic Police,
			<lb />
			Mounted Police and ITBP, which have the power
			<lb />
			to detain a person and to interrogate him in
			<lb />
			connection
			<lb />
			with
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			investigation
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			economic offences, offences under the
			<lb />
			Essential Commodities Act, Excise and
			<lb />
			Customs Act, Foreign Exchange Regulation Act
			<lb />
			etc. &quot;
			<lb />
			No doubt, these are all cases where express
			<lb />
			power of arrest was conferred on those
			<lb />
			Authorities under the concerned law.
			<lb />
			80. We may notice that a Bench of this Court in Arnesh
			<lb />
			Kumar v. State of Bihar and another 12 again considered the
			<lb />
			aspect relating to the balance that is to be struck between
			<lb />
			individual liberty and societal order, while exercising
			<lb />
			power of arrest. Though the matter arose under Section 498A
			<lb />
			of the Indian Penal Code, 1860, which deals with matrimonial
			<lb />
			cruelty read with the Dowry Prohibition Act, 1961, the Court
			<lb />
			issued directions as contained in from paragraph-11.1 to
			<lb />
			11.8. It also held as follows:
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			12 (2014) 8 SCC 273
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			104
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			&quot;12. We hasten to add that the directions
			<lb />
			aforesaid shall not only apply to the cases
			<lb />
			under Section 498-A IPC or Section 4 of the
			<lb />
			Dowry Prohibition Act, the case in hand, but
			<lb />
			also such cases where offence is punishable
			<lb />
			with imprisonment for a term which may be less
			<lb />
			than seven years or which may extend to seven
			<lb />
			years, whether with or without fine.&quot;
			<lb />
			81. Still later, we may notice that a Bench of this Court
			<lb />
			frowned upon arrest which was unwarranted in the decision
			<lb />
			reported in Rini Johar v. State of M.P. 13 and the Court also
			<lb />
			granted compensation, having regard to the manner in which
			<lb />
			the petitioner was treated in the said case. After referring
			<lb />
			to Arnesh Kumar (supra), this Court in Rini Johar (supra),
			<lb />
			inter alia, held as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;22. We have referred to the enquiry
			<lb />
			report and the legal position prevalent in
			<lb />
			the field. On a studied scrutiny of the
			<lb />
			report, it is quite vivid that the arrest of
			<lb />
			the petitioners was not made by following the
			<lb />
			procedure of arrest. Section 41-A CrPC as has
			<lb />
			been interpreted by this Court has not been
			<lb />
			followed. The report clearly shows that there
			<lb />
			have been number of violations in the arrest,
			<lb />
			and seizure. Circumstances in no case justify
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			13 (2016) 11 SCC 703
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			105
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			the manner in which the petitioners were
			<lb />
			treated.&quot;
			<lb />
			No doubt, the Court, in Arnesh Gupta (supra), was
			<lb />
			dealing with the case which dealt with a situation where
			<lb />
			the offences were punishable with imprisonment upto seven
			<lb />
			years, and as mandated in Section 41 of the CrPC., reasons
			<lb />
			had to exist for effecting an arrest as provided therein.
			<lb />
			THE POWER OF ARREST UNDER THE CRPC
			<lb />
			82. Chapter V of the CrPC deals with the arrest of
			<lb />
			persons. Section 41 of the CrPC, vide the Code of Criminal
			<lb />
			Procedure (Amendment) Act, 2008 (Act 5 of 2009, Section 5)
			<lb />
			(w.e.f. 01-11-2010), deals with the power of the Police
			<lb />
			Officer to arrest without warrant. It reads as follows after
			<lb />
			substitution:
			<lb />
			&quot;41. When police may arrest without
			<lb />
			warrant.-(1) Any police officer may without
			<lb />
			an order from a Magistrate and without a
			<lb />
			warrant, arrest any person-
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			106
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			14 (a)
			<lb />
			who commits, in the presence of a
			<lb />
			police officer, a cognizable offence;
			<lb />
			(b) against whom a reasonable complaint has
			<lb />
			been made, or credible information has
			<lb />
			been received, or a reasonable suspicion
			<lb />
			exists
			<lb />
			that
			<lb />
			he
			<lb />
			has
			<lb />
			committed
			<lb />
			a
			<lb />
			cognizable offence punishable with
			<lb />
			imprisonment for a term which may be less
			<lb />
			than seven years or which may extend to
			<lb />
			seven years whether with or without
			<lb />
			fine, if the following conditions are
			<lb />
			satisfied, namely:-
			<lb />
			(i) the police officer has reason to
			<lb />
			believe on the basis of such
			<lb />
			complaint,
			<lb />
			information,
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			suspicion that such person has
			<lb />
			committed the said offence;
			<lb />
			(ii) the police office is satisfied that
			<lb />
			such arrest is necessary-
			<lb />
			(a) to prevent such person from
			<lb />
			committing
			<lb />
			any
			<lb />
			further
			<lb />
			offence; or
			<lb />
			(b) for proper investigation of the
			<lb />
			offence; or
			<lb />
			(c) to prevent such person from
			<lb />
			causing the evidence of the
			<lb />
			offence
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			disappear
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			tampering with such evidence in
			<lb />
			any manner; or
			<lb />
			(d) to prevent such person from
			<lb />
			making any inducement, threat
			<lb />
			or promise to any person
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			14 Substituted by Act 5 of 2009, sec.5(i), for clauses (a) and (b)
			<lb />
			(w.e.f. 1-11-2010).
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			107
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			acquainted with the facts of
			<lb />
			the case so as to dissuade him
			<lb />
			from disclosing such facts to
			<lb />
			the Court or to the police
			<lb />
			officer; or
			<lb />
			(e) as unless such person is
			<lb />
			arrested, his presence in the
			<lb />
			Court whenever required cannot
			<lb />
			be ensured,
			<lb />
			and the police officer shall record
			<lb />
			while making such arrest, his
			<lb />
			reasons in writing:
			<lb />
			15 [Provided that a police officer
			<lb />
			shall, in all cases where the arrest
			<lb />
			of a person is not required under
			<lb />
			the provisions of this sub-section,
			<lb />
			record the reasons in writing for
			<lb />
			not making the arrest.]
			<lb />
			(ba) against whom credible information has
			<lb />
			been received that he has committed a
			<lb />
			cognizable offence punishable with
			<lb />
			imprisonment for a term which may extend
			<lb />
			to more than seven years whether with or
			<lb />
			without fine or with death sentence and
			<lb />
			the police officer has reason to believe
			<lb />
			on the basis of that information that
			<lb />
			such person has committed the said
			<lb />
			offence;]
			<lb />
			(c) who has been proclaimed as an offender
			<lb />
			either under this Code or by order of the
			<lb />
			State Government; or
			<lb />
			(d) in whose possession anything is found
			<lb />
			which may reasonably be suspected to be
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			15 Ins. By Act 41 of 2010, sec.2 (w.e.f. 2-11-2010).
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			108
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			stolen property and who may reasonably
			<lb />
			be suspected of having committed an
			<lb />
			offence with reference to such thing; or
			<lb />
			(e) who obstructs a police officer while in
			<lb />
			the execution of his duty, or who has
			<lb />
			escaped, or attempts to escape, from
			<lb />
			lawful custody; or
			<lb />
			(f) who is reasonably suspected of being a
			<lb />
			deserter from any of the Armed Forces of
			<lb />
			the Union; or
			<lb />
			(g) who has been concerned in, or against
			<lb />
			whom a reasonable complaint has been
			<lb />
			made, or credible information has been
			<lb />
			received, or a reasonable suspicion
			<lb />
			exists, of his having been concerned in,
			<lb />
			any act committed at any place out of
			<lb />
			India which, if committed in India,
			<lb />
			would have been punishable as an
			<lb />
			offence, and for which he is, under any
			<lb />
			law
			<lb />
			relating
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			extradition,
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			otherwise, liable to be apprehended or
			<lb />
			detained in custody in India; or
			<lb />
			(h) who, being a released convict, commits
			<lb />
			a breach of any rule made under sub-
			<lb />
			section (5) of section 356; or
			<lb />
			(i) for whose arrest any requisition,
			<lb />
			whether written or oral, has been
			<lb />
			received from another police officer,
			<lb />
			provided that the requisition specifies
			<lb />
			the person to be arrested and the offence
			<lb />
			or other cause for which the arrest is
			<lb />
			to be made and it appears therefrom that
			<lb />
			the person might lawfully be arrested
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			109
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			without a warrant by the officer who
			<lb />
			issued the requisition.
			<lb />
			16
			<lb />
			[(2) Subject to the provisions of Section
			<lb />
			42, no person concerned in a non-cognizable
			<lb />
			offence or against whom a complaint has been
			<lb />
			made or credible information has been
			<lb />
			received or reasonable suspicion exists of
			<lb />
			his having so concerned, shall be arrested
			<lb />
			except under a warrant or order of a
			<lb />
			Magistrate.].&quot;
			<lb />
			83. Section 41A of the CrPC, inserted w.e.f. 01.11.2010,
			<lb />
			provides for issuance of Notice by the Police Officer in
			<lb />
			all the cases covered by Sub-Section (1) of Section 41 of
			<lb />
			the CrPC, where the arrest of a person is not required, to
			<lb />
			appear before him. As long as a person complies with the
			<lb />
			Notice, Section 41A(iii) prohibits arrest unless the Police
			<lb />
			Officer, for reasons to be recorded, is of the view that
			<lb />
			he is to be arrested. Section 41B of the CrPC, again inserted
			<lb />
			w.e.f. 01.11.2010, casts a duty on a Police Officer, making
			<lb />
			an arrest, to bear an accurate, visible and clear
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place='footnote'>
			16 Subs. By Act 5 of 2009, sec. 5(ii), for sub-Section (2) (w.e.f.
			<lb />
			1-11-2010).
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			110
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			identification of his name. He is to prepare a Memorandum
			<lb />
			of Arrest, which is, inter alia, to be countersigned by the
			<lb />
			person arrested. Section 41D of the CrPC confers a right
			<lb />
			on the arrested person to meet an Advocate of his choice
			<lb />
			during
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			interrogation,
			<lb />
			though
			<lb />
			not
			<lb />
			throughout
			<lb />
			interrogation. Under Section 42 of the CrPC, if a person
			<lb />
			commits a non-cognizable offence in the presence of a Police
			<lb />
			Officer or he is accused of committing a non-cognizable
			<lb />
			offence, and the Police Officer, on demanding his name and
			<lb />
			residence, is met with a refusal or the giving of a name
			<lb />
			or residence, which the Officer believes to be false, arrest
			<lb />
			can be made but for the purpose of ascertaining the name
			<lb />
			and residence. In fact, he is to be released immediately
			<lb />
			on executing a bond when the true name and residence is
			<lb />
			ascertained. If there is failure to ascertain the address
			<lb />
			within twenty-four hours, inter alia, of arrest, no doubt,
			<lb />
			it is forthwith forwarded to the nearest Magistrate having
			<lb />
			jurisdiction. The Act contemplates arrest by a private
			<lb />
			person. The power and the procedure, is detailed in Section
			<lb />
			43 of the CrPC, it reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			111
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			&quot;43. Arrest by private person and procedure
			<lb />
			on such arrest.
			<lb />
			(1) Any private person may arrest or cause to
			<lb />
			be arrested any person who in his presence
			<lb />
			commits a non-bailable and cognizable
			<lb />
			offence, or any proclaimed offender, and,
			<lb />
			without unnecessary delay, shall make over or
			<lb />
			cause to be made over any person so arrested
			<lb />
			to a police officer, or, in the absence of a
			<lb />
			police officer, take such person or cause him
			<lb />
			to be taken in custody to the nearest police
			<lb />
			station.
			<lb />
			(2) If there is reason to believe that such
			<lb />
			person comes under the provisions of section
			<lb />
			41, a police officer shall re-arrest him.
			<lb />
			(3) If there is reason to believe that he has
			<lb />
			committed a non-cognizable offence, and he
			<lb />
			refuses on the demand of a police officer to
			<lb />
			give his name and residence, or gives a name
			<lb />
			or residence which such officer has reason to
			<lb />
			believe to be false, he shall be dealt with
			<lb />
			under the provisions of section 42; but if
			<lb />
			there is no sufficient reason to believe that
			<lb />
			he has committed any offence, he shall be at
			<lb />
			once released.&quot;
			<lb />
			84. Section 46 of the CrPC provides for the manner of
			<lb />
			arrest. Section 47 enables the Police Officer to search the
			<lb />
			place entered by a person sought to be arrested. Section
			<lb />
			48 of the CrPC reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			112
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			&quot;48. Pursuit of offenders into other
			<lb />
			jurisdictions. A police officer may, for the
			<lb />
			purpose of arresting without warrant any
			<lb />
			person whom he is authorised to arrest,
			<lb />
			pursue such person into any place in India.&quot;
			<lb />
			85. The person arrested is not to be subjected to more
			<lb />
			restraint than is necessary to prevent his escape, declares
			<lb />
			Section 49 of the CrPC. Every Police Officer or other
			<lb />
			person, arresting a person without a warrant, is bound
			<lb />
			forthwith to communicate to him all particulars of the
			<lb />
			offence for which he is arrested or other grounds for such
			<lb />
			arrest. This is provided for in Section 50 of the CrPC. A
			<lb />
			Police Officer, when he arrests a person without warrant
			<lb />
			and he is not accused of committing a non-bailable offence,
			<lb />
			is duty-bound to inform him of his entitlement to be
			<lb />
			released on Bail. The Police Officer is also under an
			<lb />
			obligation to inform, under Section 50A of the CrPC, a
			<lb />
			nominated person about the factum of arrest. This came into
			<lb />
			force on 23.06.2006. Section 51 deals with search of the
			<lb />
			arrested person.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			113
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			86. Section 54 of the CrPC declares that when any person
			<lb />
			is arrested, he shall be examined by a Medical Officer.
			<lb />
			Section 54A of the CrPC, inserted w.e.f. 23.06.2006,
			<lb />
			specifically provides for identification of the arrested
			<lb />
			person. Section 55A of the CrPC, inserted w.e.f.
			<lb />
			31.12.2009, makes it the duty of the person, having the
			<lb />
			custody of the person, to take reasonable care of the health
			<lb />
			and safety. Section 56 of the CrPC makes it the duty of the
			<lb />
			Police Officer, arresting without warrant, to produce the
			<lb />
			person arrested before a Magistrate having jurisdiction
			<lb />
			without unnecessary delay or before the Officer In-charge
			<lb />
			of a Police Station. This is, no doubt, subject to the
			<lb />
			provisions as to Bail. Section 57 of the CrPC, reads as
			<lb />
			follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;57. Person arrested not to be detained more
			<lb />
			than twenty-four hours. No police officer
			<lb />
			shall detain in custody a person arrested
			<lb />
			without warrant for a longer period than
			<lb />
			under all the circumstances of the case is
			<lb />
			reasonable, and such period shall not, in the
			<lb />
			absence of a special order of a Magistrate
			<lb />
			under section 167, exceed twenty-four hours
			<lb />
			exclusive of the time necessary for the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			114
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			journey from the place of arrest to the
			<lb />
			Magistrate&apos; s Court.&quot;
			<lb />
			87. The Officer In-charge of Police Station is to report
			<lb />
			about all persons arrested without warrant to the District
			<lb />
			Magistrate or the Sub-Divisional Magistrate as directed by
			<lb />
			the District Magistrate. Section 59 of the CrPC provides
			<lb />
			that no person, who has been arrested by a Police Officer,
			<lb />
			shall be discharged, except on his own bond or on Bail or
			<lb />
			under the Special Order of the Magistrate. Section 60A of
			<lb />
			the CrPC provides that no arrest is to be made, except in
			<lb />
			accordance with the provisions of the CrPC or any other law
			<lb />
			being in force, providing for arrest. Chapter XI of the CrPC
			<lb />
			provides for preventive action of the Police. Section 151
			<lb />
			of the CrPC, inter alia, empowers a Police Officer, knowing
			<lb />
			of a design by a person to commit a cognizable offence, to
			<lb />
			arrest him without orders from a Magistrate and without a
			<lb />
			warrant. Section 157 of the CrPC provides, inter alia, that
			<lb />
			the Police Officer, proceeding to investigate a case, may
			<lb />
			take measures for the arrest of the offender. Section 167
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			115
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			of the CrPC deals with a case where investigation is not
			<lb />
			completed within twenty-four hours, as fixed in Section 57
			<lb />
			of the CrPC. It provides that in such a situation, if there
			<lb />
			are grounds for believing that the accusation or
			<lb />
			information is well founded, the person arrested, is to be
			<lb />
			forwarded to the Magistrate, inter alia. Section 167
			<lb />
			empowers Magistrate to order remand of the accused person,
			<lb />
			as provided therein.
			<lb />
			A FEW WORDS ABOUT THE PROVISIONS AS TO BAIL
			<lb />
			88. Chapter XXXIII of the CrPC deals with Bail. Section 436
			<lb />
			of the CrPC deals with Bail in the case of an arrest of a
			<lb />
			person accused of a bailable offence. There is a Statutory
			<lb />
			Right to Bail in the manner provided therein. Section 437
			<lb />
			of the CrPC provides for Bail in the case of a non-bailable
			<lb />
			offence. It, essentially, deals with a situation where a
			<lb />
			person is brought before a court other than the High Court
			<lb />
			or Court of Sessions. There are certain restrictions and
			<lb />
			conditions to be fulfilled in the matter of grant of Bail
			<lb />
			on the Court, as is stated therein.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			116
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			89. Section 439 of the CrPC, confers special powers on the
			<lb />
			High Court or the Court of Sessions in regard to Bail. It
			<lb />
			reads as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;439. Special powers of High Court or Court
			<lb />
			of Session regarding bail.
			<lb />
			(1) A High Court or Court of Session may
			<lb />
			direct-
			<lb />
			(a) that any person accused of an offence and
			<lb />
			in custody be released on bail, and if the
			<lb />
			offence is of the nature specified in
			<lb />
			subsection (3) of section 437, may impose any
			<lb />
			condition which it considers necessary for
			<lb />
			the purposes mentioned in that sub-section;
			<lb />
			(b) that any condition imposed by a
			<lb />
			Magistrate when releasing an person on bail
			<lb />
			be set aside or modified: Provided that the
			<lb />
			High Court or the Court of Session shall,
			<lb />
			before granting bail to a person who is
			<lb />
			accused of an offence which is triable
			<lb />
			exclusively by the Court of Session or which,
			<lb />
			though not so triable, is punishable with
			<lb />
			imprisonment for life, give notice of the
			<lb />
			application for bail to the Public Prosecutor
			<lb />
			unless it is, for reasons to be recorded in
			<lb />
			writing, of opinion that it is not
			<lb />
			practicable to give such notice.
			<lb />
			(2) A High Court or Court of Session may
			<lb />
			direct that any person who has been released
			<lb />
			on bail under this Chapter be arrested and
			<lb />
			commit him to custody.&quot;
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			117
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			90. Section 36AC of the Act, around which much arguments
			<lb />
			were addressed reads as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;36AC. Offences to be cognizable and
			<lb />
			non-bailable
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			certain
			<lb />
			cases.
			<lb />
			-
			<lb />
			(1) Notwithstanding anything contained in
			<lb />
			the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of
			<lb />
			1974),-
			<lb />
			(a) every offence, relating to adulterated
			<lb />
			or spurious drug and punishable under clauses
			<lb />
			(a) and (c) of sub-section (1) of section 13,
			<lb />
			clause (a) of sub-section (2) of section 13,
			<lb />
			sub-section (3) of section 22, clauses (a)
			<lb />
			and (c) of section 27, section 28, section
			<lb />
			28A, section 28B and sub-sections (1) and (2)
			<lb />
			of section 30 and other offences relating to
			<lb />
			adulterated drugs or spurious drugs, shall be
			<lb />
			cognizable.
			<lb />
			(b) no person accused, of an offence
			<lb />
			punishable under clauses (a) and (c) of
			<lb />
			sub-section (1) of section 13, clause (a) of
			<lb />
			sub-section (2) of section 13, sub-section
			<lb />
			(3) of section 22, clauses (a) and (c) of
			<lb />
			section 27, section 28, section 28A, section
			<lb />
			28B and sub-sections (1) and (2) of section
			<lb />
			30 and other offences relating to adulterated
			<lb />
			drugs or spurious drugs, shall be released on
			<lb />
			bail or on his own bond unless-
			<lb />
			(i) the Public Prosecutor has been given an
			<lb />
			opportunity to oppose the application for
			<lb />
			such release; and
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			118
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			(ii) where the Public Prosecutor opposes the
			<lb />
			application, the Court is satisfied that
			<lb />
			there are reasonable grounds for believing
			<lb />
			that he is not guilty of such offence and that
			<lb />
			he is not likely to commit any offence while
			<lb />
			on bail:
			<lb />
			Provided that a person, who, is under the age
			<lb />
			of sixteen years, or is a woman or is sick or
			<lb />
			infirm, may be released on bail, if the
			<lb />
			Special Court so directs.
			<lb />
			(2) The limitation on granting of bail
			<lb />
			specified in clause (b) of sub-section (1) is
			<lb />
			in addition to the limitations under the Code
			<lb />
			of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) or any
			<lb />
			other law for the time being in force on
			<lb />
			granting of bail.
			<lb />
			(3) Nothing contained in this section shall be
			<lb />
			deemed to affect the special powers of the High
			<lb />
			Court regarding bail under section 439 of the
			<lb />
			Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)
			<lb />
			and the High Court may exercise such powers
			<lb />
			including the power under clause (b) of
			<lb />
			sub-section (1) of that section as if the
			<lb />
			reference to &quot;Magistrate&quot; in that section
			<lb />
			includes also a reference to a &quot;Special Court&quot;
			<lb />
			designated under section 36AB.&quot;
			<lb />
			91. The learned Counsel for the Union of India would submit
			<lb />
			that the Inspector, under Section 32 of the Act, cannot be
			<lb />
			treated as a Police Officer who has the power to arrest under
			<lb />
			the CrPC. Reliance is placed on Badaku Joti Savant v. State
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			119
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			of Mysore 17 . Similarly, support is drawn from Raj Kumar
			<lb />
			Karwal v. Union of India and others 18 . Reliance is also
			<lb />
			placed on Ramesh Chandra Mehta v. State of W.B. 19 , Illias
			<lb />
			v. Collector of Customs, Madras 20 , State of U.P. v. Durga
			<lb />
			Prasad 21 and Balkishan A. Devidayal v. State of
			<lb />
			Maharashtra 22 . These decisions, apparently, are relied on
			<lb />
			to show that Officers of Department, including the
			<lb />
			Directorate of Revenue Intelligence (DRI), invested with
			<lb />
			powers of investigation under the Narcotic Drugs and
			<lb />
			Psychotropic Substances Act, 1985, Customs Act, 1962 and
			<lb />
			under the Railway Property (Unlawful Possession) Act, 1966,
			<lb />
			are not Police Officers. It is, therefore, the case of the
			<lb />
			petitioner that important indispensable attribute of a
			<lb />
			Police Officer is not only authority to investigate but to
			<lb />
			also have power to file a Report under Section 173 of the
			<lb />
			CrPC.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place='footnote'>
			17 (1966) 3 SCR 698
			<lb />
			18 (1990) 2 SCC 409
			<lb />
			19 (1969) 2 SCR 461
			<lb />
			20 (1969) 2 SCR 613
			<lb />
			21 (1975) 3 SCC 210
			<lb />
			22 (1980) 4 SCC 600
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			120
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			92. It is further contended that unlike the Prevention of
			<lb />
			Money-Laundering Act, 2002, which specially provides that
			<lb />
			&quot;no Police Officer can investigate into an offence under
			<lb />
			the Act&quot;, the Act in question is silent. The special
			<lb />
			provision must prevail in case of conflict with the general
			<lb />
			provision. In view of absence of specific powers on the
			<lb />
			Inspector under the Act, provisions of CrPC will prevail.
			<lb />
			A literal interpretation, according to the plain meaning
			<lb />
			of the language, is commended for our acceptance. The
			<lb />
			provisions of Section 36AC of the Act are emphasized before
			<lb />
			us treating offences thereunder as being cognizable and
			<lb />
			non-bailable. It is submitted that there is power to arrest
			<lb />
			with the Police. The judgment in Deepak Mahajan (supra) is
			<lb />
			sought to be distinguished. The implication of Section 36AC
			<lb />
			of the Act is that the offences set-out therein can be
			<lb />
			investigated by the Police. Therefore, Section 36AC will
			<lb />
			apply notwithstanding Section 32 of the Act. Otherwise, the
			<lb />
			intention of the Legislature, in making the offence
			<lb />
			cognizable and, at the same time, to denude the Police of
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			121
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			the power to prosecute, would be a contradiction. It is
			<lb />
			pointed out that before Section 36AC of the Act, the
			<lb />
			offences relating to adulterated and spurious drugs under
			<lb />
			the Act, were non-cognizable offences. It is also contended
			<lb />
			that Section 36AC of the Act now makes an exception by
			<lb />
			empowering the Police to investigate and consequently
			<lb />
			prosecute for the offences specifically set-out in Section
			<lb />
			36AC. It is pointed out that the offences set-out in Section
			<lb />
			36AC, other than the offences relating to adulterated drugs
			<lb />
			and spurious drugs, could not have been considered
			<lb />
			cognizable in terms of Schedule I Part 2 of the CrPC. Except
			<lb />
			Section 27A and 27C and Section 30(1) of the Act, all other
			<lb />
			provisions mentioned in Section 36AC of the Act, were
			<lb />
			non-cognizable offences as per Schedule I Part 2 of the
			<lb />
			CrPC. But having regard to the amended Section 36AC of the
			<lb />
			Act, it is the special provisions in Section 36AC, which
			<lb />
			will prevail.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			122
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			THE SUBMISSIONS OF THE LEARNED AMICUS IN REGARD TO ARREST.
			<lb />
			93. When the Court pointed out that there is no express
			<lb />
			power on the Drugs Inspector under the Act to arrest and
			<lb />
			when an arrest is effected, whether it becomes necessary
			<lb />
			to register an FIR under Section 154 of the CrPC. The learned
			<lb />
			Amicus Curiae submitted as follows:
			<lb />
			He agreed that for a person to be released on
			<lb />
			Bail, he should have been remanded to custody. He
			<lb />
			should further have been arrested under Section 157
			<lb />
			of the CrPC in order that he be remanded under
			<lb />
			Section 167 of the CrPC. If he is arrested under
			<lb />
			Section 41(1) of the CrPC, immediately thereafter,
			<lb />
			a case should be registered and he should be sent
			<lb />
			to the Court seeking remand. Any case registered
			<lb />
			under Section 154 or 155 of the CrPC, is to culminate
			<lb />
			in the Report under Section 173(2) of the CrPC. There
			<lb />
			is no other way for giving disposal to the case.
			<lb />
			Filing of such a Final Report under Section 190 of
			<lb />
			the CrPC is to take cognizance, and since Section
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			123
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			32 of the Act would bar such cognizance, no purpose
			<lb />
			would be served in registering the case. The
			<lb />
			Legislative intent, under Section 32 of the Act,
			<lb />
			cannot be diluted. The Police Officer, therefore,
			<lb />
			cannot arrest under Section 157 of the CrPC. While
			<lb />
			introducing Section 36AC, the Legislature was
			<lb />
			presumed to know the bar in Section 32. There is an
			<lb />
			inconsistency between Section 32 and Section 36AC,
			<lb />
			though they were amended/introduced by the same
			<lb />
			amendment. It becomes the duty of the Court to avoid
			<lb />
			a head-on clash between the two Sections. It is
			<lb />
			contended
			<lb />
			that
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Court
			<lb />
			must
			<lb />
			effect
			<lb />
			reconciliation. Reliance is placed on judgment of
			<lb />
			this Court in D. Sanjeevayya v. Election Tribunal,
			<lb />
			Andhra Pradesh and others 23 .
			<lb />
			94. Learned Amicus Curiae further submits that Section 21
			<lb />
			of the Act speaks of the &quot;Appointment of the Inspectors&quot;.
			<lb />
			The qualifications of Inspectors are provided in Rule 49
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place='footnote'>
			23 AIR 1967 SC 1211
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			124
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			of the Drugs and Cosmetics Rules. They are Experts in the
			<lb />
			subjects so far as the powers are provided in Sections 22
			<lb />
			and 23 of the Act. The provisions in Section 23 are
			<lb />
			mandatory. The Act provides for getting a Report on the
			<lb />
			sample and the accused is also enabled to seek a Second
			<lb />
			Report from the Central Laboratory. The Police Officer may
			<lb />
			not have the qualifications. He may not know how to draw
			<lb />
			the sample. The procedure can be meaningfully followed only
			<lb />
			by the Inspectors. Legislature did not intend to give
			<lb />
			similar powers to the Police. It is further contended that
			<lb />
			if it is held that the Police can file a Final Report, upon
			<lb />
			which cognizance can be taken, it will make Section 32 of
			<lb />
			the Act non-existent. Similarly, in an attempt to interpret
			<lb />
			Section 36AC, if the Police is conferred with the power to
			<lb />
			arrest, it will lead to authorizing the Police to also
			<lb />
			register the case under Section 154 of the CrPC and to file
			<lb />
			a Final Report under Section 173(2) of the CrPC. It is
			<lb />
			difficult to harmonise Section 32 and Section 36AC of the
			<lb />
			Act, it is pointed out. The learned Amicus Curiae draws our
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			125
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			attention to the following observations of this Court in
			<lb />
			Sultana Begum v. Prem Chand Jain 24 :
			<lb />
			&quot;11. The statute has to be read as a whole to
			<lb />
			find out the real intention of the
			<lb />
			legislature.
			<lb />
			12. In Canada
			<lb />
			Sugar
			<lb />
			Refining
			<lb />
			Co. v. R. [1898 AC 735 : 67 LJPC 126] , Lord
			<lb />
			Davy observed:
			<lb />
			&quot;Every clause of a statute should be
			<lb />
			construed with reference to the context
			<lb />
			and other clauses of the Act, so as, as
			<lb />
			far as possible, to make a consistent
			<lb />
			enactment of the whole statute or series
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			statutes
			<lb />
			relating
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			subject-matter.&quot;
			<lb />
			13. This Court has adopted the same rule
			<lb />
			in M. Pentiah v. Muddala Veeramallappa [AIR
			<lb />
			1961 SC 1107 : (1961) 2 SCR 295] ; Gammon
			<lb />
			India Ltd. v. Union of India [(1974) 1 SCC
			<lb />
			596 : 1974 SCC (L&amp;S) 252 : AIR 1974 SC 960]
			<lb />
			; Mysore
			<lb />
			SRTC v. Mirja
			<lb />
			Khasim
			<lb />
			Ali
			<lb />
			Beg [(1977) 2 SCC 457 : 1974 SCC (L&amp;S) 282 :
			<lb />
			AIR 1977 SC 747] ; V. Tulasamma v. Sesha
			<lb />
			Reddy [(1977) 3 SCC 99 : AIR 1977 SC 1944]
			<lb />
			; Punjab
			<lb />
			Beverages
			<lb />
			(P)
			<lb />
			Ltd. v. Suresh
			<lb />
			Chand [(1978) 2 SCC 144 : 1978 SCC (L&amp;S) 165
			<lb />
			: AIR 1978 SC 995] ; CIT v. National Taj
			<lb />
			Traders [(1980) 1 SCC 370 : 1980 SCC (Tax) 124
			<lb />
			: AIR 1980 SC 485] ; Calcutta Gas Co.
			<lb />
			(Proprietary) Ltd. v. State of W.B. [AIR
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place='footnote'>
			24
			<lb />
			(1997) 1 SCC 373
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			126
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			1962 SC 1044 : 1962 Supp (3) SCR 1] and J.K.
			<lb />
			Cotton Spg. &amp; Wvg. Mills Co. Ltd. v. State of
			<lb />
			U.P. [AIR 1961 SC 1170 : (1961) 1 LLJ 540]
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			15. On a conspectus of the case-law
			<lb />
			indicated above, the following principles
			<lb />
			are clearly discernible:
			<lb />
			(1) It is the duty of the courts to avoid
			<lb />
			a head-on clash between two sections of the
			<lb />
			Act and to construe the provisions which
			<lb />
			appear to be in conflict with each other
			<lb />
			in such a manner as to harmonise them.
			<lb />
			(2) The provisions of one section of a
			<lb />
			statute cannot be used to defeat the other
			<lb />
			provisions unless the court, in spite of
			<lb />
			its efforts, finds it impossible to effect
			<lb />
			reconciliation between them.
			<lb />
			(3) It has to be borne in mind by all the
			<lb />
			courts all the time that when there are two
			<lb />
			conflicting provisions in an Act, which
			<lb />
			cannot be reconciled with each other, they
			<lb />
			should be so interpreted that, if
			<lb />
			possible, effect should be given to
			<lb />
			both. This is the essence of the rule of
			<lb />
			&quot;harmonious construction&quot;.
			<lb />
			(4) The courts have also to keep in mind
			<lb />
			that an interpretation which reduces one
			<lb />
			of the provisions as a &quot;dead letter&quot; or
			<lb />
			&quot;useless lumber&quot; is not harmonious
			<lb />
			construction.
			<lb />
			(5) To harmonise is not to destroy any
			<lb />
			statutory provision or to render it
			<lb />
			otiose.&quot;
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			127
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			95. Police cannot arrest as there can be no investigation
			<lb />
			by the Police. Section 36AC of the Act stipulates stringent
			<lb />
			conditions for granting Bail. It can be made applicable when
			<lb />
			the accused is remanded to the custody by the Magistrate
			<lb />
			while committing the case to the Sessions Court.
			<lb />
			96. As regards Section 41 of the CrPC, the learned Amicus
			<lb />
			Curiae would point out that empowering the Police to arrest
			<lb />
			in respect of cognizable offence, under the said
			<lb />
			provisions, being a general provision, may not be
			<lb />
			countenanced as the general provisions are overridden by
			<lb />
			the provisions of the Act. Again, arrest under Section 41
			<lb />
			of the CrPC must be followed by the registration of the case
			<lb />
			under Section 154 of the CrPC, which is not possible in view
			<lb />
			of Section 32 of the Act. The learned Amicus Curiae also
			<lb />
			voices the apprehension that if power to arrest is conferred
			<lb />
			on the Police Officer, under Section 41, then, in every
			<lb />
			special enactment, such as the Food Adulteration Act,
			<lb />
			Income-Tax Act, Food Safety and Standards Act, Customs Act,
			<lb />
			etc., the Police will arrest under Section 41 of the CrPC,
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			128
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			register a case and file a Final Report. The special
			<lb />
			provisions of those Acts, restricting cognizance only on
			<lb />
			the basis of a complaint, would be rendered nugatory.
			<lb />
			97. The learned Amicus Curiae would also submit that though
			<lb />
			there is no specific provision empowering the Drugs
			<lb />
			Inspector to arrest, Section 22(1)(d) of the Act may be
			<lb />
			interpreted and it be held that the Inspector has power
			<lb />
			to arrest. In this regard, reliance is placed on Deepak
			<lb />
			Mahajan (supra).
			<lb />
			ANALYSIS
			<lb />
			98. The arrest of a person involves an encroachment on his
			<lb />
			personal liberty. Article 21 of the Constitution of India
			<lb />
			declares that no person shall be deprived of his personal
			<lb />
			liberty and life except in accordance with procedure
			<lb />
			established by law. There can be no doubt that the power
			<lb />
			to arrest any person therefore must be premised on a law
			<lb />
			which authorizes the same.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			129
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			99. Under the Act, as noted by us, and bearing in mind the
			<lb />
			law laid down in connection with similar Statutes, we have
			<lb />
			no hesitation in rejecting the argument of the petitioner
			<lb />
			that after the amendment of Section 36AC of the Act, making
			<lb />
			the offences cognizable and non-bailable, it is open to the
			<lb />
			Police Officer to prosecute the person for the offences
			<lb />
			set-out in Section 36AC of the Act. Having regard to the
			<lb />
			express provisions of Section 32 of the Act, insofar as the
			<lb />
			prosecution is to be launched qua offences falling within
			<lb />
			the four walls of Chapter IV of the Act, and which are also
			<lb />
			the subject matter of Section 36AC of the Act, there cannot
			<lb />
			be any doubt that prosecution of the offender, for such
			<lb />
			offences, can be done only in the manner provided in Section
			<lb />
			32 of the Act. The prosecution can be launched only by the
			<lb />
			persons mentioned in Section 32 of the Act. A Police
			<lb />
			Officer, as such, does not figure as one of the persons who
			<lb />
			may prefer a report under Section 173(2) of the CrPC, on
			<lb />
			which, cognizance could be taken by the Special Court.
			<lb />
			Undoubtedly, as we have already clarified in respect of an
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			130
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			offence under Chapter IV, if the acts or omission also
			<lb />
			constitutes an offence under any other law, under Section
			<lb />
			32(3) of the Act, it may be open to the Police Officer, if
			<lb />
			he is otherwise empowered under the said law, to prosecute
			<lb />
			the person for the same offence, to act as such.
			<lb />
			100.
			<lb />
			Consequently, the registration of an FIR, which
			<lb />
			under the scheme of the CrPC, sets the ball rolling,
			<lb />
			empowering the Police Officer to investigate under Section
			<lb />
			157 of the CrPC, and gather material and finally file a
			<lb />
			Report, would all appear to us to be inapplicable to an
			<lb />
			offence under Chapter IV of the Act.
			<lb />
			101.
			<lb />
			The conundrum, however, is posed by the aspect
			<lb />
			relating to arrest. Undoubtedly, there is no express power
			<lb />
			on the Inspector to arrest under the Act. The argument of
			<lb />
			the learned Additional Solicitor General, Ms. Pinky Anand
			<lb />
			that the Drugs Inspector could not be a Police Officer as
			<lb />
			he is not a person who can file a Report under Section 173
			<lb />
			of the CrPC and, therefore, he cannot arrest, does not
			<lb />
			appeal to us. The decisions relied upon by the learned
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			131
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Counsel, referred to by us in paragraph-91 hereinbefore,
			<lb />
			only declare that the Customs Officer under the Customs Act
			<lb />
			and the other officers in the enactments, which we have
			<lb />
			referred to, are not Police Officers in the context of
			<lb />
			Section 25 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (hereinafter
			<lb />
			referred to as &apos;the Evidence Act&apos;, for short). Section 25
			<lb />
			of the Evidence Act renders inadmissible a confession made
			<lb />
			to a Police Officer. The question here is not whether the
			<lb />
			Drugs Inspector is a Police Officer and the question here
			<lb />
			is whether he is empowered to carry out arrest of a person
			<lb />
			under the Act. Still further, the question to be answered
			<lb />
			is, whether a Police officer under the CrPC is deprived of
			<lb />
			his power, under the CrPC, to arrest. These are the
			<lb />
			questions to be answered by us.
			<lb />
			102.
			<lb />
			The Court must start with the presumption that
			<lb />
			Parliament, which is author of the CrPC and also the Act
			<lb />
			in question, was aware of the provisions of the CrPC, as
			<lb />
			it existed at the time when the Act was enacted in 1940.
			<lb />
			This is following the principle that the Legislature must
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			132
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			be assumed to know the law which exists on the Statute Book
			<lb />
			when it makes a new law. It must, therefore, be assumed to
			<lb />
			know that the power of arrest is expressly conferred on the
			<lb />
			Police Officer in the manner which we have referred to. The
			<lb />
			Legislature has not, in the Act, yet conferred express power
			<lb />
			on the Drugs inspector, to arrest. However, Section
			<lb />
			22(1)(d) of the Act, which deals with the powers of the
			<lb />
			Inspector, inter alia, enables the Inspector to exercise
			<lb />
			such other powers as may be necessary for carrying out the
			<lb />
			purpose of Chapter IV or any Rules made thereunder. The
			<lb />
			sanction, which is contemplated under Chapter IV, is the
			<lb />
			criminal sanction by way of prosecuting a person for
			<lb />
			contravening the provisions of Chapter IV of the Act. In
			<lb />
			other words, the Legislature has given teeth to the law by
			<lb />
			providing for prosecuting offenders. The Inspector is at
			<lb />
			the center stage. In every other aspect, as can be seen from
			<lb />
			the Act, the implementation of its provisions is vitally
			<lb />
			dependent upon the powers and functions assigned to the
			<lb />
			Inspector. The very qualifications, which are provided in
			<lb />
			the Rules, as indispensable for being appointed as an
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			133
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Inspector, represents a carefully chosen value judgment by
			<lb />
			the Legislature to assign the implementation of the Act
			<lb />
			through the competent hands of qualified persons. The Act
			<lb />
			is enacted to achieve the highest public interest in as much
			<lb />
			as what is at stake is the health of the members of the
			<lb />
			public, which again is recognized as one of the aspects
			<lb />
			covered by the Fundamental Right protected under Article
			<lb />
			21 of the Constitution of India. Keeping the Police Officer
			<lb />
			out from the categories of persons, who could prosecute
			<lb />
			offenders for offences under Chapter IV of the Act, is also
			<lb />
			a carefully thought out ideal.
			<lb />
			THE DECISION OF THIS COURT IN DIRECTORATE OF ENFORCEMENT
			<lb />
			V. DEEPAK MAHAJAN AND ANOTHER 25
			<lb />
			103.
			<lb />
			In Deepak Mahajan (supra), the question arose in
			<lb />
			the context of provisions of Section 35 of the Foreign
			<lb />
			Exchange Regulation Act, 1973 (FERA) and Section 104 of the
			<lb />
			Customs Act, 1962, which expressly conferred power of
			<lb />
			arrest on the Officers under the Acts. The question which
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place='footnote'>
			25 (1994) 3 SCC 440
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			134
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			squarely arose was whether upon arrest being effected under
			<lb />
			Section 35 of the FERA and Section 104 of the Customs Act,
			<lb />
			a remand could be ordered under Section 167(2) of the CrPC.
			<lb />
			In the course of discussion, the Court proceeded to hold
			<lb />
			that the CrPC gives power of arrest not only to the Police
			<lb />
			Officer, but to a Magistrate and also under certain
			<lb />
			circumstances or given situations to private persons. It
			<lb />
			went on to hold that in every arrest there is custody but
			<lb />
			not vice-versa. It further held as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;54. The above deliberation leads to a
			<lb />
			derivation that to invoke Section 167(1), it
			<lb />
			is not an indispensable pre-requisite
			<lb />
			condition that in all circumstances, the
			<lb />
			arrest should have been effected only by a
			<lb />
			police officer and none else and that there
			<lb />
			must necessarily be records of entries of a
			<lb />
			case diary. Therefore, it necessarily
			<lb />
			follows that a mere production of an arrestee
			<lb />
			before a competent Magistrate by an
			<lb />
			authorised officer or an officer empowered to
			<lb />
			arrest (notwithstanding the fact that he is
			<lb />
			not a police officer in its stricto sensu) on
			<lb />
			a reasonable belief that the arrestee &quot;has
			<lb />
			been guilty of an offence punishable&quot; under
			<lb />
			the provisions of the special Act is
			<lb />
			sufficient for the Magistrate to take that
			<lb />
			person into his custody on his being
			<lb />
			satisfied
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			three
			<lb />
			preliminary
			<lb />
			conditions, namely (1) the arresting officer
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			135
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			is legally competent to make the arrest; (2)
			<lb />
			that the particulars of the offence or the
			<lb />
			accusation for which the person is arrested
			<lb />
			or other grounds for such arrest do exist and
			<lb />
			are well-founded; and (3) that the provisions
			<lb />
			of the special Act in regard to the arrest of
			<lb />
			the persons and the production of the
			<lb />
			arrestee serve the purpose of Section 167(1)
			<lb />
			of the Code.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			104.
			<lb />
			Section 35(2) in FERA and Section 104(2) of the
			<lb />
			Customs Act, provided that the person arrested was to be
			<lb />
			taken before a Magistrate without unnecessary delay. As
			<lb />
			regards the power to detain the person arrested under
			<lb />
			Section 167(2) of the CRPC, it was held as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;102. From the foregoing discussion, it is
			<lb />
			clear that the word &apos;accused&apos; or &apos;accused
			<lb />
			person&apos; is used only in a generic sense in
			<lb />
			Section 167(1) and (2) denoting the &apos;person&apos;
			<lb />
			whose liberty is actually restrained on his
			<lb />
			arrest
			<lb />
			by
			<lb />
			a
			<lb />
			competent
			<lb />
			authority
			<lb />
			on
			<lb />
			well-founded
			<lb />
			information
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			formal
			<lb />
			accusation or indictment. Therefore, the
			<lb />
			word &apos;accused&apos; limited to the scope of
			<lb />
			Section 167(1) and (2) -particularly in the
			<lb />
			light of Explanation to Section 273 of the
			<lb />
			Code includes &apos;any person arrested&apos;. The
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			136
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			inevitable consequence that follows is that
			<lb />
			&quot;any person is arrested&quot; occurring in the
			<lb />
			first limb of Section 167(1) of the Code takes
			<lb />
			within its ambit &quot;every person arrested&quot;
			<lb />
			under Section 35 of FERA or Section 104 of the
			<lb />
			Customs Act also as the case may be and the
			<lb />
			&apos;person arrested&apos; can be detained by the
			<lb />
			Magistrate in exercise of his power under
			<lb />
			Section 167(2) of the Code. In other words,
			<lb />
			the &apos;person arrested&apos; under FERA or Customs
			<lb />
			Act is assimilated with the characteristics
			<lb />
			of an &apos;accused&apos; within the range of Section
			<lb />
			167(1) and as such liable to be detained under
			<lb />
			Section 167(2) by a Magistrate when produced
			<lb />
			before him.&quot;
			<lb />
			105.
			<lb />
			The Court went on to consider the impact of other
			<lb />
			laws in regard to the scope of the expression &quot;Police
			<lb />
			Officer&quot;. It held as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;111. Neither the Police Act, 1861 (Act V
			<lb />
			of 1861) nor any other statute defines the
			<lb />
			expression &apos;police officer&apos;. Shortly stated,
			<lb />
			the main duties of the police are the
			<lb />
			prevention, detention and investigation of
			<lb />
			crimes. As the powers and duties of the State
			<lb />
			have increased and are increasing manifold,
			<lb />
			various Acts dealing with Customs, Excise,
			<lb />
			Forest, Taxes etc. have come to be passed and
			<lb />
			consequently the prevention, detention and
			<lb />
			investigation of offences as prescribed
			<lb />
			under those Acts have come to be entrusted to
			<lb />
			officers
			<lb />
			with
			<lb />
			different
			<lb />
			nomenclatures
			<lb />
			appropriate to the subject with reference to
			<lb />
			which they function. However, as stated
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			137
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			supra, though the powers of customs officers
			<lb />
			and enforcement officers are not identical to
			<lb />
			those
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			police
			<lb />
			officers
			<lb />
			qua
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			investigation under Chapter XII of the Code
			<lb />
			yet the officers under the FERA and Customs
			<lb />
			Act are vested with certain powers similar to
			<lb />
			the powers of police officers.&quot;
			<lb />
			106.
			<lb />
			Section 167(1) of the CrPC contemplates forwarding
			<lb />
			the diary which was interpreted to be not the general diary
			<lb />
			and the special diary under Section 167(2) of the CrPC. In
			<lb />
			regard to the enactments in question, this Court held as
			<lb />
			follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;113. Though an authorised officer of
			<lb />
			Enforcement or Customs is not undertaking an
			<lb />
			investigation as contemplated under Chapter
			<lb />
			XII of the Code, yet those officers are
			<lb />
			enjoying some analogous powers such as
			<lb />
			arrest,
			<lb />
			seizures,
			<lb />
			interrogation
			<lb />
			etc.
			<lb />
			Besides, a statutory duty is enjoined on them
			<lb />
			to inform the arrestee of the grounds for such
			<lb />
			arrest as contemplated under Article 22(1) of
			<lb />
			the Constitution and Section 50 of the Code.
			<lb />
			Therefore, they have necessarily to make
			<lb />
			records of their statutory functions showing
			<lb />
			the name of the informant, as well as the name
			<lb />
			of the person who violated any other
			<lb />
			provision of the Code and who has been guilty
			<lb />
			of an offence punishable under the Act,
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			138
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			nature of information received by them, time
			<lb />
			of the arrest, seizure of the contraband if
			<lb />
			any and the statements recorded during the
			<lb />
			course
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			detection
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			offence/offences.&quot;
			<lb />
			107.
			<lb />
			It also found the following powers available under
			<lb />
			five Central enactments:
			<lb />
			Sl.
			<lb />
			No.
			<lb />
			Name of the Act Power
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			search
			<lb />
			premises
			<lb />
			Power
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			search
			<lb />
			suspected
			<lb />
			persons,
			<lb />
			entering
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			leaving India
			<lb />
			Power to
			<lb />
			search
			<lb />
			persons
			<lb />
			1
			<lb />
			2
			<lb />
			3
			<lb />
			4
			<lb />
			5
			<lb />
			1. Foreign
			<lb />
			Exchange
			<lb />
			Regulation Act,
			<lb />
			1973
			<lb />
			Sec. 37
			<lb />
			Sec. 34
			<lb />
			Sec. 34
			<lb />
			2. The Customs Act Sec. 105
			<lb />
			Sec. 100
			<lb />
			Sec. 101
			<lb />
			3. The
			<lb />
			Gold
			<lb />
			(Control)
			<lb />
			Act
			<lb />
			(now repealed)
			<lb />
			Sec. 58
			<lb />
			-
			<lb />
			Sec. 60
			<lb />
			4. The Prevention
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			Food
			<lb />
			Adulteration
			<lb />
			Act.
			<lb />
			Sec. 10(2) S. 6 to be r/w
			<lb />
			S. 18 or the
			<lb />
			Sea
			<lb />
			Customs
			<lb />
			Act.
			<lb />
			-
			<lb />
			5. The
			<lb />
			Railway
			<lb />
			Property
			<lb />
			(Unlawful
			<lb />
			Possession)
			<lb />
			Act.
			<lb />
			Sec.
			<lb />
			10
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			Sec.
			<lb />
			11
			<lb />
			-
			<lb />
			-
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			139
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Power to stop
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			search
			<lb />
			conveyances
			<lb />
			Power
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			seize
			<lb />
			goods,
			<lb />
			documents
			<lb />
			etc.
			<lb />
			Power to
			<lb />
			arrest.
			<lb />
			Power to
			<lb />
			examine
			<lb />
			persons
			<lb />
			Power
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			summon
			<lb />
			persons
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			give
			<lb />
			evidence and
			<lb />
			produce
			<lb />
			documents
			<lb />
			6
			<lb />
			7
			<lb />
			8
			<lb />
			9
			<lb />
			10
			<lb />
			Sec. 36
			<lb />
			Sec. 38
			<lb />
			Sec. 35 Sec. 39 Sec. 40
			<lb />
			Sec. 106
			<lb />
			Sec. 110
			<lb />
			Sec. 104 Sec. 107 Sec. 108
			<lb />
			Sec. 61
			<lb />
			Sec. 66
			<lb />
			Sec. 68 Sec. 64 Sec. 63
			<lb />
			-
			<lb />
			Sec. 10
			<lb />
			Sec.
			<lb />
			10(B)
			<lb />
			-
			<lb />
			-
			<lb />
			-
			<lb />
			-
			<lb />
			Sec. 6
			<lb />
			-
			<lb />
			Sec. 9
			<lb />
			108.
			<lb />
			The Court further held as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;116. It should not be lost sight of the
			<lb />
			fact that a police officer making an
			<lb />
			investigation of an offence representing the
			<lb />
			State files a report under Section 173 of the
			<lb />
			Code and becomes the complainant whereas the
			<lb />
			prosecuting agency under the special Acts
			<lb />
			files a complaint as a complainant i.e. under
			<lb />
			Section 61(ii) in the case of FERA and under
			<lb />
			Section 137 of the Customs Act. To say
			<lb />
			differently, the police officer after
			<lb />
			consummation of the investigation files a
			<lb />
			report under Section 173 of the Code upon
			<lb />
			which the Magistrate may take cognizance of
			<lb />
			any offence disclosed in the report under
			<lb />
			Section 190(1)(b) of the Code whereas the
			<lb />
			empowered or authorised officer of the
			<lb />
			special Acts has to file only a complaint of
			<lb />
			facts constituting any offence under the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			140
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			provisions of the Act on the receipt of which
			<lb />
			the Magistrate may take cognizance of the
			<lb />
			said offence under Section 190(1)(a) of the
			<lb />
			Code. After taking cognizance of the offence
			<lb />
			either upon a police report or upon receiving
			<lb />
			a complaint of facts, the Magistrate has to
			<lb />
			proceed with the case as per the procedure
			<lb />
			prescribed under the Code or under the
			<lb />
			special procedure, if any, prescribed under
			<lb />
			the special Acts. Therefore, the word
			<lb />
			&apos;investigation&apos; cannot be limited only to
			<lb />
			police investigation but on the other hand,
			<lb />
			the said word is with wider connotation and
			<lb />
			flexible so as to include the investigation
			<lb />
			carried on by any agency whether he be a
			<lb />
			police officer or empowered or authorised
			<lb />
			officer or a person not being a police officer
			<lb />
			under the direction of a Magistrate to make
			<lb />
			an investigation vested with the power of
			<lb />
			investigation.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			109.
			<lb />
			In fact, as laid down in Deepak Mahajan (supra),
			<lb />
			the power of arrest can be conferred on persons other than
			<lb />
			a Police Officer. We are, for the moment, excluding the
			<lb />
			position under the CrPC that even a private person can
			<lb />
			arrest as provided in Section 43 of the CrPC. The Foreign
			<lb />
			Exchange Regulation Act, 1973 (hence repealed); the Customs
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			141
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Act, 1962; the Gold (Control) Act, 1968 (repealed); the
			<lb />
			Prevention of Food Adulteration Act, 1954 (hence repealed)
			<lb />
			and the Railway Property (Unlawful Possession) Act, 1966,
			<lb />
			in Sections 35, 104, 68, 10B and Section 6, respectively,
			<lb />
			conferred power of arrest on the Officers under these Acts.
			<lb />
			Therefore, if we interpret Section 22(1)(d) of the Act, as
			<lb />
			comprehending the power of arrest with the Drugs Inspector,
			<lb />
			then, his competency to arrest, a requirement in law, as
			<lb />
			laid down again in Deepak Mahajan (supra) (See
			<lb />
			paragraph-54), would stand satisfied. However, the further
			<lb />
			question is, what is the procedure to be followed by the
			<lb />
			Inspector, and still finally, whether the Police Officer,
			<lb />
			under the CrPC, will stand deprived of the power to arrest.
			<lb />
			The argument of the learned Amicus Curiae appears to be that
			<lb />
			since a Police Officer, once he registers an FIR under
			<lb />
			Section 154 of the CrPC, is duty-bound to carry the matter
			<lb />
			to its logical conclusion, viz., to investigate the matter
			<lb />
			as provided in the CrPC, and finally, file a Report under
			<lb />
			Section 173(2) of the CrPC, to persuade the Court to take
			<lb />
			cognizance in an appropriate case, all of which powers are
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			142
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			not available to a Police Officer in regard to offences
			<lb />
			under Chapter IV of the Act, the interpretation that avoids
			<lb />
			such a futile exercise, which also is unauthorized and
			<lb />
			illegal in law, should be adopted.
			<lb />
			110.
			<lb />
			We do agree with the learned Amicus Curie that the
			<lb />
			Police Officer, for instance, cannot be approached by any
			<lb />
			person with a complaint that a cognizable offence under
			<lb />
			Chapter IV of the Act has been committed and he is not bound
			<lb />
			to register the FIR in terms of the law which is being held
			<lb />
			down by this court in Lalita Kumari (supra). This is for
			<lb />
			the reason that if he were to register an FIR, then, he would
			<lb />
			have to pass on to the stage of Section 157 of the CrPC and,
			<lb />
			furthermore, carry out investigation, as understood in law,
			<lb />
			for which neither is he deemed qualified or empowered by
			<lb />
			the Law Giver nor is he entitled to file a Report under
			<lb />
			Section 173 of the CrPC.
			<lb />
			POWER OF ARREST UNDER THE ACT
			<lb />
			111.
			<lb />
			We are faced with a situation which projects a
			<lb />
			discord between two Statutes, viz., the CrPC and the Act,
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			143
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			and the only silver-lining appearing on the horizon, is the
			<lb />
			ambit of the power under Section 22(1)(d) of the Act. We
			<lb />
			may recapitulate the said provision, at this juncture. It
			<lb />
			reads as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;22. Powers of Inspectors. -(1) Subject to
			<lb />
			the provisions of section 23 and of any rules
			<lb />
			made by the Central Government in this
			<lb />
			behalf, an Inspector may, within the local
			<lb />
			limits of the area for which he is appointed,-
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			(d)
			<lb />
			Exercise such other powers as may be
			<lb />
			necessary for carrying out the purposes of
			<lb />
			this Chapter or any rules made there under.&quot;
			<lb />
			Apart from the same, there is no express power of arrest
			<lb />
			under the Act on the Drugs Inspector.
			<lb />
			SOME ENACTMENTS CONTAINING PROVISIONS SIMILAR TO SECTION
			<lb />
			22(1)(d) OF THE ACT
			<lb />
			112.
			<lb />
			We may notice that the Seeds Act, 1966 (Section
			<lb />
			14(1)(e), the Insecticides Act, 1968 (Section 21(f)), the
			<lb />
			Kerala Fish Seed Act, 2014 (Section 19(1)(e), Uttarakhand
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			144
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Ground Water (Regulation and Control of Development and
			<lb />
			Management) Act, 2016 [Section 13(1)(j)], contain
			<lb />
			provisions similar to what is contained in Section 22(1)(d)
			<lb />
			of the Act.
			<lb />
			113.
			<lb />
			The Weekly Holidays Act, 1942 [Section 8(1)(c)],
			<lb />
			the Jammu and Kashmir Factories Act, 1999 [Section
			<lb />
			9(1)(c)], contained provisions which confer power on the
			<lb />
			Authorities under the Act to exercise such other power as
			<lb />
			may be necessary for carrying outer purposes of the
			<lb />
			enactment. As far as the Shops and Commercial Establishment
			<lb />
			Act, 1958 [Section 19(1)(c)], after conferring the power
			<lb />
			to exercise such powers, as may be necessary for carrying
			<lb />
			out the Act, the Law Giver carves out a limitation by way
			<lb />
			of a proviso that no one shall be required, under the said
			<lb />
			Section, to answer any question or give any evidence tending
			<lb />
			to incriminate him. Such a proviso is also found in the
			<lb />
			Private Medical Establishment Act, 2007 [vide Section
			<lb />
			21(1)(b)] as also in the Jammu and Kashmir Factories Act,
			<lb />
			1999.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			145
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			SPECIFIC STATUTES CONFERRING POWERS OF ARREST; COGNIZABLE
			<lb />
			VERSUS NON-COGNIZABLE OFFENCE
			<lb />
			114.
			<lb />
			It is, however, relevant to notice the provisions
			<lb />
			of the enactments containing the power to arrest and
			<lb />
			referred to in Deepak Mahajan(supra). Section 104 of the
			<lb />
			Customs Act, 1962, at present, reads as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;104. Power to arrest. -(1) If an officer of
			<lb />
			customs empowered in this behalf by general
			<lb />
			or special order of the 3[Principal
			<lb />
			Commissioner of Customs or Commissioner of
			<lb />
			Customs] has reason to believe that any
			<lb />
			person in India or within the Indian customs
			<lb />
			waters has committed an offence punishable
			<lb />
			under section 132 or section 133 or section
			<lb />
			135 or section 135A or section 136, he may
			<lb />
			arrest such person and shall, as soon as may
			<lb />
			be, inform him of the grounds for such arrest.
			<lb />
			(2)
			<lb />
			Every
			<lb />
			person
			<lb />
			arrested
			<lb />
			under
			<lb />
			sub-section (1) shall, without unnecessary
			<lb />
			delay, be taken to a magistrate.
			<lb />
			(3)
			<lb />
			Where an officer of customs has
			<lb />
			arrested any person under sub-section (1), he
			<lb />
			shall, for the purpose of releasing such
			<lb />
			person on bail or otherwise, have the same
			<lb />
			powers and be subject to the same provisions
			<lb />
			as the officer-in-charge of a police-station
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			146
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			has and is subject to under the 4Code of
			<lb />
			Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898).
			<lb />
			(4) Notwithstanding anything contained in
			<lb />
			the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of
			<lb />
			1974), any offence relating to -
			<lb />
			(a) prohibited goods; or
			<lb />
			(b) evasion or attempted evasion of duty
			<lb />
			exceeding fifty lakh rupees,
			<lb />
			shall be cognizable.
			<lb />
			(5) Save
			<lb />
			as
			<lb />
			otherwise
			<lb />
			provided
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			sub-section (4), all other offences under the
			<lb />
			Act shall be non-cognizable.
			<lb />
			(6) Notwithstanding anything contained in
			<lb />
			the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973, (2 of
			<lb />
			1974) an offence punishable under section 135
			<lb />
			relating to -
			<lb />
			(a) evasion or attempted evasion of duty
			<lb />
			exceeding fifty lakh rupees; or
			<lb />
			(b) prohibited goods notified under section
			<lb />
			11 which are also notified under sub-clause
			<lb />
			(C) of clause (i) of sub-section (1) of
			<lb />
			section 135; or
			<lb />
			(c) import or export of any goods which have
			<lb />
			not been declared in accordance with the
			<lb />
			provisions of this Act and the market price
			<lb />
			of which exceeds one crore rupees; or
			<lb />
			(d) fraudulently availing of or attempt to
			<lb />
			avail of drawback or any exemption from duty
			<lb />
			provided under this Act, if the amount of
			<lb />
			drawback or exemption from duty exceeds fifty
			<lb />
			lakh rupees,
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			147
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			shall be non-bailable.
			<lb />
			(7) Save
			<lb />
			as
			<lb />
			otherwise
			<lb />
			provided
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			sub-section (6), all other offences under
			<lb />
			this Act shall be bailable. 26 &quot;
			<lb />
			115.
			<lb />
			Section 35 of the The Foreign Exchange Regulation
			<lb />
			Act (FERA), 1973 read as follows (FERA came to be repealed
			<lb />
			by The Foreign Exchange Management Act (FEMA), 1999]:
			<lb />
			&quot;35. Power to arrest.-(1) If any officer of
			<lb />
			Enforcement authorised in this behalf by the
			<lb />
			Central Government, by general or special
			<lb />
			order, has reason to believe that any person
			<lb />
			in India or within the Indian customs waters
			<lb />
			has been guilty of an offence punishable
			<lb />
			under this Act, he may arrest such person and
			<lb />
			26 Prior to 13.07.2006, when the present provision came to be
			<lb />
			substituted by Act 29 of 2006, the power to arrest was confined in
			<lb />
			relation to person about whom reason to believe was entertained that
			<lb />
			he had committed an offence under Section 135. As can be seen the
			<lb />
			power of arrest after 13.07.2006, has become more wide. Further, it
			<lb />
			is to be noticed, that Sections 104(4) was substituted by Act 23 of
			<lb />
			2012 w.e.f. 28.05.2012. Sub-Section (4) before substitution read as
			<lb />
			follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;4.[Notwithstanding anything contained in Code of Criminal
			<lb />
			Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898), an offence under this Act, shall not
			<lb />
			be cognizable. The change brought about by sub-Section (4) as
			<lb />
			substituted, is that the offences mentioned in sub-Section (4), have
			<lb />
			been declared to be cognizable. However, under Section 104(5), all
			<lb />
			other offences under the Act have been declared to be non-cognizable.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			148
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			shall, as soon as may be, inform him of the
			<lb />
			grounds for such arrest.
			<lb />
			(2) Every person arrested under sub-section
			<lb />
			(1) shall, without unnecessary delay, be
			<lb />
			taken to a magistrate.
			<lb />
			(3) Where any officer of Enforcement has
			<lb />
			arrested any person under sub-section (1), he
			<lb />
			shall, for the purpose of releasing such
			<lb />
			person on bail or otherwise, have the same
			<lb />
			powers and be subject to the same provisions
			<lb />
			as the officer-in-charge of a police station
			<lb />
			has, and is subject to, under the 1[Code of
			<lb />
			Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)].&quot;
			<lb />
			116.
			<lb />
			Section 68 of the Gold (Control) Act, 1968 (which
			<lb />
			also stands repealed in 1990), read as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;68. Power to arrest.
			<lb />
			(1) Any Gold Control Officer authorised by
			<lb />
			the Administrator in this behalf may, if he
			<lb />
			has reasons to believe that any person has
			<lb />
			contravened, or is contravening, or is about
			<lb />
			to contravene any provision of this Act,
			<lb />
			arrest such person and shall as soon as
			<lb />
			possible inform him of the grounds for such
			<lb />
			arrest and shall take such arrested person to
			<lb />
			the nearest magistrate within a period of
			<lb />
			twenty-four hours of such arrest excluding
			<lb />
			the time necessary for the journey from the
			<lb />
			place of arrest to the court of the magistrate
			<lb />
			and no such person shall be detained in
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			149
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			custody beyond the said period without the
			<lb />
			authority of a magistrate.
			<lb />
			(2) Any officer who has arrested any person
			<lb />
			under this section shall, for the purpose of
			<lb />
			releasing such person on bail or otherwise,
			<lb />
			have the same powers and be subject to the
			<lb />
			same provisions as the officer-in-charge of
			<lb />
			a police station has, and is subject to, under
			<lb />
			the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of
			<lb />
			1898).&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			117.
			<lb />
			Section 10(8) of the The Prevention of Food
			<lb />
			Adulteration Act, 1954 (37 Of 1954), read as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;10(8) Any food inspector may exercise the
			<lb />
			powers of a police officer under section 42
			<lb />
			of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of
			<lb />
			1974) for the purpose of ascertaining the
			<lb />
			true name and residence of the person from
			<lb />
			whom a sample is taken or an article of food
			<lb />
			is seized.&quot;
			<lb />
			It may be noticed that Section 42 of the Cr.P.C. confers
			<lb />
			power of arrest on a Police Officer to arrest even in regard
			<lb />
			to a non-cognizable offence in the circumstances mentioned
			<lb />
			therein without a warrant.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			150
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			118.
			<lb />
			Finally, Section 6 of The Railway Property
			<lb />
			(Unlawful Possession) Act, 1966, read as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;6. Power to arrest without warrant.-Any
			<lb />
			superior officer or member of the Force may,
			<lb />
			without an order from a Magistrate and
			<lb />
			without a warrant, arrest any person who has
			<lb />
			been concerned in an offence punishable under
			<lb />
			this Act or against whom a reasonable
			<lb />
			suspicion exists of his having been so
			<lb />
			concerned.&quot;
			<lb />
			Here, it is relevant to notice that the persons
			<lb />
			empowered are members of the force, which is defined as
			<lb />
			being members of the force and the word &apos;force&apos; is defined
			<lb />
			as the Railway protection force constituted under the
			<lb />
			Railway Protection Force Act, 1957. It is an armed force.
			<lb />
			119.
			<lb />
			In the Foreign Exchange Management Act, 1999,
			<lb />
			there is no express power of arrest, as such conferred.
			<lb />
			Instead, it is relevant to notice Section 37 of the said
			<lb />
			enactment:
			<lb />
			&quot;37. Power of search, seizure, etc.-
			<lb />
			(1) The Director of Enforcement and other
			<lb />
			officers of Enforcement, not below the rank
			<lb />
			of an Assistant Director, shall take up for
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			151
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			investigation the contravention referred to
			<lb />
			in section 13. -(1) The Director of
			<lb />
			Enforcement
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			other
			<lb />
			officers
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			Enforcement, not below the rank of an
			<lb />
			Assistant Director, shall take up for
			<lb />
			investigation the contravention referred to
			<lb />
			in section 13.&quot;
			<lb />
			(2) Without prejudice to the provisions of
			<lb />
			sub-section (1), the Central Government may
			<lb />
			also, by notification, authorise any officer
			<lb />
			or class of officers in the Central
			<lb />
			Government, State Government or the Reserve
			<lb />
			Bank, not below the rank of an Under Secretary
			<lb />
			to the Government of India to investigate any
			<lb />
			contravention referred to in section 13.
			<lb />
			(3) The officers referred to in sub-section
			<lb />
			(1) shall exercise the like powers which are
			<lb />
			conferred on income-tax authorities under
			<lb />
			the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961) and
			<lb />
			shall exercise such powers, subject to such
			<lb />
			limitations laid down under that Act.&quot;
			<lb />
			120.
			<lb />
			The provision for arrest is contained in the Second
			<lb />
			Schedule to the Income-Tax Act as a mode of recovery of tax.
			<lb />
			121.
			<lb />
			A perusal of Section 104(4) of the Customs Act,
			<lb />
			as it stood when this Court decided Deepak Mahajan (supra),
			<lb />
			would show that while an express power was conferred on the
			<lb />
			Customs Officer to arrest under Section 104(1), it was
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			152
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			considered to be non-cognizable offence. Further, the power
			<lb />
			of arrest was confined only to an offence committed under
			<lb />
			Section 135 of the Act. It is apposite to notice that under
			<lb />
			the CrPC, there is no power with the Police Officer to arrest
			<lb />
			in the case of a non-cognizable offence except upon a
			<lb />
			Warrant or Order of a Magistrate.
			<lb />
			122.
			<lb />
			In this regard, it may also be apposite to refer
			<lb />
			to the provisions of the Central Excise Act, 1944. Section
			<lb />
			13 confers the power to arrest. It reads as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;13. Power to arrest:-Any Central
			<lb />
			Excise Officer not below the rank of
			<lb />
			Inspector of Central Excise may, with the
			<lb />
			prior approval of the Principal Commissioner
			<lb />
			of Central Excise or Commissioner of Central
			<lb />
			Excise, arrest any person whom he has reason
			<lb />
			to believe to be liable to punishment under
			<lb />
			this Act or the rules made thereunder.&quot;
			<lb />
			123.
			<lb />
			However, Section 9A, as it stood prior to it being
			<lb />
			amended from the year 2004 onwards, declared that the
			<lb />
			offences under Section 9 were to be deemed to be
			<lb />
			non-cognizable under the provisions of the Code of Criminal
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			153
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Procedure. In Sunil Gupta v. Union of India 27 , the Division
			<lb />
			Bench of the Punjab and Haryana High Court had to answer
			<lb />
			the question as to whether the power of arrest, under
			<lb />
			Section 13 of the Act, could be exercised without a warrant,
			<lb />
			in view of the fact that under Section 9A, the offence was
			<lb />
			declared as non-cognizable. The Court took the view that
			<lb />
			Section 13 embodied a substantive power. It held, inter
			<lb />
			alia, as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;21. In our view, Section 13 embodies a
			<lb />
			substantive power. It confers the power to
			<lb />
			arrest. The procedural safeguards have been
			<lb />
			protected by Section 18. This provision
			<lb />
			merely regulates the exercise of power
			<lb />
			under Section 13. It only provides that the
			<lb />
			searches and arrests under the Central
			<lb />
			Excise Act &quot;shall be carried out in
			<lb />
			accordance with the provisions of the
			<lb />
			Code of Criminal Procedure .....&quot; In other
			<lb />
			words, an officer of the Central Excise shall
			<lb />
			make the arrest in the manner laid down
			<lb />
			in Section 46 of the Code of Criminal
			<lb />
			Procedure. He &quot;shall actually touch or
			<lb />
			confine the body of the person to be
			<lb />
			arrested.....&quot; In case of resistance, the
			<lb />
			officer of the Central Excise &quot;may use all
			<lb />
			means necessary to effect the arrest.&quot; The
			<lb />
			persons arrested &quot;shall not be subjected to
			<lb />
			more restraint than is necessary to prevent
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			27 2000(118) ELT 8 P&amp;H
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			154
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			his escape.&quot; Similarly, a search shall be
			<lb />
			carried out in accordance with the procedure
			<lb />
			laid down in Section 100. If the person of a
			<lb />
			lady has to be searched, it shall be done &quot;by
			<lb />
			another woman with strict regard to decency.&quot;
			<lb />
			Two or more independent and respectable
			<lb />
			inhabitants of the locality shall be called
			<lb />
			upon to be present. The search shall be made
			<lb />
			in their presence and &quot;a list of things seized
			<lb />
			in the course of such search ..... shall be
			<lb />
			prepared ......&quot; In a nut shell, the
			<lb />
			procedural protection contained in the
			<lb />
			Code of
			<lb />
			Criminal
			<lb />
			Procedure
			<lb />
			has
			<lb />
			been
			<lb />
			guaranteed even in case of arrests and
			<lb />
			searches under the Central Excise Act, 1944.
			<lb />
			No more.&quot;
			<lb />
			124.
			<lb />
			A Single Judge of the High Court of Gujarat, also
			<lb />
			posed the following question as the one which it had to
			<lb />
			answer in the case reported in Bhavin Impex Pvt. Ltd. v.
			<lb />
			State of Gujarat 28 , as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;1. The key question that arises for
			<lb />
			consideration in this writ petition is as to
			<lb />
			whether the authorities under the Central
			<lb />
			Excise Act, 1944 (hereinafter referred to as
			<lb />
			&apos;the Act&apos;) have the power to arrest a person
			<lb />
			under Section 13 of the Act without a warrant
			<lb />
			and without filing an FIR or lodging a
			<lb />
			complaint before a Court of competent
			<lb />
			jurisdiction.&quot;
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			28 2010(260) ELT 526 (Gujarat)
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			155
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			125.
			<lb />
			The Court purported to follow the Punjab and
			<lb />
			Haryana High Court in Sunil Gupta (supra), which we have
			<lb />
			referred and held, inter alia, as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;This Court is in agreement with the view
			<lb />
			taken by the Punjab and Haryana High Court,
			<lb />
			viz, a Central Excise Officer, (satisfying
			<lb />
			the conditions laid down under Section 13) is
			<lb />
			not debarred from arresting a person without
			<lb />
			a warrant when he has reason to believe that
			<lb />
			the person is liable to punishment under the
			<lb />
			Act or the rules made thereunder. Section 13
			<lb />
			is not curtailed by Section 18 and in fact
			<lb />
			Section 18 is merely procedural.&quot;
			<lb />
			126.
			<lb />
			We must, however, notice the judgment of this Court
			<lb />
			reported in Om Parkash and Another v. Union of India and
			<lb />
			Another 29 , a Judgment, which dealt with the Central Excise
			<lb />
			Act, 1944 and also the Customs Act, 1962. The question,
			<lb />
			however, which arose was, whether under the said
			<lb />
			enactments, as the offences were non-cognizable, were they
			<lb />
			bailable as well? Section 9A, as it was considered by this
			<lb />
			Court, read as follows:
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place='footnote'>
			29 (2011)14 SCC 1
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			156
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			&quot;9A.
			<lb />
			Certain
			<lb />
			offences
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			be
			<lb />
			non-cognizable.-(1)
			<lb />
			Notwithstanding
			<lb />
			anything contained in the Code of Criminal
			<lb />
			Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898), offences
			<lb />
			under section 9 shall be deemed to be
			<lb />
			non-cognizable within the meaning of that
			<lb />
			Code.
			<lb />
			(2) Any offence under this Chapter may,
			<lb />
			either before or after the institution of
			<lb />
			prosecution, be compounded by the Chief
			<lb />
			Commissioner of Central Excise on payment, by
			<lb />
			the person accused of the offence to the
			<lb />
			Central Government, of such compounding
			<lb />
			amount and in such manner of compounding, as
			<lb />
			may be prescribed.
			<lb />
			Provided that nothing contained in this
			<lb />
			sub-section shall apply to -
			<lb />
			(a) a person who has been allowed to compound
			<lb />
			once in respect of any of the offences under
			<lb />
			the provisions of clause (a), (b), (bb),
			<lb />
			(bbb), (bbbb) or (c) of sub-section (1)
			<lb />
			of Section 9;
			<lb />
			(b) a person who has been accused of
			<lb />
			committing an offence under this Act which is
			<lb />
			also an offence under the Narcotic Drugs
			<lb />
			and Psychotropic Substances Act, 1985 (61 of
			<lb />
			1985);
			<lb />
			(c) a person who has been allowed to compound
			<lb />
			once in respect of any offence under this
			<lb />
			Chapter for goods of value exceeding rupees
			<lb />
			one crore;
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			157
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			(d) a person who has been convicted by the
			<lb />
			court under this Act on or after the 30 th day
			<lb />
			of December, 2005.&quot;
			<lb />
			127.
			<lb />
			The Court did make reference to both Sunil
			<lb />
			Gupta (supra) and Bhavin Impex Pvt. Ltd. (supra). This Court
			<lb />
			went on to find, on an examination of the provisions, that
			<lb />
			being non-cognizable offences under the Central Excise Act,
			<lb />
			and taking note of the fact that as a general rule, though,
			<lb />
			with exceptions under the First Schedule to the CrPC,
			<lb />
			non-cognizable offences were treated as bailable, and also,
			<lb />
			taking note of Section 20 of the Excise Act, which appeared
			<lb />
			to show that the offences were bailable that they were
			<lb />
			bailable. What is, however, noteworthy for the purpose of
			<lb />
			deciding the case before us, is the statement of the law
			<lb />
			as contained in paragraph-41, which reads as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;41. In our view, the definition of
			<lb />
			&quot;non-cognizable offence&quot; in Section 2(l) of
			<lb />
			the Code makes it clear that a non-cognizable
			<lb />
			offence is an offence for which a police
			<lb />
			officer has no authority to arrest without
			<lb />
			warrant.
			<lb />
			As
			<lb />
			we
			<lb />
			have
			<lb />
			also
			<lb />
			noticed
			<lb />
			hereinbefore, the expression &quot;cognizable
			<lb />
			offence&quot; in Section 2(c) of the Code means an
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			158
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			offence for which a police officer may, in
			<lb />
			accordance with the First Schedule or under
			<lb />
			any other law for the time being in force,
			<lb />
			arrest without warrant. In other words, on a
			<lb />
			construction of the definitions of the
			<lb />
			different expressions used in the Code and
			<lb />
			also in connected enactments in respect of a
			<lb />
			non-cognizable offence, a police officer,
			<lb />
			and, in the instant case an excise officer,
			<lb />
			will have no authority to make an arrest
			<lb />
			without obtaining a warrant for the said
			<lb />
			purpose. The same provision is contained
			<lb />
			in Section 41 of the Code which specifies
			<lb />
			when a police officer may arrest without
			<lb />
			order from a Magistrate or without warrant.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			128.
			<lb />
			The Court applied the same principles in regard to
			<lb />
			the cases which it decided under the Customs Act. We may
			<lb />
			notice that Section 18 of the Central Excise Act, 1944
			<lb />
			provides for the manner of making an arrest. It reads as
			<lb />
			follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;18. Searches and arrests how to be made.-All
			<lb />
			searches made under this Act or any rules made
			<lb />
			thereunder and all arrests made under this
			<lb />
			Act shall be carried out in accordance with
			<lb />
			the provisions of the Code of Criminal
			<lb />
			Procedure,
			<lb />
			1898(5
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			1898),
			<lb />
			relating
			<lb />
			respectively to searches and arrests made
			<lb />
			under that Code.&quot;
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			159
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			129.
			<lb />
			Equally of interest, are the provisions contained
			<lb />
			in Sections 19, 20 and 21:
			<lb />
			&quot;19. Disposal of persons arrested.-Every
			<lb />
			person arrested under this Act shall be
			<lb />
			forwarded without delay to the nearest
			<lb />
			Central Excise Officer empowered to send
			<lb />
			persons so arrested to a Magistrate, or, if
			<lb />
			there is no such Central Excise Officer
			<lb />
			within a reasonable distance, to the officer
			<lb />
			in charge of the nearest police station.
			<lb />
			20. Procedure to be followed by officer in
			<lb />
			charge of police station.-The officer in
			<lb />
			charge of a police station to whom any person
			<lb />
			is forwarded under Section 19 shall either
			<lb />
			admit him to bail to appear before the
			<lb />
			Magistrate having jurisdiction, or in
			<lb />
			default of bail forward him in custody to such
			<lb />
			Magistrate.
			<lb />
			21. Inquiry how to be made by Central Excise
			<lb />
			Officers against arrested persons forwarded
			<lb />
			to them under Section 19. -
			<lb />
			(1)
			<lb />
			When any person is forwarded under Section 19
			<lb />
			to a Central Excise Officer empowered to send
			<lb />
			persons so arrested to a Magistrate, the
			<lb />
			Central Excise Officer shall proceed to
			<lb />
			inquire into the charge against him.
			<lb />
			(2) For this purpose the Central Excise
			<lb />
			Officer may exercise the same powers and
			<lb />
			shall be subject to the same provisions as the
			<lb />
			officer in charge of a police station may
			<lb />
			exercise and is subject to under the Code of
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			160
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898), when
			<lb />
			investigating a cognizable case:
			<lb />
			Provided that-
			<lb />
			(a) If the Central Excise Officer is of
			<lb />
			opinion that there is sufficient
			<lb />
			evidence or reasonable ground of
			<lb />
			suspicion against the accused person, he
			<lb />
			shall either admit him to bail to appear
			<lb />
			before a Magistrate having jurisdiction
			<lb />
			in the case, or forward him in custody
			<lb />
			to such Magistrate;
			<lb />
			(b) If it appears to the Central Excise
			<lb />
			Officer that there is not sufficient
			<lb />
			evidence or reasonable ground of
			<lb />
			suspicion against the accused person, he
			<lb />
			shall release the accused person on his
			<lb />
			executing a bond, with or without
			<lb />
			sureties as the Central Excise Officer
			<lb />
			may direct, to appear, if and when so
			<lb />
			required, before the Magistrate having
			<lb />
			jurisdiction, and shall make a full
			<lb />
			report of all the particulars of the case
			<lb />
			to his official superior.&quot;
			<lb />
			130.
			<lb />
			On a perusal of the statement of law contained in
			<lb />
			paragraph-41, we find that this Court has found that as the
			<lb />
			provisions under the enactments in question declared the
			<lb />
			offences to be non-cognizable, the officer exercising the
			<lb />
			power of arrest, could not arrest, except after obtaining
			<lb />
			a warrant for the said purpose. That they may not arrest
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			161
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			without
			<lb />
			obtaining
			<lb />
			a
			<lb />
			warrant
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			respect
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			non-cognizable offences, being the view taken by this
			<lb />
			Court, cannot be squared with the view taken by Punjab and
			<lb />
			Haryana High Court and Gujarat High Court, respectively,
			<lb />
			in Sunil Gupta (supra) and also Bhavin Impex Pvt.
			<lb />
			Ltd. (supra), which took the view in effecting arrest under
			<lb />
			the Central Excise Act, no warrant was required. It is
			<lb />
			apparently consequent upon the same that Legislature
			<lb />
			stepped in with amendments. Section 9A came to be amended
			<lb />
			and it reads as follows after the amendment:
			<lb />
			&quot;Section 9A.
			<lb />
			Certain offences to be
			<lb />
			non-cognizable.-
			<lb />
			(1) Notwithstanding anything contained in
			<lb />
			the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973(2 of
			<lb />
			1974), offences under section 9, except the
			<lb />
			offences referred to in sub-section (1A),
			<lb />
			shall be non-cognizable within the meaning of
			<lb />
			that Code.
			<lb />
			(2) Any offence under this Chapter may,
			<lb />
			either before or after the institution of
			<lb />
			prosecution, be compounded by the Principal
			<lb />
			Chief Commissioner of Central Excise or Chief
			<lb />
			Commissioner of Central Excise on payment, by
			<lb />
			the person accused of the offence to the
			<lb />
			Central Government, of such compounding
			<lb />
			amount and in such manner of compounding as
			<lb />
			may be prescribed:
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			162
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Provided that nothing contained in this sub
			<lb />
			-section shall apply to ---
			<lb />
			(a) a person who has been allowed to
			<lb />
			compound once in respect of any of the
			<lb />
			offences under the provisions of clause
			<lb />
			(a),(b),(bb),(bbb),(bbbb) or (c) of sub
			<lb />
			-section (1) of section 9;
			<lb />
			(b) a person who has been accused of
			<lb />
			committing an offence under this Act which is
			<lb />
			also an offence under the Narcotic Drugs and
			<lb />
			Psychotropic Substance Act,1985 (61 of
			<lb />
			1985);
			<lb />
			(c) a person who has been allowed to
			<lb />
			compound once in respect of any of the offence
			<lb />
			under this Chapter for goods of value
			<lb />
			exceeding rupees one crore;
			<lb />
			(d) a person who has been convicted by the
			<lb />
			court under this Act on or after the 30th day
			<lb />
			of December, 2005.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			131.
			<lb />
			The result would appear to be that acknowledging
			<lb />
			the effect of making the offences being non-cognizable to
			<lb />
			be to limit the power of the authorities under the Act for
			<lb />
			effecting arrest under the Act, to require a warrant,
			<lb />
			certain offences were declared to be cognizable as noticed
			<lb />
			in Section 9A, as amended after the Judgment in
			<lb />
			Om Parkash (supra). The resultant position after the
			<lb />
			amendment is, it became open to the Officers to effect the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			163
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			arrest in regard to a cognizable offence without obtaining
			<lb />
			a warrant.
			<lb />
			132.
			<lb />
			In regard to the Customs Act, 1962 in Section 104,
			<lb />
			under the present avatar, two changes have been brought
			<lb />
			about. Firstly, the power to arrest is available in respect
			<lb />
			of offences under Sections 132, 133, 135, 135A and 136. The
			<lb />
			offences are divided into two categories. Under Section
			<lb />
			104(4), the offences which fall within its ambit, are
			<lb />
			treated as cognizable. The other offences are treated as
			<lb />
			non-cognizable under Section 104(5). For instance, if a
			<lb />
			person is involved in an offence relating to evasion or
			<lb />
			attempted evasion of duty exceeding 50 lakhs rupees (w.e.f.
			<lb />
			01.08.2019), while the offence is cognizable, the power of
			<lb />
			arrest is conferred on the Officers under Section 104(1).
			<lb />
			The power to arrest is conferred and the only condition to
			<lb />
			be fulfilled is that the Officer has reason to believe that
			<lb />
			the person has committed offence concerned. The position
			<lb />
			is the same in respect of offence relating to prohibited
			<lb />
			goods.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			164
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			133.
			<lb />
			We have embarked upon referring to the provisions
			<lb />
			relating to arrest under the Excise Act and Customs Act and
			<lb />
			the decision of this Court in Om Prakash(supra) in taking
			<lb />
			the view as it did in paragraph-41, in order to appreciate
			<lb />
			the contention that, after the amendment to Section 36AC,
			<lb />
			the offences have been declared cognizable. If we proceed
			<lb />
			on the basis that the power of arrest can be traced from
			<lb />
			Section 22(1)(d) of the Act, then, after the amendment in
			<lb />
			Section 36AC, by which, the offences falling under Chapter
			<lb />
			IV of the Act, which are declared as cognizable and
			<lb />
			non-bailable, the decks are cleared for effecting arrest
			<lb />
			without a warrant by the Inspector.
			<lb />
			134.
			<lb />
			However, the question would arise whether there
			<lb />
			exists the power of arrest with the Drugs Inspector. We
			<lb />
			will, on the one hand, array possible objections to the
			<lb />
			conferment of such powers. The power to arrest is a drastic
			<lb />
			power. It involves encroachment on personal liberty. The
			<lb />
			Drugs Inspector is not a Police Officer under the CrPC. The
			<lb />
			Legislature was aware of the power of the Police Officer
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			165
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			to arrest when he embarks on investigation of a cognizable
			<lb />
			case, as is clear from Section 157 of the CrPC. There is
			<lb />
			another indication in the Act which may reveal the mind of
			<lb />
			the Legislature that the power of arrest was not intended
			<lb />
			to be conferred on the Drugs Inspector. Section 34AA,
			<lb />
			reads as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;34AA.-Penalty for vexatious search or
			<lb />
			seizure.-Any Inspector exercising powers
			<lb />
			under this Act or the rules made thereunder,
			<lb />
			who,-
			<lb />
			(a) without reasonable ground of suspicion
			<lb />
			searches any place, vehicle, vessel or other
			<lb />
			conveyance; or
			<lb />
			(b) vexatiously and unnecessarily searches
			<lb />
			any person; or
			<lb />
			(c) vexatiously and unnecessarily seizes any
			<lb />
			drug or cosmetic, or any substance or
			<lb />
			article, or any record, register, document or
			<lb />
			other material object; or
			<lb />
			(d) commits, as such Inspector, any other
			<lb />
			act, to the injury of any person without
			<lb />
			having reason to believe that such act is
			<lb />
			required for the execution of his duty, shall
			<lb />
			be punishable with fine which may extend to
			<lb />
			one thousand rupees.&quot;
			<lb />
			There is no reference to arrest forming the subject
			<lb />
			matter of penalty.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			166
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			135.
			<lb />
			In contrast, we must notice Section 22 of the
			<lb />
			Central Excise Act, 1944, reads as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;22. Vexatious search, seizure, etc., by
			<lb />
			Central Excise Officer.-Any Central Excise
			<lb />
			or other officer exercising powers under this
			<lb />
			Act or under the rules made thereunder who-
			<lb />
			(a) without reasonable ground of suspicion
			<lb />
			searches or causes to be searched any house,
			<lb />
			boat or place;
			<lb />
			(b) vexatiously and unnecessarily detains,
			<lb />
			searches or arrests any person;
			<lb />
			(c) vexatiously and unnecessarily seizes the
			<lb />
			movable property of any person, on pretence
			<lb />
			of seizing or searching for any article
			<lb />
			liable to confiscation under this Act;
			<lb />
			(d) commits, as such officer, any other act
			<lb />
			to the injury of any person, without having
			<lb />
			reason to believe that such act is required
			<lb />
			for the execution of his duty, shall, for
			<lb />
			every such offence, be punishable with fine
			<lb />
			which may extend to two thousand rupees. Any
			<lb />
			person wilfully and maliciously giving false
			<lb />
			information and so causing an arrest or a
			<lb />
			search to be made under this Act shall be
			<lb />
			punishable with fine which may extend to two
			<lb />
			thousand rupees or with imprisonment for a
			<lb />
			term which may extend to two years or with
			<lb />
			both.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			167
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			136.
			<lb />
			Still further, as we have noticed in the Central
			<lb />
			Excise Act, 1944, apart from the fact that the power of
			<lb />
			arrest is expressly conferred, the manner, in which the
			<lb />
			power is to be exercised, is specifically indicated, as we
			<lb />
			have noticed on a perusal of Sections 19 and 20. Section
			<lb />
			68 of the Gold Control Act, 1968 has expressly conferred
			<lb />
			power of arrest, the conditions in which the power could
			<lb />
			be exercised and further procedure to be followed.
			<lb />
			137.
			<lb />
			We have noticed that the Inspector under the Act
			<lb />
			has been conferred with a vast and formidable array of
			<lb />
			powers, and in an enactment like the Act, the taking of
			<lb />
			samples, the Report given by the Competent Officer in regard
			<lb />
			to the same and the right reserved to the concerned person
			<lb />
			to seek a further Report from the Central Laboratory, go
			<lb />
			a long way in the successful culmination of a complaint
			<lb />
			under Section 32 of the Act. The Inspector is, undoubtedly,
			<lb />
			endowed with the power of inspection, taking samples of any
			<lb />
			drug or cosmetic, searching any person, searching any
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			168
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			place,
			<lb />
			searching
			<lb />
			any
			<lb />
			vehicle,
			<lb />
			examining
			<lb />
			records,
			<lb />
			registers, documents and other material objects and seizing
			<lb />
			the same, requiring any person to produce any record,
			<lb />
			register or other document. These are powers which are
			<lb />
			expressly conferred on the Inspector. Though, a complaint
			<lb />
			could be filed by other categories of complainants in
			<lb />
			Section 32 of the Act, the Inspector is pivot around which
			<lb />
			the Act moves. Rule 51(4) makes it a duty on the part of
			<lb />
			the Drugs Inspector to investigate any complaint in writing
			<lb />
			which may be made to him. It is also his duty under Rule
			<lb />
			51(5) to institute prosecution in respect of breaches of
			<lb />
			the Act and the Rules thereunder. He is also duty-bound
			<lb />
			under Rule 51(7) to make inquiries and inspections as may
			<lb />
			be necessary to detect sale of drugs in contravention of
			<lb />
			the Act. Under Rule 52, in regard to manufacture of drugs,
			<lb />
			it is again the duty to institute prosecution for breaches
			<lb />
			besides making inspections of all premises. This is having
			<lb />
			regard to both his qualifications and also the powers
			<lb />
			conferred on him. Section 23 of the Act, undoubtedly, is
			<lb />
			the procedure to be followed by the Inspector. We are,
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			169
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			therefore, to ascertain the meaning of the expression
			<lb />
			&quot;other powers&quot;, which are essential for carrying out the
			<lb />
			object of Chapter IV and the Rules made thereunder. The
			<lb />
			Legislature has not given any hint, intending to limit the
			<lb />
			scope of the residuary powers. No doubt, the Act is a
			<lb />
			pre-Independence Act. If we interpret that it is a Drugs
			<lb />
			Inspector, acting under Section 22 of the Act, who alone
			<lb />
			can investigate offences falling under Chapter IV of the
			<lb />
			Act and there is no power for the Police Officer under the
			<lb />
			CrPC to investigate under the Act or to file a Report under
			<lb />
			Section 173 of the CrPC, which indeed is indisputable, then,
			<lb />
			a power of arrest, which is necessary for the purpose of
			<lb />
			investigating and prosecution of the offences falling
			<lb />
			within Chapter IV of the Act, must be conceded to the Drugs
			<lb />
			Inspector. The legislative intention in conferring various
			<lb />
			powers, as we have noticed in the foregoing provisions of
			<lb />
			Section 22 of the Act and declaring that all other powers,
			<lb />
			which are necessary for the purpose of the Act, are to inhere
			<lb />
			in the Drugs Inspector, reassures us that we would be
			<lb />
			correctly ascertaining the legislative intention to be that
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			170
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			on a Drug Inspector taking-up a matter falling under Chapter
			<lb />
			IV of the Act, he is invested with the power to arrest.
			<lb />
			138.
			<lb />
			There is another aspect which may have an important
			<lb />
			bearing on the issue. Under Section 36AC of the Act, the
			<lb />
			offences as mentioned therein which include some of the
			<lb />
			offences under Chapter IV of the Act are declared cognizable
			<lb />
			and non-bailable. The provision imposes restriction on
			<lb />
			the arrested person being released on bail or on his own
			<lb />
			bond unless the public prosecutor has been given an
			<lb />
			opportunity to oppose the application and when the public
			<lb />
			prosecutor opposes the application, the Court is to be
			<lb />
			satisfied that there are reasonable grounds for believing
			<lb />
			that the accused person is not guilty of such offence and
			<lb />
			that he is not likely to commit an offence.
			<lb />
			This
			<lb />
			limitation, is apart from the limitations in the CrPC, inter
			<lb />
			alia. Now, the Police Officer acting under the CrPC even
			<lb />
			proceeding for a moment on the basis that it is sufficient
			<lb />
			that a mere memorandum of arrest as required under the CrPC
			<lb />
			is prepared and further there is compliance with other
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			171
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			provisions of the CrPC also, would it suffice is the
			<lb />
			question that would arise in the following manner? We have
			<lb />
			noted from the provisions of the Act and the Rules that it
			<lb />
			is the Drugs Inspector who is empowered and duty bound to
			<lb />
			investigate the complaint about violations of acts and
			<lb />
			rules. He is the person charged with a duty of prosecuting
			<lb />
			the offenders. If the police officer is merely to be granted
			<lb />
			a power of arrest and without having any power of
			<lb />
			investigation then how would it be possible for the police
			<lb />
			officer to make any investigation under the act and if no
			<lb />
			investigation is possible, how would the Police Officer be
			<lb />
			in a position to be of any assistance to the Public
			<lb />
			Prosecutor and, therefore, to the Court in the disposal of
			<lb />
			an application for bail? In other words, it would be based
			<lb />
			on the records of investigation and material collected by
			<lb />
			the investigating officer that a Court in a case would
			<lb />
			decide as to whether bail is to be granted or not. How would
			<lb />
			the police officer seek a remand for carrying out
			<lb />
			investigation which he cannot do? If the Act and the Rules
			<lb />
			do not contemplate investigation by a Police Officer, then,
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			172
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			conferring the power of arrest on the Police Officer, would,
			<lb />
			in fact, frustrate the working of the Act. On the other
			<lb />
			hand, if it is the Drugs Inspector who can arrest, the
			<lb />
			following consequences would follow:
			<lb />
			a. He has the requisite technical qualifications to
			<lb />
			properly investigate and prosecute the offender.
			<lb />
			b. He would be able to make adequate entries in whatever
			<lb />
			document he has to maintain as a part of investigation
			<lb />
			and it would facilitate a proper and fair consideration
			<lb />
			of an application for bail within the meaning of
			<lb />
			Section 36AC of the Act and also facilitate a request
			<lb />
			for remand under Section 167 of the Cr.P.C.
			<lb />
			139.
			<lb />
			Declaring the power to arrest with the Inspector,
			<lb />
			is not to be understood as proclaiming that the Inspector
			<lb />
			is bound to arrest any person. The provisions of the CrPC,
			<lb />
			relating to arrest, would necessarily have to be followed
			<lb />
			by the Drugs Inspector. In fact, he is obliged to bear in
			<lb />
			mind the law, as declared by this Court in D.K. Basu (supra),
			<lb />
			and the peril of defying the same, would be to invite
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			173
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			consequences, inter alia, as are provided therein. As far
			<lb />
			as the arrest, not being mentioned in Section 34AA, as
			<lb />
			forming a ground for visiting the delinquent Officer with
			<lb />
			penalty, it may be noticed that there is a residuary power
			<lb />
			in Section 34AA and it would cover any act. We notice that
			<lb />
			Section 34AA(d) provides that if any Inspector, exercising
			<lb />
			powers under the Act or the Rules made thereunder, commits,
			<lb />
			as such Inspector, any other act, to the injury of any person
			<lb />
			without having reason to believe that such act is required
			<lb />
			for the execution of his duty, he shall be punishable with
			<lb />
			fine which may extend to one thousand rupees.
			<lb />
			140.
			<lb />
			Regarding the power for seeking and ordering a
			<lb />
			remand under Section 167, we would apply the principles laid
			<lb />
			down by this Court in Deepak Mahajan (supra) and the same
			<lb />
			principles would apply.
			<lb />
			141.
			<lb />
			This process of interpretation would produce the
			<lb />
			result of harmonizing two seemingly irreconcilable
			<lb />
			commands from the Law-Giver. This interpretation commends
			<lb />
			itself to us for the reason that the investigation into
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			174
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			offences, under Chapter IV of the Act, would commence, be
			<lb />
			carried out and would culminate in, in the safe hands of
			<lb />
			the competent and qualified Statutory Authority, as
			<lb />
			designated by law. It would also avoid an outside agency
			<lb />
			like a Police Officer, being obliged to register an FIR,
			<lb />
			for the reason that where arrest has to be made, a FIR is
			<lb />
			to be registered, and, when the registering of the FIR
			<lb />
			carries with it an unattainable object of preferring a Final
			<lb />
			Report under Section 173 of the CrPC, as far as the Police
			<lb />
			Officer is concerned. We make it clear that if a Police
			<lb />
			Officer is approached with regard to a complaint regarding
			<lb />
			commission of an offence falling under Chapter IV of the
			<lb />
			Act, he is not to register an FIR unless it be that a
			<lb />
			cognizable offence, other than an offence falling under
			<lb />
			Chapter IV of the Act, is also made out. He must makeover
			<lb />
			the complaint to the competent Drug Inspector so that action
			<lb />
			in according with law is immediately taken where only
			<lb />
			offences under Chapter IV are made out.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			175
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			142.
			<lb />
			As far as the arrest contemplated under Section 41
			<lb />
			of the CrPC is concerned, in case a cognizable offence,
			<lb />
			falling under Chapter IV of the Act, is committed, either
			<lb />
			in the presence of the Drugs Inspector, or in respect of
			<lb />
			which offence, a Police Officer would have power to arrest,
			<lb />
			as provided therein, viz., covered by the situations
			<lb />
			contemplated under Section 41(ba), the Drugs Inspector
			<lb />
			would be entitled to effect the arrest. We are arriving at
			<lb />
			this conclusion on the basis that since the procedure under
			<lb />
			the CrPC is to be read as applicable, except to the extent
			<lb />
			that a different procedure is to be provided under the Act,
			<lb />
			and since there is no procedure or power otherwise provided
			<lb />
			in the Act in regard to arrest, the powers and procedure
			<lb />
			available to a Police Officer, with the limitations on the
			<lb />
			said power, as laid down in D.K. Basu (supra), as also as
			<lb />
			contained in the CrPC, would be applicable.
			<lb />
			143.
			<lb />
			By way of following Deepak Mahajan (supra), we hold
			<lb />
			that the Drugs Inspector, under the Act, is invested with
			<lb />
			certain powers similar to a Police Officer. Still further,
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			176
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			we would hold that the word &quot;investigation&quot; cannot be
			<lb />
			limited only to a Police investigation, as has been noted
			<lb />
			in Deepak Mahajan (supra). Thirdly, we find that the power
			<lb />
			to arrest a person must indeed flow from the provisions
			<lb />
			of a Statute. The statutory provision under the Act is
			<lb />
			Section 22(1)(d). The arrested person, under the Act, would
			<lb />
			be an accused person to be detained under Section 167(2)
			<lb />
			of the CrPC. No doubt, the Police Officer is bound to provide
			<lb />
			assistance to the Inspector in case of need to effectuate
			<lb />
			the arrest where there is resistance or likelihood of
			<lb />
			resistance. No doubt, in regard to the arrest in relation
			<lb />
			to offences falling under Chapter IV of the Act, which do
			<lb />
			not fall under Section 36AC, the power of arrest would
			<lb />
			depend upon the provision in the Schedule to the CrPC.
			<lb />
			144.
			<lb />
			We again reiterate that the existence of the power
			<lb />
			to arrest with the Drugs Inspector is not to be understood
			<lb />
			as opening the doors to making illegal, unauthorized or
			<lb />
			unnecessary arrest. Every power comes with responsibility.
			<lb />
			In view of the impact of an arrest, the highest care must
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			177
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			be taken to exercise the same strictly as per the law. The
			<lb />
			power of arrest must be exercised, recognizing the source
			<lb />
			of his authority, to be Section 22(1)(d) of the Act, which
			<lb />
			is for carrying out the purpose of Chapter IV of the Act
			<lb />
			or any Rules made thereunder.
			<lb />
			145.
			<lb />
			Section 33P of the Act, reads as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;33P. to give directions.-The Central
			<lb />
			Government may give such directions to any
			<lb />
			State Government as may appear to the Central
			<lb />
			Government to be necessary for carrying into
			<lb />
			execution in the State any of the provisions
			<lb />
			of this Act or of any rule or order made
			<lb />
			thereunder.&quot;
			<lb />
			We notice that the Central Government is conferred with
			<lb />
			powers to give directions to the State Government for the
			<lb />
			purpose of carrying into execution, in the State, any of
			<lb />
			the provisions of the Act or any Rule or Order made
			<lb />
			thereunder. It is for the Central Government to consider
			<lb />
			the question whether it can, under the said provision, issue
			<lb />
			directions in regard to the power of arrest, which we have
			<lb />
			found, subject to what we have stated in this Judgment.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			178
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			146.
			<lb />
			Further, Section 58 of the CrPC provides that the
			<lb />
			Officers In-charge of Police Stations are to report cases
			<lb />
			of all persons arrested without warrant as provided
			<lb />
			therein. We make it clear that the Drugs Inspector must,
			<lb />
			apart from other relevant provisions of the CrPC, comply
			<lb />
			with the requirement of reporting. In view of the need to
			<lb />
			safeguard the interest of persons, who may be proceeded
			<lb />
			against by the Drugs Inspector, we also hold and direct that
			<lb />
			the Drugs Inspector will immediately, after arrest, make
			<lb />
			a report of the arrest to his superior Officer.
			<lb />
			147.
			<lb />
			It has been brought to our notice that FIRs have
			<lb />
			been filed in regard to offences under Chapter IV of the
			<lb />
			Act. In the view we have taken, no further investigation
			<lb />
			can be done by the Police Officer. However, it is in the
			<lb />
			interest of justice that the FIRs are made over by the Police
			<lb />
			Officers to the concerned Drugs Inspector at the earliest.
			<lb />
			We are persuaded to issue such directions in the exercise
			<lb />
			of our powers under Article 142 of the Constitution of
			<lb />
			India.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			179
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			148.
			<lb />
			It would appear that on an understanding of the
			<lb />
			provisions, arrests would have been effected by Police
			<lb />
			Officers in regard to the cognizable offences under Chapter
			<lb />
			IV of the Act. Having regard to the fact that we are
			<lb />
			resolving this controversy on a conspectus of the various
			<lb />
			provisions of the Act and the CrPC, we are inclined to direct
			<lb />
			that this Judgment, holding that Police Officers do not have
			<lb />
			power to arrest in regard to cognizable offences under
			<lb />
			Chapter IV of the Act, is to operate from the date of this
			<lb />
			Judgement.
			<lb />
			149.
			<lb />
			Before we proceed to the operative portion of our
			<lb />
			Judgment, we must express the hope that the vexed issues
			<lb />
			which we have resolved through this Judgment, in regard to
			<lb />
			the power of arrest, may engage the competent Legislative
			<lb />
			Body.
			<lb />
			THE CONCLUSIONS/DIRECTIONS
			<lb />
			150.
			<lb />
			Thus, we may cull out our conclusions/directions
			<lb />
			as follows:
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			180
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			I.
			<lb />
			In regard to cognizable offences under Chapter IV
			<lb />
			of the Act, in view of Section 32 of the Act and
			<lb />
			also the scheme of the CrPC, the Police Officer
			<lb />
			cannot prosecute offenders in regard to such
			<lb />
			offences. Only the persons mentioned in Section 32
			<lb />
			are entitled to do the same.
			<lb />
			II. There is no bar to the Police Officer, however, to
			<lb />
			investigate and prosecute the person where he has
			<lb />
			committed an offence, as stated under Section
			<lb />
			32(3) of the Act, i.e., if he has committed any
			<lb />
			cognizable offence under any other law.
			<lb />
			III. Having regard to the scheme of the CrPC and also
			<lb />
			the mandate of Section 32 of the Act and on a
			<lb />
			conspectus of powers which are available with the
			<lb />
			Drugs Inspector under the Act and also his duties,
			<lb />
			a Police Officer cannot register a FIR under
			<lb />
			Section 154 of the CrPC, in regard to cognizable
			<lb />
			offences under Chapter IV of the Act and he cannot
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			181
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			investigate such offences under the provisions of
			<lb />
			the CrPC.
			<lb />
			IV. Having regard to the provisions of Section
			<lb />
			22(1)(d) of the Act, we hold that an arrest can be
			<lb />
			made by the Drugs Inspector in regard to cognizable
			<lb />
			offences falling under Chapter IV of the Act
			<lb />
			without any warrant and otherwise treating it as
			<lb />
			a cognizable offence. He is, however, bound by
			<lb />
			the law as laid down in D.K. Basu (supra) and to
			<lb />
			follow the provisions of CrPC.
			<lb />
			V. It would appear that on the understanding that the
			<lb />
			Police Officer can register a FIR, there are many
			<lb />
			cases where FIRs have been registered in regard to
			<lb />
			cognizable offences falling under Chapter IV of
			<lb />
			the Act. We find substance in the stand taken by
			<lb />
			learned Amicus Curiae and direct that they should
			<lb />
			be made over to the Drugs Inspectors, if not
			<lb />
			already made over, and it is for the Drugs
			<lb />
			Inspector to take action on the same in accordance
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			182
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			with the law. We must record that we are resorting
			<lb />
			to our power under Article 142 of the Constitution
			<lb />
			of India in this regard.
			<lb />
			VI. Further, we would be inclined to believe that in
			<lb />
			a number of cases on the understanding of the law
			<lb />
			relating to the power of arrest as, in fact,
			<lb />
			evidenced by the facts of the present case, police
			<lb />
			officers would have made arrests in regard to
			<lb />
			offences under Chapter IV of the Act. Therefore,
			<lb />
			in regard to the power of arrest, we make it clear
			<lb />
			that our decision that Police Officers do not have
			<lb />
			power to arrest in respect of cognizable offences
			<lb />
			under Chapter IV of the Act, will operate with
			<lb />
			effect from the date of this Judgment.
			<lb />
			VII. We further direct that the Drugs Inspectors, who
			<lb />
			carry out the arrest, must not only report the
			<lb />
			arrests, as provided in Section 58 of the CrPC, but
			<lb />
			also immediately report the arrests to their
			<lb />
			superior Officers.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			183
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			151.
			<lb />
			In view of our conclusions/directions and subject
			<lb />
			to the same, we would, on the facts, uphold the impugned
			<lb />
			Judgment and dismiss the Appeal. We record our appreciation
			<lb />
			for the enlightening submissions of the learned Amicus
			<lb />
			Curiae Shri S. Nagamuthu.
			<lb />
			..................J.
			<lb />
			(SANJAY KISHAN KAUL)
			<lb />
			..................J.
			<lb />
			(K.M. JOSEPH)
			<lb />
			NEW DELHI,
			<lb />
			AUGUST 28, 2020.
		</body>


	</text>
</tei>