<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<head>J U D G M E N T<lb/>
 R.F. Nariman, J.<lb/>
	</head>

	<p>1.<lb/>
 I.A. No.134044 of 2019 for intervention in C.A. Nos. 20825-<lb/>
20826 of 2017 is allowed.<lb/>
</p>

<p>2.<lb/>
 These Civil Appeals have been referred to a Bench of three<lb/>
 honourable Judges of this Court by a Division Bench reference order dated<lb/>
 26.07.2019, dealing with the interpretation of Section 65B of the Indian<lb/>
 (2014) 10 SCC 473 (a three Judge Bench decision of this Court), it was<lb/>
 found that a Division Bench judgment in SLP (Crl.) No. 9431 of 2011<lb/>
 reported as Shafhi Mohammad v. State of Himachal Pradesh (2018) 2<lb/>
 SCC 801 may need reconsideration by a Bench of a larger strength.<lb/>
</p>

<p>3.<lb/>
 The brief facts necessary to appreciate the controversy in the<lb/>
 present case, as elucidated in Civil Appeals 20825-20826 of 2017, are as<lb/>
 follows:<lb/>
</p>

<p> i.<lb/>
 Two election petitions were filed by the present Respondents<lb/>
 before the Bombay High Court under Sections 80 and 81 of the<lb/>
 Representation of the People Act, 1951, challenging the election of the<lb/>
 present Appellant, namely, Shri Arjun Panditrao Khotkar (who is the<lb/>
 Returned Candidate [hereinafter referred to as the &quot;RC&quot;] belonging to<lb/>
 the Shiv Sena party from 101-Jalna Legislative Assembly Constituency)<lb/>
 to the Maharashtra State Legislative Assembly for the term commencing<lb/>
 November, 2014. Election Petition No.6 of 2014 was filed by the<lb/>
 defeated Congress (I) candidate Shri Kailash Kishanrao Gorantyal,<lb/>
 whereas Election Petition No.9 of 2014 was filed by one Shri Vijay<lb/>
 2<lb/>
 Chaudhary, an elector in the said constituency. The margin of victory for<lb/>
 the RC was extremely narrow, namely 296 votes -the RC having<lb/>
 secured 45,078 votes, whereas Shri Kailash Kishanrao Gorantyal<lb/>
 secured 44,782 votes.<lb/>
</p>

<p>ii.<lb/>
 The entirety of the case before the High Court had revolved<lb/>
 around four sets of nomination papers that had been filed by the RC. It<lb/>
 was the case of the present Respondents that each set of nomination<lb/>
 papers suffered from defects of a substantial nature and that, therefore,<lb/>
 all four sets of nomination papers, having been improperly accepted by<lb/>
 the Returning Officer of the Election Commission, one Smt. Mutha,<lb/>
 (hereinafter referred to as the &quot;RO&quot;), the election of the RC be declared<lb/>
 void. In particular, it was the contention of the present Respondents that<lb/>
 the late presentation of Nomination Form Nos. 43 and 44 by the RC -<lb/>
inasmuch as they were filed by the RC after the stipulated time of 3.00<lb/>
 p.m. on 27.09.2014 -rendered such nomination forms not being filed in<lb/>
 accordance with the law, and ought to have been rejected.<lb/>
</p>

<p>iii.<lb/>
 In order to buttress this submission, the Respondents sought<lb/>
 to rely upon video-camera arrangements that were made both inside<lb/>
 and outside the office of the RO. According to the Respondents, the<lb/>
 nomination papers were only offered at 3.53 p.m. (i.e. beyond 3.00<lb/>
 p.m.), as a result of which it was clear that they had been filed out of<lb/>
 time. A specific complaint making this objection was submitted by Shri<lb/>
 Kailash Kishanrao Gorantyal before the RO on 28.09.2014 at 11.00<lb/>
 a.m., in which it was requested that the RO reject the nomination forms<lb/>
 that had been improperly accepted. This request was rejected by the<lb/>
 RO on the same day, stating that the nomination forms had, in fact,<lb/>
 been filed within time.<lb/>
</p>

<p>4.<lb/>
 Given the fact that allegations and counter allegations were<lb/>
 made as to the time at which the nomination forms were given to the RO,<lb/>
 and that videography was available, the High Court, by its order dated<lb/>
 16.03.2016, ordered the Election Commission and the concerned officers<lb/>
 to produce the entire record of the election of this Constituency, including<lb/>
 the original video recordings. A specific order was made that this electronic<lb/>
 record needs to be produced along with the &apos;necessary certificates&apos;.<lb/>
</p>

<p>5.<lb/>
 In compliance with this order, such video recordings were<lb/>
 produced by the Election Commission, together with a certificate issued<lb/>
 with regard to the CDs/VCDs, which read as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<p>&quot;Certificate<lb/>
 This is to certify that the CDs in respect of video recording<lb/>
 done on two days of filing nomination forms of date<lb/>
 26.9.2014 and 27.9.2014 which were present in the record<lb/>
 are produced.<lb/>
</p>

<p>6.<lb/>
 Transcripts of the contents of these<lb/>
 CDs/VCDs were prepared by the High Court itself. Issue nos.6 and 7 as<lb/>
 framed by the High Court (and its answers to these issues) are important,<lb/>
 and are set out in the impugned judgment dated 24.11.2017, and extracted<lb/>
 hereinbelow:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot; Issues<lb/>
 Findings<lb/>
</item>

<item>6. Whether the petitioner proves<lb/>
 that the nomination papers at Sr.<lb/>
 Nos. 43 and 44 were not<lb/>
 presented<lb/>
 by<lb/>
 respondent/<lb/>
 Returned candidate before 3.00<lb/>
 p.m. on 27/09/2014 ?<lb/>
</item>

<item>Affirmative. (nomination<lb/>
 papers at Sr. Nos. 43<lb/>
 and<lb/>
 44<lb/>
 were<lb/>
 not<lb/>
 presented by RC before<lb/>
 3.00 p.m. of 27.9.2014.)<lb/>
</item>

<item>5<lb/>
 Sd/-<lb/>
Asst. Returning Officer<lb/>
 101 Jalna Legislative Assembly<lb/>
 Constituency/Tahsildar<lb/>
 Jalna<lb/>
 Sd/-<lb/>
Returning Officer<lb/>
 101 Jalna Legislative Assembly<lb/>
 Constituency/Tahsildar<lb/>
 Jalna&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>7. Whether the petitioner proves<lb/>
 that the respondent /Returned<lb/>
 candidate<lb/>
 submitted<lb/>
 original<lb/>
 forms A and B along with<lb/>
 nomination<lb/>
 paper<lb/>
 only<lb/>
 on<lb/>
 27/09/2014 after 3.00 p.m. and<lb/>
 along with nomination paper at<lb/>
 Sr. No. 44 ?<lb/>
</item>

<item>Affirmative. (A, B forms<lb/>
 were presented after<lb/>
 3.00 p.m. of 27.9.2014)&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>7.<lb/>
 In answering issues 6 and 7, the High Court recorded:<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;60. Many applications were given by the petitioner of<lb/>
 Election Petition No. 6/2014 to get the copies of electronic<lb/>
 record in respect of aforesaid incidents with certificate as<lb/>
 provided in section 65-B of the Evidence Act. The<lb/>
 correspondence made with them show that even after<lb/>
 leaving of the office by Smt. Mutha, the Government<lb/>
 machinery, incharge of the record, intentionally avoided to<lb/>
 give certificate as mentioned in section 65-B of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act. After production of the record in the Court in<lb/>
 this regard, this Court had allowed to Election Commission<lb/>
 by order to give copies of such record to applicants, but<lb/>
 after that also the authority avoided to give copies by<lb/>
 giving lame excuses. It needs to be kept in mind that the<lb/>
 RC is from political party which has alliance with ruling<lb/>
 party, BJP, not only in the State, but also at the center. It is<lb/>
 unfortunate that the machinery which is expected to be fair<lb/>
 did not act fairly in the present matter. The circumstances<lb/>
 of the present matter show that the aforesaid two officers<lb/>
 tried to cover up their mischief. However the material gives<lb/>
 only one inference that nomination forms Nos. 43 and 44<lb/>
 with A, B forms were presented before the RO by RC after<lb/>
 3.00 p.m. of 27.9.2014 and they were not handed over<lb/>
 prior to 3.00 p.m. In view of objection of the learned<lb/>
 counsels of the RC to using the information contained in<lb/>
 aforesaid VCDs, marked as Article A1 to A6, this Court<lb/>
 had made order on 11.7.2017 that the objections will be<lb/>
 considered in the judgment itself. This VCDs are already<lb/>
 exhibited by this Court as Exhs. 70 to 75. Thus, if the<lb/>
 contents of the aforesaid VCDs can be used in the<lb/>
 evidence, then the petitioners are bound to succeed in the<lb/>
 present matters.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>8.<lb/>
 The High Court then set out Sections 65-A and 65-B of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act, and referred to this Court&apos;s judgment in Anvar P.V. (supra).<lb/>
 The Court held in paragraph 65 of the impugned judgment that the CDs<lb/>
 that were produced by the Election Commission could not be treated as an<lb/>
 original record and would, therefore, have to be proved by means of<lb/>
 secondary evidence. Finding that no written certificate as is required by<lb/>
 Section 65-B(4) of the Evidence Act was furnished by any of the election<lb/>
 officials, and more particularly, the RO, the High Court then held:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;69. In substantive evidence, in the cross examination of<lb/>
 Smt. Mutha, it is brought on the record that there was no<lb/>
 complaint with regard to working of video cameras used<lb/>
 by the office. She has admitted that the video cameras<lb/>
 were regularly used in the office for recording the<lb/>
 aforesaid incidents and daily VCDs were collected of the<lb/>
 recording by her office. This record was created as the<lb/>
 record of the activities of the Election Commission. It is<lb/>
 brought on the record that on the first floor of the building,<lb/>
 arrangement was made by keeping electronic gazettes<lb/>
 like VCR players etc. and arrangement was made for<lb/>
 viewing the recording. It is already observed that under<lb/>
 her instructions, the VCDs were marked of this recording.<lb/>
 Thus, on the basis of her substantive evidence, it can be<lb/>
 said that the conditions mentioned in section 65-B of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act are fulfilled and she is certifying the<lb/>
 electronic record as required by section 65-B (4) of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act. It can be said that Election Commission, the<lb/>
 machinery avoided to give certificate in writing as required<lb/>
 by section 65-B (4) of the Evidence Act. But, substantive<lb/>
 evidence is brought on record of competent officer in that<lb/>
 regard. When the certificate expected is required to be<lb/>
 issued on the basis of best of knowledge and belief, there<lb/>
 is evidence on oath about it of Smt. Mutha. Thus, there is<lb/>
 something more than the contents of certificate mentioned<lb/>
 in section 65-B (4) of the Evidence Act in the present<lb/>
 matters. Such evidence is not barred by the provisions of<lb/>
 section 65-B of the Evidence Act as that evidence is only<lb/>
 on certification made by the responsible official position<lb/>
 like RO. She was incharge of the management of the<lb/>
 relevant activities and so her evidence can be used and<lb/>
 needs to be used as the compliance of the provision of<lb/>
 section 65-B of the Evidence Act. This Court holds that<lb/>
 there is compliance of the provision of section 65-B of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act in the present matter in respect of aforesaid<lb/>
 electronic record and so, the information contained in the<lb/>
 record can be used in the evidence.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>Based, therefore, on &quot;substantial compliance&quot; of the requirement of giving<lb/>
 a certificate under Section 65B of the Evidence Act, it was held that the<lb/>
 CDs/VCDs were admissible in evidence, and based upon this evidence it<lb/>
 was found that, as a matter of fact, the nomination forms by the RC had<lb/>
 been improperly accepted. The election of the RC was therefore was<lb/>
 declared void in the impugned judgment.<lb/>
</p>

<p>9.<lb/>
 Shri Ravindra Adsure, learned advocate appearing on behalf of<lb/>
 the Appellant, submitted that the judgment in Anvar P.V. (supra) covered<lb/>
 the case before us. He argued that without the necessary certificate in<lb/>
 writing and signed under Section 65B(4) of the Evidence Act, the<lb/>
 CDs/VCDs upon which the entirety of the judgment rested could not have<lb/>
 been admitted in evidence. He referred to Tomaso Bruno and Anr. v.<lb/>
 State of Uttar Pradesh (2015) 7 SCC 178, and argued that the said<lb/>
 judgment did not notice either Section 65B or Anvar P.V. (supra), and was<lb/>
 therefore per incuriam. He also argued that Shafhi Mohammad (supra),<lb/>
 being a two-Judge Bench of this Court, could not have arrived at a finding<lb/>
 contrary to Anvar P.V. (supra), which was the judgment of three Hon&apos;ble<lb/>
 Judges of this Court. In particular, he argued that it could not have been<lb/>
 held in Shafhi Mohammad (supra) that whenever the interest of justice<lb/>
 required, the requirement of a certificate could be done away with under<lb/>
 Section 65B(4). Equally, this Court&apos;s judgment dated 03.04.2018, reported<lb/>
 as (2018) 5 SCC 311, which merely followed the law laid down in Shafhi<lb/>
 Mohammad (supra), being contrary to the larger bench judgment in Anvar<lb/>
 P.V. (supra), should also be held as not having laid down good law. He<lb/>
 further argued that the Madras High Court judgment in K. Ramajyam v.<lb/>
 Inspector of Police (2016) Crl. LJ 1542, being contrary to Anvar P.V.<lb/>(supra), also does not lay down the law correctly, in that it holds that<lb/>
 evidence aliunde, that is outside Section 65B, can be taken in order to<lb/>
 make electronic records admissible. In the facts of the present case, he<lb/>
 contended that since it was clear that the requisite certificate had not been<lb/>
 issued, no theory of &quot;substantial compliance&quot; with the provisions of Section<lb/>
 65B(4), as was held by the impugned judgment, could possibly be<lb/>
 sustained in law.<lb/>
</p>

<p>10.<lb/>
 Ms. Meenakshi Arora, learned Senior Advocate appearing on<lb/>
 behalf of the Respondents, has taken us in copious detail through the facts<lb/>
 of this case, and has argued that the High Court has directed the Election<lb/>
 Commission to produce before the Court the original CDs/VCDs of the<lb/>
 video-recording done at the office of the RO, along with the necessary<lb/>
 certificate. An application dated 16.08.2016 was also made to the District<lb/>
 Election Commission and RO as well as the Assistant RO for the requisite<lb/>
 certificate under Section 65B. A reply was given on 14.09.2016, that this<lb/>
 certificate could not be furnished since the matter was sub-judice. Despite<lb/>
 this, later on, on 26.07.2017 her client wrote to the authorities again<lb/>
 requesting for issuance of certificate under Section 65B, but by replies<lb/>
 dated 31.07.2017 and 02.08.2017, no such certificate was forthcoming.<lb/>
 Finally, after having run from pillar to post, her client applied on 26.08.2017<lb/>
 to the Chief Election Commissioner, New Delhi, stating that the authorities<lb/>
 were refusing to give her client the necessary certificate under Section 65B<lb/>
 and that the Chief Election Commissioner should therefore ensure that it<lb/>
 be given to them. To this communication, no reply was forthcoming from<lb/>
 the Chief Election Commissioner, New Delhi. Given this, the High Court at<lb/>
 several places had observed in the course of the impugned judgment that<lb/>
 the authorities deliberately refused, despite being directed, to supply the<lb/>
 requisite certificate under Section 65B, as a result of which the impugned<lb/>
 judgment correctly relied upon the oral testimony of the RO herself.<lb/>
 According to Ms. Arora, such oral testimony taken down in the form of<lb/>
 writing, which witness statement is signed by the RO, would itself amount<lb/>
 to the requisite certificate being issued under Section 65B(4) in the facts of<lb/>
 this case, as was correctly held by the High Court. Quite apart from this,<lb/>
 Ms. Arora also stated that -independent of the finding given by the High<lb/>
 Court by relying upon CDs/VCDs -the High Court also relied upon other<lb/>
 documentary and oral evidence to arrive at the finding that the RC had not<lb/>
 handed over nomination forms directly to the RO at 2.20 p.m (i.e. before<lb/>
 3pm). In fact, it was found on the basis of this evidence that the nomination<lb/>
 forms were handed over and accepted by the RO only after 3.00 p.m. and<lb/>
 were therefore improperly accepted, as a result of which, the election of<lb/>
 the Appellant was correctly set aside.<lb/>
</p>

<p>11.<lb/>
 On law, Ms. Arora argued that it must not be forgotten that<lb/>
 Section 65B is a procedural provision, and it cannot be the law that even<lb/>
 where a certificate is impossible to get, the absence of such certificate<lb/>
 should result in the denial of crucial evidence which would point at the truth<lb/>
 or falsehood of a given set of facts. She, therefore, supported the decision<lb/>
 in Shafhi Mohammad (supra), stating that Anvar P.V. (supra) could be<lb/>
 considered to be good law only in situations where it was possible for the<lb/>
 party to produce the requisite certificate. In cases where this becomes<lb/>
 difficult or impossible, the interest of justice would require that a procedural<lb/>
 provision be not exalted to such a level that vital evidence would be shut<lb/>
 out, resulting in manifest injustice.<lb/>
</p>

<p>12.<lb/>
 Shri Vikas Upadhyay, appearing on behalf of the Intervenor,<lb/>
 took us through the various provisions of the Information Technology Act,<lb/>
 2000 along with Section 65B of the Evidence Act, and argued that Section<lb/>
 65B does not refer to the stage at which the certificate under Section<lb/>
 65B(4) ought to be furnished. He relied upon a judgment of the High Court<lb/>
 of Rajasthan as well as the High Court of Bombay, in addition to Kundan<lb/>
 12<lb/>Singh v. State 2015 SCC OnLine Del 13647 of the Delhi High Court, to<lb/>
 argue that the requisite certificate need not necessarily be given at the time<lb/>
 of tendering of evidence but could be at a subsequent stage of the<lb/>
 proceedings, as in cases where the requisite certificate is not forthcoming<lb/>
 due to no fault of the party who tried to produce it, but who had to apply to<lb/>
 a Judge for its production. He also argued that Anvar P.V. (supra) required<lb/>
 to be clarified to the extent that Sections 65A and 65B being a complete<lb/>
 code as to admissibility of electronic records, the &quot;baggage&quot; of Primary and<lb/>
 Secondary Evidence contained in Sections 62 and 65 of the Evidence Act<lb/>
 should not at all be adverted to, and that the drill of Section 65A and 65B<lb/>
 alone be followed when it comes to admissibility of information contained in<lb/>
 electronic records.<lb/>
</p>

<p>13.<lb/>
 It is now necessary to set out the relevant provisions of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act and the Information Technology Act, 2000. Section 3 of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act defines &quot;document&quot; as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;Document.--&quot;Document&quot; means any matter expressed<lb/>
 or described upon any substance by means of letters,<lb/>
 figures or marks, or by more than one of those means,<lb/>
 intended to be used, or which may be used, for the<lb/>
 purpose of recording that matter.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>&quot;Evidence&quot; in Section 3 is defined as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;Evidence.&quot;--&quot;Evidence&quot; means and includes-(1) all<lb/>
 statements which the Court permits or requires to be<lb/>
 made before it by witnesses, in relation to matters of fact<lb/>
 under inquiry;<lb/>
 such statements are called oral evidence;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(2) all documents including electronic records produced for<lb/>
 the inspection of the Court; such documents are called<lb/>
 documentary evidence.&quot;<lb/></item>
 <p>
 The Evidence Act also declares that the expressions &quot;Certifying<lb/>
 Authority&quot;, &quot;electronic<lb/>
 signature&quot;, &quot;Electronic<lb/>
 Signature<lb/>
 Certificate&quot;,<lb/>
 &quot;electronic form&quot;, &quot;electronic records&quot;, &quot;information&quot;, &quot;secure electronic<lb/>
 record&quot;, &quot;secure digital signature&quot; and &quot;subscriber&quot; shall have the meanings<lb/>
 respectively assigned to them in the Information Technology Act.<lb/>
</p>

<p>14.<lb/>
 Section 22-A of the Evidence Act, which deals with the<lb/>
 relevance of oral admissions as to contents of electronic records, reads as<lb/>
 follows:<lb/>
 <item>
 &quot;22A. When oral admission as to contents of<lb/>
 electronic records are relevant. --Oral admissions as to<lb/>
 the contents of electronic records are not relevant, unless<lb/>
 the genuineness of the electronic record produced is in<lb/>
 question.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>15.<lb/>
 Section 45A of the Evidence Act, on the opinion of the<lb/>
 Examiner of Electronic Evidence, then states:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;45A. Opinion of Examiner of Electronic Evidence.--<lb/>
When in a proceeding, the court has to form an opinion on<lb/>
 any matter relating to any information transmitted or stored<lb/>
 in any computer resource or any other electronic or digital<lb/>
 form, the opinion of the Examiner of Electronic Evidence<lb/>
 referred to in section 79A of the Information Technology<lb/>
 Act, 2000 (21 of 2000), is a relevant fact.<lb/>
</item>

<item>Explanation.--For the purposes of this section, an<lb/>
 Examiner of Electronic Evidence shall be an expert.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>16.<lb/>
 Sections 65-A and 65-B of the Evidence Act read as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;65A. Special provisions as to evidence relating to<lb/>
 electronic record.--The contents of electronic records<lb/>
 may be proved in accordance with the provisions of<lb/>
 section 65B.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;65B. Admissibility of electronic records.-(1)<lb/>
 Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, any<lb/>
 information contained in an electronic record which is<lb/>
 printed on a paper, stored, recorded or copied in optical or<lb/>
 magnetic media produced by a computer (hereinafter<lb/>
 referred to as the computer output) shall be deemed to be<lb/>
 also a document, if the conditions mentioned in this<lb/>
 section are satisfied in relation to the information and<lb/>
 computer in question and shall be admissible in any<lb/>
 proceedings, without further proof or production of the<lb/>
 original, as evidence or any contents of the original or of<lb/>
 any fact stated therein of which direct evidence would be<lb/>
 admissible.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(2) The conditions referred to in sub-section (1) in respect<lb/>
 of a computer output shall be the following, namely:<lb/>
</item>

<item>(a) the computer output containing the information was<lb/>
 produced by the computer during the period over which<lb/>
 the computer was used regularly to store or process<lb/>
 information for the purposes of any activities regularly<lb/>
 carried on over that period by the person having lawful<lb/>
 control over the use of the computer;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(b) during the said period, information of the kind<lb/>
 contained in the electronic record or of the kind from which<lb/>
 the information so contained is derived was regularly fed<lb/>
 into the computer in the ordinary course of the said<lb/>
 activities;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(c) throughout the material part of the said period, the<lb/>
 computer was operating properly or, if not, then in respect<lb/>
 of any period in which it was not operating properly or was<lb/>
 out of operation during that part of the period, was not<lb/>
 such as to affect the electronic record or the accuracy of<lb/>
 its contents; and<lb/>
</item>

<item>(d) the information contained in the electronic record<lb/>
 reproduces or is derived from such information fed into the<lb/>
 computer in the ordinary course of the said activities.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(3) Where over any period, the function of storing or<lb/>
 processing information for the purposes of any activities<lb/>
 regularly carried on over that period as mentioned in<lb/>
 clause (a) of sub-section (2) was regularly performed by<lb/>
 computers, whether-<lb/>
</item>

<item>(a) by a combination of computers operating over that<lb/>
 period; or<lb/>
</item>

<item>(b) by different computers operating in succession over<lb/>
 that period; or<lb/>
</item>

<item>(c) by different combinations of computers operating in<lb/>
 succession over that period; or<lb/>
</item>

<item>(d) in any other manner involving the successive operation<lb/>
 over that period, in whatever order, of one or more<lb/>
 computers and one or more combinations of computers,<lb/>
 all the computers used for that purpose during that period<lb/>
 shall be treated for the purposes of this section as<lb/>
 constituting a single computer; and references in this<lb/>
 section to a computer shall be construed accordingly.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(4) In any proceedings where it is desired to give a<lb/>
 statement in evidence by virtue of this section, a certificate<lb/>
 doing any of the following things, that is to say, -<lb/>
</item>

<item>(a) identifying the electronic record containing the<lb/>
 statement and describing the manner in which it was<lb/>
 produced;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(b) giving such particulars of any device involved in the<lb/>
 production of that electronic record as may be appropriate<lb/>
 for the purpose of showing that the electronic record was<lb/>
 produced by a computer;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(c) dealing with any of the matters to which the conditions<lb/>
 mentioned in sub-section (2) relate,<lb/></item>

 <item>
 and purporting to be signed by a person occupying a<lb/>
 responsible official position in relation to the operation of<lb/>
 the relevant device or the management of the relevant<lb/>
 activities (whichever is appropriate) shall be evidence of<lb/>
 any matter stated in the certificate; and for the purposes of<lb/>
 this subsection it shall be sufficient for a matter to be<lb/>
 stated to the best of the knowledge and belief of the<lb/>
 person stating it.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(5) For the purposes of this section,<lb/>
</item>

<item>(a) information shall be taken to be supplied to a computer<lb/>
 if it is supplied thereto in any appropriate form and<lb/>
 whether it is so supplied directly or (with or without human<lb/>
 intervention) by means of any appropriate equipment; --<lb/>
</item>

<item>(b) whether in the course of activities carried on by any<lb/>
 official, information is supplied with a view to its being<lb/>
 stored or processed for the purposes of those activities by<lb/>
 a computer operated otherwise than in the course of those<lb/>
 activities, that information, if duly supplied to that<lb/>
 computer, shall be taken to be supplied to it in the course<lb/>
 of those activities;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(c) a computer output shall be taken to have been<lb/>
 produced by a computer whether it was produced by it<lb/>
 directly or (with or without human intervention) by means<lb/>
 of any appropriate equipment.<lb/>
</item>

<item>Explanation. --For the purposes of this section any<lb/>
 reference to information being derived from other<lb/>
 information shall be a reference to its being derived<lb/>
 therefrom by calculation, comparison or any other<lb/>
 process.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>17.<lb/>
 The following definitions as contained in Section 2 of the<lb/>
 Information Technology Act, 2000 are also relevant:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;(i) &quot;computer&quot; means any electronic, magnetic, optical or<lb/>
 other high-speed data processing device or system which<lb/>
 performs logical, arithmetic, and memory functions by<lb/>
 manipulations of electronic, magnetic or optical impulses,<lb/>
 and includes all input, output, processing, storage,<lb/>
 computer software or communication facilities which are<lb/>
 connected or related to the computer in a computer<lb/>
 system or computer network;&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;(j) &quot;computer network&quot; means the inter-connection of one<lb/>
 or more computers or computer systems or<lb/>
 communication device through-(i) the use of satellite,<lb/>
 microwave, terrestrial line, wire, wireless or other<lb/>
 communication media; and (ii) terminals or a complex<lb/>
 consisting of two or more interconnected computers or<lb/>
 communication device whether or not the inter-connection<lb/>
 is continuously maintained;&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;(l) &quot;computer system&quot; means a device or collection of<lb/>
 devices, including input and output support devices and<lb/>
 excluding calculators which are not programmable and<lb/>
 capable of being used in conjunction with external files,<lb/>
 which contain computer programmes, electronic<lb/>
 instructions, input data and output data, that performs<lb/>
 logic,<lb/>
 arithmetic,<lb/>
 data<lb/>
 storage<lb/>
 and<lb/>
 retrieval,<lb/>
 communication control and other functions;&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;(o) &quot;data&quot; means a representation of information,<lb/>
 knowledge, facts, concepts or instructions which are being<lb/>
 prepared or have been prepared in a formalised manner,<lb/>
 and is intended to be processed, is being processed or<lb/>
 has been processed in a computer system or computer<lb/>
 network, and may be in any form (including computer<lb/>
 printouts magnetic or optical storage media, punched<lb/>
 cards, punched tapes) or stored internally in the memory<lb/>
 of the computer;&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;(r) &quot;electronic form&quot;, with reference to information, means<lb/>
 any information generated, sent, received or stored in<lb/>
 media, magnetic, optical, computer memory, micro film,<lb/>
 computer generated micro fiche or similar device;&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;(t) &quot;electronic record&quot; means data, record or data<lb/>
 generated, image or sound stored, received or sent in an<lb/>
 electronic form or micro film or computer generated micro<lb/>
 fiche;&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>18.<lb/>
 Sections 65A and 65B occur in Chapter V of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act which is entitled &quot;Of Documentary Evidence&quot;. Section 61 of<lb/>
 the Evidence Act deals with the proof of contents of documents, and states<lb/>
 that the contents of documents may be proved either by primary or by<lb/>
 secondary evidence. Section 62 of the Evidence Act defines primary<lb/>
 evidence as meaning the document itself produced for the inspection of the<lb/>
 court. Section 63 of the Evidence Act speaks of the kind or types of<lb/>
 secondary evidence by which documents may be proved. Section 64 of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act then enacts that documents must be proved by primary<lb/>
 evidence except in the circumstances hereinafter mentioned. Section 65 of<lb/>
 the Evidence Act is important, and states that secondary evidence may be<lb/>
 given of &quot;the existence, condition or contents of a document in the<lb/>
 following cases…&quot;.<lb/>
</p>

<p>19.<lb/>
 Section 65 differentiates between existence, condition<lb/>
 and contents of a document. Whereas &quot;existence&quot; goes to &quot;admissibility&quot; of<lb/>
 a document, &quot;contents&quot; of a document are to be proved after a document<lb/>
 becomes admissible in evidence. Section 65A speaks of &quot;contents&quot; of<lb/>
 electronic records being proved in accordance with the provisions of<lb/>
 Section 65B. Section 65B speaks of &quot;admissibility&quot; of electronic records<lb/>
 which deals with &quot;existence&quot; and &quot;contents&quot; of electronic records being<lb/>
 proved once admissible into evidence. With these prefatory observations<lb/>
 let us have a closer look at Sections 65A and 65B.<lb/>
</p>

<p>20.<lb/>
 It will first be noticed that the subject matter of Sections 65A<lb/>
 and 65B of the Evidence Act is proof of information contained in electronic<lb/>
 records. The marginal note to Section 65A indicates that &quot;special<lb/>
 provisions&quot; as to evidence relating to electronic records are laid down in<lb/>
 this provision. The marginal note to Section 65B then refers to<lb/>
 &quot;admissibility of electronic records&quot;.<lb/>
</p>

<p>21.<lb/>
 Section 65B(1) opens with a non-obstante clause, and makes<lb/>
 it clear that any information that is contained in an electronic record which<lb/>
 is printed on a paper, stored, recorded or copied in optical or magnetic<lb/>
 media produced by a computer shall be deemed to be a document, and<lb/>
 shall be admissible in any proceedings without further proof of production<lb/>
 of the original, as evidence of the contents of the original or of any facts<lb/>
 stated therein of which direct evidence would be admissible. The deeming<lb/>
 fiction is for the reason that &quot;document&quot; as defined by Section 3 of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act does not include electronic records.<lb/>
</p>

<p>22.<lb/>
 Section 65B(2) then refers to the conditions that must be<lb/>
 satisfied in respect of a computer output, and states that the test for being<lb/>
 included in conditions 65B(2(a)) to 65(2(d)) is that the computer be<lb/>
 regularly used to store or process information for purposes of activities<lb/>
 regularly carried on in the period in question. The conditions mentioned in<lb/>
 sub-sections 2(a) to 2(d) must be satisfied cumulatively.<lb/>
</p>

<p>23.<lb/>
 Under Sub-section (4), a certificate is to be produced that<lb/>
 identifies the electronic record containing the statement and describes the<lb/>
 manner in which it is produced, or gives particulars of the device involved<lb/>
 in the production of the electronic record to show that the electronic record<lb/>
 was produced by a computer, by either a person occupying a responsible<lb/>
 official position in relation to the operation of the relevant device; or a<lb/>
 person who is in the management of &quot;relevant activities&quot; -whichever is<lb/>
 appropriate. What is also of importance is that it shall be sufficient for such<lb/>
 matter to be stated to the &quot;best of the knowledge and belief of the person<lb/>
 stating it&quot;. Here, &quot;doing any of the following things…&quot; must be read as<lb/>
 doing all of the following things, it being well settled that the expression<lb/>
 &quot;any&quot; can mean &quot;all&quot; given the context (see, for example, this Court&apos;s<lb/>
 judgments in Bansilal Agarwalla v. State of Bihar (1962) 1 SCR 33 1 and<lb/>
 1</p>

<p>&quot;3. The first contention is based on an assumption that the word &quot;any one&quot; in Section 76<lb/>
 means only &quot;one of the directors, and only one of the shareholders&quot;. This question as regards<lb/>
 the interpretation of the word &quot;any one&quot; in Section 76 was raised in Criminal Appeals Nos. 98<lb/>
 to 106 of 1959 (Chief Inspector of Mines, etc.) and it has been decided there that the word<lb/>
 &quot;any one&quot; should be interpreted there as &quot;every one&quot;. Thus under Section 76 every one of the<lb/>
 shareholders of a private company owning the mine, and every one of the directors of a public<lb/>
 the conditions mentioned in sub-section (4) must also be interpreted as<lb/>
 being cumulative.<lb/>
</p>

<p>24.<lb/>
 It is now appropriate to examine the manner in which Section<lb/>
 65B was interpreted by this Court. In Anvar P.V. (supra), a three Judge<lb/>
 Bench of this Court, after setting out Sections 65A and 65B of the Evidence<lb/>
 Act, held:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;14. Any documentary evidence by way of an electronic<lb/>
 record under the Evidence Act, in view of Sections 59 and<lb/>
 65-A, can be proved only in accordance with the<lb/>
 procedure prescribed under Section 65-B. Section 65-B<lb/>
 deals with the admissibility of the electronic record. The<lb/>
 purpose of these provisions is to sanctify secondary<lb/>
 evidence in electronic form, generated by a computer. It<lb/>
 may be noted that the section starts with a non obstante<lb/>
 clause. Thus, notwithstanding anything contained in the<lb/>
 Evidence Act, any information contained in an electronic<lb/>
 record which is printed on a paper, stored, recorded or<lb/>
 copied in optical or magnetic media produced by a<lb/>
 computer shall be deemed to be a document only if the<lb/>
 conditions mentioned under sub-section (2) are satisfied,<lb/>
 company owning the mine is liable to prosecution. No question of violation of Article 14<lb/>
 therefore arises.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>2 &quot;70. Perusal of the opinion of the Full Bench in B.R. Gupta-I [Balak Ram Gupta v. Union of<lb/>
 India, AIR 1987 Del 239] would clearly indicate with regard to interpretation of the word &quot;any&quot;<lb/>
 in Explanation 1 to the first proviso to Section 6 of the Act which expands the scope of stay<lb/>
 order granted in one case of landowners to be automatically extended to all those landowners,<lb/>
 whose lands are covered under the notifications issued under Section 4 of the Act, irrespective<lb/>
 of the fact whether there was any separate order of stay or not as regards their lands. The<lb/>
 logic assigned by the Full Bench, the relevant portions whereof have been reproduced<lb/>
 hereinabove, appear to be reasonable, apt, legal and proper.&quot;<lb/>
 (emphasis added)<lb/></item>

 <item>
 without further proof or production of the original. The very<lb/>
 admissibility of such a document i.e. electronic record<lb/>
 which is called as computer output, depends on the<lb/>
 satisfaction of the four conditions under Section 65-B(2).<lb/>
 Following are the specified conditions under Section 65-<lb/>
B(2) of the Evidence Act:<lb/>
</item>

<item>(i) The electronic record containing the information should<lb/>
 have been produced by the computer during the period<lb/>
 over which the same was regularly used to store or<lb/>
 process information for the purpose of any activity<lb/>
 regularly carried on over that period by the person having<lb/>
 lawful control over the use of that computer;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(ii) The information of the kind contained in electronic<lb/>
 record or of the kind from which the information is derived<lb/>
 was regularly fed into the computer in the ordinary course<lb/>
 of the said activity;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(iii) During the material part of the said period, the<lb/>
 computer was operating properly and that even if it was<lb/>
 not operating properly for some time, the break or breaks<lb/>
 had not affected either the record or the accuracy of its<lb/>
 contents; and<lb/>
</item>

<item>(iv) The information contained in the record should be a<lb/>
 reproduction or derivation from the information fed into the<lb/>
 computer in the ordinary course of the said activity.<lb/>
</item>

<item>15. Under Section 65-B(4) of the Evidence Act, if it is<lb/>
 desired to give a statement in any proceedings pertaining<lb/>
 to an electronic record, it is permissible provided the<lb/>
 following conditions are satisfied:<lb/>
</item>

<item>(a) There must be a certificate which identifies the<lb/>
 electronic record containing the statement;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(b) The certificate must describe the manner in which the<lb/>
 electronic record was produced;<lb/>
 24<lb/>
</item>

<item>(c) The certificate must furnish the particulars of the device<lb/>
 involved in the production of that record;<lb/>
 (d) The certificate must deal with the applicable conditions<lb/>
 mentioned under Section 65-B(2) of the Evidence Act; and<lb/>
</item>

<item>(e) The certificate must be signed by a person occupying a<lb/>
 responsible official position in relation to the operation of<lb/>
 the relevant device.<lb/>
</item>

<item>16. It is further clarified that the person need only to state<lb/>
 in the certificate that the same is to the best of his<lb/>
 knowledge and belief. Most importantly, such a certificate<lb/>
 must accompany the electronic record like computer<lb/>
 printout, compact disc (CD), video compact disc (VCD),<lb/>
 pen drive, etc., pertaining to which a statement is sought<lb/>
 to be given in evidence, when the same is produced in<lb/>
 evidence. All these safeguards are taken to ensure the<lb/>
 source and authenticity, which are the two hallmarks<lb/>
 pertaining to electronic record sought to be used as<lb/>
 evidence. Electronic records being more susceptible to<lb/>
 tampering, alteration, transposition, excision, etc. without<lb/>
 such safeguards, the whole trial based on proof of<lb/>
 electronic records can lead to travesty of justice.<lb/>
</item>

<item>17. Only if the electronic record is duly produced in terms<lb/>
 of Section 65-B of the Evidence Act, would the question<lb/>
 arise as to the genuineness thereof and in that situation,<lb/>
 resort can be made to Section 45-A-opinion of Examiner<lb/>
 of Electronic Evidence.<lb/>
</item>

<item>18. The Evidence Act does not contemplate or permit the<lb/>
 proof of an electronic record by oral evidence if<lb/>
 requirements under Section 65-B of the Evidence Act are<lb/>
 not complied with, as the law now stands in India.<lb/>
</item>

<item>xxx xxx xxx<lb/>
</item>

<item>20. Proof of electronic record is a special provision<lb/>
 introduced by the IT Act amending various provisions<lb/>
 under the Evidence Act. The very caption of Section 65-A<lb/>
 of the Evidence Act, read with Sections 59 and 65-B is<lb/>
 sufficient to hold that the special provisions on evidence<lb/>
 relating to electronic record shall be governed by the<lb/>
 procedure prescribed under Section 65-B of the Evidence<lb/>
 Act. That is a complete code in itself. Being a special law,<lb/>
 the general law under Sections 63 and 65 has to yield.<lb/>
</item>

<item>21. In State (NCT of Delhi) v. Navjot Sandhu a two-Judge<lb/>
 Bench of this Court had an occasion to consider an issue<lb/>
 on production of electronic record as evidence. While<lb/>
 considering the printouts of the computerised records of<lb/>
 the calls pertaining to the cellphones, it was held at para<lb/>
 150 as follows: (SCC p. 714)<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;150. According to Section 63, &quot;secondary evidence&quot;<lb/>
 means and includes, among other things, &apos;copies made<lb/>
 from the original by mechanical processes which in<lb/>
 themselves insure the accuracy of the copy, and copies<lb/>
 compared with such copies&apos;. Section 65 enables<lb/>
 secondary evidence of the contents of a document to be<lb/>
 adduced if the original is of such a nature as not to be<lb/>
 easily movable. It is not in dispute that the information<lb/>
 contained in the call records is stored in huge servers<lb/>
 which cannot be easily moved and produced in the court.<lb/>
 That is what the High Court has also observed at para<lb/>
 276. Hence, printouts taken from the computers/servers<lb/>
 by mechanical process and certified by a responsible<lb/>
 official of the service-providing company can be led in<lb/>
 evidence through a witness who can identify the<lb/>
 signatures of the certifying officer or otherwise speak of<lb/>
 the facts based on his personal knowledge. Irrespective of<lb/>
 the compliance with the requirements of Section 65-B,<lb/>
 which is a provision dealing with admissibility of electronic<lb/>
 records, there is no bar to adducing secondary evidence<lb/>
 under the other provisions of the Evidence Act, namely,<lb/>
 Sections 63 and 65. It may be that the certificate<lb/>
 containing the details in sub-section (4) of Section 65-B is<lb/>
 26<lb/>
 not filed in the instant case, but that does not mean that<lb/>
 secondary evidence cannot be given even if the law<lb/>
 permits such evidence to be given in the circumstances<lb/>
 mentioned in the relevant provisions, namely, Sections 63<lb/>
 and 65.&quot;<lb/></item>
 <item>
 It may be seen that it was a case where a responsible<lb/>
 official had duly certified the document at the time of<lb/>
 production itself. The signatures in the certificate were<lb/>
 also identified. That is apparently in compliance with the<lb/>
 procedure prescribed under Section 65-B of the Evidence<lb/>
 Act. However, it was held that irrespective of the<lb/>
 compliance with the requirements of Section 65-B, which<lb/>
 is a special provision dealing with admissibility of the<lb/>
 electronic record, there is no bar in adducing secondary<lb/>
 evidence, under Sections 63 and 65, of an electronic<lb/>
 record.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>22. The evidence relating to electronic record, as noted<lb/>
 hereinbefore, being a special provision, the general law on<lb/>
 secondary evidence under Section 63 read with Section<lb/>
 65 of the Evidence Act shall yield to the same. Generalia<lb/>
 specialibus non derogant, special law will always prevail<lb/>
 over the general law. It appears, the court omitted to take<lb/>
 note of Sections 59 and 65-A dealing with the admissibility<lb/>
 of electronic record. Sections 63 and 65 have no<lb/>
 application in the case of secondary evidence by way of<lb/>
 electronic record; the same is wholly governed by<lb/>
 Sections 65-A and 65-B. To that extent, the statement of<lb/>
 law on admissibility of secondary evidence pertaining to<lb/>
 electronic record, as stated by this Court in Navjot Sandhu<lb/>
 case, does not lay down the correct legal position. It<lb/>
 requires to be overruled and we do so. An electronic<lb/>
 record by way of secondary evidence shall not be<lb/>
 admitted in evidence unless the requirements under<lb/>
 Section 65-B are satisfied. Thus, in the case of CD, VCD,<lb/>
 chip, etc., the same shall be accompanied by the<lb/>
 certificate in terms of Section 65-B obtained at the time of<lb/>
 27<lb/>
 taking the document, without which, the secondary<lb/>
 evidence pertaining to that electronic record, is<lb/>
 inadmissible.<lb/>
</item>

<item>23. The appellant admittedly has not produced any<lb/>
 certificate in terms of Section 65-B in respect of the CDs,<lb/>
 Exts. P-4, P-8, P-9, P-10, P-12, P-13, P-15, P-20 and P-<lb/>
22. Therefore, the same cannot be admitted in evidence.<lb/>
 Thus, the whole case set up regarding the corrupt practice<lb/>
 using songs, announcements and speeches fall to the<lb/>
 ground.<lb/>
</item>

<item>24. The situation would have been different had the<lb/>
 appellant adduced primary evidence, by making available<lb/>
 in evidence, the CDs used for announcement and songs.<lb/>
 Had those CDs used for objectionable songs or<lb/>
 announcements been duly got seized through the police or<lb/>
 Election Commission and had the same been used as<lb/>
 primary evidence, the High Court could have played the<lb/>
 same in court to see whether the allegations were true.<lb/>
 That is not the situation in this case. The speeches, songs<lb/>
 and announcements were recorded using other<lb/>
 instruments and by feeding them into a computer, CDs<lb/>
 were made therefrom which were produced in court,<lb/>
 without due certification. Those CDs cannot be admitted in<lb/>
 evidence since the mandatory requirements of Section 65-<lb/>
B of the Evidence Act are not satisfied. It is clarified that<lb/>
 notwithstanding what we have stated herein in the<lb/>
 preceding paragraphs on the secondary evidence of<lb/>
 electronic record with reference to Sections 59, 65-A and<lb/>
 65-B of the Evidence Act, if an electronic record as such is<lb/>
 used as primary evidence under Section 62 of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act, the same is admissible in evidence, without<lb/>
 compliance with the conditions in Section 65-B of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act.&quot;<lb/>
</item>



<p>25.<lb/>
 Shri Upadhyay took exception to the language of paragraph 24<lb/>
 in this judgment. According to the learned counsel, primary and secondary<lb/>
 evidence as to documents, referred to in Sections 61 to Section 65 of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act, should be kept out of admissibility of electronic records,<lb/>
 given the fact that Sections 65A and 65B are a complete code on the<lb/>
 subject.<lb/>
</p>

<p>26.<lb/>
 At this juncture, it is important to note that Section 65B has its<lb/>
 genesis in Section 5 of the Civil Evidence Act 1968 (UK), which reads as<lb/>
 follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;Admissibility of statements produced by computers.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(1) In any civil proceedings a statement contained in a<lb/>
 document produced by a computer shall, subject to rules<lb/>
 of court, be admissible as evidence of any fact stated<lb/>
 therein of which direct oral evidence would be admissible,<lb/>
 if it is shown that the conditions mentioned in subsection<lb/>
 (2) below are satisfied in relation to the statement and<lb/>
 computer in question.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(2) The said conditions are-<lb/>
</item>

<item>(a) that the document containing the statement was<lb/>
 produced by the computer during a period over which the<lb/>
 computer was used regularly to store or process<lb/>
 information for the purposes of any activities regularly<lb/>
 carried on over that period, whether for profit or not, by<lb/>
 any body, whether corporate or not, or by any individual;<lb/>
 29<lb/>
</item>

<item>(b) that over that period there was regularly supplied to the<lb/>
 computer in the ordinary course of those activities<lb/>
 information of the kind contained in the statement or of the<lb/>
 kind from which the information so contained is derived;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(c) that throughout the material part of that period the<lb/>
 computer was operating properly or, if not, that any<lb/>
 respect in which it was not operating properly or was out<lb/>
 of operation during that part of that period was not such as<lb/>
 to affect the production of the document or the accuracy of<lb/>
 its contents; and<lb/>
</item>

<item>(d) that the information contained in the statement<lb/>
 reproduces or is derived from information supplied to the<lb/>
 computer in the ordinary course of those activities.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(3) Where over a period the function of storing or<lb/>
 processing information for the purposes of any activities<lb/>
 regularly carried on over that period as mentioned in<lb/>
 subsection (2)(a) above was regularly performed by<lb/>
 computers, whether-<lb/>
</item>

<item>(a) by a combination of computers operating over that<lb/>
 period; or<lb/>
</item>

<item>(b) by different computers operating in succession over<lb/>
 that period; or<lb/>
</item>

<item>(c) by different combinations of computers operating in<lb/>
 succession over that period; or<lb/>
</item>

<item>(d) in any other manner involving the successive operation<lb/>
 over that period, in whatever order, of one or more<lb/>
 computers and one or more combinations of computers,<lb/>
 all the computers used for that purpose during that period<lb/>
 shall be treated for the purposes of this Part of this Act as<lb/>
 30<lb/>
 constituting a single computer; and references in this Part<lb/>
 of this Act to a computer shall be construed accordingly.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(4) In any civil proceedings where it is desired to give a<lb/>
 statement in evidence by virtue of this section, a certificate<lb/>
 doing any of the following things, that is to say-<lb/>
</item>

<item>(a) identifying the document containing the statement and<lb/>
 describing the manner in which it was produced;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(b) giving such particulars of any device involved in the<lb/>
 production of that document as may be appropriate for the<lb/>
 purpose of showing that the document was produced by a<lb/>
 computer;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(c) dealing with any of the matters to which the conditions<lb/>
 mentioned in subsection (2) above relate,<lb/></item>

 <item>
 and purporting to be signed by a person occupying a<lb/>
 responsible position in relation to the operation of the<lb/>
 relevant device or the management of the relevant<lb/>
 activities (whichever is appropriate) shall be evidence of<lb/>
 any matter stated in the certificate; and for the purposes of<lb/>
 this subsection it shall be sufficient for a matter to be<lb/>
 stated to the best of the knowledge and belief of the<lb/>
 person stating it.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(5) For the purposes of this Part of this Act-<lb/>
</item>

<item>(a) information shall be taken to be supplied to a computer<lb/>
 if it is supplied thereto in any appropriate form and<lb/>
 whether it is so supplied directly or (with or without human<lb/>
 intervention) by means of any appropriate equipment;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(b) where, in the course of activities carried on by any<lb/>
 individual or body, information is supplied with a view to its<lb/>
 being stored or processed for the purposes of those<lb/>
 activities by a computer operated otherwise than in the<lb/>
 31<lb/>
 course of those activities, that information, if duly supplied<lb/>
 to that computer, shall be taken to be supplied to it in the<lb/>
 course of those activities;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(c) a document shall be taken to have been produced by a<lb/>
 computer whether it was produced by it directly or (with or<lb/>
 without human intervention) by means of any appropriate<lb/>
 equipment.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(6) Subject to subsection (3) above, in this Part of this Act<lb/>
 &quot;computer &quot; means any device for storing and processing<lb/>
 information, and any reference to information being<lb/>
 derived from other information is a reference to its being<lb/>
 derived therefrom by calculation, comparison or any other<lb/>
 process.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>27.<lb/>
 It may be noticed that sub-sections (2) to (5) of Section 65B of<lb/>
 the Evidence Act are a reproduction of sub-sections (2) to (5) of Section 5<lb/>
 of the Civil Evidence Act, 1968, with minor changes 3 . The definition of<lb/>
 3 Section 69 of the UK Police and Criminal Evidence Act, 1984 dealt with evidence from<lb/>
 computer records in criminal proceedings. Section 69 read thus:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;69.-(1) In any proceedings, a statement in a document produced by a computer shall not be<lb/>
 admissible as evidence of any fact stated therein unless it is shown-<lb/></item>

 <item>
(a) that there are no reasonable grounds for believing that the statement is inaccurate<lb/>
 because of improper use of that computer;<lb/></item>
 <item>
 (b) that at all material times the computer was operating properly, or if not, that any<lb/>
 respect in which it was not operating properly or was out of operation was not such as to<lb/>
 affect the production of the document or the accuracy of its contents; and<lb/></item>
 <item>
 (c) that any relevant conditions specified in rules of court under subsection (2) below<lb/>
 are satisfied.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(2) Provision may be made by rules of court requiring that in any proceedings where it is<lb/>
 desired to give a statement in evidence by virtue of this section such information concerning the<lb/>
 statement as may be required by the rules shall be provided in such form and at such time as<lb/>
 may be so required.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>By Section 70, Sections 68 and 69 of this Act had to be read with Schedule 3 thereof, the<lb/>
 provisions of which had the same force in effect as Sections 68 and 69. Part I of Schedule 3<lb/>
 supplemented Section 68. Notwithstanding the importance of Part I of Schedule 3, we propose<lb/>
 to refer to only two provisions of it, namely:<lb/>
</p>

<p>32<lb/>
 &quot;computer&quot; under Section 5(6) of the Civil Evidence Act, 1968 was not,<lb/>
 however, adopted by Section 2(i) of the Information Technology Act, 2000,<lb/>
 which as noted above, is a &apos;means and includes&apos; definition of a much more<lb/>
 complex and intricate nature. It is also important to note Section 6(1) and<lb/>
 (5) of the Civil Evidence Act, 1968, which state as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;(1) Where in any civil proceedings a statement contained<lb/>
 in a document is proposed to be given in evidence by<lb/>
 virtue of section 2, 4 or 5 of this Act it may, subject to any<lb/>
 rules of court, be proved by the production of that<lb/>
 document or (whether or not that document is still in<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;1. Section 68(1) above applies whether the information contained in the document was<lb/>
 supplied directly or indirectly but, if it was supplied indirectly, only if each person through whom<lb/>
 it was supplied was acting under a duty; and applies also where the person compiling the<lb/>
 record is himself the person by whom the information is supplied.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;6. Any reference in Section 68 above or this Part of this Schedule to a person acting under a<lb/>
 duty includes a reference to a person acting in the course of any trade, business, profession or<lb/>
 other occupation in which he is engaged or employed or for the purposes of any paid or unpaid<lb/>
 office held by him.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>Part II supplemented Section 69 in important respects. Two provisions of it are relevant,<lb/>
 namely-<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;8. In any proceedings where it is desired to give a statement in evidence in accordance with<lb/>
 section 69 above, a certificate -<lb/></item>

 <item>
(a)<lb/>
 identifying the document containing the statement and describing the<lb/>
 manner in which it was produced;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(b)<lb/>
 giving such particulars of any device involved in the production of that<lb/>
 document as may be appropriate for the purpose of showing that the document was<lb/>
 produced by a computer;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(c)<lb/>
 dealing with any of the matters mentioned in Section 69(1) above; and<lb/>
</item>

<item>(d)<lb/>
 purporting to be signed by a person occupying a reasonable position in<lb/>
 relation to the operation of the computer, shall be evidence of anything stated in it; and for<lb/>
 the purposes of this paragraph it shall be sufficient for a matter to be stated to the best of<lb/>
 the knowledge and belief of the person stating it.<lb/>
</item>

<item>9. Notwithstanding paragraph 8 above, a court may require oral evidence to be given of<lb/>
 anything of which evidence could be given by a certificate under that paragraph.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item><lb/>
 existence) by the production of a copy of that document,<lb/>
 or of the material part thereof, authenticated in such<lb/>
 manner as the court may approve.<lb/>
</item>

<item>xxx xxx xxx<lb/>
</item>

<item>(5) If any person in a certificate tendered in evidence in<lb/>
 civil proceedings by virtue of section 5(4) of this Act wilfully<lb/>
 makes a statement material in those proceedings which<lb/>
 he knows to be false or does not believe to be true, he<lb/>
 shall be liable on conviction on indictment to imprisonment<lb/>
 for a term not exceeding two years or a fine or both.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>28.<lb/>
 Section 6(1), in essence, maintains the dichotomy between<lb/>
 proof by &apos;primary&apos; and &apos;secondary&apos; evidence -proof by production of the<lb/>
 &apos;document&apos; itself being primary evidence, and proof by production of a copy<lb/>
 of that document, as authenticated, being secondary evidence. Section<lb/>
 6(5), which gives teeth to the person granting the certificate mentioned in<lb/>
 Section 5(4) of the Act, by punishing false statements wilfully made in the<lb/>
 certificate, has not been included in the Indian Evidence Act. These<lb/>
 sections have since been repealed by the Civil Evidence Act of 1995 (UK),<lb/>
 pursuant to a UK Law Commission Report published in September, 1993<lb/>
 (Law Com. No. 216), by which the strict rule as to hearsay evidence was<lb/>
 relaxed, and hearsay evidence was made admissible in the circumstances<lb/>
 mentioned by the Civil Evidence Act of 1995. Sections 8, 9 and 13 of this<lb/>
 Act are important, and are set out hereinbelow:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;8. Proof of statements contained in documents.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(1) Where a statement contained in a document is<lb/>
 admissible as evidence in civil proceedings, it may be<lb/>
 proved-<lb/>
</item>

<item>(a) by the production of that document, or<lb/>
</item>

<item>(b) whether or not that document is still in existence, by<lb/>
 the production of a copy of that document or of the<lb/>
 material part of it,<lb/>
 authenticated in such manner as the court may approve.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(2) It is immaterial for this purpose how many removes<lb/>
 there are between a copy and the original.<lb/>
</item>

<item>9. Proof of records of business or public authority.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(1) A document which is shown to form part of the records<lb/>
 of a business or public authority may be received in<lb/>
 evidence in civil proceedings without further proof.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(2) A document shall be taken to form part of the records<lb/>
 of a business or public authority if there is produced to the<lb/>
 court a certificate to that effect signed by an officer of the<lb/>
 business or authority to which the records belong. For this<lb/>
 purpose-<lb/>
</item>

<item>(a) a document purporting to be a certificate signed by an<lb/>
 officer of a business or public authority shall be deemed to<lb/>
 have been duly given by such an officer and signed by<lb/>
 him; and<lb/>
</item>

<item>(b) a certificate shall be treated as signed by a person if it<lb/>
 purports to bear a facsimile of his signature.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(3) The absence of an entry in the records of a business or<lb/>
 public authority may be proved in civil proceedings by<lb/>
 affidavit of an officer of the business or authority to which<lb/>
 the records belong.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(4) In this section-<lb/>
&quot;records&quot; means records in whatever form;<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;business&quot; includes any activity regularly carried on over a<lb/>
 period of time, whether for profit or not, by any body<lb/>
 (whether corporate or not) or by an individual;<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;officer&quot; includes any person occupying a responsible<lb/>
 position in relation to the relevant activities of the business<lb/>
 or public authority or in relation to its records; and<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;public authority&quot; includes any public or statutory<lb/>
 undertaking, any government department and any person<lb/>
 holding office under Her Majesty.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(5) The court may, having regard to the circumstances of<lb/>
 the case, direct that all or any of the above provisions of<lb/>
 this section do not apply in relation to a particular<lb/>
 document or record, or description of documents or<lb/>
 records.&quot;<lb/></item>

<p> 
 Section 13 of this Act defines &quot;document&quot; as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;document&quot; means anything in which information of any<lb/>
 description is recorded, and &quot;copy&quot;, in relation to a<lb/>
 document, means anything onto which information<lb/>
 recorded in the document has been copied, by whatever<lb/>
 means and whether directly or indirectly;&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>29.<lb/>
 Section 15(2) of this Act repeals enactments mentioned in<lb/>
 Schedule II therein; and Schedule II repeals Part I of the Civil Evidence<lb/>
 Act, 1968 -of which Sections 5 and 6 were a part. The definition of<lb/>
 &quot;records&quot; and &quot;document&quot; in this Act would show that electronic records are<lb/>
 considered to be part of &quot;document&quot; as defined, needing no separate<lb/>
 treatment as to admissibility or proof. It is thus clear that in UK law, as at<lb/>
 present, no distinction is made between computer generated evidence and<lb/>
 other evidence either qua the admissibility of, or the attachment of weight<lb/>
 to, such evidence.<lb/>
</p>

<p>30.<lb/>
 Coming back to Section 65B of the Indian Evidence Act, sub-<lb/>
section (1) needs to be analysed. The sub-section begins with a non-<lb/>
obstante clause, and then goes on to mention information contained in an<lb/>
 electronic record produced by a computer, which is, by a deeming fiction,<lb/>
 then made a &quot;document&quot;. This deeming fiction only takes effect if the<lb/>
 further conditions mentioned in the Section are satisfied in relation to both<lb/>
 the information and the computer in question; and if such conditions are<lb/>
 met, the &quot;document&quot; shall then be admissible in any proceedings. The<lb/>
 words &quot;…without further proof or production of the original…&quot; make it clear<lb/>
 that once the deeming fiction is given effect by the fulfilment of the<lb/>
 conditions mentioned in the Section, the &quot;deemed document&quot; now<lb/>
 becomes admissible in evidence without further proof or production of the<lb/>
 original as evidence of any contents of the original, or of any fact stated<lb/>
 therein of which direct evidence would be admissible.<lb/>
</p>

<p>31.<lb/>
 The non-obstante clause in sub-section (1) makes it clear that<lb/>
 when it comes to information contained in an electronic record,<lb/>
 admissibility and proof thereof must follow the drill of Section 65B, which is<lb/>
 a special provision in this behalf -Sections 62 to 65 being irrelevant for this<lb/>
 purpose. However, Section 65B(1) clearly differentiates between the<lb/>
 &quot;original&quot; document -which would be the original &quot;electronic record&quot;<lb/>
 contained in the &quot;computer&quot; in which the original information is first stored -<lb/>
and the computer output containing such information, which then may be<lb/>
 treated as evidence of the contents of the &quot;original&quot; document. All this<lb/>
 necessarily shows that Section 65B differentiates between the original<lb/>
 information contained in the &quot;computer&quot; itself and copies made therefrom -<lb/>
the former being primary evidence, and the latter being secondary<lb/>
 evidence.<lb/>
</p>

<p>32.<lb/>
 Quite obviously, the requisite certificate in sub-section (4) is<lb/>
 unnecessary if the original document itself is produced. This can be done<lb/>
 by the owner of a laptop computer, a computer tablet or even a mobile<lb/>
 phone, by stepping into the witness box and proving that the concerned<lb/>
 device, on which the original information is first stored, is owned and/or<lb/>
 operated by him. In cases where &quot;the computer&quot;, as defined, happens to<lb/>
 be a part of a &quot;computer system&quot; or &quot;computer network&quot; (as defined in the<lb/>
 Information Technology Act, 2000) and it becomes impossible to physically<lb/>
 bring such network or system to the Court, then the only means of proving<lb/>
 information contained in such electronic record can be in accordance with<lb/>
 Section 65B(1), together with the requisite certificate under Section 65B(4).<lb/>
 This being the case, it is necessary to clarify what is contained in the last<lb/>
 sentence in paragraph 24 of Anvar P.V. (supra) which reads as &quot;…if an<lb/>
 electronic record as such is used as primary evidence under Section 62 of<lb/>
 the Evidence Act…&quot;. This may more appropriately be read without the<lb/>
 words &quot;under Section 62 of the Evidence Act,…&quot;. With this minor<lb/>
 clarification, the law stated in paragraph 24 of Anvar P.V. (supra) does not<lb/>
 need to be revisited.<lb/>
</p>

<p>33.<lb/>
 In fact, in Vikram Singh and Anr. v. State of Punjab and Anr.<lb/>
 (2017) 8 SCC 518, a three-Judge Bench of this Court followed the law in<lb/>
 Anvar P.V. (supra), clearly stating that where primary evidence in<lb/>
 electronic form has been produced, no certificate under Section 65B would<lb/>
 be necessary. This was so stated as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;25. The learned counsel contended that the tape-<lb/>
recorded conversation has been relied on without there<lb/>
 being any certificate under Section 65-B of the Evidence<lb/>
 Act, 1872. It was contended that audio tapes are recorded<lb/>
 on magnetic media, the same could be established<lb/>
 through a certificate under Section 65-B and in the<lb/>
 absence of the certificate, the document which constitutes<lb/>
 electronic record, cannot be deemed to be a valid<lb/>
 evidence and has to be ignored from consideration.<lb/>
 Reliance has been placed by the learned counsel on the<lb/>
 judgment of this Court in Anvar P.V. v. P.K. Basheer. The<lb/>
 conversation on the landline phone of the complainant<lb/>
 situate in a shop was recorded by the complainant. The<lb/>
 same cassette containing conversation by which ransom<lb/>
 call was made on the landline phone was handed over by<lb/>
 the complainant in original to the police. This Court in its<lb/>
 judgment dated 25-1-2010 has referred to the aforesaid<lb/>
 fact and has noted the said fact to the following effect:<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;5. The cassette on which the conversations had been<lb/>
 recorded on the landline was handed over by Ravi Verma<lb/>
 to SI Jiwan Kumar and on a replay of the tape, the<lb/>
 conversation was clearly audible and was heard by the<lb/>
 police.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>26. The tape-recorded conversation was not secondary<lb/>
 evidence which required certificate under Section 65-B,<lb/>
 since it was the original cassette by which ransom call was<lb/>
 tape-recorded, there cannot be any dispute that for<lb/>
 admission of secondary evidence of electronic record a<lb/>
 certificate as contemplated by Section 65-B is a<lb/>
 mandatory condition.&quot; 4<lb/>
</item>

<p>34.<lb/>
 Despite the law so declared in Anvar P.V. (supra), wherein this<lb/>
 Court made it clear that the special provisions of Sections 65A and 65B of<lb/>
 the Evidence Act are a complete Code in themselves when it comes to<lb/>
 admissibility of such evidence, a discordant note was soon struck in<lb/>
 Tomaso Bruno (supra). In this judgment, another three Judge Bench dealt<lb/>
 with the admissibility of evidence in a criminal case in which CCTV footage<lb/>
 was sought to be relied upon in evidence. The Court held:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;24. With the advancement of information technology,<lb/>
 scientific temper in the individual and at the institutional<lb/>
 level is to pervade the methods of investigation. With the<lb/>
 increasing impact of technology in everyday life and as a<lb/>
 result, the production of electronic evidence in cases has<lb/>
 become relevant to establish the guilt of the accused or<lb/>
 the liability of the defendant. Electronic documents stricto<lb/>
 sensu are admitted as material evidence. With the<lb/>
 amendment to the Evidence Act in 2000, Sections 65-A<lb/>
 and 65-B were introduced into Chapter V relating to<lb/>
 documentary evidence. Section 65-A provides that<lb/>
 contents of electronic records may be admitted as<lb/>
 evidence if the criteria provided in Section 65-B is<lb/>
 complied with. The computer generated electronic records<lb/>
 in evidence are admissible at a trial if proved in the<lb/>
 manner specified by Section 65-B of the Evidence Act.<lb/>
 Sub-section (1) of Section 65-B makes admissible as a<lb/>
 document, paper printout of electronic records stored in<lb/>
 optical or magnetic media produced by a computer,<lb/>
 subject to the fulfilment of the conditions specified in sub-<lb/>
section (2) of Section 65-B. Secondary evidence of<lb/>
 contents of document can also be led under Section 65 of<lb/>
 the Evidence Act. PW 13 stated that he saw the full video<lb/>
 recording of the fateful night in the CCTV camera, but he<lb/>
 has not recorded the same in the case diary as nothing<lb/>
 substantial to be adduced as evidence was present in it.<lb/>
</item>

<item>25. The production of scientific and electronic evidence in<lb/>
 court as contemplated under Section 65-B of the Evidence<lb/>
 Act is of great help to the investigating agency and also to<lb/>
 the prosecution. The relevance of electronic evidence is<lb/>
 also evident in the light of Mohd. Ajmal Amir<lb/>
 Kasab v. State of Maharashtra [(2012) 9 SCC 1] , wherein<lb/>
 production of transcripts of internet transactions helped<lb/>
 the prosecution case a great deal in proving the guilt of the<lb/>
 accused. Similarly, in State (NCT of Delhi) v. Navjot<lb/>
 Sandhu, the links between the slain terrorists and the<lb/>
 masterminds of the attack were established only through<lb/>
 phone call transcripts obtained from the mobile service<lb/>
 providers.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>35.<lb/>
 What is clear from this judgment is that the judgment of Anvar<lb/>
 P.V. (supra) was not referred to at all. In fact, the judgment in State v.<lb/>
 Navjot Sandhu (2005) 11 SCC 600 was adverted to, which was a<lb/>
 judgment specifically overruled by Anvar P.V. (supra). It may also be<lb/>
 stated that Section 65B(4) was also not at all adverted to by this judgment.<lb/>
 Hence, the declaration of law in Tomaso Bruno (supra) following Navjot<lb/>
 Sandhu (supra) that secondary evidence of the contents of a document<lb/>
 can also be led under Section 65 of the Evidence Act to make CCTV<lb/>
 footage admissible would be in the teeth of Anvar P.V., (supra) and cannot<lb/>
 be said to be a correct statement of the law. The said view is accordingly<lb/>
 overruled.<lb/>
</p>

<p>36 We now come to the decision in Shafhi Mohammad (supra).<lb/>
 In this case, by an order dated 30.01.2018 made by two learned Judges of<lb/>
 this Court, it was stated:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;21. We have been taken through certain decisions which<lb/>
 may be referred to. In Ram Singh v. Ram Singh [Ram<lb/>
 Singh v. Ram Singh, 1985 Supp SCC 611] , a three-Judge<lb/>
 Bench considered the said issue. English judgments<lb/>
 in R. v. Maqsud Ali [R. v. Maqsud Ali, (1966) 1 QB 688]<lb/>
 and R. v. Robson [R. v. Robson, (1972) 1 WLR 651] and<lb/>
 American Law as noted in American Jurisprudence 2d<lb/>
 (Vol. 29) p. 494, were cited with approval to the effect that<lb/>
 it will be wrong to deny to the law of evidence advantages<lb/>
 to be gained by new techniques and new devices,<lb/>
 provided the accuracy of the recording can be proved.<lb/>
 Such evidence should always be regarded with some<lb/>
 caution and assessed in the light of all the circumstances<lb/>
 of each case. Electronic evidence was held to be<lb/>
 admissible subject to safeguards adopted by the Court<lb/>
 about the authenticity of the same. In the case of tape-<lb/>
recording, it was observed that voice of the speaker must<lb/>
 be duly identified, accuracy of the statement was required<lb/>
 to be proved by the maker of the record, possibility of<lb/>
 tampering was required to be ruled out. Reliability of the<lb/>
 piece of evidence is certainly a matter to be determined in<lb/>
 the facts and circumstances of a fact situation. However,<lb/>
 threshold admissibility of an electronic evidence cannot be<lb/>
 ruled out on any technicality if the same was relevant.<lb/>
</item>

<item>22. In Tukaram<lb/>
 S.<lb/>
 Dighole v. Manikrao<lb/>
 Shivaji<lb/>
 Kokate [(2010) 4 SCC 329], the same principle was<lb/>
 reiterated. This Court observed that new techniques and<lb/>
 devices are the order of the day. Though such devices are<lb/>
 susceptible to tampering, no exhaustive rule could be laid<lb/>
 down by which the admission of such evidence may be<lb/>
 judged. Standard of proof of its authenticity and accuracy<lb/>
 has to be more stringent than other documentary<lb/>
 evidence.<lb/>
</item>

<item>23. In Tomaso Bruno v. State of U.P. [(2015) 7 SCC 178],<lb/>
 a three-Judge Bench observed that advancement of<lb/>
 information technology and scientific temper must pervade<lb/>
 the method of investigation. Electronic evidence was<lb/>
 relevant to establish facts. Scientific and electronic<lb/>
 evidence can be a great help to an investigating agency.<lb/>
 Reference was made to the decisions of this Court<lb/>
 in Mohd.<lb/>
 Ajmal<lb/>
 Amir<lb/>
 Kasab v. State<lb/>
 of<lb/>
 Maharashtra [(2012) 9 SCC 1] and State (NCT of<lb/>
 Delhi) v. Navjot Sandhu.<lb/>
</item>

<item>24. We may, however, also refer to the judgment of this<lb/>
 Court in Anvar P.V. v. P.K. Basheer, delivered by a three-<lb/>
Judge Bench. In the said judgment in para 24 it was<lb/>
 observed that electronic evidence by way of primary<lb/>
 evidence was covered by Section 62 of the Evidence Act<lb/>
 to which procedure of Section 65-B of the Evidence Act<lb/>
 was not admissible. However, for the secondary evidence,<lb/>
 procedure of Section 65-B of the Evidence Act was<lb/>
 required to be followed and a contrary view taken<lb/>
 in Navjot Sandhu that secondary evidence of electronic<lb/>
 record could be covered under Sections 63 and 65 of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act, was not correct. There are, however,<lb/>
 observations in para 14 to the effect that electronic record<lb/>
 can be proved only as per Section 65-B of the Evidence<lb/>
 Act.<lb/>
</item>

<item>25. Though in view of the three-Judge Bench judgments<lb/>
 in Tomaso Bruno and Ram Singh [1985 Supp SCC 611] ,<lb/>
 it can be safely held that electronic evidence is admissible<lb/>
 and provisions under Sections 65-A and 65-B of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act are by way of a clarification and are<lb/>
 procedural provisions. If the electronic evidence is<lb/>
 authentic and relevant the same can certainly be admitted<lb/>
 subject to the Court being satisfied about its authenticity<lb/>
 and procedure for its admissibility may depend on fact<lb/>
 situation such as whether the person producing such<lb/>
 evidence is in a position to furnish certificate under<lb/>
 Section 65-B(4).<lb/>
</item>

<p>26. Sections 65-A and 65-B of the Evidence Act, 1872<lb/>
 cannot be held to be a complete code on the subject.<lb/>
 In Anvar P.V., this Court in para 24 clarified that primary<lb/>
 evidence of electronic record was not covered under<lb/>
 Sections 65-A and 65-B of the Evidence Act. Primary<lb/>
 evidence is the document produced before the Court and<lb/>
 the expression &quot;document&quot; is defined in Section 3 of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act to mean any matter expressed or described<lb/>
 upon any substance by means of letters, figures or marks,<lb/>
 or by more than one of those means, intended to be used,<lb/>
 or which may be used, for the purpose of recording that<lb/>
 matter.<lb/>
</p>

<p>27. The term &quot;electronic record&quot; is defined in Section 2(1)<lb/>
 (t) of the Information Technology Act, 2000 as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;2.(1)(t) &quot;electronic record&quot; means data, record or data<lb/>
 generated, image or sound stored, received or sent in an<lb/>
 electronic form or micro film or computer generated micro<lb/>
 fiche;&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>28. The expression &quot;data&quot; is defined in Section 2(1)(o) of<lb/>
 the Information Technology Act as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;2.(1)(o) &quot;data&quot; means a representation of information,<lb/>
 knowledge, facts, concepts or instructions which are being<lb/>
 prepared or have been prepared in a formalised manner,<lb/>
 and is intended to be processed, is being processed or<lb/>
 has been processed in a computer system or computer<lb/>
 network, and may be in any form (including computer<lb/>
 printouts magnetic or optical storage media, punched<lb/>
 cards, punched tapes) or stored internally in the memory<lb/>
 of the computer;&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>29. The applicability of procedural requirement under<lb/>
 Section 65-B(4) of the Evidence Act of furnishing<lb/>
 certificate is to be applied only when such electronic<lb/>
 evidence is produced by a person who is in a position to<lb/>
 produce such certificate being in control of the said device<lb/>
 and not of the opposite party. In a case where electronic<lb/>
 evidence is produced by a party who is not in possession<lb/>
 of a device, applicability of Sections 63 and 65 of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act cannot be held to be excluded. In such case,<lb/>
 procedure under the said sections can certainly be<lb/>
 invoked. If this is not so permitted, it will be denial of<lb/>
 justice to the person who is in possession of authentic<lb/>
 evidence/witness but on account of manner of proving,<lb/>
 such document is kept out of consideration by the court in<lb/>
 the absence of certificate under Section 65-B(4) of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act, which party producing cannot possibly<lb/>
 secure. Thus, requirement of certificate under Section 65-<lb/>
B(4) is not always mandatory.<lb/>
</item>

<item>30. Accordingly, we clarify the legal position on the subject<lb/>
 on the admissibility of the electronic evidence, especially<lb/>
 by a party who is not in possession of device from which<lb/>
 the document is produced. Such party cannot be required<lb/>
 to produce certificate under Section 65-B(4) of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act. The applicability of requirement of certificate<lb/>
 being procedural can be relaxed by the court wherever<lb/>
 interest of justice so justifies.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>37.<lb/>
 It may be noted that the judgments referred to in paragraph 21<lb/>
 of Shafhi Mohammed (supra) are all judgments before the year 2000,<lb/>
 when Amendment Act 21 of 2000 first introduced Sections 65A and 65B<lb/>
 into the Evidence Act and can, therefore, be of no assistance on<lb/>
 interpreting the law as to admissibility into evidence of information<lb/>
 contained in electronic records. Likewise, the judgment cited in paragraph<lb/>
 22, namely Tukaram S. Dighole v. Manikrao Shivaji Kokate (2010) 4<lb/>
 SCC 329 is also a judgment which does not deal with Section 65B. In fact,<lb/>
 paragraph 20 of the said judgment states the issues before the Court as<lb/>
 follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;20. However, in the present case, the dispute is not<lb/>
 whether a cassette is a public document but the issues are<lb/>
 whether:<lb/>
</item>

<item>(i) the finding by the Tribunal that in the absence of any<lb/>
 evidence to show that the VHS cassette was obtained by<lb/>
 the appellant from the Election Commission, the cassette<lb/>
 placed on record by the appellant could not be treated as<lb/>
 a public document is perverse; and<lb/>
</item>

<item>(ii) a mere production of an audio cassette, assuming that<lb/>
 the same is a certified copy issued by the Election<lb/>
 Commission, is per se conclusive of the fact that what is<lb/>
 contained in the cassette is the true and correct recording<lb/>
 of the speech allegedly delivered by the respondent or his<lb/>
 agent?&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>The second issue was answered referring to judgments which did not deal<lb/>
 with Section 65B at all.<lb/>
</p>

<p>38.<lb/>
 Much succour was taken from the three Judge Bench decision<lb/>
 in Tomaso Bruno (supra) in paragraph 23, which, as has been stated<lb/>
 hereinabove, does not state the law on Section 65B correctly. Anvar P.V.<lb/>
(supra) was referred to in paragraph 24, but surprisingly, in paragraph 26,<lb/>
 the Court held that Sections 65A and 65B cannot be held to be a complete<lb/>
 Code on the subject, directly contrary to what was stated by a three Judge<lb/>
 Bench in Anvar P.V. (supra). It was then &quot;clarified&quot; that the requirement of<lb/>
 a certificate under Section 64B(4), being procedural, can be relaxed by the<lb/>
 Court wherever the interest of justice so justifies, and one circumstance in<lb/>
 which the interest of justice so justifies would be where the electronic<lb/>
 device is produced by a party who is not in possession of such device, as a<lb/>
 result of which such party would not be in a position to secure the requisite<lb/>
 certificate.<lb/>
</p>

<p>39.<lb/>
 Quite apart from the fact that the judgment in Shafhi<lb/>
 Mohammad (supra) states the law incorrectly and is in the teeth of the<lb/>
 judgment in Anvar P.V. (supra), following the judgment in Tomaso Bruno<lb/>
 (supra) -which has been held to be per incuriam hereinabove -the<lb/>
 underlying reasoning of the difficulty of producing a certificate by a party<lb/>
 who is not in possession of an electronic device is also wholly incorrect.<lb/>
</p>

<p>40.<lb/>
 As a matter of fact, Section 165 of the Evidence Act empowers<lb/>
 a Judge to order production of any document or thing in order to discover<lb/>
 or obtain proof of relevant facts. Section 165 of the Evidence Act states as<lb/>
 follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;Section 165. Judge&apos;s power to put questions or order<lb/>
 production.-The Judge may, in order to discover or to<lb/>
 obtain proper proof of relevant facts, ask any question he<lb/>
 pleases, in any form, at any time, of any witness, or of the<lb/>
 parties about any fact relevant or irrelevant; and may order<lb/>
 the production of any document or thing; and neither the<lb/>
 parties nor their agents shall be entitled to make any<lb/>
 objection to any such question or order, nor, without the<lb/>
 leave of the Court, to cross-examine any witness upon any<lb/>
 answer given in reply to any such question.<lb/></item>

 <item>
 Provided that the judgment must be based upon facts<lb/>
 declared by this Act to be relevant, and duly proved:<lb/>
</item>

<item>Provided also that this section shall not authorize any<lb/>
 Judge to compel any witness to answer any question or to<lb/>
 produce any document which such witness would be<lb/>
 entitled to refuse to answer or produce under sections 121<lb/>
 to 131, both inclusive, if the question were asked or the<lb/>
 document were called for by the adverse party; nor shall<lb/>
 the Judge ask any question which it would be improper for<lb/>
 any other person to ask under section 148 or 149; nor<lb/>
 shall he dispense with primary evidence of any document,<lb/>
 except in the cases hereinbefore excepted.<lb/>
</item>

<p>41.<lb/>
 Likewise, under Order XVI of the Civil Procedure Code, 1908<lb/>
 (&quot;CPC&quot;) which deals with &apos;Summoning and Attendance of Witnesses&apos;, the<lb/>
 Court can issue the following orders for the production of documents:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;6. Summons to produce document.-Any person may<lb/>
 be summoned to produce a document, without being<lb/>
 summoned to give evidence; and any person summoned<lb/>
 merely to produce a document shall be deemed to have<lb/>
 complied with the summons if he causes such document<lb/>
 to be produced instead of attending personally to produce<lb/>
 the same.<lb/>
</item>

<item>7. Power to require persons present in Court to give<lb/>
 evidence or produce document.-Any person present in<lb/>
 Court may be required by the Court to give evidence or to<lb/>
 produce any document then and there in his possession or<lb/>
 power.<lb/>
</item>

<item>xxx xxx xxx<lb/>
</item>

<item>10. Procedure where witness fails to comply with<lb/>
 summons.-(1) Where a person has been issued<lb/>
 summons either to attend to give evidence or to produce a<lb/>
 document, fails to attend or to produce the document in<lb/>
 compliance with such summons, the Court-(a) shall, if<lb/>
 the certificate of the serving officer has not been verified<lb/>
 by the affidavit, or if service of the summons has affected<lb/>
 by a party or his agent, or (b) may, if the certificate of the<lb/>
 serving officer has been so verified, examine on oath the<lb/>
 serving officer or the party or his agent, as the case may<lb/>
 be, who has effected service, or cause him to be so<lb/>
 examined by any Court, touching the service or non-<lb/>
service of the summons.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(2) Where the Court sees reason to believe that such<lb/>
 evidence or production is material, and that such person<lb/>
 has, without lawful excuse, failed to attend or to produce<lb/>
 the document in compliance with such summons or has<lb/>
 intentionally avoided service, it may issue a proclamation<lb/>
 requiring him to attend to give evidence or to produce the<lb/>
 document at a time and place to be named therein; and a<lb/>
 copy of such proclamation shall be affixed on the outer<lb/>
 door or other conspicuous part of the house in which he<lb/>
 ordinarily resides.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(</item>

<item>3) In lieu of or at the time of issuing such proclamation, or<lb/>
 at any time afterwards, the Court may, in its discretion,<lb/>
 issue a warrant, either with or without bail, for the arrest of<lb/>
 such person, and may make an order for the attachment<lb/>
 of his property to such amount as it thinks fit, not<lb/>
 exceeding the amount of the costs of attachment and of<lb/>
 any fine which may be imposed under rule 12:<lb/>
 Provided that no Court of Small Causes shall make an<lb/>
 order for the attachment of immovable property.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>42.<lb/>
 Similarly, in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (&quot;CrPC&quot;),<lb/>
 the Judge conducting a criminal trial is empowered to issue the following<lb/>
 orders for production of documents:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;91. Summons to produce document or other thing.-<lb/>
</item>

<item>(1) Whenever any Court or any officer in charge of a police<lb/>
 station considers that the production of any document or<lb/>
 other thing is necessary or desirable for the purposes of<lb/>
 any investigation, inquiry, trial or other proceeding under<lb/>
 this Code by or before such Court or officer, such Court<lb/>
 may issue a summons, or such officer a written order, to<lb/>
 the person in whose possession or power such document<lb/>
 or thing is believed to be, requiring him to attend and<lb/>
 produce it, or to produce it, at the time and place stated in<lb/>
 the summons or order.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(2) Any person required under this section merely to<lb/>
 produce a document or other thing shall be deemed to<lb/>
 have complied with the requisition if he causes such<lb/>
 document or thing to be produced instead of attending<lb/>
 personally to produce the same.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(3) Nothing in this section shall be deemed-(a) to affect<lb/>
 sections 123 and 124 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1<lb/>
 of 1872), or the Bankers&apos; Books Evidence Act, 1891 (13 of<lb/>
 1891), or (b) to apply to a letter, postcard, telegram or<lb/>
 other document or any parcel or thing in the custody of the<lb/>
 postal or telegraph authority.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;349. Imprisonment or committal of person refusing to<lb/>
 answer or produce document.-If any witness or person<lb/>
 called to produce a document or thing before a Criminal<lb/>
 Court refuses to answer such questions as are put to him<lb/>
 or to produce any document or thing in his possession or<lb/>
 power which the Court requires him to produce, and does<lb/>
 not, after a reasonable opportunity has been given to him<lb/>
 so to do, offer any reasonable excuse for such refusal,<lb/>
 such Court may, for reasons to be recorded in writing,<lb/>
 sentence him to simple imprisonment, or by warrant under<lb/>
 the hand of the Presiding Magistrate or Judge commit him<lb/>
 to the custody of an officer of the Court for any term not<lb/>
 exceeding seven days, unless in the meantime, such<lb/>
 person consents to be examined and to answer, or to<lb/>
 produce the document or thing and in the event of his<lb/>
 persisting in his refusal, he may be dealt with according to<lb/>
 the provisions of section 345 or section 346.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>43.<lb/>
 Thus, it is clear that the major premise of Shafhi Mohammad<lb/>
 (supra) that such certificate cannot be secured by persons who are not in<lb/>
 possession of an electronic device is wholly incorrect. An application can<lb/>
 always be made to a Judge for production of such a certificate from the<lb/>
 requisite person under Section 65B(4) in cases in which such person<lb/>
 refuses to give it.<lb/>
</p>

<p>44.<lb/>
 Resultantly, the judgment dated 03.04.2018 of a Division<lb/>
 Bench of this Court reported as (2018) 5 SCC 311, in following the law<lb/>
 incorrectly laid down in Shafhi Mohammed (supra), must also be, and is<lb/>
 hereby, overruled.<lb/>
</p>

<p>45.<lb/>
 However, a caveat must be entered here. The facts of the<lb/>
 present case show that despite all efforts made by the Respondents, both<lb/>
 through the High Court and otherwise, to get the requisite certificate under<lb/>
 Section 65B(4) of the Evidence Act from the authorities concerned, yet the<lb/>
 authorities concerned wilfully refused, on some pretext or the other, to give<lb/>
 such certificate. In a fact-circumstance where the requisite certificate has<lb/>
 been applied for from the person or the authority concerned, and the<lb/>
 person or authority either refuses to give such certificate, or does not reply<lb/>
 to such demand, the party asking for such certificate can apply to the Court<lb/>
 for its production under the provisions aforementioned of the Evidence Act,<lb/>
 CPC or CrPC. Once such application is made to the Court, and the Court<lb/>
 then orders or directs that the requisite certificate be produced by a person<lb/>
 to whom it sends a summons to produce such certificate, the party asking<lb/>
 for the certificate has done all that he can possibly do to obtain the<lb/>
 requisite certificate. Two Latin maxims become important at this stage. The<lb/>
 first is lex non cogit ad impossibilia i.e. the law does not demand the<lb/>
 impossible, and impotentia excusat legem i.e. when there is a disability<lb/>
 that makes it impossible to obey the law, the alleged disobedience of the<lb/>
 law is excused. This was well put by this Court in Re: Presidential Poll<lb/>
 (1974) 2 SCC 33 as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;14. If the completion of election before the expiration of<lb/>
 the term is not possible because of the death of the<lb/>
 prospective candidate it is apparent that the election has<lb/>
 commenced before the expiration of the term but<lb/>
 completion before the expiration of the term is rendered<lb/>
 impossible by an act beyond the control of human agency.<lb/>
 The necessity for completing the election before the<lb/>
 expiration of the term is enjoined by the Constitution in<lb/>
 public and State interest to see that the governance of the<lb/>
 country is not paralysed by non-compliance with the<lb/>
 provision that there shall be a President of India.<lb/>
</item>

<item>15. The impossibility of the completion of the election to fill<lb/>
 the vacancy in the office of the President before the<lb/>
 expiration of the term of office in the case of death of a<lb/>
 candidate as may appear from Section 7 of the 1952 Act<lb/>
 does not rob Article 62(1) of its mandatory character. The<lb/>
 maxim of law impotentia excusat legam is intimately<lb/>
 connected with another maxim of law lex non cogit ad<lb/>
 impossibilia. Impotentia excusat legam is that when there<lb/>
 is a necessary or invincible disability to perform the<lb/>
 mandatory part of the law that impotentia excuses. The<lb/>
 law does not compel one to do that which one cannot<lb/>
 possibly perform. &quot;Where the law creates a duty or charge,<lb/>
 and the party is disabled to perform it, without any default<lb/>
 in him, and has no remedy over it, there the law will in<lb/>
 general excuse him.&quot; Therefore, when it appears that the<lb/>
 performance of the formalities prescribed by a statute has<lb/>
 been rendered impossible by circumstances over which<lb/>
 the persons interested had no control, like the act of God,<lb/>
 the circumstances will be taken as a valid excuse. Where<lb/>
 the act of God prevents the compliance of the words of a<lb/>
 statute, the statutory provision is not denuded of its<lb/>
 mandatory character because of supervening impossibility<lb/>
 caused by the act of God. (See Broom&apos;s Legal<lb/>
 Maxims 10th Edn. at pp. 162-163 and Craies on Statute<lb/>
 Law 6th Edn. at p. 268).&quot;<lb/></item>
<p> 
 It is important to note that the provision in question in Re Presidential Poll<lb/>
(supra) was also mandatory, which could not be satisfied owing to an act of<lb/>
 God, in the facts of that case. These maxims have been applied by this<lb/>
 Court in different situations in other election cases -see Chandra Kishore<lb/>
 Jha v. Mahavir Prasad and Ors. (1999) 8 SCC 266 (at paragraphs 17 and<lb/>
 21); Special Reference 1 of 2002 (2002) 8 SCC 237 (at paragraphs 130<lb/>
 and 151) and Raj Kumar Yadav v. Samir Kumar Mahaseth and Ors.<lb/>
(2005) 3 SCC 601 (at paragraphs 13 and 14).<lb/></p>

<p>46.<lb/>
 These Latin maxims have also been applied in several other<lb/>
 contexts by this Court. In Cochin State Power and Light Corporation v.<lb/>
 State of Kerala (1965) 3 SCR 187, a question arose as to the exercise of<lb/>
 an option of purchasing an undertaking by the State Electricity Board under<lb/>
 Section 6(4) of the Indian Electricity Act, 1910. The provision required a<lb/>
 notice of at least 18 months before the expiry of the relevant period to be<lb/>
 given by such State Electricity Board to the State Government. Since this<lb/>
 mandatory provision was impossible of compliance, it was held that the<lb/>
 State Electricity Board was excused from giving such notice, as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;Sub-section (1) of Section 6 expressly vests in the State<lb/>
 Electricity Board the option of purchase on the expiry of<lb/>
 the relevant period specified in the license. But the State<lb/>
 Government claims that under sub-section (2) of Section 6<lb/>
 it is now vested with the option. Now, under sub-section<lb/>
 (2) of Section 6, the State Government would be vested<lb/>
 with the option only &quot;where a State Electricity Board has<lb/>
 not been constituted, or if constituted, does not elect to<lb/>
 purchase the undertaking&quot;. It is common case that the<lb/>
 State Electricity Board was duly constituted. But the State<lb/>
 Government claims that the State Electricity Board did not<lb/>
 elect to purchase the undertaking. For this purpose, the<lb/>
 State Government relies upon the deeming provisions of<lb/>
 sub-section (4) of Section 6, and contends that as the<lb/>
 Board did not send to the State Government any<lb/>
 intimation in writing of its intention to exercise the option<lb/>
 as required by the sub-section, the Board must be<lb/>
 deemed to have elected not to purchase the undertaking.<lb/>
 Now, the effect of sub-section (4) read with sub-section (2)<lb/>
 of Section 6 is that on failure of the Board to give the<lb/>
 notice prescribed by sub-section (4), the option vested in<lb/>
 the Board under sub-section (1) of Section 6 was liable to<lb/>
 be divested. Sub-section (4) of Section 6 imposed upon<lb/>
 the Board the duty of giving after the coming into force of<lb/>
 Section 6 a notice in writing of its intention to exercise the<lb/>
 option at least 18 months before the expiry of the relevant<lb/>
 period. Section 6 came into force on September 5, 1959,<lb/>
 and the relevant period expired on December 3, 1960. In<lb/>
 the circumstances, the giving of the requisite notice of 18<lb/>
 months in respect of the option of purchase on the expiry<lb/>
 of December 2, 1960, was impossible from the very<lb/>
 commencement of Section 6. The performance of this<lb/>
 impossible duty must be excused in accordance with the<lb/>
 maxim, lex non cogitia ad impossibilia (the law does not<lb/>
 compel the doing of impossibilities), and sub-section (4) of<lb/>
 Section 6 must be construed as not being applicable to a<lb/>
 case where compliance with it is impossible. We must<lb/>
 therefore, hold that the State Electricity Board was not<lb/>
 required to give the notice under sub-section (4) of Section<lb/>
 6 in respect of its option of purchase on the expiry of 25<lb/>
 years. It must follow that the Board cannot be deemed to<lb/>
 have elected not to purchase the undertaking under sub-<lb/>
section (4) of Section 6. By the notice served upon the<lb/>
 appellant, the Board duly elected to purchase the<lb/>
 undertaking on the expiry of 25 years. Consequently, the<lb/>
 State Government never became vested with the option of<lb/>
 purchasing the undertaking under sub-section (2) of<lb/>
 Section 6. The State Government must, therefore, be<lb/>
 restrained from taking further action under its notice, Ex.<lb/>
 G, dated November 20, 1959.&quot; 5<lb/>
</item>

<p>47.<lb/>
 In Raj Kumar Dubey v. Tarapada Dey and Ors. (1987) 4<lb/>
 SCC 398, the maxim non cogit ad impossibilia was applied in the context<lb/>
 of the applicability of a mandatory provision of the Registration Act, 1908,<lb/>
 as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;6. We have to bear in mind two maxims of equity which<lb/>
 are well settled, namely, actus curiae neminem gravabit -<lb/>
An act of the Court shall prejudice no man. In<lb/>
 Broom&apos;s Legal Maxims, 10th Edn., 1939 at page 73 this<lb/>
 maxim is explained that this maxim was founded upon<lb/>
 justice and good sense; and afforded a safe and certain<lb/>
 guide for the administration of the law. The above maxim<lb/>
 should, however, be applied with caution. The other<lb/>
 maxim is lex non cogit ad impossibilia (Broom&apos;s Legal<lb/>
 Maxims -page 162) -The law does not compel a man<lb/>
 to do that which he cannot possibly perform. The law itself<lb/>
 and the administration of it, said Sir W. Scott, with<lb/>
 reference to an alleged infraction of the revenue laws,<lb/>
 must yield to that to which everything must bend, to<lb/>
 necessity; the law, in its most positive and peremptory<lb/>
 impossibilities, and the administration of laws must adopt<lb/>
 that general exception in the consideration of all particular<lb/>
 cases.<lb/>
</item>

<item>7. In this case indisputably during the period from 26-7-<lb/>
1978 to December 1982 there was subsisting injunction<lb/>
 preventing the arbitrators from taking any steps.<lb/>
 Furthermore, as noted before the award was in the<lb/>
 custody of the court, that is to say, 28-1-1978 till the return<lb/>
 of the award to the arbitrators on 24-11-1983, arbitrators<lb/>
 or the parties could not have presented the award for its<lb/>
 registration during that time. The award as we have noted<lb/>
 before was made on 28-11-1977 and before the expiry of<lb/>
 the four months from 28-11-1977, the award was filed in<lb/>
 the court pursuant to the order of the court. It was argued<lb/>
 that the order made by the court directing the arbitrators to<lb/>
 keep the award in the custody of the court was wrong and<lb/>
 without jurisdiction, but no arbitrator could be compelled to<lb/>
 disobey the order of the court and if in compliance or<lb/>
 obedience with court of doubtful jurisdiction, he could not<lb/>
 take back the award from the custody of the court to take<lb/>
 any further steps for its registration then it cannot be said<lb/>
 that he has failed to get the award registered as the law<lb/>
 required. The aforesaid two legal maxims -the law does<lb/>
 not compel a man to do that which he cannot possibly<lb/>
 perform and an act of the court shall prejudice no<lb/>
 man would, apply with full vigour in the facts of this case<lb/>
 and if that is the position then the award as we have noted<lb/>
 before was presented before the Sub-Registrar, Arambagh<lb/>
 on 25-11-1983 the very next one day of getting<lb/>
 possession of the award from the court. The Sub-Registrar<lb/>
 pursuant to the order of the High Court on 24-6-1985<lb/>
 found that the award was presented within time as the<lb/>
 period during which the judicial proceedings were pending<lb/>
 that is to say, from 28-1-1978 to 24-11-1983 should be<lb/>
 excluded in view of the principle laid down in Section 15 of<lb/>
 the Limitation Act, 1963. The High Court, therefore, in our<lb/>
 opinion, was wrong in holding that the only period which<lb/>
 should be excluded was from 26-7-1978 till 20-12-1982.<lb/>
 We are unable to accept this position. 26-7-1978 was the<lb/>
 date of the order of the learned Munsif directing<lb/>
 maintenance of status quo and 20-12-1982 was the date<lb/>
 when the interim injunction was vacated, but still the<lb/>
 award was in the custody of the court and there is ample<lb/>
 evidence as it would appear from the narration of events<lb/>
 hereinbefore made that the arbitrators had tried to obtain<lb/>
 the custody of the award which the court declined to give<lb/>
 to them.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>48.<lb/>
 These maxims have also been applied to tenancy legislation -<lb/>
see M/s B.P. Khemka Pvt. Ltd. v. Birendra Kumar Bhowmick and Anr.<lb/>
 (1987) 2 SCC 401 (at paragraph 12), and have also been applied to relieve<lb/>
 authorities of fulfilling their obligation to allot plots when such plots have<lb/>
 been found to be un-allottable, owing to the contravention of Central<lb/>
 statutes -see Hira Tikoo v. U.T., Chandigarh and Ors. (2004) 6 SCC 765<lb/>
 (at paragraphs 23 and 24).<lb/>
</p>

<p>49.<lb/>
 On an application of the aforesaid maxims to the present case,<lb/>
 it is clear that though Section 65B(4) is mandatory, yet, on the facts of this<lb/>
 case, the Respondents, having done everything possible to obtain the<lb/>
 necessary certificate, which was to be given by a third-party over whom the<lb/>
 Respondents had no control, must be relieved of the mandatory obligation<lb/>
 contained in the said sub-section.<lb/>
</p>

<p>50.<lb/>We may hasten to add that Section 65B does not speak of the<lb/>
 stage at which such certificate must be furnished to the Court. In Anvar<lb/>
 P.V. (supra), this Court did observe that such certificate must accompany<lb/>
 the electronic record when the same is produced in evidence. We may only<lb/>
 add that this is so in cases where such certificate could be procured by the<lb/>
 person seeking to rely upon an electronic record. However, in cases where<lb/>
 either a defective certificate is given, or in cases where such certificate has<lb/>
 been demanded and is not given by the concerned person, the Judge<lb/>
 conducting the trial must summon the person/persons referred to in<lb/>
 Section 65B(4) of the Evidence Act, and require that such certificate be<lb/>
 given by such person/persons. This, the trial Judge ought to do when the<lb/>
 electronic record is produced in evidence before him without the requisite<lb/>
 certificate in the circumstances aforementioned. This is, of course, subject<lb/>
 to discretion being exercised in civil cases in accordance with law, and in<lb/>
 accordance with the requirements of justice on the facts of each case.<lb/>
 When it comes to criminal trials, it is important to keep in mind the general<lb/>
 principle that the accused must be supplied all documents that the<lb/>
 prosecution seeks to rely upon before commencement of the trial, under<lb/>
 the relevant sections of the CrPC.<lb/>
</p>

<p>51.<lb/>
 In a recent judgment, a Division Bench of this Court in State of<lb/>
 Karnataka v. M.R. Hiremath (2019) 7 SCC 515, after referring to Anvar<lb/>
 P.V. (supra) held:<lb/>
</p>

<p>&quot;16. The same view has been reiterated by a two-<lb/>
Judge Bench of this Court in Union of India v. Ravindra<lb/>
 V. Desai [(2018) 16 SCC 273]. The Court emphasised<lb/>
 that non-production of a certificate under Section 65-B<lb/>
 on an earlier occasion is a curable defect. The Court<lb/>
 relied upon the earlier decision in Sonu v. State of<lb/>
 Haryana [(2017) 8 SCC 570], in which it was held:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;32. … The crucial test, as affirmed by this Court,<lb/>
 is whether the defect could have been cured at the<lb/>
 stage of marking the document. Applying this test to<lb/>
 the present case, if an objection was taken to the<lb/>
 CDRs being marked without a certificate, the court<lb/>
 could have given the prosecution an opportunity to<lb/>
 rectify the deficiency.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>17. Having regard to the above principle of law, the<lb/>
 High Court erred in coming to the conclusion that the<lb/>
 failure to produce a certificate under Section 65-B(4) of<lb/>
 the Evidence Act at the stage when the charge-sheet<lb/>
 was filed was fatal to the prosecution. The need for<lb/>
 production of such a certificate would arise when the<lb/>
 electronic record is sought to be produced in evidence<lb/>
 at the trial. It is at that stage that the necessity of the<lb/>
 production of the certificate would arise.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>52.<lb/>
 It is pertinent to recollect that the stage of admitting<lb/>
 documentary evidence in a criminal trial is the filing of the charge-sheet.<lb/>
 When a criminal court summons the accused to stand trial, copies of all<lb/>
 documents which are entered in the charge-sheet/final report have to be<lb/>
 given to the accused. Section 207 of the CrPC, which reads as follows, is<lb/>
 mandatory 6 . Therefore, the electronic evidence, i.e. the computer output,<lb/>
 has to be furnished at the latest before the trial begins. The reason is not<lb/>
 far to seek; this gives the accused a fair chance to prepare and defend the<lb/>
 charges levelled against him during the trial. The general principle in<lb/>
 criminal proceedings therefore, is to supply to the accused all documents<lb/>
 that the prosecution seeks to rely upon before the commencement of the<lb/>
 trial. The requirement of such full disclosure is an extremely valuable right<lb/>
 and an essential feature of the right to a fair trial as it enables the accused<lb/>
 to prepare for the trial before its commencement.<lb/>
</p>

<item>6 &quot;Section 207. Supply to the accused of copy of police report and other documents.-In<lb/>
 any case where the proceeding has been instituted on a police report, the Magistrate shall<lb/>
 without delay furnish to the accused, free of costs, a copy of each of the following:-<lb/>
</item>

<item>(i)<lb/>
 the police report;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(ii)<lb/>
 the first information report recorded under section 154;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(iii)<lb/>
 the statements recorded under sub-section (3) of section 161 of all<lb/>
 persons whom the prosecution proposes to examine as its witnesses, excluding<lb/>
 therefrom any part in regard to which a request for such exclusion has been made by<lb/>
 the police officer under sub-section (6) of section 173;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(iv)<lb/>
 the confessions and statements, if any, recorded under section 164;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(v)<lb/>
 any other document or relevant extract thereof forwarded to the<lb/>
 Magistrate with the police report under sub-section (5) of section 173:<lb/>
 Provided that the Magistrate may, after perusing any such part of a statement as is referred to<lb/>
 in clause (iii) and considering the reasons given by the police officer for the request, direct that<lb/>
 a copy of that part of the statement or of such portion thereof as the Magistrate thinks proper,<lb/>
 shall be furnished to the accused:<lb/>
 Provided further that if the Magistrate is satisfied that any document referred to in clause (v) is<lb/>
 voluminous, he shall, instead of furnishing the accused with a copy thereof, direct that he will<lb/>
 only be allowed to inspect it either personally or through pleader in Court.&quot;<lb/>
</item>



<p>53.<lb/>In a criminal trial, it is assumed that the investigation is<lb/>
 completed and the prosecution has, as such, concretised its case against<lb/>
 an accused before commencement of the trial. It is further settled law that<lb/>
 the prosecution ought not to be allowed to fill up any lacunae during a trial.<lb/>
 As recognised by this Court in Central Bureau of Investigation v. R.S.<lb/>
 Pai (2002) 5 SCC 82, the only exception to this general rule is if the<lb/>
 prosecution had &apos;mistakenly&apos; not filed a document, the said document can<lb/>
 be allowed to be placed on record. The Court held as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;7. From the aforesaid sub-sections, it is apparent that<lb/>
 normally, the investigating officer is required to produce<lb/>
 all the relevant documents at the time of submitting the<lb/>
 charge-sheet. At the same time, as there is no specific<lb/>
 prohibition, it cannot be held that the additional<lb/>
 documents cannot be produced subsequently. If some<lb/>
 mistake is committed in not producing the relevant<lb/>
 documents at the time of submitting the report or the<lb/>
 charge-sheet, it is always open to the investigating<lb/>
 officer to produce the same with the permission of the<lb/>
 court.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>54.<lb/>
 Therefore, in terms of general procedure, the prosecution is<lb/>
 obligated to supply all documents upon which reliance may be placed to an<lb/>
 accused before commencement of the trial. Thus, the exercise of power by<lb/>
 the courts in criminal trials in permitting evidence to be filed at a later stage<lb/>
 should not result in serious or irreversible prejudice to the accused. A<lb/>
 balancing exercise in respect of the rights of parties has to be carried out<lb/>
 by the court, in examining any application by the prosecution under<lb/>
 Sections 91 or 311 of the CrPC or Section 165 of the Evidence Act.<lb/>
 Depending on the facts of each case, and the Court exercising discretion<lb/>
 after seeing that the accused is not prejudiced by want of a fair trial, the<lb/>
 Court may in appropriate cases allow the prosecution to produce such<lb/>
 certificate at a later point in time. If it is the accused who desires to<lb/>
 produce the requisite certificate as part of his defence, this again will<lb/>
 depend upon the justice of the case -discretion to be exercised by the<lb/>
 Court in accordance with law.<lb/>
</p>

<p>55.<lb/>
 The High Court of Rajasthan in Paras Jain v. State of<lb/>
 Rajasthan 2015 SCC OnLine Raj 8331, decided a preliminary objection<lb/>
 that was raised on the applicability of Section 65B to the facts of the case.<lb/>
 The preliminary objection raised was framed as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;3. (i) Whether transcriptions of conversations and for that<lb/>
 matter CDs of the same filed alongwith the charge-sheet<lb/>
 are not admissible in evidence even at this stage of the<lb/>
 proceedings as certificate as required u/Sec. 65-B of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act was not obtained at the time of procurement<lb/>
 of said CDs from the concerned service provider and it<lb/>
 was not produced alongwith charge-sheet in the<lb/>
 prescribed form and such certificate cannot be filed<lb/>
 subsequently.&quot;<lb/></item>
<p> 
 After referring to Anvar P.V. (supra), the High Court held:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;15. Although, it has been observed by Hon&apos;ble Supreme<lb/>
 Court that the requisite certificate must accompany the<lb/>
 electronic record pertaining to which a statement is sought<lb/>
 to be given in evidence when the same is produced in<lb/>
 evidence, but in my view it does not mean that it must be<lb/>
 produced alongwith the charge-sheet and if it is not<lb/>
 produced alongwith the charge-sheet, doors of the Court<lb/>
 are completely shut and it cannot be produced<lb/>
 subsequently in any circumstance. Section 65-B of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act deals with admissibility of secondary<lb/>
 evidence in the form of electronic record and the<lb/>
 procedure to be followed and the requirements be fulfilled<lb/>
 before such an evidence can be held to be admissible in<lb/>
 evidence and not with the stage at which such a certificate<lb/>
 is to be produced before the Court. One of the principal<lb/>
 issues arising for consideration in the above case before<lb/>
 Hon&apos;ble Court was the nature and manner of admission of<lb/>
 electronic records.<lb/>
</item>

<item>16. From the facts of the above case it is revealed that the<lb/>
 election of the respondent to the legislative assembly of<lb/>
 the State of Kerala was challenged by the appellant-Shri<lb/>
 Anwar P.V. by way of an election petition before the High<lb/>
 Court of Kerala and it was dismissed vide order dated<lb/>
 16.11.2011 by the High Court and that order was<lb/>
 challenged by the appellant before Hon&apos;ble Supreme<lb/>
 Court. It appears that the election was challenged on the<lb/>
 ground of corrupt practices committed by the respondent<lb/>
 and in support thereof some CDs were produced<lb/>
 alongwith the election petition, but even during the course<lb/>
 of trial certificate as required under Section 65-B of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act was not produced and the question of<lb/>
 admissibility of the CDs as secondary evidence in the form<lb/>
 of electronic record in absence of requisite certificate was<lb/>
 considered and it was held that such electronic record is<lb/>
 not admissible in evidence in absence of the certificate. It<lb/>
 is clear from the facts of the case that the question of<lb/>
 stage at which such electronic record is to be produced<lb/>
 was not before the Hon&apos;ble Court.<lb/>
</item>

<item>17. It is to be noted that it has been clarified by Hon&apos;ble<lb/>
 Court that observations made by it are in respect of<lb/>
 secondary evidence of electronic record with reference to<lb/>
 Sections 59, 65-A and 65-B of the Evidence Act and if an<lb/>
 electronic record as such is used as primary evidence<lb/>
 under Section 62 of the Evidence Act, the same is<lb/>
 admissible in evidence without compliance with the<lb/>
 conditions in Section 65-B of the Evidence Act.<lb/>
</item>

<item>18. To consider the issue raised on behalf of the<lb/>
 petitioners in a proper manner, I pose a question to me<lb/>
 whether an evidence and more particularly evidence in the<lb/>
 form of a document not produced alongwith the charge-<lb/>
sheet cannot be produced subsequently in any<lb/>
 circumstances. My answer to the question is in negative<lb/>
 and in my opinion such evidence can be produced<lb/>
 subsequently also as it is well settled legal position that<lb/>
 the goal of a criminal trial is to discover the truth and to<lb/>
 achieve that goal, the best possible evidence is to be<lb/>
 brought on record.<lb/>
</item>

<item>19. Relevant portion of sub-sec. (1) of Sec. 91 Cr.P.C.<lb/>
 provides that whenever any Court considers that the<lb/>
 production of any document is necessary or desirable for<lb/>
 the purposes of any trial under the Code by or before such<lb/>
 Court, such Court may issue a summons to the person in<lb/>
 whose possession or power such document is believed to<lb/>
 be, requiring him to attend and produce it or to produce it,<lb/>
 at the time and place stated in the summons. Thus, a wide<lb/>
 discretion has been conferred on the Court enabling it<lb/>
 during the course of trial to issue summons to a person in<lb/>
 whose possession or power a document is believed to be<lb/>
 requiring him to produce before it, if the Court considers<lb/>
 that the production of such document is necessary or<lb/>
 desirable for the purposes of such trial. Such power can<lb/>
 be exercised by the Court at any stage of the proceedings<lb/>
 before judgment is delivered and the Court must exercise<lb/>
 the power if the production of such document is necessary<lb/>
 or desirable for the proper decision in the case. It cannot<lb/>
 be disputed that such summons can also be issued to the<lb/>
 complainant/informer/victim of the case on whose instance<lb/>
 the FIR was registered. In my considered view when<lb/>
 under this provision Court has been empowered to issue<lb/>
 summons for the producment of document, there can be<lb/>
 no bar for the Court to permit a document to be taken on<lb/>
 record if it is already before it and the Court finds that it is<lb/>
 necessary for the proper disposal of the case irrespective<lb/>
 of the fact that it was not filed along with the charge-sheet.<lb/>
 I am of the further view that it is the duty of the Court to<lb/>
 take all steps necessary for the production of such a<lb/>
 document before it.<lb/>
</item>

<item>20. As per Sec. 311 Cr.P.C., any Court may, at any stage<lb/>
 of any trial under the Code, summon any person as a<lb/>
 witness, or examine any person in attendance, though not<lb/>
 summoned as a witness, or recall or re-examine any<lb/>
 person already examined; and the Court shall summon<lb/>
 and examine or recall and re-examine any such person if<lb/>
 his evidence appears to it to be essential to the just<lb/>
 decision of the case. Under this provision also wide<lb/>
 discretion has been conferred upon the Court to exercise<lb/>
 its power and paramount consideration is just decision of<lb/>
 the case. In my opinion under this provision it is<lb/>
 permissible for the Court even to order production of a<lb/>
 document before it if it is essential for the just decision of<lb/>
 the case.<lb/>
</item>

<p>21. As per Section 173(8) Cr.P.C. carrying out a further<lb/>
 investigation and collection of additional evidence even<lb/>
 after filing of charge-sheet is a statutory right of the police<lb/>
 and for that prior permission of the Magistrate is not<lb/>
 required. If during the course of such further investigation<lb/>
 additional evidence, either oral or documentary, is<lb/>
 collected by the Police, the same can be produced before<lb/>
 the Court in the form of supplementary charge-sheet. The<lb/>
 prime consideration for further investigation and collection<lb/>
 of additional evidence is to arrive at the truth and to do<lb/>
 real and substantial justice. The material collected during<lb/>
 further investigation cannot be rejected only because it<lb/>
 has been filed at the stage of the trial.<lb/>
</p>

<p>22. As per Section 231 Cr.P.C., the prosecution is entitled<lb/>
 to produce any person as a witness even though such<lb/>
 person is not named in the charge-sheet.<lb/>
</p>

<item>23. When legal position is that additional evidence, oral or<lb/>
 documentary, can be produced during the course of trial if<lb/>
 in the opinion of the Court production of it is essential for<lb/>
 the proper disposal of the case, how it can be held that the<lb/>
 certificate as required under Section 65-B of the Evidence<lb/>
 Act cannot be produced subsequently in any<lb/>
 circumstances if the same was not procured alongwith the<lb/>
 electronic record and not produced in the Court with the<lb/>
 charge-sheet. In my opinion it is only an irregularity not<lb/>
 going to the root of the matter and is curable. It is also<lb/>
 pertinent to note that certificate was produced alongwith<lb/>
 the charge-sheet but it was not in a proper form but during<lb/>
 the course of hearing of these petitioners, it has been<lb/>
 produced on the prescribed form.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>56.<lb/>
 In Kundan Singh (supra), a Division Bench of the Delhi<lb/>
 High Court held:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;50. Anwar P.V. (supra) partly overruled the earlier<lb/>
 decision of the Supreme Court on the procedure to prove<lb/>
 electronic record(s) in Navjot Sandhu (supra), holding that<lb/>
 Section 65B is a specific provision relating to the<lb/>
 admissibility of electronic record(s) and, therefore,<lb/>
 production of a certificate under Section 65B(4) is<lb/>
 mandatory. Anwar P.V. (supra) does not state or hold that<lb/>
 the said certificate cannot be produced in exercise of<lb/>
 powers of the trial court under Section 311 Cr.P.C or, at<lb/>
 the appellate stage under Section 391 Cr.P.C. Evidence<lb/>
 Act is a procedural law and in view of the pronouncement<lb/>
 in Anwar<lb/>
 P.V. (supra)<lb/>
 partly<lb/>
 overruling Navjot<lb/>
 Sandhu (supra), the prosecution may be entitled to invoke<lb/>
 the aforementioned provisions, when justified and<lb/>
 required. Of course, it is open to the court/presiding officer<lb/>
 at that time to ascertain and verify whether the responsible<lb/>
 officer could issue the said certificate and meet the<lb/>
 requirements of Section 65B.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>57.<lb/>
 Subject to the caveat laid down in paragraphs 50 and 54<lb/>
 above, the law laid down by these two High Courts has our concurrence.<lb/>
 So long as the hearing in a trial is not yet over, the requisite certificate can<lb/>
 be directed to be produced by the learned Judge at any stage, so that<lb/>
 information contained in electronic record form can then be admitted, and<lb/>
 relied upon in evidence.<lb/>
</p>

<p>58.<lb/>
 It may also be seen that the person who gives this certificate<lb/>
 can be anyone out of several persons who occupy a &apos;responsible official<lb/>
 position&apos; in relation to the operation of the relevant device, as also the<lb/>
 person who may otherwise be in the &apos;management of relevant activities&apos;<lb/>
 spoken of in Sub-section (4) of Section 65B. Considering that such<lb/>
 certificate may also be given long after the electronic record has actually<lb/>
 been produced by the computer, Section 65B(4) makes it clear that it is<lb/>
 sufficient that such person gives the requisite certificate to the &quot;best of his<lb/>
 knowledge and belief&quot; (Obviously, the word &quot;and&quot; between knowledge and<lb/>
 belief in Section 65B(4) must be read as &quot;or&quot;, as a person cannot testify to<lb/>
 the best of his knowledge and belief at the same time).<lb/>
</p>

<p>59.<lb/>
 We may reiterate, therefore, that the certificate required under<lb/>
 Section 65B(4) is a condition precedent to the admissibility of evidence by<lb/>
 way of electronic record, as correctly held in Anvar P.V. (supra), and<lb/>
 incorrectly &quot;clarified&quot; in Shafhi Mohammed (supra). Oral evidence in the<lb/>
 place of such certificate cannot possibly suffice as Section 65B(4) is a<lb/>
 mandatory requirement of the law. Indeed, the hallowed principle in Taylor<lb/>
 v. Taylor (1876) 1 Ch.D 426, which has been followed in a number of the<lb/>
 judgments of this Court, can also be applied. Section 65B(4) of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act clearly states that secondary evidence is admissible only if<lb/>
 lead in the manner stated and not otherwise. To hold otherwise would<lb/>
 render Section 65B(4) otiose.<lb/>
</p>

<p>60.<lb/>
 In view of the above, the decision of the Madras High Court in<lb/>
 K. Ramajyam (supra), which states that evidence aliunde can be given<lb/>
 through a person who was in-charge of a computer device in the place of<lb/>
 the requisite certificate under Section 65B(4) of the Evidence Act is also an<lb/>
 incorrect statement of the law and is, accordingly, overruled.<lb/>
</p>

<p>61.<lb/>
 While on the subject, it is relevant to note that the Department<lb/>
 of Telecommunication&apos;s license conditions [i.e. under the &apos;License for<lb/>
 Provision of Unified Access Services&apos; framed in 2007, as also the<lb/>
 subsequent &apos;License Agreement for Unified License&apos; and the &apos;License<lb/>
 Agreement for provision of internet service&apos;] generally oblige internet<lb/>
 service providers and providers of mobile telephony to preserve and<lb/>
 maintain electronic call records and records of logs of internet users for a<lb/>
 limited duration of one year 7 . Therefore, if the police or other individuals<lb/>
 (interested, or party to any form of litigation) fail to secure those records -<lb/>
or secure the records but fail to secure the certificate -within that period,<lb/>
 the production of a post-dated certificate (i.e. one issued after<lb/>
 commencement of the trial) would in all probability render the data<lb/>
 unverifiable. This places the accused in a perilous position, as, in the event<lb/>
the accused wishes to challenge the genuineness of this certificate by<lb/>
 seeking the opinion of the Examiner of Electronic Evidence under Section<lb/>
 45A of the Evidence Act, the electronic record (i.e. the data as to call logs<lb/>
 in the computer of the service provider) may be missing.<lb/>
</p>

<p>62.<lb/>
 To obviate this, general directions are issued to cellular<lb/>
 companies and internet service providers to maintain CDRs and other<lb/>
 relevant records for the concerned period (in tune with Section 39 of the<lb/>
 Evidence Act) in a segregated and secure manner if a particular CDR or<lb/>
 other record is seized during investigation in the said period. Concerned<lb/>
 parties can then summon such records at the stage of defence evidence,<lb/>
 or in the event such data is required to cross-examine a particular witness.<lb/>
 This direction shall be applied, in criminal trials, till appropriate directions<lb/>
 are issued under relevant terms of the applicable licenses, or under<lb/>
 Section 67C of the Information Technology Act, which reads as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;67C. Preservation and retention of information by<lb/>
 intermediaries.-(1) Intermediary shall preserve and<lb/>
 retain such information as may be specified for such<lb/>
 duration and in such manner and format as the Central<lb/>
 Government may prescribe.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(2) any intermediary who intentionally or knowingly<lb/>
 contravenes the provisions of sub-section (1) shall be<lb/>
 punished with an imprisonment for a term which may<lb/>
 extend to three years and also be liable to fine.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>63.<lb/>
 It is also useful, in this context, to recollect that on 23 April<lb/>
 2016, the conference of the Chief Justices of the High Courts, chaired by<lb/>
 the Chief Justice of India, resolved to create a uniform platform and<lb/>
 guidelines governing the reception of electronic evidence. The Chief<lb/>
 Justices of Punjab and Haryana and Delhi were required to constitute a<lb/>
 committee to &quot;frame Draft Rules to serve as model for adoption by High<lb/>
 Courts&quot;. A five-Judge Committee was accordingly constituted on 28 July,<lb/>
 2018 8 . After extensive deliberations, and meetings with several police,<lb/>
 investigative and other agencies, the Committee finalised its report in<lb/>
 November 2018. The report suggested comprehensive guidelines, and<lb/>
 recommended their adoption for use in courts, across several categories of<lb/>
 proceedings. The report also contained Draft Rules for the Reception,<lb/>
 Retrieval, Authentication and Preservation of Electronic Records. In the<lb/>
 opinion of the Court, these Draft Rules should be examined by the<lb/>
 concerned authorities, with the object of giving them statutory force, to<lb/>
 guide courts in regard to preservation and retrieval of electronic evidence.<lb/>
</p>

<p>64.<lb/>
 We turn now to the facts of the case before us. In the present<lb/>
 case, by the impugned judgment dated 24.11.2017, Election Petition<lb/>
 respectively, the election of the RC being declared to be void under<lb/>
 Section 100 of the Representation of the People Act, 1951, inter alia, on<lb/>
 the ground that as nomination papers at serial numbers 43 and 44 were<lb/>
 not presented by the RC before 3.00 p.m. on 27.09.2014, such nomination<lb/>
 papers were improperly accepted.<lb/>
</p>

<p>65.<lb/>
 However, by an order dated 08.12.2017, this Court admitted<lb/>
 the Election Appeal of the Appellant, and stayed the impugned judgment<lb/>
 and order.<lb/>
</p>

<p>66.<lb/>
 We have heard this matter after the five year Legislative<lb/>
 Assembly term is over in November 2019. This being the case, ordinarily, it<lb/>
 would be unnecessary to decide on the merits of the case before us, as the<lb/>
 term of the Legislative Assembly is over. However, having read the<lb/>
 impugned judgment, it is clear that the learned Single Judge was<lb/>
 anguished by the fact that the Election Commission authorities behaved in<lb/>
 a partisan manner by openly favouring the Appellant. Despite the fact that<lb/>
 the reason given of &quot;substantial compliance&quot; with Section 65B(4) in the<lb/>
 absence of the requisite certificate being incorrect in law, yet, considering<lb/>
 that the Respondent had done everything in his power to obtain the<lb/>
 requisite certificate from the appropriate authorities, including directions<lb/>
 from the Court to produce the requisite certificate, no such certificate was<lb/>
 forthcoming. The horse was directed to be taken to the water to drink -but<lb/>
 it refused to drink, leading to the consequence pointed out in paragraph 49<lb/>
 of this judgment (supra).<lb/>
</p>

<p>67.<lb/>
 Even otherwise, apart from evidence contained in electronic<lb/>
 form, the High court arrived at the following conclusion:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;48. The evidence in cross examination of Smt. Mutha<lb/>
 shows that when Labade was sent to the passage for<lb/>
 collecting nomination forms, she continued to accept the<lb/>
 nomination forms directly from intending candidates and<lb/>
 their proposers in her office. Her evidence shows that on<lb/>
 27.9.2014 the last nomination form which was directly<lb/>
 presented to her was form No. 38 of Anand Mhaske. The<lb/>
 time of receipt of this form was mentioned in the register of<lb/>
 nomination forms as 2.55 p.m. In respect of subsequent<lb/>
 nomination forms from Sr. Nos. 39 to 64, the time of<lb/>
 acceptance is mentioned as 3.00 p.m. Smt. Mutha admits<lb/>
 that the candidates of nomination form Nos. 39 to 64 (form<lb/>
 No. 64 was the last form filed) were not present before her<lb/>
 physically at 3.00 p.m. At the cost of repetition, it needs to<lb/>
 be mentioned here that form numbers of RC are 43 and<lb/>
 44. The oral evidence and the record like register of<lb/>
 nomination forms does not show that form Nos. 43 and 44<lb/>
 were presented to RO at 2.20 p.m. of 27.9.2014. As per<lb/>
 the evidence of Smt. Mutha and the record, one Arvind<lb/>
 Chavan, a candidate having form Nos. 33, 34 and 35 was<lb/>
 present before her between 2.15 p.m. and 2.30 p.m. In<lb/>
 nomination form register, there is no entry showing that<lb/>
 any nomination form was received at 2.20 p.m. Form Nos.<lb/>
 36 and 37 of Sunil Khare were entered in the register at<lb/>
 2.40 p.m. Thus, according to Smt. Mutha, form No. 38,<lb/>
 which was accepted by her directly from the candidate<lb/>
 was tendered to her at 2.55 p.m. of 27.9.2014 and after<lb/>
 that she had done preliminary examination of form No. 38<lb/>
 and check list was given by her to that candidate. Thus, it<lb/>
 is not possible that form Nos. 43 and 44 were directly<lb/>
 handed over to Smt. Mutha by RC at 2.20 p.m. or even at<lb/>
 3.00 p.m. of 27.9.2014.<lb/>
</p>

<p>50. Smt. Mutha (PW 2) did not show the time as 2.20 p.m.<lb/>
 of handing over the check list to RC and she showed the<lb/>
 time as 3.00 p.m., but this time was shown in respect of all<lb/>
 forms starting from Sr. Nos. 39 to 64. Thus, substantive<lb/>
 evidence of Smt. Mutha and the aforesaid record falsifies<lb/>
 the contention of the RC made in the pleading that he had<lb/>
 handed over the nomination forms (form Nos. 43 and 44)<lb/>
 directly to RO prior to 3.00 p.m., at 2.20 p.m.&quot;<lb/>
</p>

<p>68.<lb/>
 Thus, it is clear that apart from the evidence in the form<lb/>
 of electronic record, other evidence was also relied upon to arrive at the<lb/>
 same conclusion. The High Court&apos;s judgment therefore cannot be faulted.<lb/>
</p>

<p>69.<lb/>
 Shri Adsure, however, attacked the impugned judgment when it<lb/>
 held that the improper acceptance of the nomination form of the RC<lb/>
 himself being involved in the matter, no further pleadings and particulars on<lb/>
 whether the election is &quot;materially affected&quot; were required, as it can be<lb/>
 assumed that if such plea is accepted, the election would be materially<lb/>
 affected, as the election would then be set aside. He cited a Division<lb/>
 Bench judgment of this Court in Rajendra Kumar Meshram v. Vanshmani<lb/>
 Prasad Verma (2016) 10 SCC 715, wherein an election petition was filed<lb/>
 against the appellant, inter alia, on the ground that as the appellant -the<lb/>
 returned candidate -was a Government servant, his nomination had been<lb/>
 improperly accepted. The Court held that the requirement of Section<lb/>
 100(1)(d) of the Representation of People Act, 1951, being that the election<lb/>
 can be set aside only if such improper acceptance of the nomination has<lb/>
 &quot;materially affected&quot; the result of the election, and there being no pleading<lb/>
 or evidence to this effect, the election petition must fail. This Court stated:<lb/>
</p>

<p>&quot;9. As Issues 1 and 2 extracted above, have been<lb/>
 answered in favour of the returned candidate and there is<lb/>
 no cross-appeal, it is only the remaining issues that<lb/>
 survive for consideration. All the said issues centre round<lb/>
 the question of improper acceptance of the nomination<lb/>
 form of the returned candidate. In this regard, Issue 6<lb/>
 which raises the question of material effect of the improper<lb/>
 acceptance of nomination of the returned candidate on the<lb/>
 result of the election may be specifically noticed.<lb/>
</p>

<p>10. Under Section 100(1)(d), an election is liable to be<lb/>
 declared void on the ground of improper acceptance of a<lb/>
 nomination if such improper acceptance of the nomination<lb/>
 has materially affected the result of the election. This is in<lb/>
 distinction to what is contained in Section 100(1)(c) i.e.<lb/>
 improper rejection of a nomination which itself is a<lb/>
 sufficient ground for invalidating the election without any<lb/>
 further requirement of proof of material effect of such<lb/>
 rejection on the result of the election. The above<lb/>
 distinction must be kept in mind. Proceeding on the said<lb/>
 basis, we find that the High Court did not endeavour to go<lb/>
 into the further question that would be required to be<lb/>
 determined even if it is assumed that the appellant<lb/>
 returned candidate had not filed the electoral roll or a<lb/>
 certified copy thereof and, therefore, had not complied<lb/>
 with the mandatory provisions of Section 33(5) of the 1951<lb/>
 Act.<lb/>
</p>

<p>11. In other words, before setting aside the election on the<lb/>
 above ground, the High Court ought to have carried out a<lb/>
 further exercise, namely, to find out whether the improper<lb/>
 acceptance of the nomination had materially affected the<lb/>
 result of the election. This has not been done<lb/>
 notwithstanding Issue 6 framed which is specifically to the<lb/>
 above effect. The High Court having failed to determine<lb/>
 the said issue i.e. Issue 6, naturally, it was not empowered<lb/>
 to declare the election of the appellant returned candidate<lb/>
 as void even if we are to assume that the acceptance of<lb/>
 the nomination of the returned candidate was improper.&quot;<lb/>
</p>

<p>70.<lb/>
 On the other hand, Ms. Meenakshi Arora cited a Division<lb/>
 Bench judgment in Mairembam Prithviraj v. Pukhrem Sharatchandra<lb/>
 Singh (2017) 2 SCC 487. In this judgment, several earlier judgments of<lb/>
 this Court were cited on the legal effect of not pleading or proving that the<lb/>
 election had been &quot;materially affected&quot; by the improper acceptance of a<lb/>
 nomination under Section 100(1)(d)(i) of the Representation of People Act,<lb/>
 1951. After referring to Durai Muthuswami v. N. Nachiappan and Ors.<lb/>
1973(2) SCC 45 and Jagjit Singh v. Dharam Pal Singh 1995 Supp (1)<lb/>
 SCC 422, this Court then referred to a three-Judge Bench judgment in<lb/>
 Vashist Narain Sharma v. Dev Chandra 1955 (1) SCR 509 as under:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;25. It was held by this Court in Vashist Narain<lb/>
 Sharma v. Dev Chandra [(1955) 1 SCR 509] as under:<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;9. The learned counsel for the respondents concedes that<lb/>
 the burden of proving that the improper acceptance of a<lb/>
 nomination has materially affected the result of the<lb/>
 election lies upon the petitioner but he argues that the<lb/>
 question can arise in one of three ways:<lb/>
</item>

<item>(1) where the candidate whose nomination was improperly<lb/>
 accepted had secured less votes than the difference<lb/>
 between the returned candidate and the candidate<lb/>
 securing the next highest number of votes,<lb/>
</item>

<item>(2) where the person referred to above secured more<lb/>
 votes, and<lb/>
</item>

<item>(3) where the person whose nomination has been<lb/>
 improperly accepted is the returned candidate himself.<lb/>
</item>

<item>It is agreed that in the first case the result of the election is<lb/>
 not materially affected because if all the wasted votes are<lb/>
 added to the votes of the candidate securing the highest<lb/>
 votes, it will make no difference to the result and the<lb/>
 returned candidate will retain the seat. In the other two<lb/>
 cases it is contended that the result is materially<lb/>
 affected. So far as the third case is concerned it may be<lb/>
 readily conceded that such would be the conclusion…&quot;<lb/>
 This Court then concluded:<lb/>
 &quot;26. Mere finding that there has been an improper<lb/>
 acceptance of the nomination is not sufficient for a<lb/>
 declaration that the election is void under Section 100(1)<lb/>
 (d). There has to be further pleading and proof that the<lb/>
 result of the election of the returned candidate was<lb/>
 materially affected. But, there would be no necessity of<lb/>
 any proof in the event of the nomination of a returned<lb/>
 candidate being declared as having been improperly<lb/>
 accepted, especially in a case where there are only two<lb/>
 candidates in the fray. If the returned candidate&apos;s<lb/>
 nomination is declared to have been improperly accepted<lb/>
 it would mean that he could not have contested the<lb/>
 election and that the result of the election of the returned<lb/>
 candidate was materially affected need not be proved<lb/>
 further…&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>71.<lb/>
 None of the earlier judgments of this Court referred to in<lb/>
 Mairembam Prithviraj (supra) have been adverted to in Rajendra Kumar<lb/>
 Meshram (supra) cited by Shri Adsure. In particular, the judgment of three<lb/>
 learned Judges of this Court in Vashist Narain Sharma (supra) has<lb/>
 specifically held that where the person whose nomination has been<lb/>
 improperly accepted is the returned candidate himself, it may be readily<lb/>
 conceded that the conclusion has to be that the result of the election would<lb/>
 be &quot;materially affected&quot;, without there being any necessity to plead and<lb/>
 prove the same. The judgment in Rajendra Kumar Meshram (supra), not<lb/>
 having referred to these earlier judgments of a larger strength binding upon<lb/>
 it, cannot be said to have declared the law correctly. As a result thereof, the<lb/>
 impugned judgment of the High Court is right in its conclusion on this point<lb/>
 also.<lb/>
</p>

<p>72.<lb/>
 The reference is thus answered by stating that:<lb/>
</p>

<p>(a)<lb/>
 Anvar P.V. (supra), as clarified by us hereinabove, is the law<lb/>
 declared by this Court on Section 65B of the Evidence Act. The<lb/>
 judgment in Tomaso Bruno (supra), being per incuriam, does not lay<lb/>
 down the law correctly. Also, the judgment in SLP (Crl.) No. 9431 of<lb/>
 2011 reported as Shafhi Mohammad (supra) and the judgment dated<lb/>
 03.04.2018 reported as (2018) 5 SCC 311, do not lay down the law<lb/>
 correctly and are therefore overruled.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(b)<lb/>
 The clarification referred to above is that the required<lb/>
 certificate under Section 65B(4) is unnecessary if the original document<lb/>
 itself is produced. This can be done by the owner of a laptop computer,<lb/>
 computer tablet or even a mobile phone, by stepping into the witness<lb/>
 box and proving that the concerned device, on which the original<lb/>
 information is first stored, is owned and/or operated by him. In cases<lb/>
 where the &quot;computer&quot; happens to be a part of a &quot;computer system&quot; or<lb/>
 &quot;computer network&quot; and it becomes impossible to physically bring such<lb/>
 system or network to the Court, then the only means of providing<lb/>
 information contained in such electronic record can be in accordance<lb/>
 with Section 65B(1), together with the requisite certificate under Section<lb/>
 65B(4). The last sentence in Anvar P.V. (supra) which reads as &quot;…if an<lb/>
 electronic record as such is used as primary evidence under Section 62<lb/>
 of the Evidence Act…&quot; is thus clarified; it is to be read without the words<lb/>
 &quot;under Section 62 of the Evidence Act,…&quot; With this clarification, the law<lb/>
 stated in paragraph 24 of Anvar P.V. (supra) does not need to be<lb/>
 revisited.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(c)<lb/>
 The general directions issued in paragraph 62 (supra) shall<lb/>
 hereafter be followed by courts that deal with electronic evidence, to<lb/>
 ensure their preservation, and production of certificate at the<lb/>
 appropriate stage. These directions shall apply in all proceedings, till<lb/>
 rules and directions under Section 67C of the Information Technology<lb/>
 Act and data retention conditions are formulated for compliance by<lb/>
 telecom and internet service providers.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(d)<lb/>
 Appropriate rules and directions should be framed in exercise<lb/>
 of the Information Technology Act, by exercising powers such as in<lb/>
 Section 67C, and also framing suitable rules for the retention of data<lb/>
 involved in trial of offences, their segregation, rules of chain of custody,<lb/>
 stamping and record maintenance, for the entire duration of trials and<lb/>
 appeals, and also in regard to preservation of the meta data to avoid<lb/>
 corruption. Likewise, appropriate rules for preservation, retrieval and<lb/>
 production of electronic record, should be framed as indicated earlier,<lb/>
 after considering the report of the Committee constituted by the Chief<lb/>
 Justice&apos;s Conference in April, 2016.<lb/>
</p>

<p>73.<lb/>
 These appeals are dismissed with costs of INR One Lakh each<lb/>
 to be paid by Shri Arjun Panditrao Khotkar (i.e. the Appellant in C.A. Nos.<lb/>
 20825-20826 of 2017) to both Shri Kailash Kushanrao Gorantyal and Shri<lb/>
 Vijay Chaudhary.<lb/>
</p>

<p>…………………..………………J.<lb/>
 (R. F. Nariman)<lb/>
 ……………..……………………J.<lb/>
 (S. Ravindra Bhat)<lb/>
 ……………..……………………J.<lb/>
 (V. Ramasubramanian)<lb/>
 New Delhi.<lb/>
 14 th July, 2020.<lb/>
</p>


<p> J U D G M E N T<lb/>
 V. Ramasubramanian.J<lb/>
</p>

<p>1.<lb/>
 While I am entirely in agreement with the opinion<lb/>
 penned by R. F. Nariman, J. I also wish to add a few lines<lb/>
 about (i) the reasons for the acrimony behind Section 65B of<lb/>
 the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (hereinafter &quot;Evidence Act&quot;) (ii)<lb/>
 how even with the existing rules of procedure, the courts<lb/>
 fared well, without any legislative interference, while dealing<lb/>
 with evidence in analogue form, and (iii) how after machines<lb/>
 in analogue form gave way to machines in electronic form,<lb/>
 certain jurisdictions of the world changed their legal<lb/>
 landscape, over a period of time, by suitably amending the<lb/>
 law, to avoid confusions and conflicts.<lb/>
</p>

<p>I. Reasons for the acrimony behind Section 65B<lb/>
</p>

<p>2.<lb/>
 Documentary evidence, in contrast to oral evidence, is<lb/>
 required to pass through certain check posts, such as<lb/>
 (i) admissibility (ii) relevancy and (iii) proof, before it is<lb/>
 allowed entry into the sanctum. Many times, it is<lb/>
 difficult to identify which of these check posts is<lb/>
 required to be passed first, which to be passed next<lb/>
 and which to be passed later. Sometimes, at least in<lb/>
 practice, the sequence in which evidence has to go<lb/>
 through these three check posts, changes. Generally<lb/>
 and theoretically, admissibility depends on relevancy.<lb/>
 Under Section 136 of the Evidence Act, relevancy must<lb/>
 be established before admissibility can be dealt with.<lb/>
 Therefore if we go by Section 136, a party should first<lb/>
 show relevancy, making it the first check post and<lb/>
 admissibility the second one. But some documents,<lb/>
 such as those indicated in Section 68 of the Evidence<lb/>
 Act, which pass the first check post of relevancy and<lb/>
 the second check post of admissibility may be of no<lb/>
 value unless the attesting witness is examined. Proof of<lb/>
 execution of such documents, in a manner established<lb/>
 by law, thus constitutes the third check post. Here<lb/>
 again, proof of execution stands on a different footing<lb/>
 than proof of contents.<lb/>
</p>

<p>3.<lb/>
 It must also be noted that whatever is relevant may not<lb/>
 always be admissible, if the law imposes certain<lb/>
 conditions. For instance, a document, whose contents<lb/>
 are relevant, may not be admissible, if it is a document<lb/>
 requiring stamping and registration, but had not been<lb/>
 duly stamped and registered. In other words, if<lb/>
 admissibility is the cart, relevancy is the horse, under<lb/>
 Section 136. But certain provisions of law place the<lb/>
 cart before the horse and Section 65B appears to be<lb/>
 one of them.<lb/>
</p>

<p>4.<lb/>
 Section 136 which confers a discretion upon the Judge<lb/>
 to decide as to the admissibility of evidence reads as<lb/>
 follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>136. Judge to decide as to admissibility of<lb/>
 evidence. --<lb/></item>
<item> 
When either party proposes to give evidence of<lb/>
 any fact, the Judge may ask the party<lb/>
 proposing to give the evidence in what manner<lb/>
 the alleged fact, if proved, would be relevant;<lb/>
 and the Judge shall admit the evidence if he<lb/>
 thinks that the fact, if proved, would be<lb/>
 relevant, and not otherwise.<lb/></item>
<item> 
 If the fact proposed to be proved is one of which<lb/>
 evidence is admissible only upon proof of some<lb/>
 other fact, such lastmentioned fact must be<lb/>
 proved before evidence is given of the fact first<lb/>
 mentioned, unless the party undertakes to give<lb/>
 proof of such fact, and the Court is satisfied<lb/>
 with such undertaking.<lb/></item>

<item> 
 If the relevancy of one alleged fact depends<lb/>
 upon another alleged fact being first proved,<lb/>
 the Judge may, in his discretion, either permit<lb/>
 evidence of the first fact to be given before the<lb/>
 second fact is proved, or require evidence to be<lb/>
 given of the second fact before evidence is<lb/>
 given of the first fact.<lb/>
</item>

<p>5.<lb/>
 There are three parts to Section 136. The first part<lb/>
 deals with the discretion of the Judge to admit the<lb/>
 evidence, if he thinks that the fact sought to be proved<lb/>
 is relevant. The second part of Section 136 states that<lb/>
 if the fact proposed to be proved is one, of which<lb/>
 evidence is admissible only upon proof of some other<lb/>
 fact, such last mentioned fact must be proved before<lb/>
 evidence is given of the fact first mentioned. But this<lb/>
 rule is subject to a small concession, namely, that if<lb/>
 the party undertakes to produce proof of the last<lb/>
 mentioned fact later and the Court is satisfied<lb/>
 about such undertaking, the Court may proceed to<lb/>
 admit evidence of the first mentioned fact. The<lb/>
 third part of Section 136 deals with the relevancy of<lb/>
 one alleged fact, which depends upon another alleged<lb/>
 fact being first proved. The third part of Section 136<lb/>
 has no relevance for our present purpose.<lb/>
</p>

<p>6.<lb/>
 Illustration (b) under Section 136 provides an easy<lb/>
 example of the second part of Section 136. Illustration<lb/>
 (b) reads as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>(b) It is proposed to prove, by a copy, the<lb/>
 contents of a document said to be lost.<lb/></item>

<item>
 The fact that the original is lost must be proved<lb/>
 by the person proposing to produce the copy,<lb/>
 before the copy is produced.<lb/>
</item>

<p>7.<lb/>
 What is laid down in Section 65B as a precondition for<lb/>
 the admission of an electronic record, resembles what<lb/>
 is provided in the second part of Section 136. For<lb/>
 example, if a fact is sought to be proved through the<lb/>
 contents of an electronic record (or information<lb/>
 contained in an electronic record), the Judge is first<lb/>
 required to see if it is relevant, if the first part of<lb/>
 Section 136 is taken to be applicable.<lb/>
</p>

<p>8.<lb/>
 But Section 65B makes the admissibility of the<lb/>
 information contained in the electronic record subject<lb/>
 to certain conditions, including certification. The<lb/>
 certification is for the purpose of proving that the<lb/>
 information which constitutes the computer output<lb/>
 was produced by a computer which was used regularly<lb/>
 to store or process information and that the<lb/>
 information so derived was regularly fed into the<lb/>
 computer in the ordinary course of the said activities.<lb/>
</p>

<p>9.<lb/>
 In other words, if we go by the requirements of Section<lb/>
 136, the computer output becomes admissible if the<lb/>
 fact sought to be proved is relevant. But such a fact is<lb/>
 admissible only upon proof of some other fact namely,<lb/>
 that it was extracted from a computer used regularly<lb/>
 etc. In simple terms, what is contained in the<lb/>
 computer output can be equated to the first<lb/>
 mentioned fact and the requirement of a<lb/>
 certification can be equated to the last mentioned<lb/>
 fact, referred to in the second part of Section 136<lb/>
 read with Illustration (b) thereunder.<lb/>
</p>

<p>10. But Section 65B(1) starts with a nonobstante clause<lb/>
 excluding the application of the other provisions and it<lb/>
 makes<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 certification,<lb/>
 a<lb/>
 precondition<lb/>
 for<lb/>
 admissibility. While doing so, it does not talk about<lb/>
 relevancy. In a way, Sections 65A and 65B, if read<lb/>
 together, mixup both proof and admissibility, but not<lb/>
 talk about relevancy. Section 65A refers to the<lb/>
 procedure prescribed in Section 65B, for the purpose<lb/>
 of proving the contents of electronic records, but<lb/>
 Section 65B speaks entirely about the preconditions<lb/>
 for admissibility. As a result, Section 65B places<lb/>
 admissibility as the first or the outermost check post,<lb/>
 capable of turning away even at the border, any<lb/>
 electronic evidence, without any enquiry, if the<lb/>
 conditions stipulated therein are not fulfilled.<lb/>
</p>

<p>11. The placement by Section 65B, of admissibility as the<lb/>
 first or the border check post, coupled with the fact<lb/>
 that a number of &apos;computer systems&apos; (as defined in<lb/>
 Section 2(l) of the Information Technology Act, 2000)<lb/>
 owned by different individuals, may get involved in the<lb/>
 production of an electronic record, with the &apos;originator&apos;<lb/>
 (as defined in Section 2(za) of the Information<lb/>
 Technology Act, 2000) being different from the<lb/>
 recipients or the sharers, has created lot of acrimony<lb/>
 behind Section 65B, which is evident from the judicial<lb/>
 opinion swinging like a pendulum.<lb/>
</p>

<p>II. How the courts dealt with evidence in analogue form<lb/>
 without legislative interference and the shift<lb/>
</p>

<p>12. It is a matter of fact and record that courts all over the<lb/>
 world were quick to adapt themselves to evidence in<lb/>
 analogue form, within the framework of archaic,<lb/>
 centuries old rules of evidence. It was not as if evidence<lb/>
 in analogue form was incapable of being manipulated.<lb/>
 But the courts managed the show well by applying time<lb/>
 tested rules for sifting the actual from the manipulated.<lb/>
</p>

<p>13. It is no doubt true that the felicity with which courts<lb/>
 adapted themselves to appreciating evidence in<lb/>
 analogue form was primarily due to the fact that in<lb/>
 analogue technology, one is able to see and/ or<lb/>
 perceive something that is happening. In analogue<lb/>
 technology, a wave is recorded or used in its original<lb/>
 form. When someone speaks or sings, a signal is taken<lb/>
 directly by the microphone and laid onto a tape, if we<lb/>
 take the example of an analogue tape recorder. Both,<lb/>
 the wave from the microphone and the wave on the<lb/>
 tape, are analogue and the wave on the tape can be<lb/>
 read, amplified and sent to a speaker to produce the<lb/>
 sound. In digital technology, the analogue wave is<lb/>
 sampled at some interval and then turned into<lb/>
 numbers that are stored in a digital device. Therefore,<lb/>
 what are stored, are in terms of numbers and they are,<lb/>
 in turn, converted into voltage waves to produce what<lb/>
 was stored.<lb/>
</p>

<p>14. The difference between something in analogue form<lb/>
 and the same thing in digital form and the reason why<lb/>
 digital format throws more challenges, was presented<lb/>
 pithily in an article titled &apos;Electronic evidence and<lb/>
 the meaning of &quot;original&quot;&apos;, 9 by Stephen Mason<lb/>
 (Barrister and recognised authority on electronic<lb/>
 9 Stephen Mason, Electronic evidence and the meaning of &quot;original&quot;, 79 Amicus Curiae<lb/>
 signatures and electronic evidence). Taking the<lb/>
 example of a photograph in both types of form, the<lb/>
 learned author says the following:<lb/>
</p>

<item>For instance, a photograph taken with an<lb/>
 analogue camera (that is, a camera with a film)<lb/>
 can only remain a single object. It cannot be<lb/>
 merged into other photographs, and split off<lb/>
 again. It remains a physical object. A<lb/>
 photograph taken with a digital camera differs<lb/>
 markedly. The digital object, made up of a<lb/>
 series of zeros and the number one, can be,<lb/>
 and frequently is, manipulated and altered<lb/>
 (especially in fashion magazines and for<lb/>
 advertisements). Things can be taken out and<lb/>
 put in to the image, in the same way the water<lb/>
 droplets can merge and form a single, larger<lb/>
 droplet. The new, manipulated digital image<lb/>
 can also be divided back into its constituent<lb/>
 parts.<lb/></item>

<item> 
 Herein lies the interesting point: when three<lb/>
 droplets of water fuse and then separate into<lb/>
 three droplets, it is to be questioned whether<lb/>
 the three droplets that merge from the bigger<lb/>
 droplet were the identical droplets that existed<lb/>
 before they merged. In the same way, consider<lb/>
 a digital object that has been manipulated and<lb/>
 added to, and the process is then reversed. The<lb/>
 original object that was used remains (unless it<lb/>
 was never saved independently, and the<lb/>
 changes made to the image were saved in the<lb/>
 original file), but another object, with the<lb/>
 identical image (or near identical, depending on<lb/>
 the system software and application software)<lb/>
 now exists. Conceptually, it is possible to argue<lb/>
 94<lb/>
 that the two digital images are different: one is<lb/>
 the original, the other a copy of the original that<lb/>
 was manipulated and returned to its original<lb/>
 state (whatever &quot;original&quot; means). But both<lb/>
 images are identical, apart from some<lb/>
 additional meta data that might, or might not<lb/>
 be conclusive. However, it is apparent that the<lb/>
 images, if viewed together, are identical -will<lb/>
 be identical, and the viewer will not be able to<lb/>
 determine which is the original, and which<lb/>
 image was manipulated. In this respect, the<lb/>
 digital images are no different from the droplets<lb/>
 of rain that fall, merge, then divide: there is no<lb/>
 telling whether the droplets that split are<lb/>
 identical to the droplets that came together to<lb/>
 form the larger droplet.<lb/>
</item>

<p>15. That courts did not have a problem with the evidence<lb/>
 in analogue form is established by several judicial<lb/>
 precedents, in U.K., which were also followed by our<lb/>
 courts. A device used to clandestinely record a<lb/>
 conversation between two individuals was allowed in<lb/>
 Harry Parker vs. Mason 10 in proving fraud on the part<lb/>
 of the plaintiff. While Harry Parker was a civil<lb/>
 proceeding, the principle laid down therein found<lb/>
 acceptance in a criminal trial in R. vs. Burr and<lb/>
 Sullivan. 11 The High Court of Judiciary in Scotland<lb/>
 admitted in evidence, the tape record of a conversation<lb/>
 between the complainant and a black mailer, in Hopes<lb/>
 and Lavery vs. H. M. Advocate. 12 A conversation<lb/>
 recorded in police cell overheard without any<lb/>
 deception, beyond setting up a tape recorder without<lb/>
 warning, was admitted in evidence in R. vs. Mills. 13<lb/>
</p>

<p>16. Then came R. vs. Maqsud Ali 14 where Marshall J.<lb/>
 drew an analogy between taperecordings and<lb/>
 photographs and held that just as evidence of things<lb/>
 seen through telescopes or binoculars have been<lb/>
 admitted, despite the fact that those things could<lb/>
 not be picked up by the naked eye, the devices<lb/>
 used for recording conversations could also be<lb/>
 admitted, provided the accuracy of the recording<lb/>
 can be proved and the voices recorded properly<lb/>
 identified.<lb/>
</p>

<p>17. Following the above precedents, this Court also held in<lb/>
 S. Pratap Singh vs. State of Punjab, 15 Yusaffalli<lb/>
 Esmail Nagree vs. State of Maharashtra, 16 N. Sri<lb/>
 Rama Reddy vs. V. V. Giri, 17 R.M. Malkani vs. State<lb/>
 of<lb/>
 Maharashtra, 18<lb/>
 Ziyauddin<lb/>
 Burhanuddin<lb/>
 Bukhari vs. Brijmohan Ramdass Mehra, 19 Ram<lb/>
 Singh vs. Col. Ram Singh, 20 Tukaram S. Dighole vs.<lb/>
 Manikrao Shivaji Kokate, 21 that tape records of<lb/>
 conversations and speeches are admissible in evidence<lb/>
 under the Indian Evidence Act, subject to certain<lb/>
 conditions. In Ziyauddin Burhanuddin Bukhari and<lb/>
 Tukaram S. Dighole, this Court further held that tape<lb/>
 records constitute &quot;document&quot; within the meaning of<lb/>
 the expression under Section 3 of the Evidence Act.<lb/>
 Thus, without looking up to the law makers to come up<lb/>
 with necessary amendments from time to time, the<lb/>
 courts themselves developed certain rules, over a<lb/>
 period of time, to test the authenticity of these<lb/>
 documents in analogue form and these rules have in<lb/>
 fact, worked well.<lb/>
</p>

<p>18. There was also an important question that bothered<lb/>
 the courts while dealing with evidence in analogue<lb/>
 form. It was as to whether such evidence was direct or<lb/>
 hearsay. In The Statute of Liberty, Sapporo Maru<lb/>
 M/S (Owners) vs. Steam Tanker Statute of Liberty<lb/>
 (Owners), 22 the film recording of a radar set of echoes<lb/>
 of ships within its range was held to be real evidence.<lb/>
 The court opined that there was no distinction between<lb/>
 a photographer operating a camera manually and the<lb/>
 observations of a barometer operator or its equivalent<lb/>
 operation by a recording mechanism. The Judge<lb/>
 rejected the contention that the evidence was hearsay.<lb/></item>
<p> 19. but when it comes to a computer, one of the<lb/>
 earliest of cases where the Court of Appeal had to deal<lb/>
 with evidence in the form of a printout from a<lb/>
 computer was in R. vs. Pettigrew. 23 In that case, the<lb/>
 printout from a computer operated by an employee of<lb/>
 the Bank of England was held to be hearsay. But the<lb/>
 academic opinion about the correctness of the decision<lb/>
 was sharply divided. While Professor Smith 24<lb/>
 considered the evidence in this case as direct and not<lb/>
 hearsay, Professor Tapper 25 took the view that the<lb/>
 printout was partly hearsay and partly not. Professor<lb/>
 Seng 26 thought that both views were plausible.<lb/>
</p>

<p>20. But the underlying theory on the basis of which<lb/>
 academicians critiqued the above judgment is that<lb/>
 wherever the production of the output was made<lb/>
 possible without human intervention, the evidence<lb/>
 should be taken as direct. This is how the position was<lb/>
 explained in Castle vs. Cross, 27 in which the printout<lb/>
 from the Intoximeter was held to be direct and not<lb/>
 hearsay, on the ground that the breath alcohol value in<lb/>
 the printout comprised information produced by the<lb/>
 Intoximeter without the data being processed through<lb/>
 a human brain.<lb/>
</p>

<p>21. In R vs. Robson Mitchell and Richards, 28 a printout<lb/>
 of telephone calls made on a mobile telephone was<lb/>
 taken as evidence of the calls made and received in<lb/>
 association with the number. The Court held &quot;where a<lb/>
 machine observes a fact and records it, that<lb/>
 record states a fact. It is evidence of what the<lb/>
 machine recorded and this was printed out. The<lb/>
 record was not the fact but the evidence of the<lb/>
 fact&quot;.<lb/>
 space, has made electronic records more prone to<lb/>
 manipulation and consequently to a greater degree of<lb/>
 suspicion. Therefore, law makers interfered, sometimes<lb/>
 making things easy for courts and sometimes creating<lb/>
 a lot of confusion. But over a period of time, certain<lb/>
 jurisdictions have come up with reasonably good<lb/>
 solutions. Let us now take a look at them.<lb/>
</p>

<p>III. Legislative developments in U.S.A., U.K. and Canada<lb/>
 on the admissibility of electronic records<lb/></p>
<p> 
 POSITION IN USA<lb/>
</p>

<p>23. The Federal Rules of Evidence (FRE) of the United<lb/>
 States of America as amended with effect from<lb/>
 01.12.2017 recognise the availability of more than one<lb/>
 option to a person seeking to produce an electronic<lb/>
 record. Under the amended rules, a person can follow<lb/>
 either the traditional route under Rule 901 or the route<lb/>
 of selfauthentication under Rule 902 whereunder a<lb/>
 certificate of authenticity will elevate its status. Rules<lb/>
 901 and 902 of FRE read as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>Rule 901. Authenticating or Identifying<lb/>
 Evidence<lb/>
</item>

<item>(a) In General. To satisfy the requirement of<lb/>
 authenticating or identifying an item of<lb/>
 evidence, the proponent must produce evidence<lb/>
 sufficient to support a finding that the item is<lb/>
 what the proponent claims it is.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(b) Examples. The following are examples only<lb/>
 -not a complete list-of evidence that satisfies<lb/>
 the requirement:<lb/>
</item>

<item>(1) Testimony<lb/>
 of<lb/>
 a<lb/>
 Witness<lb/>
 with<lb/>
 Knowledge. Testimony that an item is what it is<lb/>
 claimed to be.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(2) Non expert Opinion About Handwriting. A<lb/>
 non expert&apos;s opinion that handwriting is<lb/>
 genuine, based on a familiarity with it that was<lb/>
 not acquired for the current litigation.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(3) Comparison by an Expert Witness or the<lb/>
 Trier<lb/>
 of<lb/>
 Fact. A<lb/>
 comparison<lb/>
 with<lb/>
 an<lb/>
 authenticated specimen by an expert witness<lb/>
 or the trier of fact.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(4) Distinctive Characteristics and the Like. The<lb/>
 appearance, contents, substance, internal<lb/>
 patterns, or other distinctive characteristics of<lb/>
 the item, taken together with all the<lb/>
 circumstances.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(5) Opinion<lb/>
 About<lb/>
 a<lb/>
 Voice. An<lb/>
 opinion<lb/>
 identifying a person&apos;s voice-whether heard<lb/>
 firsthand or through mechanical or electronic<lb/>
 transmission or recording-based on hearing<lb/>
 the voice at any time under circumstances that<lb/>
 connect it with the alleged speaker.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(6) Evidence<lb/>
 About<lb/>
 a<lb/>
 Telephone<lb/>
 Conversation. For a telephone conversation,<lb/>
 102<lb/>
 evidence that a call was made to the number<lb/>
 assigned at the time to:<lb/>
</item>

<item>(A) a particular person, if circumstances,<lb/>
 including selfidentification, show that the<lb/>
 person answering was the one called; or<lb/>
</item>

<item>(B) a particular business, if the call was made<lb/>
 to a business and the call related to business<lb/>
 reasonably transacted over the telephone.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(7) Evidence About Public Records. Evidence<lb/>
 that:<lb/>
</item>

<item>(A) a document was recorded or filed in a public<lb/>
 office as authorized by law; or<lb/>
</item>

<item>(B) a purported public record or statement is<lb/>
 from the office where items of this kind are<lb/>
 kept.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(8) Evidence About Ancient Documents or Data<lb/>
 Compilations. For<lb/>
 a<lb/>
 document<lb/>
 or<lb/>
 data<lb/>
 compilation, evidence that it:<lb/>
</item>

<item>(A) is in a condition that creates no suspicion<lb/>
 about its authenticity;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(B) was in a place where, if authentic, it would<lb/>
 likely be; and<lb/>
</item>

<item>(C) is at least 20 years old when offered.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(9) Evidence<lb/>
 About<lb/>
 a<lb/>
 Process<lb/>
 or<lb/>
 System. Evidence describing a process or<lb/>
 system and showing that it produces an<lb/>
 accurate result.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(10) Methods Provided by a Statute or<lb/>
 Rule. Any<lb/>
 method<lb/>
 of<lb/>
 authentication<lb/>
 or<lb/>
 identification allowed by a federal statute or a<lb/>
 rule prescribed by the Supreme Court.<lb/>
</item>

<item>Rule 902. Evidence That Is Self<lb/>
 Authenticating<lb/></item>
<item> 
 The following items of evidence are self<lb/>
 authenticating; they require no extrinsic<lb/>
 evidence of authenticity in order to be admitted:<lb/>
 103<lb/>
</item>

<item>(1) Domestic Public Documents That Are Sealed<lb/>
 and Signed. A document that bears:<lb/>
</item>

<item>(A) a seal purporting to be that of the United<lb/>
 States; any state, district, commonwealth,<lb/>
 territory, or insular possession of the United<lb/>
 States; the former Panama Canal Zone; the<lb/>
 Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands; a political<lb/>
 subdivision of any of these entities; or a<lb/>
 department, agency, or officer of any entity<lb/>
 named above; and<lb/>
</item>

<item>(B) a signature purporting to be an execution or<lb/>
 attestation.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(2) Domestic Public Documents That Are Not<lb/>
 Sealed but Are Signed and Certified. A<lb/>
 document that bears no seal if:<lb/>
</item>

<item>(A) it bears the signature of an officer or<lb/>
 employee of an entity named in Rule 902(1)(A);<lb/>
 and<lb/>
</item>

<item>(B) another public officer who has a seal and<lb/>
 official duties within that same entity certifies<lb/>
 under seal-or its equivalent-that the signer<lb/>
 has the official capacity and that the signature<lb/>
 is genuine.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(3) Foreign Public Documents. A document that<lb/>
 purports to be signed or attested by a person<lb/>
 who is authorized by a foreign country&apos;s law to<lb/>
 do so. The document must be accompanied by<lb/>
 a final certification that<lb/>
 certifies<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 genuineness of the signature and official<lb/>
 position of the signer or attester-or of any<lb/>
 foreign official whose certificate of genuineness<lb/>
 relates to the signature or attestation or is in a<lb/>
 chain of certificates of genuineness relating to<lb/>
 the signature or attestation. The certification<lb/>
 may be made by a secretary of a United States<lb/>
 embassy or legation; by a consul general, vice<lb/>
 consul, or consular agent of the United States;<lb/>
 or by a diplomatic or consular official of the<lb/>
 foreign country assigned or accredited to the<lb/>
 United States. If all parties have been given a<lb/>
 reasonable opportunity to investigate the<lb/>
 104<lb/>
 document&apos;s authenticity and accuracy, the<lb/>
 court may, for good cause, either:<lb/>
</item>

<item>(A) order that it be treated as presumptively<lb/>
 authentic without final certification; or<lb/>
</item>

<item>(B) allow it to be evidenced by an attested<lb/>
 summary with or without final certification.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(4) Certified Copies of Public Records. A copy of<lb/>
 an official record-or a copy of a document that<lb/>
 was recorded or filed in a public office as<lb/>
 authorized by law-if the copy is certified as<lb/>
 correct by:<lb/>
</item>

<item>(A) the custodian or another person authorized<lb/>
 to make the certification; or<lb/>
</item>

<item>(B) a certificate that complies with Rule 902(1),<lb/>
 (2), or (3), a federal statute, or a rule prescribed<lb/>
 by the Supreme Court.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(5) Official Publications. A book, pamphlet, or<lb/>
 other publication purporting to be issued by a<lb/>
 public authority.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(6) Newspapers<lb/>
 and<lb/>
 Periodicals. Printed<lb/>
 material purporting to be a newspaper or<lb/>
 periodical.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(7) Trade Inscriptions and the Like. An<lb/>
 inscription, sign, tag, or label purporting to have<lb/>
 been affixed in the course of business and<lb/>
 indicating origin, ownership, or control.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(8) Acknowledged<lb/>
 Documents. A<lb/>
 document<lb/>
 accompanied<lb/>
 by<lb/>
 a<lb/>
 certificate<lb/>
 of<lb/>
 acknowledgment that is lawfully executed by a<lb/>
 notary public or another officer who is<lb/>
 authorized to take acknowledgments.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(9) Commercial<lb/>
 Paper<lb/>
 and<lb/>
 Related<lb/>
 Documents. Commercial paper, a signature on<lb/>
 it, and related documents, to the extent allowed<lb/>
 by general commercial law.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(10) Presumptions Under a Federal Statute. A<lb/>
 signature, document, or anything else that a<lb/>
 federal statute declares to be presumptively or<lb/>
 prima facie genuine or authentic.<lb/>
 105<lb/>
</item>

<item>(11) Certified Domestic Records of a Regularly<lb/>
 Conducted Activity. The original or a copy of a<lb/>
 domestic record that meets the requirements of<lb/>
 Rule 803(6)(A)-(C), as shown by a certification<lb/>
 of the custodian or another qualified person<lb/>
 that complies with a federal statute or a rule<lb/>
 prescribed by the Supreme Court. Before the<lb/>
 trial or hearing, the proponent must give an<lb/>
 adverse party reasonable written notice of the<lb/>
 intent to offer the record-and must make the<lb/>
 record and certification available for inspection<lb/>
 -so that the party has a fair opportunity to<lb/>
 challenge them.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(12) Certified Foreign Records of a Regularly<lb/>
 Conducted Activity. In a civil case, the original<lb/>
 or a copy of a foreign record that meets the<lb/>
 requirements of Rule 902(11), modified as<lb/>
 follows: the certification, rather than complying<lb/>
 with a federal statute or Supreme Court rule,<lb/>
 must be signed in a manner that, if falsely<lb/>
 made, would subject the maker to a criminal<lb/>
 penalty in the country where the certification is<lb/>
 signed. The proponent must also meet the<lb/>
 notice requirements of Rule 902(11).<lb/>
</item>

<item>(13) Certified Records Generated by an<lb/>
 Electronic Process or System. A record<lb/>
 generated by an electronic process or system<lb/>
 that produces an accurate result, as shown by<lb/>
 a certification of a qualified person that<lb/>
 complies with the certification requirements of<lb/>
 Rule 902(11) or (12). The proponent must also<lb/>
 meet the notice requirements of Rule 902(11).<lb/>
</item>

<item>(14) Certified Data Copied from an Electronic<lb/>
 Device, Storage Medium, or File. Data copied<lb/>
 from an electronic device, storage medium, or<lb/>
 file, if authenticated by a process of digital<lb/>
 identification, as shown by a certification of a<lb/>
 qualified person that complies with the<lb/>
 certification requirements of Rule 902(11) or<lb/>
 (12). The proponent also must meet the notice<lb/>
 requirements of Rule 902(11).<lb/>
</item>

<p>24. An important decision in the American jurisprudence<lb/>
 on this issue was delivered by Chief Magistrate Judge<lb/>
 of District of Maryland in Lorraine vs. Markel<lb/>
 American Insurance Co. 29 In this case, Paul Grimm,<lb/>
 J. while dealing with a challenge to an arbitrator&apos;s<lb/>
 decision in an insurance dispute, dealt with the issue<lb/>
 whether emails discussing the insurance policy in<lb/>
 question, were admissible as evidence. The Court,<lb/>
 while extending the applicability of Rules 901 and 902<lb/>
 of FRE to electronic evidence, laid down a broad test<lb/>
 for admissibility of electronically stored information. 30<lb/>
 This decision was rendered in 2007 and the FRE were<lb/>
 amended in 2017.<lb/>
</p>



<p>25. Subrules (13) and (14) were incorporated in Rule 902<lb/>
 under the amendment of the year 2017. Until then, a<lb/>
 person seeking to produce electronic records had to fall<lb/>
 back mostly upon Rule 901 (except in few cases<lb/>
 covered by subrules (11) and (12) of Rule 902). It<lb/>
 means that the benefit of selfauthentication was not<lb/>
 available until then [until the advent of subrules (13)<lb/>
 and (14), except in cases covered by subrules (11) and<lb/>
 (12)]. Nevertheless, the introduction of subrules (13)<lb/>
 and (14) in Rule 902 did not completely exclude the<lb/>
 application of the general provisions of Rule 901.<lb/>
</p>

<p>26. Rule 901 applies to all evidence across the board. It is<lb/>
 a general provision. But Rule 902 is a special provision<lb/>
 dealing with evidence that is selfauthenticating.<lb/>
 Records generated by an electronic process or system<lb/>
 and data copied from an electronic device, storage<lb/>
 medium or file, are included in subrules (13) and (14)<lb/>
 of Rule 902 of the Federal Rules of Evidence.<lb/>
</p>

<p>27. But FRE 902 does not exclude the application of FRE<lb/>
901. It is only when a party seeks to invoke the benefit<lb/>
 of selfauthentication that Rule 902 applies. If a party<lb/>
 chooses not to claim the benefit of selfauthentication,<lb/>
 he is free to come under Rule 901, even if the evidence<lb/>
 sought to be adduced is of an electronically stored<lb/>
 information (ESI).<lb/>
</p>

<p>28. In an article titled &apos;EDiscovery: Authenticating<lb/>
 Common Types of ESI Chart&apos;, authored by Paul W.<lb/>
 Grimm (the Judge who delivered the verdict in<lb/>
 Lorraine) and coauthored by Gregory P. Joseph and<lb/>
 published by Thomson Reuters (2017), the learned<lb/>
 authors have given a snapshot of the different methods<lb/>
 of authentication of various types of ESI (electronically<lb/>
 stored information). In a subsequent article (2018)<lb/>
 titled &apos;Admissibility of Electronic Evidence&apos; published<lb/>
 under the caption &apos;GrimmBrady Chart&apos; (referring to<lb/>
 Paul W. Grimm and Kevin F. Brady) on the website<lb/>
 &quot;complexdiscovery.com&quot;, a condensed chart is provided<lb/>
 which throws light on the different methods of<lb/>
 authentication of ESI. The chart is reproduced in the<lb/>
 form of a table, with particular reference to the relevant<lb/>
 subrules of Rules 901 and 902 of the Federal Rules of<lb/>
 Evidence as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>S. No. Type of ESI<lb/>
 Potential Authentication<lb/>
 Methods<lb/>
</item>

<item>1.<lb/>
 Email, Text<lb/>
 Messages, and<lb/>
 Instant Messages<lb/>
 Witness with personal knowledge<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 (901(b)(1))<lb/>
 Expert testimony or comparison<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 with<lb/>
 authenticated<lb/>
 examples<lb/>
 (901(b)(3))<lb/>
 Distinctive<lb/>
 characteristics<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 including circumstantial evidence<lb/>
 (901(b)(4))<lb/>
 System or process capable of<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 proving reliable and dependable<lb/>
 result (901(b)(9))<lb/>
 Trade inscriptions (902(7))<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 Certified copies of business<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 record (902(11))<lb/>
 Certified records generated by an<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 electronic<lb/>
 process<lb/>
 or<lb/>
 system<lb/>
 (902(13))<lb/>
 Certified data copied from an<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 electronic device, storage medium,<lb/>
 or file (902(14))<lb/>
</item>

<item>2.<lb/>
 Chat Room Postings,<lb/>
 Blogs, Wikis, and<lb/>
 Other Social Media<lb/>
 Conversations<lb/>
 Witness with personal knowledge<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
</item>

<item>(901(b)(1))<lb/>
 Expert testimony or comparison<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 with<lb/>
 authenticated<lb/>
 examples<lb/>
 (901(b)(3))<lb/>
 Distinctive<lb/>
 characteristics<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 including circumstantial evidence<lb/>
 (901(b)(4))<lb/>
 System or process capable of<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 proving reliable and dependable<lb/>
 result<lb/>
 Official publications (902(5))<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 Newspapers and periodicals<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
</item>

<item>(902(6))<lb/>
 Certified records generated by an<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 electronic<lb/>
 process<lb/>
 or<lb/>
 system<lb/>
 (902(13))<lb/>
 Certified data copied from an<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 electronic device, storage medium,<lb/>
 or file (902(14))<lb/>
</item>

<item>3.<lb/>
 Social Media Sites<lb/>
 (Facebook, LinkedIn,<lb/>
 Twitter,<lb/>
 Instagram, and<lb/>
 Snapchat)<lb/>
 Witness with personal knowledge<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
</item>

<item>(901(b)(1))<lb/>
 Expert testimony or comparison<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 with<lb/>
 authenticated<lb/>
 examples<lb/>
 (901(b)(3))<lb/>
 Distinctive<lb/>
 characteristics<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 including circumstantial evidence<lb/>
 (901(b)(4))<lb/>
 Public records (901(b)(7))<lb/>
</item>

<item>■<lb/>
 System or process capable of<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 proving reliable and dependable<lb/>
 result (901(b)(9))<lb/>
 Official publications (902(5))<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 Certified records generated by an<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 electronic<lb/>
 process<lb/>
 or<lb/>
 system<lb/>
 (902(13))<lb/>
 Certified data copied from an<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 electronic device, storage medium,<lb/>
 or file (902(14))<lb/>
</item>

<item>4.<lb/>
 Digitally Stored Data<lb/>
 and Internet of<lb/>
 Things<lb/>
 Witness with personal knowledge<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
</item>

<item>(901(b)(1))<lb/>
 Expert testimony or comparison<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 with<lb/>
 authenticated<lb/>
 examples<lb/>
 (901(b)(3))<lb/>
 Distinctive<lb/>
 characteristics<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 including circumstantial evidence<lb/>
 (901(b)(4))<lb/>
 System or process capable of<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 proving reliable and dependable<lb/>
 result (901(b)(9))<lb/>
 Certified records generated by an<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 electronic<lb/>
 process<lb/>
 or<lb/>
 system<lb/>
 (902(13))<lb/>
 Certified data copied from an<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 electronic device, storage medium,<lb/>
 or file (902(14))<lb/>
</item>

<item>5.<lb/>
 Computer Processes,<lb/>
 Animations,<lb/>
 Virtual Reality, and<lb/>
 Simulations<lb/>
 Witness with personal knowledge<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 (901(b)(1))<lb/>
 Expert testimony or comparison<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 with<lb/>
 authenticated<lb/>
 examples<lb/>
 (901(b)(3))<lb/>
 System or process capable of<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 proving reliable and dependable<lb/>
 result (901(b)(9))<lb/>
 Certified records generated by an<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 electronic<lb/>
 process<lb/>
 or<lb/>
 system<lb/>
 (902(13))<lb/>
</item>

<item>6.<lb/>
 Digital Photographs<lb/>
 Witness with personal knowledge<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
</item>

<item>(901(b)(1))<lb/>
 System or process capable of<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 providing reliable and dependable<lb/>
 result (901(b)(9))<lb/>
 Official publications (902(5))<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 Certified records generated by an<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 electronic<lb/>
 process<lb/>
 or<lb/>
 system<lb/>
 (902(13))<lb/>
 Certified data copied from an<lb/>
 ■<lb/>
 electronic device, storage medium,<lb/>
 or file (902(14))<lb/>
</item>

<p>29. It is interesting to note that while the Indian Evidence<lb/>
 Act is of the year 1872, the Federal Rules of Evidence<lb/>
 were adopted by the order of the Supreme Court of the<lb/>
 United States exactly 100 years later, in 1972 and they<lb/>
 were enacted with amendments made by the Congress<lb/>
 to take effect on 01.07.1975. Yet, the Rules were found<lb/>
 inadequate to deal with emerging situations and hence,<lb/>
 several amendments were made, including the one<lb/>
 made in 2017 that incorporated specific provisions<lb/>
 relating to electronic records under subrules (13) and<lb/>
 (14) of FRE 902. After this amendment, a lot of options<lb/>
 have been made available to litigants seeking to rely<lb/>
 upon electronically stored information, one among<lb/>
 them being the route provided by subrules (13) and<lb/>
 (14) of FRE 902. This development of law in the US<lb/>
 demonstrates that, unlike in India, law has kept pace<lb/>
 with technology to a great extent.<lb/></p>

<p> 
 POSITION IN UK<lb/>
</p>

<p>30. As pointed out in the main opinion, Section 65B, in its<lb/>
 present form, is a poor reproduction of Section 5 of the<lb/>
 UK Civil Evidence Act, 1968. The language employed in<lb/>
 subsections (2), (3), (4) and (5) of Section 65B is<lb/>
 almost in pari materia (with minor differences) with<lb/>
 subsections (2) to (5) of Section 5 of the UK Civil<lb/>
 Evidence Act, 1968. However, subsection (1) of Section<lb/>
 65B is substantially different from subsection (1) of<lb/>
 Section 5 of the UK Civil Evidence Act, 1968. But it<lb/>
 also contains certain additional words in subsection<lb/>
 (1) namely &quot;without further proof or production of the<lb/>
 original&quot;. For easy comparison and appreciation, sub<lb/>
 section (1) of Section 65B of the Indian Evidence Act<lb/>
 and subsection (1) of Section 5 of UK Civil Evidence<lb/>
 Act, 1968 are presented in a tabular form as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>Section 65B(1), Indian<lb/>
 Evidence Act, 1872<lb/>
 Section 5(1), Civil Evidence<lb/>
 Act, 1968 [UK]<lb/>
</item>

<item>Notwithstanding<lb/>
 anything<lb/>
 contained in this Act, any<lb/>
 information contained in an<lb/>
 In any civil proceedings a<lb/>
 statement<lb/>
 contained<lb/>
 in<lb/>
 a<lb/>
 document<lb/>
 produced<lb/>
 by<lb/>
 a<lb/>
 electronic record which is printed<lb/>
 on a paper, stored, recorded or<lb/>
 copied in optical or magnetic<lb/>
 media produced by a computer<lb/>
 (hereinafter referred to as the<lb/>
 computer<lb/>
 output)<lb/>
 shall<lb/>
 be<lb/>
 deemed to be also a document, if<lb/>
 the conditions mentioned in this<lb/>
 section are satisfied in relation to<lb/>
 the information and computer in<lb/>
 question and shall be admissible<lb/>
 in any proceedings, without<lb/>
 further proof or production of the<lb/>
 original, as evidence of any<lb/>
 contents of the original or of any<lb/>
 fact stated therein of which direct<lb/>
 evidence would be admissible.<lb/>
 computer shall, subject to rules of<lb/>
 court, be admissible as evidence<lb/>
 of any fact stated therein of<lb/>
 which direct oral evidence would<lb/>
 be admissible, if it is shown that<lb/>
 the conditions mentioned in<lb/>
 subsection (2) below are satisfied<lb/>
 in relation to the statement and<lb/>
 computer in question.<lb/>
</item>

<p>31. But the abovementioned Section 5 of the U.K. Act of<lb/>
 1968 was repealed by the Civil Evidence Act, 1995.<lb/>
 Section 15(2) of the Civil Evidence Act, 1995 repealed<lb/>
 the enactments specified in Schedule II therein. Under<lb/>
 Schedule II of the 1995 Act, Part I of the 1968 Act<lb/>
 containing Sections 110 were repealed. The effect is<lb/>
 that when Section 65B was incorporated in the Indian<lb/>
 Evidence Act, by Act 21 of 2000, by copying sub<lb/>
 sections (2) to (5) of Section 5 of the UK Civil Evidence<lb/>
 Act, 1968, Section 5 itself was not there in the U.K.<lb/>
 statute book, as a result of its repeal under the 1995<lb/>
 Act.<lb/>
</p>

<p>32. The repeal of Section 5 under the 1995 Act was a<lb/>
 sequel to the recommendations made by the Law<lb/>
 Commission in September 1993. Part III of the Law<lb/>
 Commission&apos;s report titled &apos;The Hearsay Rule in Civil<lb/>
 Proceedings&apos; noted the problems with the 1968 Act, one<lb/>
 of which concerned computer records. Paragraphs 3.14<lb/>
 to 3.21 in Part III of the Law Commission&apos;s report read<lb/>
 as follows:<lb/>
 Computer records<lb/>
</p>

<item>3.14 A fundamental mistrust and fear of the<lb/>
 potential for error or mechanical failure can be<lb/>
 detected in the elaborate precautions governing<lb/>
 computer records in section 5 of the 1968 Act.<lb/>
 The Law Reform Committee had not<lb/>
 recommended special provisions for such<lb/>
 records, and section 5 would appear to<lb/>
 have been something of an afterthought<lb/>
 with its many safeguards inserted in order<lb/>
 to gain acceptance of what was then a<lb/>
 novel form of evidence. Twentyfive years<lb/>
 later, technology has developed to an extent<lb/>
 where computers and computergenerated<lb/>
 documents are relied on in every area of<lb/>
 business and have long been accepted in<lb/>
 banking and other important recordkeeping<lb/>
 fields. The conditions have been widely<lb/>
 criticised, and it has been said that they<lb/>
 are aimed at operations based on the type<lb/>
 of mainframe operations common in the<lb/>
 mid 1960s, which were primarily intended<lb/>
 to process in batches thousands of similar<lb/>
 transactions on a daily basis.<lb/>
</item>

<item>3.15 So far as the statutory conditions are<lb/>
 concerned, there is a heavy reliance on the<lb/>
 need to prove that the document has been<lb/>
 produced in the normal course of business and<lb/>
 in an uninterrupted course of activity. It is at<lb/>
 least<lb/>
 questionable<lb/>
 whether<lb/>
 these<lb/>
 requirements provide any real safeguards<lb/>
 in relation to the reliability of the<lb/>
 hardware or software concerned. In<lb/>
 addition, they are capable of operating to<lb/>
 exclude wide categories of documents,<lb/>
 particularly those which are produced as the<lb/>
 result of an original or a &quot;one off&quot; piece of work.<lb/>
 Furthermore, they provide no protection against<lb/>
 the inaccurate inputting of data.<lb/>
</item>

<item>3.16 We have already referred to the overlap<lb/>
 between sections 4 and 5. If compliance with<lb/>
 section 5 is a prerequisite, then computer<lb/>
 generated<lb/>
 documents<lb/>
 which<lb/>
 pass<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 conditions setout in section 5(2) &quot;shall&quot; be<lb/>
 admissible, notwithstanding the fact that they<lb/>
 originated from a chain of human sources and<lb/>
 that it has not been established that the<lb/>
 persons in the chain acted under a duty. In<lb/>
 other words, the record provisions of section 4,<lb/>
 which exist to ensure the reliability of the core<lb/>
 information, are capable of being disapplied. In<lb/>
 the context of our proposed reforms, we do not<lb/>
 consider that this apparent discrepancy is of<lb/>
 any significance, save that it illustrates the fact<lb/>
 that section 5 was something of an<lb/>
 afterthought.<lb/>
</item>

<item>3.17 Computergenerated evidence falls<lb/>
 into two categories. First, there is the<lb/>
 situation envisaged by the 1968 Act,<lb/>
 where the computer is used to file and<lb/>
 store information provided to it by human<lb/>
 beings. Second, there is the case where the<lb/>
 record has itself been produced by the<lb/>
 computer, sometimes entirely by itself but<lb/>
 possibly with the involvement of some other<lb/>
 machine. Examples of this situation are<lb/>
 computers which are fed information by<lb/>
 monitoring devices. A particular example is<lb/>
 automatic stock control systems, which are<lb/>
 now in common use and which allow for<lb/>
 purchase orders to be automatically produced.<lb/>
 Under such systems evidence of contract<lb/>
 formation will lie solely in the electronic<lb/>
 messages automatically generated by the<lb/>
 seller&apos;s and buyer&apos;s computers. It is easy to<lb/>
 see how uncertainty as to how the courts<lb/>
 may deal with the proof and enforceability<lb/>
 of such contracts is likely to stifle the full<lb/>
 development and effective use of such<lb/>
 technology. Furthermore, uncertainty may<lb/>
 deter parties from agreeing that contracts made<lb/>
 in this way are to be governed by English law<lb/>
 and litigated in the English courts.<lb/>
</item>

<item>3.18 It is interesting to compare the technical<lb/>
 manner in which the admissibility of computer<lb/>
 generated records has developed, compared<lb/>
 with cases concerning other forms of<lb/>
 sophisticated<lb/>
 technologically<lb/>
 produced<lb/>
 118<lb/>
 evidence, for example radar records (See<lb/>
 Sapporo Maru (Owners) v. Statue of Liberty<lb/>
 (Owners) [1968] 1 W.L.R. 739). In the Statue of<lb/>
 Liberty case radar records, produced without<lb/>
 human involvement and reproduced in<lb/>
 photographic form, were held to be admissible<lb/>
 to establish how a collision of two ships had<lb/>
 occurred. It was held that this was &quot;real&quot;<lb/>
 evidence, no different in kind from a monitored<lb/>
 tape recording of a conversation. Furthermore,<lb/>
 in these cases, no extra tests of reliability need<lb/>
 be met and the common law rebuttable<lb/>
 presumption is applied, that the machine was<lb/>
 in order at the material time. The same<lb/>
 presumption has been applied to intoximeter<lb/>
 printouts (Castle v. Cross [1984] 1 W.L.R.<lb/>
 1372).<lb/>
</item>

<item>3.19 There are a number of cases which<lb/>
 establish the way in which courts have sought<lb/>
 to distinguish between types of computer<lb/>
 generated evidence, by finding in appropriate<lb/>
 cases that the special procedures are<lb/>
 inapplicable because the evidence is original or<lb/>
 direct evidence. As might be expected, case law<lb/>
 on computergenerated evidence is more likely<lb/>
 to be generated by criminal cases of theft or<lb/>
 fraud, where the incidence of such evidence is<lb/>
 high and the issue of admissibility is more<lb/>
 likely to be crucial to the outcome and hence<lb/>
 less liable to be agreed. For example, even in<lb/>
 the first category of cases, where human<lb/>
 involvement exists, a computergenerated<lb/>
 document may not be considered to be hearsay<lb/>
 if the computer has been used as a mere tool,<lb/>
 to produce calculations from data fed to it by<lb/>
 humans, no matter how complex the<lb/>
 calculations, or how difficult it may be for<lb/>
 119<lb/>
 humans to reproduce its work, provided the<lb/>
 computer was not &quot;contributing its own<lb/>
 knowledge&quot; (R v. Wood (1983) 76 Cr. App. R.<lb/>
 23).<lb/>
</item>

<p>3.20 There was no disagreement with the<lb/>
 view that the provisions relating to<lb/>
 computer records were outdated and that<lb/>
 there<lb/>
 was<lb/>
 no<lb/>
 good<lb/>
 reason<lb/>
 for<lb/>
 distinguishing between different forms of<lb/>
 record keeping or maintaining a different<lb/>
 regime for the admission of computer<lb/>
 generated documents. This is the position in<lb/>
 Scotland under the 1988 Act. Furthermore, we<lb/>
 were informed of fears that uncertainty over the<lb/>
 treatment of such records in civil litigation in<lb/>
 the United Kingdom was a significant<lb/>
 hindrance to commerce and needed reform.<lb/>
</p>

<p>3.21 Consultees considered that the real<lb/>
 issue for concern was authenticity that<lb/>
 this was a matter which was best dealt<lb/>
 with<lb/>
 by<lb/>
 a<lb/>
 vigilant<lb/>
 attitude<lb/>
 that<lb/>
 concentrated upon the weight to be<lb/>
 attached<lb/>
 to<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 evidence,<lb/>
 in<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 circumstances of the individual case,<lb/>
 rather than by reformulating complex and<lb/>
 inflexible conditions as to admissibility.<lb/>
</p>

<item>(emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</item>

<p>33. In Part IV of the 1993 Report, titled &apos;Recommendations<lb/>
 for Reform&apos;, Paragraph 4.43 dealt with the<lb/>
 recommendations of the Law Commission in relation to<lb/>
 computer records. Paragraph 4.43 of the Law<lb/>
 Commission&apos;s report along with Recommendation Nos.<lb/>
 13, 14 and 15 are reproduced for easy reference:<lb/>
</p>

<item>(b) Computerised records<lb/>
4.43 In the light of the criticisms of the present<lb/>
 provisions and the response on consultation,<lb/>
 we have decided to recommend that no special<lb/>
 provisions be made in respect of computerised<lb/>
 records. This is the position in Scotland under<lb/>
 the 1988 Act and reflects the overwhelming<lb/>
 view of commentators, practitioners and others.<lb/>
 That is not to say that we do not recognise that,<lb/>
 as familiarity with and confidence in the<lb/>
 inherent reliability of computers has grown, so<lb/>
 has concern over the potential for misuse,<lb/>
 through the capacity to hack, corrupt, or alter<lb/>
 information, in manner which is undetectable.<lb/>
 We do not underestimate these dangers.<lb/>
 However the current provisions of section 5 do<lb/>
 not afford any protection and it is not possible<lb/>
 to legislate protectively. Nothing in our<lb/>
 proposals will either encourage abuse, or<lb/>
 prevent a proper challenge to the admissibility<lb/>
 of computerised records, where abuse is<lb/>
 suspected. Security and authentication are<lb/>
 problems that experts in the field are constantly<lb/>
 addressing and it is a fast evolving area. The<lb/>
 responses from experts in this field, such as the<lb/>
 C.B.I., stressed that, whilst computergenerated<lb/>
 information should be treated similarly to other<lb/>
 records, such evidence should be weighed<lb/>
 according to its reliability, with parties being<lb/>
 encouraged to provide information as to the<lb/>
 security of their systems. We have proposed a<lb/>
 wide definition for the word &quot;document&quot;. This<lb/>
 will cover documents in any form and in<lb/>
 particular will be wide enough to cover<lb/>
 computergenerated information.<lb/>
 We therefore recommend that:<lb/>
</item>

<item>13. Documents, including those stored by<lb/>
 computer, which form part of the records<lb/>
 of a business or public authority should be<lb/>
 admissible as hearsay evidence under<lb/>
 clause 1 of our draft Bill and the ordinary<lb/>
 notice and weighing provisions should<lb/>
 apply.<lb/>
</item>

<item>14. The current provisions governing the<lb/>
 manner of proof of business records<lb/>
 should be replaced by a simpler regime<lb/>
 which allows, unless the court otherwise<lb/>
 directs, for a document to be taken to form<lb/>
 part of the records of a business or public<lb/>
 authority, if it is certified as such, and<lb/>
 received in evidence without being spoken<lb/>
 to in court. No special provisions should be<lb/>
 made in respect of the manner of proof of<lb/>
 computerized records.<lb/>
</item>

<item>15. The absence of an entry should be<lb/>
 capable of being formally proved by<lb/>
 affidavit of an officer of the business or<lb/>
 authority to which the records belong.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(emphasis in original)<lb/>
</item>

<p>34. The above recommendations of the Law Commission<lb/>
 (U.K.) made in 1993, led to the repeal of Section 5 of<lb/>
 the 1968 Act, under the 1995 Act. The rules of<lb/>
 evidence in civil cases, in so far as electronic records<lb/>
 are concerned, thus got liberated in U.K. in 1995 with<lb/>
 the repeal of Section 5 of the U.K. Civil Evidence<lb/>
 Act,1968.<lb/>
</p>

<p>35. But there is a separate enactment in the U.K.,<lb/>
 containing the rules of evidence in criminal<lb/>
 proceedings and that is the Police and Criminal<lb/>
 Evidence Act, 1984. Section 69 of the said Act laid<lb/>
 down rules for determining when a statement in a<lb/>
 document produced by a computer shall not be<lb/>
 admissible as evidence of any fact stated therein.<lb/>
 Section 69 of the said Act laid down three conditions<lb/>
 (there are too many negatives in the language employed<lb/>
 in Section 69). In simple terms, they require that it<lb/>
 must be shown (i) that there are no reasonable grounds<lb/>
 for believing that the statement is not inaccurate<lb/>
 because of improper use of the computer; (ii) that at all<lb/>
 material times the computer was operating properly<lb/>
 and (iii) that the additional conditions specified in the<lb/>
 rules made by the court are also satisfied.<lb/></p>
<p> 36. the abovementioned section 69 of the polics and<lb/> criminal evidences act,1984 (PACE) was replaced by<lb/>
 Section 60 of the Youth Justice and Criminal Evidence<lb/>
 Act, 1999. This repeal was also a sequel to the<lb/>
 recommendations made by the Law Commission in<lb/>
 June 1997 under its report titled &quot;Evidence in Criminal<lb/>
 Proceedings: Hearsay and Related Topics&quot;. Part 13 of<lb/>
 the Law Commission&apos;s Report dealt with computer<lb/>
 evidence in extenso. The problems with Section 69 of<lb/>
 the 1984 Act, the response during the Consultative<lb/>
 Process and the eventual recommendations of the U.K.<lb/>
 Law Commission are contained in paragraphs 13.1 to<lb/>
 13.23. They are usefully extracted as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<p>13.1 In Minors ([1989] 1 WLR 441, 443D-E.)<lb/>
 Steyn J summed up the major problem posed<lb/>
 for the rules of evidence by computer output:<lb/>
</p>

<item>Often the only record of the<lb/>
 transaction, which nobody can be<lb/>
 expected to remember, will be in the<lb/>
 memory of a computer… If computer<lb/>
 output cannot relatively readily be<lb/>
 used as evidence in criminal cases,<lb/>
 much crime (and notably offences<lb/>
 involving dishonesty) would in practice<lb/>
 be immune from prosecution. On the<lb/>
 124<lb/>
 other hand, computers are not<lb/>
 infallible.<lb/>
 They<lb/>
 do<lb/>
 occasionally<lb/>
 malfunction. Software systems often<lb/>
 have &quot;bugs&quot;. …Realistically, therefore,<lb/>
 computers must be regarded as<lb/>
 imperfect devices.<lb/>
</item>

<item>13.2 The legislature sought to deal with this<lb/>
 dilemma by section 69 of PACE, which imposes<lb/>
 important additional requirements that must be<lb/>
 satisfied before computer evidence is adduced<lb/>
 -whether it is hearsay or not (Shephard [1993]<lb/>
 AC 380).<lb/>
</item>

<item>13.3 In practice, a great deal of hearsay<lb/>
 evidence is held on computer, and so section 69<lb/>
 warrants careful attention. It must be examined<lb/>
 against the requirement that the use of<lb/>
 computer evidence should not be unnecessarily<lb/>
 impeded, while giving due weight to the<lb/>
 fallibility of computers.<lb/>
</item>

<item>PACE, SECTION 69<lb/>
</item>

<item>13.4 In the consultation paper we dealt in<lb/>
 detail with the requirements of section 69: in<lb/>
 essence it provides that a document produced<lb/>
 by a computer may not be adduced as evidence<lb/>
 of any fact stated in the document unless it is<lb/>
 shown that the computer was properly<lb/>
 operating and was not being improperly used.<lb/>
 If there is any dispute as to whether the<lb/>
 conditions in section 69 have been satisfied,<lb/>
 the court must hold a trial within the trial to<lb/>
 decide whether the party seeking to rely on the<lb/>
 document has established the foundation<lb/>
 requirements of section 69.<lb/>
 125<lb/>
</item>

<item>13.5 In essence, the party relying on computer<lb/>
 evidence must first prove that the computer is<lb/>
 reliable -or, if the evidence was generated by<lb/>
 more than one computer, that each of them is<lb/>
 reliable (Cochrane [1993] Crim LR 48). This<lb/>
 can be proved by tendering a written<lb/>
 certificate, or by calling oral evidence. It is<lb/>
 not possible for the party adducing the<lb/>
 computer evidence to rely on a presumption<lb/>
 that the computer is working correctly<lb/>
 (Shephard [1993] AC 380, 384E). It is also<lb/>
 necessary for the computer records themselves<lb/>
 to be produced to the court (Burr v DPP [1996]<lb/>
 Crim LR 324).<lb/>
</item>

<item>The problems with the present law<lb/>
</item>

<item>13.6 In the consultation paper we came to the<lb/>
 conclusion that the present law was<lb/>
 unsatisfactory, for five reasons.<lb/>
</item>

<item>13.7 First, section 69 fails to address the major<lb/>
 causes of inaccuracy in computer evidence. As<lb/>
 Professor Tapper has pointed out, &quot;most<lb/>
 computer error is either immediately detectable<lb/>
 or results from error in the data entered into the<lb/>
 machine&quot;.<lb/>
</item>

<p>13.8 Secondly, advances in computer<lb/>
 technology make it increasingly difficult<lb/>
 to comply with section 69: it is becoming<lb/>
 &quot;increasingly impractical to examine (and<lb/>
 therefore certify) all the intricacies of<lb/>
 computer operation&quot;. These problems existed<lb/>
 even before networking became common.<lb/>
</p>

<p>13.9 A third problem lies in the difficulties<lb/>
 confronting the recipient of a computer<lb/>
 produced document who wishes to tender it in<lb/>
evidence: the recipient may be in no position to<lb/>
 satisfy the court about the operation of the<lb/>
 computer. It may well be that the recipient&apos;s<lb/>
 opponent is better placed to do this.<lb/>
</item>

<item>13.10 Fourthly, it is illogical that section 69<lb/>
 applies where the document is tendered in<lb/>
 evidence (Shephard [1993] AC 380), but not<lb/>
 where it is used by an expert in arriving at his<lb/>
 or her conclusions (Golizadeh [1995] Crim LR<lb/>
 232), nor where a witness uses it to refresh his<lb/>
 or her memory (Sophocleous v Ringer [1988]<lb/>
RTR 52). If it is safe to admit evidence which<lb/>
 relies on and incorporates the output from the<lb/>
 computer, it is hard to see why that output<lb/>
 should not itself be admissible; and conversely,<lb/>
 if it is not safe to admit the output, it can hardly<lb/>
 be safe for a witness to rely on it.<lb/>
</item>

<item>13.11 At the time of the publication of the<lb/>
 consultation paper there was also a problem<lb/>
 arising from the interpretation of section 69. It<lb/>
 was held by the Divisional Court in McKeown v<lb/>
 DPP ([1995] Crim LR 69) that computer evidence<lb/>
 is inadmissible if it cannot be proved that the<lb/>
 computer was functioning properly -even<lb/>
 though the malfunctioning of the computer had<lb/>
 no effect on the accuracy of the material<lb/>
 produced. Thus, in that case, computer<lb/>
 evidence could not be relied on because there<lb/>
 was a malfunction in the clock part of an<lb/>
 Intoximeter machine, although it had no effect<lb/>
 on the accuracy of the material part of the<lb/>
 printout (the alcohol reading). On appeal, this<lb/>
 interpretation has now been rejected by the<lb/>
 House of Lords: only malfunctions that affect<lb/>
 the way in which a computer processes, stores<lb/>
 or retrieves the information used to generate<lb/>
 127<lb/>
 the statement are relevant to section 69 (DPP v<lb/>
 McKeown; DPP v Jones [1997] 1 WLR 295).<lb/>
</item>

<item>13.12 In coming to our conclusion that the<lb/>
 present law did not work satisfactorily, we<lb/>
 noted that in Scotland, some Australian<lb/>
 states, New Zealand, the United States<lb/>
 and Canada, there is no separate scheme<lb/>
 for computer evidence, and yet no<lb/>
 problems appear to arise. Our provisional<lb/>
 view was that section 69 fails to serve any<lb/>
 useful purpose, and that other systems operate<lb/>
 effectively and efficiently without it.<lb/>
</item>

<item>13.13 We provisionally proposed that section<lb/>
 69 of PACE be repealed without replacement.<lb/>
 Without section 69, a common law presumption<lb/>
 comes into play (Phipson, para 2314, approved<lb/>
 by the Divisional Court in Castle v Cross [1984]<lb/>
 1 WLR 1372, 1377B):<lb/>
 In the absence of evidence to the<lb/>
 contrary, the courts will presume that<lb/>
 mechanical instruments were in order<lb/>
 at the material time.<lb/>
</item>

<item>13.14 Where a party sought to rely on the<lb/>
 presumption, it would not need to lead evidence<lb/>
 that the computer was working properly on the<lb/>
 occasion in question unless there was evidence<lb/>
 that it may not have been -in which case the<lb/>
 party would have to prove that it was (beyond<lb/>
 reasonable doubt in the case of the prosecution,<lb/>
 and on the balance of probabilities in the case<lb/>
 of the defence). The principle has been applied<lb/>
 to such devices as speedometers (Nicholas v<lb/>
 Penny [1950] 2 KB 466) and traffic lights<lb/>
 (Tingle Jacobs &amp; Co v Kennedy [1964] 1 WLR<lb/>
 638), and in the consultation paper we saw no<lb/>
 reason why it should not apply to computers.<lb/>
</item>


<item> The response on consultation<lb/></item>

<item>
 13.15 On consultation, the vast majority of<lb/>
 those who dealt with this point agreed with us.<lb/>
 A number of those in favour said that<lb/>
 section 69 had caused much trouble with<lb/>
 little benefit.<lb/>
</item>

<item>13.16 The most cogent contrary argument<lb/>
 against our proposal came from David<lb/>
 Ormerod. In his helpful response, he contended<lb/>
 that the common law presumption of regularity<lb/>
 may not extend to cases in which computer<lb/>
 evidence is central. He cites the assertion of the<lb/>
 Privy Council in Dillon v R ([1982] AC 484) that<lb/>
 &quot;it is well established that the courts will not<lb/>
 presume the existence of facts which are<lb/>
 central to an offence&quot;. If this were literally true<lb/>
 it would be of great importance in cases where<lb/>
 computer evidence is central, such as<lb/>
 Intoximeter cases (R v Medway Magistrates&apos;<lb/>
 Court, ex p Goddard [1995] RTR 206). But such<lb/>
 evidence has often been permitted to satisfy a<lb/>
 central element of the prosecution case. Some<lb/>
 of these cases were decided before section 69<lb/>
 was introduced (Castle v Cross [1984] 1 WLR<lb/>
 1372); others have been decided since its<lb/>
 introduction, but on the assumption (now held<lb/>
 to be mistaken) (Shephard [1993] AC 380) that<lb/>
 it did not apply because the statement<lb/>
 produced by the computer was not hearsay<lb/>
 (Spiby (1990) 91 Cr App R 186; Neville [1991]<lb/>
 Crim LR 288). The presumption must have been<lb/>
 applicable; yet the argument successfully relied<lb/>
 upon in Dillon does not appear to have been<lb/>
 raised.<lb/>
</item>

<item>129<lb/>
 13.17 It should also be noted that Dillon was<lb/>
 concerned not with the presumption regarding<lb/>
 machines but with the presumption of the<lb/>
 regularity of official action. This latter<lb/>
 presumption was the analogy on which the<lb/>
 presumption for machines was originally<lb/>
 based; but it is not a particularly close analogy,<lb/>
 and the two presumptions are now clearly<lb/>
 distinct.<lb/>
</item>

<item>13.18 Even where the presumption applies, it<lb/>
 ceases to have any effect once evidence of<lb/>
 malfunction has been adduced. The question is,<lb/>
 what sort of evidence must the defence adduce,<lb/>
 and how realistic is it to suppose that the<lb/>
 defence will be able to adduce it without any<lb/>
 knowledge of the working of the machine? On<lb/>
 the one hand the concept of the evidential<lb/>
 burden is a flexible one: a party cannot be<lb/>
 required to produce more by way of evidence<lb/>
 than one in his or her position could be<lb/>
 expected to produce. It could therefore take<lb/>
 very little for the presumption to be rebutted, if<lb/>
 the party against whom the evidence was<lb/>
 adduced could not be expected to produce<lb/>
 more. For example, in Cracknell v Willis ([1988]<lb/>
 AC 450) the House of Lords held that a<lb/>
 defendant is entitled to challenge an<lb/>
 Intoximeter reading, in the absence of any<lb/>
 signs of malfunctioning in the machine itself, by<lb/>
 testifying (or calling others to testify) about the<lb/>
 amount of alcohol that he or she had drunk.<lb/>
</item>

<item>13.19 On the other hand it may be unrealistic<lb/>
 to suppose that in such circumstances the<lb/>
 presumption would not prevail. In Cracknell v<lb/>
 Willis Lord Griffiths ([1988] AC 450 at p 468C-<lb/>
D) said:<lb/>
</item>

<item>130<lb/>
 If Parliament wishes to provide that<lb/>
 either there is to be an irrebuttable<lb/>
 presumption that the breath testing<lb/>
 machine is reliable or that the<lb/>
 presumption can only be challenged by<lb/>
 a particular type of evidence then<lb/>
 Parliament<lb/>
 must<lb/>
 take<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 responsibility of so deciding and spell<lb/>
 out its intention in clear language.<lb/>
 Until then I would hold that evidence<lb/>
 which, if believed, provides material<lb/>
 from<lb/>
 which<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 inference<lb/>
 can<lb/>
 reasonably be drawn that the machine<lb/>
 was unreliable is admissible.<lb/></item>

<item> 
 But his Lordship went on:<lb/>
</item>

<item>I am myself hopeful that the good<lb/>
 sense of the magistrates and the<lb/>
 realisation by the motoring public that<lb/>
 approved breath testing machines are<lb/>
 proving reliable will combine to ensure<lb/>
 that few defendants will seek to<lb/>
 challenge a breath analysis by<lb/>
 spurious evidence of their consumption<lb/>
 of alcohol. The magistrates will<lb/>
 remember that the presumption of law<lb/>
 is that the machine is reliable and they<lb/>
 will no doubt look with a critical eye on<lb/>
 evidence such as was produced by<lb/>
 Hughes v McConnell ([1985] RTR 244)<lb/>
 before being persuaded that it is not<lb/>
 safe to rely upon the reading that it<lb/>
 produces ([1988] AC 450, 468D-E).<lb/>
</item>

<item>13.20 Lord Goff did not share Lord Griffiths&apos;<lb/>
 optimism that motorists would not seek to<lb/>
 challenge the analysis by spurious evidence of<lb/>
 131<lb/>
 their consumption of alcohol, but did share his<lb/>
 confidence in<lb/>
 the good sense of magistrates who,<lb/>
 with their attention drawn to the<lb/>
 safeguards for defendants built into<lb/>
 the Act …, will no doubt give proper<lb/>
 scrutiny to such defences, and will be<lb/>
 fully aware of the strength of the<lb/>
 evidence provided by a printout, taken<lb/>
 from an approved device, of a<lb/>
 specimen of breath provided in<lb/>
 accordance<lb/>
 with<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 statutory<lb/>
 procedure ([1988] AC 450 at p 472B-<lb/>
C).<lb/>
</item>

<item>13.21 These dicta may perhaps be read as<lb/>
 implying<lb/>
 that<lb/>
 evidence<lb/>
 which<lb/>
 merely<lb/>
 contradicts the reading, without directly casting<lb/>
 doubt on the reliability of the device, may be<lb/>
 technically admissible but should rarely be<lb/>
 permitted to succeed. However, it is significant<lb/>
 that Lord Goff referred in the passage quoted to<lb/>
 the safeguards for defendants which are built<lb/>
 into the legislation creating the drinkdriving<lb/>
 offences. In the case of other kinds of computer<lb/>
 evidence, where (apart from section 69) no such<lb/>
 statutory safeguards exist, we think that the<lb/>
 courts can be relied upon to apply the<lb/>
 presumption in such a way as to recognise the<lb/>
 difficulty faced by a defendant who seeks to<lb/>
 challenge the prosecution&apos;s evidence but is not<lb/>
 in a position to do so directly. The presumption<lb/>
 continues to apply to machines other than<lb/>
 computers (and until recently was applied to<lb/>
 nonhearsay statements by computers) without<lb/>
 the safeguard of section 69; and we are not<lb/>
 aware of any cases where it has caused<lb/>
 injustice because the evidential burden cast on<lb/>
 132<lb/>
 the defence was unduly onerous. Bearing in<lb/>
 mind that it is a creature of the common law,<lb/>
 and a comparatively modern one, we think it is<lb/>
 unlikely that it would be permitted to work<lb/>
 injustice.<lb/>
</item>

<item>13.22 Finally it should not be forgotten that<lb/>
 section 69 applies equally to computer evidence<lb/>
 adduced by the defence. A rule that prevents a<lb/>
 defendant from adducing relevant and cogent<lb/>
 evidence, merely because there is no positive<lb/>
 evidence that it is reliable, is in our view unfair.<lb/>
</item>

<item>Our recommendation<lb/>
 13.23 We are satisfied that section 69<lb/>
 serves no useful purpose. We are not<lb/>
 aware of any difficulties encountered in<lb/>
 those<lb/>
 jurisdictions<lb/>
 that<lb/>
 have<lb/>
 no<lb/>
 equivalent. We are satisfied that the<lb/>
 presumption of proper functioning would apply<lb/>
 to computers, thus throwing an evidential<lb/>
 burden on to the opposing party, but that that<lb/>
 burden would be interpreted in such a way as<lb/>
 to ensure that the presumption did not result in<lb/>
 a conviction merely because the defence had<lb/>
 failed to adduce evidence of malfunction which<lb/>
 it was in no position to adduce. We believe, as<lb/>
 did the vast majority of our respondents, that<lb/>
 such a regime would work fairly. We<lb/>
 recommend the repeal of section 69 of<lb/>
 PACE. (Recommendation 50)<lb/>
</item>

<item>(emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</item>

<p>37. Based on the above recommendations of the U.K. Law<lb/>
 Commission, Section 69 of the PACE, 1984, was<lb/>
 declared by Section 60 of the Youth Justice and<lb/>
 Criminal Evidence Act, 1999, to have ceased to have<lb/>
 effect. Section 60 of the 1999 Act reads as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;Section 69 of the Police and Criminal Evidence<lb/>
 Act, 1984 (evidence from computer records<lb/>
 inadmissible unless conditions relating to<lb/>
 proper use and operation of computer shown to<lb/>
 be satisfied) shall cease to have effect&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>38. It will be clear from the above discussion that when our<lb/>
 lawmakers passed the Information Technology Bill in<lb/>
 the year 2000, adopting the language of Section 5 of<lb/>
 the UK Civil Evidence Act, 1968 to a great extent, the<lb/>
 said provision had already been repealed by the UK<lb/>
 Civil Evidence Act, 1995 and even the Police and<lb/>
 Criminal Evidence Act, 1984 was revamped by the<lb/>
 1999 Act to permit hearsay evidence, by repealing<lb/>
 Section 69 of PACE, 1984.<lb/></p>
<p> 
 POSITION IN CANADA<lb/>
</p>

<p>39. Pursuant to a proposal mooted by the Canadian Bar<lb/>
 Association hundred years ago, requesting all<lb/>
 Provincial Governments to provide for the appointment<lb/>
 of Commissioners to attend conferences organised for<lb/>
 the purpose of promoting uniformity of legislation<lb/>
 among the provinces, a meeting of the Commissioners<lb/>
 took place in Montreal in 1918. In the said meeting, a<lb/>
 Conference of Commissioners on Uniformity of Laws<lb/>
 throughout Canada was organised. In 1974, its name<lb/>
 was changed to Uniform Law Conference of Canada.<lb/>
 The objective of the Conference is primarily to achieve<lb/>
 uniformity in subjects covered by existing legislations.<lb/>
 The said Conference recommended a model law on<lb/>
 Uniform Electronic Evidence in September 1998.<lb/>
</p>

<p>40. The above recommendations of the Uniform Law<lb/>
 Conference later took shape in the form of<lb/>
 amendments to the Canada Evidence Act, 1985.<lb/>
 Section 31.1 of the said Act deals with authentication<lb/>
 of electronic documents and it reads as follows:<lb/></p>

<item> 
 Authentication of electronic documents<lb/></item>
<item> 
 31.1 Any person seeking to admit an electronic<lb/>
 document as evidence has the burden of<lb/>
 proving its authenticity by evidence capable of<lb/>
 135<lb/>
 supporting a finding that the electronic<lb/>
 document is that which it is purported to be.<lb/>
</item>

<p>41. Section 31.2 deals with the application of &apos;best<lb/>
 evidence rule&apos; in relation to electronic documents and it<lb/>
 reads as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>Application of best evidence rule -<lb/>
electronic documents<lb/></item>

<item>
 31.2(1) The best evidence rule in respect of an<lb/>
 electronic document is satisfied<lb/>
</item>

<item>(a) on proof of the integrity of the electronic<lb/>
 documents system by or in which the electronic<lb/>
 document was recorded or stored; or<lb/>
</item>

<item>(b) if an evidentiary presumption established<lb/>
 under section 31.4 applies.<lb/></item>

<item> 
 Printouts<lb/>
</item>

<item>(2) Despite subsection (1), in the absence of<lb/>
 evidence to the contrary, an electronic<lb/>
 document in the form of a printout satisfies the<lb/>
 best evidence rule if the printout has been<lb/>
 manifestly or consistently acted on, relied on or<lb/>
 used as a record of the information recorded or<lb/>
 stored in the printout.<lb/>
</item>

<p>42. Section 31.3 indicates the method of proving the<lb/>
 integrity of an electronic documents system, by or in<lb/>
 which an electronic document is recorded or stored.<lb/>
 Section 31.3 reads as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<p>136<lb/>
</p>

<item>Presumption of integrity<lb/>
 31.3 For the purposes of subsection 31.2(1), in<lb/>
 the absence of evidence to the contrary, the<lb/>
 integrity of an electronic documents system<lb/>
 by or in which an electronic document is<lb/>
 recorded or stored is proven<lb/>
</item>

<item>(a) by evidence capable of supporting a finding<lb/>
 that at all material times the computer system<lb/>
 or other similar device used by the electronic<lb/>
 documents system was operating properly or,<lb/>
 if it was not, the fact of its not operating<lb/>
 properly did not affect the integrity of the<lb/>
 electronic document and there are no other<lb/>
 reasonable grounds to doubt the integrity of the<lb/>
 electronic documents system;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(b) if it is established that the electronic<lb/>
 document was recorded or stored by a party<lb/>
 who is adverse in interest to the party seeking<lb/>
 to introduce it; or<lb/>
</item>

<item>(c) if it is established that the electronic<lb/>
 document was recorded or stored in the<lb/>
 usual and ordinary course of business by a<lb/>
 person who is not a party and who did not<lb/>
 record or store it under the control of the party<lb/>
 seeking to introduce it.<lb/>
</item>

<p>43. Section 31.5 is an interesting provision which permits<lb/>
 evidence to be presented in respect of any<lb/>
 standard, procedure, usage or practice concerning<lb/>
 the manner in which electronic documents are to<lb/>
 be recorded or stored. This is for the purpose of<lb/>
 determining under any rule of law whether an<lb/>
 electronic document is admissible. Section 31.5 reads<lb/>
 as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>Standards may be considered<lb/></item>

<item>
 31.5 For the purpose of determining under any<lb/>
 rule of law whether an electronic document is<lb/>
 admissible, evidence may be presented in<lb/>
 respect of any standard, procedure, usage or<lb/>
 practice concerning the manner in which<lb/>
 electronic documents are to be recorded or<lb/>
 stored, having regard to the type of business,<lb/>
 enterprise or endeavour that used, recorded or<lb/>
 stored the electronic document and the nature<lb/>
 and purpose of the electronic document.<lb/>
</item>

<p>44. Under Section 31.6(1), matters covered by Section<lb/>
 31.2(2), namely the printout of an electronic document,<lb/>
 the matters covered by Section 31.3, namely the<lb/>
 integrity of an electronic documents system, and<lb/>
 matters covered by Section 31.5, namely evidence in<lb/>
 respect of any standard, procedure, usage or practice,<lb/>
 may be established by affidavit. Section 31.6 reads as<lb/>
 follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>Proof by affidavit<lb/>
 138<lb/>
</item>

<p>31.6(1) The matters referred to in subsection<lb/>
 31.2(2) and sections 31.3 and 31.5 and in<lb/>
 regulations made under section 31.4 may be<lb/>
 established by affidavit.<lb/></item>

<item> 
 Crossexamination<lb/>
</p>

<item>(2) A party may crossexamine a deponent of<lb/>
 an affidavit referred to in subsection (1) that<lb/>
 has been introduced in evidence<lb/>
</item>

<item>(a) as of right, if the deponent is an adverse<lb/>
 party or is under the control of an adverse<lb/>
 party; and<lb/>
</item>

<item>(b) with leave of the court, in the case of any<lb/>
 other deponent.<lb/>
</item>

<p>45. Though a combined reading of Sections 31.3 and<lb/>
 31.6(1) of the Canada Evidence Act, 1985, gives an<lb/>
 impression as though a requirement similar to the one<lb/>
 under Section 65B of Indian Evidence Act, 1872 also<lb/>
 finds a place in the Canadian law, there is a very<lb/>
 important distinction found in the Canadian law.<lb/>
 Section 31.3(b) takes care of a contingency where<lb/>
 the electronic document was recorded or stored by<lb/>
 a party who is adverse in interest to the party<lb/>
 seeking to produce it. Similarly, Section 31.3(c)<lb/>
 gives leverage for the party relying upon an<lb/>
 electronic document to establish that the same<lb/>
 was recorded or stored in the usual and ordinary<lb/>
 course of business by a person who is not a party<lb/>
 and who did not record or store it under the<lb/>
 control of the party seeking to introduce it.<lb/>
</p>

<p>IV. Conclusion<lb/>
</p>

<p>46. It will be clear from the above discussion that the<lb/>
 major jurisdictions of the world have come to terms<lb/>
 with the change of times and the development of<lb/>
 technology and finetuned their legislations. Therefore,<lb/>
 it is the need of the hour that there is a relook at<lb/>
 Section 65B of the Indian Evidence Act, introduced 20<lb/>
 years ago, by Act 21 of 2000, and which has created a<lb/>
 huge judicial turmoil, with the law swinging from one<lb/>
 extreme to the other in the past 15 years from Navjot<lb/>
 sandhu to anvar to tomaso bruno to<lb/> sonu to shafhi mohammad</p>

<p> 47. with the above , I respectfully agree with <lb/>
conclusions reached by R>F> Nariman J that the <lb/>
appeals are to be dismissed with costs as proposed<lb/>
....................... J <lb/> ( V. RAMASUBRANIAN)<lb/>
July 14, 2020<lb/>NEW DELHI </p> 


</text>
</tei>
