<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<head>
			J U D G M E N T
			<lb />
			RANJAN GOGOI, J
			<lb />
		</head>

		<p>
			1.
			<lb />
			Leave granted in Special Leave Petition (Civil) No.36324 of
			<lb />
			2017
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			In State of Uttaranchal vs. Sandeep Kumar Singh and others 1
			<lb />
			[Civil Appeal No.4494 of 2006) the following question arose for
			<lb />
			consideration of this Court:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;Whether a person belonging to a Scheduled Caste
			<lb />
			in relation to a particular State would be entitled or
			<lb />
			not, to the benefits or concessions allowed to
			<lb />
			1 (2010) 12 SCC 794
			<lb />
			Digitally signed by
			<lb />
			VINOD LAKHINA
			<lb />
			Date: 2018.09.04
			<lb />
			15:12:44 IST
			<lb />
			Reason:
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Scheduled Caste candidate in the matter of
			<lb />
			employment, in any other State?&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			In the course of the deliberations that took place this Court
			<lb />
			noticed the Constitution Bench judgments of this Court in Marri
			<lb />
			Chandra Shekhar Rao vs. Dean, Seth G.S. Medical College and others 2
			<lb />
			and Action Committee on Issue of Caste Certificate to Scheduled Castes
			<lb />
			and Scheduled Tribes in the State of Maharashtra and another vs.
			<lb />
			Union of India and another 3 . The view of a three Judge Bench of this
			<lb />
			Court in S. Pushpa and others vs. Sivachanmugavelu and others 4 was
			<lb />
			also noticed and the same was perceived to be somewhat contrary to
			<lb />
			the view expressed by the Constitution Bench in the above two cases.
			<lb />
			This Court also took note of the fact that a two judge Bench of this
			<lb />
			Court in Subhash Chandra and another vs. Delhi Subordinate Services
			<lb />
			Selection Board and others 5 held that the dicta in S. Pushpa (supra) is
			<lb />
			an obiter and does not lay down any binding ratio. The Bench hearing
			<lb />
			the case i.e. State of Uttaranchal vs. Sandeep Kumar Singh and others
			<lb />
			(supra) took the view that &quot;it was not open to a two judge Bench to
			<lb />
			say that the decision of a three judge Bench rendered following
			<lb />
			the Constitution Bench judgments to be per incuriam&quot;. In this
			<lb />
			regard, the canons of judicial discipline carved out by this Court in
			<lb />
			Central Board of Dawoodi Bohra Community and another vs. State of
			<lb />
			Maharashtra and another 6 were recalled and eventually in paragraph
			<lb />
			13 of the opinion rendered in State of Uttaranchal vs. Sandeep Kumar
			<lb />
			Singh and others (supra) the reference of the question noted below
			<lb />
			was made to a larger Bench:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;13. A very important question of law as to
			<lb />
			interpretation of Articles 16(4), 341 and 342 arises
			<lb />
			for consideration in this appeal. Whether the
			<lb />
			Presidential Order issued under Article 341(1) or
			<lb />
			Article 342(1) of the Constitution has any bearing
			<lb />
			on the State&apos;s action in making provision for the
			<lb />
			reservation of appointments or posts in favour of
			<lb />
			any Backward Class of citizens which, in the
			<lb />
			opinion of the State, is not adequately represented
			<lb />
			in the services under the State? The extent and
			<lb />
			nature of interplay and interaction among Articles
			<lb />
			16(4), 341(1) and 342(1) of the Constitution is
			<lb />
			required to be resolved.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			The said Civil Appeal No.4494 of 2006 (State of Uttaranchal
			<lb />
			vs. Sandeep Kumar Singh and others) was disposed of by the larger
			<lb />
			Bench of this Court by order dated 6 th August, 2014, in the light of the
			<lb />
			findings of the High Court recorded in paragraph 4 of the High Court
			<lb />
			order to the effect that the order impugned suffers from an apparent
			<lb />
			illegality as the appointing authority of the petitioner therein is the
			<lb />
			University and the University had acted at the dictate of the State
			<lb />
			Government, which has no power to ask for cancellation of an
			<lb />
			appointment made in accordance with the advertisement. In the
			<lb />
			aforesaid order dated 6 th August, 2014 this Court took the view that
			<lb />
			the conclusions recorded in paragraph 4 of the High Court order
			<lb />
			cannot be said to be legally flawed and accordingly closed the said
			<lb />
			Civil Appeal (No. 4494 of 2006) on the aforesaid basis. The question
			<lb />
			referred was not answered.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			However, the question arising and referred to in the State of
			<lb />
			Uttaranchal vs. Sandeep Kumar Singh and others (supra) was felt to be
			<lb />
			surviving and subsisting in the present appeals also. Accordingly, by
			<lb />
			an order of the Court dated 7 th August, 2014, the very same question
			<lb />
			as formulated in paragraph 13 of the judgment in State of Uttaranchal
			<lb />
			vs. Sandeep Kumar Singh and others (supra), as extracted above, has
			<lb />
			been referred for an answer by a five judge Bench of this Court. That
			<lb />
			is how we are in seisin of the matters.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			The factual matrix need not detain us and a brief resume
			<lb />
			will suffice.
			<lb />
			The question as to whether a policy in furtherance of the
			<lb />
			enabling provision contained in Article 16(4) of the Constitution of
			<lb />
			India could extend to giving of benefits beyond the Scheduled Castes
			<lb />
			and Scheduled Tribes of a State/Union Territory enumerated in the
			<lb />
			Presidential Orders framed/issued under Articles 341 and 342 of the
			<lb />
			Constitution of India had arisen in the bunch of writ petitions filed
			<lb />
			before the High Court of Delhi against the order/orders of the Central
			<lb />
			Administrative Tribunal.
			<lb />
			The learned Tribunal following Marri
			<lb />
			Chandra Shekhar Rao (supra) and Action Committee (supra), in
			<lb />
			preference to the view expressed in S. Pushpa (supra) (three judge
			<lb />
			Bench) held that insofar as the Union Territory of Delhi is concerned,
			<lb />
			a migrant Scheduled Caste person would not be entitled to the
			<lb />
			benefits conferred on members of the Scheduled Castes enumerated in
			<lb />
			the list for the Union Territory of Delhi by the Presidential Order (i.e.
			<lb />
			the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes Lists (Modification) Order,
			<lb />
			1956) in question. The Delhi High Court sitting in a Full Bench
			<lb />
			(perhaps in view of the importance of the question) found the decision
			<lb />
			in S. Pushpa (supra) to be more directly relatable to the issue at hand
			<lb />
			i.e. being one of services in the Union Territory and, therefore, felt to
			<lb />
			be bound by the decision of the three judge Bench of this Court in S.
			<lb />
			Pushpa (supra). While doing so, the Delhi High court in paragraph 66
			<lb />
			of the judgment emphasised on the necessity of an authoritative
			<lb />
			pronouncement on the issue(s) arising. Accordingly, certificate to
			<lb />
			appeal under Article 134A of the Constitution was granted by the
			<lb />
			High Court. Paragraph 66 of the judgment of the Full Bench of the
			<lb />
			Delhi High Court will require a specific notice and is, therefore,
			<lb />
			reproduced below:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;66. This court summarizes its conclusions, as
			<lb />
			follows: (1) The decisions in Marri, Action
			<lb />
			Committee, Milind and Channaiah have all ruled
			<lb />
			that scheduled caste and tribe citizens moving from
			<lb />
			one State to another cannot claim reservation
			<lb />
			benefits, whether or not their caste is notified in the
			<lb />
			state where they migrate to, since the exercise of
			<lb />
			notifying scheduled castes or tribes is region (state)
			<lb />
			specific, i.e &quot; in relation&quot; to the state of their origin.
			<lb />
			These judgments also took note of the Presidential
			<lb />
			Notifications, which had enjoined such citizens to
			<lb />
			be &quot;residents&quot; in relation to the state which
			<lb />
			provided for such reservations.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(2) The considerations which apply to Scheduled
			<lb />
			Caste and Tribe citizens who migrate from state to
			<lb />
			state, apply equally in respect of those who migrate
			<lb />
			from a state to a union territory, in view of the text
			<lb />
			of Articles 341 (1) and 342 (1), i.e. only those castes
			<lb />
			and tribes who are notified in relation to the
			<lb />
			concerned Union Territory, are entitled to such
			<lb />
			benefits. This is reinforced by the Presidential
			<lb />
			Notification in relation to Union Territories, of 1951.
			<lb />
			Only Parliament can add to such notification, and
			<lb />
			include other castes, or tribes, in view of Articles
			<lb />
			341 (2), Article 342(2) which is also reinforced
			<lb />
			by Article 16(3). States cannot legislate on this
			<lb />
			aspect; nor can the executive Union or state, add
			<lb />
			to or alter the castes, or tribes in any notification in
			<lb />
			relation to a state or Union Territory, either through
			<lb />
			state legislation or through policies or circulars.
			<lb />
			Differentiation between residents of states, who
			<lb />
			migrate to states, and residents of states who
			<lb />
			migrate to Union Territories would result in
			<lb />
			invidious discrimination and overclassification
			<lb />
			thus denying equal access to reservation benefits,
			<lb />
			to those who are residents of Union Territories, and
			<lb />
			whose castes or tribes are included in the
			<lb />
			Presidential Order in respect of such Union
			<lb />
			Territories. The Pushpa interpretation has led to
			<lb />
			peculiar consequences, whereby:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(i) The resident of a state, belonging to a scheduled
			<lb />
			caste, notified in that state, cannot claim
			<lb />
			reservation benefit, if he takes up residence in
			<lb />
			another state, whether or not his caste is included
			<lb />
			in the latter State&apos;s list of scheduled castes;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii) However, the resident of a state who moves to a
			<lb />
			Union Territory would be entitled to carry his
			<lb />
			reservation benefit, and status as member of
			<lb />
			scheduled caste, even if his caste is not included as
			<lb />
			a scheduled caste, for that Union Territory;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) The resident of a Union Territory would
			<lb />
			however, be denied the benefit of reservation, if he
			<lb />
			moves to a State, because he is not a resident
			<lb />
			scheduled caste of that State.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iv) The resident of a Union Territory which later
			<lb />
			becomes a State, however, can insist that after
			<lb />
			such event, residents of other states, whose castes
			<lb />
			may or may not be notified, as scheduled castes,
			<lb />
			cannot be treated as such members in such newly
			<lb />
			formed states;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(v) Conversely, the scheduled caste resident of a
			<lb />
			state which is converted into a Union Territory,
			<lb />
			cannot protest against the treatment of scheduled
			<lb />
			caste residents of other states as members of
			<lb />
			scheduled caste of the Union Territory, even though
			<lb />
			their castes are not included in the list of such
			<lb />
			castes, for the Union Territory.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(3) The ruling in Pushpa is clear that if the resident
			<lb />
			of a state, whose caste is notified as Scheduled
			<lb />
			caste or scheduled tribe, moves to a Union
			<lb />
			Territory, he carries with him the right to claim that
			<lb />
			benefit, in relation to the Union Territory, even
			<lb />
			though if he moves to another state, he is denied
			<lb />
			such benefit (as a result of the rulings in Marri and
			<lb />
			Action Committee). The ruling in Pushpa, being
			<lb />
			specific about this aspect visàvis Union
			<lb />
			Territories, is binding; it was rendered by a Bench
			<lb />
			of three judges. (4) The later ruling in Subhash
			<lb />
			Chandra doubted the judgment in Pushpa, holding
			<lb />
			that it did not appreciate the earlier larger Bench
			<lb />
			judgments in the correct perspective. Yet, Subhash
			<lb />
			Chandra cannot be said to have overruled Pushpa,
			<lb />
			since it was rendered by a smaller Bench of two
			<lb />
			judges. This approach of Subhash Chandra has
			<lb />
			been doubted, and the question as to the correct
			<lb />
			view has been referred to a Constitution Bench in
			<lb />
			the State of Uttaranchal case.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(5) By virtue of the specific ruling applicable in the
			<lb />
			case of Union Territories, in Pushpa, whatever may
			<lb />
			be the doubts entertained as to the soundness of its
			<lb />
			reasoning, the High Courts have to apply its ratio,
			<lb />
			as it is by a formation of three judges; the said
			<lb />
			decision did notice the earlier judgments in Marri
			<lb />
			and Action Committee. Article 141 and the
			<lb />
			discipline enjoined by the doctrine of precedent
			<lb />
			compels this Court to follow the Pushpa ruling.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(6) In matters pertaining to incidence of
			<lb />
			employment, such as seniority, promotion and
			<lb />
			accelerated seniority or promotional benefits,
			<lb />
			flowing out of Articles 16 (4A) and (4B) of the
			<lb />
			Constitution, there may be need for clarity,
			<lb />
			whichever rule is ultimately preferred i.e the
			<lb />
			Pushpa view or the Marri and Action Committee
			<lb />
			view. In such event, it may be necessary for the
			<lb />
			guidance of decision makers and High Courts, to
			<lb />
			spell out whether the correct view should be applied
			<lb />
			prospectively. Furthermore, it may be also
			<lb />
			necessary to clarify what would be meant by
			<lb />
			prospective application of the correct rule, and
			<lb />
			whether such employment benefits flowing after
			<lb />
			recruitment, would be altered if the Marri view is to
			<lb />
			be preferred.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			Civil Appeal Nos.99359937 of 2014 from the decision of the
			<lb />
			Calcutta High court pertain to claims made by persons belonging to
			<lb />
			Uraons and Mundas members of the Scheduled Tribes communities
			<lb />
			who have migrated to the Union Territory of Andaman &amp; Nicobar
			<lb />
			Island. The High Court rejected the claim of reservation made by the
			<lb />
			aforesaid migrants Scheduled Tribes communities confining such
			<lb />
			benefits to the Scheduled Castes communities enumerated in the list
			<lb />
			appearing in the Presidential Order pertaining to the Union Territory
			<lb />
			of Andaman &amp; Nicobar Island.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			Before delving into the constitutional provisions which
			<lb />
			would be necessary to be dealt with for answering the reference a brief
			<lb />
			look at the preconstitutional position on the issue would throw
			<lb />
			considerable light and provide a sound insight to the multifaceted
			<lb />
			questions that the reference has given rise to.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			The caste system in India, which is the bane of a just social
			<lb />
			order, has a long history which can be traced to the earliest times.
			<lb />
			Ancient Hindu religious scriptures refer to the practice. Division of
			<lb />
			Society based on birth and the calling/profession of a person has
			<lb />
			continued to dominate Hindu thinking and way of life and is perhaps
			<lb />
			one of the thorny problems inherited by the British Administration
			<lb />
			which had tried to resolve the same by giving legal recognition to what
			<lb />
			came to be termed as the &quot;depressed classes&quot;. Such recognition was
			<lb />
			in the form of a protective regime which extended to representation in
			<lb />
			the Legislature and in the services under the State. Exercises in
			<lb />
			finding out the numerical strength of the depressed class in the early
			<lb />
			20 th Century (By Southborough Committee) revealed a grim picture
			<lb />
			indicating such number to be as high as 20 per cent of the majority
			<lb />
			population (Hindu) in eight (08) Indian Provinces of Madras, Bombay,
			<lb />
			Bengal, United Provinces, Punjab, Bihar and Orissa, Central Provinces
			<lb />
			and Assam. The above figure did not include primitive or aboriginal
			<lb />
			tribes who later came to be known as the Scheduled Tribes and
			<lb />
			included in the list of Scheduled Tribes under the different
			<lb />
			Presidential Orders issued from time to time.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			10.
			<lb />
			The Government of India Act, 1935 (hereinafter referred to
			<lb />
			as &quot;1935 Act&quot;) (also referred to as &quot;the Constitution Act&quot;) brought into
			<lb />
			force the expression &quot;Scheduled Castes&quot; for the first time in Indian
			<lb />
			Constitutional history. Entry 26 Part I of the First Schedule to the
			<lb />
			1935 Act stipulates that &quot;the Scheduled Castes mean such castes,
			<lb />
			races or tribes or parts of or groups within the castes, races or
			<lb />
			tribes, being castes, races, tribes, parts or groups, which appear
			<lb />
			to His Majesty in Council to correspond to the classes of persons
			<lb />
			formerly known as &apos;the depressed classes&apos;, as His Majesty in
			<lb />
			Council may specify&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			11.
			<lb />
			Thereafter a Gazette Notification was published on 6 th June,
			<lb />
			1936 promulgating the Government of India (Scheduled Castes) Order,
			<lb />
			1936 notifying the list of castes that are to be considered as &quot;the
			<lb />
			Scheduled Castes&quot; across the territory of India.
			<lb />
			A look at the
			<lb />
			Schedule which consisted of nine (09) parts i.e. Madras, Bombay,
			<lb />
			Bengal, United Provinces, Punjab, Bihar, Central Provinces, Assam,
			<lb />
			Orissa would indicate that identification of the different castes for
			<lb />
			inclusion as Scheduled Castes in the Schedule to the 1935 Act was
			<lb />
			based on an elaborate exercise conducted for each of the Provinces so
			<lb />
			much so that while some castes have been identified as Scheduled
			<lb />
			Castes throughout a Province, others have been so identified to limited
			<lb />
			areas within a province. The post constitutional exercise by the
			<lb />
			Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order, 1950 and the Constitution
			<lb />
			(Scheduled Tribes) Order, 1950, as originally enacted under Articles
			<lb />
			341 and 342 of the Constitution, was basically an exercise in re
			<lb />
			casting the Schedule to the 1935 Act. The subsequent amendments to
			<lb />
			the aforesaid two Orders, from time to time, have been necessitated to
			<lb />
			bring the position in tune with the amendments to the First Schedule
			<lb />
			to the Constitution made at different points of time by creation of new
			<lb />
			States and alterations in the area and boundaries of existing States.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			12.
			<lb />
			Article 366 of the Constitution which defines expressions
			<lb />
			appearing in the Constitution specifically defines &apos;Scheduled Castes&apos;
			<lb />
			[clause (24)] to mean &quot;such castes, races or tribes or parts of or
			<lb />
			groups within such castes, races or tribes as are deemed under
			<lb />
			Article 341 to be Scheduled Castes for the purposes of this
			<lb />
			Constitution&quot;. Similarly, clause (25) of Article 366 defines &quot;Scheduled
			<lb />
			Tribes&quot; to mean &quot;such tribes or tribal communities or parts of or
			<lb />
			groups within such tribes or tribal communities as are deemed
			<lb />
			under Article 342 to be Scheduled Tribes for the purposes of this
			<lb />
			Constitution&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			13.
			<lb />
			Part XVI of the Constitution of India deals with special
			<lb />
			provisions relating to certain classes.
			<lb />
			Article 330 provides for
			<lb />
			reservation of seats for Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes in the
			<lb />
			House of the People (Lok Sabha) whereas Article 332 contains similar
			<lb />
			provisions so far as the Legislative Assemblies of the States are
			<lb />
			concerned. Article 335 of the Constitution provides that &quot;the claims
			<lb />
			of the members of the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes
			<lb />
			shall be taken into consideration, consistently with the
			<lb />
			maintenance of efficiency of administration, in the making of
			<lb />
			appointments to services and posts in connection with the
			<lb />
			affairs of the Union or of a State&quot;. By the Constitution (Eighty
			<lb />
			Second) Amendment Act, 2000 a proviso to Article 335 was added to
			<lb />
			provide that the members of the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled
			<lb />
			Tribes may be granted relaxation in qualifying marks in any
			<lb />
			examination or standards of evaluation can be lowered in matters of
			<lb />
			promotion to any class or classes of services or posts in connection
			<lb />
			with the affairs of the Union or of a State. Article 338 of the
			<lb />
			Constitution provides for a National Commission for Scheduled Cates
			<lb />
			which is invested with the following duties:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;(a) to investigate and monitor all matters relating
			<lb />
			to the safeguards provided for the Scheduled Castes
			<lb />
			under this Constitution or under any other law for
			<lb />
			the time being in force or under any order of the
			<lb />
			Government and to evaluate the working of such
			<lb />
			safeguards;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b) to inquire into specific complaints with respect
			<lb />
			to the deprivation of rights and safeguards of the
			<lb />
			Scheduled Castes;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(c) to participate and advise on the planning
			<lb />
			process of socioeconomic development of the
			<lb />
			Scheduled Castes and to evaluate the progress of
			<lb />
			their development under the Union and any State;
			<lb />
			the Scheduled Castes and to evaluate the progress
			<lb />
			of their development under the Union and any
			<lb />
			State;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(d) to present to the President, annually and at
			<lb />
			such other times as the Commission may deem fit,
			<lb />
			reports upon the working of those safeguards; deem
			<lb />
			fit, reports upon the working of those safeguards;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(e) to make in such reports recommendations as to
			<lb />
			the measures that should be taken by the Union or
			<lb />
			any State for the effective implementation of those
			<lb />
			safeguards and other measures for the protection,
			<lb />
			welfare and socioeconomic development of the
			<lb />
			Scheduled Castes; and
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(f) to discharge such other functions in relation to
			<lb />
			the protection, welfare and development and
			<lb />
			advancement of the Scheduled Castes as the
			<lb />
			President may, subject to the provisions of any law
			<lb />
			made by Parliament, by the rule specify.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			14.
			<lb />
			Similarly, Article 338A provides for a National Commission
			<lb />
			for Scheduled Tribes which is vested with similar duties as in the case
			<lb />
			of the Commission for the Scheduled Castes.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			15.
			<lb />
			Article 341(1) of the Constitution empowers the President
			<lb />
			with respect to any State or Union Territory, and where it is a State,
			<lb />
			after consultation with the Governor thereof, by public notification, to
			<lb />
			specify the castes, races or tribes or parts of or groups within castes,
			<lb />
			races or tribes which shall for the purposes of the Constitution be
			<lb />
			deemed to be Scheduled Castes in relation to that State or Union
			<lb />
			Territory, as the case may be.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			16.
			<lb />
			In case of Scheduled Tribes the President has been similarly
			<lb />
			empowered under Article 342(1) of the Constitution. Subclause (2) of
			<lb />
			Article 341 and Article 342 empowers the Parliament by law to include
			<lb />
			in or exclude from the list of Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes
			<lb />
			specified in the Notification issued under clause (1) thereof any caste,
			<lb />
			race or tribe/tribal community or part of or group within any caste,
			<lb />
			race or tribe/tribal community. It is further provided that except as
			<lb />
			provided i.e. by Parliament by law(s) made, the notification issued
			<lb />
			under Article 341(1) or Article 342(1) shall not be varied by any
			<lb />
			subsequent notification.
			<lb />
			The constitutional mandate, therefore,
			<lb />
			appears to be that any caste, race or tribe/tribal community or part of
			<lb />
			or group within any caste, race or tribe/tribal community as has been
			<lb />
			specified in the Presidential Order under clause (1) of Article 341 or
			<lb />
			Article 342 can be altered only by Parliament by law(s) made.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			17.
			<lb />
			Article 341 and Article 342 also makes it clear that the
			<lb />
			caste, race or tribe or part of or group within any caste, race or tribe
			<lb />
			as specified in the Presidential Order under Article 341(1) or a tribe or
			<lb />
			tribal community as may be specified in the Presidential Order under
			<lb />
			Article 342(1) shall be deemed to be Scheduled Castes/Scheduled
			<lb />
			Tribes for the purposes of the Constitution in relation to that State or
			<lb />
			Union Territory, as the case may be. The above position is further
			<lb />
			made clear by clause (2) of the two Presidential Orders which are in
			<lb />
			the following terms.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;Clause 2 of the Constitution (Scheduled Castes)
			<lb />
			Order, 1950
			<lb />
			<item>
				2. Subject to the provisions of this Order, the castes,
				<lb />
				races or tribes or parts of, or groups within, castes or
				<lb />
				tribes specified in Parts I to XXV of the Schedule to
				<lb />
				this Order shall, in relation to the States to which
				<lb />
				those Parts respectively relate, be deemed to be
				<lb />
				Scheduled Castes so far as regards member thereof
				<lb />
				resident in the localities specified in relation to them
				<lb />
				in those Parts of that Schedule.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				Clause 2 of the Constitution (Scheduled Tribes)
				<lb />
				Order, 1950
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				2. The Tribes or tribal communities, or parts of, or
				<lb />
				groups within, tribes or tribal communities, specified
				<lb />
				in Parts I to XXII of the Schedule to this Order shall,
				<lb />
				in relation to the States to which those Parts
				<lb />
				respectively relate, be deemed to be Scheduled Tribes
				<lb />
				so far as regards members thereof residents in the
				<lb />
				localities specified in relation to them respectively in
				<lb />
				those Parts of that Schedule.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				18.
				<lb />
				There are various parameters by which a caste/race is
				<lb />
				recognized as &apos;Scheduled Caste/Scheduled Tribe&apos; in a State/Union
				<lb />
				Territory or a particular part thereof. There is no doubt that before
				<lb />
				the Presidential Orders were issued under Article 341(1) or under
				<lb />
				Article 342(1), elaborate enquiries were made and only after such
				<lb />
				enquiries that the Presidential Orders were issued. While doing so, the
				<lb />
				Presidential Orders not only provided that even specified parts or
				<lb />
				groups of castes, races or tribes/tribal community could be Scheduled
				<lb />
				Castes/Tribes in a particular State/Union Territory but also made it
				<lb />
				clear that certain castes or tribes or parts/groups thereof could be
				<lb />
				Scheduled Castes/Tribes only in specified/particular areas/districts of
				<lb />
				a State/Union Territory. The reason for such an exercise by reference
				<lb />
				to specific areas of a State is that judged by standards of educational,
				<lb />
				social backwardness, etc. races or tribes may not stand on the same
				<lb />
				footing throughout the State. The consideration for specifying a
				<lb />
				particular caste or tribe or class for inclusion in the list of Scheduled
				<lb />
				Castes and Scheduled Tribes or Backward Classes in any given State
				<lb />
				depends on the nature and extent of the disadvantages and social
				<lb />
				hardships suffered by the concerned members of the class in that
				<lb />
				State. These may be absent in another State to which the persons
				<lb />
				belonging to some other State may migrate.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				19.
				<lb />
				The Presidential Orders which enumerate lists of
				<lb />
				castes/races, tribes recognized as &apos;Scheduled Caste/Scheduled Tribe&apos;
				<lb />
				cannot be challenged or agitated in a court of law except, perhaps, on
				<lb />
				the limited ground as held in M. Nagaraj and others vs. Union of India
				<lb />
				and others 7 . A few illustrations may clarify the position. The question
				<lb />
				whether Dohar caste is a subcaste of Chamar caste which is
				<lb />
				recognized as a scheduled caste came up for consideration in Bhaiya
				<lb />
				Lal vs. Harikishan Singh 8 . This Court held that the court cannot
				<lb />
				enquire into whether Dohar caste is a subcaste of Chamar caste and
				<lb />
				whether the same must be deemed to have been included in the
				<lb />
				Presidential Order. In Bhaiya Lal (supra), this Court held that before
				<lb />
				issuing notifications under Articles 341 and 342, an elaborate enquiry
				<lb />
				is made and as a result of the enquiry social justice is sought to be
				<lb />
				done to the castes, races or tribes as may appear to be necessary. It
				<lb />
				was further held that only Parliament is empowered to amend the
				<lb />
				Notification under Articles 341(2) and 342(2) of the Constitution, as is
				<lb />
				underlined by the expression &quot;but save as aforesaid a notification
				<lb />
				issued under the said clause shall not be varied by any
				<lb />
				subsequent notification&quot; occurring in each of the said provisions. In
				<lb />
				Bhaiya Lal (supra), this Court held as under:
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;10...The object of Article 341(1) plainly is to provide
				<lb />
				additional protection to the members of the Scheduled
				<lb />
				Castes having regard to the economic and educational
				<lb />
				backwardness from which they suffer. It is obvious
				<lb />
				that in specifying castes, races or tribes, the President
				<lb />
				has been expressly authorised to limit the notification
				<lb />
				to parts of or groups within the castes, races or tribes,
				<lb />
				and that must mean that after examining the
				<lb />
				educational and social backwardness of a caste, race
				<lb />
				or tribe, the President may well come to the conclusion
				<lb />
				that not the whole caste, race or tribe but parts of or
				<lb />
				groups within them should be specified. Similarly, the
				<lb />
				President can specify castes, races or tribes or parts
				<lb />
				thereof in relation not only to the entire State, but in
				<lb />
				relation to parts of the State where he is satisfied that
				<lb />
				the examination of the social and educational are
				<lb />
				backwardness of the race, caste or tribe justifies such
				<lb />
				specification. In fact, it is well known that before a
				<lb />
				notification is issued under Article 341(1), an elaborate
				<lb />
				enquiry is made and it is as a result of this enquiry
				<lb />
				that social justice is sought to be done to the castes,
				<lb />
				races or tribes as may appear to be necessary, and in
				<lb />
				doing justice, it would obviously be expedient not only
				<lb />
				to specify parts or groups of castes, races or tribes, but
				<lb />
				to make the said specification by reference to different
				<lb />
				areas in the State. Educational and social
				<lb />
				backwardness in regard to these castes, races or tribes
				<lb />
				may not be uniform or of the same intensity in the
				<lb />
				whole of the State; it may vary in degree or in kind in
				<lb />
				different areas and that may justify the division of the
				<lb />
				State into convenient and suitable areas for the
				<lb />
				purpose of issuing the public notification in
				<lb />
				question...&quot;
				<lb />
				[Underlining added]
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				20.
				<lb />
				Whenever States&apos; reorganization had taken place in the
				<lb />
				past, Parliament had exercised its powers under Article 341(2)
				<lb />
				and Article 342(2) and provided for specific Castes/Tribes that
				<lb />
				were entitled to be recognised as Scheduled Castes and
				<lb />
				Scheduled Tribes in relation to the reorganized States/Union
				<lb />
				Territories. The Scheme of the Constitution (Scheduled Castes)
				<lb />
				and (Scheduled Tribes) Orders makes it clear that Parliament&apos;s
				<lb />
				intention was to extend the benefits of reservation in relation to
				<lb />
				the States/Union Territories only to the castes, races or tribes as
				<lb />
				mentioned in the Presidential Orders.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				21.
				<lb />
				The Orders of 1950 was amended by the Constitution
				<lb />
				(Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes Order), by the
				<lb />
				Amendment Act, 1956 (Act 63/1956). Another amending Act
				<lb />
				was enacted by parliament in 1976. Earlier, orders had been
				<lb />
				made for the first time in relation to certain territories, such as
				<lb />
				the Constitution (Andaman and Nicobar Islands) Scheduled
				<lb />
				Tribes Order, 1959. Further, amendments had taken place as
				<lb />
				and when parliament reorganized states, through separate
				<lb />
				Reorganisation Acts, which led to large scale modification of the
				<lb />
				Presidential Orders. Illustratively, when new States/Union
				<lb />
				Territories were formed such as, Nagaland, Pondicherry, or
				<lb />
				Sikkim, the Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes Orders were
				<lb />
				made in relation to the new States/Union Territories, for
				<lb />
				instance, the Constitution (Nagaland) Scheduled Tribes Order,
				<lb />
				1970 after the reorganisation of Assam; the Constitution
				<lb />
				(Sikkim) Scheduled Castes Order, 1978; the Constitution
				<lb />
				(Sikkim) Scheduled Tribes Order, 1978) upon creation of the
				<lb />
				State of Sikkim; the recent ones being upon creation of the States
				<lb />
				of Uttarakhand, Chhattisgarh, and Jharkhand. Likewise, when
				<lb />
				previous Union Territories (such as Goa, Mizoram and Arunachal
				<lb />
				Pradesh)
				<lb />
				were
				<lb />
				constituted
				<lb />
				into
				<lb />
				States,
				<lb />
				consequential
				<lb />
				amendments were made to the Scheduled Castes and Tribes
				<lb />
				Orders.
				<lb />
				All such amendments/enactments were made by
				<lb />
				Parliament.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				22.
				<lb />
				Though in a different context i.e. in relation to
				<lb />
				Backward Classes this Court in M.C.D. v. Veena and Ors. 9 , has
				<lb />
				specifically held that migrants are not entitled for reservation as
				<lb />
				9 (2001) 6 SCC 571
				<lb />
				Other Backward Classes (OBCs) in the States/Union Territories
				<lb />
				where they have migrated. The relevant portion of the judgment
				<lb />
				that may be noticed is as hereunder:
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;6. Castes or groups are specified in relation to a
				<lb />
				given State or Union Territory, which obviously
				<lb />
				means that such caste would include caste
				<lb />
				belonging to an OBC group in relation to that
				<lb />
				State or Union Territory for which it is specified.
				<lb />
				The matters that are to be taken into
				<lb />
				consideration for specifying a particular caste in
				<lb />
				a particular group belonging to OBCs would
				<lb />
				depend on the nature and extent of
				<lb />
				disadvantages and social hardships suffered by
				<lb />
				that caste or group in that State. However, it
				<lb />
				may not be so in another State to which a
				<lb />
				person belonging thereto goes by migration. It
				<lb />
				may also be that a caste belonging to the same
				<lb />
				nomenclature is specified in two States but the
				<lb />
				considerations on the basis of which they had
				<lb />
				been specified may be totally different. So the
				<lb />
				degree of disadvantages of various elements
				<lb />
				which constitute the data for specification may
				<lb />
				also be entirely different. Thus, merely because
				<lb />
				a given caste is specified in one State as
				<lb />
				belonging to OBCs does not necessarily mean
				<lb />
				that if there be another group belonging to the
				<lb />
				same nomenclature in another State, a person
				<lb />
				belonging to that group is entitled to the rights,
				<lb />
				privileges and benefits admissible to the
				<lb />
				members of that caste. These aspects have to be
				<lb />
				borne in mind in interpreting the provisions of
				<lb />
				the Constitution with reference to application of
				<lb />
				reservation to OBCs.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				23.
				<lb />
				A Constitution Bench of this Court in Marri Chandra
				<lb />
				Shekhar Rao (supra) had the occasion to consider the question as
				<lb />
				to whether a member of the Gouda community which is
				<lb />
				recognised as &quot;Scheduled Tribe&quot; in the Constitution (Scheduled
				<lb />
				Tribes) Order, 1950 for the State of Andhra Pradesh would be
				<lb />
				entitled to admission in a medical institution situated in the
				<lb />
				State of Maharashtra. This Court noticed the fact that the father
				<lb />
				of the petitioner in Marri Chandra Shekhar Rao (supra) was an
				<lb />
				employee in Fertilizer Corporation of India, a public sector
				<lb />
				undertaking and thereafter in Rashtriya Chemicals and
				<lb />
				Fertilizers Limited, a Government of India undertaking. He
				<lb />
				belonged to the Gouda community, a recognized Scheduled Tribe
				<lb />
				of Andhra Pradesh. On his appointment he was stationed at
				<lb />
				Bombay. The petitioner came to Bombay at the age of nine years.
				<lb />
				He completed his studies in Bombay; he submitted an
				<lb />
				application for his admission in the medical institutions run by
				<lb />
				Bombay Municipal Corporation which was denied. This denial of
				<lb />
				admission was based on the Government of India circular dated
				<lb />
				22 nd February, 1985, according to which a person who migrates
				<lb />
				from one State to another is entitled to the benefit of being
				<lb />
				Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes in the State of origin and not
				<lb />
				in the State to which he or she migrates. The appellant was held
				<lb />
				not entitled to be admitted to the Medical College on the basis
				<lb />
				that he belonged to a Scheduled Tribe in his original State i.e.
				<lb />
				Andhra Pradesh.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				24.
				<lb />
				After referring to various provisions of the Constitution
				<lb />
				of India, the background in which the Presidential Orders were
				<lb />
				issued and several earlier judgments of this Court, it was held as
				<lb />
				under:
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;9. It appears that Scheduled Castes and
				<lb />
				Scheduled Tribes in some States had to suffer
				<lb />
				the social disadvantages and did not have the
				<lb />
				facilities for development and growth. It is,
				<lb />
				therefore, necessary in order to make them
				<lb />
				equal in those areas where they have so suffered
				<lb />
				and are in the state of underdevelopment to
				<lb />
				have reservations or protection in their favour so
				<lb />
				that they can compete on equal terms with the
				<lb />
				more advantageous or developed sections of the
				<lb />
				community. Extreme social and economic
				<lb />
				backwardness arising out of traditional practices
				<lb />
				of untouchability is normally considered as
				<lb />
				criterion for including a community in the list of
				<lb />
				Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes. The
				<lb />
				social conditions of a caste, however, varies from
				<lb />
				State to State and it will not be proper to
				<lb />
				generalise any caste or any tribe as a Scheduled
				<lb />
				Tribe or Scheduled Caste for the whole country.
				<lb />
				This, however, is a different problem whether a
				<lb />
				member or the Scheduled Caste in one part of
				<lb />
				the country who migrates to another State or
				<lb />
				any other Union territory should continue to be
				<lb />
				treated as a Scheduled Caste or Scheduled Tribe
				<lb />
				in which he has migrated. That question has to
				<lb />
				be judged taking into consideration the interest
				<lb />
				and wellbeing of the Scheduled Castes and
				<lb />
				Scheduled Tribes in the country as a whole.&quot;
				<lb />
				[underlining is ours]
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				25.
				<lb />
				In Marri Chandra Shekhar Rao (supra), rejecting the
				<lb />
				contention that a member of Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes
				<lb />
				should get the benefit of the status &apos;for the purpose of the
				<lb />
				Constitution throughout the territory of India&apos;, it was
				<lb />
				observed that if such contention is to be accepted the expression
				<lb />
				&quot;In relation of that State&quot; would become nugatory.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				26.
				<lb />
				Marri Chandra Shekhar Rao (supra) was followed by
				<lb />
				another Constitution Bench of this Court in Action Committee
				<lb />
				(supra). After referring to Articles 14, 15(1), 15(4), 16(4) and 19
				<lb />
				and Part XVI of the Constitution of India and the decisions
				<lb />
				governing the field and also Articles 341 and 342, it was held as
				<lb />
				under:
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;3. On a plain reading of clause (1) of Articles 341
				<lb />
				and 342 it is manifest that the power of the
				<lb />
				President is limited to specifying the castes or
				<lb />
				tribes which shall, for the purposes of the
				<lb />
				Constitution, be deemed to be Scheduled Castes
				<lb />
				or Scheduled Tribes in relation to a State or a
				<lb />
				Union Territory, as the case may be. Once a
				<lb />
				notification is issued under clause (1) of Articles
				<lb />
				341 and 342 of the Constitution, Parliament can
				<lb />
				by law include in or exclude from the list of
				<lb />
				Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes, specified
				<lb />
				in the notification, any caste or tribe but save for
				<lb />
				that limited purpose the notification issued under
				<lb />
				clause (1), shall not be varied by any subsequent
				<lb />
				notification. What is important to notice is that
				<lb />
				the castes or tribes have to be specified in
				<lb />
				relation to a given State or Union Territory. That
				<lb />
				means a given caste or tribe can be a Scheduled
				<lb />
				Caste or a Scheduled Tribe in relation to the
				<lb />
				State or Union Territory for which it is specified.
				<lb />
				These are the relevant provisions with which we
				<lb />
				shall be concerned while dealing with the
				<lb />
				grievance made in this petition.
				<lb />
				....
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				16. We may add that considerations for
				<lb />
				specifying a particular caste or tribe or class for
				<lb />
				inclusion
				<lb />
				in
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				list
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				Scheduled
				<lb />
				Castes/Schedule Tribes or backward classes in a
				<lb />
				given State would depend on the nature and
				<lb />
				extent of disadvantages and social hardships
				<lb />
				suffered by that caste, tribe or class in that State
				<lb />
				which may be totally non est in another State to
				<lb />
				which persons belonging thereto may migrate.
				<lb />
				Coincidentally it may be that a caste or tribe
				<lb />
				bearing the same nomenclature is specified in
				<lb />
				two States but the considerations on the basis of
				<lb />
				which they have been specified may be totally
				<lb />
				different. So also the degree of disadvantages of
				<lb />
				various elements which constitute the input for
				<lb />
				specification may also be totally different.
				<lb />
				Therefore, merely because a given caste is
				<lb />
				specified in State A as a Scheduled Caste does
				<lb />
				not necessarily mean that if there be another
				<lb />
				caste bearing the same nomenclature in another
				<lb />
				State the person belonging to the former would
				<lb />
				be entitled to the rights, privileges and benefits
				<lb />
				admissible to a member of the Scheduled Caste
				<lb />
				of the latter State &quot;for the purposes of this
				<lb />
				Constitution&quot;. This is an aspect which has to be
				<lb />
				kept in mind and which was very much in the
				<lb />
				minds of the Constitutionmakers as is evident
				<lb />
				from the choice of language of Articles 341 and
				<lb />
				342 of the Constitution....&quot;
				<lb />
				[underlining is ours]
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				27.
				<lb />
				Marri Chandra Shekhar Rao (supra) and Action
				<lb />
				Committee (supra) were followed in Subhash Chandra and
				<lb />
				another (supra). After referring to various judgments on the
				<lb />
				point and also the various circulars, this Court in Subhash
				<lb />
				Chandra and another (supra) held as under:
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;69. Both the Central Government and the State
				<lb />
				Government indisputably may lay down a policy
				<lb />
				decision in regard to reservation having regard to
				<lb />
				Articles 15 and 16 of the Constitution of India
				<lb />
				but such a policy cannot violate other
				<lb />
				constitutional provisions. A policy cannot have
				<lb />
				primacy over the constitutional scheme. If for the
				<lb />
				purposes of Articles 341 and 342 of the
				<lb />
				Constitution of India, State and the Union
				<lb />
				Territory are on a par on the ground of
				<lb />
				administrative exigibility (sic) or in exercise of the
				<lb />
				administrative power, the constitutional interdict
				<lb />
				contained in clause (2) of Article 341 or clause (2)
				<lb />
				of Article 342 of the Constitution of India cannot
				<lb />
				be got rid of.
				<lb />
				.......
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				75. If a caste or tribe is notified in terms of the
				<lb />
				Scheduled Castes Order or the Scheduled Tribes
				<lb />
				Order, the same must be done in terms of clause
				<lb />
				(1) of Article 341 as also that of Article 342 of the
				<lb />
				Constitution of India, as the case may be. No
				<lb />
				deviation from the procedure laid down therein is
				<lb />
				permissible in law. If any amendment/alteration
				<lb />
				thereto is required to be made, recourse to the
				<lb />
				procedure laid down under clause (2) thereof
				<lb />
				must be resorted to.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				28.
				<lb />
				In Marri Chandra Shekhar Rao (supra), the
				<lb />
				Constitution Bench observed that the expression &quot;in relation to
				<lb />
				that State&quot; must be read meaningfully and harmoniously. It
				<lb />
				was observed that if a member of Scheduled Castes/Scheduled
				<lb />
				Tribes gets the benefit of that status throughout the territory of
				<lb />
				India, the expression &quot;in relation to that State&quot; would become
				<lb />
				nugatory. If the special privileges or the rights granted to
				<lb />
				scheduled castes or scheduled tribes in a particular State are to
				<lb />
				be made available in all the States and if such benefits are to be
				<lb />
				carried from State &apos;A&apos; to State &apos;B&apos; on migration, the mandate of
				<lb />
				Article 341/342 would get compromised. Such a consequence
				<lb />
				must be avoided for it is a fundamental rule of interpretation, be
				<lb />
				it of a statutory enactment or of the Constitution, that wherever
				<lb />
				and whenever there is a conflict between two provisions, the
				<lb />
				same should be so interpreted as to give effect to both.
				<lb />
				&quot;…….Nothing is surplus in a Constitution and no part should be
				<lb />
				made nugatory…..&quot;. [Marri Chandra Shekhar Rao (supra)]
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				29.
				<lb />
				The issue has to be viewed from another perspective.
				<lb />
				If a member of a Scheduled Caste/ Scheduled Tribe of Andhra
				<lb />
				Pradesh who had migrated to Maharashtra is to be given the
				<lb />
				benefit of reservation it will amount to depriving a member of a
				<lb />
				Scheduled Caste/Scheduled Tribe of Maharashtra by reducing
				<lb />
				the reservation earmarked for them. It is in this context, in Marri
				<lb />
				Chandra Shekhar Rao (supra), that the Constitution Bench
				<lb />
				observed as under:
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;14. ....But having regard to the purpose, it
				<lb />
				appears to us that harmonious construction
				<lb />
				enjoins that we should give to each expression
				<lb />
				-&quot;in relation to that State&quot; or &quot;for the purposes
				<lb />
				of this Constitution&quot; -its full meaning and give
				<lb />
				their full effect. This must be so construed that
				<lb />
				one must not negate the other. The construction
				<lb />
				that reservation made in respect of the Scheduled
				<lb />
				Caste or Tribe of that State is so determined to be
				<lb />
				entitled to all the privileges and rights under the
				<lb />
				Constitution in that State would be the most
				<lb />
				correct way of reading, consistent with the
				<lb />
				language,
				<lb />
				purpose
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				scheme
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				Constitution. Otherwise, one has to bear in mind
				<lb />
				that if reservations to those who are treated as
				<lb />
				Scheduled Caste or Tribe in Andhra Pradesh are
				<lb />
				also given to a boy or a girl who migrates and
				<lb />
				gets deducted (sic inducted) in the State of
				<lb />
				Maharashtra or other States where that caste or
				<lb />
				tribe is not treated as Scheduled Caste or
				<lb />
				Scheduled Tribe then either reservation will have
				<lb />
				the effect of depriving the percentage to the
				<lb />
				member of that caste or tribe in Maharashtra
				<lb />
				who would be entitled to protection or it would
				<lb />
				denude the other nonScheduled Castes or non
				<lb />
				Scheduled Tribes in Maharashtra to the
				<lb />
				proportion that they are entitled to. This cannot
				<lb />
				be logical or correct result designed by the
				<lb />
				Constitution.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				30.
				<lb />
				Unhesitatingly, therefore, it can be said that a person
				<lb />
				belonging to a Scheduled Caste in one State cannot be deemed to
				<lb />
				be a Scheduled Caste person in relation to any other State to
				<lb />
				which he migrates for the purpose of employment or education.
				<lb />
				The expressions &quot;in relation to that State or Union Territory&quot;
				<lb />
				and &quot;for the purpose of this Constitution&quot; used in Articles 341
				<lb />
				and 342 of the Constitution of India would mean that the
				<lb />
				benefits of reservation provided for by the Constitution would
				<lb />
				stand confined to the geographical territories of a State/Union
				<lb />
				Territory in respect of which the lists of Scheduled
				<lb />
				Castes/Scheduled Tribes have been notified by the Presidential
				<lb />
				Orders issued from time to time.
				<lb />
				A person notified as a
				<lb />
				Scheduled Caste in State &apos;A&apos; cannot claim the same status in
				<lb />
				another State on the basis that he is declared as a Scheduled
				<lb />
				Caste in State &apos;A&apos;.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				31.
				<lb />
				In S. Pushpa (supra), the Pondicherry Government had
				<lb />
				appointed Selection Grade Teachers in 1995 under the
				<lb />
				Scheduled Castes quota from amongst the scheduled castes
				<lb />
				candidates registered in the employment exchange in
				<lb />
				Pondicherry but also extended the benefit of reservation to
				<lb />
				scheduled castes candidates of other States and Union
				<lb />
				Territories.
				<lb />
				The Chennai Bench of Central Administrative
				<lb />
				Tribunal (&quot;CAT&quot; for short) quashed the selection process holding
				<lb />
				that migrant Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes candidates
				<lb />
				could not be considered for appointment for posts within the
				<lb />
				union territory of Pondicherry. In S. Pushpa (supra) the issue was
				<lb />
				with regard to the extent of benefit that Scheduled Castes
				<lb />
				candidates of other States/Union Territories would be entitled to
				<lb />
				in Pondicherry. This Court held that in the matter of providing
				<lb />
				reservation, it was open to the Pondicherry Government to apply
				<lb />
				or adopt a policy to give the benefit of reservation to migrant
				<lb />
				Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes. In paragraphs 17 and
				<lb />
				21 in S. Pushpa (supra), it was held as under:
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;17. We do not find anything inherently wrong or
				<lb />
				any infraction of any constitutional provision in
				<lb />
				such a policy. The principle enunciated in Marri
				<lb />
				Chandra Shekhar Rao cannot have application
				<lb />
				here as UT of Pondicherry is not a State. As
				<lb />
				shown above, a Union Territory is administered
				<lb />
				by the President through an Administrator
				<lb />
				appointed by him. In the context of Article 246,
				<lb />
				Union Territories are excluded from the ambit of
				<lb />
				the expression &quot;State&quot; occurring therein. This
				<lb />
				was clearly explained by a Constitution Bench in
				<lb />
				T.M. Kanniyan v. ITO. In New Delhi Municipal
				<lb />
				Council v. State of Punjab the majority has
				<lb />
				approved the ratio of T.M. Kanniyan and has
				<lb />
				held that the Union Territories are not States for
				<lb />
				the purpose of Part XI of the Constitution (para
				<lb />
				145). The Tribunal has, therefore, clearly erred
				<lb />
				in applying the ratio of Marri Chandra Shekhar
				<lb />
				Rao in setting aside the selection and
				<lb />
				appointment of migrant SC candidates.
				<lb />
				(underlining is ours)
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				*** *** ***
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				21. ....Article 16(4) is not controlled by a
				<lb />
				Presidential Order issued under Article 341(1) or
				<lb />
				Article 342(1) of the Constitution in the sense
				<lb />
				that reservation in the matter of appointment on
				<lb />
				posts may be made in a State or Union Territory
				<lb />
				only for such Scheduled Castes and Scheduled
				<lb />
				Tribes which are mentioned in the Schedule
				<lb />
				appended to the Presidential Order for that
				<lb />
				particular State or Union Territory. This article
				<lb />
				does not say that only such Scheduled Castes
				<lb />
				and Scheduled Tribes which are mentioned in
				<lb />
				the Presidential Order issued for a particular
				<lb />
				State alone would be recognised as backward
				<lb />
				classes of citizens and none else. If a State or
				<lb />
				Union Territory makes a provision whereunder
				<lb />
				the benefit of reservation is extended only to
				<lb />
				such Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes
				<lb />
				which are recognised as such in relation to that
				<lb />
				State or Union Territory then such a provision
				<lb />
				would be perfectly valid. However, there would
				<lb />
				be no infraction of clause (4) of Article 16 if a
				<lb />
				Union Territory by virtue of its peculiar position
				<lb />
				being governed by the President as laid down in
				<lb />
				Article 239 extends the benefit of reservation
				<lb />
				even to such migrant Scheduled Castes or
				<lb />
				Scheduled Tribes who are not mentioned in the
				<lb />
				Schedule to the Presidential Order issued for
				<lb />
				such Union Territory. The UT of Pondicherry
				<lb />
				having adopted a policy of the Central
				<lb />
				Government whereunder all Scheduled Castes
				<lb />
				or Scheduled Tribes, irrespective of their State
				<lb />
				are eligible for posts which are reserved for
				<lb />
				SC/ST candidates, no legal infirmity can be
				<lb />
				ascribed to such a policy and the same cannot
				<lb />
				be held to be contrary to any provision of law.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				32.
				<lb />
				The upshot of the aforesaid discussion would lead us
				<lb />
				to the conclusion that the Presidential Orders issued under
				<lb />
				Article 341 in regard to Scheduled Castes and under Article 342
				<lb />
				in regard to Scheduled Tribes cannot be varied or altered by any
				<lb />
				authority including the Court. It is the Parliament alone which
				<lb />
				has been vested with the power to so act, that too, by laws made.
				<lb />
				Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes thus specified in relation
				<lb />
				to a State or a Union Territory does not carry the same status in
				<lb />
				another State or Union Territory. Any expansion/deletion of the
				<lb />
				list of Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes by any authority
				<lb />
				except Parliament would be against the constitutional mandate
				<lb />
				under Articles 341 and 342 of the Constitution of India.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				33.
				<lb />
				Article 16(4) is an enabling provision. It enables the
				<lb />
				State to provide to backward classes including Scheduled Castes
				<lb />
				and Scheduled Tribes reservation in appointments to public
				<lb />
				services. Such reservation is to be provided on the basis of
				<lb />
				quantifiable data indicating the adequacy or inadequacy, as may
				<lb />
				be, of the representation of such classes in Government service.
				<lb />
				The data which is the basis of the satisfaction of the State being
				<lb />
				verifiable, is open to judicial scrutiny on the limited ground of
				<lb />
				relevance of the circumstances on which the satisfaction is
				<lb />
				moulded. The policy decision to provide reservation, of course, is
				<lb />
				beyond the pale of judicial review.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				34.
				<lb />
				It is an unquestionable principle of interpretation that
				<lb />
				interrelated statutory as well as constitutional provisions have to
				<lb />
				be harmoniously construed and understood so as to avoid making
				<lb />
				any provision nugatory and redundant. If the list of Scheduled
				<lb />
				Castes/Scheduled Tribes in the Presidential Orders under Article
				<lb />
				341/342 is subject to alteration only by laws made by Parliament,
				<lb />
				operation of the lists of Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes
				<lb />
				beyond the classes or categories enumerated under the
				<lb />
				Presidential Order for a particular State/Union Territory by
				<lb />
				exercise of the enabling power vested by Article 16(4) would have
				<lb />
				the obvious effect of circumventing the specific constitutional
				<lb />
				provisions in Articles 341/342. In this regard, it must also be
				<lb />
				noted that the power under Article 16(4) is not only capable of
				<lb />
				being exercised by a legislative provision/enactment but also by
				<lb />
				an Executive Order issued under Article 166 of the Constitution.
				<lb />
				It will, therefore, be in consonance with the constitutional scheme
				<lb />
				to understand the enabling provision under Article 16(4) to be
				<lb />
				available to provide reservation only to the classes or categories of
				<lb />
				Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes enumerated in the
				<lb />
				Presidential orders for a particular State/Union Territory within
				<lb />
				the geographical area of that State and not beyond. If in the
				<lb />
				opinion of a State it is necessary to extend the benefit of
				<lb />
				reservation to a class/category of Scheduled Castes/Scheduled
				<lb />
				Tribes beyond those specified in the Lists for that particular State,
				<lb />
				constitutional discipline would require the State to make its views
				<lb />
				in the matter prevail with the central authority so as to enable an
				<lb />
				appropriate parliamentary exercise to be made by an amendment
				<lb />
				of the Lists of Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes for that
				<lb />
				particular State. Unilateral action by States on the touchstone of
				<lb />
				Article 16(4) of the Constitution could be a possible trigger point of
				<lb />
				constitutional anarchy and therefore must be held to be
				<lb />
				impermissible under the Constitution.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				35.
				<lb />
				The decision in S. Pushpa (supra) may now be taken
				<lb />
				up to understand the basis on which the conclusion recorded
				<lb />
				therein was recorded. In S. Pushpa (supra) a distinction was found
				<lb />
				by this Court in the constitutional status of a Union Territory and
				<lb />
				a State in relation to the Union/Central Government.
				<lb />
				The
				<lb />
				provisions of Article 239 and 239A of the Constitution; Section
				<lb />
				3(8) of the General Clauses Act, 1897 defining &apos;Central
				<lb />
				Government&apos; and the provisions of the Government of Union
				<lb />
				Territories Act, 1963 were considered to arrive at the following
				<lb />
				conclusion:
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;14. The effect of these provisions is also that
				<lb />
				the Administrator (Lt Governor of Pondicherry)
				<lb />
				and his Council of Ministers act under the
				<lb />
				general control of and are under an obligation
				<lb />
				to comply with any particular direction issued
				<lb />
				by the President. Further, the Administrator
				<lb />
				(Lt Governor of Pondicherry) while acting
				<lb />
				under the scope of the authority given to him
				<lb />
				under Article 239 of the Constitution would be
				<lb />
				the Central Government.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				36.
				<lb />
				It is on the aforesaid basis that the concerned
				<lb />
				Notification/Government Order dated 16 th February, 1974 by
				<lb />
				which it was provided that Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes
				<lb />
				candidates from outside the Union Territory of Pondicherry
				<lb />
				should also be considered for appointment to posts reserved for
				<lb />
				Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes in the Union Territory
				<lb />
				Administration and the communication of the Government of
				<lb />
				India dated 6 th October, 1995 to the same effect were upheld.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				37.
				<lb />
				The First Schedule to the Constitution, as original
				<lb />
				enacted, provided for three (03) categories of States i.e. Part &apos;A&apos;,
				<lb />
				Part &apos;B&apos; and Part &apos;C&apos; States to comprise the territory of India. The
				<lb />
				States Reorganization Act, 1956 and the consequential
				<lb />
				Constitution (Seventh Amendment) Act, 1956 drastically altered
				<lb />
				the provisions of the First Schedule to the Constitution by
				<lb />
				establishment of new States; alteration in the area and
				<lb />
				boundaries of existing States and also by abolition of the three
				<lb />
				(03) categories of States; and by classification of certain areas as
				<lb />
				Union Territories. Pursuant thereto the Government of Union
				<lb />
				Territories Act, 1963 was enacted to provide for Legislative
				<lb />
				Assemblies and Councils of Ministers for certain Union
				<lb />
				Territories and for certain other incidental matters. It will not be
				<lb />
				necessary to specifically deal with the provisions of the aforesaid
				<lb />
				Act in any great detail except to say that in course of time most
				<lb />
				of the Union Territories (except for Pondicherry), which had been
				<lb />
				provided with their own Legislatures and Councils of Ministers
				<lb />
				have graduated to become fullfledged States on the basis of
				<lb />
				enactment of several State Reorganisation Acts details of which
				<lb />
				have been mentioned (para 21).
				<lb />
				The Union Territory of
				<lb />
				Pondicherry, as on date, stands out as sole Union Territory
				<lb />
				which has a Legislature and Council of Ministers, apart from
				<lb />
				Delhi.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				38.
				<lb />
				Delhi, which was one of the original Union Territories,
				<lb />
				came to be called as &quot;National Capital Territory of Delhi&quot;. This
				<lb />
				change was introduced by the Constitution (SixtyNinth
				<lb />
				Amendment) Act, 1991 with effect from 1 st February, 1992 by
				<lb />
				insertion of Article 239AA in Part VIII of the Constitution (i.e.
				<lb />
				Special provisions with respect to Delhi). Article 239AA(3)(a)
				<lb />
				empower the Legislative Assembly of the National Capital
				<lb />
				Territory of Delhi to make laws with respect to any matters
				<lb />
				enumerated in the State List or in the Concurrent List (i.e. List II
				<lb />
				and List III of the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution of India)
				<lb />
				subject to certain exceptions. It is here that the Union Territory
				<lb />
				of Delhi i.e. National Capital Territory of Delhi is enjoined a
				<lb />
				special status inasmuch as power to enact laws on any of the
				<lb />
				subjects in List II and List III is a constitutional conferment as
				<lb />
				opposed to the position in the erstwhile Union Territories and the
				<lb />
				present day Union Territory of Pondicherry where the power to
				<lb />
				frame/make laws has been conferred on the Union Territory
				<lb />
				Legislatures by a Parliamentary enactment i.e. Section 18 of the
				<lb />
				Government of Union Territories Act, 1963. The above narration
				<lb />
				has been considered necessary only to make the discussion
				<lb />
				complete. We make it clear that we are not entering into any
				<lb />
				discussion as to the special position/status of Delhi, if any, by
				<lb />
				virtue of the provisions contained in Article 239AA as the said
				<lb />
				issue does not arise for consideration in the present reference.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				39.
				<lb />
				The above view coupled with the scope and ambit of
				<lb />
				the present reference may also not require us to go into the
				<lb />
				correctness of the view expressed by this Court in paragraph 14
				<lb />
				of the decision in S. Pushpa (supra) (as already extracted). The
				<lb />
				resolution of the question formulated for an answer is capable of
				<lb />
				being reached by adopting an entirely different perspective which
				<lb />
				we intend to do hereinafter.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				40.
				<lb />
				The federal nature of the Constitution finds broad
				<lb />
				manifestation in two principal areas i.e. division of legislative
				<lb />
				power and exercise thereof by the Union and the constituent
				<lb />
				States and secondly, which is more relevant and important to the
				<lb />
				subject in hand, is the constitutional provisions relating to
				<lb />
				services under the Union and the States as dealt with in Part XIV
				<lb />
				of the Constitution.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				41.
				<lb />
				The subject finds an elaborate study by Dr. D.D. Basu
				<lb />
				in &quot;Commentary on the Constitution of India&quot; 10 . According to Dr.
				<lb />
				D.D. Basu, &quot;In India though the Union and the States have
				<lb />
				their own public services, (vide Entry 70 of List I and Entry
				<lb />
				41 of List II) there is no clearcut bifurcation in the
				<lb />
				administration of the Union and the State laws as in the
				<lb />
				U.S.A. The State officials administer the State laws as well
				<lb />
				the Union laws applicable within that Sate whereas the
				<lb />
				members of the Union Services while working within a
				<lb />
				State, also carry out State laws, insofar as they may be
				<lb />
				applicable. The second peculiarity of the Indian federal
				<lb />
				system of administration is that though the federal and
				<lb />
				State Governments have civil services of their own to
				<lb />
				manage their own households, there are certain services
				<lb />
				known as the AllIndia Services, which are common to both
				<lb />
				the federal and State Governments.
				<lb />
			</p>
			<p>
				The organisation of the Civil services in the Indian
				<lb />
				federal system may be demonstrated as thus:
				<lb />
				All India Services
				<lb />
				Central Civil
				<lb />
				Services
				<lb />
				State Civil Services
				<lb />
				Central Secretariat
				<lb />
				Services&quot;
				<lb />
				Subordinate Services
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				42.
				<lb />
				At the State Level, as Dr. D.D. Basu points out, &quot;the
				<lb />
				State Civil Services administer the subject solely belonging
				<lb />
				to the State Governments, according to the federal
				<lb />
				distribution of subjects thus including the Judicial,
				<lb />
				Executive,
				<lb />
				Medical,
				<lb />
				Engineering,
				<lb />
				Police,
				<lb />
				Education
				<lb />
				branches. Their members are under the exclusive control of
				<lb />
				the respective State Governments and their duties are
				<lb />
				confined to the territories of the State by which they have
				<lb />
				been appointed, unless sent on deputation to the Union
				<lb />
				Government&quot;. 11 These State Civil Services may be Administrative
				<lb />
				Services, Forest Services etc. [illustratively, in case of Himachal
				<lb />
				Pradesh, Himachal Pradesh Administrative Service (HPAS) is a
				<lb />
				type of service, so is, Himachal Pradesh Forest Service (HPFS).
				<lb />
				The recruitment to these services is conducted by way of Civil
				<lb />
				Services Examinations organised by the Statespecific Public
				<lb />
				Service Commission e.g. in case of Himachal Pradesh, it is
				<lb />
				Himachal Pradesh Public Service Commission. As stated earlier,
				<lb />
				persons inducted into the State Service of a particular State
				<lb />
				cannot be transferred to any other State. These officers are
				<lb />
				concerned with only the affairs of the state in which they are
				<lb />
				appointed.
				<lb />
				These services (like HPAS, HPFS) may, for
				<lb />
				convenience, be called as Superior Services/Higher Services with
				<lb />
				reference to a State. But in addition to these higher services,
				<lb />
				there are also services that may, again for convenience, be called
				<lb />
				as Subordinate Services/Lower Level Jobs. The posts in these
				<lb />
				services are like those of Clerks, School Teachers; Drivers,
				<lb />
				Attendants, Safai Workers, etc. For the purpose of recruitment of
				<lb />
				Subordinate Servants, states have in place Statespecific Selection
				<lb />
				Commissions.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				43.
				<lb />
				At the Federal Level, civil administration is carried out
				<lb />
				by the members of -(1) All India Services (specifically provided for
				<lb />
				in Article 312); (2) Central Civil Services (although, not specifically
				<lb />
				provided for in the Constitution but are regulated by creation of
				<lb />
				statutory Rules framed under the proviso to Article 309). These
				<lb />
				are again Superior Services and the selection/recruitment is by
				<lb />
				the Union Public Service Commission.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				ALL INDIA SERVICES
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				There are three All India Services (AIS) -(a) Indian Administrative
				<lb />
				Service (IAS); (b) Indian Forest Service (IFoS); (c) Indian Police
				<lb />
				Service (IPS). As regards AIS, Dr. D.D. Basu 12 says that, &quot;the
				<lb />
				peculiarity of the AIS from the federal standpoint is that -
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				(a)
				<lb />
				Though they are recruited and their conditions of
				<lb />
				service are determined by the Union Government, they have
				<lb />
				to administer both Union and the State subjects,
				<lb />
				accordingly as their services are placed at the disposal of
				<lb />
				the Union or a State Government, in connection with the
				<lb />
				affairs of the Union or the State, as the case may be.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				(b)
				<lb />
				While serving in a State, they are controlled by
				<lb />
				the State Government, except as regards the imposition of
				<lb />
				the penalty of dismissal, removal or compulsory retirement,
				<lb />
				which can be awarded only by the Union Government.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				(c)
				<lb />
				In a sense, this system is an exception to the
				<lb />
				usual federal precedent inasmuch as it is intended to fill up
				<lb />
				the strategic posts both under the Union and State
				<lb />
				Governments by men of superior calibre, recruited on a
				<lb />
				uniform basis, through the UPSC. Thus, while a Deputy
				<lb />
				Collector may be a member of the State Civil Service, the
				<lb />
				Additional Collector and the Collector may be members of
				<lb />
				the Indian Administrative Service. The category of AIS thus
				<lb />
				breaks through the federal division so far as the
				<lb />
				administrative services in India are concerned. In fact, the
				<lb />
				principal agents of a Sate administration are members of
				<lb />
				the AIS and it would be a mistake to suppose that the AIS
				<lb />
				exist for the administration of the Union subjects. Broadly,
				<lb />
				speaking, the administration of a State is run both by the
				<lb />
				members of the AIS and State Services, the latter supplying
				<lb />
				only the intermediate and subordinate tiers.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				(d)
				<lb />
				Though the bulk of recruitment to the AIS is by
				<lb />
				competitive examination, a certain proportion is selected by
				<lb />
				promotion from amongst members of the State Civil
				<lb />
				Services.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				(e)
				<lb />
				Though a member of AIS may be required to serve
				<lb />
				anywhere in India, on recruitment, he is usually assigned to
				<lb />
				a State or States jointly, or, in a technical language, is
				<lb />
				included in a State cadre or Joint cadre and continues to
				<lb />
				serve there until or unless he is called upon to serve the
				<lb />
				Union Government, in any of its Departments.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				(f)
				<lb />
				While employed under a State, again, the
				<lb />
				members of the AIS do not have to work only in the
				<lb />
				Secretariat of the State but also in the Districts as already
				<lb />
				stated and members of these services are expected to
				<lb />
				acquire experience of the business in the district as well as
				<lb />
				Secretariat administration and there is a constant
				<lb />
				interchange of officers between the Secretariat and the
				<lb />
				Districts, just as there is such an interchange between the
				<lb />
				States and the Union Secretariats on the other hand.&quot;
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				44.
				<lb />
				Therefore, the members of the All India Services are
				<lb />
				common to the Union and the States and they serve, by turn,
				<lb />
				both the Union and State Governments. The members of these
				<lb />
				services although recruited by the Centre their services are
				<lb />
				placed under various State cadres. &quot;It is evident from Article
				<lb />
				312(1) that the members of the AIS are common to the Union
				<lb />
				and the States. Curiously, however, there is a cadre for the
				<lb />
				Indian Administrative Service only in the States, according
				<lb />
				to the Indian Administrative Service (Cadre) Rules, 1954
				<lb />
				and there is no separate cadre for members of this service
				<lb />
				in the Government of India. Each members of the Indian
				<lb />
				Administrative Service therefore, belongs to the cadre of one
				<lb />
				State or the other.&quot; 13
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				45.
				<lb />
				There are many State Cadres e.g. Bihar Cadre,
				<lb />
				Rajasthan Cadre and Joint Cadres like AGMUT (for Arunachal
				<lb />
				Pradesh + Goa + Mizoram + the 7 Union Territories). These
				<lb />
				officers remain in the allotted Cadres till they retire. They are not
				<lb />
				normally to be transferred from one State Cadre to another State
				<lb />
				Cadre though they have the accountability to serve both under
				<lb />
				the State and the Centre.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				46.
				<lb />
				At this juncture, the Union of India&apos;s Affidavit may also
				<lb />
				be referred to, which states with reference to AIS that, &quot;the
				<lb />
				conditions of service of these services (AIS) are regulated by
				<lb />
				the DoPT by way of executive and statutory instructions,
				<lb />
				statutory rules formulated under Article 309 of the
				<lb />
				Constitution and Act of Parliament etc. The functional
				<lb />
				control of some of the services rests with other Ministries
				<lb />
				and Departments also. The Ministry of Home Affairs
				<lb />
				exercises functional control on IPS and the Ministry of
				<lb />
				Environment &amp; Forest &amp; Climate Change exercises
				<lb />
				functional control on IFoS. Members of these services are
				<lb />
				allocated a cadre under a State or Union Territory and they
				<lb />
				serve the Union as well as the State, whichever is allotted to
				<lb />
				them. Thus their services are All India Services. Their
				<lb />
				recruitment is by the Union Public Service Commission and
				<lb />
				as they serve the Union as well as the States, their
				<lb />
				recruitment is on pan India basis. Every citizen of this
				<lb />
				country having the required qualification is eligible to be
				<lb />
				considered for the appointment. It is pertinent to note that
				<lb />
				before selection in the AIS, there is no specification or
				<lb />
				indication of the cadre in Union, Union Territory or State,
				<lb />
				which they may serve. Upon selection alone, they would be
				<lb />
				allocated cadre depending upon the merit and the
				<lb />
				preferences they would have made at the time of applying.
				<lb />
				Upon selection they could be allocated to serve through any
				<lb />
				of the 25 states or 7 Union Territories of Delhi; Puducherry;
				<lb />
				Chandigarh; Daman &amp; Diu; Dadra &amp; Nagar Haveli;
				<lb />
				Andaman &amp; Nicobar; Lakshadweep coupled with the states
				<lb />
				of Arunachal Pradesh, Goa and Mizoram&quot; 14 .
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				47.
				<lb />
				CENTRAL CIVIL SERVICES
				<lb />
				The Central Civil Services (CCS), as Dr. D.D. Basu
				<lb />
				points out, &quot;are engaged in administering the Union subjects,
				<lb />
				such as the Posts and Telegraphs, Customs and Excise,
				<lb />
				Income Tax. In short, these constitute all the administrative
				<lb />
				services in the Central Departments which have not so far
				<lb />
				been included in the list of All India Services. They are
				<lb />
				under the exclusive control of the Union Government.
				<lb />
				Besides the Central Services, there are other Services
				<lb />
				intended for work solely in the Central Secretariat, or, in
				<lb />
				other words, those who are to manage the offices of the
				<lb />
				Central Departments. Both the Central Civil Services and
				<lb />
				Central Secretariat Services are subdivided into Class I, II,
				<lb />
				III, IV, (= Group A, B, C, D 15 ) according to the rank and
				<lb />
				responsibilities of the officers… Members of the Central
				<lb />
				Services are also sent on transfer or deputation to States
				<lb />
				where offices relating to the Union subjects or Public Sector
				<lb />
				Undertakings relating thereto are located.&quot; 16 All that we
				<lb />
				would like to add is that though the members of these services
				<lb />
				are concerned only with the affairs of the Union/Centre they
				<lb />
				discharge such duties in the offices and establishments of the
				<lb />
				Union Government as may be located in the States and the Union
				<lb />
				Territories. The Central Civil Services (Classification, Control and
				<lb />
				Appeal) Rules, 1965 [CCS Rules, 1965] (enacted under the
				<lb />
				proviso to Article 309) are the governing statutory Rules with
				<lb />
				reference to these services. Rule 4 of CCS Rules, 1965 classifies
				<lb />
				the Central Civil Services into four types -
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				(i)
				<lb />
				Central Civil Services, Group A (45 services as per the
				<lb />
				Schedule to the Rules);
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				(ii)
				<lb />
				Central Civil Services, Group B (33 services as per the
				<lb />
				Schedule to the Rules);
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				(iii) Central Civil Services, Group C (5 services as per the
				<lb />
				Schedule to the Rules);
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				(iv)
				<lb />
				Central Civil Services, Group D (1 service as per the
				<lb />
				Schedule to the Rules) 17 .
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				48.
				<lb />
				CCS Group A:
				<lb />
				The Affidavit of the Union of India says that, &quot;recruitment
				<lb />
				to Group A services is made by UPSC. The recruitment is
				<lb />
				again on all India basis. This is the reason the personnel
				<lb />
				belonging to these 45 services work in the posts of Union
				<lb />
				and the Union Territories (UT) across the length and breadth
				<lb />
				of the country. The Cadre Controlling Authority of Group A
				<lb />
				services are the respective ministries of the Government of
				<lb />
				India. For example, the first service being the
				<lb />
				Archaeological Service, the Cadre Controlling Authority is
				<lb />
				the Ministry of Culture, Central Government. Another
				<lb />
				example, the 12 th service being the Indian Foreign Service
				<lb />
				and this is controlled by Ministry of External Affairs. No. 16
				<lb />
				is the Indian Revenue Service and it is controlled by the
				<lb />
				Ministry of Finance. The members of these services being
				<lb />
				recruited pursuant to the Central Service Exams conducted
				<lb />
				by the UPSC are allocated to the respective services.
				<lb />
				Whichever Ministry seeks recruitment to the service in this
				<lb />
				Group, sends requisition to UPSC as per procedure
				<lb />
				prescribed and UPSC accordingly advertises for the post in
				<lb />
				Group A. Every citizen of India is eligible to apply as per the
				<lb />
				qualifications and requirements in the notification. DOPT is
				<lb />
				the nodal Ministry for regulating the conditions of service of
				<lb />
				all Central Civil Services as per Allocation of Business
				<lb />
				Rules. As per the conditions of service, every employee is
				<lb />
				required to give an undertaking agreeing to the conditions
				<lb />
				of all India transfer liability at the time of joining service.
				<lb />
				Central Civil Services employees belonging to Group A serve
				<lb />
				the Union of India and that is the reason why these services
				<lb />
				are across the length and breadth of the country, wherever
				<lb />
				there is an office of the Central Government. Member of the
				<lb />
				Groups A service are governed by CCS Rules of 1965 as well
				<lb />
				as Central Civil Services (Conduct) Rules 1972; Central Civil
				<lb />
				Services (Pension) Rules 1972 and such other Rules made by
				<lb />
				the Central Ministries.&quot;
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				49.
				<lb />
				CCS Group B:
				<lb />
				As mentioned earlier, there are 33 Group B Services.
				<lb />
				Amongst these, are the Union Territory Services listed at No. 28
				<lb />
				and No. 29 and known as the &apos;Delhi and Andaman and Nicobar
				<lb />
				Islands Civil Service&apos; abbreviated as &apos;DANICS&apos; and &apos;Delhi and
				<lb />
				Andaman and Nicobar Islands Police Service&apos; (Grade II)
				<lb />
				abbreviated as &apos;DANIPS&apos;. While at this stage we may have also a
				<lb />
				look at Union Territory services in some detail.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				UNION TERRITORY SERVICES
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				50.
				<lb />
				The Government of India (Ministry of Home Affairs) by
				<lb />
				way of a notification dated 6 th August, 2003, and in the exercise
				<lb />
				of the proviso to Article 309, enacted &apos;the National Capital
				<lb />
				Territory of Delhi, Andaman and Nicobar Islands, Lakshadweep,
				<lb />
				Daman and Diu and Dadra and Nagar Havel (Civil Service) Rules,
				<lb />
				2003 [DANICS Rules, 2003]. As also, &apos;the National Capital
				<lb />
				Territory of Delhi, Andaman and Nicobar Islands, Lakshadweep,
				<lb />
				Daman and Diu and Dadra and Nagar Havel (Police Service)
				<lb />
				Rules, 2003 [DANIPS Rules, 2003].
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				51.
				<lb />
				The DANICS/DANIPS Rules, 2003 define:
				<lb />
				*
				<lb />
				&apos;Administration&apos; to mean the Government of the
				<lb />
				National Capital Territory of Delhi in respect National Capital
				<lb />
				Territory of Delhi and Union Territory Administration in respect of
				<lb />
				the Union Territories of -Andaman &amp; Nicobar Islands;
				<lb />
				Lakshadweep; Daman &amp; Diu; Dadra &amp; Nagar Haveli [under Rule
				<lb />
				2(a)]
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				* &apos;Commission&apos; to mean the Union Public Service Commission
				<lb />
				[under Rule 2(h)].
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				* &apos;Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes&apos; to have the same
				<lb />
				meaning as are assigned to them by Articles 366(24) and 366(25)
				<lb />
				[under Rule 2(n)].
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				The DANICS/DANIPS Rules, 2003, further, state that posts in
				<lb />
				Junior Administrative GradeI, Junior Administrative GradeII,
				<lb />
				Selection Grade will be Central Civil Services (Group A), whereas
				<lb />
				Entry Grade shall be Central Civil Services (Group B) [Rule 3].
				<lb />
				The vacancies in DANICS/DANIPS shall be filled in on the basis
				<lb />
				of the Civil Services Examination conducted by UPSC [Rule 7].
				<lb />
				Every member of DANICS/DANIPS allocated to an Administration
				<lb />
				shall be posted against a duty post 18 under the Administration by
				<lb />
				the Administrator [Rule 12]. More importantly, the Government of
				<lb />
				India shall, from time to time, allocate a member of
				<lb />
				DANICS/DANIPS to any Administration for posting [Rule 12].
				<lb />
				Nothing in the Rules affects reservations, relaxation in agelimit
				<lb />
				and other concessions required to be provided for the Scheduled
				<lb />
				Castes, the Scheduled Tribes, Other Backward Classes and other
				<lb />
				special categories of persons in accordance with the orders issued
				<lb />
				by the Government of India from time to time in this regard [Rule
				<lb />
				17: the Saving clause]. The Sanctioned Strength for DANICS and
				<lb />
				DANIPS is in the DANICS/DANIPS Rules, 2003 (approximately
				<lb />
				398 DANICS; approximately 355 DANIPS).
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				52.
				<lb />
				As per the Union of India&apos;s Affidavit, DANICS and
				<lb />
				DANIPS are &apos;Union Territory Services&apos; 19 . The Affidavit says, &quot;...at
				<lb />
				Serial 28 and 29 of the Schedule (to CCS Rules, 1965), we
				<lb />
				have the Union Territory Services known as DANICS and
				<lb />
				DANIPS&quot;. The Affidavit, further, says that, &quot;DANICS/DANIPS
				<lb />
				Officers are posted in Delhi; Andaman &amp; Nicobar Islands;
				<lb />
				Lakshadweep; Daman &amp; Diu; Dadra &amp; Nagar Haveli. The
				<lb />
				recruitment to all the Union Territories for these Group B
				<lb />
				posts are common. They are also centralised and the
				<lb />
				Appointing Authority is none other than the Ministry of
				<lb />
				Home Affairs (Joint Secretary). For the recruitment to these
				<lb />
				services, it is the very same examination meant for AIS and
				<lb />
				CCS Group A. Any citizen of India is eligible to apply,
				<lb />
				subject to the conditions prescribed. As per the Service
				<lb />
				Rules, transfer undertakings throughout the Union
				<lb />
				Territories covered under DANICS/DANIPS is taken from
				<lb />
				these officers. This is the reason why the Union of India
				<lb />
				while inviting applications for recruitment considers all
				<lb />
				candidates, including reserved candidates on all India
				<lb />
				basis. Group B Cadre of DANICS/DANIPS is the Feeder Cadre
				<lb />
				for IAS and IPS respectively (i.e. AIS). They retire invariably
				<lb />
				in these Offices, some of them reaching high positions in the
				<lb />
				Central Government. Recruitment to AIS; CCS Group A; CCS
				<lb />
				Group B (Gazetted) is conducted through UPSC. In the Civil
				<lb />
				Services Examination, the applicants are common when the
				<lb />
				applications are made. Every aspirant seeks recruitment to
				<lb />
				the services and it is only as per the marks and ranking
				<lb />
				that allocations are made eventually to AIS; CCS Group A;
				<lb />
				CCS Group B. Therefore, when UPSC undertakes the
				<lb />
				recruitment, it is naturally a pan India recruitment and
				<lb />
				therefore, it is necessary to seek applications including
				<lb />
				from reserved candidates from all over India.&quot; 20
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				53.
				<lb />
				But it is not the Members of the All India Services
				<lb />
				(AGMUT Cadre); Central Civil Services (Group &apos;A&apos; and &apos;B&apos;) and the
				<lb />
				&apos;DANICS&apos; and &apos;DANIPS&apos; who alone are the public servants in the
				<lb />
				States and the Union Territories engaged in the discharge of
				<lb />
				duties in connection with the affairs of the Union. There are and
				<lb />
				20 Page 4, 5 of the Affidavit.
				<lb />
				bound to be public servants that work the subordinate services.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				CCS Group C:
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				54.
				<lb />
				At the subordinate level these are the Group &apos;C&apos; posts.
				<lb />
				In the Schedule to CCS Rules, 1965, there are 5 such services.
				<lb />
				The Union of India&apos;s Affidavit says that, &quot;These posts, in so far,
				<lb />
				as they relate to services under the Union of India are
				<lb />
				concerned are recruited by the Staff Selection Commission
				<lb />
				(which is the Recruiting Agency under the DoPT). The
				<lb />
				members of CCS Group C get promoted to CCS Group B.
				<lb />
				Recruitment to posts in this group arise out of requisition
				<lb />
				made by the concerned ministries all over India. These
				<lb />
				requisitions, upon reaching, the Staff Selection Commission
				<lb />
				are processed and selection takes place and appointments
				<lb />
				are made. Even from these appointees, undertaking for all
				<lb />
				India transfer liability is taken. As these are posts under
				<lb />
				the Central Government and these employees are liable to
				<lb />
				transferred anywhere in the country and the recruitment
				<lb />
				being centralised for all such posts in the country, it has
				<lb />
				been consistent policy of the Union of India to have pan
				<lb />
				India eligibility.&quot;
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				55.
				<lb />
				With regard to CCS Group D posts, in the affidavit of
				<lb />
				the Union it is stated that &quot;the posts under this category are
				<lb />
				primarily of what used to be Class IV employees now referred
				<lb />
				to as the Multi Tasking staff. In recent years, Central Pay
				<lb />
				Commission has recommended against any further
				<lb />
				recruitment to these posts in Group D. Further it has also
				<lb />
				been recommended that the existing posts will be merged
				<lb />
				with Group C. Hence, this is now a vanishing cadre 21 .&quot;
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				56.
				<lb />
				The broad picture that emanates from the above
				<lb />
				discussion and narration is that insofar as the services in
				<lb />
				connection with the affairs of the Union is concerned (Central
				<lb />
				Services), wherever the establishment may be located i.e. in the
				<lb />
				National Capital Territory of Delhi or in a State or within the
				<lb />
				geographical areas of Union Territory, recruitment to all positions
				<lb />
				is on an All India basis and reservation provided for is again a
				<lb />
				pan India reservation. This by itself, from one perspective, may
				<lb />
				appear to be in departure from the rule set out in Part XVI of the
				<lb />
				Constitution of India (Articles 341 and 342). However, the close
				<lb />
				look undertaken hereinbefore indicates such a position is fully in
				<lb />
				accord with the constitutional structure of a federal polity.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				NATIONAL CAPITAL TERRITORY OF DELHI
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				57.
				<lb />
				In case of National Capital Territory of Delhi,
				<lb />
				especially, to make the picture even clearer, a reference may be
				<lb />
				made to &apos;Delhi Administration Subordinate Service Rules, 1967&apos;.
				<lb />
				Rule 3 of the aforesaid Rules is to the following effect:
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;3. Constitution of service and its classification.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				(1) On and from the date of commencement of these
				<lb />
				Rules, there shall be constituted one Central Civil
				<lb />
				Service, known as the Subordinate Service of the
				<lb />
				Delhi Administration.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				(2) The Service shall have four Grades, namely-
				<lb />
				Grade I
				<lb />
				Grade II
				<lb />
				Grade III
				<lb />
				Grade IV
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				(3) The posts in Grade I shall be Central Civil posts,
				<lb />
				Class II Group &apos;B&apos; (Gazetted) and those in Grades II,
				<lb />
				III and IV shall be Central Civil posts Group &apos;C&apos; (Non
				<lb />
				Gazetted).
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				(4) Members of the service shall, in the normal
				<lb />
				course be eligible for appointment to various Grades
				<lb />
				of the service to which they belong and not to the
				<lb />
				other service.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				(underlining is ours)
				<lb />
				Subordinate services in the National Capital Territory of
				<lb />
				Delhi are, therefore, clearly Central Civil Services. The Affidavit of
				<lb />
				the Union also points out this feature by stating that, &quot;The posts
				<lb />
				in CCS Group C are in the subordinate services.
				<lb />
				The
				<lb />
				equivalent in the Union Territory of Delhi is the Delhi
				<lb />
				Administrative Subordinate Services (DASS) and the
				<lb />
				Recruiting Agency in the place of Staff Selection
				<lb />
				Commission is the Delhi Subordinate Service Selection
				<lb />
				Board (DSSSB). Members of the Delhi Administrative
				<lb />
				Subordinate Services are the Feeder Cadre for Central Civil
				<lb />
				Services Group B (DANICS). It is for these reasons that the
				<lb />
				policy (of pan India eligibility) consistently adopted.&quot; 22
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				58.
				<lb />
				A combined reading of these provisions of the DASS
				<lb />
				Rules, 1967 and CCS Rules, 1965, therefore, more than
				<lb />
				adequately explains the nature of Subordinate Services in the
				<lb />
				NCT of Delhi. These clearly are General Central Services and
				<lb />
				perhaps, it is owing to this state of affairs that the Union of India
				<lb />
				in its Affidavit has stated that, &quot;Members of the Delhi
				<lb />
				Administrative Subordinate Services are the Feeder Cadre
				<lb />
				for Central Civil Services Group B (DANICS). It is for these
				<lb />
				reasons that the policy (of pan India eligibility) is
				<lb />
				consistently adopted.&quot;
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				59.
				<lb />
				While examining the validity of reservation of seats in
				<lb />
				medical colleges for local candidates in Delhi, this Court in Dr.
				<lb />
				Jagdish Saran and Others Vs. Union of India 23 had made certain
				<lb />
				observations with regard to the special status that the capital city
				<lb />
				enjoys, which today, has come to be known as the National
				<lb />
				Capital Territory of Delhi. The observations of this Court in
				<lb />
				paragraphs 10 and 56 may be usefully recapitulated and,
				<lb />
				therefore, is set out below:
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;10. The capital city is not just a part of India. It is
				<lb />
				miniaturised India, a fact often forgotten by the
				<lb />
				administration in the field of culture and education,
				<lb />
				especially visavis regional, minorities. It is
				<lb />
				magapolitan and people from all parts flock to this
				<lb />
				outsized city. But we cannot exaggerate this factor,
				<lb />
				for the presence of the farther regions like the South
				<lb />
				and the Northeast, populationwise, is minimal and
				<lb />
				precarious. Shri Balakrishnan insisted that the
				<lb />
				23 (1980) 2 SCC 768
				<lb />
				University was sustained by Central Government
				<lb />
				finances, collected from the whole country, and the
				<lb />
				benefits must likewise belong to all qualified students
				<lb />
				from everywhere. These are valuable aspects to shape
				<lb />
				policy but the court must test constitutionality and
				<lb />
				no more. To that extent alone we will weigh these
				<lb />
				factors in moulding our verdict.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				xxx xxx xxx
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				56. We may windup by articulating the core thought
				<lb />
				that vitalises our approach. Anyone who lives inside
				<lb />
				India can never be considered an &apos;outsider&apos; in Delhi.
				<lb />
				The people in the States are caught in a happy
				<lb />
				network of mutuality, woven into a lovely garment of
				<lb />
				humanity, whose warp and woof is India. This is the
				<lb />
				underlying fundamental of the preambular resolve
				<lb />
				registered in our National Parchment. So we insist
				<lb />
				that blind and bigoted local patriotism in xenophobic
				<lb />
				exclusivism is destructive of our Freedom and only if
				<lb />
				compelling
				<lb />
				considerations
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				gross
				<lb />
				injustice,
				<lb />
				desperate backwardness and glaring inequality
				<lb />
				desiderate such a purposeful course can protective
				<lb />
				discrimination gain entrance into the portals of
				<lb />
				college campuses. The Administration has a
				<lb />
				constitutional responsibility not to be a mere
				<lb />
				thermometer where mercury rises with populist
				<lb />
				pressure but to be a thermostat that transforms the
				<lb />
				mores of groups to stay in the conscience of the
				<lb />
				nation viz. the Constitution.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				60.
				<lb />
				The Affidavit of the Union does not touch upon the
				<lb />
				details of Subordinate Services in other Union Territories.
				<lb />
				Neither the authorities of the other Union Territories have laid
				<lb />
				before the Court any relevant material in this regard. We,
				<lb />
				therefore, refrain from addressing the issue in question as far as
				<lb />
				other Union Territories are concerned and have confined our
				<lb />
				discussions and the consequential views only to the National
				<lb />
				Capital Territory of Delhi.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				61.
				<lb />
				Accordingly, we answer the question referred in terms
				<lb />
				of the views expressed in para 34 of this opinion. We further hold
				<lb />
				that so far as the National Capital Territory of Delhi is concerned
				<lb />
				the pan India Reservation Rule in force is in accord with the
				<lb />
				constitutional scheme relating to services under the Union and
				<lb />
				the States/Union Territories.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				62.
				<lb />
				In view of the conclusions reached as above, it will not
				<lb />
				be necessary to remit Civil Appeal Nos. 1085 of 2013, 10081 of
				<lb />
				2014, 8141 of 2014, 8802 of 2012, 1086 of 2013 and Civil Appeal
				<lb />
				arising out of Special Leave Petition (Civil) No.36324 of 2017
				<lb />
				(pertaining to Delhi) for further consideration by the appropriate
				<lb />
				Bench. Accordingly, we dispose of the said appeals (pertaining to
				<lb />
				Delhi) in terms of the present order.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				So far as Civil Appeal Nos.99359937 of 2014 pertaining to
				<lb />
				the U.T. of Andaman and Nicobar Island are concerned the issue
				<lb />
				may be decided by the appropriate Bench in the light of the views
				<lb />
				expressed herein on adequate and sufficient materials being
				<lb />
				placed before the Bench by the contesting parties.
				<lb />
				..……………………………………., J.
				<lb />
				[RANJAN GOGOI]
				<lb />
				..……………………………………., J.
				<lb />
				[N.V. RAMANA]
				<lb />
				..……………………………………., J.
				<lb />
				[MOHAN M. SHANTANAGOUDAR]
				<lb />
				..……………………………………., J.
				<lb />
				[S. ABDUL NAZEER]
				<lb />
				PLACE: NEW DELHI
				<lb />
				DATE: 30 th AUGUST, 2018
				<lb />
			</p>


			<head>
				J U D G M E N T
				<lb />
				R. BANUMATHI, J.
				<lb />
			</head>
			<p>
				Reference Order:-
				<lb />
				I have gone through the judgment proposed by His Lordship
				<lb />
				Justice Ranjan Gogoi. I agree with the following conclusions arrived at in
				<lb />
				paras (30) and (34) and the reasonings thereon.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;A person notified as a Scheduled Caste in State &apos;A&apos; cannot claim the
				<lb />
				same status in another State on the basis that he is declared as a
				<lb />
				Scheduled Caste in State &apos;A&apos;......&quot;.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				&quot;.......It will, therefore, be in consonance with the constitutional scheme
				<lb />
				to understand the enabling provision under Article 16(4) to be available
				<lb />
				to provide reservation only to the classes or categories of Scheduled
				<lb />
				Castes/Scheduled Tribes enumerated in the Presidential orders for a
				<lb />
				particular State/Union Territory within the geographical area of that
				<lb />
				State/Union Territory (Union Territory added by me) and not
				<lb />
				beyond.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				With due respect, I do not agree with the conclusion arrived at in para
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				(61) and the reasonings thereon.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;......So far as the National Capital Territory of Delhi is concerned the
				<lb />
				pan-India Reservation Rule in force is in accord with the constitutional
				<lb />
				scheme relating to services under the Union and the States/Union
				<lb />
				Territories.&quot;
				<lb />
				For agreeing with the conclusion arrived at in paras (30) and (34) and
				<lb />
				for differing from the conclusions in para (61) and the reasonings
				<lb />
				thereon, I have given my own reasonings.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				2.
				<lb />
				The extent and nature of interplay and interaction under Articles
				<lb />
				16(4), 341(1) and 342(1) of the Constitution of India was referred to the
				<lb />
				Constitution Bench in State of Uttaranchal v. Sandeep Kumar Singh
				<lb />
				and Ors., (2010) 12 SCC 794, with the following reference:-
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;13. A very important question of law as to interpretation of Articles
				<lb />
				16(4), 341 and 342 arises for consideration in this appeal. Whether the
				<lb />
				Presidential Order issued under Article 341(1) or Article 342(1) of the
				<lb />
				Constitution has any bearing on the State&apos;s action in making provision
				<lb />
				for the reservation of appointments or posts in favour of any Backward
				<lb />
				Class of citizens which, in the opinion of the State, is not adequately
				<lb />
				represented in the services under the State? The extent and nature of
				<lb />
				interplay and interaction among Articles 16(4), 341(1) and 342(1) of the
				<lb />
				Constitution is required to be resolved.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				3.
				<lb />
				Territory of India:-Article 1(1) of the Constitution of India
				<lb />
				declares that India, that is Bharat, shall be a Union of States. As
				<lb />
				amended by the Constitution Seventh (Amendment) Act, 1956. Article 1
				<lb />
				of the Constitution reads as under:-
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				1.
				<lb />
				Name and territory of the Union.-(1) India, that is Bharat,
				<lb />
				shall be a Union of States.
				<lb />
				(2) The States and the territories thereof shall be as specified in
				<lb />
				the First Schedule.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				(3) The territory of India shall comprise-
				<lb />
				(a) the territories of the States;
				<lb />
				(b) the Union Territories specified in the First Schedule; and
				<lb />
				(c) such other territories as may be acquired.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				4.
				<lb />
				Under the Constitution of India, as initially enacted, the States
				<lb />
				were divided into Part A States, Part B States, Part C States and the
				<lb />
				territories in Part D. Substantial changes were made by the Constitution
				<lb />
				(Seventh Amendment) Act,
				<lb />
				1956
				<lb />
				which
				<lb />
				incorporated
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				recommendations of the States Reorganisation Commission and was to
				<lb />
				have effect in concert with the States Reorganisation Act, 1956. The
				<lb />
				four categories of States that existed were reduced to two categories.
				<lb />
				The first of these categories -Part A and Part B States comprised one
				<lb />
				class, called &quot;States&quot;. The second category comprised the areas which
				<lb />
				had earlier been included in Part C and Part D States; these areas were
				<lb />
				called &quot;Union Territories&quot;. Some additions and deletions were made to
				<lb />
				the existing lists. Now as per Schedule I, there are twenty-nine States
				<lb />
				and Seven Union Territories.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				5.
				<lb />
				The expression &quot;State&quot; is not defined in the Constitution. It is
				<lb />
				defined in the General Clauses Act, 1897 which is made applicable to
				<lb />
				the interpretation of the Constitution by Article 367. As on the date of the
				<lb />
				commencement of the Constitution, clause (58) in Section 3 of the
				<lb />
				General Clauses Act, 1897 defined &quot;State&quot; in the following words:-
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;3. (58) &apos;State&apos;, -shall mean a Part A State, a Part B State or a Part C
				<lb />
				State.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				The said definition was amended by the Adaptation of Laws Order No. 1
				<lb />
				of 1956 issued by the President in exercise of the power conferred upon
				<lb />
				him by Article 372-A of the Constitution introduced by the Constitution
				<lb />
				Seventh (Amendment) Act, 1956. The amended definition &apos;State&apos; reads
				<lb />
				thus:-
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;3. (58) &apos;State&apos;, -
				<lb />
				(a) as respects any period before the commencement of the
				<lb />
				Constitution (Seventh Amendment) Act, 1956, shall mean a Part A
				<lb />
				State, a Part B State or a Part C State; and
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				(b) as respects any period after such commencement, shall
				<lb />
				mean a State specified in the First Schedule to the Constitution and
				<lb />
				shall include a Union Territory.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				6.
				<lb />
				Clause (30) in Article 366 defines the &quot;Union Territory&quot; in the
				<lb />
				following words:-
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				&quot;366. (30) &apos;Union Territory&apos; means any Union Territory specified in the
				<lb />
				First Schedule and includes any other territory comprised with the
				<lb />
				territory of India but not specified in that Schedule.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				7.
				<lb />
				Clause (24) of Article 366 defines &quot;Scheduled Castes&quot; and clause
				<lb />
				(25) of Article 366 defines &quot;Scheduled Tribes&quot;. The latter means &quot;such
				<lb />
				tribes or tribal communities or parts of or groups within such tribes or
				<lb />
				tribal communities as are deemed under Article 342 to be &apos;Scheduled
				<lb />
				Tribes&apos; for the purposes of this Constitution&quot;. Article 341(1) of the
				<lb />
				Constitution empowers the President, in consultation with the Governor
				<lb />
				of the State concerned, to specify Scheduled Castes by public
				<lb />
				notification. Equally, Article 342(1) of the Constitution empowers the
				<lb />
				President &quot;with respect to any State or Union Territory, and where it is a
				<lb />
				State, after consultation with the Governor thereof, by public notification,
				<lb />
				specify the tribes or tribal communities or parts of or groups within tribes
				<lb />
				or tribal communities which shall for the purposes of this Constitution be
				<lb />
				deemed to be &apos;Scheduled Tribes&apos; in relation to that State or Union
				<lb />
				Territory, as the case may be&quot;. Article 342(2) of the Constitution
				<lb />
				empowers &quot;Parliament, by law, to include in or exclude from the list of
				<lb />
				&apos;Scheduled Tribes&apos; specified in a notification issued under clause (1),
				<lb />
				any tribe or tribal community or part of or group within any tribe or tribal
				<lb />
				community, but save as aforesaid a notification issued under the said
				<lb />
				clause shall not be varied by any subsequent notification.&quot; Until the
				<lb />
				Presidential Notification is modified by appropriate amendment by
				<lb />
				Parliament in exercise of the power under Article 341(2) of the
				<lb />
				Constitution, the Presidential Notification issued under Article 341(1) is
				<lb />
				final and conclusive and any caste or group cannot be added to it or
				<lb />
				subtracted by any action either by the State Government or by a Court
				<lb />
				on adducing of evidence. In other words, it is the constitutional mandate
				<lb />
				that the tribes or tribal communities or parts of or groups within such
				<lb />
				tribes or tribal communities specified by the President, after consultation
				<lb />
				with the Governor in the public notification, will be &apos;Scheduled Tribes&apos;
				<lb />
				subject to the law made by Parliament alone, which may, by law, include
				<lb />
				in or exclude from the list of &apos;Scheduled Tribes&apos; specified by the
				<lb />
				President. Thereafter, it cannot be varied except by law made by the
				<lb />
				Parliament.
				<lb />
			</p>

			<p>
				8.
				<lb />
				The President of India alone is competent or authorized to issue
				<lb />
				an appropriate Notification in terms of Article 341(1) and Article 342(1).
				<lb />
				Cumulative reading of Articles 338, 341 and 342 indicate that:-
				<lb />
			</p>

			<item>
				a) Only the President could notify castes/tribes as
				<lb />
				Scheduled Castes/Tribes and also indicate conditions
				<lb />
				attaching to such declaration. A public Notification by the
				<lb />
				President specifying the particular castes or tribes as
				<lb />
				SC/ST shall be final for the purpose of Constitution and
				<lb />
				shall be exhaustive.
				<lb />
			</item>

			<item>
				b) Once a notification is issued under clause (1) of Articles
				<lb />
				341 and 342 of the Constitution, the Parliament can by
				<lb />
				law include in or exclude from the list of Scheduled
				<lb />
				Castes or Scheduled Tribes, specified in the notification,
				<lb />
				any caste or tribe but save for that limited purpose the
				<lb />
				notification issued under clause (1), shall not be varied
				<lb />
				by any subsequent notification 24 .
				<lb />
			</item>

			<p>
				9.
				<lb />
				It is stated that before notification was issued under
				<lb />
				Article
				<lb />
				341(1) and Article 342(1) notifying certain caste/race or group as
				<lb />
				Scheduled Caste/Scheduled Tribe, an elaborate enquiry was made and
				<lb />
				also after such enquiry, the Presidential Order was issued. While doing
				<lb />
				so, Presidential Order not only specified parts or groups of caste, races
				<lb />
				or tribes but also made the said specification by reference to different
				<lb />
				areas in the State. By perusal of the Presidential Order, it is clear that
				<lb />
				some caste/race is actually confined with reference to a particular area;
				<lb />
				for instance, confined to a particular taluk in a district. The reason for
				<lb />
				such specification by reference to different areas in the State being
				<lb />
				educational, social backwardness, races or tribes cannot be the same
				<lb />
				throughout the State. The consideration for specifying a particular caste
				<lb />
				or tribe or class for inclusion in the list of Scheduled Castes and
				<lb />
				Scheduled Tribes or Backward Classes in a given State would depend
				<lb />
				on the nature and extent of the disadvantages and social hardships
				<lb />
					suffered in that State. These may be absent in another State to which
					<lb />
					these persons belonging to other States may migrate.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					10. Whenever States&apos; reorganization took place in the past, Parliament
					<lb />
					exercised its powers under Articles 341(2) and 342(2) and provided for
					<lb />
					specific Castes/Tribes that had to be Scheduled Castes and Scheduled
					<lb />
					Tribes in relation to the reorganized States/Union Territories. The
					<lb />
					Constitution Scheduled Caste Orders and the Constitution Scheduled
					<lb />
					Castes (Union Territories) Order, also clarify that Parliament&apos;s intention
					<lb />
					was to extend benefits of reservation in relation to the States/Union
					<lb />
					Territories in terms of the castes, races or tribes mentioned as per the
					<lb />
					Presidential Orders themselves.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					11. Presidential Order which provided for castes/races, tribes
					<lb />
					recognized as &apos;Scheduled Caste/Scheduled Tribe&apos; and their
					<lb />
					interpretation cannot be challenged or agitated in a court of law. The
					<lb />
					question whether Dohar caste is a sub-caste of Chamar caste which is
					<lb />
					recognized as a Scheduled Caste came up for consideration in Bhaiya
					<lb />
					Lal v. Harikishan Singh, AIR 1965 SC 1557, wherein this Court held
					<lb />
					that the court cannot enquire into whether Dohar caste is a sub-caste of
					<lb />
					Chamar caste and whether the same must be deemed to have been
					<lb />
					included in the Presidential Order. In Bhaiya Lal&apos;s case, this Court held
					<lb />
					&quot;...that before a notification is issued under Article 341(1), an elaborate
					<lb />
					enquiry is made and it is as a result of this enquiry that social justice is
					<lb />
					sought to be done to the castes, races or tribes as may appear to be
					<lb />
					necessary, and in doing justice...&quot; and while doing so, the notification not
					<lb />
					only to specify parts or groups of castes, races or tribes but to make
					<lb />
					specification by reference to different areas in the State. In Bhaiya
					<lb />
					Lal&apos;s case, the Supreme Court held that only the Parliament is
					<lb />
					empowered to amend the Notification under Articles 341(2) and 342(2)
					<lb />
					of the Constitution.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					12. Presidential Notification (Scheduled Caste) Order 1950:-The
					<lb />
					List of Scheduled Castes is contained in the Constitution (Scheduled
					<lb />
					Castes) Order 1950. The Presidential Notifications of 1950 and 1951
					<lb />
					(as amended) in relation to Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes of
					<lb />
					various States, very importantly provided that:-
					<lb />
				</p>


				<item>
					2. Subject to the provisions of this Order, the castes, races or tribes
					<lb />
					or parts of, or groups within, castes or tribes specified in [Parts I to
					<lb />
					XXV] of the Schedule to this Order shall, in relation to the States to
					<lb />
					which those Parts respectively relate, be deemed to be Scheduled
					<lb />
					Castes so far as regards members thereof resident in the localities
					<lb />
					specified in relation to them respectively in those Parts of that
					<lb />
					Schedule.&quot;
					<lb />
				</item>

				<p>
					The Presidential Notification of 1950 was amended by the Constitution
					<lb />
					(Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes Order), Amendment Act,
					<lb />
					1956, (Act No.63 of 1956). Another amending Act was enacted by
					<lb />
					Parliament in 1976. Further, amendments had taken place as and when
					<lb />
					Parliament reorganized States like Bombay, Andhra Pradesh,
					<lb />
					Uttarakhand, Chhattisgarh and Jharkhand through separate Acts. All
					<lb />
					these were Parliamentary enactments. Presidential Notification
					<lb />
					pertaining to Union Territories, Scheduled Castes (Union Territories)
					<lb />
					Order, 1951 specifies Scheduled Castes resident in the Union Territories
					<lb />
					of Delhi, Chandigarh and Daman and Diu. When new Union Territories
					<lb />
					were formed such as Pondicherry, Sikkim, Goa, Daman and Diu,
					<lb />
					Arunachal Pradesh, Mizoram, the Scheduled Castes or Scheduled
					<lb />
					Tribes Orders were made in relation to those new Union Territories.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					13. The Constitution (Scheduled Tribes) Order, 1950 25 :-In exercise
					<lb />
					of the powers conferred by clause (1) of Article 342 of the Constitution of
					<lb />
					India the President has, after consultation with the Governors of the
					<lb />
					States concerned, made the Constitution (Scheduled Tribes) Order,
					<lb />
					1950, specifying the tribes or communities which shall be deemed to be
					<lb />
					Scheduled Tribes in the States mentioned therein. This Order has been
					<lb />
					amended by the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes Orders
					<lb />
					(Amendment) Act, 1976 (Act No.108 of 1976), the Constitution
					<lb />
					(Scheduled Tribes) Order (Amendment) Act, 1991 (16 of 1991), the
					<lb />
					Constitution (Scheduled Tribes) Order (Second Amendment) Act, 1991
					<lb />
					(39 of 1991), the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes Orders
					<lb />
					(Amendment) Act, 2002 (32 of 2002), the Scheduled Castes and
					<lb />
					Scheduled Tribes Orders (Amendment) Act, 2002 (10 of 2003), the
					<lb />
					Constitution (Scheduled Tribes) Order (Amendment) Act, 2003 (47 of
					<lb />
					2003), the Constitution (Scheduled Tribes) Order (Amendment) Act 2006
					<lb />
					(48 of 2006), the Constitution (Scheduled Tribes) Order (Amendment)
					<lb />
					Act, 2008 (14 of 2008) and the Constitution (Scheduled Tribes) Union
					<lb />
					Territories Order (Amendment) Act, 2008 (2 of 2009). As it stands
					<lb />
					amended, it specifies the Scheduled Tribes resident in the States of
					<lb />
					Andhra Pradesh, Assam, Bihar, Gujarat, Himachal Pradesh, Karnataka,
					<lb />
					Kerala, Madhya Pradesh, Maharashtra, Manipur, Meghalaya, Orissa,
					<lb />
					Rajasthan, Tamil Nadu, Tripura, West Bengal.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					14. Article 16(4) is only an enabling provision to provide reservation to
					<lb />
					backward classes. Clause (4) of Article 16 of the Constitution cannot be
					<lb />
					made applicable for the purpose of grant of benefit of reservation for
					<lb />
					Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes in a State or Union Territory, who
					<lb />
					have migrated to another State or Union Territory and they are not
					<lb />
					members of the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes in the State to
					<lb />
					which they have migrated. The Presidential Orders made under Article
					<lb />
					341 and Article 342 have an overriding status. The presence of Articles
					<lb />
					338, 338A, 341, 342 of the Constitution clearly shows that it precludes
					<lb />
					any tinkering or deviation from the list of castes or tribes notified in the
					<lb />
					Presidential Order which are reserved for that State or that Union
					<lb />
					territory.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					15. India is huge. There is Unity in Diversity. Diversity in terms of
					<lb />
					language, culture, demography, geographical area, development of
					<lb />
					regions, opportunities available to individuals for education and to make
					<lb />
					social and economical advancement etc. Some States are well-
					<lb />
					developed; some other States are developing; few other States are
					<lb />
					under-developed. All the affirmative action of the States is to provide
					<lb />
					equality of opportunity to the socially and economically disadvantaged
					<lb />
					group. Under Article 15(4) of the Constitution, State is empowered to
					<lb />
					make special provisions for the advancement of any socially and
					<lb />
					educationally backward class of citizens or for the Scheduled Castes or
					<lb />
					Scheduled Tribes. Article 16 of the Constitution of India lays down that
					<lb />
					there shall be equality of opportunity for all citizens in matters relating to
					<lb />
					employment or appointment to any office under the State. Article 16(4)
					<lb />
					of the Constitution empowers the State to make provisions to provide
					<lb />
					reservation to the backward classes in employment or appointment to
					<lb />
					any posts and thereby to create equally opportunities for their socio-
					<lb />
					economic empowerment and their emancipation. Article 16(4) speaks of
					<lb />
					one type of reservation namely reservation of appointments/posts.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					16. Article 16(4) of the Constitution is an enabling provision directed
					<lb />
					towards achieving equality of opportunity in services under the State.
					<lb />
					Observing that Article 14 of the Constitution is the genus while Article 16
					<lb />
					is the species, in E. P. Royappa v. State of Tamil Nadu and Anr.,
					<lb />
					(1974) 4 SCC 3, it was held that:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<item>
					&quot;85. .........Article 16 embodies the fundamental guarantee that there
					<lb />
					shall be equality of opportunity for all citizens in matters relating to
					<lb />
					employment or appointment to any office under the State. Though
					<lb />
					enacted as a distinct and independent fundamental right because of its
					<lb />
					great importance as a principle ensuring equality of opportunity in
					<lb />
					public employment which is so vital to the building up of the new
					<lb />
					classless egalitarian society envisaged in the Constitution, Article 16 is
					<lb />
					only an instance of the application of the concept of equality enshrined
					<lb />
					in Article 14. In other words, Article 14 is the genus while Article 16 is a
					<lb />
					species. Article 16 gives effect to the doctrine of equality in all matters
					<lb />
					relating to public employment. The basic principle which, therefore,
					<lb />
					informs both Articles 14 and 16 is equality and inhibition against
					<lb />
					discrimination. Now, what is the content and reach of this great
					<lb />
					equalising principle? It is a founding faith, to use the words of Bose. J.,
					<lb />
					&quot;a way of life&quot;, and it must not be subjected to a narrow pedantic or
					<lb />
					lexicographic approach. We cannot countenance any attempt to
					<lb />
					truncate its all-embracing scope and meaning, for to do so would be to
					<lb />
					violate its activist magnitude. Equality is a dynamic concept with many
					<lb />
					aspects and dimensions and it cannot be &quot;cribbed, cabined and
					<lb />
					confined&quot; within traditional and doctrinaire limits........&quot; [Underlining
					<lb />
					added]
					<lb />
				</item>

				<p>
					17. The Constitution Bench of nine Judges in Indra Sawhney and
					<lb />
					Ors. v. Union of India and Ors., (1992) Supp 3 SCC 217, observed
					<lb />
					that Article 16(4) of the Constitution is aimed at &apos;protective equality&apos; and
					<lb />
					it was held as under:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<item>
					&quot;563. Thus, Article 16(1) and (4) operate in the same field. Both are
					<lb />
					directed towards achieving equality of opportunity in services under the
					<lb />
					State. One is broader in sweep and expansive in reach. Other is
					<lb />
					limited in approach and narrow in applicability. Former applies to &apos;all&apos;
					<lb />
					citizens whereas latter is available to &apos;any&apos; in Article 16(4) read together
					<lb />
					indicate that they are part of same scheme. The one is substantive
					<lb />
					equality and other is protective equality. Article 16(1) is fundamental
					<lb />
					right of a citizen whereas Article 16(4) is an obligation of the State.
					<lb />
					The former is enforceable in a Court of law, whereas the latter is &apos;not
					<lb />
					constitutional compulsion&apos; but an enabling provision. Whether Article
					<lb />
					16(4) is in substance, &apos;an exception&apos;, &apos;a proviso&apos;, or an &apos;emphatic way of
					<lb />
					putting the extent to which equality of opportunity could be carried&apos;, or
					<lb />
					&apos;presumed to exhaust all exceptions in favour of backward class&apos;, or
					<lb />
					&apos;expressly designed as benign discrimination devoted to lifting to
					<lb />
					backward classes&apos;, but if Article 16(1) is the positive aspect of equality
					<lb />
					of opportunity&apos;, Article 16(4) is a complete Code for reservation for
					<lb />
					backward class of citizens as it not only provides for exercise of power
					<lb />
					but also lays down the circumstances, in which the power can be
					<lb />
					exercised, and the purpose and extent or its exercise. One is
					<lb />
					mandatory and operates automatically whereas the other comes into
					<lb />
					play on identification of backward class of citizens and their inadequate
					<lb />
					representation.&quot; [Underlining added]
					<lb />
				</item>

				<p>
					18. Article 16(4) of the Constitution is not an exception; but a facet of
					<lb />
					Article 14 and Article 16(1) of the Constitution; it enables the State to
					<lb />
					effectuate equality of opportunity to any backward class. As held in
					<lb />
					Chattar Singh and Ors. v. State of Rajasthan and Ors. (1996) 11
					<lb />
					SCC 742 in paras (17) and (18), that &quot;....It gives power to the state to
					<lb />
					effectuate the opportunity of equality to any backward class of citizens.
					<lb />
					……..The object of reservation for the Scheduled Casts and Scheduled
					<lb />
					Tribes is to bring them into the mainstream of national life, while the
					<lb />
					objective in respect of the backward classes is to remove their social
					<lb />
					and educational handicaps. Therefore, they are always treated
					<lb />
					dissimilar and they do not form an integrated class with Dalits and Tribes
					<lb />
					for the purpose of Article 16(4) or 15 (4)...&quot;.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					19. In State of Kerala and Anr. v. N.M. Thomas and Ors. (1976) 2
					<lb />
					SCC 310 in para (178), it was held that &quot;...differences and disparities
					<lb />
					exist among men and things and they cannot be treated alike by the
					<lb />
					application of the same laws but the law has to come in terms with life
					<lb />
					and must be able to recognize the genuine differences and disparities
					<lb />
					that exist in human nature. Legislature has also to enact legislation to
					<lb />
					meet specific ends by making a reasonable and rational classification..&quot;.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					20. A Constitution Bench of this Court in Marri Chandra Shekhar Rao
					<lb />
					v. Dean, Seth G.S. Medical College and Ors., (1990) 3 SCC 130 had
					<lb />
					the occasion to consider the question as to whether a member of Gouda
					<lb />
					community which is recognised as &quot;Scheduled Tribe&quot; in the Constitution
					<lb />
					(Scheduled Tribes) Order, 1950 would be entitled to admission in a
					<lb />
					medical institution situated in the State of Maharashtra. Based on the
					<lb />
					Government of India circular dated 22.02.1985, the appellant was
					<lb />
					denied admission to the Medical College on the ground that Marri
					<lb />
					Chandra Shekhar Rao was not a &apos;Scheduled Tribe&apos; in the migrated State
					<lb />
					i.e. State of Maharashtra.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					21. After referring to various provisions of Constitution of India,
					<lb />
					background in which the Presidential Order was issued and earlier
					<lb />
					judgments, in Marri Chandra Shekhar Rao&apos;s case, it was held as
					<lb />
					under:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<item>
					&quot;9. It appears that Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes in some
					<lb />
					States had to suffer the social disadvantages and did not have the
					<lb />
					facilities for development and growth. It is, therefore, necessary in
					<lb />
					order to make them equal in those areas where they have so suffered
					<lb />
					and are in the state of underdevelopment to have reservations or
					<lb />
					protection in their favour so that they can compete on equal terms with
					<lb />
					the more advantageous or developed sections of the community.
					<lb />
					Extreme social and economic backwardness arising out of traditional
					<lb />
					practices of untouchability is normally considered as criterion for
					<lb />
					including a community in the list of Scheduled Castes and Scheduled
					<lb />
					Tribes. The social conditions of a caste, however, varies from State to
					<lb />
					State and it will not be proper to generalise any caste or any tribe as a
					<lb />
					Scheduled Tribe or Scheduled Caste for the whole country. This,
					<lb />
					however, is a different problem whether a member or the Scheduled
					<lb />
					Caste in one part of the country who migrates to another State or any
					<lb />
					other Union territory should continue to be treated as a Scheduled
					<lb />
					Caste or Scheduled Tribe in which he has migrated. That question has
					<lb />
					to be judged taking into consideration the interest and well-being of the
					<lb />
					Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes in the country as a whole.&quot;
					<lb />
				</item>

				<p>
					22. Marri Chandra Shekhar Rao case was followed by another
					<lb />
					Constitution Bench of this Court in Action Committee on issue of
					<lb />
					caste certificate to Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes in the
					<lb />
					State of Maharashtra and Anr. v. Union of India and Anr. (1994) 5
					<lb />
					SCC 244. In Action Committee&apos;s case, it was held as under:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<item>
					&quot;3. On a plain reading of clause (1) of Articles 341 and 342 it is
					<lb />
					manifest that the power of the President is limited to specifying the
					<lb />
					castes or tribes which shall, for the purposes of the Constitution, be
					<lb />
					deemed to be Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes in relation to a
					<lb />
					State or a Union Territory, as the case may be. Once a notification is
					<lb />
					issued under clause (1) of Articles 341 and 342 of the Constitution,
					<lb />
					Parliament can by law include in or exclude from the list of Scheduled
					<lb />
					Castes or Scheduled Tribes, specified in the notification, any caste or
					<lb />
					tribe but save for that limited purpose the notification issued under
					<lb />
					clause (1), shall not be varied by any subsequent notification. What is
					<lb />
					important to notice is that the castes or tribes have to be specified in
					<lb />
					relation to a given State or Union Territory. That means a given caste
					<lb />
					or tribe can be a Scheduled Caste or a Scheduled Tribe in relation to
					<lb />
					the State or Union Territory for which it is specified. These are the
					<lb />
					relevant provisions with which we shall be concerned while dealing
					<lb />
					with the grievance made in this petition.
					<lb />
					....
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					16. We may add that considerations for specifying a particular caste or
					<lb />
					tribe or class for inclusion in the list of Scheduled Castes/Schedule
					<lb />
					Tribes or backward classes in a given State would depend on the
					<lb />
					nature and extent of disadvantages and social hardships suffered by
					<lb />
					that caste, tribe or class in that State which may be totally non est in
					<lb />
					another State to which persons belonging thereto may migrate.
					<lb />
					Coincidentally it may be that a caste or tribe bearing the same
					<lb />
					nomenclature is specified in two States but the considerations on the
					<lb />
					basis of which they have been specified may be totally different. So
					<lb />
					also the degree of disadvantages of various elements which constitute
					<lb />
					the input for specification may also be totally different. Therefore,
					<lb />
					merely because a given caste is specified in State A as a Scheduled
					<lb />
					Caste does not necessarily mean that if there be another caste bearing
					<lb />
					the same nomenclature in another State the person belonging to the
					<lb />
					former would be entitled to the rights, privileges and benefits
					<lb />
					admissible to a member of the Scheduled Caste of the latter State &quot;for
					<lb />
					the purposes of this Constitution&quot;. This is an aspect which has to be
					<lb />
					kept in mind and which was very much in the minds of the Constitution-
					<lb />
					makers as is evident from the choice of language of Articles 341 and
					<lb />
					342 of the Constitution....&quot;
					<lb />
				</item>

				<p>
					Marri Chandra Shekhar Rao&apos;s case and Action Committee&apos;s case
					<lb />
					were followed in Subhash Chandra and Anr. v. Delhi Subordinate
					<lb />
					Services Selection Board and Ors., (2009) 15 SCC 458. In Subhash
					<lb />
					Chandra case, the Supreme Court reiterated that &quot;If a caste or tribe is
					<lb />
					notified in terms of the Scheduled Castes Order or the Scheduled Tribes
					<lb />
					Order, the same must be done in terms of clause (1) of Article 341 as
					<lb />
					also that of Article 342 of the Constitution of India, as the case may be.
					<lb />
					No deviation from the procedure laid down therein is permissible in law.
					<lb />
					If any amendment/alteration thereto is required to be made, recourse to
					<lb />
					the procedure laid down under clause (2) thereof must be resorted to.&quot;
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					23. In Marri Chandra Shekhar Rao&apos;s case, it was held that a
					<lb />
					Scheduled Caste or Scheduled Tribe of any State which depends on the
					<lb />
					nature and extent of disadvantages and social hardships suffered by the
					<lb />
					caste, tribe or class in that State or area may be non-existent in another
					<lb />
					State. The inclusion of the castes, races or tribes is mainly based on the
					<lb />
					degree of disadvantages or hardships faced by the castes, races or
					<lb />
					tribes in that State or in some cases or in part area of the State. For
					<lb />
					instance, in the Presidential Order relating to the State of Tamil Nadu,
					<lb />
					the caste Kanikaran, Kanikkar (in Kanyakumari District and Shenkottah
					<lb />
					and Ambasaundram taluks of Tirunelveli district) are notified as
					<lb />
					Scheduled Castes. This shows that the President can specify castes,
					<lb />
					races or tribes or parts thereof in relation not only to the entire State but
					<lb />
					in relation to the parts of the State. The President has been authorised
					<lb />
					to limit the notification to parts of the State or groups within castes, races
					<lb />
					or tribes. In Marri Chandra Shekhar Rao case, the Constitution Bench
					<lb />
					therefore held that the expression &quot;in relation to that State&quot; must be read
					<lb />
					meaningfully; otherwise the expression &quot;in relation to that State&quot; would
					<lb />
					come nugatory.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					24. The Presidential Order issued under Article 341 of the Constitution
					<lb />
					in regard to Scheduled Castes and Article 342 of the Constitution in
					<lb />
					regard to Scheduled Tribes cannot be varied by anyone or by the Court.
					<lb />
					Only the Parliament by law include or exclude from the list of Scheduled
					<lb />
					Castes or Scheduled Tribes specified in a notification issued under
					<lb />
					Article 341(1) and Article 342(1) of the Constitution respectively any
					<lb />
					caste, race or tribe or parts or group within any caste, race or tribe. The
					<lb />
					Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes thus specified in relation to one
					<lb />
					State or Union Territory does not carry their status in another State or
					<lb />
					Union Territory. When the Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes are
					<lb />
					specified for each State and in some cases, specific areas of the State
					<lb />
					or Union Territory, neither the State legislature nor the courts can include
					<lb />
					or exclude other Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes so specified in
					<lb />
					some States or Union Territories which would be against the mandate of
					<lb />
					Articles 341 and 342 of the Constitution and the Presidential Orders
					<lb />
					issued thereon. If that is permitted, it would amount to addition or
					<lb />
					alteration of the Presidential Order which is violative of the Constitutional
					<lb />
					Scheme.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					25. State of Maharashtra v. Milind and Ors. (2001) 1 SCC 4, dealt
					<lb />
					with a question as to whether the notified Scheduled Tribe being Halba
					<lb />
					or Halbi as contained in item 19 of the Presidential Order would include
					<lb />
					&quot;Halba-Koshti&quot;. This Court held that addition of &quot;Halba-Koshti&quot; in the
					<lb />
					Presidential Order would amount to amendment thereto which is
					<lb />
					impermissible in law. In Milind&apos;s case, it was held as under:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<item>
					&quot;33......The jurisdiction of the High Court would be much more
					<lb />
					restricted while dealing with the question whether a particular caste or
					<lb />
					tribe would come within the purview of the notified Presidential Order,
					<lb />
					considering the language of Articles 341 and 342 of the Constitution.
					<lb />
					These being the parameters and in the case in hand, the Committee
					<lb />
					conducting the inquiry as well as the Appellate Authority, having
					<lb />
					examined all relevant materials and having recorded a finding that
					<lb />
					Respondent 1 belonged to &quot;Koshti&quot; caste and has no identity with
					<lb />
					&quot;Halba/Halbi&quot; which is the Scheduled Tribe under Entry 19 of the
					<lb />
					Presidential Order, relating to the State of Maharashtra, the High Court
					<lb />
					exceeded its supervisory jurisdiction by making a roving and in-depth
					<lb />
					examination of the materials afresh and in coming to the conclusion
					<lb />
					that &quot;Koshtis&quot; could be treated as &quot;Halbas&quot;. In this view the High Court
					<lb />
					could not upset the finding of fact in exercise of its writ jurisdiction.
					<lb />
					Hence, we have to essentially answer Question 2 also in the negative.
					<lb />
					Hence it is answered accordingly.&quot;
					<lb />
				</item>

				<p>
					26. When the Parliament restricts the benefit of reservation by
					<lb />
					inclusion of a caste as a Scheduled Caste to a State or part of State i.e.
					<lb />
					certain specified districts in a State, the Court cannot express any
					<lb />
					opinion as to its correctness. Hence, as regards the inclusion of
					<lb />
					caste &quot;Mochi&quot; in the list of Scheduled Castes within a particular area
					<lb />
					as per Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order
					<lb />
					(Second
					<lb />
					Amendment) Act, 2002, it was held that it was not for the Court to
					<lb />
					render any opinion in regard to the correctness of the same. [vide
					<lb />
					Shree Surat Valsad Jilla K.M.G.
					<lb />
					Parishad v. Union of
					<lb />
					India and Ors. (2007) 5 SCC 360].
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					27. The executive instructions/circulars issued by the Government of
					<lb />
					India also reiterate to well-settled position. The circular
					<lb />
					No.
					<lb />
					BC-16014/1/82-SC &amp; BCD-I dated 06.08.1984 of the Ministry of Home
					<lb />
					Affairs addressed to all State Governments and UT Administration states
					<lb />
					that SC and ST on migration from the State of his origin to another
					<lb />
					State will not lose his status as SC/ST;
					<lb />
					but will be entitled to the
					<lb />
					concession/benefits admissible to the SC/ST from the State of his origin
					<lb />
					and not from the State where he has migrated. The relevant portion of
					<lb />
					the said circular reads as under:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<item>
					No. BC-16014/1/82-SC &amp; BCD-I
					<lb />
					Government of India/Bharat Sarkar
					<lb />
					Ministry of Home Affairs/GrihMantralaya
					<lb />
					New Delhi, the 6 th August, 1984
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					To,
					<lb />
					The Chief Secretaries of All State
					<lb />
					Governments and U.T. Administrations.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					Subject: -Verification of claim of candidates belonging to
					<lb />
					Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes and migrants from other
					<lb />
					States/Union Territories-Form of certificate-Amendment to.
					<lb />
					Sir,
					<lb />
					……..
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					2.
					<lb />
					The instructions issued in this Ministry&apos;s letter of even number
					<lb />
					dated the 18.11.1982 will continue. It is, however, clarified that the
					<lb />
					Scheduled Caste/Scheduled Tribe person on migration from the State
					<lb />
					of his origin to another State will not lose his status as Scheduled
					<lb />
					Caste/Scheduled Tribes but he will be entitled to the
					<lb />
					concessions/benefits admissible to the Scheduled Castes/Scheduled
					<lb />
					Tribes from the State of his origin and not from the State where he has
					<lb />
					migrated……
					<lb />
					(Underlining added)
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					Yours faithfully
					<lb />
					Sd/-
					<lb />
					Joint Secretary to Govt. of India
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					28. The same thing was reiterated in the circular dated 22.02.1985
					<lb />
					issued by the Ministry of Home Affairs which has also clarified that a
					<lb />
					Scheduled Caste/Scheduled Tribe person who has migrated from the
					<lb />
					State of origin to some other State for the purpose of seeking education,
					<lb />
					employment, etc. will be deemed to be a Scheduled Caste/Tribe of the
					<lb />
					State of his origin and will be entitled to derive benefits from the State of
					<lb />
					origin and not from the State to which he has migrated.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<p>
					29. My Conclusion for agreeing with the view taken in paras (30)
					<lb />
					and (32):-It is now settled law that a person belonging to Scheduled
					<lb />
					Caste/Scheduled Tribe in State &apos;A&apos; cannot claim the same status in
					<lb />
					another State &apos;B&apos; on the ground that he is declared as a Scheduled
					<lb />
					Caste/Scheduled Tribe in State &apos;A&apos;. The expressions &quot;in relation to that
					<lb />
					State or Union Territory&quot; and &quot;for the purpose of this Constitution&quot; used
					<lb />
					in Articles 341 and 342 of the Constitution of India are to be meaningfully
					<lb />
					interpreted. A given caste or tribe can be a Scheduled Caste or a
					<lb />
					Scheduled Tribe in relation to that State or Union Territory for which it is
					<lb />
					specified. Thus, the person notified as a Scheduled Caste in State &apos;A&apos;
					<lb />
					cannot claim the same status in another State on the basis that he was
					<lb />
					declared Scheduled Caste in State &apos;A&apos;. Article 16(4) has to yield to the
					<lb />
					Constitutional mandate of Articles 341 and 342.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					Union Territories:
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					30. Part VIII of the Constitution of India deals with Union Territories.
					<lb />
					Article 239 provides that the Union Territory shall be administered by the
					<lb />
					President acting through an Administrator to be appointed by him.
					<lb />
					Article 239 reads as follows:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<item>
					&quot;239. Administration of Union Territories
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					(1) Save as otherwise provided by Parliament by law, every Union
					<lb />
					Territory shall be administered by the President acting, to such extent
					<lb />
					as he thinks fit, through an administrator to be appointed by him with
					<lb />
					such designation as he may specify.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					(2)
					<lb />
					Notwithstanding anything contained in Part VI, the President
					<lb />
					may appoint the Governor of a State as the administrator of an
					<lb />
					adjoining Union Territory, and where a Governor is so appointed, he
					<lb />
					shall exercise his functions as such administrator independently of his
					<lb />
					Council of Ministers.&quot;
					<lb />
				</item>

				<p>
					31. Article 239A was inserted by the Constitution (Fourteenth
					<lb />
					Amendment) Act, 1962. Article 239A of the Constitution of India
					<lb />
					empowers the Parliament to create by law legislatures and Council of
					<lb />
					Ministers in the then Union Territories of Himachal Pradesh, Manipur,
					<lb />
					Goa, Daman &amp; Diu and Pondicherry. Arunachal Pradesh and Mizoram
					<lb />
					were added later. With Himachal Pradesh, Manipur, Tripura, Goa and
					<lb />
					Mizoram all becoming full-fledged States, the only Union Territory left
					<lb />
					under Article 239A is Pondicherry. Now, Union Territory of Pondicherry
					<lb />
					(Puducherry) also has a legislature and Council of Ministers.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					32. Article 341 empowers the President &quot;with respect to any State or
					<lb />
					Union Territory, and where it is a State, after consultation with the
					<lb />
					Governor thereof, by public notification, specify the castes, races or
					<lb />
					tribes or parts of or groups within castes, races or tribes which shall for
					<lb />
					the purposes of this Constitution, be deemed to be Scheduled Caste in
					<lb />
					relation to that State or Union Territory as the case may be.&quot; Equally
					<lb />
					Article 342(1) empowers the President &quot;with respect to any State or
					<lb />
					Union Territory, and where it is a State, after consultation with the
					<lb />
					Governor thereof, by public notification, specify the tribes or tribal
					<lb />
					communities or parts of or groups within tribes or tribal communities
					<lb />
					which shall for the purposes of the Constitution be deemed to be
					<lb />
					Scheduled Tribes in relation to that State or Union Territory, as the case
					<lb />
					may be&quot;. Articles 341(2) and 342(2) of the Constitution empower the
					<lb />
					Parliament alone by law to include or exclude from the list of Scheduled
					<lb />
					Castes/Scheduled Tribes specified by notification issued under Articles
					<lb />
					341(1) and 342(1) of the Constitution of India. Until the Presidential
					<lb />
					Notification is modified by appropriate amendment by Parliament in
					<lb />
					exercise of the power under Articles 341(2) or 342(2) of the Constitution,
					<lb />
					the Presidential Notification issued under Articles 341(1) and 342(1) of
					<lb />
					the Constitution is final and conclusive. No caste or group can be added
					<lb />
					to it or subtracted by any action either by the State Government or by a
					<lb />
					Court on adducing of evidence. Articles 341 and 342 of the Constitution
					<lb />
					do not make any distinction between a &apos;State&apos; or &apos;Union Territory&apos;.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					33. Constitution (Scheduled Castes) (Union Territories) Order,
					<lb />
					1951:-In exercise of powers under Clause (1) of Articles 341 and 342
					<lb />
					of the Constitution, the Presidential Notifications were issued specifying
					<lb />
					Scheduled Castes in relation to various Union Territories. List of
					<lb />
					Scheduled Castes are declared in relation to each Union Territory
					<lb />
					separately. Presidential Notification pertaining to Union Territories,
					<lb />
					Scheduled Castes (Union Territories) Order, 1951 specifies Scheduled
					<lb />
					Castes resident in the Union Territories of Delhi, Chandigarh and Daman
					<lb />
					and Diu. The Presidential Order provided that:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<item>
					&quot;Subject to the provisions of this Order, the castes, races or tribes or
					<lb />
					parts of, or groups within, castes or tribes, specified in *[Parts I to III] of
					<lb />
					the Schedule to this Order shall, in relation to the *[Union territories] to
					<lb />
					which those parts respectively relate, be deemed to be Scheduled
					<lb />
					Castes so far as regards members thereof resident in the localities
					<lb />
					specified in relation to them respectively in those Parts of that
					<lb />
					Schedule.&quot;
					<lb />
					As and when there is reorganisation of the Union Territories, in exercise
					<lb />
					of the powers conferred under Article 341(1) of the Constitution, the
					<lb />
					President has made various orders.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<p>
					34. The Constitution (Scheduled Tribes) (Union Territories) Order,
					<lb />
					1951 26 :-In exercise of the powers conferred by clause (1) of Article 342
					<lb />
					of the Constitution of India, as amended by the Constitution (First
					<lb />
					Amendment) Act, 1951, the President made the Constitution (Scheduled
					<lb />
					Tribes) (Part C States) Order, 1951, specifying the tribes or communities
					<lb />
					which shall be deemed to be &apos;Scheduled Tribes&apos; in Part C State. This
					<lb />
					Order was adapted for the Union Territories by the Scheduled Castes
					<lb />
					and Scheduled Tribes Lists (Modification) Order, 1956.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					35. When new territories were formed, such as Pondicherry
					<lb />
					(Puducherry), or Sikkim, the Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes
					<lb />
					Orders were made in relation to the new territories. In exercise of the
					<lb />
					powers under Articles 341(1) and 342(1), the President has made the
					<lb />
					orders -The Constitution (Dadra and Nagar Haveli) Scheduled Castes
					<lb />
					Order, 1962; The Constitution (Dadra and Nagar Haveli) Scheduled
					<lb />
					Tribes Order, 1962; The Constitution (Pondicherry) Scheduled Castes
					<lb />
					Order, 1964; The Constitution (Goa, Daman and Diu) Scheduled Caste
					<lb />
					Order, 1968; The Constitution (Goa, Daman and Diu) Scheduled Tribes
					<lb />
					Order, 1968; In the case of Goa, the Goa, Daman and Diu
					<lb />
					Reorganisation Act, 1987 (Act No.18 of 1987), by Section 19 amended
					<lb />
					the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes Orders.
					<lb />
				</p>


				<p>
					36. Union Territories do not become merged with the Central
					<lb />
					Government:-The Union Territories are centrally administered by the
					<lb />
					President acting through an administrator. As held by this Court in New
					<lb />
					Delhi Municipal Council v. State of Punjab &amp; Ors. (1997) 7 SCC 339,
					<lb />
					the President, who is the executive head of a Union Territory while
					<lb />
					administering the Union Territory, does not function as the head of the
					<lb />
					Central Government, but as the head of the Union Territory under
					<lb />
					powers specially vested in him under Article 239 of the Constitution
					<lb />
					thereby occupying a position analogous to that of a Governor in a State.
					<lb />
					Though the Union Territories are centrally administered under the
					<lb />
					provisions of Article 239, they do not become merged with the Central
					<lb />
					Government as has been held by this Court in Satya Dev Bushahri v.
					<lb />
					Padam Dev and Ors. AIR 1954 SC 587. They are centrally
					<lb />
					administered; but they retain their independent identity [Chandigarh
					<lb />
					Administration and Anr. v. Surinder Kumar and Ors. (2004) 1 SCC
					<lb />
					530]. The Union Territory does not entirely lose its existence as an entity
					<lb />
					though large control is exercised by the Union of India. [Government of
					<lb />
					NCT Delhi v. All India Central Civil Accounts, Jao&apos;s Association and
					<lb />
					Ors. (2002) 1 SCC 344]
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					37.
					<lb />
					View taken in Pushpa and Chandigarh Administration -not
					<lb />
					correct view:-Reliance was placed upon Pushpa&apos;s case to contend
					<lb />
					that Article 16(4) is not controlled by the Presidential Order issued under
					<lb />
					Article 341(1) or Article 342(1) to the Officers appointed to the post in the
					<lb />
					Union Territories need not be confined to only such Schedule
					<lb />
					Castes/Schedule Tribes of the particular Union Territory. In Pushpa&apos;s
					<lb />
					case, the Supreme Court was confined with the question as to whether,
					<lb />
					selection and appointment already made to migrants&apos; Schedule Caste
					<lb />
					candidates of other States against the quota reserved for the Schedule
					<lb />
					Caste candidates in the Union Territory of Pondicherry was legal and
					<lb />
					valid. In S. Pushpa and Ors. v. Shivachanmugavelu and Ors. (2005)
					<lb />
					3 SCC 1, Pondicherry Government appointed Selection Grade Teachers
					<lb />
					in 1995 under the Scheduled Castes quota not only from the Scheduled
					<lb />
					Castes candidates of Pondicherry but also such candidates of
					<lb />
					Scheduled Castes from other States. In Pushpa&apos;s case, this Court
					<lb />
					upheld the policy of the Pondicherry Government extending the benefit
					<lb />
					of reservation of SC/ST seats even to those candidates who came from
					<lb />
					other States. The Pondicherry Government proceeded on the basis that
					<lb />
					since Central Government jobs were open to all SC/ST candidates
					<lb />
					irrespective of origin of their States, the same may apply to jobs with a
					<lb />
					Union Territory as well. In Pushpa&apos;s case, this Court held that in the
					<lb />
					matter of providing reservation, it was open to the Pondicherry
					<lb />
					Government to extend the benefit of reservation to migrant Scheduled
					<lb />
					Caste and Scheduled Tribe candidates and that the same will not be an
					<lb />
					infraction of clause (4) of Article 16 of the Constitution of India.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					38. In Pushpa&apos;s case, the principle that &quot;when members of Scheduled
					<lb />
					Castes/Scheduled Tribes migrate to another State, they do not carry
					<lb />
					with them the special privileges and advantages&quot;, was held not
					<lb />
					applicable in case of Union Territories. In para (21) of Pushpa&apos;s case, it
					<lb />
					was held as under:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<item>
					&quot;21.....Article 16(4) is not controlled by a Presidential Order issued
					<lb />
					under Article 341(1) or Article 342(1) of the Constitution in the sense
					<lb />
					that reservation in the matter of appointment on posts may be made in
					<lb />
					a State or Union Territory only for such Scheduled Castes and
					<lb />
					Scheduled Tribes which are mentioned in the Schedule appended to
					<lb />
					the Presidential Order for that particular State or Union Territory. This
					<lb />
					article does not say that only such Scheduled Castes and Scheduled
					<lb />
					Tribes which are mentioned in the Presidential Order issued for a
					<lb />
					particular State alone would be recognised as backward classes of
					<lb />
					citizens and none else. If a State or Union Territory makes a provision
					<lb />
					whereunder the benefit of reservation is extended only to such
					<lb />
					Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes which are recognised as such
					<lb />
					in relation to that State or Union Territory then such a provision would
					<lb />
					be perfectly valid. However, there would be no infraction of clause (4)
					<lb />
					of Article 16 if a Union Territory by virtue of its peculiar position being
					<lb />
					governed by the President as laid down in Article 239 extends the
					<lb />
					benefit of reservation even to such migrant Scheduled Castes or
					<lb />
					Scheduled Tribes who are not mentioned in the Schedule to the
					<lb />
					Presidential Order issued for such Union Territory. The UT of
					<lb />
					Pondicherry having adopted a policy of the Central Government
					<lb />
					whereunder all Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes, irrespective of
					<lb />
					their State are eligible for posts which are reserved for SC/ST
					<lb />
					candidates, no legal infirmity can be ascribed to such a policy and the
					<lb />
					same cannot be held to be contrary to any provision of law.&quot;
					<lb />
					(Underlining added)
					<lb />
				</item>

				<p>
					In my considered view, the above observation in Pushpa&apos;s case is not a
					<lb />
					correct view. The judgment in Pushpa&apos;s case is contrary to the views
					<lb />
					taken in Marri Chandra Shekhar Rao&apos;s case. The judgment in
					<lb />
					Pushpa&apos;s case is contrary to the views taken in Marri Chandra
					<lb />
					Shekhar Rao&apos;s case. Facts of Pushpa&apos;s case disclose that the
					<lb />
					Government of Pondicherry had throughout proceeded on the basis that
					<lb />
					being a Union Territory all orders regarding reservation for SC/ST in
					<lb />
					respect of post/services under the Central Government were applicable
					<lb />
					to post/services as under the Pondicherry administration. The decision
					<lb />
					in Pushpa&apos;s case therefore cannot be taken to be an authoritative
					<lb />
					pronouncement. Clause (2) of Article 341 of the Constitution empowers
					<lb />
					Parliament alone by law to include or exclude from the lists of Scheduled
					<lb />
					Castes specified in a notification issued under clause (1) of Article 341.
					<lb />
					No executive action or order or modification or variance of the same is
					<lb />
					possible and any such variance would be against the constitutional
					<lb />
					scheme.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					39. In Pushpa&apos;s case, the posts advertised were of Selection Grade
					<lb />
					Teachers under the Pondicherry Services and not for Central
					<lb />
					Government jobs. It may be that Pondicherry is a Union Territory; but the
					<lb />
					posts/services exclusively coming under Pondicherry administration is
					<lb />
					meant only for the Scheduled Casts/Scheduled Tribes as notified under
					<lb />
					the Presidential Order for Pondicherry. In fact, Pondicherry (Union
					<lb />
					Territory) itself by referring to Subhash Chandra&apos;s case has taken the
					<lb />
					decision that reservation benefits to posts/services arising under the
					<lb />
					Union Territory of Pondicherry will be confined only to the Scheduled
					<lb />
					Castes/Scheduled Tribes notified by virtue of Presidential Order. The
					<lb />
					said Government Order of the Pondicherry Government was upheld by
					<lb />
					this Court in Puducherry Scheduled Caste People Welfare
					<lb />
					Association v. Chief Secretary to Government, Union Territory of
					<lb />
					Pondicherry and Ors. (2014) 9 SCC 236, wherein this Court held as
					<lb />
					under:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<item>
					&quot;13. It is important to bear in mind that it is by virtue of the notification
					<lb />
					of President under Article 341(1) that the Scheduled Castes come into
					<lb />
					being. The members of the Scheduled Castes are drawn from castes,
					<lb />
					races or tribes, they attain a new status by virtue of Presidential Order.
					<lb />
					Clause (2) of Article 341 empowers Parliament alone by law to include
					<lb />
					or exclude from the list of Scheduled Castes specified in a notification
					<lb />
					issued under clause (1) by the President. By no executive power,
					<lb />
					amendment, modification, alteration or variance in the Presidential
					<lb />
					Order is permissible. It is not open to the executive to do anything
					<lb />
					directly or indirectly which may lead to any change in the Presidential
					<lb />
					Order. Once Presidential Order has been issued under Article 341(1)
					<lb />
					or Article 342(1), any amendment in the Presidential Order can only be
					<lb />
					made by Parliament by law as provided in Article 341(2) or Article
					<lb />
					342(2), as the case may be, and in no other manner. The interpretation
					<lb />
					of &quot;resident&quot; in the Presidential Order as &quot;of origin&quot; amounts to altering
					<lb />
					the Presidential Order.&quot;
					<lb />
				</item>

				<p>
					40. The principle in Pushpa&apos;s case was not accepted in Subhash
					<lb />
					Chandra&apos;s case. It was held that although Union Territory is
					<lb />
					administered by the Union Government, socio-political aspect of the
					<lb />
					Union Territory cannot be mixed up with administrative aspect. In
					<lb />
					Subhash Chandra&apos;s case, it was held that if the principle applied in
					<lb />
					Pushpa&apos;s case is to be given a logical extension, it will lead to an
					<lb />
					absurdity, that the Scheduled Castes Order in a State/Union Territory
					<lb />
					brought under the control of the President under Article 341 of the
					<lb />
					Constitution could be altered by virtue of a notification issued in
					<lb />
					pursuance of Article 16(4) of the Constitution, which is not in
					<lb />
					consonance with the Constitutional Scheme.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					41. Let us refer to the facts of Chandigarh Administration and
					<lb />
					Another v. Surinder Kumar and Others (2004) 1 SCC 530. Ministry of
					<lb />
					Home Affairs, Government of India issued various circulars pertaining to
					<lb />
					the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes. The circular dated
					<lb />
					22.02.1985 regarding &quot;Issue of Scheduled Caste/Scheduled Tribe
					<lb />
					certificate to migrants from other States/Union Territories&quot;, issued by the
					<lb />
					Ministry of Home Affairs clarified that a Scheduled Caste/Tribe person
					<lb />
					who has migrated from the State of origin to some other State for the
					<lb />
					purpose of seeking education, employment, etc. will be deemed to be a
					<lb />
					Scheduled Caste/Tribe of the State of his origin and will be entitled to
					<lb />
					derive benefits from the State of origin and not from the State to which
					<lb />
					he has migrated. Based on the aforesaid circular of the Government of
					<lb />
					India, the Home Secretary, Chandigarh Administration vide his letter
					<lb />
					dated 28.07.1986 sought clarification from the Government of India,
					<lb />
					Ministry of Home Affairs, as to whether, these instructions are applicable
					<lb />
					in the Union Territory of Chandigarh. Chandigarh Administration received
					<lb />
					the reply dated 26.08.1986 from Ministry of Welfare stating that there is
					<lb />
					no discrimination in the employment under the Central Government
					<lb />
					between the Schedule Caste/Schedule Tribes of one State or another
					<lb />
					and Union Territories and that the same may be followed by the
					<lb />
					Chandigarh Administration. The letter dated 26.08.1986 stated that
					<lb />
					Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes of any other State/Union Territory
					<lb />
					would be entitled to the benefits and facilities provided in the services
					<lb />
					under the Union Territory of Chandigarh. Further the said circular leaves
					<lb />
					it to the Chandigarh Administration to seek further clarification. The
					<lb />
					above letter of Government of India is in clear violation of Constitutional
					<lb />
					scheme.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					42. Pursuant to the said letter, Chandigarh Administration sought
					<lb />
					clarification from the Department of Personnel and Training. However,
					<lb />
					they have not received any response. The clarification was issued by the
					<lb />
					Home Secretary, Chandigarh Administration vide letter dated
					<lb />
					07.09.1999. The said letter had given a clarification based on the
					<lb />
					Government of India circular dated 02.02.1985 stating that a Schedule
					<lb />
					Caste/Schedule Tribe of any other State or Union Territory would not be
					<lb />
					entitled to the benefits of reservation in the services in the Chandigarh
					<lb />
					Administration and that the benefit of reservation to persons belonging
					<lb />
					to reserved categories in other States in the Chandigarh Administration
					<lb />
					is to be discontinued with effect from 07.09.1999. In Chandigarh
					<lb />
					Administration case, the Supreme Court took the view that the stand
					<lb />
					taken by Chandigarh Administration discontinuing the benefits of
					<lb />
					reservation with effect from 07.09.1999 was untenable. With due
					<lb />
					respect, I am not in agreement with the view taken in Chandigarh
					<lb />
					Administration case . The letter dated 26.08.1986 sent by the Ministry
					<lb />
					of Welfare/Kalyan Mantralaya is contrary to the letter dated 22.02.1985
					<lb />
					sent by the Ministry of Home Affairs and also against the Constitutional
					<lb />
					scheme.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					43. It was held in Subhash Chandra that Chandigarh
					<lb />
					Administration and Pushpa proceeded on the basis that Marri
					<lb />
					Chandra Shekhar Rao and Action Committee would have no
					<lb />
					application in relation to Union Territories. Observing that both Articles
					<lb />
					341 and 342 not only refer to the State but also to the Union Territory. In
					<lb />
					para (64) of Subhash Chandra&apos;s case, it was held as under:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<item>
					&quot;64. Although Union Territories are administered by the Central
					<lb />
					Government, yet it is difficult to conceive that the socio-political aspect
					<lb />
					can be mixed up with the administrative aspect. Article 341 leads to
					<lb />
					grant of constitutional rights upon a person whose affinity to a
					<lb />
					caste/tribe would attract the Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order or
					<lb />
					the Constitution (Scheduled Tribes) Order. Once a person comes
					<lb />
					within the purview of presidential promulgation, he would be entitled to
					<lb />
					constitutional and other statutory or administrative benefits attached
					<lb />
					thereto. In our opinion, such socio-political rights created in our
					<lb />
					Constitution cannot be segregated keeping in view the administrative
					<lb />
					exigencies.&quot;
					<lb />
				</item>

				<p>
					44. As per the scheme of the Constitution under Articles 341, 342 and
					<lb />
					239 of the Constitution, only those Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes
					<lb />
					as notified in the Presidential Notification for the respective Union
					<lb />
					Territory can legitimately claim the benefit of reservation in that Union
					<lb />
					Territory. Even though the Union Territories are centrally administered,
					<lb />
					though the administrator/Lieutenant Governor so far as the
					<lb />
					administrative aspects of the Union Territories, each Union Territory has
					<lb />
					its own identity. Each of the Union Territories would be bound by their
					<lb />
					respective Presidential Order of Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes for
					<lb />
					giving benefit of reservation to Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes in
					<lb />
					employment. Only those persons, who come within the purview of the
					<lb />
					Presidential Notification, would be entitled to constitutional and other
					<lb />
					statutory benefits of reservation in the respective Union Territory. If the
					<lb />
					benefit of reservation is to be extended to Scheduled Castes/Scheduled
					<lb />
					Tribes from all over the country then it would amount to inclusion of
					<lb />
					caste, races or tribes to the Presidential Order pertaining to that Union
					<lb />
					Territory. As discussed earlier, such inclusion or exclusion in the
					<lb />
					Presidential Order can be done only by the Parliament in the manner as
					<lb />
					indicated in Articles 341(2) and 342(2) of the Constitution of India. By no
					<lb />
					executive order, amendment, alteration or variance in the Presidential
					<lb />
					Order is permissible.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					Whether there can be PAN India reservation of SCs and STs to
					<lb />
					services under various Union Territories of India
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					45. Under Central Civil Services (Classification, Control and Appeal)
					<lb />
					Rules, 1965 [CCS(CCA) Rules, 1965], there are four categories of
					<lb />
					services namely:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<item>
					(i)
					<lb />
					Central Civil Services, Group A;
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					(ii) Central Civil Services, Group B;
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					(iii) Central Civil Services, Group C; and
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					(iv) Central Civil Services, Group D
					<lb />
				</item>

				<p>
					Central Civil Services -Group A:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					46. As per the Schedule to Central Civil Services (CCA) Rules, 1965,
					<lb />
					under Group &apos;A&apos;, there are forty five services inter alia like -(i)
					<lb />
					Archaeological Service (Serial No.1); (ii) Central Health Service (Serial
					<lb />
					No.5); (iii) Indian Defence Accounts Service (Serial No.11); (iv) Indian
					<lb />
					Foreign Service (Serial No.12); (v) Indian Meteorological Service (Serial
					<lb />
					No.13); (vi) Indian Postal Service (Serial No.14); (vii) Indian Posts and
					<lb />
					Telegraphs Traffic Service (Serial No.15); (viii) Indian Revenue Service
					<lb />
					(Serial No.16); (ix) Indian Salt Service (Serial No.17); (x) Directorate
					<lb />
					General of Mines Safety (Serial No.19); (xi) Indian Telecommunication
					<lb />
					Service (Serial No.22); (xii) Central Legal Service (Grades I,II, III and IV)
					<lb />
					(Serial No.25); (xiii) Delhi and Andaman and Nicobar Islands Civil
					<lb />
					Service, Grade I (DANICS) (Serial No.28); (xiv) Delhi and Andaman and
					<lb />
					Nicobar Islands Police Service, Grade II (DANIPS) (Serial No.29); (xv)
					<lb />
					Company Law Board Service (Serial No.38); (xvi) Labour Officers of the
					<lb />
					Central Pool (Serial No.39); and (xvii) Armed Forces Headquarters Civil
					<lb />
					Services (Serial No.44).
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					47. By reading of the categories of services, the said services of
					<lb />
					Group &apos;A&apos; are concerned only with the services of the Union of India and
					<lb />
					the appointment to Group &apos;A&apos; services are made by the President. The
					<lb />
					Cadre Controlling Authority of Group &apos;A&apos; services are the respective
					<lb />
					ministries of the Government of India. Recruitment to Group &apos;A&apos; services
					<lb />
					is made by the Union Public Service Commission (UPSC) and the
					<lb />
					recruitment is on all-India basis. So far as the recruitment to Group &apos;A&apos;
					<lb />
					services is concerned, Union of India in its counter affidavit has stated
					<lb />
					as under:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<item>
					&quot;a. ……… Recruitment to Group A services is made by the UPSC.
					<lb />
					This recruitment is again on all India basis…………
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					b. Whichever ministry seeks recruitment to the service in this Group
					<lb />
					sends requisition to UPSC as per procedure prescribed and UPSC
					<lb />
					accordingly advertises for the post in Group A. Every citizen of
					<lb />
					India is eligible to apply as per the qualifications and requirements
					<lb />
					in the notification.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					c. DoPT is the nodal ministry for regulating the conditions of service of
					<lb />
					all Central Civil Services as per Allocation of Business Rules. As
					<lb />
					per the conditions of service, every employee is required to give an
					<lb />
					undertaking agreeing to the conditions of the all India transfer
					<lb />
					liability at the time of joining the service.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					d. Central Civil Services employees belonging to Group A serve the
					<lb />
					Union of India and that is the reason why these services are across
					<lb />
					the length and breadth of the country, wherever there is an office of
					<lb />
					the Central Government.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					e. Member of the Group A service are governed by Central Civil
					<lb />
					Services (Class, Control &amp; Appeal) Rules, 1965 as well as Central
					<lb />
					Civil Services (Conduct) Rules, 1972 &amp; Central Civil Services
					<lb />
					(Pension) Rules, 1972 and such other rules made by the central
					<lb />
					ministries.&quot; 27
					<lb />
				</item>

				<p>
					Central Civil Services -Group B:-
					<lb />
				</p>
				<p>
					48. Under Rule 5, the Central Civil Services -Group &apos;B&apos; are specified
					<lb />
					in the Schedule and there are thirty-two such services mentioned. Some
					<lb />
					(DANICS) and Delhi, Andaman and Nicobar Islands, Lakshdweep,
					<lb />
					Daman &amp; Diu and Dadra &amp; Nagar Haveli Police Services (DANIPS). In
					<lb />
					the counter affidavit filed by the Union of India, it is stated as under:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<item>
					&quot;a. …….DANICS/DANIPS officers are posted in Delhi, Andaman &amp;
					<lb />
					Nicobar Islands, Lakshdweep, Daman &amp; Diu and Dadra &amp; Nagar
					<lb />
					Haveli. The recruitment to all the Union Territories for these Group
					<lb />
					B posts are common. They are also centralised and the appointing
					<lb />
					authority is none other than Ministry of Home Affairs, Government
					<lb />
					of India. The recruitment to these services is the very same
					<lb />
					examination meant for the All India Services (IAS/IPS) on the one
					<lb />
					hand and the Central Civil Services Group A on the other. Any
					<lb />
					citizen of India is eligible to apply, subject to the conditions
					<lb />
					prescribed. As per service rules, transfer undertakings throughout
					<lb />
					the Union Territories covered under DANICS/DANIPS is taken from
					<lb />
					these officers.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					b. This is the reason why the Union of India while inviting applications
					<lb />
					for recruitment considers all candidates, including reserved
					<lb />
					candidates on all India basis. Group B cadre of DANICS and
					<lb />
					DANIPS is the feeder cadre for IAS and IPS respectively. They
					<lb />
					retire invariably in these offices, some of them reaching high
					<lb />
					positions in the central government.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					c. As indicated above recruitment to the All India Services, CCS
					<lb />
					Group A as well as CCS Group B (Gazetted) is conducted through
					<lb />
					UPSC in the Civil Services Examination, the applicants are
					<lb />
					common when the applications are made, every aspirant seeks
					<lb />
					recruitment to the services and it is only as per the marks and
					<lb />
					ranking that allocations are made eventually to All India Services,
					<lb />
					Group A and Group B. Therefore, when UPSC undertakes the
					<lb />
					recruitment, it is naturally a PAN India recruitment and therefore it is
					<lb />
					necessary to seek applications including from reserved candidates
					<lb />
					from all over India.&quot; 28
					<lb />
				</item>

				<p>
					Central Civil Services -Group C:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					50. There are five services under Central Civil Services -Group &apos;C&apos;
					<lb />
					under CCS (CCA) Rules. Some of the posts noted in Group &apos;C&apos; and
					<lb />
					their appointing authorities are as under:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<item>
					PART III -Central Civil Services, Group &apos;C&apos;
					<lb />
					(Except for Civilians in Defence Services)
					<lb />
					Description of service
					<lb />
					(2)
					<lb />
					Appointing
					<lb />
					Authority
					<lb />
					(3)
					<lb />
					Description of service
					<lb />
					(2)
					<lb />
					Appointing
					<lb />
					Authority
					<lb />
					(3)
					<lb />
					Central
					<lb />
					Secretariat
					<lb />
					Clerical
					<lb />
					Service, Upper Division and
					<lb />
					Lower
					<lb />
					Division
					<lb />
					Grade
					<lb />
					(Serial No.1)
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					Deputy
					<lb />
					Secretary
					<lb />
					or
					<lb />
					Director, Cadre
					<lb />
					Authority
					<lb />
					General
					<lb />
					Central
					<lb />
					Service,
					<lb />
					Group &apos;C&apos; (Serial No.4)
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					(i) Posts
					<lb />
					in
					<lb />
					the
					<lb />
					Ministry/Department
					<lb />
					of
					<lb />
					Government other than
					<lb />
					the posts in respect of
					<lb />
					which specific provision
					<lb />
					has been made by a
					<lb />
					general or special order of
					<lb />
					the President
					<lb />
					(ii) Posts in non-Secretariat
					<lb />
					Office other than posts in
					<lb />
					respect of which specific
					<lb />
					provision has been made
					<lb />
					by a general or special
					<lb />
					order of the President
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					(iii) Posts
					<lb />
					in
					<lb />
					Union
					<lb />
					Territories
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					(iv) All Group &apos;C&apos; posts of the
					<lb />
					Departmentalized
					<lb />
					Accounts Office of the
					<lb />
					Government of India
					<lb />
					Deputy Secretary or
					<lb />
					Director
					<lb />
					in
					<lb />
					the
					<lb />
					Ministry/Department
					<lb />
					of Government
					<lb />
					Head of Office
					<lb />
					Head of Office of
					<lb />
					such other authority
					<lb />
					as may be specified
					<lb />
					by
					<lb />
					the
					<lb />
					Administrator.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					Controller
					<lb />
					of
					<lb />
					Accounts or Deputy
					<lb />
					Controller General of
					<lb />
					Accounts
					<lb />
					in
					<lb />
					a
					<lb />
					Ministry
					<lb />
					or
					<lb />
					Department
					<lb />
					where
					<lb />
					there is no Controller
					<lb />
					of Accounts.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<p>
					Insofar as Group &apos;C&apos; services of Union of India are concerned, they are
					<lb />
					recruited by the Staff Selection Commission (SSC) which is the
					<lb />
					recruiting agency under DoPT. Members of these services get promoted
					<lb />
					to CCS -Group &apos;B&apos;. In the counter affidavit filed by the Union of India, it
					<lb />
					is stated as under:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<item>
					&quot;a. ……Recruitment to posts in Group C arise out of requisition made
					<lb />
					by the concerned ministries all over India. These requisitions upon
					<lb />
					reaching the Staff Selection Commission are processed and
					<lb />
					selection takes place and appointments are made. Even from
					<lb />
					these appointees undertaking for all India transfer liability is taken.
					<lb />
					As these are posts under Central Government and these
					<lb />
					employees are liable to be transferred anywhere in the country and
					<lb />
					the recruitment being centralised for all such posts in the country, it
					<lb />
					had been consistent policy of the Union of India to have PAN India
					<lb />
					eligibility.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					b. The posts in CCS Group C are in the subordinate services. The
					<lb />
					equivalent in the Union Territory of Delhi is the Delhi Administrative
					<lb />
					Subordinate Services (DASS) and the recruiting agency in the
					<lb />
					place of Staff Selection Commission is the Delhi Subordinate
					<lb />
					Service Selection Board (DSSSB).
					<lb />
					Members of Delhi
					<lb />
					Administrative Subordinate Services are the feeder cadre for
					<lb />
					Central Civil Services Group B (DANICS). It is for these reasons
					<lb />
					that the policy is consistently adopted.&quot;
				</item>

				<p>
					<lb />
					Central Civil Services -Group D:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					51. Class IV employees now referred to as Multi-Tasking Staff (MTS)
					<lb />
					come under this category. Some of the posts noted in Group &apos;D&apos; and
					<lb />
					their appointing authorities are as under:-
					<lb />
					PART IV -Central Civil Services, Group &apos;D&apos;
					<lb />
					(Except for Civilians in Defence Services)
					<lb />
					Description of service
					<lb />
					(2)
					<lb />
					Appointing
					<lb />
					Authority
					<lb />
					(3)
					<lb />
					General Central Service, Group &apos;D&apos; (Serial No.1)
					<lb />
				</p>

				<item>
					(i) Posts in Ministries or Departments of Government other
					<lb />
					than posts in respect of which specific provision has
					<lb />
					been made by a general or special order of the
					<lb />
					President.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					(ii) Posts in non-Secretariat Offices other than posts in
					<lb />
					respect of which specific provision has been made by a
					<lb />
					general or special order of the President.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					(iii) Posts in Union Territories
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					(iv) All Group &apos;D&apos; posts of the Departmentalized Accounts
					<lb />
					Offices of the Government of India
					<lb />
					Under Secretary
					<lb />
					Head of Office
					<lb />
					Head of Office or such other
					<lb />
					authority as may be specified
					<lb />
					by the Administrator
					<lb />
					Deputy Controller of Accounts
					<lb />
					or Assistant Controller General
					<lb />
					of Accounts in a Ministry or
					<lb />
					Department where there is no
					<lb />
					Deputy Controller of Accounts.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<p>
					52. As pointed out earlier, there is centralised recruitment conducted
					<lb />
					by UPSC for the Central Civil Services in Group &apos;A&apos; and Group &apos;B&apos;. For
					<lb />
					this centralised recruitment, applications are invited from candidates
					<lb />
					across the country and Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes of all the
					<lb />
					States/Union Territories are entitled to apply for the reserved posts.
					<lb />
					Recruitment to various posts in Group &apos;A&apos; and Group &apos;B&apos; (Gazetted)
					<lb />
					categories for services in States/Union Territories are presently filled
					<lb />
					only through UPSC by centralised recruitment. After recruitment, the
					<lb />
					Group &apos;A&apos; and Group &apos;B&apos; officers are posted across the country wherever
					<lb />
					there are offices of Central Government.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					53. Services mentioned at Serial No.28 that is Delhi and Andaman
					<lb />
					and Nicobar Islands Civil Service, Grade-II (DANICS) are Group &apos;B&apos;
					<lb />
					civil services. DANICS officers are posted at Delhi, Andaman and
					<lb />
					Nicobar Islands, Lakshadweep, Daman and Diu and Dadra and Nagar
					<lb />
					Haveli. DANICS -Group &apos;B&apos; civil service officers are directly recruited
					<lb />
					through the Central Civil Services examination conducted by UPSC.
					<lb />
					Since DANICS is a centralised recruitment conducted through UPSC
					<lb />
					naturally applications are invited from the candidates across the country
					<lb />
					including reserved candidates of Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					54. Delhi, Andaman and Nicobar Islands Police Services
					<lb />
					(DANIPS) are recruited directly through centralised civil services
					<lb />
					examination conducted by UPSC. DANIPS are posted at Delhi and
					<lb />
					other Union Territories -Andaman and Nicobar Islands, Lakshadweep
					<lb />
					Islands, Daman and Diu and Dadar and Nagar Haveli. The cadre
					<lb />
					strength is controlled by the Ministry of Home Affairs, Government of
					<lb />
					India. Two-thirds of DANIPS are filled by direct recruitment and
					<lb />
					remaining are promoted from non-gazetted police officers of Union
					<lb />
					Territory of Delhi and other Union Territories. Since, DANIPS officers
					<lb />
					are recruited through a centralised recruitment conducted through
					<lb />
					UPSC, applications are invited from candidates from across the country
					<lb />
					including reserved candidates of Scheduled Castes and Scheduled
					<lb />
					Tribes of all the States and Union Territories. Thus, up to Group &apos;B&apos;
					<lb />
					(Gazetted) of Central Civil Services including the Group &apos;B&apos; (Gazetted)
					<lb />
					services of Union Territories, there is Centralised Civil Services
					<lb />
					Examination conducted by UPSC with PAN INDIA reservation.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					55. Serial No.32, Group &apos;B&apos; of CCS (CCA) Rules refers to General
					<lb />
					Central Services. At the risk of repetition, we may usefully refer to Serial
					<lb />
					No.32 which reads as under:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					Serial
					<lb />
					No.
					<lb />
					General Central Service, Group &apos;B&apos;-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					32
					<lb />
					(i) Post in any Ministry of Department of
					<lb />
					Government of India, other than the post
					<lb />
					in respect of which specific provision has
					<lb />
					been made by a general or special order of
					<lb />
					the President.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					(i-a) Posts outside a Ministry or
					<lb />
					Department of Government of India, other
					<lb />
					than the posts in respect of which specific
					<lb />
					provision has been made by a general or
					<lb />
					special order of the president.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					(ii) Posts in Union Territories other than
					<lb />
					Delhi Administration, the Andaman and
					<lb />
					Nicobar Islands and the Laccadive,
					<lb />
					Minicoy and Amindive Islands
					<lb />
					(iii) Delhi Administration-All posts
					<lb />
					(iv) The Andaman and Nicobar Islands-All
					<lb />
					Posts
					<lb />
					(v) The Lakshadweep Administration-All
					<lb />
					Posts
					<lb />
					Secretary in the Ministry
					<lb />
					or Department
					<lb />
					In respect of posts in an
					<lb />
					office under the control
					<lb />
					of a Head of Department
					<lb />
					directly
					<lb />
					under
					<lb />
					the
					<lb />
					Government.
					<lb />
					-Head of the Department
					<lb />
					In respect of other posts
					<lb />
					-
					<lb />
					Secretary
					<lb />
					in
					<lb />
					the
					<lb />
					Ministry or Department
					<lb />
					Administrator
					<lb />
					Chief Secretary
					<lb />
					Chief Commissioner
					<lb />
					Administrator
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					As seen from the above, Serial No.32(i) and (i-a) relates to the posts
					<lb />
					under the Government of India for which the appointing authority is the
					<lb />
					Secretary in the Ministry or Department/Head of the Department
					<lb />
					respectively. Serial No.32 (ii) of Central Civil Services (CCA) Rules,
					<lb />
					1965 relates to &quot;Posts in Union Territories other than Delhi
					<lb />
					Administration, the Andaman and Nicobar Islands and the
					<lb />
					Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindive Islands&quot;. The appointing authority
					<lb />
					is shown to be the &apos;Administrator&apos;. Serial No.32 (iii) to (v) relate to &apos;All
					<lb />
					posts&apos; in Delhi administration, Andaman and Nicobar Islands and the
					<lb />
					Lakshadweep administration respectively. Serial No.32(ii) posts in the
					<lb />
					Union Territories (other than Delhi Administration, the Andaman &amp;
					<lb />
					Nicobar Islands and the Laacadive, Minicoy and Amindive Islands)
					<lb />
					Group &apos;B&apos; (Gazetted) posts for which recruitment is conducted by UPSC.
					<lb />
					Since there is centralised recruitment conducted by UPSC for Group &apos;B&apos;
					<lb />
					(Gazetted), naturally applications are invited from the candidates across
					<lb />
					the
					<lb />
					country
					<lb />
					including
					<lb />
					reserved
					<lb />
					candidates
					<lb />
					of
					<lb />
					Scheduled
					<lb />
					Castes/Schedules Tribes from all the States/Union Territories. Up to the
					<lb />
					level of Group &apos;B&apos; (Gazetted) of Central Civil Services, since there is
					<lb />
					centralised recruitment for which there is PAN INDIA reservation of
					<lb />
					Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes, Scheduled Castes/Scheduled
					<lb />
					Tribes from any State/Union Territory are entitled to apply for the
					<lb />
					reserved posts for Group &apos;B&apos; examinations conducted by UPSC.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					56. When it comes to services under Union Territories, there are so
					<lb />
					many other services like teaching, clerical cadre, police services,
					<lb />
					Medical Officers, Health Services, Stenographers, Typists, services
					<lb />
					under the Revenue department, services under public-sector
					<lb />
					undertakings, services under the municipalities and the corporations in
					<lb />
					the Union Territories and various other services which are concerned
					<lb />
					with the administration of Union Territories. These services under the
					<lb />
					Union Territories would fall under Group &apos;B&apos;, Group &apos;C&apos; and Group &apos;D&apos; and
					<lb />
					their recruitment is within the exclusive domain of the respective Union
					<lb />
					Territories. Though the government servants under the Union Territories
					<lb />
					are governed by Central Civil Services Rules, the services under the
					<lb />
					Union Territories are essentially different from All India Services. For
					<lb />
					recruitment to services under respective Union Territories, there are
					<lb />
					different modes of recruitment for the different Union Territories.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					57. This Court posed the question whether there is other category of
					<lb />
					employees in UT administration and what is the practice followed for
					<lb />
					recruitment. In response to the question, Union of India, on instructions,
					<lb />
					filed the following response:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<item>
					SCOPE OF SC/ST RESERVATION IN UTs
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					1.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					Puducherry
					<lb />
					:
					<lb />
					Reserved posts confined to local
					<lb />
					reserved candidates.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					2.
					<lb />
					Chandigarh
					<lb />
					:
					<lb />
					Reserved posts filled up by
					<lb />
					candidates from all India.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					3.
					<lb />
					Daman &amp; Diu
					<lb />
					:
					<lb />
					Reserved posts confined to local
					<lb />
					reserved candidates for Group C
					<lb />
					posts. For Group B it is opened to
					<lb />
					candidates from all India but local
					<lb />
					candidates get additional 20 marks.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					4.
					<lb />
					Dadra &amp; Nagar
					<lb />
					Haveli
					<lb />
					:
					<lb />
					Reserved posts confined to local
					<lb />
					reserved candidates for Group C
					<lb />
					posts. For Group B it is opened to
					<lb />
					candidates from all India but local
					<lb />
					candidates get additional 20 marks.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					5.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					Lakshadweep
					<lb />
					:
					<lb />
					Reserved posts confined to local
					<lb />
					reserved candidates.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					6.
					<lb />
					A &amp; N Islands
					<lb />
					:
					<lb />
					For Group C posts locally reserved.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					7.
					<lb />
					NCT of Delhi
					<lb />
					:
					<lb />
					Reserved posts filled up by
					<lb />
					candidates from all India.
					<lb />
				</item>

				<p>
					For the above response that there is PAN India reservation of the
					<lb />
					reserved candidates for recruitment by Union Territories of Chandigarh,
					<lb />
					Dadra and Nagar Haveli and NCT of Delhi, no authenticated documents
					<lb />
					were produced to substantiate the same. When there are Presidential
					<lb />
					Orders notifying the Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes for Union
					<lb />
					Territories of Chandigarh, Dadra and Nagar Haveli, calling for application
					<lb />
					from the Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes candidates from all over
					<lb />
					India for the reserved posts of services under various Union Territories,
					<lb />
					be it Group &apos;B&apos; or Group &apos;C&apos;, is not in accordance with the constitutional
					<lb />
					scheme.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					58. For Group &apos;B&apos; and Group &apos;C&apos; posts falling within the services of the
					<lb />
					Union Territories, recruitment is made by the Staff Selection Board of
					<lb />
					respective Union Territories. For instance, let me refer to the Staff
					<lb />
					Selection Board of UT Administration of Daman and Diu whose home
					<lb />
					page reads as under:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<item>
					&quot;In exercise of the powers conferred by the provision of Article 239 of
					<lb />
					the Constitution of India, the Administrator of Daman &amp; Diu is pleased
					<lb />
					to make following rules to regulate the method of recruitment to all
					<lb />
					Group &apos;B&apos; and &apos;C&apos; categories of posts under the Administration of
					<lb />
					Daman &amp; Diu.
					<lb />
					It aims to &quot;ensure a uniform and transparent process and procedures
					<lb />
					for recruitment of all Group &apos;B&apos; and &apos;C&apos; categories of posts under the
					<lb />
					Administration of Daman and Diu through an autonomous body,
					<lb />
					without disturbing the existing recruitment processes and procedures
					<lb />
					and for ensuring that cumulative outcome of the recruitment is to
					<lb />
					provide just and fair opportunities to all the candidates and for matters
					<lb />
					connected therewith or incidental thereto 30 .&quot;
					<lb />
				</item>

				<p>
					59. In response to the question posed by the court, Union of India filed
					<lb />
					response affidavit stating that in Union Territories Daman and Diu and
					<lb />
					Dadra and Nagar Haveli, for Group &apos;B&apos;, it is opened to candidates from
					<lb />
					all over India. Local candidates with domicile certificate get additional
					<lb />
					twenty per cent marks. Response filed by the Union of India that there
					<lb />
					is PAN India reservation for Group &apos;B&apos; services of Daman and Diu and
					<lb />
					Dadra and Nagar Haveli, no authenticated documents/format of any
					<lb />
					application for Group &apos;B&apos; posts conducted by Daman and Diu was
					<lb />
					produced before us. Even assuming that there is such PAN India
					<lb />
					reservation for recruitment of Group &apos;B&apos; conducted by the Union Territory
					<lb />
					of Daman and Diu, when there are Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes
					<lb />
					as notified in the Presidential Order (Reorganisation Act, 1987 in respect
					<lb />
					of SCs/STs), there cannot be PAN India reservation as it is not in
					<lb />
					accordance with the constitutional scheme.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					60. Pointing out that services in the Union Territories are different from
					<lb />
					All India Services and that the mode of recruitment are also different, in
					<lb />
					para (29) of Subhash Chandra and another v. Delhi Subordinate
					<lb />
					Service Selection Board and others (2009) 15 SCC 458, it was held
					<lb />
					as under:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<item>&quot;</item>

				<item>
					29. Concededly, in respect of education or service, there exists a
					<lb />
					distinction between State Services and State-run institutions including
					<lb />
					the Union Territory Services and Union Territory-run institutions on the
					<lb />
					one hand, and the Central Civil Services and the institutions run by the
					<lb />
					Central Government on the other. Whereas in the case of the former,
					<lb />
					the reservation whether for admission or appointment in an institution
					<lb />
					and employment or appointment in the services or posts in a State or
					<lb />
					Union Territory must confine to the members of the Scheduled Castes
					<lb />
					and Scheduled Tribes as notified in the Presidential Orders but in
					<lb />
					respect of All India Services, Central Civil Services or admission to an
					<lb />
					institution run and founded by the Central Government, the members
					<lb />
					of the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes and other reserved
					<lb />
					category candidates irrespective of their State for which they have
					<lb />
					been notified are entitled to the benefits thereof. It is not denied or
					<lb />
					disputed that services in the Union Territory is essentially different from
					<lb />
					All India Services. It is also beyond any controversy that machinery for
					<lb />
					recruitment is also different. Indisputably again, not only the conditions
					<lb />
					of recruitment but also conditions of service differ.&quot;
					<lb />
				</item>

				<p>
					I am in full agreement with the view taken by Justice Sinha in Subhash
					<lb />
					Chandra case.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					61. Rule 3 of Delhi Administration Subordinate Services (DASS)
					<lb />
					Rules, 1967 deals with constitution of services and its classification in
					<lb />
					Delhi Administration. As per Rule 3(3) of DASS Rules, the post in
					<lb />
					Grade-I, Class-II Group &apos;B&apos; (Gazetted) and those in Grades II, III and IV
					<lb />
					shall be Central Civil Services Posts. But as noted earlier, as per Serial
					<lb />
					No.32 -General Central Service, Group &apos;B&apos;, insofar as Delhi
					<lb />
					Administration -All Posts (Serial No. 32 (iii)), the Appointing
					<lb />
					Authority is the Chief Secretary. The subordinate services in the
					<lb />
					National Capital Territory of Delhi though &quot;Central Civil Services&quot;, they
					<lb />
					are neither All India Services nor services under Union of India so as to
					<lb />
					attract Pan India Reservation.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					62. Even in the counter affidavit filed by the Union of India, by referring
					<lb />
					to Group &apos;C&apos; services, it is stated that CCS -Group &apos;C&apos; are in the
					<lb />
					subordinate services and there are equivalent services in the Union
					<lb />
					Territory of Delhi. For recruitment of other employees in the Union
					<lb />
					Territory of Delhi, there is Delhi Administrative Subordinate Services
					<lb />
					(DASS) and the recruiting agency is Delhi Subordinate Staff Selection
					<lb />
					Board (DSSSB). Members of Delhi Administrative Subordinate Services
					<lb />
					are stated to be the feeder cadre for Central Civil Services -Group &apos;B&apos;
					<lb />
					(DANICS). 31
					<lb />
					Merely because members of Delhi Administrative
					<lb />
					Subordinate Services are the feeder category for DANICS, PAN India
					<lb />
					reservation cannot be extended to Delhi Subordinate Services or to
					<lb />
					services under various Union Territories. Likewise, merely because,
					<lb />
					DANICS and DANIPS (Serial Nos. 28 and 29 of Group &apos;B&apos; Services) are
					<lb />
					the feeder category for IAS and IPS, it cannot be said that the Pan India
					<lb />
					Reservation is applicable to services under National Capital Territory of
					<lb />
					Delhi.
					<lb />
				</p>


				<p>
					63. So far as Group &apos;B&apos; and Group &apos;C&apos; posts falling under the services
					<lb />
					of the Union Territories, recruitment is done by the respective Staff
					<lb />
					Selection Board of respective Union Territories.
					<lb />
					Serial No.4 (iii) -
					<lb />
					&apos;Posts in Union Territories&apos; of Group &apos;C&apos; in CCS (CCA) Rules is
					<lb />
					shown and the appointing authority is stated as Head of the Office of
					<lb />
					such other authority as may be specified by the Administrator.
					<lb />
					Merely because the posts in the Union Territories and the appointing
					<lb />
					authority are shown in Group &apos;C&apos; in CCS (CCA) Rules, that does not
					<lb />
					mean that those Group &apos;C&apos; and Group &apos;D&apos; posts are available for the
					<lb />
					Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes of all the States/Union
					<lb />
					Territories. For recruitment of Group &apos;B&apos; and Group &apos;C&apos; posts of services
					<lb />
					under the respective Union Territories, since the examination is
					<lb />
					conducted by the respective Union Territories like Delhi Subordinate
					<lb />
					Staff Selection Board and other Union Territories Staff Selection Boards
					<lb />
					of respective Union Territories, reservation of posts of Scheduled
					<lb />
					Castes/Scheduled Tribes must be confined only to those Scheduled
					<lb />
					Castes/Scheduled Tribes as notified in the Presidential Order of the
					<lb />
					respective Union Territories. For recruitment of Group &apos;B&apos; and Group &apos;C&apos;
					<lb />
					posts under various Union Territories including Union Territory of Delhi,
					<lb />
					there cannot be PAN INDIA reservation of Scheduled Castes/Scheduled
					<lb />
					Tribes, lest, it would defeat the very object of the Presidential Orders
					<lb />
					issued specifying the Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes for respective
					<lb />
					Union Territories.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					64. As pointed out earlier, services under the Union Territories though
					<lb />
					they are Central Government services, they are services under the
					<lb />
					respective Union Territories and not under the direct control of Union of
					<lb />
					India/different Ministries. Procedure for recruitment to the various posts
					<lb />
					for the services of Union Territories are different as followed by
					<lb />
					respective Union Territories. The persons appointed for the services of
					<lb />
					Union Territories might be governed by CCS (CCA) Rules; but they are
					<lb />
					employees of respective Union Territories. The appointing authorities
					<lb />
					are the authorities under the administration of Union Territories and not
					<lb />
					under the Ministries of Union of India. Central Civil Services are the
					<lb />
					services directly under Union of India. Contrarily, various services under
					<lb />
					the Union Territories are the services under the respective Union
					<lb />
					Territories. Such services under Union Territories cannot be said to be
					<lb />
					Central Civil Services that is services under Union of India to extend the
					<lb />
					benefit of PAN India reservation for recruitment to the services under
					<lb />
					respective Union Territories including Union Territory of Delhi.
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					65. In exercise of the powers conferred by clause (1) of Article 341,
					<lb />
					the President issued the Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Union
					<lb />
					Territories Order, 1951 in the Presidential Order specifying Scheduled
					<lb />
					Castes in relation to Delhi and the thirty-six castes/groups notified are as
					<lb />
					under:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<item>
					Part 1 -Delhi
					<lb />
					Throughout the Union Territory
					<lb />
					Adi Dharmi
					<lb />
					19.
					<lb />
					Kachhandha
					<lb />
					Agria
					<lb />
					20.
					<lb />
					Kanjar or Giarah
					<lb />
					Aheria
					<lb />
					21.
					<lb />
					Khatik
					<lb />
					Balal
					<lb />
					22.
					<lb />
					Koli
					<lb />
					Banjara
					<lb />
					23.
					<lb />
					Lalbegi
					<lb />
					Bawaria
					<lb />
					24.
					<lb />
					Madri
					<lb />
					Bazigar
					<lb />
					25.
					<lb />
					Mallah
					<lb />
					Bhangi
					<lb />
					26.
					<lb />
					Mazhabi
					<lb />
					Bhil
					<lb />
					27.
					<lb />
					Meghwal
					<lb />
					10.
					<lb />
					Chamar,
					<lb />
					l
					<lb />
					Chanwan Chmanr,
					<lb />
					Jatya or Jatav
					<lb />
					Chamar,
					<lb />
					Mochi
					<lb />
					Ramadasia,
					<lb />
					Ravidasi, Reghgrh
					<lb />
					or Raigharh
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					28.
					<lb />
					Naribut
					<lb />
					11.
					<lb />
					Chohra (Sweeper)
					<lb />
					29.
					<lb />
					Nat (Rana), Badi
					<lb />
					12.
					<lb />
					Chuhra (Balmiki)
					<lb />
					30.
					<lb />
					Pasi
					<lb />
					13.
					<lb />
					Dhanak or Dhanuk
					<lb />
					31.
					<lb />
					Perna
					<lb />
					14.
					<lb />
					Dhobi
					<lb />
					32.
					<lb />
					Sansi or Bhedkut
					<lb />
					15.
					<lb />
					Dom
					<lb />
					33.
					<lb />
					Sapera
					<lb />
					16.
					<lb />
					Gharrami
					<lb />
					34.
					<lb />
					Sikligar
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					17.
					<lb />
					Julaha (Weaver)
					<lb />
					35.
					<lb />
					Singiwala
					<lb />
					or
					<lb />
					Kalbelila
					<lb />
				</item>

				<p>
					18.
					<lb />
					Karbirpanthi
					<lb />
					36.
					<lb />
					Sirkiband
					<lb />
				</p>
				<p>
					In relation to Delhi, there are thirty-six castes notified as Scheduled
					<lb />
					Castes in the Presidential Order. The members of the Scheduled
					<lb />
					Castes in Delhi are drawn from castes, races and by virtue of the
					<lb />
					Presidential Order pertaining to Delhi, they attain the status of the
					<lb />
					Scheduled Caste. In view of the Presidential Order issued for the
					<lb />
					Scheduled Castes to Delhi, only those Scheduled Castes can claim the
					<lb />
					benefit of reservation in the employment under the Union Territory of
					<lb />
					Delhi who are notified in the Presidential Order. Neither the Delhi
					<lb />
					Government nor the court can add any caste or group to the list of
					<lb />
					Scheduled Castes notified in the Presidential Order. Once a Presidential
					<lb />
					Order has been issued under Article 341(1) of the Constitution, any
					<lb />
					addition or deletion to the Presidential Order can only be made by the
					<lb />
					Parliament by law as provided under Article 341(2) and in no other
					<lb />
					manner. Merely because, Delhi Subordinate Services is a feeder
					<lb />
					category for DANICS, there cannot be Pan India Reservation of the
					<lb />
					SCs and STs for the services under Group &apos;C&apos; and &apos;D&apos; categories, for
					<lb />
					which recruitment are made by the Delhi Subordinate Staff Selection
					<lb />
					Board (DSSSB).
					<lb />
				</p>

				<p>
					66. Likewise, the Presidential Order has notified the following
					<lb />
					Scheduled Castes for the Union Territory of Chandigarh, Daman and
					<lb />
					Diu, Puducherry and Dadra and Nagar Haveli:-
					<lb />
				</p>

				<item>
					Part II -Chandigarh
					<lb />
					Bhangi (Hadi) 4.
					<lb />
					Mahyavanshi
					<lb />
					(Vankar)
					<lb />
					Chambhar,
					<lb />
					Mochi
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					5.
					<lb />
					Mang
					<lb />
					Mahar
					<lb />
					The Schedule -Puducherry
					<lb />
					Adi Andhra
					<lb />
					9.
					<lb />
					Pallan
					<lb />
					Adi
					<lb />
					Dravida
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					10.
					<lb />
					Parayan,
					<lb />
					Sambavar
					<lb />
					Chakkiliya
					<lb />
					n
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					11.
					<lb />
					Samban
					<lb />
					Jambuvulu
					<lb />
					12.
					<lb />
					Thoti
					<lb />
					Kuravan
					<lb />
					13.
					<lb />
					Valluvan
					<lb />
					Madiga
					<lb />
					14.
					<lb />
					Vetan
					<lb />
					Mala, Mala
					<lb />
					Masti
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					15.
					<lb />
					Vetriyan
					<lb />
					Paky
					<lb />
					16.
					<lb />
					Puthirai Vannan
					<lb />
					The Schedule -Dadra and Nagar Haveli
					<lb />
					Bhangi
					<lb />
				</item>

				<item>
					3.
					<lb />
					Mahar
					<lb />
					Chamar
					<lb />
					4.
					<lb />
					Mahayavanshi
					<lb />
				</item>

				<p>
					67. Let me take the case of Andaman &amp; Nicobar Islands. The
					<lb />
					Constitution (Andaman and Nicobar Islands) Scheduled Tribes Order,
					<lb />
					1959 has notified the following tribes or tribal communities who have
					<lb />
					been included in the Schedule for the Andaman &amp; Nicobar Islands:-
					<lb />
				</p>
				The Schedule
				<lb />
				The
				<lb />
				Andamanese
				<lb />
				(including Chariar or
				<lb />
				Chari, Kora, Tabo or
				<lb />
				Bo, Yere, Kede, Bea
				<lb />
				Balawa,
				<lb />
				Bojigiyab,
				<lb />
				Juwai and Kol
				<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			4.
			<lb />
			Sentinelese
			<lb />
			Jarawas
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			5.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			Nicoberese
			<lb />
			Onges
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			The Shompens
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			When Andaman &amp; Nicobar Islands is recruiting persons to the services
			<lb />
			of Group &apos;B&apos;, &apos;C&apos; and &apos;D&apos; under its administration, it has to necessarily
			<lb />
			follow the policy of recruiting members from amongst the Scheduled
			<lb />
			Tribes who are notified as Scheduled Tribes in the Presidential
			<lb />
			Notification for Andaman and Nicobar Islands. It will not be appropriate
			<lb />
			to extend the benefit of reservation to the SCs and STs from other
			<lb />
			States/Union Territories, lest it would deprive the notified Scheduled
			<lb />
			Tribes of the Andaman and Nicobar Islands.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			68. It may be that the candidates recruited by the respective Union
			<lb />
			Territories for Group &apos;B&apos; and Group &apos;C&apos; may become the feeder
			<lb />
			categories for further promotion in Group &apos;A&apos; and Group &apos;B&apos; of All India
			<lb />
			Services respectively in the Central Civil Services. The fact that the
			<lb />
			candidates who are recruited by the respective Union Territories become
			<lb />
			the feeder categories for further promotion in the Central Civil Services
			<lb />
			is not a ground for extending the benefit of all India reservation to the
			<lb />
			Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes for the reserved posts in the
			<lb />
			respective Union Territories. Be it noted that the candidates recruited by
			<lb />
			the various State Governments under Group &apos;A&apos; of respective State
			<lb />
			services become the feeder category for IAS and IPS. The persons
			<lb />
			recruited for Group &apos;B&apos; and Group &apos;C&apos; by the respective Union Territories
			<lb />
			stand on the same footing as that of the candidates so recruited by the
			<lb />
			various States where only the Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes of
			<lb />
			the respective States can apply.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			69. A letter dated 10.05.2013 by Special Secretary (Services)
			<lb />
			addressed to all the Secretaries/Heads of Departments of NCT of Delhi
			<lb />
			has been filed by the Union of India. The letter relates to the subject
			<lb />
			&quot;Reservation policy to be followed with regard to SCs/STs in civil posts
			<lb />
			under GNCTD&quot;. The said letter refers to the judgment in Pushpa&apos;s
			<lb />
			case and states that the Ministry of Law and Justice has opined that the
			<lb />
			law declared by the Supreme Court in Pushpa&apos;s case applies to the
			<lb />
			NCT of Delhi and that Pushpa&apos;s case cannot be ignored. Relevant
			<lb />
			portion of the said letter reads as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>


		<p>
			71. As discussed earlier in para (8), in case of Union Territories,
			<lb />
			though administrative control to certain extent is exercised by the Union
			<lb />
			of India, Union Territories do not lose their identity as an entity. The
			<lb />
			existing practice of PAN INDIA reservation followed in Delhi and
			<lb />
			Chandigarh is against the constitutional scheme and also against the
			<lb />
			executive instructions dated 06.08.1984 and 22.02.1985 issued by the
			<lb />
			Ministry of Home Affairs.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			72. As pointed our earlier, the Ministry of Home Affairs in its circular
			<lb />
			dated 06.08.1984 addressed to all the State Governments and Union
			<lb />
			Territories administration stated that SCs and STs on migration from the
			<lb />
			State of his origin to other State will not loose his status as SCs/STs; but
			<lb />
			will be entitled to the concession/benefits to the SCs/STs from the State
			<lb />
			of his origin and not from the State where he has migrated. The same
			<lb />
			thing was reiterated in the letter dated 22.02.1985 of the Ministry of
			<lb />
			Home Affairs, Government of India. If PAN India reservation is to be
			<lb />
			extended to the Union Territories like Delhi, Chandigarh, Puducherry,
			<lb />
			Andaman &amp; Nicobar Islands or Daman &amp; Diu for Group &apos;C&apos; and &apos;D&apos;
			<lb />
			services for which recruitment are made by the respective Union
			<lb />
			Territories, the very object of the Constitutional Scheme of upliftment of
			<lb />
			the SCs/STs of these Union Territories will be defeated. All India
			<lb />
			reservation to the services under the Union Territories including the
			<lb />
			Union Territory of Delhi will be against the mandate of Articles 341 and
			<lb />
			342 of the Constitution and against the Constitutional Scheme.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			73. Marri Chandra Shekhar Rao and Action Committee are
			<lb />
			applicable to the States and they are applicable with equal force to the
			<lb />
			Union Territories including Union Territory of Delhi. There cannot be any
			<lb />
			distinction between the States and the Union Territories. Likewise, there
			<lb />
			can be no distinction between Union Territory of Delhi and other Union
			<lb />
			Territories. When Presidential Orders of Scheduled Castes/Scheduled
			<lb />
			Tribes are notified for various Union Territories including Union Territory
			<lb />
			of Delhi extending PAN India reservation to the employment falling
			<lb />
			under the services of Union Territories including Union Territory of Delhi,
			<lb />
			will be against the Constitutional scheme and the law laid down in Marri
			<lb />
			Chandra Shekhar Rao and Action Committee.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			74. Article 16(4) of the Constitution has to yield to the
			<lb />
			constitutional mandate of Articles 341 and 342 of the Constitution.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			The Presidential Order issued under Article 341 in regard to Scheduled
			<lb />
			Castes and Article 342 in regard to Scheduled Tribes cannot be varied
			<lb />
			by anyone or by the Court. Only the Parliament by law include or
			<lb />
			exclude from the list of Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes specified
			<lb />
			in the notification issued under Article 341 (1) and Article 342(1)
			<lb />
			respectively any caste, race or tribe or parts or group within any caste,
			<lb />
			race or tribe. The Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes thus specified
			<lb />
			in relation to one State or Union Territory does not carry the status in
			<lb />
			another State or Union Territory. When the Scheduled Castes or
			<lb />
			Scheduled Tribes are specified for each State in relation to one State or
			<lb />
			Union Territory, neither the State legislature, the administration of the
			<lb />
			Union Territories and nor the courts can include or exclude other
			<lb />
			Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes so notified in the Presidential
			<lb />
			Order. Providing all India reservation to the services of Union Territories
			<lb />
			including Union Territory of Delhi, would be against the mandate of
			<lb />
			Articles 341 and 342 and the Presidential Orders issued thereon. If that
			<lb />
			is permitted, it would amount to addition or alteration of the Presidential
			<lb />
			Order which is impermissible and violative of the Constitutional Scheme.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			75. It is the responsibility of each State/Union Territory to provide for
			<lb />
			such reservation/affirmative action by positive discretion to bring
			<lb />
			backward classes/Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes in the
			<lb />
			respective States/areas to provide socio-economic empowerment. If the
			<lb />
			reservation to the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes are to be
			<lb />
			extended to all categories of Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes all
			<lb />
			over India or to the migrants then there is every possibility of the
			<lb />
			Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes of other developed States and
			<lb />
			Union Territories squandering reservations to the Scheduled Castes and
			<lb />
			Scheduled Tribes who are disadvantaged in the respective States/Union
			<lb />
			Territories including Union Territory of Delhi. If this is permitted, it would
			<lb />
			defeat the very object of providing reservation to the disadvantaged
			<lb />
			Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes in a particular State or Union
			<lb />
			territory. The enabling provision of Article 16(4) of the Constitution has to
			<lb />
			yield to the constitutional scheme of Article 341 and Article 342 of the
			<lb />
			Constitution.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			76. Conclusion:-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			 Insofar as the States, I agree with the majority view that a
			<lb />
			person who is recognised as a member of Scheduled
			<lb />
			Castes/Scheduled Tribes in his original State, will be
			<lb />
			entitled to all the benefits of reservation under the
			<lb />
			Constitution in that State only and not in other
			<lb />
			States/Union Territories and not entitled to the benefits of
			<lb />
			reservation in the migrated State/Union Territory.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 Marri Chandra Shekhar Rao and Action Committee
			<lb />
			are applicable to the States and they are applicable with
			<lb />
			equal force to the Union Territories including Union
			<lb />
			Territory of Delhi. There cannot be any distinction
			<lb />
			between the States and the Union Territories. Likewise,
			<lb />
			there can be no distinction between Union Territory of
			<lb />
			Delhi and other Union Territories. When Presidential
			<lb />
			Orders of Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes are
			<lb />
			notified for various Union Territories including Union
			<lb />
			Territory of Delhi extending PAN India reservation to the
			<lb />
			employment falling under the services of Union
			<lb />
			Territories including Union Territory of Delhi, will be
			<lb />
			against the Constitutional scheme and the law laid down
			<lb />
			in Marri Chandra Shekhar Rao and Action
			<lb />
			Committee.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 Since there is centralised recruitment upto Group &apos;B&apos;
			<lb />
			(Gazetted) services conducted by UPSC for the Central
			<lb />
			Civil Services posts in the States/Union Territories of
			<lb />
			India, there has to be necessarily PAN India reservation
			<lb />
			for Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes for those
			<lb />
			recruitment conducted by UPSC. Sofaras Group &apos;B&apos; and
			<lb />
			Group &apos;C&apos; posts falling under services of Union Territories
			<lb />
			including Union Territory of Delhi for which recruitment is
			<lb />
			conducted by the respective Union Territories, benefit of
			<lb />
			reservation in employment (Article 16(4)) is to be
			<lb />
			extended only to those Scheduled Castes/Scheduled
			<lb />
			Tribes specified in the Presidential Order of the respective
			<lb />
			Union Territories. Insofar as the posts recruited by the
			<lb />
			Staff Selection Board of the respective Union Territories
			<lb />
			including the Union Territory of Delhi, there cannot be
			<lb />
			PAN India reservation for Group &apos;B&apos;, Group &apos;C&apos; and Group
			<lb />
			&apos;D&apos; posts falling under the services of various Union
			<lb />
			Territories and such PAN India reservation would be
			<lb />
			against the constitutional scheme and Marri Chandra
			<lb />
			Shekhar Rao and Action Committee.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			…………….……………J.
			<lb />
			[R. BANUMATHI]
			<lb />
			New Delhi;
			<lb />
			August 30, 2018
			<lb />
			UPON hearing the counsel the Court made the following
			<lb />
			O R D E R
			<lb />
			CIVIL APPEAL NO.8375 OF 2014
			<lb />
			Civil Appeal No.8375 of 2014 is de-linked from Civil
			<lb />
			Appeal No.1085/2013 (Bir Singh Vs. Delhi Jal Board &amp; Ors.)
			<lb />
			and other connected matters and list the same for hearing
			<lb />
			before the appropriate Bench.
			<lb />
			CIVIL APPEAL NO(S). 1085/2013, 9935-9937/2014, 10081/2014,
			<lb />
			8141/2014, 8802/2012, 1086/2013 AND CIVIL APPEAL (@ SLP(C) No.
			<lb />
			36324/2017)
			<lb />
			Leave granted in Special Leave Petition (Civil)
			<lb />
			No.36324 of 2017.
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Mr. Justice Ranjan Gogoi pronounced the
			<lb />
			judgment of the Bench comprising His Lordship, Hon&apos;ble Mr.
			<lb />
			Justice
			<lb />
			N.V.
			<lb />
			Ramana,
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Mr.
			<lb />
			Justice
			<lb />
			Mohan
			<lb />
			M.
			<lb />
			Shantanagoudar and Ho&apos;ble Mr. Justice S. Abdul Nazeer.
			<lb />
			Civil Appeal Nos. 1085/2013, 10081/2014, 8141/2014,
			<lb />
			8802/2012, 1086/2013 and Civil Appeal arising out of SLP(C)
			<lb />
			NO.36324/2017 (Pertaining to Delhi) are disposed of in
			<lb />
			terms of the signed reportable judgment and Civil Appeal
			<lb />
			No.9935-9937 of 2014 (Pertaining to U.T. of Andaman and
			<lb />
			Nicobar Island) will be listed before the appropriate
			<lb />
			Bench.
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Mrs. Justice R. Banumathi pronounced the
			<lb />
			separate reportable judgment.
			<lb />
			[VINOD LAKHINA]
			<lb />
			[SAROJ KUMARI GAUR]
			<lb />
			AR-cum-PS
			<lb />
			BRANCH OFFICER
			<lb />
			[TWO SIGNED REPORTABLE JUDGMENTS ARE PLACED ON THE FILE]
		</p>


	</text>
</tei>