<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>THE HIGH COURT OF SIKKIM : GANGTOK <lb/>(Civil Appellate Jurisdiction) <lb/>DATED : 31.08.2019 <lb/>------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------<lb/>SINGLE BENCH : THE HON&apos;BLE MRS. JUSTICE MEENAKSHI MADAN RAI, JUDGE <lb/>------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------<lb/>RFA No.09 of 2016 <lb/>Appellant <lb/>: <lb/>Joybells School Authority, <lb/>Through Mr. P.J.S. Walia, <lb/>Chairman, Joy Bells School, <lb/>Near Khangri Petrol Pump, <lb/>Tadong, East Sikkim. <lb/>versus <lb/>Respondents <lb/>: <lb/>1. Mr. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon, <lb/>S/o Late Karma Pintso, <lb/>R/o Syari, Gangtok, East Sikkim. <lb/>2. Mrs. Althea Joy Singh, <lb/>W/o Col. S.S. Singh, <lb/>Principal of Joy Bells School, <lb/>Near Khangri Petrol Pump, <lb/>Tadong, Gangtok, East Sikkim. <lb/>3. Mr. N.D. Chingapa, <lb/>S/o T.N. Chingapa, <lb/>R/o Lucy Building, <lb/>Nam-Nang, Gangtok, East Sikkim. <lb/>4. Mrs. Tashi Dolma Kazini, <lb/>W/o Mr. N.D. Chingapa, <lb/>R/o Lucy Building, <lb/>Nam-Nang, Gangtok, East Sikkim. <lb/>Appeal under Order XLI of the Code of <lb/>Civil Procedure, 1908 <lb/>--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------<lb/>Appearance <lb/>Mr. T.B. Thapa, Senior Advocate with Mr. Ranjan Chettri and <lb/>Mr. Khem Raj Sapkota, Advocates, for the Appellant. <lb/>Mr. A.K. Upadhyaya, Senior Advocate with Mr. Sonam Rinchen <lb/>Lepcha, Advocate, for the Respondent No.1. <lb/>None present for Respondent No.2. <lb/>Mr. S.S. Hamal, Advocate, for Respondents No.3 and 4. <lb/>--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------<lb/>CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/>Petitioner <lb/>: <lb/>Mr. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon, <lb/>S/o Late Karma Pintso, <lb/>R/o Syari, Gangtok, East Sikkim. <lb/>versus <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>Respondents <lb/>: <lb/>1. Mrs. Althea Joy Singh, <lb/>W/o Col. S.S. Singh, <lb/>Principal of Joy Bells School, <lb/>Near Khangri Petrol Pump, <lb/>Tadong, Gangtok, East Sikkim. <lb/>2. Joybells School Authority, <lb/>Through Mr. P.J.S. Walia, <lb/>Chairman, Joy Bells School, <lb/>Near Khangri Petrol Pump, <lb/>Tadong, East Sikkim. <lb/>3. Mr. N.D. Chingapa, <lb/>S/o T.N. Chingapa, <lb/>R/o Lucy Building, <lb/>Nam-Nang, Gangtok, East Sikkim. <lb/>4. Mrs. Tashi Dolma Kazini, <lb/>W/o Mr. N.D. Chingapa, <lb/>R/o Lucy Building, <lb/>Nam-Nang, Gangtok, East Sikkim. <lb/>Cross-Objection under Order XLI Rule 22 of the <lb/>Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 <lb/>--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------<lb/>Appearance <lb/>Mr. A.K. Upadhyaya, Senior Advocate with Mr. Sonam Rinchen <lb/>Lepcha, Advocate, for the Petitioner. <lb/>None present for Respondent No.1. <lb/>Mr. T.B. Thapa, Senior Advocate with Mr. Ranjan Chettri and <lb/>Mr. Khem Raj Sapkota, Advocates, for Respondent No.2. <lb/>Mr. S.S. Hamal, Advocate, for Respondents No.3 and 4. <lb/>--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------<lb/></front>

			<body>J U D G M E N T <lb/>Meenakshi Madan Rai, J. <lb/>1. <lb/>The learned trial Court vide the impugned Judgment <lb/>dated 30.04.2016, decreed the Suit of the Plaintiff (Respondent <lb/>No.1 in this Appeal and Petitioner in the Cross Objection), on <lb/>grounds of &quot;bona fide requirement for personal occupation&quot; of <lb/>the Plaintiff. Arrears in rent were ordered to be paid by the <lb/>Defendant No.2 (Appellant herein and Respondent No.2 in the <lb/>Cross Objection), from April 2012, till filing of the Suit with <lb/>pendent lite and future interest, till recovery of possession. The <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>Counter-Claim of the Defendant No.2 (Appellant herein) was <lb/>dismissed. Aggrieved thereof, the Appellant assails the impugned <lb/>Judgment supra. <lb/>2. <lb/>A Cross Objection was filed by the Respondent No.1 <lb/>before this Court, assailing the finding of the learned trial Court <lb/>on Issues No.1 and 2. The Appeal and the Cross Objection are <lb/>being disposed of by this Judgment. <lb/>3. <lb/>(a) The Respondent No.1 (in the Appeal herein and <lb/>the Petitioner in the Cross Objection) was the Plaintiff before the <lb/>learned trial Court; <lb/>(b) the Respondent no.2 (in the Appeal herein and <lb/>Respondent No.1 in the Cross Objection) was the Defendant <lb/>No.1 before the learned trial Court; <lb/>(c) the Appellant (in the Appeal herein and <lb/>Respondent No.2 in the Cross Objection) was the Defendant <lb/>No.2 before the learned trial Court; and <lb/>(d) the Respondents No.3 and 4 (in the Appeal <lb/>herein and Respondents No.3 and 4 in the Cross Objection) were <lb/>the proforma Defendants No.3 and 4 before the learned trial <lb/>Court. <lb/>The parties shall be referred to in their order of appearance <lb/>before this Court, in the Appeal. <lb/>4. <lb/>The facts briefly stated, as set out by the <lb/>Respondent No.1, are that he had purchased two RCC buildings <lb/>viz. (i) four storeyed building measuring 48 feet x 47 feet, and <lb/>(ii) three storeyed building measuring 36 feet x 36 feet, with <lb/>surrounding land, standing on Plot No.104/904 alongside <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>National Highway 31A, under Tadong Block at Sokeythang, East <lb/>Sikkim, from the Respondents No.3 and 4, vide a Sale Deed <lb/>dated 11.11.2011, duly registered and mutated in his name on <lb/>19.12.2011. The property in dispute is the four storeyed RCC <lb/>building at (i) supra, measuring 48 feet x 47 feet, (hereinafter <lb/>the &quot;suit property&quot;). The Respondent No.2 used to be the <lb/>Principal of the Appellant School, while P.J.S. Walia representing <lb/>the Appellant, is the present Chairman of the School. Vide Lease <lb/>Deed, dated 23.03.1996, the Respondent No.3 leased out the <lb/>suit property to Respondent No.2, who later left Gangtok having <lb/>handed over the suit property to the Appellant, without the <lb/>consent or knowledge of the Respondents No.3 and 4, despite <lb/>Clause 9 of the Lease Deed prohibiting subletting. That, the <lb/>Respondent No.1, aged above 50 years and being beset with <lb/>physical ailments, decided to discontinue working as a <lb/>Contractor and instead sought to develop the suit property into a <lb/>hotel complex. Pursuant thereto, on 21.08.2012, he issued three <lb/>months&quot; advance Legal Notice to the Appellant, requiring him to <lb/>vacate the suit property by the end of the Academic Session of <lb/>2012, which the Appellant failed to comply. This gave rise to the <lb/>Eviction Suit on the grounds of &quot;bona fide use and occupation&quot; <lb/>and default in payment of rent for four months continuously. It <lb/>was also asserted that the Appellant was a trespasser in the suit <lb/>property. <lb/>5. <lb/>Denying and disputing the allegations, the Appellant <lb/>in his Written Statement, expressed ignorance of the change in <lb/>ownership of the suit property from the Respondents No.3 and 4 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>to the Respondent No.1, which he learnt of, only on receipt of a <lb/>copy of the alleged Sale Deed document and khatian parcha, <lb/>appended to the summons served on him. Claiming a right of <lb/>pre-emption over the suit property being the tenant, for the <lb/>amount as indicated in the Sale Deed, he alleged that the sale <lb/>transaction was a sham transaction to cause him loss. The Lease <lb/>Deed, executed between Respondent No.2 and Respondent No.3 <lb/>did not bind him as the period therein had expired prior to his <lb/>taking over as the Chairman of the Appellant School, in 2002. <lb/>That, the School started in 1984 and has continued to be a <lb/>tenant under the tenancy laws of the State and the Respondent <lb/>No.2 was the Principal from 1990. Denying default in payment of <lb/>rent, it was averred that the Respondents No.3 and 4 received <lb/>rent till November, 2011, thereafter rent was remitted to the <lb/>Respondent No.1, on Legal Notice dated 18.05.2012, being <lb/>issued by him to the Appellant. That, the Respondent No.1 owns <lb/>a multi storeyed RCC building at Syari, from which he earns <lb/>sufficient income from rent, besides, a hotel could be opened in <lb/>any of the buildings purchased by him from the Respondent No.3 <lb/>near the Appellant School. <lb/>6. <lb/>A Counter-Claim was filed by the Appellant, seeking <lb/>to exercise the right of pre-emption on payment of the amount <lb/>mentioned in the Sale Deed, executed between the Respondent <lb/>No.1 and Respondents No.3 and 4. In his Written Statement to <lb/>the Counter-Claim, the Respondent No.1 reiterated that <lb/>Respondent No.2 and not the Appellant, had been originally <lb/>inducted as a tenant, rendering the Appellant a trespasser in the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>suit property. The consideration value reflected on the Sale Deed <lb/>was due to family relations between the Respondents No.1, 3 <lb/>and 4 but the market value would be much higher. Besides, the <lb/>provisions of Revenue Order No.I of 1917 prohibits the Appellant <lb/>from exercising the right of pre-emption, hence the Counter-<lb/>Claim be dismissed. <lb/>7. <lb/>On account of her non-appearance before the <lb/>learned trial Court despite service of summons, the Respondent <lb/>No.2 was proceeded ex parte. <lb/>8. <lb/>The learned trial Court initially struck the following <lb/>four issues for settlement; <lb/>&quot;1. Whether the Defendants No. 1 and 2 are liable <lb/>to be evicted from the Suit Premises allegedly being <lb/>trespassers in the Suit Premises and the Plaintiff requiring <lb/>the same for his bona fide use and occupation? (Onus on <lb/>the Plaintiff) <lb/>2. Whether the Plaintiff is entitled to arrears of rent <lb/>from the Defendants No.1 and 2 from November, 2011 till <lb/>decision in the Suit? (Onus on the Plaintiff) <lb/>3. Whether the Defendant No.2 has a right of pre-<lb/>emption over the Suit Premises from Plaintiff and the <lb/>Proforma Defendants No.3 and 4? (Onus on the <lb/>Defendant No.2) <lb/>4. Whether the Defendant No.2 has the right to <lb/>purchase the Suit Property in view of the provisions of <lb/>Revenue Order No.1 of 1917? (Onus on the Defendant <lb/>No.2)&quot; <lb/>Later in time, on the Suit being transferred to the Court of the <lb/>learned District Judge, Special Division-II, East Sikkim at <lb/>Gangtok from that of the learned District Judge, (East) Sikkim, <lb/>the learned Presiding Officer of this Court, in his wisdom, vide <lb/>Order dated 21.04.2016, opined that although Issue No.2 supra <lb/>was framed regarding arrears of rent but the issue of default had <lb/>not been specifically framed and proceeded to re-frame Issue <lb/>No.2 as follows; <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>&quot;2.Whether defendants have defaulted in payment <lb/>of monthly rent from November, 2011 up to December, <lb/>2012 and are liable to be evicted from the suit premises? <lb/>Whether the Plaintiff is entitled to arrears of rent from the <lb/>defendant No.1 and 2 from November, 2011 till decision <lb/>in the suit?&quot; <lb/>9. <lb/>Before the learned trial Court, the Respondent No.1 <lb/>examined two witnesses including himself. The Appellant also <lb/>examined two witnesses including P.J.S. Walia (representing the <lb/>Appellant School). On behalf of Respondents No.3 and 4, <lb/>Respondent No.3 was examined. Each party filed documents in <lb/>support of their respective contentions. On consideration of the <lb/>evidence and documents furnished before it, the learned trial <lb/>Court in Issue No.1, concluded as follows; <lb/>&quot;… 65. It is seen in the evidence that the plaintiff in <lb/>the instant suit is suffering from blood pressure and <lb/>backache. Undoubtedly the suit premises is required for <lb/>the bonafide reason for the &quot;personal occupation&quot; of the <lb/>plaintiff, i.e., for the establishment of hotel business at <lb/>the fag end of his life for his livelihood. <lb/>……………………………………………………………………………………………… <lb/>71. ……Therefore, in my humble view the defendant <lb/>No. 2 cannot use and occupy the suit premises unless <lb/>expressly consented in written or oral by the plaintiff. <lb/>However, considering the future of the students who are <lb/>studying in the said School and are in the mid session, <lb/>the defendant No. 2 should be allowed to run the School <lb/>till the end of this session. Thus, this Issue is decided in <lb/>affirmative.&quot; <lb/>In Issue No.2, the learned trial Court went into an elaborate <lb/>discussion of the words &quot;willful default&quot; while relying on a <lb/>decision of the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court in a matter dealing with <lb/>the Tamil Nadu Buildings (Lease and Rent Control) Act, 1960 and <lb/>inter alia concluded that; <lb/>&quot;82. ……I hold that there is no willful default of rent <lb/>on the part of the defendants. However, the plaintiff <lb/>entitled (sic) to recover the arrear rent from the <lb/>defendants from the month of April, 2012 till disposal of <lb/>this case at the rate of ₹12,000/-per month since there is <lb/>no fresh or new agreement of enhancement of rents with <lb/>the plaintiff. Although the plaintiff has stepped into the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>shoes of the original owner but he cannot take the benefit <lb/>of the earlier Lease Deed (Exhibit-1) drawn between the <lb/>proforma defendants and the defendant No. 1 in the year <lb/>1996 which has been already expired on 2001 and not <lb/>entitled to claim the enhanced rate by virtue of the said <lb/>Lease Deed as same became ineffective or nonest. Thus, <lb/>this Issue is decided accordingly.&quot; <lb/>Issues No.3 and 4 were taken up together and the prayers of the <lb/>Respondent No.1 seeking to pay fifty times the usual registration <lb/>fees and to validate the Lease Deed of 1996, Exhibit 1, in terms <lb/>of the provisions contained in Notification No.2947/G dated <lb/>22.11.1946 was rejected by the Court with the reasoning that <lb/>the Respondent No.1 was not the original signatory to Exhibit 1. <lb/>The learned Court further concluded that the Appellant had no <lb/>right of pre-emption over the suit property, the same having <lb/>been lost by estoppel and acquiescence and the provisions of <lb/>Revenue Order No.I of 1917. <lb/>10. <lb/>Before this Court, learned Senior Counsel for the <lb/>Appellant canvassed the arguments that contrary to the <lb/>ratiocination of this Court on &quot;personal occupation&quot; as held in <lb/>Ashok Kumar Rai v. Girmey Goparma 1 , wherein eviction was <lb/>granted to enable the grown son of the Appellant to set up a <lb/>separate establishment, and his daughter-in-law to earn an <lb/>income, the learned trial Court held that the Respondent No.1 <lb/>required the suit property for his personal occupation, for the <lb/>purpose of establishing a hotel business. That, no evidence <lb/>either oral or documentary was forwarded in support of personal <lb/>occupation or bona fide requirement of the Respondent No.1. <lb/>Dwelling on the differences between the phrase &quot;personal <lb/>1 AIR 2012 Sikk 29 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>occupation&quot; as used in Notification No.6326-600-H&amp;W-B, dated <lb/>14.04.1949, (for short the &quot;Notification of 1949&quot;) as opposed to <lb/>the phrase &quot;bona fide requirement,&quot; as emanates in the Gangtok <lb/>Rent Control and Eviction Act 1 of 1956, (for short the &quot;Act of <lb/>1956&quot;), it was urged that the term &quot;personal occupation of the <lb/>landlords&quot; in the Notification of 1949 connotes the idea that <lb/>accommodation is needed directly and substantially for the <lb/>occupation of the landlord as interpreted by this Court in Paul <lb/>Sangay v. Mahabir Prasad Agarwalla 2 . That, interpretation of the <lb/>words &quot;personal occupation&quot; as found in other Rent Acts cannot <lb/>be resorted to. That, the term &quot;bona fide&quot; suggests that the <lb/>need must be genuine and not a mere desire or motivated by <lb/>extraneous considerations in trying to recover possession from <lb/>the tenant and the terms &quot;personal occupation&quot; and &quot;bona fide <lb/>requirement&quot; are neither synonymous nor interchangeable. It <lb/>was next contended that there was collusion between the <lb/>Respondent No.1 and the Respondent No.3, who, in cross-<lb/>examination, admitted that, he had sent a letter dated <lb/>16.11.2011 to the Principal, Joy Bells School, stating that he <lb/>required the suit property for running a hotel business when, in <lb/>fact, the alleged sale transaction was already executed between <lb/>the Respondent No.3 and the Respondent No.1. This collusion <lb/>was not considered by the learned trial Court. Besides, the <lb/>prohibition of Revenue Order No.I of 1917 is not applicable to <lb/>the Appellant as the suit falls outside the rural area. Prolix <lb/>arguments were advanced by learned Senior Counsel pertaining <lb/>2 AIR 1980 SIKKIM 13 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>to a Gift Deed, dated 22.09.1977, executed by the father of <lb/>Respondent No.4 to her, the area covered by the Gift Deed, the <lb/>Sale Deed dated 11.11.2011 executed between the Respondents <lb/>No.3, 4 and Respondent No.1, emphasizing that, the documents <lb/>supra pertaining to the same property contradict each other in <lb/>terms of details and measurements. That, the Respondent No.3, <lb/>has falsely claimed to be the owner of the building and sans <lb/>authority granted &quot;No Objection&quot; on 16.11.1995, to the <lb/>functioning of the School, when Respondent No.4 is the actual <lb/>owner. The undervaluation of the suit property, as also non-<lb/>production of attesting witnesses to the alleged Sale Deed, was <lb/>questioned by the Appellant. That, despite determination of the <lb/>Lease Deed, Exhibit 1, on 23.03.2001, the School Management <lb/>continued to pay rents to the Respondents No.3 and 4 who <lb/>continued to accept the rents till November, 2011 and thereafter <lb/>vide Exhibit 2/S and Exhibit 2/T. That, no benefit accrues from <lb/>the default clause of the Lease Deed, to the Respondent No.1, as <lb/>afforded by the learned trial Court, vide the impugned Judgment. <lb/>That, the Lease, if any, is governed by the Transfer of Property <lb/>Act, 1882 (for short the &quot;T.P. Act&quot;) and determination thereof <lb/>must be as per the said Act, while the Tenancy is governed by <lb/>the relevant Tenancy Act. Thus, the Respondent No.1 cannot <lb/>seek eviction of the tenant, both on grounds of determination of <lb/>the Lease Deed and under the Notification of 1949. That, the <lb/>Appellant does not challenge the title but only the alleged sham <lb/>sale transaction, shearing the Respondent No.1 of locus standi to <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>file the Suit. Hence, the impugned Judgment and Decree be set <lb/>aside and a Decree be passed dismissing the Eviction Suit. <lb/>11. <lb/>Per contra, learned Senior Counsel for the <lb/>Respondent No.1, while conceding that the Lease Deed was <lb/>executed between the Respondent No.2 and Respondent No.3, <lb/>contended on the one hand, that the School is the lessee of the <lb/>suit property by virtue of the fact that the Appellant had been <lb/>paying rent in terms of Clauses 2, 14 and 15 of the Lease Deed, <lb/>Exhibit 1. That, after the suit property was purchased by the <lb/>Respondent No.1 he has stepped into the shoes of the original <lb/>owner and thereby sought eviction of the Appellant. The refusal <lb/>of the Respondent No.1 to accept the rent amount of <lb/>Rs.12,000/-(Rupees twelve thousand) only, was for the reason <lb/>that it was less than the enhanced rent, liable to be paid in <lb/>terms of Clause 12 of the Lease Deed, resulting in a clear default <lb/>of over more than four months. That, Clause 13 of the Lease <lb/>Deed permits the Respondent No.1 to ask Respondent No.2 and <lb/>the Appellant to vacate the suit property, by issuing an advance <lb/>Notice of three months. In a contradictory argument, it was <lb/>strangely canvassed that Clause 12 of the Lease Deed is a <lb/>Renewal Clause providing for renewal of the Lease on expiry of <lb/>five years but as no such renewal was sought, the Appellant <lb/>thereby became a trespasser into the suit property, on and from <lb/>23.03.2001 and is liable to pay mesne profits by way of <lb/>damages. That, the Lease Deed cannot be impliedly renewed as <lb/>sought to be made out by the Appellant, for which support was <lb/>garnered from the ruling in Shanti Prasad Devi and Another v. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>Shankar Mahto and Others 3 . That, the Respondent No.1 <lb/>commenced preparations for building a hotel in the suit property <lb/>as the Appellant had agreed to vacate by the end of the <lb/>Academic Session of 2012, hence, the provisions of Section 115 <lb/>of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 are applicable. That, the suit <lb/>property is required bona fide by the Respondent No.1 due to his <lb/>advancing age and physical ailments disabling him to work as a <lb/>Contractor and was not demolished under cross-examination. On <lb/>this count reliance was placed on Ashok Kumar Rai v. Girmey <lb/>Goparma 4 . That, the Notification of 1949 being dealt with herein, <lb/>is concerned only with &quot;personal occupation&quot; and hence the <lb/>words &quot;bona fide&quot; as required in the Act of 1956, is extraneous, <lb/>for which reliance was placed on Renula Bose, Srimati v. Rai <lb/>Manmatha Nath Bose and Others 5 . While rueing the denial of the <lb/>learned trial Court for eviction on ground of default, it was <lb/>contended that despite this finding, the Respondent No.1 was, <lb/>however, found to be entitled to arrears of rent. <lb/>12. <lb/>That, sale transaction and value thereof was due to <lb/>the family relations between the Respondents No.1, 3 and 4 and <lb/>inapplicable to the Appellant. Despite awareness of the sale <lb/>transaction, the Appellant allowed its completion and thereafter <lb/>put forth claims of pre-emption but the provisions of Revenue <lb/>Order No.I of 1917, renders the Appellant ineligible thereof. <lb/>Relying on the ratio of Lingala Kondala Rao v. Vootukuri Narayana <lb/>3 AIR 2005 SC 2905 <lb/>4 AIR 2012 Sikk 29 <lb/>5 AIR 1945 PC 108 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>Rao 6 , it was next contended that the tenant cannot challenge the <lb/>document conferring title on the landlord, besides, the Appellant <lb/>had accepted the Respondent No.1 as his landlord by virtue of <lb/>the rent remittance. The issue of sham transaction found no <lb/>place before the learned trial Court, as evident from the absence <lb/>of an issue struck on this aspect. That, Issues No.3 and 4 have <lb/>been discussed and decided against the Appellant, thus no <lb/>further question need arise on these. <lb/>13. <lb/>Learned Counsel for the Respondents No.3 and 4, <lb/>while supporting the contention of the Appellant, reiterated that <lb/>the question of sham transaction cannot be raised at the <lb/>Appellate stage, not having been averred or argued at trial. <lb/>That, the legality of the sale transaction between the Respondent <lb/>No.1 and the Respondents No.3 and 4, suffers no infirmity and <lb/>questions on title cannot be raised by a tenant in an Eviction <lb/>Suit. That, the provisions of Revenue Order No.I of 1917 debars <lb/>the Appellant from pre-emption, hence, the Appeal deserves to <lb/>be dismissed. <lb/>14. <lb/>In his Cross Objection to the Appeal, the Respondent <lb/>No.1 agitated that the Judgment of the learned trial Court in <lb/>respect of Issues No.1 and 2, are contrary to law and deserve to <lb/>be set aside. The conclusion of the learned trial Court at not <lb/>having held the Appellant and Respondent No.2 as trespassers, <lb/>in view of the non-renewal of the Lease Deed, was also assailed. <lb/>That, the decision of the learned trial Court to reject the prayer <lb/>6 (2003) 1 SCC 672 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>for validation of Exhibit 1, in terms of Notification No.2947/G, <lb/>dated 22.11.1946, was contrary to the decisions of this Court. <lb/>Pausing here for a moment, it may be pointed out that the <lb/>prayer for setting aside the finding in Issue No.1, was <lb/>subsequently withdrawn at the final hearing, by learned Senior <lb/>Counsel for the Respondent No.1. <lb/>15. <lb/>Learned Senior Counsel for the Appellant submitted <lb/>that the Cross-Objection deserves a dismissal as no grounds <lb/>arise to sustain it. While urging the grounds put forth in <lb/>Interlocutory Application (I.A.) No.5 of 2017 which is an <lb/>application under Order XLI Rule 27 read with Section 151 of the <lb/>Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (for short the &quot;CPC, 1908&quot;), <lb/>learned Senior Counsel for the Appellant sought admission of a <lb/>copy of the khasra records of Respondent No.1, which were not <lb/>in their possession during trial. That, the document establishes <lb/>that the property was not in the joint names of Respondents <lb/>No.3 and 4 but only of Respondent No.4, contrary to the Sale <lb/>Deed, Exhibit 2. To establish this assertion, the Appellant filed <lb/>I.A. No.7 of 2018, another application under Order XLI Rule 27 <lb/>read with Section 151 of the CPC, 1908, seeking to admit and <lb/>exhibit the entire records of the registration proceedings relating <lb/>to registration of the Sale Deed dated 11.11.2011. <lb/>16. <lb/>Disputing the maintainability of both the petitions <lb/>supra, learned Senior Counsel for the Respondent No.1 <lb/>contended that the title of the Respondent No.1 as the landlord, <lb/>is being assailed, which was not the case of the Appellant at <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>trial, besides, the Appellant had attorned to the Respondent No.1 <lb/>as his landlord, by tendering rent to him. That, the additional <lb/>evidence proposed to be brought in Appeal, was available in the <lb/>Office of the District Collector and the Appellant is seeking to <lb/>introduce fresh pleadings and evidence at this stage, which is <lb/>impermissible, hence both the petitions be dismissed. <lb/>17. <lb/>Learned Counsel for the Respondents No.3 and 4, <lb/>while, also objecting to the I.As supra, sought outright rejection <lb/>of the petitions, lacking ingredients stipulated in Order XLI Rule <lb/>27 of the CPC, 1908, and the khas records, being public <lb/>documents, were maintained in the Office of the Registrar/ <lb/>District Collector, East, and therefore available, had it been <lb/>sought for. That, the title of the Respondent No.1 was never in <lb/>dispute and no issue on this aspect was framed by the learned <lb/>trial Court. That the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court in Lingala Kondala <lb/>Rao (supra) has held that the tenant cannot challenge the title of <lb/>the landlord. That in view of the said submissions, these <lb/>documents are not required for pronouncement of Judgment <lb/>herein, and the I.As consequently be disregarded. <lb/>18. <lb/>I.A. No.8 of 2019 was filed by the Respondent No.3 <lb/>under Order XLI Rule 27 read with Section 151 of the CPC, 1908, <lb/>seeking permission of this Court to produce attested copy of <lb/>registered Gift Deed document executed on 22.09.1977, by the <lb/>father of Respondent No.4 in respect of his three storeyed RCC <lb/>building located at Tadong Block and another Gift Deed <lb/>document executed on 01.09.1981, by Respondent No.4 in <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>favour of the Respondent No.3, with respect to the suit property <lb/>along with Construction Order issued to the Respondent No.3, by <lb/>the concerned authority. That, these documents were necessary <lb/>to abrogate the allegations made by the Appellant in the I.As <lb/>supra. <lb/>19. <lb/>Learned Senior Counsel for the Appellant, sought <lb/>rejection of the petition, as the Sale transaction is false, sham, <lb/>collusive and void. <lb/>20. <lb/>The rival submissions canvassed by learned Counsel <lb/>for the parties were heard and carefully considered, the <lb/>documents and evidence on record as also the impugned <lb/>Judgment were meticulously perused including the citations <lb/>made at the Bar. <lb/>21. <lb/>The questions that fall for consideration before this <lb/>Court are; <lb/>(i) <lb/>Whether there was a jural relationship between the <lb/>Appellant and the Respondent No.1? <lb/>(ii) <lb/>Whether the suit premises were required by the <lb/>Respondent No.1 for his &quot;personal occupation&quot; as <lb/>envisaged in Notification No.6326-600-H&amp;W-B of the <lb/>Health and Works Department, Government of Sikkim, <lb/>dated 14.04.1949? <lb/>(iii) <lb/>Whether the finding of the learned trial Court with <lb/>regard to arrears of rent to be paid by the Appellant to <lb/>the Respondent No.1 from the month of April, 2012 till <lb/>the filing of the Suit, despite concluding absence of <lb/>default in rent payment, was correct? <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>(iv) <lb/>Whether the learned trial Court ought to have allowed <lb/>validation of the Lease Deed in terms of Notification <lb/>No.2947/G dated 22.11.1946? <lb/>22. <lb/>To address the first question formulated, it is <lb/>essential to note that contradictory arguments were variously <lb/>raised by the Respondent No.1, as regards the status of the <lb/>Appellant vis-à-vis the Respondent No.1, (i) that the Appellant <lb/>was paying rent in terms of the Lease Deed and was therefore a <lb/>lessee on the suit property; (ii) refusal by the Respondent No.1 <lb/>to accept the rent of Rs.12,000/-(Rupees twelve thousand) <lb/>only, as it was less than the amount envisaged under Clause 12 <lb/>of the Lease Deed, resulted in default in rent for more than four <lb/>months; (iii) contrarily, it was urged that as the Lease Deed had <lb/>expired and was not renewed, the Appellant was a trespasser on <lb/>the suit property as the Lease Deed cannot be impliedly <lb/>renewed, revealing a confusion in his stance. <lb/>23. <lb/>It is an admitted position that a Lease Deed, Exhibit <lb/>1, was executed between the Respondent No.2 and Respondent <lb/>No.3 in the year 1996, for a period of five years, from <lb/>23.03.1996 up to 22.03.2001. The School undisputedly started <lb/>running from the premises since 1984. The Lease Deed <lb/>determined on 23.03.2001 and despite non-renewal, the School <lb/>continued to function from the same premises while rent <lb/>continued to be remitted by the Appellant and accepted by the <lb/>Respondents No.3 and 4. In 2011, the Respondents No. 3 and 4 <lb/>sold the property to Respondent No.1, vide Exhibit 2, a Sale <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>Deed dated 11.11.2011, registered on 09.12.2011. The property <lb/>thus came to be mutated in the name of the Respondent No.1 <lb/>vide the parcha khatiyan, Exhibit 3. Thus, after the transaction, <lb/>it is evident that the Respondent No.1 stepped into the shoes of <lb/>the Respondents No.3 and 4. Indeed, the provisions of Section <lb/>109 of the T.P. Act, which deals with the rights of the Lessor&apos;s <lb/>transferee are relevant herein. The Section is reproduced <lb/>hereinbelow for easy reference; <lb/>&quot;109. Rights of lessor&apos;s transferee.-If the lessor <lb/>transfers the property leased, or any part thereof, or any <lb/>part of his interest therein, the transferee, in the absence <lb/>of a contract to the contrary, shall possess all the rights, <lb/>and, if the lessee so elects, be subject to all the liabilities <lb/>of the lessor as to the property or part transferred so long <lb/>as he is the owner of it; but the lessor shall not, by <lb/>reason only of such transfer cease to be subject to any of <lb/>the liabilities imposed upon him by the lease, unless the <lb/>lessee elects to treat the transferee as the person liable to <lb/>him: <lb/>Provided that the transferee is not entitled to arrears of <lb/>rent due before the transfer, and that, if the lessee, not <lb/>having reason to believe that such transfer has been <lb/>made, pays rent to the lessor, the lessee shall not be <lb/>liable to pay such rent over again to the transferee. <lb/>The lessor, the transferee and the lessee may determine <lb/>what proportion of the premium or rent reserved by the <lb/>lease is payable in respect of the part so transferred, and, <lb/>in case they disagree, such determination may be made <lb/>by any Court having jurisdiction to entertain a suit for the <lb/>possession of the property leased.&quot; <lb/>The Section, as evident, postulates that the rights attached to a <lb/>property which arise out of the possession and control of the <lb/>property, will pass with the property. The Section does not insist <lb/>that the transfer of the landlord&apos;s rights can take effect only if <lb/>the tenant attorns. The Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court in Ambica Prasad <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>v. Mohd. Alam and Another <lb/>7 , while discussing the provisions of <lb/>Section 109 of the T.P. Act, held as hereinbelow extracted; <lb/>&quot;15. … From a perusal of the aforesaid section, it is <lb/>manifest that after the transfer of lessor&apos;s right in favour <lb/>of the transferee, the latter gets all rights and liabilities of <lb/>the lessor in respect of subsisting tenancy. The section <lb/>does not insist that transfer will take effect only when <lb/>the tenant attorns. It is well settled that a transferee of <lb/>the landlord&apos;s rights steps into the shoes of the landlord <lb/>with all the rights and liabilities of the transferor <lb/>landlord in respect of the subsisting tenancy. The section <lb/>does not require that the transfer of the right of the <lb/>landlord can take effect only if the tenant attorns to him. <lb/>Attornment by the tenant is not necessary to confer <lb/>validity of the transfer of the landlord&apos;s rights. Since <lb/>attornment by the tenant is not required, a notice under <lb/>Section 106 in terms of the old terms of lease by the <lb/>transferor (sic transferee) landlord would be proper and <lb/>so also the suit for ejectment.&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>The evidence establishes sale vide Exhibit 2 hence, in terms of <lb/>this provision and Exhibit 2, Sale Deed, the Respondent No.1 has <lb/>unequivocally stepped into the shoes of Respondents No.3 and <lb/>4. <lb/>24. <lb/>The Sale Deed between the Respondent No.1 and <lb/>Respondents No.3 and 4 was executed on 11.11.2011 and the <lb/>property registered in the name of the Respondent No.1 on <lb/>19.12.2011. A Notice for eviction was issued to the Appellant by <lb/>the Respondent No.1 on 21.08.2012 vide Exhibit 2/Y, which is <lb/>not denied by the Appellant. Perusal of Exhibit 2/U indicates that <lb/>during August 2012, rent was being remitted by the Appellant to <lb/>the Respondent No.1. <lb/>25. <lb/>It is relevant now to consider the provisions of <lb/>Section 111 of the T.P. Act, which provides for determination of <lb/>Lease and states inter alia that a Lease of immoveable property <lb/>7 (2015) 13 SCC 13 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>determines by efflux of the time limited thereby. The relevant <lb/>provision is, as extracted below; <lb/>&quot;111.Determination <lb/>of <lb/>lease.-A <lb/>lease <lb/>of <lb/>immoveable property determines-<lb/>(a) by efflux of the time limited thereby; <lb/>(b) ……………… <lb/>(c) ……………… <lb/>(d) ……………… <lb/>(e) ……………… <lb/>(f) ……………… <lb/>(g) ……………… <lb/>(h) ………………&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>On the anvil of this statute, it is clear that the Lease Deed, <lb/>Exhibit 1, entered into between the Respondents No.2 and 3, <lb/>determined on 23.03.2001, the period of existence of the Lease <lb/>being from 23.03.1996 to 22.03.2001. Clause 12 of Exhibit 1, <lb/>which provides for renewal of the Lease with enhancement of <lb/>rent to the extent of 10% to 15% above the existing rent, was <lb/>not resorted to by either of the concerned parties. The <lb/>documents Exhibit 2/S (collectively) and Exhibit 2/T (collectively) <lb/>are conclusive of the fact that the amount of rent of Rs.12,000/-<lb/>(Rupees twelve thousand) only, continued to be paid by the <lb/>Appellant School and received by the Respondents No.3 and 4 till <lb/>November, 2011. Exhibit 2/T and Exhibit 2/U reveal that rent for <lb/>the month of December, 2011 was sent to both the Respondent <lb/>No.4 and the Respondent No.1, although it was refused by both <lb/>payees. This mode of remittance to both Respondents No.3 and <lb/>4 and to Respondent No.1, albeit separately, continued till <lb/>March, 2012 vide Exhibit 2/T. From April, 2012 vide Exhibit 2/U, <lb/>it appears that rent remittance, by Money Order, was made to <lb/>the Respondent No.1, upto April, 2013. The act of rent <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>remittance coupled with the specific admission of the Appellant <lb/>in his evidence that Joy Bells School was the tenant under <lb/>Respondents No.3 and 4, and thereafter of Respondent No.1 <lb/>after the School came to learn of the alleged sale, discloses his <lb/>indubitable attornment to the Respondent No.1 as his landlord. <lb/>26. <lb/>That having been said, the provisions of Section 116 <lb/>of the T.P. Act, which deals with the effect of holding over, is of <lb/>relevance here, which reads as follows; <lb/>&quot;116. Effect of holding over.-If a lessee or under-<lb/>lessee of property remains in possession thereof after the <lb/>determination of the lease granted to the lessee, and the <lb/>lessor or his legal representative accepts rent from the <lb/>lessee or under-lessee, or otherwise assents to his <lb/>continuing in possession, the lease is, in the absence of <lb/>an agreement to the contrary, renewed from year to year, <lb/>or from month to month, according to the purpose for <lb/>which the property is leased, as specified in section 106.&quot; <lb/>The provision is self-explanatory and does not necessitate <lb/>elucidation. Section 106, the provision referred to in the Section <lb/>supra, deals with duration of certain Leases in absence of written <lb/>contract or local usage, and provides as follows; <lb/>&quot;106. Duration of certain leases in absence of <lb/>written contract or local usage.-(1) In the absence of a <lb/>contract or local law or usage to the contrary, a lease of <lb/>immovable property for agricultural or manufacturing <lb/>purposes shall be deemed to be a lease from year to year, <lb/>terminable, on the part of either lessor or lessee, by six <lb/>months&apos; notice; and a lease of immovable property for <lb/>any other purpose shall be deemed to be a lease from <lb/>month to month, terminable, on the part of either lessor <lb/>or lessee, by fifteen days&apos; notice. <lb/>(2) Notwithstanding anything contained in any <lb/>other law for the time being in force, the period <lb/>mentioned in sub-section (1) shall commence from the <lb/>date of receipt of notice. <lb/>(3) A notice under sub-section (1) shall not be <lb/>deemed to be invalid merely because the period <lb/>mentioned therein falls short of the period specified under <lb/>that sub-section, where a suit or proceeding is filed after <lb/>the expiry of the period mentioned in that sub-section. <lb/>(4) Every notice under sub-section (1) must be in <lb/>writing, signed by or on behalf of the person giving it, and <lb/>either be sent by post to the party who is intended to be <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>bound by it or be tendered or delivered personally to such <lb/>party, or to one of his family or servants at his residence, <lb/>or (if such tender or delivery is not practicable) affixed to <lb/>a conspicuous part of the property.&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>27. <lb/>On the determination of Exhibit 1, the Lease of the <lb/>immoveable property, being neither for agricultural or <lb/>manufacturing purposes, is deemed to be a Lease from month to <lb/>month. Although the purchase and mutation has been <lb/>vehemently contested by the Appellant, terming it to be a sham <lb/>transaction, however this is altogether a tangential matter and <lb/>cannot be considered in an eviction proceeding. Besides, during <lb/>the course of arguments, learned Senior Counsel for the <lb/>Appellant conceded that he had no challenge to the title of the <lb/>property, he only assailed the process of transfer. On this <lb/>aspect, appropriate reference may be made to the observation of <lb/>the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court, in Keshar Bai v. Chhunulal 8 , as <lb/>follows; <lb/>&quot;…15. The High Court has expressed that the <lb/>respondent was justified in asking the appellant to <lb/>produce the documents. Implicit in this observation is <lb/>the High Court&apos;s view that the respondent could have in <lb/>an eviction suit got the title of the appellant finally <lb/>adjudicated upon. There is a fallacy in this reasoning. In <lb/>eviction proceedings the question of title to the <lb/>properties in question may be incidentally gone into, but <lb/>cannot be decided finally. <lb/>16. A similar question fell for consideration of this <lb/>Court in Bhogadi Kannababu [Bhogadi Kannababu <lb/>v. Vuggina Pydamma 9 . In that case it was argued that <lb/>the landlady was not entitled to inherit the properties in <lb/>question and hence could not maintain the application for <lb/>eviction on the ground of default and sub-letting under <lb/>the A.P. Tenancy Act. This Court referred to its decision <lb/>in Tej Bhan Madan v. Addl. District Judge 10 in which it <lb/>was held that a tenant was precluded from denying the <lb/>title of the landlady on the general principle of estoppel <lb/>between the landlord and the tenant and that this <lb/>principle, in its basic foundations, means no more than <lb/>that under certain circumstances law considers it unjust <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">8 (2014) 11 SCC 438 <lb/>9 (2006) 5 SCC 532 <lb/>10 (1988) 3 SCC 137 <lb/>RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>to allow a person to approbate and reprobate. Section <lb/>116 of the Evidence Act is clearly applicable to such a <lb/>situation. This Court held that even if the landlady was <lb/>not entitled to inherit the properties in question, she <lb/>could still maintain the application for eviction and the <lb/>finding of fact recorded by the courts below in favour of <lb/>the landlady, was not liable to be disturbed. The position <lb/>on law was stated by this Court as under: (Bhogadi <lb/>Kannababu <lb/>case [Bhogadi <lb/>Kannababu v. Vuggina <lb/>Pydamma.] <lb/>&quot;19. In this connection, we may also point out that <lb/>in an eviction petition filed on the ground of sub-letting <lb/>and default, the court needs to decide whether <lb/>relationship of landlord and tenant exists and not the <lb/>question of title to the properties in question, which may <lb/>be incidentally gone into, but cannot be decided finally in <lb/>the eviction proceeding.&quot;&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>Hence, no further discussions need ensue on the title of the suit <lb/>property to finally decide it. Consequently, the requirement of <lb/>filing documents by the Respondent No.3, as depicted in I.A. <lb/>No.8 of 2019, does not arise. Neither are the documents sought <lb/>to be filed by the Appellant under I.A.5 of 2017 and I.A.7 of <lb/>2018, necessary or relevant. The Appellant cannot, in view of <lb/>the foregoing discussions, be tainted with the brush of a <lb/>trespasser, and the ambiguous stand adopted by the Respondent <lb/>No.1, on this point, finds no foothold. The finding of the learned <lb/>trial Court that &quot;the defendant No.2 cannot use and occupy the <lb/>suit premises unless expressly consented in written or oral by <lb/>the plaintiff&quot; in my considered opinion, is an erroneous <lb/>conclusion in view of the afore discussed provisions of law. In <lb/>conclusion, considering the action of both the Appellant and the <lb/>Respondent No.1, it cannot, but be concluded that jural <lb/>relationship exists between the Respondent No.1 and the <lb/>Appellant, which answers the first question. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>28. <lb/>While addressing the second question formulated <lb/>hereinabove i.e. &quot;Whether the suit premises were required by <lb/>the Respondent No.1 for his &quot;personal occupation&quot; as envisaged <lb/>in Notification No.6326-600-H&amp;W-B of the Health and Works <lb/>Department, Government of Sikkim, dated 14.04.1949?,&quot; it is <lb/>essential to reproduce the relevant provisions of the Notification <lb/>of 1949 which reads as hereunder; <lb/>&quot;GOVERNMENT OF SIKKIM <lb/>Health and Works Department <lb/>Notification No.6326-600-H&amp;W-B. <lb/>Under powers conferred in para 2 of Notification <lb/>No.1366-G, dated the 28th July 1947, the following Rules <lb/>have been framed to regulate letting and sub-letting of <lb/>premises controlling rents thereof and unreasonable eviction <lb/>of tenants as the scarcity of housing accommodation still <lb/>exists in Sikkim. <lb/>I The landlords can charge rent for premises either for <lb/>residential or business purposes on the basis of the rents <lb/>prevailing in locality in year 1939, plus an increase upto 50 <lb/>per cent so long as the scarcity of housing accommodation <lb/>lasts. <lb/>2. The landlords cannot eject the tenants so long as the <lb/>scarcity of housing accommodation lasts, but when the <lb/>whole or part of the premises are required for their personal <lb/>occupation or for thorough overhauling the premises or on <lb/>failure by the tenants to pay rent for four months the <lb/>landlords may be permitted to evict the tenant on due <lb/>application to the Chief Court. <lb/>3-Any tenant may apply to this Department for fixing <lb/>his rent. On receipt of such application the Department will <lb/>enquire about the rent prevailing in the locality in 1939, and <lb/>fix rent as per Rule (I) above. <lb/>4-Any person acting in contravention of this Notification <lb/>will be liable to prosecution under para. 4. of notification <lb/>No.I366-066-G, dated the 28th July, 1947. <lb/>5. The tenant means those person in actual occupation. <lb/>Landlord means owners of the premises. <lb/>These rules will come into force with immediate effect. <lb/>By order of his Highness the Maharaja of Sikkim. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>R.B. Singh <lb/>Gangtok, <lb/>Secretary, <lb/>Health and Works Department; <lb/>The 14 th , April, 1949. <lb/>Government of Sikkim.&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>29. <lb/>The Notification inter alia seeks to regulate <lb/>unreasonable eviction of tenants so long as the scarcity of <lb/>housing accommodation still exists in Sikkim. As per the <lb/>Notification, &quot;Landlords means owners of the premises,&quot; and <lb/>&quot;The tenant means those person(sic) in actual occupation.&quot; In <lb/>view of the discussions that have ensued in Question No.1, it <lb/>cannot be disputed that the Respondent No.1 is the owner of <lb/>the premises and thus the landlord, while the position of the <lb/>Appellant as the tenant, thereby remains undisputed. The <lb/>Notification enumerates three grounds for the eviction of a <lb/>tenant; (i) personal occupation of the landlord; (ii) thorough <lb/>overhauling of the premises; and (iii) failure by the tenants to <lb/>pay rent for four months. We may notice that the Notification <lb/>mandates that there cannot be unreasonable eviction of tenants <lb/>as the scarcity of &quot;housing accommodation&quot; exists in Sikkim. It <lb/>would pertinently be questioned as to whether running a School <lb/>in tenanted premises for business purposes would also <lb/>tantamount to &quot;housing accommodation.&quot; Stroud&apos;s Judicial <lb/>Dictionary of Words and Phrases, Fifth Edition by John S. James, <lb/>Volume 2 D-H at page No.1188 explains the meaning of &quot;house&quot; <lb/>inter alia as follows; <lb/>&quot;(12) (Public Health (London) Act 1891 (c.76), <lb/>s.141), &quot;&quot;house&quot; includes schools, also factories and other <lb/>buildings in which persons are employed&quot;; a building <lb/>used by day for religious exercises, and by night as a <lb/>refuge for the destitute, but which contained sleeping <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>accommodation, was a &quot;house&quot; within s.2(1)(e) of that <lb/>Act (R. v. Mead, 64 L.J.M.C. 108).&quot; <lb/>30. <lb/>The Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court in The Tata Engineering <lb/>And Locomotive Company Ltd. v. The Gram Panchayat, Pimpri <lb/>Waghere 11 inter alia held that; <lb/>&quot;20. The weight of judicial opinion is conclusively <lb/>in favour of the view that the word &quot;house&quot; extends to a <lb/>building which is used for business and should not be <lb/>restricted to a mere dwelling house (see Land Law, Cases <lb/>and Materials by R.H. Mandsley and E.H. Burn, Third <lb/>Edition, p.832).&quot; <lb/>Besides the dictionary meaning and judicial opinion supra, while <lb/>perusing the Notification of 1949, paragraph I of the Notification <lb/>mentions that &quot;landlords can charge rent for premises either for <lb/>residential or &quot;business purposes&quot; on the basis of the rents <lb/>prevailing in locality in year 1939, (sic) plus an increase upto 50 <lb/>per cent so long as the scarcity of housing accommodation <lb/>lasts.&quot; Thus, the answer to the question is found in the <lb/>Notification itself, which conclusively includes accommodation <lb/>used for &quot;business purposes&quot; as also &quot;housing accommodation.&quot; <lb/>31. <lb/>That having been settled, it is now essential to <lb/>examine what &quot;personal occupation&quot; would include. While citing <lb/>the decision in Paul Sangay&quot;s case (supra), it was contended by <lb/>learned Senior Counsel for the Appellant at great length, that the <lb/>ratio interprets the said term as accommodation which is needed <lb/>directly and substantially for occupation of the landlord and is <lb/>narrower in scope than &quot;bona fide occupation&quot; which has already <lb/>been detailed in his arguments. Pausing here for a moment, it <lb/>11 (1976) 4 SCC 177 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>may be noticed that the Judgment also records that the Court is <lb/>aware of the long catena of cases of the different High Courts <lb/>construing the expression &quot;landlord&quot; or &quot;for the occupation of the <lb/>landlord&quot; or &quot;his own occupation&quot; and after referring to the <lb/>Judgments of several High Courts, concluded that; <lb/>&quot;20. I can understand that if the enactment in <lb/>question providing for ejectment of tenants on the ground <lb/>of a requirement of the landlord uses the expression <lb/>&quot;occupation of the landlord&quot; or &quot;his own occupation&quot; or <lb/>other similar expressions referring to the landlord only, <lb/>like the enactments which were considered and construed <lb/>by the Calcutta High Court in Pushpalata&apos;s case and the <lb/>Patna High Court in Bidhu Bhusan&apos;s case, and the Andhra <lb/>Pradesh High Court in Balaiah&apos;s case, such expressions <lb/>may be required to be construed as not applying strictly <lb/>or exclusively to the landlord himself, but as including his <lb/>family or dependents or other normal emanations. …&quot; <lb/>The Court observed that as the Gangtok Rent Control and <lb/>Eviction Act, 1956, uses both the expressions &quot;landlord&quot; and <lb/>also &quot;his dependents,&quot; it would neither be proper nor be <lb/>permissible to allow the expression &quot;landlord&quot; to expand and <lb/>emanate indefinitely and thus to include members of his family <lb/>or any other person, whether dependent upon him or not. The <lb/>Court was of the opinion that this would amount to adding <lb/>words to the provisions of the enactment and thus to redraft the <lb/>same. The Court went on to hold that it was not shown by any <lb/>clear or clinching evidence that the two sons of the Plaintiff <lb/>therein were also his dependents. Thereafter taking into <lb/>consideration the evidence on record, the Court held that it is <lb/>not the case of the plaintiff at any stage that he requires the <lb/>suit-premises as he genuinely intends to establish his sons in <lb/>business but his case all-through was that his sons have said <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>that they want to start separate and independent business and <lb/>the suit-premises are necessary therefor. The two sons were not <lb/>examined during trial. The learned Court was of the view that <lb/>unless both the sons of the Plaintiff step into the witness box, <lb/>the Plaintiff&quot;s case fails. Before parting with the case, the Court <lb/>went on to observe as hereinbelow; <lb/>&quot;27. ... As I have already pointed out at the out-<lb/>set, I have proceeded on the basis that the Gangtok Rent <lb/>Control and Eviction Act, 1956 applies to this case. I have <lb/>also pointed out that this Court has both in Jokhiram&apos;s <lb/>case (1977-1 Sikkim LJ 30) and in Sakuntala Bai&apos;s <lb/>case (1977-1 Sikkim LJ 33) held that even if the said Act <lb/>of 1956 is not applicable, the suit for eviction of tenants <lb/>would be governed by the provisions of law contained in <lb/>the Notification No. 6326-600/H&amp;WB, dated 14th Apr. <lb/>1949 and that the provisions of law as contained in the <lb/>said notification are also more or less similar. But I <lb/>should, however, point out that in Para. 2 of the <lb/>Notification of 1949, the ground of ejectment is <lb/>requirement of the premises for the &quot;personal occupation&quot; <lb/>of the landlord, while as I have already noted, under the <lb/>Act of 1956 the ground of ejectment is requirement of the <lb/>premises for the bona fide occupation of the landlord or <lb/>his dependents. I have already pointed out, relying on the <lb/>Supreme Court case of D.N. Sangavi v. A.T. Das (AIR <lb/>1974 SC 1026), that the expression &quot;personal <lb/>occupation&quot; <lb/>must <lb/>connote <lb/>the <lb/>idea <lb/>that <lb/>the <lb/>accommodation is needed directly and substantially for <lb/>the occupation of the landlord and I have already pointed <lb/>out hereinbefore that even if the occupation of the suit-<lb/>premises was necessary for starting independent business <lb/>for the two sons, that would not have been a case of <lb/>requirement &quot;for the personal &quot;occupation&quot; of the <lb/>landlord&quot;. That being so, the plaintiff&quot;s claim for <lb/>ejectment of the tenant must also fail even if the <lb/>provisions of law contained in the aforesaid Notification <lb/>of 1949 were to apply to this case.&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>Since the Judgment supra was dealing with the Gangtok Rent <lb/>Control and Eviction Act 1 of 1956, the Court was differentiating <lb/>between what &quot;landlord&quot; and &quot;his dependents,&quot; in the context of <lb/>the Act entailed, as already extracted supra. At best the remarks <lb/>made in the concluding portion of Paragraph 27 of the Judgment <lb/>referring to the Notification of 1949, which is highlighted, is <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>obiter dictum and the Appellant can obtain no benefit from this <lb/>observation whatsoever. Besides, it may pertinently be pointed <lb/>out that it is no more res integra that a landlord cannot be non-<lb/>suited for the purpose that he failed to examine his family <lb/>member who intends to do business in the required premises. <lb/>32. <lb/>In this context, it would be appropriate to refer to <lb/>the decision of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Mehmooda Gulshan <lb/>v. Javaid Hussain Mungloo 12 wherein the Hon&apos;ble Court was taking <lb/>into consideration an Appeal under Section (11)(i)(h) of the <lb/>Jammu and Kashmir Houses and Shop Rent Control Act, 1966, <lb/>which reads as follows; <lb/>&quot;11.(1)(h) where the house or shop is reasonably <lb/>required by the landlord either for the purposes of <lb/>building or re-building, or his own occupation or for the <lb/>occupation of any person for whose benefit the house or <lb/>shop is held.&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>Allowing the Appeal of the landlady, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court <lb/>inter alia held as follows; <lb/>&quot;12. We fail to understand the approach made by <lb/>the High Court. It has clearly come in evidence of the <lb/>appellant that her one son is unemployed and in view of <lb/>unemployment, he was frustrated. The appellant&apos;s <lb/>husband had contracted second marriage and he had <lb/>deserted the appellant. The appellant herself was <lb/>unemployed with no source of income. The appellant, <lb/>hence, prayed that the property be returned to her so <lb/>that her son can look after the family. In cross-<lb/>examination, she denied the suggestion that the son was <lb/>doing business with his father. It had also been stated <lb/>further that &quot;except the premises and the residential <lb/>house, the plaintiff has no other property&quot;. The trial court <lb/>has meticulously analysed and appreciated the reasonable <lb/>requirement of the premises for the business to be <lb/>12 (2017) 5 SCC 683 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>managed by the son of the appellant especially in her <lb/>peculiar family circumstances. In our view, the trial court <lb/>has appreciated the evidence in the right perspective and <lb/>held that it is not mere desire but genuine need. The <lb/>finding of the trial court was challenged mainly on the <lb/>ground that the son, for whose benefit the eviction is <lb/>sought, has not been examined. <lb/>13. Mere non-examination of the family member <lb/>who intends to do the business cannot be taken as a <lb/>ground for repelling the reasonable requirement of the <lb/>landlord. Under the Act, the landlord needs to establish <lb/>only a reasonable requirement. No doubt, it is not a <lb/>simple desire. It must be a genuine need. Whether the <lb/>requirement is based on a desire or need, will depend on <lb/>the facts of each case. <lb/>......................................................................................&quot; <lb/>33. <lb/>With regard to the term &quot;personal occupation,&quot; in <lb/>Mst. Bega Begum and Others v. Abdul Ahad Khan (dead) by L.Rs and <lb/>others 13 the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court was considering the <lb/>provisions of Section 11(1)(h) of the Jammu and Kashmir <lb/>Houses and Shops Rent Control Act, 1966. The landlords sought <lb/>eviction on the grounds that they required to extend their <lb/>business by running a hotel business themselves. The learned <lb/>trial Court dismissed the suit of the Plaintiffs which was <lb/>confirmed by the Hon&quot;ble High Court of Jammu and Kashmir on <lb/>grounds that the Plaintiffs had not proved their &quot;personal <lb/>necessity.&quot; Allowing the Appeal, the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court held <lb/>that the words &quot;reasonable requirement&quot; in sub-section 11(h) of <lb/>the Act postulates that there must be an element of need as <lb/>opposed to a mere desire or wish and concluded as follows; <lb/>&quot;13. Moreover, Section 11(h) of the Act uses the <lb/>words &quot;reasonable requirement&quot; which undoubtedly <lb/>postulate that there must be an element of need as <lb/>opposed to a mere desire or wish. The distinction <lb/>between desire and need should doubtless be kept in <lb/>mind but not so as to make even the genuine need as <lb/>nothing but a desire as the High Court has done in this <lb/>case. It seems to us that the connotation of the term <lb/>13 (1979) 1 SCC 273 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>&quot;need&quot; or &quot;requirement&quot; should not be artificially extended <lb/>nor its language so unduly stretched or strained as to <lb/>make it impossible or extremely difficult for the landlord <lb/>to get a decree for eviction. Such a course would defeat <lb/>the very purpose of the Act which affords the facility of <lb/>eviction of the tenant to the landlord on certain specified <lb/>grounds. This appears to us to be the general scheme of <lb/>all the Rent Control Acts prevalent in other States in the <lb/>country. This Court has considered the import of the <lb/>word &quot;requirement&quot; and pointed out that it merely <lb/>connotes that there should be an element of need. <lb/>…………………………………………………………………………………………… <lb/>19. Having regard, therefore, to the circumstances <lb/>mentioned above, we are unable to subscribe to the view <lb/>that the words &quot;own occupation&quot; must be so narrowly <lb/>interpreted so as to indicate actual physical possession of <lb/>the landlord personally and nothing short of that. We, <lb/>therefore, overrule the argument of the respondents on <lb/>this point.&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>It was reasoned that if the Plaintiff&quot;s (landlords) found that their <lb/>present business had become dull and was not yielding sufficient <lb/>income to maintain themselves and it was necessary to occupy <lb/>the house as to run a hotel business, it cannot by any stretch of <lb/>imagination be said that the plaintiffs had merely a desire rather <lb/>than a bona fide need for evicting the tenants. <lb/>34. <lb/>In Joginder Pal v. Naval Kishore Behal 14 , the Hon&apos;ble <lb/>Supreme Court while interpreting &quot;own use,&quot; inter alia concluded <lb/>that; <lb/>&quot;33. Our conclusions are crystallised as under: <lb/>(i) The words &quot;for his own use&quot; as occurring in <lb/>Section 13(3)(a)(ii) of the East Punjab Urban Rent <lb/>Restriction Act, 1949 must receive a wide, liberal and <lb/>useful meaning rather than a strict or narrow <lb/>construction. <lb/>(ii) The expression-landlord requires for &quot;his own <lb/>use&quot;, is not confined in its meaning to actual physical <lb/>user by the landlord personally. The requirement not <lb/>only of the landlord himself but also of the normal <lb/>&quot;emanations&quot; of the landlord is included therein. All the <lb/>cases and circumstances in which actual physical <lb/>occupation or user by someone else, would amount to <lb/>occupation or user by the landlord himself, cannot be <lb/>14 (2002) 5 SCC 397 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>exhaustively enumerated. It will depend on a variety of <lb/>factors such as interrelationship and interdependence -<lb/>economic or otherwise, between the landlord and such <lb/>person in the background of social, socio-religious and <lb/>local customs and obligations of the society or region to <lb/>which they belong. <lb/>(iii) The tests to be applied are: (i) whether the <lb/>requirement pleaded and proved may properly be <lb/>regarded as the landlord&apos;s own requirement; and, (ii) <lb/>whether on the facts and in the circumstances of a given <lb/>case, actual occupation and user by a person other than <lb/>the landlord would be deemed by the landlord as &quot;his <lb/>own&quot; occupation or user. The answer would, in its turn, <lb/>depend on (i) the nature and degree of relationship <lb/>and/or dependence between the landlord pleading the <lb/>requirement as &quot;his own&quot; and the person who would <lb/>actually use the premises; (ii) the circumstances in <lb/>which the claim arises and is put forward; and (iii) the <lb/>intrinsic tenability of the claim. The court on being <lb/>satisfied of the reasonability and genuineness of claim, <lb/>as distinguished from a mere ruse to get rid of the <lb/>tenant, will uphold the landlord&apos;s claim. <lb/>(iv) While casting its judicial verdict, the court shall <lb/>adopt a practical and meaningful approach guided by the <lb/>realities of life. <lb/>(v) In the present case, the requirement of the <lb/>landlord of the suit premises for user as office of his <lb/>chartered accountant son is the requirement of landlord <lb/>&quot;for his own use&quot; within the meaning of Section <lb/>13(3)(a)(ii).&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>35. <lb/>In the same vein, in Kailash Chand and Another v. <lb/>Dharam Dass 15 an application seeking an order of eviction under <lb/>Section 14(3)(a)(i) of the Himachal Pradesh Urban Rent Control <lb/>Act, 1987 (hereinafter the &quot;Act&quot;) was allowed by the Rent <lb/>Controller and the tenant was ordered to be evicted. The order <lb/>was maintained in Appeal by the Appellate Authority. The <lb/>Hon&apos;ble High Court in exercise of revisional jurisdiction set aside <lb/>the order of eviction. Before the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court, the <lb/>aggrieved landlords urged that the residential accommodation on <lb/>the first floor which was in occupation of the tenants was <lb/>required by them to accommodate their large family. The <lb/>Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court, set aside the Order of the Hon&quot;ble High <lb/>15 (2005) 5 SCC 375 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>Court and upholding that of the Rent Controller and the <lb/>Appellate Authority, dealt with the expression &quot;his own <lb/>occupation&quot; and inter alia observed as follows; <lb/>&quot;24. The expression &quot;his own occupation&quot; as <lb/>occurring in sub-clause (i) of clause (a) of sub-section <lb/>(3) is not to be assigned a narrow meaning. It has to be <lb/>read liberally and given a practical meaning. &quot;His own <lb/>occupation&quot; does not mean occupation by the landlord <lb/>alone and as an individual. The expressions &quot;for his own <lb/>use&quot; and &quot;for occupation by himself&quot; as occurring in two <lb/>other Rent Control Acts, have come up for the <lb/>consideration of this Court in Joginder Pal v. Naval <lb/>Kishore Behal 16 and Dwarkaprasad v. Niranjan 17 . It was <lb/>held that the requirement of members of the family of <lb/>the landlord or of the one who is dependent on the <lb/>landlord, is the landlord&apos;s own requirement. Regard will <lb/>be had to the social or socio-religious milieu and <lb/>practices prevalent in a particular section of society or a <lb/>particular region to which the landlord belongs, while <lb/>interpreting such expressions. The requirement of the <lb/>family <lb/>members <lb/>for <lb/>residence <lb/>is <lb/>certainly <lb/>the <lb/>requirement by the landlord for &quot;his own occupation&quot;. <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>36. <lb/>In Phiroze Bamanji Desai v. Chandrakant M. Patel and <lb/>others 18 , the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court considered the terms <lb/>reasonable and bona fide requirement in the Bombay Rents, <lb/>Hotel and Lodging House Rates Control Act (57 of 1947) and <lb/>inter alia held as follows; <lb/>&quot;7. Now, the decision of the District Judge was <lb/>based on two findings recorded by him in favour of the <lb/>appellant. One was that the appellant reasonably and <lb/>bona fide required the ground floor premises for his own <lb/>use and occupation, and the other was that greater <lb/>hardship would not be caused to the first respondent by <lb/>passing a decree for eviction than what would be caused <lb/>to the appellant by refusing to pass it. Both these findings <lb/>were interfered with by the High Court and the question is <lb/>whether the High Court was within its power in doing so. <lb/>Taking up first for consideration the finding that the <lb/>appellant reasonably and bona fide required the ground <lb/>floor premises for his own use and occupation, it may be <lb/>pointed out straight away that this finding was clearly one <lb/>of fact. The District Judge did not misdirect himself in <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">16 (2002) 5 SCC 397 <lb/>17 (2003) 4 SCC 549 <lb/>18 AIR 1974 SC 1059 <lb/>RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>regard to the true meaning of the word &quot;requires&quot; in <lb/>Section 13(1)(g) and interpreted it correctly to mean that <lb/>there must be an element of need before a landlord can <lb/>be said to &quot;require&quot; premises for his own use and <lb/>occupation. It is not enough that the landlord should <lb/>merely desire to use and occupy the premises. What is <lb/>necessary is that he should need them for his own use <lb/>and occupation. This was the correct test applied by the <lb/>District Judge to the facts found by him. If he had applied <lb/>a wrong test on a misconstruction of the word &quot;requires&quot;, <lb/>the finding recorded by him would have been vitiated by <lb/>an error of law. But the correct test having been applied, <lb/>the finding of the District Judge that the appellant <lb/>reasonably and bona fide required the ground floor <lb/>premises for his own use and occupation was <lb/>unquestionably a finding of fact and it was not competent <lb/>to the High Court, in the exercise of its revisional power <lb/>under Section 29, sub-section (3), to interfere with this <lb/>finding by reappreciating the evidence. …&quot; <lb/>37. <lb/>The plethora of decisions interpreting the terms &quot;for <lb/>himself,&quot; &quot;for his own occupation,&quot; &quot;by himself,&quot; &quot;for his own <lb/>use,&quot; are all, in my considered opinion, to be construed as <lb/>&quot;personal occupation of the landlord.&quot; &quot;Personal occupation&quot; <lb/>would, therefore, on the cornerstone of the ratiocinations supra, <lb/>include not only the landlord but all normal emanations of the <lb/>landlord, including his dependents and kith and kin, while also <lb/>duly considering the social milieu in the Indian context and <lb/>cannot be constricted only to the landlord. Thus, the intention of <lb/>the enactment is not to deprive the landlord of his premises <lb/>when it is indeed required for his personal occupation, be it for <lb/>himself or anyone dependent on him. The interpretation of these <lb/>words &quot;personal occupation&quot; as emanates in the Notification of <lb/>1949, would therefore be covered by the umbrella of the <lb/>interpretations supra. The argument of learned Senior Counsel <lb/>for the Appellant that the Respondent No.1 is well to do, has <lb/>sufficient property whereby he derives sufficient income, is of no <lb/>consequence. In any event, no evidence was led by the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>Appellant to establish ownership of property and sufficiency of <lb/>income thereof. Further, the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court has inter <lb/>alia held in Sait Nagjee Purushotham &amp; Co. Ltd. v. Vimalabai <lb/>Prabhulal and Others 19 as follows; <lb/>&quot;4. … It is true that the landlords have their <lb/>business spreading over Chennai and Hyderabad and if <lb/>they wanted to expand their business at Calicut it cannot <lb/>be said to be unnatural thereby denying the eviction of <lb/>the tenant from the premises in question. It is always the <lb/>prerogative of the landlord that if he requires the <lb/>premises in question for his bona fide use for expansion <lb/>of business this is no ground to say that the landlords are <lb/>already having their business at Chennai and Hyderabad <lb/>therefore, it is not genuine need. It is not the tenant who <lb/>can dictate the terms to the landlord and advise him <lb/>what he should do and what he should not. It is always <lb/>the privilege of the landlord to choose the nature of the <lb/>business and the place of business. However, the Trial <lb/>Court held in favour of the tenant-appellant. But the <lb/>appellate court as well as the High Court after scrutinizing <lb/>the evidence on record reversed the finding of the trial <lb/>court and held that the need of establishing the business <lb/>at Calicut by the landlords cannot be said to be lacking in <lb/>bona fides.&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>38. <lb/>Thus, as observed in the Judgment supra it is always <lb/>the prerogative of the landlord that if he requires the premises in <lb/>question for his bona fide use for expansion of business, the <lb/>tenants cannot be heard to say that the landlords already have <lb/>their business at other places. The tenant cannot dictate terms <lb/>to the landlord and advise him about what he should do and <lb/>what he should not. It is for the landlord to choose the nature <lb/>and place of business, as also earlier held in Mst. Begum and <lb/>Others supra. Although learned Senior Counsel for the Appellant <lb/>sought to make it appear as though the learned trial Court had <lb/>arrived at the finding that the Appellant required the premises <lb/>19 (2005) 8 SCC 252 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>for his personal occupation, on account of his hypertension and <lb/>backache but on a reading of the Judgment, it is clear that the <lb/>learned trial Court while considering &quot;personal occupation&quot; held <lb/>that the suit property is required for &quot;the bonafide reason for the <lb/>&quot;personal occupation&quot; of the plaintiff, i.e., for the establishment <lb/>of hotel business at the fag end of his life for his livelihood.&quot; On <lb/>this point, the finding of the learned trial Court cannot be <lb/>faulted. <lb/>39. <lb/>The contention of the Appellant that the terms <lb/>&quot;personal occupation&quot; and &quot;bona fide requirement&quot; are neither <lb/>synonymous nor interchangeable, also appears to be a rather <lb/>restricted view of the matter, since the two terms cannot be <lb/>ensconed into water tight compartments completely isolated <lb/>from each other. When a personal necessity arises then <lb/>essentially a bona fide requirement is also to be proved. This <lb/>would be evident from a reading of the Judgment of the Hon&quot;ble <lb/>Supreme Court in Mst. Bega Begum and Others supra, wherein, <lb/>while discussing &quot;personal necessity,&quot; it has been stated that the <lb/>Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court was in disagreement with the finding of <lb/>the Hon&quot;ble High Court that the Plaintiffs had not proved that <lb/>they had any bona fide need for occupation of the building in <lb/>question. Further, in Kailash Chand and Another supra, the words <lb/>were used together inasmuch as it was held as follows; <lb/>&quot;25. ………Take the case of a landlord knocking the <lb/>doors of the court seeking its assistance for a roof over <lb/>his head or for a reasonably comfortable living, when he <lb/>is himself either in a rented accommodation or squeezing <lb/>himself and his family members in a limited space, while <lb/>the tenant protected by the rent control law is <lb/>comfortably occupying the premises of the landlord or a <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>part thereof. Provisions like Section 14(3)(a)(i) of the Act <lb/>should be so interpreted as to advance the cause of justice <lb/>instructed by the realities of life and practical wisdom. While <lb/>the tenant needs to be protected, the courts would not <lb/>ordinarily deny the relief to the landlord, who genuinely <lb/>and bona fide requires the premises in occupation of the <lb/>tenant for occupation by himself or for the members of <lb/>his family, unless they feel convinced that the so-called <lb/>requirement of the landlord was a ruse for getting rid of <lb/>an inconvenient tenant or was otherwise mala fide and <lb/>did not fall within the four corners of the ground for <lb/>eviction provided by the law.&quot; <lb/>(emphasis supplied) <lb/>Hence, where personal necessity arises, bona fide requirement is <lb/>to be established along with an element of need as opposed to <lb/>desire. In order to prove bona fide requirement, the Respondent <lb/>No.1 herein entered the dock before the learned trial Court and <lb/>deposed that he is 50 years of age and suffering from various <lb/>physical ailments and therefore decided to purchase the suit <lb/>property along with other attached properties to develop the <lb/>same into a hotel complex. These facts went undecimated in <lb/>cross-examination. It is thus concluded that the Respondent <lb/>No.1 has proved that the premises were required for his personal <lb/>occupation which also includes occupation for business purposes. <lb/>40. <lb/>Coming to Question No.3 formulated hereinabove i.e. <lb/>&quot;Whether the finding of the learned trial Court with regard to <lb/>arrears of rent to be paid by the Appellant to the Respondent <lb/>No.1 from the month of April, 2012 till the filing of the Suit, <lb/>despite concluding absence of default in rent payment, was <lb/>correct?,&quot; the finding of the learned trial Court on Issue No.2 has <lb/>already been extracted hereinabove. The learned trial Court has <lb/>held that there was no wilful default of rent on the part of the <lb/>Appellant. It is further stated that the arrears of rent is to be <lb/>paid from April, 2012 till disposal of the case. In the first <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>instance, the Notification of 1949 nowhere provides for &quot;willful <lb/>default,&quot; the words discussed at length by the learned trial Court <lb/>is alien to the Notification of 1949, under discussion herein. It <lb/>specifically provides only for &quot;failure by the tenants to pay rent <lb/>for four months&quot; and bears no qualifying term such as &quot;wilful.&quot; It <lb/>is essential to remark here that the Notification does not specify <lb/>that the four months are to be in continuation. Be that as it may, <lb/>since this point has not been raised before this Court, it requires <lb/>no discussion. It is now appropriate to consider whether there <lb/>was default in rent payment and thereby arrears of rent. Exbt. <lb/>2/S, the rent receipts reveal that rent was received by the <lb/>Respondent No.4 for the months of December 2005, January <lb/>2006, February 2006, April 2006 to December 2006, January <lb/>2007 to December 2007, January 2008 to December 2008, <lb/>January 2009 to December 2009 and January 2011 to October, <lb/>2011. Exhibit 2/T which are Money Order Acknowledgment Cards <lb/>reveal that it was sent by the Appellant School to the <lb/>Respondent No.4 for the months of December 2011 which was <lb/>refused by her. Thereafter rent appears to have been sent for <lb/>the month of January, 2012 which was also refused by the payee <lb/>and returned to sender. This continued for the months of <lb/>February, 2012 to February, 2013. From March 2013, it was <lb/>addressed to the Respondent No.1. Thus, the documents speak <lb/>for themselves. Hence, there was no default in payment of rent <lb/>at any point in time but on the refusal of the Respondent No.1 to <lb/>accept the rent and in view of the continuing occupation of the <lb/>Appellant of the suit premises, arrears of rent have accrued. The <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>finding of the learned trial Court that the arrears of rent from <lb/>April, 2012 appears to be erroneous in view of the documentary <lb/>evidence on record. The arrears, evidently accrues from <lb/>December, Thus, the finding of the learned trial Court that <lb/>there was no default of rent on the part of the Defendants, is not <lb/>erroneous except that the word &quot;wilful&quot; has been erroneously <lb/>employed. The finding that the Respondent No. 1 was entitled to <lb/>recover the arrears of rent, is also not erroneous. The finding of <lb/>the learned trial Court that the Respondent No.1 cannot take the <lb/>benefit of the Lease Deed, Exhibit 1 which had already expired, <lb/>is also not erroneous, in view of the detailed discussions in <lb/>Question No.1 supra. <lb/>41. <lb/>With regard to the last question formulated <lb/>hereinabove i.e. &quot;Whether the learned trial Court ought to have <lb/>allowed validation of the Lease Deed in terms of Notification <lb/>No.2947/G dated 22.11.1946?,&quot; it is an admitted position that <lb/>the Lease Deed was entered into on 23.03.1996 and determined <lb/>on 23.03.2001. As discussed supra in Question No.1, the <lb/>provisions of the T.P. Act fell into place. Neither the Respondent <lb/>No.1 nor the Appellant were the original parties to the Lease <lb/>Deed. The Notification No.2947/G dated 22.11.1946 reads as <lb/>follows; <lb/>&quot;SIKKIM STATE <lb/>GENERAL DEPARTMENT <lb/>Notification No. 2947/G <lb/>Amendment of para 2 of Notification No: 385/G dated the <lb/>11th April, 1928. <lb/>An unregistered document (which ought in the <lb/>opinion of the court to have been registered) may <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>40 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>however be validated and admitted in court to prove title <lb/>or other matters contained in the document on payment <lb/>of a penalty upto fifty times the usual registration fee. <lb/>Issued by order of H.H. the Maharaja of Sikkim. <lb/>Gangtok <lb/>T. Tsering <lb/>The 22nd Nov., 46 <lb/>(Offs) General Secretary to <lb/>H.H. The Maharaja of Sikkim. <lb/>Copy of memo No. 2553/C&amp;F dated the 18th Sept., <lb/>1949, from the Dewan, Sikkim State to the Tahasildar, <lb/>East Sikkim. <lb/>A copy of Rule regarding registration of document <lb/>(1930) is sent herewith. <lb/>The seals of registration fees is one rupee fee every <lb/>Rs.100/-or fraction thereof on the value of property or <lb/>properties.&quot; <lb/>How validation of the document would have helped the case of <lb/>the Appellant is beyond comprehension. <lb/>42. <lb/>So far as I.A. No.05 of 2017, I.A. No.07 of 2018 and <lb/>I.A. No.08 of 2019 are concerned, since the matters pertaining <lb/>to title cannot be taken up in an Eviction Suit and since all the <lb/>documents sought to be filed by the parties vide the I.As pertain <lb/>to title, I am of the considered opinion that it is not necessary <lb/>for a just decision in the matter. I.A. No.05 of 2017, I.A. No.07 <lb/>of 2018 and I.A. No.08 of 2019 stand rejected and disposed of <lb/>accordingly. <lb/>43. <lb/>In the end result, it is ordered as follows; <lb/>(i) the Appellant shall vacate the suit premises within <lb/>six months from today and hand over vacant <lb/>possession to the Respondent No.1; <lb/>(ii) the Respondent No. 1 is entitled to arrears of rent <lb/>from December, 2011 till the Appellant vacates the <lb/>suit property in terms of the orders supra; <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>41 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>(iii) the amount of rent deposited by the Appellant with <lb/>effect from September, 2016 till August, 2019 in <lb/>terms of the undertaking given by the Appellant on <lb/>28.10.2016, in the State Bank of Sikkim Account <lb/>bearing No.502672, maintained in the name of the <lb/>Registrar General, High Court of Sikkim, be released <lb/>to the Respondent No.1 with the interest accrued on <lb/>the deposit, if any; and <lb/>(iv) the sum of Rs.6,84,000/-(Rupees six lakhs and <lb/>eighty four thousand) only, (along with the interest <lb/>accrued on the deposit, if any), deposited vide <lb/>Cheque of the IDBI Bank bearing No.035162, dated <lb/>28.09.2016, by the Appellant, in compliance of the <lb/>Orders of this Court, dated 22.09.2016, and <lb/>presently deposited in the State Bank of Sikkim <lb/>Account bearing No.502672, maintained in the name <lb/>of the Registrar General, High Court of Sikkim, also <lb/>be released to the Respondent No.1. This shall be on <lb/>completion of the period of Appeal. <lb/>44. <lb/>Appeal dismissed. <lb/>45. <lb/>Cross Objection allowed to the extent as discussed <lb/>hereinabove. <lb/>46. <lb/>Copy of this Judgment be sent to the learned trial <lb/>Court for information. <lb/>47. <lb/>In the circumstances, no order as to costs. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RFA No.09 of 2016 and CO No.01 of 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>42 <lb/></page>

			<body>Joy Bells School Authority vs. Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon and Others <lb/>and <lb/>Tsewang Gyatso Kaleon vs. Joy Bells School Authority and Others <lb/>48. <lb/>Records of the learned trial Court be remitted <lb/>forthwith. <lb/>( Meenakshi Madan Rai ) <lb/>Judge <lb/>31.08.2019 <lb/>Approved for reporting : Yes <lb/>ml <lb/>Internet : Yes </body>


	</text>
</tei>
