<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>IN THE HIGH COURT OF SIKKIM: GANGTOK <lb/>(Criminal Appellate Jurisdiction) <lb/>-------------------------------------------------------------------------------<lb/>SINGLE BENCH: -BHASKAR RAJ PRADHAN, JUDGE. <lb/>-------------------------------------------------------------------------------<lb/>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai <lb/>… Appellant. <lb/>Versus <lb/>State of Sikkim <lb/>… Respondent. <lb/>An Appeal under Section 374 (2) of the <lb/>Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973. <lb/>-------------------------------------------------------------------------------<lb/>Appearance: <lb/>Mr. Zangpo Sherpa, Legal Aid Counsel with Ms. Mon Maya <lb/>Subba, Advocates for the Appellant. <lb/>Mr. S.K Chettri and Mr. D. K. Siwakoti, Assistant Public <lb/>Prosecutor for the State-Respondent. <lb/>-------------------------------------------------------------------------------<lb/></front>

			<body>J U D G M E N T <lb/>(13.09.2017) <lb/>Bhaskar Raj Pradhan, J <lb/>1. <lb/>The Judgment of the Learned Special Court dated <lb/>17.09.2015 (the impugned judgment) sentences the convict to <lb/>undergo simple imprisonment of 5 years and to pay a fine of <lb/>₹10,000/-(Rupees ten thousand) only under Section 9 (m) and 9 <lb/>(n) and punishable under Section 10 of the Protection of Children <lb/>from Sexual Offences Act, 2012 (POCSO Act, 2012). In default of <lb/>payment of fine, the convict was directed to further undergo simple <lb/>imprisonment of 3 (three) months. However, the period of <lb/>detention already undergone by the convict during investigation <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>and trial was to be set off against this period of imprisonment as <lb/>provided under Section 428 Cr.P.C. The fine, if recovered, was to <lb/>be handed over to the victim as compensation under Section 357 of <lb/>the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (Cr.P.C.). <lb/>2. <lb/>The convict/appellant herein seeks to assail the impugned <lb/>judgment passed by the Special Judge. Mr. Zangpo Sherpa, Legal <lb/>Aid Counsel for the Appellant submits that the Learned Special <lb/>Judge ought not to have relied upon the testimony of the victims <lb/>alone when there were certain inconsistencies in the facts. He <lb/>further submits that the Learned Special Court had erred in not <lb/>considering the delay in lodging the First Information Report (FIR). <lb/>He further submits that the prosecution had failed to examine <lb/>necessary witnesses and the testimonies of those witnesses who <lb/>had been examined were inconsistent. Mr. Zangpo Sherpa, relies <lb/>upon Mohd Ali alias Guddu v. State of U.P. 1 and Govt. of NCT of <lb/>Delhi v. Mullah Muzib 2 . <lb/>3. <lb/>The Apex Court in re: Mohd Ali alias Guddu (supra) would <lb/>hold that there can be no iota of doubt that the conviction can be <lb/>based on soul testimony of prosecutrix, even without corroboration, <lb/>if it is impeachable and beyond reproach. However, when a Court <lb/>on studied scrutiny of the evidence finds it difficult to accept the <lb/>version of the prosecutrix, because it is not irreproachable, then <lb/>there is a requirement for search of such direct or circumstantial <lb/>evidence which would lend assurance to her testimony and in such <lb/>cases where such other evidence does not support the story of the <lb/>prosecutrix it can be discarded. <lb/>1 2015 (7) SCC 272 <lb/>2 2015 SCC OnLine Del 7228 <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>4. <lb/>The facts of the case in re: Mullah Muzib (supra) is <lb/>distinguishable as would be seen in the later part of this judgment. <lb/>Mullah Muzib (supra) was a case of material contradiction in the <lb/>testimonies of the two witnesses, the victim and his uncle, because <lb/>of which the High Court had held that the evidence produced is not <lb/>cogent enough to prove that the accused had carnal intercourse <lb/>with the victim. <lb/>5. <lb/>Mr. S. K. Chettri, Learned Assistant Public Prosecutor for the <lb/>State would strongly contend that the judgment sought to be <lb/>assailed was a reasoned one, the testimonies of the two child <lb/>victims were cogent and reliable, the prosecution had been able to <lb/>establish the ingredients of the offences charged and therefore the <lb/>same needs no interference. <lb/>Mr. S. K. Chettri, relies upon <lb/>Dharma Rama Bhargare v. State of Maharashtra 3 , Gurbachan <lb/>Singh v. Satpal Singh &amp; Ors 4 ., State of H.P. v. Asha Ram 5 , State of <lb/>Himachal Pradesh v. Suresh Kumar Alias DC 6 ., Mohd. Imran Khan <lb/>v. State Government (NCT of Delhi) 7 , Swaroop Singh v. State of <lb/>Madhya Pradesh 8 and Sanjok Rai v. State of Sikkim 9 . <lb/>FACTUAL MATRIX <lb/>6. <lb/>The relevant facts for the purpose of deciding this appeal is <lb/>that on 31.12.2014 at 19.00 hrs an FIR was lodged at the Naya <lb/>Bazar Police Station by P.W.4 alleging commission of rape on two <lb/>(1973) 1 SCC 537. <lb/>(1990) 1 SCC 445 <lb/>(2005) 13 SCC 766 <lb/>(2009) 16 SCC 697 <lb/>(2011) 10 SCC 192 <lb/>(2013) 14 SCC 565 <lb/>2017 SCC OnLine Sikk 76. <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>minor children, Ms. R and Ms. S, by the convict. The investigation <lb/>was conducted by P.W.13. The charge-sheet was filed on <lb/>16.02.2015. On 18.03.2015 the Learned Special Judge framed two <lb/>charges. The first charge related to minor victim Ms. R, aged 11 <lb/>years. It was alleged that since 2012 to December, 2014 the <lb/>convict being a relative of Ms. R, committed aggravated sexual <lb/>assault on her repeatedly, which offence fell under Section 9(l), <lb/>9(m) and 9(n) and punishable under Section 10 of the POCSO Act, <lb/>2012. The second charge related to the aggravated sexual assault <lb/>on the other child victim, Ms. S, aged about 6 years. It was alleged <lb/>that sometime in the year 2014 the said offence was committed by <lb/>the convict, which offence fell under Section 9(m) and punishable <lb/>under Section 10 of the POCSO Act, 2012. 13 witnesses were <lb/>examined by the prosecution. <lb/>7. <lb/>The victim, Ms. R, was examined as P.W.2. Her mother was <lb/>examined as P.W.1 and her father was examined as P.W.6., Ms R&apos;s <lb/>sister-in-law, who noticed some swelling over the chest of Ms. R, <lb/>inquired about it and was informed by Ms. R that she was sexually <lb/>assaulted by her &apos;dewa&apos; (uncle), was examined as P.W.8. <lb/>8. <lb/>The next victim, Ms. S, was examined as P.W.3. Her father <lb/>was examined as P.W.5. <lb/>9. <lb/>First informant for both the offences was examined as <lb/>P.W.4. P.W.7 and P.W.9 are the seizure witnesses of the birth <lb/>certificates of Ms. R, and Ms. S, vide seizure memos (Exhibit-7 and <lb/>Exhibit-9). <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>10. <lb/>P.W.11 is the Gynaecologist at the STNM Hospital, Gangtok <lb/>who examined Ms. R and Ms. S, both on 01.01.2015 and proved <lb/>his reports (Exhibit-13 and Exhibit-12) respectively. <lb/>11. <lb/>P.W.12 was the Station House Officer (SHO) at the <lb/>relevant time of lodging the first information by P.W.4 alleging that <lb/>his elder brother, the convict, had committed rape on Ms. R and <lb/>Ms. S. <lb/>12. <lb/>P.W. 13 was the Investigating Officer who on completion of <lb/>the investigation laid the charge-sheet before the Court of the <lb/>Learned Special Judge. Charges were framed on 18.03.2015 and <lb/>the trial culminated in the conviction of the convict. <lb/>EVIDENCE RELATING TO ASSUALT ON Ms. R. <lb/>13. <lb/>Ms. R has deposed that she knows the accused who is <lb/>her &apos;Dewa&apos; (uncle). She further states that on 14.11.2014, after <lb/>attending her school, she went to the place where her mother <lb/>works at the site. At the site she went to drink water to the house <lb/>of the convict. When she was drinking the water given by P.W.4, <lb/>the brother of the convict, P.W.4 left. Thereafter, the convict came <lb/>from behind and fondled her breasts and threatened her not to tell <lb/>anyone. Ms. R further states that only after several days, she told <lb/>about the incident to her sister-in-law, P.W.8. Ms. R identified her <lb/>signatures on the questionnaire put by the Magistrate (Exhibit-1) <lb/>and her statement recorded under Section 164 Cr.P.C. (Exhibit-2). <lb/>14. <lb/>In cross examination Ms. R confirmed that on <lb/>14.11.2014 P.W.4 and his brother, the convict, where together in <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>their house. Ms. R also admitted that she narrated about the <lb/>alleged incident to P.W.8 only after few days and she did not tell <lb/>her mother about the same. Ms. R further admitted that the <lb/>relation between the convict and her family was not healthy and <lb/>cordial. Ms. R clearly denied the suggestion of the defence Counsel <lb/>that the convict had not come from behind and fondled her breasts <lb/>and that the convict had not threatened her not to disclose to <lb/>anyone about the incident. Ms. R could not recollect when her <lb/>statement was recorded by the Police. <lb/>15. <lb/>P.W.8 deposed that about 4 to 5 months prior to the date <lb/>of her deposition in Court (i.e. 16.04.2015) she had noticed some <lb/>swelling over the chest of Ms. R, inquired from her about the same <lb/>and was told by Ms. R, that she was sexually assaulted by her <lb/>&apos;Dewa&apos; (uncle). P.W.8 thereafter informed Ms. R&apos;s mother, P.W.1 <lb/>about the incident. Thereafter, they inquired about the incident <lb/>from the convict, who replied that P.W.1 had taken some loan from <lb/>him and taking advantage of that the convict used to sexually <lb/>assault Ms. R. <lb/>16. <lb/>On cross examination P.W.8 admitted that she had <lb/>informed P.W.1 about the incident in the month of November, 2014 <lb/>but does not remember the exact date. P.W.8 denied the <lb/>suggestion made by the defence that Ms. R had not disclosed about <lb/>the commission of sexual assault on her by the convict. P.W.8 also <lb/>denied the suggestion made by the defence that her allegation that <lb/>the convict had admitted to the crime was a false statement. P.W.8 <lb/>admitted that P.W.1 was also present with her when the convict <lb/>confessed about the incident. P.W.8 also admitted that the relation <lb/>between the convict and P.W.1 was not good and cordial. P.W.8 <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>denied the suggestion made by the defence that it was because of <lb/>this strained relationship that Ms. R&apos;s family had lodged the false <lb/>complaint against the convict. <lb/>17. <lb/>P.W.1, the mother of Ms. R, recognized the convict as her <lb/>brother-in-law. On 14.11.2014, P.W.8 told her that the convict had <lb/>committed rape on Ms. R. P.W.1 requested P.W.8 to inquire about <lb/>the matter from Ms. R, after which P.W.8 inquired from Ms. R and <lb/>confirmed that the convict had committed rape on Ms. R. After that <lb/>P.W.1 inquired about the incident from Ms. R, reported the matter <lb/>to the village Panchayat and thereafter they reported it to the <lb/>Police. <lb/>18. <lb/>In cross examination P.W.1 reiterated her statement about <lb/>P.W.8 informing her that the convict had committed rape on Ms. R. <lb/>She also admitted, in cross examination, that she had also noticed <lb/>that the breast of Ms. R was swollen. P.W.1 admitted that they had <lb/>reported the matter to the Police after seven days of the incident. <lb/>P.W.1 admitted of having taken a loan of ₹ 3000/-from the convict <lb/>prior to the incident and that she had not returned the amount to <lb/>the convict. P.W.1 denied that the relation between the convict and <lb/>her was not cordial prior to the incident. All other suggestion made <lb/>by the defence was denied by P.W.8. <lb/>19. <lb/>P.W.6, the father of Ms. R, also identified the convict as his <lb/>cousin. P.W.6 deposed that on 31.12.2014 he learnt that convict <lb/>had committed sexual assault on Ms. R and Ms. S and thereafter <lb/>they reported the matter before the Panchayat and later to the <lb/>Police. P.W.6 also deposed that on 31.12.2014 the Police had <lb/>seized birth certificate of his daughter, Ms. R and identified Exhibit-<lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>8 as the birth certificate of Ms. R. P.W. 6 also deposed that on the <lb/>same day the Police had also seized the birth certificate of Ms. S <lb/>vide Exhibit-9 and identified the said birth certificate as Exhibit-10. <lb/>20. <lb/>In cross examination, P.W.6 admitted that P.W.1 was his <lb/>wife. P.W.6 denied the suggestion that his wife had informed about <lb/>the alleged incident during second or third week of November, <lb/>2014. P.W.6 admitted that he did not have any personal knowledge <lb/>about this case and that what he deposed was on the basis of <lb/>hearsay. P.W.6 denied the suggestion of the defence that the <lb/>relation between his family and the convict was not good or cordial <lb/>prior to the incident. P.W.6 also admitted that the complaint <lb/>(Exhibit-5) was prepared on instruction given by the Police and it <lb/>was prepared at a place in West Sikkim. P.W.6 denied the <lb/>suggestion made by the defence that his wife had not told him that <lb/>the convict had committed sexual assault on Ms. R and Ms. S. <lb/>21. <lb/>The evidence of Ms. R, was amply corroborated by the <lb/>evidence of P.W.8 to whom Ms. R narrated about the incident. The <lb/>evidence of P.W.8 is corroborated by the evidence of P.W.1, the <lb/>mother of Ms. R to whom P.W.8 narrated what was told to P.W.8 <lb/>by Ms. R. <lb/>22. <lb/>P.W.4, the first informant and the natural brother of the <lb/>convict, identified the convict in Court. P.W.4 stated that on <lb/>29.12.2014, one lady from his village (not examined), told him that <lb/>the convict had committed rape on her minor grand-daughter, Ms. <lb/>S and another Ms. R. <lb/>P.W.4 further deposed that again on <lb/>31.12.2014 P.W.1 also told him that P.W.8 had told her that the <lb/>convict had committed rape on Ms. R and Ms. S and thereafter as <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>per the request made by the &apos;Panchayat&apos; (not examined), affixed <lb/>his signature to the FIR (Exhibit-5). P.W.4 identified his signatures <lb/>in (Exhibit-5) and the formal FIR (Exhibit-6). P.W.4 also identified <lb/>(Exhibit-6). <lb/>23. <lb/>In cross examination, P.W.4 admitted that the FIR <lb/>(Exhibit-5) was not scribed by him but by the &apos;Panchayat&apos; and he <lb/>did not know the contents thereof. P.W.4 further stated that he had <lb/>not given any instructions while preparing the FIR. P.W.4 admitted <lb/>that the signature in the FIR (Exhibit-5) was his and volunteered to <lb/>say that it was prepared at his house by the &apos;Panchayat&apos; in the <lb/>presence of Police. P.W.4 admitted that the Police had visited his <lb/>house before lodging of the FIR. P.W.4 further admitted that he <lb/>had no personal knowledge about the case. P.W.4 denied the <lb/>suggestions of the defence that he had not been told by the <lb/>grandmother of the victim, and P.W.1 about the alleged incidents. <lb/>P.W.4 further stated that he could not say whether the relation <lb/>between the convict and Ms. R&apos;s family was cordial or not. P.W.4 <lb/>stated that he could not say whether Ms. R came to his house for <lb/>drinking water prior to the incident. P.W.4 further stated that he <lb/>could not say as to when the alleged incident occurred. P.W.4 <lb/>admitted that he did not know what the FIR (Exhibit-6) was but <lb/>admitted that he had signed the same at his residence and <lb/>identified his signature. <lb/>24. <lb/>P.W.7 and P.W.9 both identified the convict in the Court as <lb/>their co-villager. They are seizure witnesses. P.W.7 and P.W.9 <lb/>stated that the Police had seized the birth certificate of Ms. S <lb/>(Exhibit-8) vide seizure memo (Exhibit-7) and identified their <lb/>signatures thereon. <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>25. <lb/>P.W.11 is the Gynaecologist who examined Ms. R on <lb/>01.01.2015 at 6.55 p.m. Ms. R was brought for examination with <lb/>the alleged history of assault by the convict. Ms. R told P.W.11 that <lb/>she was molested by the convict on 14.11.2014 by <lb/>playing/massaging the breast area of Ms. R from the back. Ms. R <lb/>denied sexual intercourse or penetration to P.W.11. On clinical <lb/>examination of Ms. R P.W.11 gave a finding that there was no <lb/>sufficient injury to determine sexual intercourse but fondling of the <lb/>breast was likely. The cross examination of P.W.11 by the defence <lb/>yielded no fruitful result in their favour. <lb/>EVIDENCE RELATING TO ASSUALT ON Ms. S. <lb/>26. <lb/>Ms. S also identified the convict in Court as a co-villager. <lb/>She could not remember the date, month and year of the incident. <lb/>On the relevant day when she was returning from school, alone on <lb/>reaching the house of the convict, the convict held Ms. S and <lb/>rubbed himself against her for some time. The convict then told Ms. <lb/>S not to tell anyone about the incident and also gave ₹ 11/-to her. <lb/>Ms. S went home and told her mother about it. Ms. S identified her <lb/>signatures on the questionnaire put by the Magistrate (Exhibit-3) <lb/>and her statement recorded under Section 164 Cr.P.C. (Exhibit-4). <lb/>27. <lb/>On cross examination Ms. S denied the suggestion of the <lb/>defence that they were other persons present at the time of the <lb/>incident. She reiterated that she had narrated about the incident to <lb/>her mother only. She could not remember when her statement was <lb/>recorded. All other suggestions made by the defence were denied <lb/>by Ms. S. <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>28. <lb/>P.W.5, the father of Ms. S identified the convict in Court as <lb/>a co-villager. P.W.5 stated that on 31.12.2014, at around 5 to 6 <lb/>p.m., his wife telephonically called him to the house of the convict. <lb/>P.W.5 further stated that when he went to the house of the convict <lb/>his wife informed him that the convict had committed sexual <lb/>assault on his minor daughter, Ms. S. He saw that the convict was <lb/>taken by the Police. <lb/>29. <lb/>In cross examination P.W.5 admitted that he had no <lb/>personal knowledge about the case and it was based on hearsay. <lb/>P.W.5 denied all other suggestion made by the defence. <lb/>30. <lb/>P.W.6, as stated earlier, also stated that the Police has <lb/>seized the birth certificate (Exhibit-10) of Ms. S vide seizure memo <lb/>(Exhibit-9). <lb/>31. <lb/>P.W.7 and P.W.9 both identified the convict in the Court as <lb/>their co-villager. They are seizure witnesses. P.W.7 and P.W.9 <lb/>stated that the Police had seized the birth certificate of Ms. S <lb/>(Exhibit-10) vide seizure memo (Exhibit-9) and identified their <lb/>signatures thereon. <lb/>32. <lb/>P.W.11 is the Gynaecologist who examined Ms. S on <lb/>01.01.2015 at 7.05 p.m. Ms. S was brought for examination with <lb/>the alleged history of assault by the convict. Ms. S told P.W.11 that <lb/>she was sexually assaulted by the convict on her way back from <lb/>school. According to P.W.11 Ms. S could not recollect the date by <lb/>her but remembered she was given ₹ 11/-by the convict after <lb/>which he took out his private part and rubbed against her. Ms. S <lb/>denied penetration. On clinical examination of Ms. S, P.W.11 gave <lb/>a finding that there was no evidence of penetrative sexual <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>intercourse. The cross examination of P.W.11 by the defence <lb/>yielded no fruitful result in their favour. <lb/>33. <lb/>P.W.12, the SHO of the Police Station, proved the FIR <lb/>(Exhibit-5), the registration of the case and the endorsement of the <lb/>same to Sub-Inspector, P.W.13, for investigation. <lb/>CONSIDERATION <lb/>34. <lb/>It is settled law that conviction can be founded on the <lb/>testimony of the prosecutrix alone unless there are compelling <lb/>reasons for seeking corroboration. It is equally well settled that the <lb/>evidence of prosecutrix is more reliable than that of an injured <lb/>witness. <lb/>35. <lb/>The Apex Court would have occasion to examine a case of <lb/>a father charged for raping his own daughter in which the High <lb/>Court had reversed the order of conviction passed by the Trial <lb/>Court in spite of <lb/>the testimony of the prosecutrix remaining <lb/>unimpeached after lengthy cross examination. This was also a case <lb/>in which suggestion was that a false case had been hoisted against <lb/>the accused at the instance of her mother (who had strained <lb/>relations with the father and residing separately). in re: State of <lb/>H.P. v. Asha Ram (supra) the Apex Court would hold:-<lb/>&quot;5. We record our displeasure and dismay, the way the High <lb/>Court dealt casually with an offence so grave, as in the case at hand, <lb/>overlooking the alarming and shocking increase of sexual assault on <lb/>minor girls. The High Court was swayed by the sheer insensitivity, <lb/>totally oblivious of the growing menace of sexual violence against <lb/>minors much less by the father. The High Court also totally overlooked <lb/>the prosecution evidence, which inspired confidence and merited <lb/>acceptance. It is now a well-settled principle of law that conviction can <lb/>be founded on the testimony of the prosecutrix alone unless there are <lb/>compelling reasons for seeking corroboration. The evidence of a <lb/>prosecutrix is more reliable than that of an injured witness. The <lb/>testimony of the victim of sexual assault is vital, unless there are <lb/>compelling reasons which necessitate looking for corroboration of her <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>statement, the courts should find no difficulty in acting on the <lb/>testimony of a victim of sexual assault alone to convict an accused <lb/>where her testimony inspires confidence and is found to be reliable. It <lb/>is also a well-settled principle of law that corroboration as a condition <lb/>for judicial reliance on the testimony of the prosecutrix is not a <lb/>requirement of law but a guidance of prudence under the given <lb/>circumstances. The evidence of the prosecutrix is more reliable than <lb/>that of an injured witness. Even minor contradictions or insignificant <lb/>discrepancies in the statement of the prosecutrix should not be a <lb/>ground for throwing out an otherwise reliable prosecution case&quot;. <lb/>36. <lb/>In re: State of Himachal Pradesh v. Sanjay Kumar 10 the <lb/>Apex Court would hold:-<lb/>&quot;31. After thorough analysis of all relevant and attendant <lb/>factors, we are of the opinion that none of the grounds, on which the <lb/>High Court has cleared the respondent, has any merit. By now it is well <lb/>settled that the testimony of a victim in cases of sexual offences is <lb/>vital and unless there are compelling reasons which necessitate <lb/>looking for corroboration of a statement, the courts should find no <lb/>difficulty to act on the testimony of the victim of a sexual assault alone <lb/>to convict the accused. No doubt, her testimony has to inspire <lb/>confidence. Seeking corroboration to a statement before relying upon <lb/>the same as a rule, in such cases, would literally amount to adding <lb/>insult to injury. The deposition of the prosecutrix has, thus, to be <lb/>taken as a whole. Needless to reiterate that the victim of rape is not <lb/>an accomplice and her evidence can be acted upon without <lb/>corroboration. She stands at a higher pedestal than an injured witness <lb/>does. If the court finds it difficult to accept her version, it may seek <lb/>corroboration from some evidence which lends assurance to her <lb/>version. To insist on corroboration, except in the rarest of rare cases, <lb/>is to equate one who is a victim of the lust of another with an <lb/>accomplice to a crime and thereby insult womanhood. It would be <lb/>adding insult to injury to tell a woman that her claim of rape will not <lb/>be believed unless it is corroborated in material particulars, as in the <lb/>case of an accomplice to a crime. Why should the evidence of the girl <lb/>or the woman who complains of rape or sexual molestation be viewed <lb/>with the aid of spectacles fitted with lenses tinged with doubt, disbelief <lb/>or suspicion? The plea about lack of corroboration has no substance <lb/>(See Bhupinder Sharma v. State of H.P. [Bhupinder Sharma v. State of <lb/>H.P., (2003) 8 SCC 551 : 2004 SCC (Cri) 31] ). Notwithstanding this <lb/>legal position, in the instant case, we even find enough corroborative <lb/>material as well, which is discussed hereinabove.&quot; <lb/>37. <lb/>The evidence produced makes it unequivocally clear that at <lb/>the time of the actual assault, Ms. R and the convict were the only <lb/>two present. The evidence of Ms. R is truthful and reliable. The <lb/>defence could not break her in spite of her tender age. The fact <lb/>that she narrated the incident to P.W.8 is corroborated by P.W.8 <lb/>and P.W.1. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">10 (2017) 2 SCC 51 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>38. <lb/>P.W.4, the natural brother of the convict and incidentally <lb/>the first informant, naturally, in cross examination, stated that he <lb/>could not say whether Ms. R came to his house for drinking water <lb/>prior to the incident. P.W.4&apos;s hesitation to recollect the fact does <lb/>not weaken the evidence of Ms. R. More so, when P.W.4, the first <lb/>informant does not deny his signature on the written FIR (Exhibit-<lb/>5) and the formal FIR (Exhibit-6). It is quite obvious that the <lb/>hesitation was due to the fact that the convict was, in fact, the real <lb/>brother of P.W.4. <lb/>39. <lb/>Similarly, the evidence produced with reference to the <lb/>alleged offence against Ms. S also makes it evident that at the time <lb/>of the sexual assault on Ms. S by the convict they were the only <lb/>two present. The deposition of Ms. S is also truthful and reliable. <lb/>40. <lb/>The evidence of Ms. S however stands alone. Although <lb/>P.W.5, the father of Ms. S, was examined according to him it was <lb/>his wife who told him about the incident. Mr. Zangpo Sherpa <lb/>appearing for the convict would argue that the mother of Ms. S not <lb/>being examined, the Special Court ought to have considered this <lb/>fact before holding that the evidence of the prosecutrix is <lb/>unimpeachable. Unfortunately, the mother of Ms. S and the wife of <lb/>P.W. 5, was not brought to the witness box. The truth of the <lb/>evidence of P.W.5 of what he heard from the mother of Ms. S <lb/>cannot be accepted, being hearsay. However, the evidence of Ms. S <lb/>stood the cross examination of the defence and remained un-<lb/>demolished. The Learned Special Judge has relied upon her <lb/>testimony. There is no cogent reason for this Court to upset the <lb/>said finding of the Learned Special Judge. <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>41. <lb/>The Learned Special Judge on examination of the evidence <lb/>held that the evidence of both Ms. R and Ms. S could not be <lb/>discredited in cross examination. The Learned Special Judge would <lb/>believe the evidence of P.W.1 the mother of Ms. R. The Learned <lb/>Special Judge rejected the argument of the defence that the non <lb/>examination of the mother of Ms. S and the Panchayat had created <lb/>reasonable doubt on the prosecution case by holding that since <lb/>there were no eye witnesses their non examination was of no <lb/>consequence. This Court finds no necessity to upset the above <lb/>finding of the Learned Special Court. <lb/>42. <lb/>The relevant provisions of the POCSO Act, 2012 are <lb/>extracted herein below:-<lb/>&quot;9. Aggravated Sexual Assault.-<lb/>(m) Whoever commits sexual assault on a child below twelve years; or <lb/>(n) whoever, being a relative of the child through blood or adoption or <lb/>marriage or guardianship or in foster care, or having domestic <lb/>relationship with a parent of the child, or who is living in the same or <lb/>shared household with the child, commits sexual assault on such <lb/>child;.................&quot; <lb/>........................................... <lb/>is set to commit aggravated sexual assault.&quot; <lb/>43. <lb/>The term sexual assault has been defined in Section 7 of <lb/>the POCSO Act, 2012, which provides:-<lb/>&quot;7. Sexual Assault.-Whoever, with sexual intent touches the vagina, <lb/>penis, anus or breast of the child or makes the child touch the vagina, <lb/>penis, anus or breast of such persons or any other person, or does any <lb/>other act with sexual intent which involves physical contact without <lb/>penetration is said to commit sexual assault.&quot; <lb/>44. <lb/>The ingredients of aggravated sexual assault in terms of <lb/>Section 9(m) of the POCSO Act, 2012 are: <lb/>1. Commission of sexual assault, <lb/>2. That sexual assault must be on a child below 12 years. <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>45. <lb/>The ingredient of sexual assault as defined in Section 7 of <lb/>the POCSO Act, 2012 are: <lb/>1. Sexual intent, <lb/>2. Touch of the vagina, penis, anus or breast of the child <lb/>by the accused or making the child touch the vagina, <lb/>penis, anus or breast of the accused or any other <lb/>person or <lb/>doing any other act with sexual intent which involves <lb/>physical contact without penetration. <lb/>46. <lb/>The word &apos;child&apos; has been defined in Section 2(d) of the <lb/>POCSO Act, 2012 as under:-<lb/>&quot;2(d) &quot;child&quot; means any person below the age of [eighteen] years;&quot; <lb/>47. <lb/>On examination of the evidence, the Learned Special Judge <lb/>had come to a finding that:-<lb/>&quot;33. On the date of incident the victims were aged about 11 years and <lb/>6 years. In Exhibit-8 and Exhibit-10 the Birth Certificate (s) (sic), dates <lb/>of birth of the victims are 22.09.2004 and 26.12.2008. In fact the <lb/>defence has not disputed the age of the minor victims.&quot; <lb/>48. <lb/>Mr. Zangpo Sherpa, appearing for the convict does not, <lb/>fairly, contest the finding of the Learned Special Judge regarding <lb/>the age of Ms. R and Ms. S before this Court also. This Court sees <lb/>no cogent reason to disturb the finding of the Learned Special <lb/>Judge regarding the age of Ms. R and Ms. S. relying upon the birth <lb/>certificates of Ms. S (exhibit-10) issued on 24.02.2009 and Ms. R <lb/>(exhibit-8) issued on 30.04.2008 by the Government of Sikkim, <lb/>Office of the Chief Registrar Birth and Death, Department of Health <lb/>Care, Human Services &amp; Family Welfare Department. P.W.7 and <lb/>P.W.9 have proved the seizure of the birth certificates of Ms. R vide <lb/>seizure memo (exhibit-7) and of Ms. S vide seizure memo (exhibit-<lb/>9). P.W.7 is the father of Ms. R. Both the birth certificates are <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>certificate issued by the Government and issued under Section <lb/>12/17 of the Registration of Births and Deaths Act, 1969 and Rule <lb/>8/13 of the Sikkim Registration of Births and Deaths Rule, 1999 <lb/>certifying that the information has been taken from the original <lb/>record of birth which is the register for the particular area and <lb/>giving details of the date of birth, place of birth, name of mother, <lb/>name of father, nationality of father and mother, address of the <lb/>parents at the time of birth, permanent address, registration <lb/>number, date of issue and date of registration. Under Section 35 of <lb/>the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 an entry in any public or other <lb/>official book, register or record or an electronic record, stating of <lb/>fact in issue or relevant fact, and made by a public servant in the <lb/>discharge of official duty, or by any other person in performance of <lb/>a duty especially enjoined by the law of the country in which such <lb/>book, register, or record or an electronic record is kept, is itself a <lb/>relevant fact. The said Exhibit-8 and Exhibit-10 are under the <lb/>signature of the Registrar of Births and Deaths. The said birth <lb/>certificates are admissible in evidence. <lb/>49. <lb/>Ms. R stated that the convict is &apos;Dewa&apos; (uncle). P.W.1, <lb/>mother of Ms. R stated that the convict is her brother-in-law. P.W.6 <lb/>the father of Ms. R stated that the convict was his cousin. The <lb/>convict was therefore a relative of Ms. R through blood. <lb/>50. <lb/>Ms. R stated that the convict came from behind, fondled <lb/>her breast and threatened her not to tell anyone. It is evident that <lb/>the convict had committed aggravated sexual assault as defined in <lb/>Sections 9 (m) and 9 (n) of the POCSO Act, 2012. The sexual <lb/>intent of the convict is clear from the act of fondling Ms. R&apos;s breast <lb/>and threatening her not to tell anyone. <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>51. <lb/>Ms. S stated that the convict held her and rubbed himself <lb/>against her for some time. The convict also told Ms. S not to tell <lb/>anyone and further gave an amount of ₹ 11/-to her. It is evident <lb/>that the convict had committed aggravated sexual assault as <lb/>defined under Section 9 (m) of the POCSO Act, 2012. The sexual <lb/>intent is clear from the act of the convict of rubbing himself against <lb/>Ms. S and thereafter telling Ms. S not to tell anyone and further <lb/>giving an amount of ₹ 11/-to her. <lb/>52. <lb/>Mr. Zangpo Sherpa, would argue that there was <lb/>inconsistency in the version of the Prosecution witnesses. <lb/>53. <lb/>The evidence produced reflects that besides Ms. R and Ms. <lb/>S and the convict there was no one else when the alleged offences <lb/>were committed on Ms. R and Ms. S on two different occasions. <lb/>Thus, minor discrepancies, are bound to occur when the other <lb/>witnesses who merely heard what was told to them narrate about <lb/>the incident. It is significant to note that the evidence of Ms. R and <lb/>Ms. S, although both of tender age, are cogent and unblemished in <lb/>spite of being subjected to cross examination by the defence. The <lb/>minor discrepancies pointed out by Mr. Zangpo Sherpa does not <lb/>relate to the ingredients of the offences for which the convict is <lb/>aggrieved. <lb/>54. <lb/>While examining such cases of sexual abuse on minor <lb/>children it would be vital to keep in mind the observations of the <lb/>Apex Court in re: State of H.P. v. Sanjay Kumar (supra):-<lb/>&quot;22. We have already narrated the case of the prosecution as well <lb/>as the testimonies of the prosecutrix, her mother PW 1 and the <lb/>medical evidence. After going through the evidence of the prosecutrix <lb/>and her mother, we find that apart from some minor and trivial <lb/>discrepancies with regard to the period of stomach ache or about the <lb/>medicine taken from the local doctor/chemist, insofar as material <lb/>particulars of the incident are concerned, version of both these <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>witnesses is in sync with each other. Here is a case where charge of <lb/>sexual assault on a girl aged nine years is levelled. More pertinently, <lb/>this is to be seen in the context that the respondent, who is accused of <lb/>the crime, is the uncle in relation. Entire matter has to be examined in <lb/>this perspective taking into consideration the realities of life that <lb/>prevail in Indian social milieu.&quot; <lb/>55. <lb/>Mr. Zangpo Sherpa further sought to point out various <lb/>discrepancies between the statement of Ms. R under Section 164 <lb/>Cr.P.C. and her deposition in Court. <lb/>56. <lb/>The defence had ample opportunity to use the said <lb/>previous statement of Ms. R taken under Section 164 Cr.P.C. to <lb/>contradict Ms. R. However, the defence did not do so. At the <lb/>Appellate stage the convict cannot be permitted to take advantage <lb/>of such discrepancies, even if it is existed, when the defence failed <lb/>to contradict Ms. R in the manner provided under law. It must be <lb/>remembered that evidence given in the Court under oath has great <lb/>sanctity, which is why it is called substantive evidence. A statement <lb/>under Section 164 Cr.P.C. can be used for both corroboration and <lb/>contradiction. The object of recording a statement under section <lb/>164 Cr.P.C. is to deter the witness from changing a stand by <lb/>denying the contents of her previously recorded statement and to <lb/>tide over immunity from prosecution by the witness under Section <lb/>164 Cr.P.C. At the time of recording a statement under Section 164 <lb/>Cr.P.C. no opportunity is provided to cross examine the witness <lb/>and as such it cannot be treated as substantive evidence. (See: R. <lb/>Shaji v. State of Kerala 11 ). <lb/>57. <lb/>Under Section 145 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 a <lb/>witness may be cross examined as to previous statements made by <lb/>him in writing or reduced into writing, and relevant to matters in <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">11 (2013) 14 SCC 266 <lb/></note>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>question, without such writing being shown to him, or being <lb/>proved; but, if it is intended to contradict him by the writing, his <lb/>attention must, before the writing can be proved, be called to those <lb/>parts of it which are to be used for the purpose of contradicting <lb/>him. Under Section 157 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 in order <lb/>to corroborate the testimony of a witness, any former statement <lb/>made by such witness relating to the same fact, at or about the <lb/>time when the fact took place, or before any authority legally <lb/>competent to investigate the fact, may be proved. Thus the <lb/>discrepancies pointed out by Mr. Zangpo Sherpa cannot come to <lb/>the rescue of the convict at the Appellate stage. <lb/>58. <lb/>Mr. Zangpo Sherpa would also argue that the evidence of <lb/>Prosecution witnesses would show that the relation between the <lb/>convict and P.W.1, the mother of the victim, Ms. R was not good <lb/>and cordial prior to the incident. The Learned Special Judge has <lb/>examined this argument and held that: -<lb/>&quot;26. PW-1 is the mother of the victim R. Even if, the relation <lb/>between PW-1 and accused is not good then also it is not <lb/>believable that she use the prosecutrix as an instrument to <lb/>wreak her vengeance against the accused. She being the <lb/>mother cannot be expected to expose the modesty of her own <lb/>daughter. I do not think that the mother of the victim will use <lb/>her minor daughter as an instrument for her enmity with the <lb/>accused, if any, and jeopardize her life involving in such kind of <lb/>heinous offence.&quot; <lb/>59. <lb/>This Court is in complete agreement with the reasoning <lb/>given by the Learned Special Court as quoted above. The <lb/>observations made by the Apex Court in paragraph 5 of the <lb/>judgment in re: State of H.P. v. Sanjay Kumar (supra) quoted <lb/>above, on a similar factual narrative, would suffice to reject the <lb/>contention of Mr. Zangpo Sherpa. <lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>60. <lb/>Mr. Zangpo Sherpa would also argue that as per Ms. R the <lb/>date of the alleged incident is 14.11.2014 but the FIR was filed <lb/>only on 31.12.2014 and as such there is a delay in the FIR which <lb/>was not considered by the Learned Special Judge. This statement <lb/>that the contention of delay was not considered by the Learned <lb/>Special Judge, however, is incorrect. Paragraphs 20 and 21 of the <lb/>Judgment of the Learned Special Judge deals extensively on the <lb/>aspect of delay in lodging the FIR and rejects the same. <lb/>61. <lb/>Ms. R stated that the incident was of 14.11.2014 and that <lb/>she informed P.W.8 after several days. P.W.8 states that after <lb/>inquiring about the swelling over Ms. R&apos;s chest from Ms. R and on <lb/>being told she was sexually assaulted by her &apos;Dewa&apos; (uncle) she <lb/>informed P.W.1, the mother of Ms. R, about what she heard from <lb/>Ms. R. In cross examination P.W.8 admitted that she had informed <lb/>P.W.1 about the incident in the month of November, 2014 but does <lb/>not remember the exact date. There is a contradiction in the <lb/>statement of P.W.1, on when she was informed by P.W.8 because <lb/>in her deposition in Court, P.W.1 states that on 14.11.2014 itself <lb/>she was informed by P.W.8 that convict had committed rape on Ms. <lb/>R. However, P.W.1 goes on to state that she requested P.W.8 <lb/>thereafter to inquire about the matter from Ms. R who on inquiry <lb/>confirmed the same after which P.W.1 inquired about the incident <lb/>directly from Ms. R, reported the matter to the Village Panchayat <lb/>and thereafter they reported to the Police. Evidently the evidence is <lb/>not cogent regarding when and how the information regarding the <lb/>sexual assault on Ms. R was transmitted till it reached the Police <lb/>Station. <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>62. <lb/>Ms. S does not remember at all the date, month and year <lb/>of the incident. <lb/>P.W.5 the father of Ms. S stated that on <lb/>31.12.2014 his wife called him to the house of the convict and on <lb/>reaching there she informed him that the convict had sexually <lb/>assaulted Ms. S. The fact that P.W.5 received a telephone call from <lb/>his wife on 31.12.2014 and heard from her after reaching the <lb/>house of the convict is admissible in evidence under Section 60 of <lb/>the Indian Evidence Act, 1872. The FIR was lodged by P.W.4 on <lb/>31.12.2014 itself who states that on 21.12.2014 he received <lb/>information about the incident from one Lady (not examined), <lb/>grandmother of Ms. S about rape having been committed by the <lb/>convict on both Ms. S and Ms. R. P.W.4 further goes to state that <lb/>on 31.12.2014 P.W.1 also told her that P.W.8 told her that the <lb/>convict had committed rape on Ms. R and Ms. S and thereafter on <lb/>the request of the Panchayat he affixed his signature on the FIR. <lb/>63. <lb/>However, the evidence of Ms. R and Ms. S on the material <lb/>aspect of commission of aggravated sexual assault on them does <lb/>inspire confidence. In such event discrepancies as pointed out <lb/>above, of other witnesses, who did not have direct knowledge <lb/>about the aggravated sexual assault on Ms. R and Ms. S, or of <lb/>P.W.4, the first informant and an interested witness, fades into <lb/>insignificance when the direct and cogent evidence of Ms. R and <lb/>Ms. S are available. There are no contradictions on the direct <lb/>evidences given by Ms. R and Ms. S about the crime and the other <lb/>witnesses examined by the prosecution. <lb/>64. <lb/>In State of Himachal Pradesh v. Sanjay Kumar 12 the Apex <lb/>Court would examine a delay in lodging an FIR of 3 years on which <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">12 (2017) 2 SCC 51 <lb/></note>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>ground the High Court of Himachal Pradesh had been swayed and <lb/>over turned the judgment of conviction in a rape case rendered by <lb/>the Trial Court. The Apex Court in the said Judgment would hold:-<lb/>&quot;30. By no means, it is suggested that whenever such charge <lb/>of rape is made, where the victim is a child, it has to be treated <lb/>as a gospel truth and the accused person has to be convicted. <lb/>We have already discussed above the manner in which the <lb/>testimony of the prosecutrix is to be examined and analysed in <lb/>order to find out the truth therein and to ensure that deposition <lb/>of the victim is trustworthy. At the same time, after taking all <lb/>due precautions which are necessary, when it is found that the <lb/>prosecution version is worth believing, the case is to be dealt <lb/>with all sensitivity that is needed in such cases. In such a <lb/>situation one has to take stock of the realities of life as well. <lb/>Various studies show that in more than 80% cases of such <lb/>abuses, perpetrators have acquaintance with the victims who <lb/>are not strangers. The danger is more within than outside. Most <lb/>of the time, acquaintance rapes, when the culprit is a family <lb/>member, are not even reported for various reasons, not difficult <lb/>to fathom. The strongest among those is the fear of attracting <lb/>social stigma. Another deterring factor which many times <lb/>prevents such victims or their families to lodge a complaint is <lb/>that they find whole process of criminal justice system <lb/>extremely intimidating coupled with absence of victim <lb/>protection mechanism. Therefore, time is ripe to bring about <lb/>significant reforms in the criminal justice system as well. <lb/>Equally, there is also a dire need to have a survivor-centric <lb/>approach towards victims of sexual violence, particularly, the <lb/>children, keeping in view the traumatic long-lasting effects on <lb/>such victims.&quot; <lb/>65. <lb/>This Court has examined the evidence of Ms. R and Ms. S <lb/>and come to the conclusion that the same are not only truthful and <lb/>reliable but their evidences alone could be the basis of conviction. <lb/>In such circumstances, as held by the Apex Court, it is important to <lb/>deal with it with all sensitivity that is needed in such cases taking <lb/>stock of the realities of life. The assault amounts to aggravated <lb/>sexual assault under the POCSO Act, 2012. The victims are children <lb/>aged 6 and 11 years. The incident relates to a rural area of West <lb/>Sikkim. The families of both Ms. R and Ms. S come from lower <lb/>income strata of Society. The convict was a relative of Mr. R and a <lb/>co-villager of Ms. S. Consciousness, alertness and consequences of <lb/>procedural laws would definitely not be considerations for such <lb/>witnesses who are bound to make exaggerations, and sometimes <lb/></body>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>embellish the evidence. When such heinous offences are committed <lb/>on minor children it may perhaps also be expected that the family <lb/>members may be confused, ill advised and may not understand the <lb/>nuances of not reporting the crime on time. As far back in the year <lb/>1973 V. R. Krishna Iyer J, would hold, and very appropriate to the <lb/>present case, in re: Shivaji Sahabrao Bobade &amp; Anr. v. State of <lb/>Maharashtra 13 :-<lb/>&quot;(8) Now to the facts. The scene of murder is rural, the witnesses to <lb/>the case are rustics and so their behavioural pattern and <lb/>perceptive habits have to be judged as such. The too <lb/>sophisticated approaches familiar in courts based on unreal <lb/>assumptions about human conduct cannot obviously be applied <lb/>to those given to the lethargic ways of our villages. When <lb/>scanning the evidence of the various witnesses we have to <lb/>inform ourselves that the variances on the fringes, <lb/>discrepancies in details, contradictions in narrations and <lb/>embellishments in inessential parts cannot militate against the <lb/>veracity of the core of the testimony provided there is the <lb/>impress of truth and conformity to probability in the substantial <lb/>fabric of testimony delivered........................... <lb/>11 <lb/>.............The sluggish chronometric sense of the country-side <lb/>community in India is notorious since time is hardly of the <lb/>essence of their slow life; and even urban folk make mistakes <lb/>about time when no particular reason to observe and remember <lb/>the hour of minor event like taking a morning meal existed.&quot; <lb/>SENTENCE <lb/>66. <lb/>The Learned Special Judge was examining two different <lb/>offences committed by the convict to different victims, Ms. R and <lb/>Ms. S. However, the Learned Special Judge, in the operative part of <lb/>the judgment, held as under:-<lb/>&quot;I, therefore, hold that the accused Deo Kumar Rai is guilty <lb/>under Section 9 (m) and 9 (n) of Protection of Children from <lb/>Sexual Offences Act, 2012, punishable under Section 10 of <lb/>Protection of Children from Sexual Offences Act, 2012. Thus, I <lb/>do hereby convict the accused Deo Kumar Rai under Section 9 <lb/>(m) and 9 (n) of Protection of Children from Sexual Offences <lb/>Act, 2012, punishable under Section 10 of Protection of <lb/>Children from Sexual Offences Act, 2012.&quot; <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">13 (1973) 2 SCC 793 <lb/></note>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>67. <lb/>Vide order on sentence dated 17.09.2015 the Learned <lb/>Special Judge would sentence the convict in the following manner:-<lb/>&quot;4. <lb/>After considering the submissions made by Ld. Addl. <lb/>Special P. P. as well as Ld. Counsel for the convict and <lb/>considering the facts and circumstances of the case, the ends of <lb/>justice would meet if the convict Deo Kumar Rai is sentenced to <lb/>undergo:-<lb/>Simple imprisonment of 5 years and to pay a fine of <lb/>Rs.10,000/-(Rupees ten thousand) only under Section 9 (m) <lb/>and 9 (n) of Protection of Children from Sexual Offences Act, <lb/>2012, punishable under Section 10 of Protection of Children <lb/>from Sexual Offences Act, 2012. In default of payment of fine, <lb/>the convict shall further undergo simple imprisonment of 3 <lb/>(three) months. <lb/>However, the period of detention already undergone by <lb/>convict during investigation and trial shall be set off against this <lb/>period of imprisonment as provided under Section 428 Cr.P.C.. <lb/>5. The fine amount (supra), if recovered shall be handed over <lb/>to the victims as compensation under Section 357 of the Code <lb/>of Criminal Procedure, 1973.&quot; <lb/>68. <lb/>Section 9 (n) of the POCSO Act, 2012, as quoted above, <lb/>deals with commission of sexual assault on a child being a relative <lb/>of the child. Section 9 (m) of the POCSO Act, 2012 however deals <lb/>with sexual assault on a child below 12 years. Both Ms. R and Ms. S <lb/>being below 12 years the convict was liable to be convicted and <lb/>punished under Section 9 (m) of the POCSO Act, 2012 for having <lb/>committed sexual assault on a child below 12 years. <lb/>69. <lb/>Section 71 IPC provides:-<lb/>&quot;71. Limit of punishment of offence made up of several <lb/>offences.-Where anything which is an offence is made up of <lb/>parts, any of which parts is itself an offence, the offender shall <lb/>not be punished with the punishment of more than one of such <lb/>his offences, unless it be so expressly provided. <lb/>Where anything is an offence falling within two or more <lb/>separate definitions of any law in force for the time being by <lb/>which offences are defined or punished, or <lb/>where several acts, of which one or more than one <lb/>would by itself or themselves constitute an offence, constitute, <lb/>when combined, a different offence, <lb/>the offender shall not be punished with a more severe <lb/>punishment than the Court which tries him could award for any <lb/>one of such offences.&quot; <lb/></body>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>70. <lb/>In re: STATE REPRESENTED BY INSPECTOR OF POLICE, <lb/>PUDUKOTTAI, T.N v. A. PARTHIBAN 14 , held as under:-<lb/>&quot;7. The crucial question is whether the alleged act is an <lb/>offence and if the answer is in the affirmative, whether it is <lb/>capable of being construed as offence under one or more <lb/>provisions. That is the essence of Section 71 IPC, in the <lb/>backdrop of Section 220 CrPC.&quot; <lb/>71. <lb/>Section 71 IPC would thus be attracted. The convict, in so <lb/>far as it relates to the offence committed on Ms. R, shall not be <lb/>punished with the punishment of more than one of such offences. <lb/>72. <lb/>Section 9 (n) of the POCSO Act, 2012, as quoted above, <lb/>however, deals with commission of sexual assault on a child being <lb/>a relative of the child. The evidence available makes it evident that <lb/>Ms. R is a relative of the convict. Ms. R stated that the convict is <lb/>her &apos;Dewa&apos; (uncle). P.W.8, P.W.1 and P.W.6 also corroborated the <lb/>said fact. Thus the convict was liable to be convicted and punished <lb/>under Section 9 (n) of the POCSO Act, 2012, also. <lb/>73. <lb/>While conducting a trial of different offences allegedly <lb/>committed against two victims the Special Judge must clearly and <lb/>cogently specify the offences of which, and the Sections of the <lb/>POCSO Act, 2012 under which, the accused is convicted and <lb/>punishment to which he is sentenced. <lb/>74. <lb/>The Learned Special Judge, while writing the operative part <lb/>of the judgment seem to have lost sight of the law and the fact <lb/>that the Learned Special Judge was in fact conducting a trial of two <lb/>separate and distinct offences committed on two victims. This is a <lb/>requirement under the provision of Section 354 Cr.P.C. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">14 <lb/>(2006) 11 SCC 473 <lb/></note>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>75. <lb/>The Learned Special Judge while conducting a trial of two <lb/>offences committed against two victims must keep conscious of the <lb/>fact that the Special Court is required to render justice to two <lb/>victims. <lb/>76. <lb/>Section 31 of the Cr.P.C. which deals with sentences in <lb/>cases of conviction of several offences at one trial provides:-<lb/>&quot;31. Sentence in cases of conviction of several <lb/>offences at one trial. -<lb/>(1) When a person is convicted at one trial of two or <lb/>more offences, the Court may, subject to the provisions of <lb/>section 71 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860), sentence him <lb/>for such offences, to the several punishments prescribed <lb/>therefore which such Court is competent to inflict; such <lb/>punishments when consisting of imprisonment to commence <lb/>the one after the expiration of the other in such order as the <lb/>Court may direct, unless the Court directs that such <lb/>punishments shall run concurrently. <lb/>(2) In the case of consecutive sentences, it shall not be <lb/>necessary for the Court by reason only of the aggregate <lb/>punishment for the several offences being in excess of the <lb/>punishment which it is competent to inflict on conviction of a <lb/>single offence, to send the offender for trial before a higher <lb/>Court: Provided that-<lb/>(a) in no case shall such person be sentenced to <lb/>imprisonment for longer period than fourteen years; <lb/>(b) the aggregate punishment shall not exceed twice the <lb/>amount of punishment which the Court is competent to <lb/>inflict for a single offence. <lb/>(3) For the purpose of appeal by a convicted person, the <lb/>aggregate of the consecutive sentences passed against him <lb/>under this section shall be deemed to be a single sentence.&quot; <lb/>77. <lb/>Section 10 of the POCSO Act, 2012 provides:-<lb/>&quot;10. <lb/>Punishment for aggravated sexual assault.-Whoever, <lb/>commits aggravated sexual assault shall be punished with <lb/>imprisonment of either description for a term which shall not be <lb/></body>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>less than five years but which may extend to seven years, and <lb/>shall also be liable to fine.&quot; <lb/>78. <lb/>Each of the offences defined in sub-section (a) to (u) of <lb/>Section 9 of the POCSO Act, 2012 are distinct and different <lb/>offences having different ingredients. Thus, the convict was liable <lb/>to be punished separately for the offence committed on Ms. R <lb/>under Section 9 (n) and on Ms. S under Section 9 (m). Under <lb/>Section 10 each of the said offences under Section 9 (m) and 9 (n) <lb/>of the POCSO Act, 2012 shall be punished with imprisonment of <lb/>either description for a term which shall not be less than 5 years <lb/>but which may extent to 7 years, and shall also be liable to fine. <lb/>Thus the convict was liable for the offence on Ms. S under Section <lb/>9 (m) of the POCSO Act, 2012 for a term which shall not be less <lb/>than 5 years but which may extend to 7 years, and shall also be <lb/>liable to fine. Similarly, the convict was also liable for the offence <lb/>on Ms. R under section 9 (n) of the POCSO Act, 2012 for a term <lb/>which shall not be less than 5 years but which may extend to 7 <lb/>years, and shall also be liable to fine. <lb/>79. <lb/>The Learned Special Judge while sentencing must keep in <lb/>mind the provisions of Section 31 Cr.P.C. which provides that when <lb/>a person is convicted at one trial of two or more offences, the Court <lb/>may, subject to the provision of section 71 of the IPC, sentence <lb/>him for such offences, the several punishments prescribed thereof <lb/>which such Court is competent to inflict. It is desirable that the <lb/>Learned Special Court should at least record what punishment it <lb/>awards for each of the two distinct offences. As this is not done <lb/>complications would necessary arise at the appellate stage. Proper <lb/>course of action would have been to pass a separate sentence for <lb/></body>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>each offence. The question in such situations as to what <lb/>interpretation should be given to such a composite sentence was <lb/>pursuasively answered by a Division Bench of the Allahabad High <lb/>Court in re: Murlidhar Dalmia v. State 15 in which it would hold:-<lb/>&quot;Such a view does find support from some cases, but we do not <lb/>agree with the view and are of opinion that such a composite <lb/>sentence of imprisonment should be taken to mean that <lb/>identical sentence was awarded for each of the offences of <lb/>which the accused was convicted and that all such identical <lb/>sentences for all the offences were ordered to run concurrently. <lb/>This seems to us to be the most logical interpretation as <lb/>otherwise the appellate or the revisional court cannot be in a <lb/>position to determine the specific punishments which the trial <lb/>court is supposed to have contemplated to award for each <lb/>offence and whose total was simply mentioned as the sentence <lb/>awarded to the accused. It can be said that ordinarily courts do <lb/>make the separate sentences concurrent and that it is only in <lb/>special cases that the courts order sentences to run <lb/>consecutively. Section 35, Code of Criminal Procedure, provides <lb/>that when a person is convicted at one trial of two or more <lb/>offences, the court may sentence him for such offences to the <lb/>several punishments prescribed therefor which such court was <lb/>competent to inflict and that such punishments, when <lb/>consisting of imprisonment or transportation, shall commence <lb/>the one after the expiration of the other in such order as the <lb/>court may direct, unless the court directs that such <lb/>punishments shall run concurrently. This means that when a <lb/>court intends to award separate sentences for the various <lb/>offences to run consecutively it is to express the order in which <lb/>the sentences for the various offences would run. When the <lb/>court passes just one sentence for the various offences, it <lb/>would be too much to suppose that the court had separate <lb/>sentences for each offence in mind and failed to give expression <lb/>to its intention about the extent of the sentences and also failed <lb/>to mention the order in which the sentences for the various <lb/>offences were to run. <lb/>It would be more probable in such a case that the court <lb/>contemplated the sentences to run concurrently and just <lb/>expressed the, maximum sentence which the court thought <lb/>that the accused should undergo for what he had done. No <lb/>difficulty arises in interpreting one sentence awarded as a <lb/>sentence for each offence with the direction that the sentences <lb/>were to run concurrently. A difficulty may arise when the <lb/>sentence awarded be in excess of the maximum sentence which <lb/>could have been awarded for any of the offences of which the <lb/>accused had been convicted, because in that case it would not <lb/>be proper to hold that the court intended to pass an illegal <lb/>sentence and did pass an illegal sentence. In such a case it can <lb/>be held that the sentence passed for such an offence was the <lb/>maximum fixed under law for that offence and that the court <lb/>ordered such maximum sentence to run concurrently with the <lb/>higher sentence passed for other offences. This view agrees <lb/>with the view expressed by this Court in Sohan Ahir v. King-<lb/>Emperor (1) , where DANIELS, J., interpreted a sentence of 18 <lb/>months&apos; rigorous imprisonment under sections 326 and 147, <lb/>Indian Penal Code as meaning that the Magistrate passed <lb/>concurrent identical sentences under each section. When the <lb/>composite sentence consists of or includes fine, the amount of <lb/>fine should be taken ordinarily to be the total of the fines the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">15 1952 SCC OnLine All 232 : ILR (1953) 1 All 834 : AIR 1953 All 245 <lb/></note>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>trial court intended to impose for various offences and it may <lb/>be presumed in the absence of any special circumstances that <lb/>an equal amount of fine was imposed for each offence. It would <lb/>follow that the acquittal of the accused for some offence must <lb/>mean corresponding reduction in fine.&quot; <lb/>80. <lb/>Section 537 of the old Criminal Procedure Code <lb/>corresponds to the present Section 465 of Cr.P.C. No failure of <lb/>justice would have occasioned the convict for the irregularity in <lb/>passing a composite sentence by the Learned Special Judge. <lb/>81. <lb/>Therefore, so interpreted, while this Court confirms the <lb/>composite sentences awarded by the Learned Special Judge, it is <lb/>hoped that the Learned Special Judge while imposing sentence may <lb/>keep in mind the aforesaid observations. <lb/>82. <lb/>The convict is therefore sentenced for the offence on Ms. <lb/>S under Section 9 (m) of the POCSO Act, 2012 for a term of 5 <lb/>years and to pay a fine of ₹ 5,000/-(Rupees five thousand) and <lb/>further the convict is also sentenced for the offence on Ms. R under <lb/>section 9 (n) of the POCSO Act, 2012 for a term of 5 years and to <lb/>pay a fine of ₹ 5,000/-(Rupees five thousand). The sentences to <lb/>run concurrently. <lb/>83. <lb/>The Learned Special Judge has directed that the period of <lb/>detention already under gone by convict during investigation and <lb/>trial shall be set off against the period of imprisonment as provided <lb/>under Section 428 Cr.P.C. The said direction is maintained. <lb/>84. <lb/>The Learned Special Judge has also directed that the fine <lb/>amount, if recovered shall be handed over to the victims as <lb/>compensation under Section 357 of the Cr.P.C. The same is also <lb/>maintained. <lb/></body>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>COMPENSATION <lb/>85. <lb/>Section 33 (8) of the POCSO Act, 2012 provides:-<lb/>&quot;33 (8) In appropriate cases, the Special Court may, in addition to the <lb/>punishment, direct payment of such compensation as may be <lb/>prescribed to the child for any physical or mental trauma caused to <lb/>him or for immediate rehabilitation of such child.&quot; <lb/>86. <lb/>Rule 7 of the Protection of Children from Sexual Offences <lb/>Rules, 2012 (POCSO Rules, 2012) provides:-<lb/>&quot;7.Compensation.-(1) The Special Court may, in appropriate cases, <lb/>on its own or on an application filed by or on behalf of the child, pass <lb/>an order for interim compensation to meet the immediate needs of the <lb/>child for relief or rehabilitation at any stage after registration of the <lb/>First Information Report. Such interim compensation paid to the child <lb/>shall be adjusted against the final compensation, if any. <lb/>(2) The Special Court may, on its own or on an application filed by or <lb/>on behalf of the victim, recommend the award of compensation where <lb/>the accused is convicted, or where the case ends in acquittal or <lb/>discharge, or the accused is not traced or identified, and in the opinion <lb/>of the Special Court the child has suffered loss or injury as a result of <lb/>that offence. <lb/>(3) Where the Special Court, under sub-section (8) of Section 33 of the <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Act read with sub-sections (2) and (3) of Section 357-A of the Code of <lb/>Criminal Procedure, makes a direction for the award of compensation <lb/>to the victim, it shall take into account all relevant factors relating to <lb/>the loss or injury caused to the victim, including the following-<lb/>(i) type of abuse, gravity of the offence and the severity of the mental <lb/>or physical harm or injury suffered by the child; <lb/>(ii) the expenditure incurred or likely to be incurred on his medical <lb/>treatment for physical and/or mental health; <lb/>(iii) loss of educational opportunity as a consequence of the offence, <lb/>including absence from school due to mental trauma, bodily injury, <lb/>medical treatment, investigation and trial of the offence, or any other <lb/>reason; <lb/>(iv) loss of employment as a result of the offence, including absence <lb/>from place of employment due to mental trauma, bodily injury, medical <lb/>treatment, investigation and trial of the offence, or any other reason; <lb/>(v) the relationship of the child to the offender, if any; <lb/>(vi) whether the abuse was a single isolated incidence or whether the <lb/>abuse took place over a period of time; <lb/>(vii) whether the child become pregnant as a result of the offence; <lb/>(viii) whether the child contracted a sexually transmitted disease (STD) <lb/>as a result of the offence; <lb/>(ix) whether the child contracted human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) <lb/>as a result of the offence; <lb/></div>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>(x) any disability suffered by the child as a result of the offence; <lb/>(xi) financial condition of the child against whom the offence has been <lb/>committed so as to determine his need for rehabilitation; <lb/>(xii) any other factor that the Special Court may consider to be <lb/>relevant. <lb/>(4) The compensation awarded by the Special Court is to be paid by <lb/>the State Government from the Victims Compensation Fund or other <lb/>scheme or fund established by it for the purposes of compensating and <lb/>rehabilitating victims under Section 357-A of the Code of Criminal <lb/>Procedure or any other laws for the time being in force, or, where such <lb/>fund or scheme does not exist, by the State Government. <lb/>(5) The State Government shall pay the compensation ordered by the <lb/>Special Court within 30 days of receipt of such order. <lb/>(6) Nothing in these rules shall prevent a child or his parent or <lb/>guardian or any other person in whom the child has trust and <lb/>confidence from submitting an application for seeking relief under any <lb/>other rules or scheme of the Central Government or State <lb/>Government.&quot; <lb/>87. <lb/>Section 357 of Cr.P.C. provides:-<lb/>&quot;357. Order to pay compensation.-(1) When a Court imposes a <lb/>sentence of fine or a sentence (including a sentence of death) of which <lb/>fine forms a part, the Court may, when passing judgment order the <lb/>whole or any part of the fine recovered to be applied-<lb/>(a) in defraying the expenses properly incurred in the prosecution; <lb/>(b) in the payment to any person of compensation for any loss or <lb/>injury caused by the offence, when compensation is, in the opinion of <lb/>the Court, recoverable by such person in a Civil Court; <lb/>(c) when any person is convicted of any offence for having caused <lb/>the death of another person or of having abetted the commission of <lb/>such an offence, in paying compensation to the persons who are, under <lb/>the Fatal Accidents Act, 1855 (13 of 1855), entitled to recover <lb/>damages from the person sentenced for the loss resulting to them from <lb/>such death; <lb/>(d) when any person is convicted of any offence which includes <lb/>theft, criminal misappropriation, criminal breach of trust, or cheating, <lb/>or of having dishonestly received or retained, or of having voluntarily <lb/>assisted in disposing of, stolen property knowing or having reason to <lb/>believe the same to be stolen, in compensating any bona fide <lb/>purchaser of such property for the loss of the same if such property is <lb/>restored to the possession of the person entitled thereto. <lb/>(2) If the fine is imposed in a case which is subject to appeal, no <lb/>such payment shall be made before the period allowed for presenting <lb/>the appeal has elapsed, or if an appeal be presented, before the <lb/>decision of the appeal. <lb/>(3) When a Court imposes a sentence, of which fine does not form <lb/>a part, the Court may, when passing judgment order the accused <lb/>person to pay, by way of compensation such amount as may be <lb/>specified in the order to the person who has suffered any loss or injury <lb/></body>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>by reason of the act for which the accused person has been so <lb/>sentenced. <lb/>(4) An order under this section may also be made by an Appellant <lb/>Court or by the High Court or Court of Session when exercising its <lb/>powers of revision. <lb/>(5) At the time of awarding compensation in any subsequent civil <lb/>suit relating to the same matter, the Court shall take into account any <lb/>sum paid or recovered as compensation under this section.&quot; <lb/>88. <lb/>Section 357 A of Cr.P.C. provides:-<lb/>&quot;357A. Victim compensation scheme. -(1) Every State <lb/>Government in co-ordination with the Central Government shall <lb/>prepare a scheme for providing funds for the purpose of compensation <lb/>to the victim or his dependents who have suffered loss or injury as a <lb/>result of the crime and who require rehabilitation. <lb/>(2) Whenever a recommendation is made by the Court for <lb/>compensation, the District Legal Service Authority or the State Legal <lb/>Service Authority, as the case may be, shall decide the quantum of <lb/>compensation to be awarded under the scheme referred to in sub-<lb/>section (1). <lb/>(3) If the trial Court, at the conclusion of the trial, is satisfied, <lb/>that the compensation awarded under section 357 is not adequate for <lb/>such rehabilitation, or where the cases end in acquittal or discharge <lb/>and the victim has to be rehabilitated, it may make recommendation <lb/>for compensation. <lb/>(4) Where the offender is not traced or identified, but the victim <lb/>is identified, and where no trial takes place, the victim or his <lb/>dependents may make an application to the State or the District Legal <lb/>Services Authority for award of compensation. <lb/>(5) On receipt of such recommendations or on the application <lb/>under sub-section (4), the State or the District Legal Services <lb/>Authority shall, after due enquiry award adequate compensation by <lb/>completing the enquiry within two months. <lb/>(6) The State or the District Legal Services Authority, as the <lb/>case may be, to alleviate the suffering of the victim, may order for <lb/>immediate first-aid facility or medical benefits to be made available <lb/>free of cost on the certificate of the police officer not below the rank of <lb/>the officer in charge of the police station or a Magistrate of the area <lb/>concerned, or any other interim relief as the appropriate authority <lb/>deems fit.&quot; <lb/>89. <lb/>In exercise of the powers conferred by Section 357 (A) of <lb/>Cr.P.C. the Sikkim Compensation of Victims or his Dependents <lb/>(Amendment) Schemes, 2013 came into force in Sikkim on <lb/>24.06.2013. The said Scheme was amended vide Sikkim <lb/>Compensation of Victims or his Dependents (Amendment) <lb/>Schemes, 2013 and the maximum limit of compensation was <lb/></body>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>enhanced under particular heads of loss or injury. On 25.11.2016 <lb/>Sikkim Compensation of Victims or his Dependents (Amendment) <lb/>Schemes, 2016 was notified in the Sikkim Government Gazette <lb/>making it applicable from 18.11.2016. The said amendment of <lb/>2016 further enhances the maximum limit of compensation on <lb/>various heads of loss or injury. <lb/>90. <lb/>Section 357 of Cr.P.C. relates to compensation payable by <lb/>the convict. Section 357 (A) of Cr.P.C. on the other hand deals with <lb/>Victim Compensation Schemes of State Government&apos;s for providing <lb/>funds for the purpose of compensation to the victim or his <lb/>dependence who have suffered loss or injury as a result of the <lb/>crime and who require rehabilitation. <lb/>91. <lb/>Under Section 33 (8) of the POCSO Act, 2012 the Special <lb/>Court, in appropriate cases in addition to the punishment, direct <lb/>payment of such compensation as may be prescribed to the child <lb/>for any physical or mental trauma caused to him or for immediate <lb/>rehabilitation of such child. The Learned Special Judge has <lb/>however, not complied with the mandatory duty of the court to <lb/>apply its mind to the question of the award or refusal of <lb/>compensation in a particular case in every criminal case. <lb/>92. <lb/>Under Rule 7 (1) of the POCSO Rules, 2012 the Special <lb/>Court may, in appropriate cases, on its own or an application filed <lb/>by or on behalf of the child, pass an order for interim compensation <lb/>to meet the immediate needs of the child for relief or rehabilitation <lb/>at any stage after registration of the FIR. Such interim <lb/></body>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>compensation paid to the child shall be adjusted against the final <lb/>compensation, if any. In the present case the Learned Special <lb/>Judge has not considered payment of compensation, interim or <lb/>otherwise, as mandated under Section 33 (8) of the POCSO Act, <lb/>2012 read with Rule 7 of the POCSO Rules, 2012. <lb/>93. <lb/>Under the provisions of Rule 7 (2) of the POCSO Rules, <lb/>2012, the Special Court may, on its own or on an application filed <lb/>by or on behalf of the victim, recommend the award of <lb/>compensation where the accused is convicted and in the opinion of <lb/>the Special Court the child has suffered loss or injury as a result of <lb/>that offence. <lb/>94. <lb/>Under Rule 7 (3) of the POCSO Rules, 2012, which is an <lb/>inclusive Rule and therefore not exhaustive, the relevant factors to <lb/>be considered while directing compensation have been enumerated <lb/>for the guidance of the Special Court. <lb/>95. <lb/>Under Rule 7 (4) of the POCSO Rules, 2012, the <lb/>compensation awarded by the Special Court is to be paid by the <lb/>State Government from the Victims Compensation Fund or other <lb/>scheme or fund established by it for the purposes of compensating <lb/>and rehabilitating victims under Section 357 A of Cr.P.C. or any <lb/>other law for the time in force. <lb/>96. <lb/>Under Rule 7 (5) of the POCSO Rules, 2012, the State <lb/>Government shall pay the compensation ordered by the Special <lb/>Court within 30 days of receipt of such order. <lb/></body>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>97. <lb/>Under Rule 7 (6) of the POCSO Rules, 2012 a child or his <lb/>parent or guardian or any other person in whom the child has trust <lb/>and confidence may submit an application for seeking relief under <lb/>any other rules or schemes of the Central Government or State <lb/>Government. <lb/>98. <lb/>Many a times due to the peculiar facts of the case a Trial <lb/>Judge may be faced with the situation where it is found that in <lb/>addition to the punishment, compensation must be directed to be <lb/>paid. In such situations the Trial Court is not helpless. Section 33 <lb/>(8) of the POCSO Act, 2012 read with Rule 7 of the POCSO Rules, <lb/>2012 was made precisely for the said purpose. The Special Judge <lb/>has the power and therefore must also exercise it, in appropriate <lb/>cases, to direct payment of compensation as per the Sikkim <lb/>Compensation to Victims or his Dependents Scheme, 2011 as <lb/>amended till date. The aforesaid provisions are victim centric. It is <lb/>meant for the purpose of rehabilitation of the victim who has <lb/>suffered loss or injury as a result of the crime and who require <lb/>rehabilitation. The Special Court is required to consider whether or <lb/>not there is a need for directing payment of compensation by firstly <lb/>making adequate inquiry and thereafter giving reasons. The <lb/>quantum of compensation must be as prescribed under the <lb/>provisions of the Sikkim Compensation to Victims or his <lb/>Dependents Scheme, 2011 as amended till date. As per the <lb/>schedule thereto the particulars of loss or injury as well as the <lb/>maximum limit of compensation is provided. While making the <lb/>recommendation by the Court and while deciding the quantum of <lb/>compensation payable under the Sikkim Compensation to Victims <lb/></body>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>or his Dependents Scheme, 2011 as amended till date the ethos of <lb/>Section 33(8) of the POCSO Act, 2012, Rule 7 of the POCSO Rules, <lb/>2012 and Section 357(A) of Cr.P.C. which have direct roots in the <lb/>concept of victimology must always be in its mind. <lb/>99. <lb/>In re: Ankush Shivahi Gaikwad v. State of Maharastra 16 <lb/>the Apex Court would hold:-<lb/>&quot;33. The long line of judicial pronouncements of this Court recognised <lb/>in no uncertain terms a paradigm shift in the approach towards victims <lb/>of crimes who were held entitled to reparation, restitution or <lb/>compensation for loss or injury suffered by them. This shift from <lb/>retribution to restitution began in the mid-1960s and gained <lb/>momentum in the decades that followed. Interestingly the clock <lb/>appears to have come full circle by the lawmakers and courts going <lb/>back in a great measure to what was in ancient times common place. <lb/>Harvard Law Review (1984) in an article on Victim Restitution in <lb/>Criminal Law Process: A Procedural Analysis sums up the historical <lb/>perspective of the concept of restitution in the following words: <lb/>&quot;Far from being a novel approach to sentencing, restitution has <lb/>been employed as a punitive sanction throughout history. In ancient <lb/>societies, before the conceptual separation of civil and criminal law, it <lb/>was standard practice to require an offender to reimburse the victim or <lb/>his family for any loss caused by the offense. The primary purpose of <lb/>such restitution was not to compensate the victim, but to protect the <lb/>offender from violent retaliation by the victim or the community. It <lb/>was a means by which the offender could buy back the peace he had <lb/>broken. As the State gradually established a monopoly over the <lb/>institution of punishment, and a division between civil and criminal law <lb/>emerged, the victim&apos;s right to compensation was incorporated into civil <lb/>law.&quot; <lb/>100. <lb/>In re: State of Madhya Pradesh v. Mehtaab 17 the Apex <lb/>Court would hold:-<lb/>&quot;8. Apart from the sentence and fine/compensation to be paid by the <lb/>accused, the court has to award compensation by the State under <lb/>Section 357-A CrPC when the accused is not in a position to pay fair <lb/>compensation as laid down by this Court in Suresh v. State of Haryana. <lb/>This Court held: <lb/>&quot;16. We are of the view that it is the duty of the courts, <lb/>on taking cognizance of a criminal offence, to ascertain whether <lb/>there is tangible material to show commission of crime, <lb/>whether the victim is identifiable and whether the victim of <lb/>crime needs immediate financial relief. On being satisfied on an <lb/>application or on its own motion, the court ought to direct grant <lb/>of interim compensation, subject to final compensation being <lb/>determined later. Such duty continues at every stage of a <lb/>criminal case where compensation ought to be given and has <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">16 (2013) 6 SCC 770 <lb/>17 (2015) 5 SCC 197 <lb/></note>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>not been given, irrespective of the application by the victim. At <lb/>the stage of final hearing it is obligatory on the part of the court <lb/>to advert to the provision and record a finding whether a case <lb/>for grant of compensation has been made out and, if so, who is <lb/>entitled to compensation and how much. Award of such <lb/>compensation can be interim. Gravity or offence and need of <lb/>victim are some of the guiding factors to be kept in mind, apart <lb/>from such other factors as may be found relevant in the facts <lb/>and circumstances of an individual case. <lb/>101. <lb/>In re: Hari Singh v. Sukhbir Singh 18 , 551 the Apex Court <lb/>would hold:-<lb/>&quot;10. Sub-section (1) of Section 357 provides power to award <lb/>compensation to victims of the offence out of the sentence of fine <lb/>imposed on accused. In this case, we are not concerned with sub-<lb/>section (1). We are concerned only with sub-section (3). It is an <lb/>important provision but courts have seldom invoked it. Perhaps due to <lb/>ignorance of the object of it. It empowers the court to award <lb/>compensation to victims while passing judgment of conviction. In <lb/>addition to conviction, the court may order the accused to pay some <lb/>amount by way of compensation to victim who has suffered by the <lb/>action of accused. It may be noted that this power of courts to award <lb/>compensation is not ancillary to other sentences but it is in addition <lb/>thereto. This power was intended to do something to reassure the <lb/>victim that he or she is not forgotten in the criminal justice system. It <lb/>is a measure of responding appropriately to crime as well of reconciling <lb/>the victim with the offender. It is, to some extent, a constructive <lb/>approach to crimes. It is indeed a step forward in our criminal justice <lb/>system. We, therefore, recommend to all courts to exercise this power <lb/>liberally so as to meet the ends of justice in a better way. <lb/>11. The payment by way of compensation must, however, be <lb/>reasonable. What is reasonable, may depend upon the facts and <lb/>circumstances of each case. The quantum of compensation may be <lb/>determined by taking into account the nature of crime, the justness of <lb/>claim by the victim and the ability of accused to pay. If there are more <lb/>than one accused they may be asked to pay in equal terms unless <lb/>their capacity to pay varies considerably. The payment may also vary <lb/>depending upon the acts of each accused. Reasonable period for <lb/>payment of compensation, if necessary by instalments, may also be <lb/>given. The court may enforce the order by imposing sentence in <lb/>default. <lb/>12. Joginder in this case is an unfortunate victim. His power of speech <lb/>has been permanently impaired. Doctor has certified that he is unable <lb/>to speak and that is why he has not stepped into the witness box for <lb/>the prosecution. The lifelong disability of the victim ought not to be <lb/>bypassed by the court. He must be made to feel that the court and <lb/>accused have taken care of him. Any such measure which would give <lb/>him succour is far better than a sentence by deterrence.&quot; <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">18 (1988) 4 SCC <lb/></note>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>102. <lb/>In re: Manohar Singh v. State of Rajasthan &amp; Ors. 19 the <lb/>Apex Court would hold:-<lb/>&quot;11. Just compensation to the victim has to be fixed having regard to <lb/>the medical and other expenses, pain and suffering, loss of earning <lb/>and other relevant factors. While punishment to the accused is one <lb/>aspect, determination of just compensation to the victim is the other. <lb/>At times, evidence is not available in this regard. Some guess work in <lb/>such a situation is inevitable. The compensation is payable under <lb/>Sections 357 and 357-A CrPC. While under Section 357 CrPC, financial <lb/>capacity of the accused has to be kept in mind, Section 357-A CrPC <lb/>under which compensation comes out of the State funds, has to be <lb/>invoked to make up the requirement of just compensation.&quot; <lb/>103. <lb/>In re: Ankush Shivahi Gaikwad (supra) the Apex Court <lb/>would hold:-<lb/>&quot;66. To sum up: while the award or refusal of compensation in a <lb/>particular case may be within the court&apos;s discretion, there exists a <lb/>mandatory duty on the court to apply its mind to the question in every <lb/>criminal case. Application of mind to the question is best disclosed by <lb/>recording reasons for awarding/refusing compensation. It is axiomatic <lb/>that for any exercise involving application of mind, the Court ought to <lb/>have the necessary material which it would evaluate to arrive at a fair <lb/>and reasonable conclusion. It is also beyond dispute that the occasion <lb/>to consider the question of award of compensation would logically arise <lb/>only after the court records a conviction of the accused. Capacity of the <lb/>accused to pay which constitutes an important aspect of any order <lb/>under Section 357 CrPC would involve a certain enquiry albeit <lb/>summary unless of course the facts as emerging in the course of the <lb/>trial are so clear that the court considers it unnecessary to do so. Such <lb/>an enquiry can precede an order on sentence to enable the court to <lb/>take a view, both on the question of sentence and compensation that it <lb/>may in its wisdom decide to award to the victim or his/her family.&quot; <lb/>104. <lb/>In the present case aggravated sexual assault on Ms. R <lb/>and Ms. S has been proved against the convict. The fine imposed <lb/>by the Learned Special Judge of ₹ 10,000/-(Rupees ten thousand) <lb/>is payable as compensation only on realisation from the convict. It <lb/>is obviously not adequate, keeping in mind the fact that there are <lb/>two victims aged 6 and 11 years, who have suffered aggravated <lb/>sexual assaults. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">19 2015 (89) ACC 266 (SC) <lb/></note>

			<page>40 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>105. <lb/>In terms of Section 33 (8) of the POCSO Act, 2012 read <lb/>with the POCSO Rules, 2012 and Section 357 (A) (3) of Cr.P.C. the <lb/>Learned Special Judge was required to come to a conclusion <lb/>whether the compensation awarded under Section 357 of Cr.P.C. is <lb/>adequate or not for the rehabilitation of Ms. R and Ms. S. The <lb/>considerations are cogently enumerated in Rule 7 of the POCSO <lb/>Rule, 2012. In the facts of the present case the type of abuse, <lb/>gravity of the offence and the severity of the mental and physical <lb/>harm suffered by the victims would be relevant. The fact that the <lb/>aggravated sexual assault on Ms. R and Ms. S were isolated <lb/>incidents would also be a relevant factor. Equally important would <lb/>be the financial condition of Ms. R and Ms. S which as per the <lb/>evidence available was definitely not good. The shock of such <lb/>heinous sexual assault by Ms. R&apos;s own uncle on Ms. R and by a <lb/>person known to Ms. S on Ms. S would also be a relevant <lb/>consideration. The Special Court is required to ask itself as to what <lb/>is required to rehabilitate the victim who has suffered both <lb/>mentally and physically to get over that trauma. The Learned <lb/>Special Judge did not do so. Under the Sikkim Compensation to <lb/>Victims or his Dependents Schemes, 2011 as amended till date for <lb/>sexual assault (excluding rape) an amount of ₹50,000/-(Rupees <lb/>fifty thousand) is prescribed as the maximum limit of <lb/>compensation. As such the Sikkim State Legal Services Authority is <lb/>directed to pay Ms. R and Ms. S just compensation of ₹45,000/-<lb/>(Rupees forty five thousand) each from the Victim Compensation <lb/>Fund provided by the State Government to it. The said amounts <lb/>shall be deposited in interest bearing fixed deposits in the accounts <lb/>of Ms. R and Ms. S payable to them on their turning 18 years of <lb/>age. If Ms. R and Ms. S do not have saving accounts for the <lb/></body>

			<page>41 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>purpose of opening of fixed deposits as directed, the Sikkim State <lb/>Legal Services Authority shall assist Ms. R and Ms. S through its <lb/>panel lawyers to do so. As required under Rule 7 (5) of the POCSO <lb/>Rules, 2012 the State Government shall pay the compensation <lb/>within 30 days of the receipt of this judgment. <lb/>106. <lb/>The Appeal against conviction is dismissed. The sentences <lb/>imposed by the Learned Special Judge&apos;s stands explained as above. <lb/>107. <lb/>The convict is in jail. He shall continue there to serve the <lb/>remaining of the sentences. <lb/>108. <lb/>Copy of this judgment be remitted to the Court of learned <lb/>Special Judge, East Sikkim at Gangtok, forthwith along with records <lb/>of the Court for compliance. Copy of this judgment may also be <lb/>forwarded to the Sikkim State Legal Services Authority for payment <lb/>of compensation payable to Ms. R and Ms. S and for compliance of <lb/>other directions. <lb/>109. <lb/>Urgent certified photocopy of this judgment, if applied for, <lb/>be supplied to the learned Counsels for the parties upon <lb/>compliance of all formalities. <lb/>110. <lb/>It is seen that the Investigating Officer while preparing the <lb/>charge-sheet; the Learned Judicial Magistrate while recording the <lb/>statement of Ms. R and Ms. S under Section 164 of Cr.P.C. and the <lb/>Learned Special Judge while recoding the deposition of Ms. R and <lb/>Ms. S were not conscious that the identity of the child cannot be <lb/>compromised and that the identity of the child is not only the name <lb/>of the child but the whole identity of the child, the identity of the <lb/>child&apos;s family, school, relatives, neighbourhood or any other <lb/></body>

			<page>42 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 13 of 2016 <lb/>Deo Kumar Rai v. State of Sikkim <lb/>information by which the identity of the child may be revealed. It is <lb/>urged that the guidelines laid down by this Court in Rabin Burman <lb/>v. State of Sikkim 20 be followed to ensure strict compliance of the <lb/>law with regard to non disclosure of the identity of the child with <lb/>the sensitivity the situation commands. <lb/>(Bhaskar Raj Pradhan) <lb/>Judge <lb/>13.09.2017 <lb/>Approved for reporting: yes. <lb/>Avi/to <lb/>Internet: yes. <lb/>20 2017 SCC OnLine Sikk 143 </body>


	</text>
</tei>
