<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<p>2.<lb/> Forwarding<lb/> his<lb/> arguments<lb/> for<lb/> the<lb/> Appellants, Learned Counsel submitted that the occurrence of<lb/> the incident is a far-fetched imaginary narrative of the<lb/> Prosecution considering the improbabilities and the anomalies<lb/> that are nestled in the Prosecution case. While walking this<lb/> Court through the evidence of the Prosecution witnesses, it was<lb/> submitted that there are apparent contradictions in the evidence<lb/> of P.W.1 and P.W.2, as found in their statements under Section<lb/> 164 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (for short,<lb/> &quot;Cr.P.C.&quot;) and their evidence before the Court. That, the<lb/> consistent stand of the Prosecution has been that P.W.1 and<lb/> P.W.2 after the incident on 07-12-2006 spent the night in the<lb/> house of P.W.10 and on the next date, they left for<lb/> Jorethang, where they spent the night in the Jorethang Car<lb/> Parking Plaza area. Contrarily, the evidence of P.W.7, a driver<lb/> and relative of P.W.2 is to the effect that on 08-12-2016 after<lb/> his duty was over, he found P.W.1 and P.W.2 in the Parking area<lb/> and took them to his home, thereby demolishing the Prosecution<lb/> stand of the two girls having spent the night at the parking lot,<lb/> by their own witness. That apart, it is the evidence of P.W.1 and<lb/> P.W.2 that P.W.3 their school friend had requested them to drop<lb/> her home, which is in contradiction to the evidence of P.W.3 who<lb/> stated that P.W.1 and P.W.2 desired to reach her to her home<lb/> and she was unaware of their whereabouts after they reached<lb/> her village.<lb/> That, her evidence nowhere reveals that they<lb/> reached her home. The next glaring anomaly that arises is that<lb/> in Exhibit 7, the original FIR lodged by P.W.4 and P.W.5 the time<lb/> MEENAKSHI<lb/> MADAN RAI<lb/> Digitally signed by<lb/> MEENAKSHI MADAN RAI<lb/> Date: 2020.08.25<lb/> 11:51:10 +05&apos;30&apos;<lb/> Sangam Rai and Another vs. State of Sikkim<lb/> of offence is mentioned at &quot;1300 hours&quot;, the formal FIR, Exhibit<lb/> 8, reveals that the incident occurred at around 2 p.m., while the<lb/> girls by their evidence seek to convince the Court that the<lb/> incident took place late in the evening when it was dark by<lb/> stating that they managed to escape from the clutches of the<lb/> Appellants when the headlights of passing vehicles focused on<lb/> the place of incident. That, the falsity in their evidence is<lb/> apparent as in their statements under Section 164 Cr.P.C. they<lb/> have nowhere stated that the incident took place in the late<lb/> evening or for that matter when it was dark, but that it was 3.30<lb/> p.m. It is pertinent to note that P.W.1 makes no mention of any<lb/> vehicle lights in her statement under Section 164 Cr.P.C. and<lb/> stated that the incident took place at 3.30 p.m. P.W.2 in her<lb/> Section 164 Cr.P.C. statement lends support to the statement of<lb/> P.W.1 that the incident took place at 3.30 p.m., but P.W.2 in<lb/> Court stated that the incident pertained to 5.30 p.m. of the<lb/> relevant day. The further evidence of P.W.1 and P.W.2 is to the<lb/> effect that after the incident they wanted to report the matter at<lb/> the Sumbuk Police Out Post (O.P.), but no Police personnel was<lb/> present at the Sumbuk O.P. However, the Investigating Officer<lb/> (I.O.) P.W.23 has deposed that every Police O.P. is manned by<lb/> Police personnel at any given point of time, rendering false the<lb/> statement of P.W.1 and P.W.2. That, P.W.4 and P.W.5 the<lb/> fathers of the two girls have stated that they went missing from<lb/> 07-12-2016, but P.W.1 and P.W.2 did not inform their respective<lb/> fathers of their whereabouts after they were allegedly molested,<lb/> which casts a doubt on the veracity of the two girls&quot; evidence.<lb/></p>

			<p>MEENAKSHI<lb/> MADAN RAI<lb/> Digitally signed by MEENAKSHI<lb/> MADAN RAI<lb/> Date: 2020.08.25 11:51:58 +05&apos;30&apos;<lb/> Sangam Rai and Another vs. State of Sikkim<lb/> That, the contradictory evidence on record and the statement of<lb/> the Appellants in their examinations under Section 313 Cr.P.C.<lb/> reveals that the two girls were caught smoking at the place of<lb/> the alleged incident by the Appellants and to ward off the<lb/> consequences of their unexpected behaviour they have foisted a<lb/> false case against the Appellants which is borne out by the<lb/> contradictory and inconsistent evidence on record. That, there<lb/> seemingly was a verbal altercation between P.W.1 and P.W.2 on<lb/> one side and the two Appellants and a Child in conflict with Law<lb/> (for short, &quot;CICL&quot;) on the other, but there is no evidence<lb/> whatsoever of any physical scuffle that the Appellants resorted<lb/> to nor is it borne out by the medical examination of P.W.1 and<lb/> P.W.2 whereby no injuries were detected on them. That, the<lb/> Learned Trial Court failed to take into consideration the cross-<lb/>examination of the P.W.1 and P.W.2 or any of the Prosecution<lb/> witnesses which in fact demolished the Prosecution case and<lb/> hence the Learned Trial Court was in error in convicting and<lb/> sentencing the Appellants, who thereby deserve an acquittal. To<lb/> fortify his submissions, Learned Counsel placed reliance on Lal<lb/> Bahadur Kami vs. The State of Sikkim 1 , Binod Sanyasi vs. State of<lb/> Sikkim<lb/> 2 and Deepan Darjee vs. State of Sikkim 3 .<lb/></p>

			<p>3.<lb/> For his part Learned Additional Public Prosecutor<lb/> while making strenuous efforts to support the Prosecution case<lb/> fairly admitted that anomalies existed in the Prosecution case<lb/> with regard to the time of the offence which was reflected in<lb/> 1 2017 SCC OnLine Sikk 173 : 2018 Cri.L.J. 439<lb/> 2 2019 SCc OnLine Sikk 111<lb/> 3 2019 SCC OnLine Sikkim 130<lb/> MEENAKSHI<lb/> MADAN RAI<lb/> Digitally signed by<lb/> MEENAKSHI MADAN RAI<lb/> Date: 2020.08.25 11:52:41<lb/> +05&apos;30&apos;<lb/> Sangam Rai and Another vs. State of Sikkim<lb/> Exhibit 7, Exhibit 8 and the deposition of P.W.2 who stated that<lb/> it was 5.30 p.m. That, these anomalies are trivial and deserve<lb/> to be ignored. That, it is now settled law that undue importance<lb/> should not be attached to the minor anomalies which exist in<lb/> the Prosecution case, by the Court, if they do not substantially<lb/> affect the Prosecution case. It is clear that the incident indeed<lb/> occurred during the evening around 5.30 p.m., as per P.W.1<lb/> and P.W.2 and the vehicles passing by the place of incident had<lb/> their head lights on which deterred the Appellants from<lb/> continuing with their misdemeanour. That, the evidence of the<lb/> Doctor also corroborates the evidence of P.W.1 and P.W.2 with<lb/> regard to the molestation perpetrated on them by the<lb/> Appellants, as during their medical examination they have<lb/> informed the Doctor that they were sexually assaulted by the<lb/> Appellants. That, mere absence of physical injuries on the two<lb/> girls is no ground for disbelieving them. That, they were<lb/> traumatized by the incident and being ashamed and afraid of<lb/> narrating the incident to their parents instead of returning home<lb/> they went to Jorethang. It was further contended that due to<lb/> the trauma the two girls continued to remain out of their house<lb/> till the morning of 10-12-2016. On being found by P.W.7 on 08-<lb/>12-2016, they were able to tell him of the incident and call their<lb/> parents to Jorethang on 10-12-2016. Hence, the Appellants are<lb/> guilty as found by the Learned Trial Court and the Judgment<lb/> and Order on Sentence suffers from no infirmities.<lb/></p>

			<p>4.<lb/> I have considered the rival contentions of Learned<lb/> Counsel, perused all documents on record as also the evidence<lb/> MEENAKSHI<lb/> MADAN RAI<lb/> Digitally signed by<lb/> MEENAKSHI MADAN RAI<lb/> Date: 2020.08.25 11:53:32<lb/> +05&apos;30&apos;<lb/> Sangam Rai and Another vs. State of Sikkim<lb/> and the impugned Judgment and Order on Sentence. I have<lb/> also perused the citations made at the Bar.<lb/></p>

			<p>5.<lb/> The question for consideration before this Court is<lb/> whether the evidence on record suffices to convict the Appellants<lb/> of the offences charged with.<lb/></p>

			<p>6.<lb/> Before delving into the merits of the matter, I<lb/> advert briefly to the facts of the Prosecution case.<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> On 11-12-2016, at around 1310 hours, a written report<lb/> was received from P.W.4 father of P.W.2 and P.W.5 father of the<lb/> victim P.W.1, to the effect that in the afternoon of 07-12-2016<lb/> their children P.W.1 and P.W.2 had gone to reach P.W.3 to her<lb/> residence. On their way home, they came across the two<lb/> Appellants and a minor boy (CICL) near the View Point (place of<lb/> occurrence). The trio obstructed the path of the minor girls and<lb/> touched them inappropriately on various parts of their body<lb/> including their genitals, while also attempting to undress<lb/> them. The FIR, Exhibit 7 came to be lodged and registered on<lb/> the same date. It was endorsed to the I.O. P.W.23 for<lb/> investigation, on completion of which Charge-Sheet came to be<lb/> filed against the Appellants and the CICL, under Sections 341,<lb/> 354 and 34 of the IPC, read with Section 8 of the Protection of<lb/> Children from Sexual Offences Act, 2012 (for short, POCSO Act,<lb/> 2012).<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii)<lb/> For clarity, it is essential to mention here that in the<lb/> instant matter P.W.1 is the victim having been allegedly<lb/> molested by the two Appellants herein. P.W.2 was the victim of<lb/> MEENAKSHI<lb/> MADAN RAI<lb/> Digitally signed by<lb/> MEENAKSHI MADAN RAI<lb/> Date: 2020.08.25<lb/> 11:54:16 +05&apos;30&apos;<lb/> Sangam Rai and Another vs. State of Sikkim<lb/> molestation by the CICL whose trial was segregated and taken<lb/> up before the Juvenile Justice Board.<lb/></p>

			<p>(iii)<lb/> The Learned Trial Court framed Charge against the<lb/> Appellants under Section 341/34, Section 354B/34 and Section<lb/> 354/34 of the IPC, read with Section 8 of the POCSO Act,<lb/> 2012. Both the Appellants entered a plea of &quot;not guilty&quot; and<lb/> claimed trial, the Prosecution therefore examined 24 (twenty-<lb/>four) witnesses in a bid to establish their case, on closure of<lb/> which both Appellants were examined under Section 313 of the<lb/> Cr.P.C., followed by final arguments of the parties. The Learned<lb/> Trial Court on consideration of the evidence on record<lb/> pronounced the impugned Judgment and Order on Sentence.<lb/></p>

			<p>7.<lb/> Pausing here for a moment it is relevant to point out<lb/> that the Prosecution case inter alia was that the victim P.W.1<lb/> was a minor, aged about 14 years at the time of the incident.<lb/> The Learned Trial Court was not inclined to consider this ground<lb/> as no original Birth Certificate of P.W.1 was furnished to buttress<lb/> this contention. All that the Prosecution succeeded in offering<lb/> was a photocopy of the document, which the Court disregarded<lb/> as being inadequate evidence. On this count, the Court also<lb/> disbelieved the evidence of P.W.18, the Doctor posted as the<lb/> Chief Medical Officer, South Sikkim, at the relevant time, as he<lb/> failed to produce the Birth Certificate Register allegedly<lb/> containing entries of the date of birth of the victim.<lb/> Consequently both Appellants were acquitted of the offence<lb/> under Section 8 of the POCSO Act, 2012 read with Section 34 of<lb/> MEENAKSHI<lb/> MADAN RAI<lb/> Digitally signed by<lb/> MEENAKSHI MADAN RAI<lb/> Date: 2020.08.25<lb/> 11:55:05 +05&apos;30&apos;<lb/> Sangam Rai and Another vs. State of Sikkim<lb/> the IPC. This finding of the Learned Trial Court is unassailed by<lb/> the Prosecution, hence discussions thereof stand truncated here.<lb/></p>

			<p>8.<lb/> The conviction of the Appellants is based on the<lb/> testimony of P.W.1 and P.W.2. As a general Rule Courts can act<lb/> even on the testimony of a sole witness provided her evidence is<lb/> wholly reliable, cogent and consistent. In the impugned<lb/> Judgment the Learned Trial Court has summed up the<lb/> Prosecution case in two short Paragraphs being Paragraph 67<lb/> and Paragraph 70 which reads as follows;<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;67. It is admitted fact that there are minor<lb/> contradiction in the statements of PW-1 and PW-2<lb/> but it is settled legal proposition that while<lb/> appreciating the evidence of a witness, minor<lb/> discrepancies on trivial matters, which do not affect<lb/> the core of the prosecution case, may not prompt<lb/> the court to reject the evidence in its entirely.<lb/> ………………………………………………………………………<lb/></item>

			<item>70.<lb/> The case in hand the evidence of PW-<lb/>1(victim) and PW-2 clearly proved that both the<lb/> accused persons with their common intention<lb/> restrained the victim(PW-1) to go out of the said<lb/> chautara(resting shed) by holding her hand and<lb/> pulled down. Both the accused persons thereafter<lb/> touched all over her body including her breast with<lb/> sexual intent. They also pushed the victim on the<lb/> ground and got on top of her and also fondled her<lb/> body.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>9.<lb/> From a reading of the above Paragraphs, it concludes<lb/> that neither the cross-examination of P.W.1 and P.W.2 have<lb/> been considered by the Learned Trial Court nor have the<lb/> evidence of the other witnesses found place in the discussions<lb/> which ensued in the impugned Judgment although the evidence<lb/> of the Prosecution witnesses have been widely reproduced earlier<lb/> on in the Judgment.<lb/> MEENAKSHI<lb/> MADAN RAI<lb/> Digitally signed by<lb/> MEENAKSHI MADAN RAI<lb/> Date: 2020.08.25<lb/> 11:55:48 +05&apos;30&apos;<lb/> indeed held that minor contradictions and discrepancies are to<lb/> be disregarded by the Courts for the reason that mental<lb/> capabilities of a human being cannot be expected to be attuned<lb/> to absorb all the details and that minor discrepancies are bound<lb/> to occur. At the same time we must not lose sight of the caution<lb/> spelled out in the same Judgment which requires the Courts to<lb/> exercise care and caution and sift the truth from the<lb/> untruth, examine whether there are exaggerations and<lb/> improvements. On the anvil of this discretion vested on the<lb/> Courts, I proceed to examine the evidence of the Prosecution<lb/> witnesses.<lb/></p>

			<p>11.<lb/> On careful consideration of the evidence on record,<lb/> it is indeed clear that there are anomalies in the evidence of the<lb/> Prosecution witnesses. The FIR, Exhibit 7, lodged by P.W.4 and<lb/> P.W.5, dated 11-12-2016, reveals that the incident alleged took<lb/> place on 07-12-2016. As per the FIR, P.W.1 and P.W.2 reached<lb/> the place of incident at around 1300 hours after dropping off<lb/> their school friend to her house. When they reached the place<lb/> of incident they found the Appellants and the CICL there, after<lb/> which the alleged incident took place. While the Appellant No.1<lb/> and the CICL were known to both P.W.1 and P.W.2 being their<lb/> co-villagers, the Appellant No.2 was not known to them. It is<lb/> evident that, as per the FIR Exhibit 7, the time of occurrence of<lb/> the incident is said to be &quot;1300 hours&quot;, while Exhibit 8 the<lb/> 4 Criminal Appeal no.660 of 2008 : (2010) 8 SCC 191<lb/> MEENAKSHI<lb/> MADAN RAI<lb/> Digitally signed by MEENAKSHI<lb/> MADAN RAI<lb/> Date: 2020.08.25 11:56:33 +05&apos;30&apos;<lb/> Sangam Rai and Another vs. State of Sikkim<lb/> formal FIR records the time of incident as &quot;1400 hours&quot;. The<lb/> evidence of P.W.1, under cross-examination, is to the effect<lb/> that the incident occurred during the &quot;day light&quot; (sic), her<lb/> deposition was recorded by the Court on 18-08-2017. P.W.2<lb/> came to be examined on 18-09-2017 and evidently made an<lb/> effort to improve the Prosecution case by stating that it was<lb/> around 5.30 p.m. when they reached the place of incident after<lb/> dropping P.W.3 at her residence. P.W.23, the I.O. in his<lb/> evidence has not revealed the time of the incident. Reverting<lb/> back to the evidence of P.W.1 she has stated that &quot;Due to the<lb/> focus light (sic) of the second vehicle the two accused persons<lb/> could not do any further indecent act upon me and I and my<lb/> junior friend ran away from the chowtara.&quot; and admitted under<lb/> cross-examination that the meaning of the word &quot;focus light&quot; of<lb/> the vehicle means the lights coming from the headlights of the<lb/> vehicle. In the same breath, she admitted that the alleged<lb/> incident occurred during the day time. P.W.2 has, as already<lb/> stated, said that the incident took place around 5.30 p.m., but<lb/> admits that the incident occurred during the day time. In other<lb/> words, it emerges from their evidence that it was daytime when<lb/> the incident occurred. If the evidence of P.W.1 that the vehicles<lb/> which passed by had their headlights on is to be believed, then,<lb/> it would appear that it was dark and the lights of the vehicles<lb/> had been turned on, but the evidence of both the girls contrarily<lb/> indicate that the incident took place during the daytime. It is<lb/> pertinent to note that P.W.1 makes no mention of any vehicle<lb/> lights in her statement under Section 164 Cr.P.C. and both<lb/> MEENAKSHI<lb/> MADAN RAI<lb/> Digitally by<lb/> MEENAKSHI MADAN RAI<lb/> Date: 2020.08.25 11:57:12<lb/> +05&apos;30&apos;<lb/> Sangam Rai and Another vs. State of Sikkim<lb/> P.W.1 and P.W.2 stated that the incident took place at 3.30<lb/> p.m., but digressing from this statement P.W.2 in Court stated<lb/> that the incident pertained to 5.30 p.m. of the relevant day.<lb/> P.W.1 speaks of two passing vehicles, P.W.2 refers to three.<lb/> While it is necessary to bear in mind that a statement recorded<lb/> under Section 164 Cr.P.C. can never be used as substantive<lb/> evidence, but it can be used both for contradiction and<lb/> corroboration of a witness who made it. Both P.W.1 and P.W.2<lb/> were confronted with their statements made under Section 164<lb/> Cr.P.C. during cross-examination and the contradictory evidence<lb/> that emerged were none too flattering for the Prosecution case<lb/> and did little to enhance the confidence of this Court in the<lb/> witnesses&quot; persistent inconsistent stands. In the light of this<lb/> anomalous evidence before the Court, it is not for the Court to<lb/> draw assumptions of the time of the incident. It is the bounden<lb/> duty of the Prosecution to convince the Court by leading<lb/> unfaltering evidence of the time of the incident, which then has<lb/> to be established beyond a reasonable doubt. These<lb/> requirements are sadly lacking in the Prosecution case.<lb/></p>

			<p>12.<lb/> Both P.W.1 and P.W.2 in their evidence have stated<lb/> that on the following day, i.e., 08-12-2016, after having spent<lb/> the night of 07-12-2016 in the house of P.W.10, they went to<lb/> Jorethang. Thereafter, on 09-12-2016 they verbally reported<lb/> the incident to Jorethang Police Station. It is their unequivocal<lb/> statement that P.W.7 accompanied them to the Police Station.<lb/> Surprisingly their statements find no substantiation either in the<lb/> evidence of P.W.7 or P.W.23. In fact, if their deposition is taken<lb/> MEENAKSHI<lb/> MADAN RAI<lb/> Digitally signed by<lb/> MEENAKSHI MADAN RAI<lb/> Date: 2020.08.25<lb/> 11:57:50 +05&apos;30&apos;<lb/> Sangam Rai and Another vs. State of Sikkim<lb/> to be the truth, then it would cast an aspersion on the Police<lb/> personnel manning the Jorethang Police Station on 09-12-2016<lb/> as it could be presumed that they had failed to comply with the<lb/> provisions of Section 154 of the Cr.P.C., which mandates that<lb/> every information relating to the commission of a cognizable<lb/> offence, if given orally to an officer in charge of a police station,<lb/> shall be reduced to writing by him or under his direction, and be<lb/> read over to the informant, and every such information,<lb/> whether given in writing or reduced to writing as aforesaid, shall<lb/> be signed by the person giving it, and the substance thereof<lb/> shall be entered in a book to be kept by such officer in such<lb/> form as the State Government may prescribe in this behalf.<lb/> However, in my considered opinion, the evidence of P.W.1 and<lb/> P.W.2 on this aspect is unbelievable and inspires no confidence<lb/> as neither have they stated the time at which they went to the<lb/> Police Station nor have they stated as to who they gave the<lb/> information to. In contrast, P.W.7 states that the two girls after<lb/> spending the night, i.e., on 08-12-2016, in his house, told him<lb/> that they had come to Jorethang in connection with a School<lb/> Project and spent the next night, i.e., 09-12-2016, also in his<lb/> house informing him that their School Project was not yet<lb/> completed. P.W.1 in her evidence stated that they did not<lb/> inform P.W.7 of the incident. If that be so, the statement that<lb/> P.W.7 accompanied them to the Police Station is incorrect and<lb/> contradictory. The evidence of P.W.7 nowhere reveals that he<lb/> had accompanied P.W.1 and P.W.2 to the Jorethang Police<lb/> Station on 09-12-2016 and is evidently a false statement made<lb/> MEENAKSHI<lb/> MADAN RAI<lb/> Digitally signed by<lb/> MEENAKSHI MADAN RAI<lb/> Date: 2020.08.25 11:58:36<lb/> +05&apos;30&apos;<lb/> by the two girls.<lb/> At no point of time between 08-12-2016 and<lb/> the morning of 10-12-2016, when P.W.7 took them to the taxi<lb/> stand in order to send them to their village, did they ever inform<lb/> him of the alleged incident nor did they inform him that on 09-<lb/>12-2016, they had verbally reported the incident at the<lb/> Jorethang Police Station. It is admitted by both P.W.1 and<lb/> P.W.2 under cross-examination that they did not inform P.W.7<lb/> of the incident during their stay in his house. It may relevantly<lb/> be remarked here that, as per P.W.10, P.W.1 and P.W.2<lb/> informed her of the incident of molestation, but described the<lb/> place of occurrence as near a &quot;Mandir&quot;, while P.W.1 under cross-<lb/>examination admitted having narrated to P.W.10 about the<lb/> incident, however P.W.2 denied having told P.W.10 of the<lb/> incident. P.W.23 for his part supported the evidence of P.W.10<lb/> and P.W.1 pertaining to narration of the incident. This also<lb/> points to the inconsistencies in the Prosecution case. P.W.10<lb/> has stated that the two girls arrived at her house at about 09.30<lb/> p.m. on 07-12-2016 after the alleged incident. P.W.1 and<lb/> P.W.2 have not thrown any light on their whereabouts in the<lb/> intervening hours between 2 p.m. and 09.30 p.m. Even<lb/> assuming that the incident took place at 5.30 p.m., their<lb/> whereabouts between 5.30 p.m. and 9.30 p.m. has neither been<lb/> divulged by P.W.1 and P.W.2 nor does investigation shed any<lb/> light on this aspect nor has P.W.23 made any statement in this<lb/> regard.<lb/></p>

			<p>13.<lb/> The next point that rears its head for consideration<lb/> is the stand taken by the I.O. that the two girls had spent the<lb/> MEENAKSHI<lb/> MADAN RAI<lb/> Digitally signed by<lb/> MEENAKSHI MADAN RAI<lb/> Date: 2020.08.25<lb/> 11:59:20 +05&apos;30&apos;<lb/> Sangam Rai and Another vs. State of Sikkim<lb/> night of 08-12-2016 at the Jorethang Parking Plaza. However,<lb/> P.W.1 and P.W.2 have not stated in their evidence in Court that<lb/> they spent the night at the Parking Plaza. Hence, it emerges<lb/> that there is no evidence to establish that they had spent the<lb/> night at Jorethang Car Plaza as sought to be made out by<lb/> P.W.23. P.W.1 herself has stated that at Jorethang they first<lb/> went to the Plaza where P.W.2 met her brother P.W.7, who took<lb/> them to his house. P.W.2 has also denied having stated<lb/> anything in her Section 164 Cr.P.C. statement about having<lb/> spent a night in the Jorethang Car Plaza as, according to her, it<lb/> would be a false statement.<lb/></p>

			<p>14.<lb/> Now, the question of which of the Appellants<lb/> assaulted which of the two girls also appears rather<lb/> nebulous since it is in the evidence of P.W.1 that both the<lb/> Appellants herein assaulted her, while P.W.2 was assaulted by<lb/> the CICL. The evidence of P.W.15, the Medical Officer who<lb/> examined them contrarily states that both P.W.1 and P.W.2<lb/> alleged molestation on each of them, by the two Appellants and<lb/> the CICL, thereby leading to doubts about the perpetrators of<lb/> the alleged offence.<lb/> That apart, the other contradictory<lb/> evidence on record is that while P.W.1 and P.W.2 insist that<lb/> P.W.3 had requested them to drop her home after school, P.W.3<lb/> denies this circumstance and has stated that they volunteered<lb/> to reach her home. That, they are not even her friends, but<lb/> only her schoolmates. The evidence on P.W.3 also reveals that<lb/> she parted ways with P.W.1 and P.W.2 on reaching her village,<lb/> therefore their claim of reaching P.W.3 to her house is evidently<lb/> MEENAKSHI<lb/> MADAN RAI<lb/> Digitally signed by<lb/> MEENAKSHI MADAN RAI<lb/> Date: 2020.08.25 12:00:06<lb/> +05&apos;30&apos;<lb/> Sangam Rai and Another vs. State of Sikkim<lb/> a false statement. The evidence of P.W.6, P.W.7 and P.W.10<lb/> reveals that both the alleged girls showed no inclination of<lb/> contacting their parents between 07-12-2016 and 09-12-2016.<lb/> P.W.6 had met both the alleged girls in Jorethang but, according<lb/> to him, they did not make any effort to communicate anything<lb/> to him. P.W.7 the cousin of P.W.2 testified that even after P.W.1<lb/> and P.W.2 spent two nights in his home they did not express<lb/> any desire to contact their family members either over<lb/> telephone or cell phones. P.W.10 would depose that she and<lb/> her parents own mobile phones but both P.W.1 and P.W.2 did<lb/> not express any desire to contact their parents or inform them<lb/> of the incident. The evidence of P.W.10 leads one to wonder<lb/> why the two alleged girls opted to spend the night at her house<lb/> as she has stated that the houses of the two girls were closer to<lb/> their school than her house. P.W.23 has also lent credence to<lb/> this evidence by stating that the houses of the alleged girls is<lb/> about fifteen minutes walking distance from their school, while<lb/> that of P.W.10 is about 40 to 50 minutes. According to the I.O.,<lb/> they did not go home as they were traumatised by the incident.<lb/> The evidence of both PW 1 and 2 nowhere reveals that they<lb/> were traumatised by the incident. It appears to be a figment of<lb/> the imagination of the I.O. considering that P.W.11 the mother<lb/> of P.W.1 has deposed that her daughter confides in her. The<lb/> question of P.W.1 being unable to confide in her mother about<lb/> the incident due to fear and shame is demolished by the<lb/> statement of P.W.11. P.W.11 has also brought to light before<lb/> this Court the conduct of the two girls by stating that after the<lb/> MEENAKSHI<lb/> MADAN RAI<lb/> Digitally signed by<lb/> MEENAKSHI MADAN RAI<lb/> Date: 2020.08.25 12:00:51<lb/> +05&apos;30&apos;<lb/> Sangam Rai and Another vs. State of Sikkim<lb/> instant incident both of them had been kept in the custody of an<lb/> NGO from where they made good their escape. In the light of<lb/> the evidence that the Prosecution has furnished I find that the<lb/> statement of P.W.1 and P.W.2 pertaining to their intention of<lb/> lodging a complaint before the Sumbuk O.P. on 07-12-2016 is<lb/> completely unreliable. Besides, the I.O. P.W.23 has testified<lb/> that the Police O.P. is manned round the clock by Police<lb/> personnel.<lb/></p>

			<p>15.<lb/> In the circumstances, after careful consideration of<lb/> the entire evidence on record, contrary to the submissions of<lb/> the Learned Additional Public Prosecutor that the anomalies in<lb/> the Prosecution case are trivial and ought to be ignored, I find<lb/> that it strikes at the root of the Prosecution case. P.W.1 and<lb/> P.W.2 failed to return home on 07-12-2016 for reasons best<lb/> known to them. It may be true that they encountered the<lb/> Appellants and the CICL at the place of incident which gave<lb/> them an excuse to spin a yarn about an evidently non-existent<lb/> incident. I am of the considered opinion that there is no<lb/> evidence whatsoever against the Appellants under the charges<lb/> framed against them. The Learned Trial Court for its part failed<lb/> to take into consideration the cross-examination of P.W.1 and<lb/> P.W.2 which demolishes the Prosecution case. The evidence of<lb/> P.W.3, P.W.6, P.W.7, P.W.10, P.W.11, P.W.15, have also not<lb/> been considered at all by the Learned Trial Court as appears<lb/> from the discussions which have ensued in the impugned<lb/> Judgment, although their evidence, as already noticed, has been<lb/> reproduced extensively earlier on in the impugned Judgment.<lb/></p>

			<p>MEENAKSHI<lb/> MADAN RAI<lb/> Digitally signed by<lb/> MADAN RAI<lb/> Date: 2020.08.25 12:01:35 +05&apos;30&apos;<lb/> Sangam Rai and Another vs. State of Sikkim<lb/> Hence, basing a conviction on the tremulous foundation of the<lb/> inconsistent, uncorroborated and capricious evidence of P.W.1<lb/> and P.W.2 would deprive the Appellants of one fruitful year each<lb/> of their lives. The Prosecution has failed by the evidence<lb/> furnished, to establish its case beyond a reasonable doubt<lb/> against the Appellants and the Learned Trial Court was in error<lb/> in convicting and sentencing the Appellants.<lb/></p>

			<p>16.<lb/> Consequently, Appeal is allowed.<lb/></p>

			<p>17.<lb/> The conviction and sentence imposed on the<lb/> Appellants vide the impugned Judgment and Order on Sentence<lb/> of the Learned Trial Court are set aside.<lb/></p>

			<p>18.<lb/> The Appellants No.1 and 2 are acquitted of the<lb/> offence charged with, i.e., under Section 341/34 and Section<lb/> 354/34 of the IPC.<lb/></p>

			<p>19.<lb/> Both Appellants No.1 and 2 are on bail vide Order of<lb/> this Court, dated 27-08-2019, in I.A. No.01 of 2019. They are<lb/> discharged from their bail bonds.<lb/></p>

			<p>20.<lb/> Fine, if any, deposited by the Appellants in terms of<lb/> the impugned Order on Sentence, be reimbursed to them.<lb/></p>

			<p>21.<lb/> No order as to costs.<lb/></p>

			<p>22.<lb/> Copy of this Judgment be forwarded forthwith to the<lb/> Learned Trial Court for information and compliance.<lb/></p>

			<p>( Meenakshi Madan Rai )<lb/> Judge<lb/> 25-08-2020<lb/> ds<lb/> Approved for reporting : Yes<lb/> MEENAKSHI<lb/> MADAN RAI<lb/> Digitally signed by<lb/> MEENAKSHI MADAN RAI<lb/> Date: 2020.08.25 12:02:23<lb/> +05&apos;30&apos;</p>


	</text>
</tei>
