<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1. <lb/>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>THE HIGH COURT OF SIKKIM: GANGTOK <lb/>(Criminal Appeal Jurisdiction) <lb/>-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------<lb/>D.B.: THE HON&apos;BLE MRS. JUSTICE MEENAKSHI MADAN RAI, JUDGE <lb/>THE HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE BHASKAR RAJ PRADHAN, JUDGE. <lb/>-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------<lb/>Crl. A. No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim <lb/>.… Appellant <lb/>versus <lb/>Suren Rai, <lb/>S/o Shri Dhan Bahadur Rai, <lb/>R/o Near Karmatar Junior High School, <lb/>Darjeeling -West Bengal. <lb/>…. Respondent <lb/>-----------------------------------------------------------------------------<lb/>An Appeal under Section 378 Criminal Procedure Code, <lb/>1973. <lb/>Appearance: <lb/>Mr. Karma Thinlay and Mr. Thinlay Dorjee Bhutia <lb/>Addl. Public Prosecutors with Mr. S.K Chettri and <lb/>Ms. Pollin Rai, Asstt. Public Prosecutors for the <lb/>Appellant. <lb/>Mr. B. Sharma, Senior Advocate with Mr. Sajal <lb/>Sharma, Advocate for the Respondent. <lb/>-----------------------------------------------------------------------------<lb/>JUDGMENT <lb/>(04.06.2018) <lb/>Bhaskar Raj Pradhan, J <lb/>1. <lb/>The death is homicidal. It is also gruesome. Multiple and <lb/>gaping chop wounds on the back of the neck, below the skull <lb/>with a sharp, moderately heavy weapon have done away with a <lb/>young human life of barely 27 years in the prime of his youth. <lb/>The heinous act was committed inside a temporary shed in the <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>compound of one Padam Kumar Rai (P.W.5) in which the <lb/>deceased and Suren Rai (Respondent), another &quot;lumberjack&quot;, <lb/>hired by him were residing till the night of the incident. The <lb/>evidence of the brutal act is smeared all over the temporary <lb/>shed. Dark coloured round collared &apos;T&apos; shirt of the deceased <lb/>with cuts over the neck and the right side of shoulder stained <lb/>with blood and more at the back and aluminium GIS sheet <lb/>walls of the temporary shed with a spray of blood. There is no <lb/>quarrel about the aforesaid facts and also stands proved by <lb/>cogent evidence. <lb/>2. <lb/>The day before the incident, past sunset, at around 8.00 <lb/>p.m. on 23.05.2013, the version of the altercation between <lb/>Suren Rai and the deceased regarding the deceased&apos;s mobile <lb/>which had gone missing would be complained about by Suren <lb/>Rai to Padam Kumar Rai. This was at the house of Padam <lb/>Kumar Rai, a little distance from the temporary shed, but <lb/>within his compound, where the gruesome act would take <lb/>place. As requested, Padam Kumar Rai would, a little later <lb/>after 8.00 p.m., visit the temporary shed and find Suren Rai <lb/>having his meal and the deceased sitting close by. Padam <lb/>Kumar Rai would inquire about the mobile and admonition <lb/>both Suren Rai and the deceased not to quarrel about trifles <lb/>and look for the mobile instead. Padam Kumar Rai would <lb/>return to his house. Suren Rai would shortly follow. Padam <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>Kumar Rai would again ask Suren Rai if the mobile was found. <lb/>Suren Rai would, thereafter, leave Padam Kumar Rai&apos;s house. <lb/>Thereafter, Padam Kumar Rai would retire to bed as it would <lb/>be raining heavily. There is also no dispute about the aforesaid <lb/>facts which also stands proved by cogent evidence. Padam <lb/>Kumar Rai would depose and prove these facts and is <lb/>admitted by Suren Rai. <lb/>3. <lb/>What happened thereafter till the next morning is <lb/>unknown, save the disclosure and the confessional statement <lb/>of Suren Rai recorded under Section 27 of the Indian Evidence <lb/>Act, 1872 and Section 164 of the Code of Criminal Procedure <lb/>(Cr.P.C.) respectively and the last scene theory pressed by the <lb/>Prosecution, it is pleaded. <lb/>4. <lb/>The next morning at around 6.00 a.m. on 24.05.2013, <lb/>much after the first rays of the sun would illuminate <lb/>Okherbotey, Padam Kumar Rai would notice something <lb/>unusual. Smoke was not coming out of the temporary shed as <lb/>usual. He would find it curious and walk to the temporary <lb/>shed from his house to discover the cadaver of the deceased in <lb/>a sleeping position covered with a blanket and the tell-tale <lb/>signs of the gruesome act smeared all over. These facts also <lb/>stand proved by the evidence of Padam Kumar Rai. <lb/>5. <lb/>At 8.45 a.m., the same morning, a written complaint <lb/>(exhibit-12) by Padam Kumar Rai received by the Naya Bazar <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>Police Station in West Sikkim would lead to the registration of <lb/>the First Information Report (FIR) (exhibit-13) and set in <lb/>motion the investigation taken up by Police Inspector, Mr. <lb/>Chewang D. Bhutia, Investigating Officer (P.W.10) alleging that <lb/>Suren Rai had done away with the deceased and absconded. <lb/>The same day, Suren Rai would be apprehended from <lb/>Karmatar School ground in the neighbouring State of West <lb/>Bengal by two Police Officers, Constable Topden Lepcha <lb/>(P.W.6) and Home Guard, Yamnath Sharma (P.W.7) and <lb/>brought to the Naya Bazar Police Station to face justice. These <lb/>facts also stand proved by the Prosecution. The arrest of Suren <lb/>Rai is also not an issue. <lb/>6. <lb/>The deceased was Monit Rai, the dead &quot;lumberjack&quot; and <lb/>temporary shed-mate of Suren Rai, the then accused, and now <lb/>acquitted and a free man. These facts also stands proved by <lb/>the prosecution. <lb/>7. <lb/>When the Investigating Officer would visit the crime <lb/>scene it would still be fresh with evidence, both physical and <lb/>biological, of the gruesome incident the night before. On <lb/>24.05.2013 at 1100 hours the Investigating Officer would seize <lb/>blood stained red/white/pink printed quilt; blood stained old <lb/>while &apos;T&apos; shirt with &quot;Pirelli&quot; printed on it; one pair of blood <lb/>stained old blue slipper; one pair of red blood stained slipper; <lb/>one faded black cap with &quot;Chattanooga&quot;; one light brown <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>Adidas track pant; one blue &apos;T&apos; shirt with &quot;Adventure Tour&quot; <lb/>printed on it and one light green &apos;T&apos; shirt with &quot;Angry Birds&quot; <lb/>printed on it through Property Seizure Memo (exhibit-16) in <lb/>the presence of two witnesses Bhadrey Bishwakarma (P.W.8) <lb/>and Dhiraj Rai (P.W.9). The seizures vide Property Seizure <lb/>Memo (exhibit-16) also stands proved by the Investigating <lb/>Officer and the two seizure witnesses named above. <lb/>8. <lb/>On 24.05.2013 at 1115 hours the Investigating Officer <lb/>would further seize white/green/grey old sleeping bag with <lb/>blood stain; plastic mat with blood stain (red and green); <lb/>controlled sample of blood collected from place of occurrence <lb/>in a glass container; controlled sample of mud collected from <lb/>the place of occurrence in a plastic container; one plastic <lb/>profile mat (black) with blood stain; one blood stained jute <lb/>sack with &quot;M.P.&quot; printed on it through Property Seizure Memo <lb/>(exhibit-18) from the place of occurrence in the presence of two <lb/>witnesses, Bhadrey Bishwakarma and Dhiraj Rai. The seizure <lb/>vide Property Seizure Memo (exhibit-18) would also be proved <lb/>by the Investigating Officer and the two seizure witnesses <lb/>named above. <lb/>9. <lb/>On the same day i.e 24.05.2013 at half an hour past mid <lb/>noon, the Investigating Officer would forward Suren Rai to the <lb/>Medical Officer stationed at the Jorethang-Primary Health <lb/>Center (PHC) for his medical examination. Dr. S. N. Adhikari <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>(P.W.1) would then examine him and record his observation in <lb/>the Medical Report (exhibit-1). However, in the said Medical <lb/>Report of Suren Rai, Dr. S. N. Adhikari would endorse:-<lb/>&quot;Suren Rai, 27 years s/o Dhan Bdr. Rai r/o Karmatar <lb/>(W.B.). As stated by accused, he has assaulted on Monit <lb/>Rai of same place with &apos;khukuri&apos; which leads to death of <lb/>the victim at the place of occurrence (Zoom/West <lb/>Sikkim).&quot; <lb/>10. Dr. S. N. Adhikari in his deposition before the Trial Court <lb/>however, would not expound about the extra judicial <lb/>confession recorded in the Medical Report and only state that <lb/>on examination of Suren Rai, there was no complaint or <lb/>injuries and that he was physically and mentally sound and fit <lb/>for custody. We would not be confident about the purported <lb/>extra-judicial confession because the truth of what was <lb/>scribed by Dr. S. N. Adhikari in the Medical Report would not <lb/>be brought forth in his oral testimony and it was made whilst <lb/>in custody of the police and thus clearly barred by Section 26 <lb/>of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872. <lb/>11. On 24.05.2013 at 1245 hours the Investigating Officer <lb/>would seize three wearing apparels of Suren Rai, i.e., blood <lb/>stained black &apos;T&apos; shirt with &quot;Marshall&quot; printed on it, blue faded <lb/>blood stained jeans pant with &apos;Salsa&apos; printed on the inner side <lb/>and one faded blue blood stained underwear with &quot;Jookey&quot; <lb/>written on it through property seizure memo (exhibit-19) from <lb/>Suren Rai at Naya Bazar Police Station in the presence of two <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>witnesses, Bhadrey Bishwakarma and Dhiraj Rai. The seizure <lb/>vide Property Seizure Memo (exhibit-19) would be proved by <lb/>the Investigating Officer and the two seizure witnesses named <lb/>above. The Investigating Officer would specifically depose that <lb/>the police escort party produced Suren Rai at Naya Bazar, <lb/>Police Station on 24.05.2013 at 1245 hours, after completion <lb/>of medical examination and seize the said wearing apparels <lb/>from the possession of Suren Rai. The defence wouldn&apos;t be <lb/>able to tarnish this deposition. At 1250 hours thereafter the <lb/>Investigating Officer would arrest Suren Rai at the Naya Bazar <lb/>Police Station where he would be produced by Constable <lb/>Topden Lepcha and Home Guard Yamnath Sharma. <lb/>12. It is said; Suren Rai confessed to his crime, made a <lb/>disclosure statement (exhibit-14) which would be recorded <lb/>under Section 27 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872, before the <lb/>Investigating Officer at 1255 p.m. on 24.5.2013, in the <lb/>presence of two independent witnesses and signed the same <lb/>stating that he had hidden the &quot;khukuri&quot; near Padam Kumar <lb/>Rai&apos;s residence and he could show it to the police. The <lb/>confession to the Investigating Officer and the disclosure <lb/>statement are highly contested. <lb/>13. The same May midsummer afternoon on 24.05.2013 at <lb/>1325 hours the alleged weapon of offence, an 18 inch long <lb/>&quot;khukuri&quot;, the traditional curved machete and the symbol of <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>the Nepalese/Gorkha communities&apos; valour, would also be <lb/>recovered from an open space just outside the kitchen window <lb/>within the compound of Padam Kumar Rai, unfortunately, <lb/>allegedly used for the dastardly act. The Property Seizure <lb/>Memo (exhibit-15) would be proved by the Investigating Officer <lb/>and two seizure witnesses, Bhadrey Bishwakarma and Dhiraj <lb/>Rai and the said &quot;khukuri&quot; identified by them. However, both <lb/>the said seizure witnesses would state that the alleged <lb/>&quot;khukuri&quot; was lying in an open place which could be easily <lb/>seen by everyone. The prosecution case as deposed by the <lb/>Investigating Officer that the recovery of the &quot;khukuri&quot; was <lb/>pursuant to the disclosure statement would, therefore, be <lb/>contested by the defence as being tainted. <lb/>14. On 06.06.2013 an application (exhibit-7) would be made <lb/>by the Investigating Officer to the Learned Judicial Magistrate, <lb/>West District at Gayzing (P.W.3) with a request to record the <lb/>confessional statement of Suren Rai under Section 164 Cr.P.C. <lb/>as he volunteers to depose about the facts with regard to the <lb/>case. <lb/>15. The Learned Judicial Magistrate would put preliminary <lb/>questions (exhibit-8) to Suren Rai after he was brought to the <lb/>Court on 06.06.2013 at 13.30 hours by one Krishna Bahadur <lb/>Rai from the District Jail Namchi, which was recorded and <lb/>later proved during trial, through the Learned Judicial <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>Magistrate. As many as 16 questions would be put to Suren <lb/>Rai by the Learned Judicial Magistrate. <lb/>16. The Learned Judicial Magistrate, thereafter, would give <lb/>four days time for reflection to Suren Rai informing him that <lb/>he should not mix around with the police or any other person <lb/>and accordingly would send him to jail and direct him to <lb/>appear on 10.06.2013 at 10.00 a.m. <lb/>17. Suren Rai would be produced on 10.06.2013 before the <lb/>Learned Judicial Magistrate after which he would be placed in <lb/>custody of the staff of the Learned Judicial Magistrate and the <lb/>Head Constable would be directed to leave the Court premises. <lb/>On being satisfied that there were no policemen in the Court <lb/>and chamber from where the Court could be seen or heard, <lb/>the Learned Judicial Magistrate would put six questions to <lb/>Suren Rai, record the memorandum of statement of the <lb/>accused (exhibit-9) in compliance of Section 164 Cr.P.C., <lb/>explain to Suren Rai that he was not bound to make any <lb/>statement before her, record her satisfaction that the <lb/>statement was voluntary and the fact that it was made in her <lb/>presence and thereafter record the confession of the then <lb/>accused, Suren Rai, under Section 164 Cr.P.C. on 10.06.2013 <lb/>(exhibit-10). The said confession would read as under:-<lb/>&quot;At the relevant time I was working at Zoom, West <lb/>Sikkim in the house of one Padma, I was given the job of <lb/>cutting firewood along with one Manit Rai. We both are <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>permanent residents of Karmatar, Darjeeling, West Bengal <lb/>and were at Zoom for the work. <lb/>On the relevant day, I drank some alcohol with Manit <lb/>Rai at our temporary shed at around 2100 hours at Zoom, <lb/>West Sikkim and we were little intoxicated and the said Manit <lb/>Rai went out. Around 2130 hours, while I was still at my <lb/>temporary shed, Manit Rai returned back and he had drank <lb/>more alcohol outside and started provoking me into a fight for <lb/>no reason. He also hurled a khukuri at me to kill me, however <lb/>I dodged myself from that, after which I took the khukuri from <lb/>him and stabbed him at the back of his neck thrice and <lb/>stayed there for about an hour. At the time he was still alive. <lb/>Thereafter I ran off towards Naya Bazar and the next <lb/>day at about 0830 hours, the police apprehended me.&quot; <lb/>18. The investigation of the case which would commence on <lb/>25.04.2013 would result in a final report dated 22.07.2013 <lb/>within barely three months of the incident and a Sessions trial <lb/>Case would be registered on 26.08.2013. Supplementary <lb/>charge-sheets would however, be filed only on 01.10.2015. The <lb/>first supplementary charge-sheet would relate to blood <lb/>collected in a glass container seized from the place of <lb/>occurrence on 24.05.2013 vide Property Seizure Memo <lb/>(exhibit-18), controlled sample gauge piece with blood stains of <lb/>the deceased, black hair samples having blood stains of the <lb/>deceased, black hair samples of the deceased, six black hair <lb/>strands of Suren Rai and blood sample of Suren Rai collected <lb/>vide requisition dated 06.06.2013 (exhibit-11). The evidence <lb/>collected and seized on 03.07.2013 would be sent to CFSL, <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>Kolkatta for DNA comparison and analysis and vide expert <lb/>opinion dated 03.08.2015 under the signature of Dr. Anil <lb/>Kumar Sharma, Deputy Director (Biology) and Scientist &apos;D&apos;, <lb/>from CFSL Kolkata (P.W.11) the result would be placed before <lb/>the Court. The other supplementary charge-sheet would relate <lb/>to the soil sample collected from the place of occurrence, blood <lb/>stained &quot;khukuri&quot; seized vide Property Seizure Memo (exhibit-<lb/>15), blood stained black &apos;T&apos; shirt with &quot;Marshall&quot; printed on it, <lb/>blood stained faded blue jeans pant with &quot;Salsa&quot; printed on it <lb/>and blood stained underwear with &quot;Jookey&quot; printed on it all <lb/>seized on 24.05.2013 from the possession of Suren Rai vide <lb/>Property Seizure Memo (exhibit-19). The expert opinion dated <lb/>08.09.2015 (exhibit-26) would also be placed before the Court. <lb/>The expert who gave the said opinion would be one Dr. P. Paul <lb/>Ramesh from CFSL, Kolkata. The expert would not be <lb/>examined. However, the expert opinion would be exhibited by <lb/>the Investigating Officer without a protest by the defence. <lb/>19. These seizures of the biological as well as physical <lb/>evidence and the expert opinions would reveal disturbing and <lb/>unfortunate situation. The seizures and collection of blood <lb/>samples and hair samples would take place on 24.05.2013 <lb/>and 06.06.2013. The seized evidence would be forwarded and <lb/>received by the CFSL, Kolkatta on 24.07.2013. The CFSL, <lb/>Kolkatta would keep these evidences till 17.03.2015 and <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>10.07.2015 and finally give its opinion on 29.06.2015 and <lb/>25.07.2015 during which period material evidence collected <lb/>would degrade to such an extent that the experts examining <lb/>them would not be able to decipher the evidence completely. <lb/>20. The truth of what transpired that rainy night when a <lb/>young 27 year old youth lost his life and that too by multiple <lb/>assaults below the skull and on the neck would be accessible <lb/>to the Investigating Officer within the confines of the little <lb/>temporary shed strewn with evidence which had the <lb/>propensity to narrate the gruesome story. The voiceless cry for <lb/>justice of the deceased could have been heard from the blood <lb/>soaked clothes, GIS sheets, profile mat, jute sack, slippers, <lb/>track pants and the quilt recovered and seized. An <lb/>investigative mind with a determination to do justice and seek <lb/>the truth would do so from each of these evidences. The <lb/>Investigating Officer should be mindful of what is commonly <lb/>known as &quot;Locard&apos;s Principle&quot; formulated by Dr. Edmond <lb/>Locard. Simply put it is: &quot;Every contact leaves a trace&quot;. This <lb/>principle explained means that the perpetrator of a crime will <lb/>bring something into the crime scene and leave with <lb/>something from it and that both can be used as forensic <lb/>evidence. We would believe that forensic evidence and not <lb/>limited to finger prints alone would be available at the scene of <lb/>crime, which, it is quite obvious, the perpetrator had not even <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>bothered to tamper. The scene of crime and in this case the <lb/>little temporary shed, immediately sanitized from any outside <lb/>interference, would be a place where the perpetrator would <lb/>have stepped, touched and been in physical contact with the <lb/>material objects available and therefore, rich with both <lb/>biological and physical evidence. The biological evidence like <lb/>blood and hair seen at this place of occurrence and seized are <lb/>required to be not only preserved carefully and scientifically <lb/>but also examined in right earnest to come to a definite <lb/>conclusion before time chooses to erode the evidence and fog <lb/>the vision. Those inanimate objects would have witnessed <lb/>silently the gruesome act and could serve as witnesses to the <lb/>perpetrator committing homicide. Similarly, the scene of crime <lb/>ought to be scanned for finger print and foot prints which <lb/>would obviously be available. The physical evidence would <lb/>never lie or commit perjury or forget. The Investigating <lb/>agencies human failure alone in finding it, preserving it and <lb/>studying it would allow it to remain inanimate and voiceless. <lb/>We would believe that the forensic evidence would be <lb/>decipherable with the use of scientific methods and <lb/>technology. We would desire, nay implore the State to <lb/>introduce and make available to the investigative agencies <lb/>new, updated scientific methods and technologies for forensic <lb/>examination although we are certain that we would not err <lb/>even if we were to adjure the State to do so. This was a little <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>diversion, much necessitated by the facts of this case, now <lb/>back to the facts. <lb/>21. Suren Rai would be charged for manslaughter. The trial, <lb/>however, would result in acquittal of Suren Rai. The State is <lb/>aggrieved by the Impugned Judgment dated 29.02.2016 of the <lb/>Learned Sessions Judge, West Sikkim at Gyalshing <lb/>in <lb/>Sessions Trial Case No. 06 of 2014. <lb/>22. The Appeal is therefore, against acquittal. The <lb/>presumption of innocence in favour of Suren Rai from the <lb/>lodging of the FIR till judgment day is now fortified. If the view <lb/>adopted by the Trial Court is a reasonable one in the <lb/>conclusion reached by it and had its ground well set out on <lb/>the materials on record, numerous precedents from the <lb/>Supreme Court would say-the acquittal may not be interfered <lb/>with. <lb/>23. There being no eye witness to the crime the present case <lb/>is based on circumstantial evidence. The law, to prove a case <lb/>on circumstantial evidence, is also well settled. The <lb/>circumstances from which the conclusion of the guilt is to be <lb/>drawn must be fully established. The facts so established <lb/>should be consistent only with the hypothesis of the guilt of <lb/>Suren Rai and no other. The circumstances should be of <lb/>conclusive nature and should exclude every possible <lb/>hypothesis except that it is Suren Rai and Suren Rai alone <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>who is guilty of murder. The chain of evidence must be so <lb/>complete as not to leave any reasonable ground for the <lb/>conclusion consistent with the innocence of Suren Rai and the <lb/>Court must be judicially confident that it is Suren Rai who is <lb/>guilty and the heinous act has been perpetrated by him and <lb/>none other. <lb/>24. The question, so vital, to be answered by the Trial Judge <lb/>was whether on the fateful intervening night of 23.05.2013 <lb/>and 24.05.2013 did Suren Rai assault the deceased Monit Rai <lb/>with the &quot;khukuri&quot; and murder him? <lb/>25. The solitary charge for murder was framed on <lb/>23.05.2014 and in the trial that ensued, 11 witnesses would <lb/>be examined by the prosecution. The statement of the then <lb/>accused, Suren Rai, on his examination under Section 313 <lb/>Cr.P.C. to explain the various incriminating circumstances <lb/>appearing in the evidence against him, would be conducted on <lb/>30.07.2015 and 16.02.2016 in the end of which Suren Rai <lb/>would plead innocence and state that he had not committed <lb/>the offence. Suren Rai would also resile from his confessional <lb/>statement. <lb/>26. The judgement of acquittal by the Learned Sessions <lb/>Judge is based on the Trial Courts judicial analysis on four <lb/>pivotal issues. The Learned Sessions Judge would not believe <lb/>the prosecution version of the recording of the disclosure <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>statement (exhibit-14) purportedly under Section 27 of the <lb/>Indian Evidence Act, 1872 in the presence of two witnesses <lb/>and the subsequent recovery of the alleged weapon of offence, <lb/>the &quot;khukuri&quot;, vide Property Seizure Memo (exhibit-15). The <lb/>Learned Session Judge would also not believe the last scene <lb/>theory put-forth by the prosecution. The judicial confession of <lb/>Suren Rai made before the Learned Judicial Magistrate would <lb/>be disregarded. The evidence of Padam Kumar Rai, the <lb/>employer of both the deceased and Suren Rai, the <lb/>&quot;lumberjacks&quot; and in whose compound the gruesome act was <lb/>committed would not also inspire confidence in the Learned <lb/>Sessions Judge due to which the Learned Sessions Judge <lb/>would hold the evidence of Padam Kumar Rai, Bhadrey <lb/>Bishwakarma and Dhiraj Rai &quot;totally doubtful&quot;. <lb/>27. The Learned Sessions Judge would believe the <lb/>explanation given by Suren Rai in his statement under Section <lb/>313 Cr.P.C. by which he would state that due to the <lb/>continuous harassment and threat by the deceased he had left <lb/>for Karmatar around 8.30 p.m. on 23.05.2013. <lb/>28. It was the same night that the deceased was mercilessly <lb/>hacked to death. This is well established. <lb/>29. The burden of proof so heavily set on the prosecution to <lb/>prove every ingredient of the alleged offence of murder would <lb/>be held not satisfied and the Learned Sessions Judge would <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>find that the gap between the deceased last seen alive by <lb/>Padam Kumar Rai and his finding the dead body the next <lb/>morning was so wide that the trial Court could not rule out the <lb/>possibility of a third person coming in between. A purported <lb/>confession of Suren Rai to the Investigating Officer would also <lb/>not be believed and thus Suren Rai would be held not guilty <lb/>and acquitted of the solitary charge of murder. <lb/>30. We have meticulously examined the evidences, oral and <lb/>documentary, as well as the impugned judgment. This is a <lb/>case of a brutal murder. This is also a case in which Suren Rai <lb/>has been acquitted by the trial Court. The able assistance <lb/>rendered by Mr. Karma Thinlay Namgyal, the Additional Public <lb/>Prosecutor and Mr. B. Sharma, Senior Advocate, appearing for <lb/>the Respondent are well appreciated. The various judicial <lb/>pronouncements of the Supreme Court relied upon by the <lb/>Learned Counsels have guided our judgment in the present <lb/>case. <lb/>31. The Learned Sessions Judge would hold that the death <lb/>was homicidal and proved by the medical evidence. Dr. O. T. <lb/>Lepcha, (P.W.2) the Medico Legal Specialist at the S.T.N.M. <lb/>Hospital, Gangtok has coherently and convincingly proved his <lb/>Autopsy Report (exhibit-2). <lb/>32. It was the deceased who succumbed to the multiple <lb/>wounds by a sharp, moderately heavy weapon in the <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>intervening night of 23.05.2013 and 24.05.2013 in the <lb/>temporary shed in which the deceased and Suren Rai were <lb/>residing within the premises owned by Padam Kumar Rai and <lb/>the subsequent recovery of the dead body of the deceased are <lb/>also proved by the evidence of Padam Kumar Rai, the evidence <lb/>of the Investigating Officer, inquest witnesses Bhadrey <lb/>Bishwakarma and Dhiraj Rai proving the Inquest Report <lb/>(exhibit-20) of the inquest conducted on 24.05.2013, the <lb/>evidence of Dr. O. T. Lepcha and the Autopsy Report (exhibit-<lb/>2) and the Dead Body Challan (exhibit-3) proved by Dr. O. T. <lb/>Lepcha. The FIR proved by Padam Kumar Rai corroborates the <lb/>above facts. The photographs marked (exhibit-21) (collectively) <lb/>captures and freezes the Investigating Officers first memory of <lb/>the scene of crime evidencing the heinous act upon the <lb/>deceased, when he exhibits the same during his deposition. <lb/>33. The arrest of Suren Rai from Karmatar by two Police <lb/>Officers Constable, Topden Lepcha and Home Guard, Yamnath <lb/>Sharma on 24.05.2015 would be proved by their evidence as <lb/>well as the arrest Memo (exhibit-24) proved by the <lb/>Investigating Officer. The Learned Sessions Judge would find <lb/>fault in the failure of the prosecution to examine any witness <lb/>from Karmatar or any evidence as to what time the accused <lb/>reached Karmatar. The Learned Sessions Judge would <lb/>consequently doubt the entire evidence of the prosecution <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>witnesses. Constable Topden Lepcha would depose that on <lb/>24.05.2010 at around 9.00 a.m. as per the instructions given <lb/>by the Station House Officer, Naya Bazar Police Station he and <lb/>Home Guard Yamnath Sharma went to Karmatar to <lb/>apprehend Suren Rai, met him at the Karmatar School <lb/>ground, apprehended him and brought him to Naya Bazar <lb/>Police Station. In cross-examination Constable Topden Lepcha <lb/>would state that it would take 10 to 15 minutes to reach <lb/>Karmatar from Naya Bazar Police Station and 30 to 35 <lb/>minutes from the place of occurrence. Padam Kumar Rai <lb/>would depose that Suren Rai left his house after 8.00 p.m. on <lb/>23.05.2013. Suren Rai would himself explain in his statement <lb/>under Section 313 Cr.P.C. that he left for Karmatar at 8.30 <lb/>p.m. on 23.05.2013. It is thus clear that Suren Rai would <lb/>have reached Karmatar 30 to 35 minutes thereafter. The <lb/>failure of the prosecution to examine any witness from <lb/>Karmatar, which could be for any number of reasons ought <lb/>not to have distracted the focus of the Learned Sessions Judge <lb/>to see whether from the evidence available the prosecution had <lb/>been able to establish their case. In re: Raja v. State of <lb/>Haryana 1 the Supreme Court would hold:-<lb/>&quot;13. ....... It is well settled in law that non-examination of <lb/>material witness is not a mathematical formula for discarding the <lb/>weight of the testimony available on record, if the same is natural, <lb/>trustworthy and convincing ......&quot; <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">1 (2015) 11 SCC 43 <lb/></note>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>34. All other circumstances having been cogently proved by <lb/>the prosecution, the four pivotal issues examined by the <lb/>Learned Special Judge are required to be reconsidered in the <lb/>present appeal within the parameters of settled law of <lb/>appreciation of appeal against acquittal. If the evidence <lb/>produced and proved gives rise to a strong suspicion but does <lb/>not conclusively prove the guilt, Suren Rai&apos;s acquittal is to be <lb/>upheld. If the evidence produced and proved gives rise to two <lb/>probable conclusions one in favour of Suren Rai and the other <lb/>against, even then Suren Rai&apos;s acquittal is to be upheld. <lb/>Judicial Confession <lb/>35. On 06.06.2013 the Investigating Officer vide a <lb/>communication (exhibit-7) would appraise the Learned <lb/>Judicial Magistrate that Suren Rai was arrested on <lb/>24.05.2013 and sent to judicial custody on the same date and <lb/>further that Suren Rai &quot;volunteers to depose facts with regard <lb/>to the instant case in the Hon&apos;ble Court of law.&quot; <lb/>The <lb/>Investigating Officer, therefore, would request the Learned <lb/>Judicial Magistrate to record the statement of Suren Rai under <lb/>Section 164 Cr.P.C. The said application would be examined <lb/>by the Learned Judicial Magistrate on the same date. On <lb/>06.06.2013 itself, Suren Rai, having been brought before the <lb/>Learned Judicial Magistrate at 1330 hours, would be placed in <lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>custody of peon Dhrona Sharma and the police would be <lb/>directed to leave the premises. Having satisfied herself that <lb/>there was no policeman in the Court or in any place where the <lb/>proceedings could be seen or heard except the peon, not <lb/>concerned in the investigation of the crime, as necessary to <lb/>guard the witness, the Learned Judicial Magistrate would put <lb/>16 questions to Suren Rai to ensure the voluntariness of the <lb/>confession to be recorded. It would be explained to Suren Rai <lb/>that she was a Magistrate and had no concern with the police. <lb/>Suren Rai would be asked whether he had any complaint of ill <lb/>treatment against the police or other person responsible for <lb/>bringing him to the Court. Suren Rai would reply with a &quot;no&quot;. <lb/>Suren Rai would be asked whether he consented to be <lb/>examined by the Learned Judicial Magistrate. He would reply <lb/>in the affirmative. Suren Rai would be asked if he wished to <lb/>make any statement. He would again reply in the affirmative. <lb/>Suren Rai would be specifically asked whether he wanted to <lb/>consult an advocate of his choice before proceeding any <lb/>further. He would reply with a &quot;no&quot;. Suren Rai would be <lb/>informed that he was not bound to make a statement or there <lb/>is no compulsion that he should make a statement. He would <lb/>say he understood the information. Suren Rai would also be <lb/>informed that if he made a statement it would be taken down <lb/>and may be used against him as evidence. He would say he <lb/>understood the information. Suren Rai would be asked <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>whether the police or any other person threatened him to <lb/>make a statement. He would say &quot;no&quot;. Suren Rai would be <lb/>asked whether the police or anyone else promised him that <lb/>lesser punishment would be awarded if he made a statement <lb/>or that he would be acquitted. Suren Rai would state &quot;no they <lb/>have not told me anything like that&quot;. Suren Rai would be asked <lb/>whether the police or any other person had given him any <lb/>allurement to make a statement and the reply would be a &quot;no&quot;. <lb/>Suren Rai would be specifically asked if he was under <lb/>pressure of the police to make statement under Section 164 <lb/>Cr.P.C. and the reply would again be a &quot;no&quot;. Suren Rai would <lb/>be asked if he still desired to make a statement and the reply <lb/>would be a &quot;yes&quot;. When asked when it first occurred to him <lb/>that he should make the statement and why did it occur to <lb/>him to do so, Suren Rai would reply: &quot;immediately after I was <lb/>arrested and realized that I had made a mistake&quot;. When asked <lb/>why he was making a statement, Suren Rai would state: <lb/>&quot;because I had committed the offence&quot;. Suren Rai would be <lb/>specifically asked whether he was making the statement <lb/>voluntarily, Suren Rai would reply with a &quot;yes&quot;. Finally, Suren <lb/>Rai would be informed that he was given four days time for <lb/>reflection. He would also be told not to keep in touch with the <lb/>police. On being asked whether he understood the same he <lb/>would reply with a &quot;yes&quot;. Accordingly, Suren Rai would be <lb/>given four days time for reflection and sent to jail with <lb/></body>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>personnel with a direction to appear before the Learned <lb/>Judicial Magistrate on 10.06.2013 at 10 a.m. <lb/>36. The aforesaid details culled out from the record of the <lb/>questionnaires put to Suren Rai amply and substantially fulfil <lb/>the requirements of Section 164 (2) of Cr.P.C. Complete and <lb/>adequate examination seems to have been undertaken by the <lb/>Learned Judicial Magistrate to satisfy herself regarding the <lb/>voluntariness of the statement of Suren Rai to be recorded. <lb/>37. On 10.06.2013 Suren Rai would be produced by a Head <lb/>Constable from the District Jail. He would be placed in <lb/>custody of the Learned Judicial Magistrate&apos;s staff and the <lb/>Head Constable from the District Jail would be directed to <lb/>leave the Court premises. The Learned Judicial Magistrate <lb/>would satisfy herself that there was no policeman in the Court <lb/>and chamber from where the Court could be seen or heard. <lb/>Thereafter, the Learned Judicial Magistrate would inform <lb/>Suren Rai that she was a Magistrate and had no connection <lb/>with the police. Suren Rai would be asked whether he <lb/>understood the said fact to which he would reply with a &quot;yes&quot;. <lb/>Suren Rai would once again be asked whether he had any <lb/>complain of ill treatment by the police and the answer would <lb/>be a &quot;no&quot;. Suren Rai would be asked whether he was induced, <lb/>coerced, promised or advised by the police to make a <lb/>statement and the answer would be a &quot;no&quot;. Suren Rai would <lb/></body>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>be asked whether the statement he offered to make was <lb/>induced by any harsh treatment and if so by whom and the <lb/>answer would be a &quot;no&quot;. Suren Rai would be informed that he <lb/>was a free agent and not bound to make any statement. He <lb/>would also be informed that it is open to him to make <lb/>statement before her or not. Suren Rai would answer that he <lb/>had understood the information. Suren Rai would be asked <lb/>whether he still desired to make a statement after having been <lb/>given four days of reflection time to think about it and the <lb/>reply would be: &quot;yes, since I have committed the offence, I <lb/>desire to make my statement.&quot; The Learned Judicial <lb/>Magistrate, thereafter, would explain to the accused that he is <lb/>not bound to make any statement before her. The Learned <lb/>Judicial Magistrate would believe that the statement was made <lb/>voluntarily. <lb/>Having <lb/>satisfied <lb/>herself <lb/>regarding <lb/>the <lb/>voluntariness of the statement, the Learned Judicial <lb/>Magistrate would record the confessional statement after <lb/>which the mandate of Section 164 (4) and 281 of Cr.P.C. would <lb/>be complied with. Memorandum of the statement of the <lb/>accused recorded under Section 164 of Cr.P.C. would be <lb/>prepared and signed by both the Learned Judicial Magistrate <lb/>as well as the accused as required. However, the statement of <lb/>Suren Rai would be recorded in the &quot;form for recording <lb/>deposition&quot; and the details of Suren Rai, the Magistrate <lb/>recording the deposition, the date of the deposition, the name <lb/></body>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>of the person deposing, his father&apos;s name, age, village would be <lb/>duly filled which would read thus:-<lb/>&quot;FORM FOR RECORDING DEPOSITION <lb/>The deposition of accused Suren Rai for the Court taken on Oath <lb/>solemn affirmation before me Subarna Rai, Judicial Magistrate, West <lb/>Sikkim at Gyalshing on this the 10 th day of June, 2013 <lb/>My name is Suren Rai <lb/>My father&apos;s name is Dhan Bahadur Rai, <lb/>I am aged about 27 yrs. <lb/>My home is at village Karmatar, Darjeeling, West <lb/>Bengal <lb/>I reside at present at village Karmatar, Darjeeling, West Bengal <lb/>where I am a labourer.&quot; <lb/>38. The Learned Judicial Magistrate would be examined and <lb/>she would depose that she had been satisfied that Suren Rai <lb/>had understood the nature of the proceeding and he was <lb/>willing to give his statement voluntarily despite knowing that it <lb/>would be used against him. The Learned Judicial Magistrate <lb/>would also depose that the contents of the confession so <lb/>recorded was read over and explained to Suren Rai in Nepali <lb/>and admitted by him to be his true statement. The Learned <lb/>Judicial Magistrate would also be cross-examined by the <lb/>defence when she would state that she had not informed the <lb/>accused about free legal aid before recording his confession <lb/>under Section 164 Cr.P.C. The defence would take a denial <lb/>that the statement under Section 164 Cr.P.C. was voluntarily. <lb/>No question would be asked, as sought to be raised in the <lb/>present appeal, on the issue of purported administration of <lb/></body>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>oath on Suren Rai, in the manner detailed above, before <lb/>recording his confession. <lb/>39. As we would find that the issue of administration of oath <lb/>on an accused before recording a confession raised important <lb/>question to be judicially answered, a reference would be made <lb/>vide Order dated 03.07.2017 to the Full Court. The Full Court <lb/>would render its judgment dated 10.03.2018 answering all the <lb/>three questions referred. <lb/>40. From the perusal of the records it is quite clear that the <lb/>mandate of Section 164 and 281 of Cr.P.C. had been <lb/>substantially complied with by the Learned Judicial Magistrate <lb/>before recording the confession. The Learned Sessions Judge <lb/>would, however, hold that Suren Rai would explain in a <lb/>statement under Section 313 Cr.P.C. that he had expressed <lb/>his desire to make the statement on being pressurised by the <lb/>Investigating Officer. The Learned Sessions Judge would also <lb/>hold that the statement recorded under Section 164 of Cr.P.C. <lb/>is not a substantive piece of evidence and could be used only <lb/>to corroborate the statement of the witnesses or to contradict <lb/>them. On the said two grounds, the Learned Sessions Judge <lb/>would not rely upon the confession. <lb/>41. The Full Bench of this Court vide its judgment dated <lb/>10.03.2018 in re: State of Sikkim v. Suren Rai would hold:-<lb/></body>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>&quot;&quot;Confessions&quot; are one species of the genus &quot;admission&quot; <lb/>consisting of a direct acknowledgement of guilt by an accused <lb/>in a criminal case. &quot;Confessions&quot; are thus &quot;admissions&quot; but all <lb/>admissions are not confessions. A confession can be acted <lb/>upon if the Court is satisfied that it is voluntary and true. <lb/>Judgment of conviction can also be based on confession if it is <lb/>found to be truthful, deliberate and voluntary and if clearly <lb/>proved. An unambiguous confession, as held by the Supreme <lb/>Court, if admissible in evidence, and free from suspicion <lb/>suggesting its falsity, is a valuable piece of evidence which <lb/>possess a high probative force because it emanates directly <lb/>from the person committing the offence. To act on such <lb/>confessions the Court must be extremely vigilant and <lb/>scrutinize every relevant factor to ensure that the confession is <lb/>truthful and voluntary. Although the word confession has not <lb/>been defined in the Evidence Act, 1872 the Privy Council in re: <lb/>Pakala Narayanaswami v. King Emperor has clearly laid <lb/>down that a confession must either admit in terms the offence, <lb/>or at any rate substantially all the facts which constitute the <lb/>offence. As abundant caution the Courts have sought for <lb/>corroboration of the confession though. As per Taylor&apos;s <lb/>Treaties on the law of Evidence, Vol. I a confession is <lb/>considered highly reliable because no rational person would <lb/>make admission against his own interest prompted by his <lb/>conscience to tell the truth. If the Court finds that the <lb/>confession was voluntary, truthful and not caused by any <lb/>inducement, threat or promise it gains a high degree of <lb/>probability. To insulate such confession from any extraneous <lb/>pressure affecting the voluntariness and truthfulness the laws <lb/>have provided various safeguards and protections. A <lb/>confession is made acceptable against the accused <lb/>fundamental right of silence. A confession by hope or promise <lb/>of gain or advantage is equally unacceptable as a confession <lb/>by reward or immunity, by force or fear or by violence or <lb/>threat. As held by the Supreme Court in re: Navjot Sandhu <lb/>(supra) the authority recording the confession at the pre-trial <lb/>stage must address himself to the issue whether the accused <lb/>has come forward to make the confession in an atmosphere <lb/></body>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>free from fear, duress or hope of some advantage or reward <lb/>induced by the person in authority. It is therefore, the solemn <lb/>duty of the authorities both investigating agencies as well as <lb/>Courts to ensure, before acting on such confession, that the <lb/>same is safe to be acted upon and that there is no element of <lb/>doubt that the confession is voluntary and truthful and not <lb/>actuated by any inducement, threat or promise from any <lb/>quarter. To do so the Magistrate must create an atmosphere <lb/>and an environment which would allow voluntary confession <lb/>induced by nothing else but his conscience to speak the truth <lb/>and confess the crime. In deciding whether a particular <lb/>confession attracts the frown of Section 24 of the Evidence <lb/>Act, the question has to be considered from the point of view of <lb/>the confessing accused as to how the inducement, threat or <lb/>promise proceeding from a person in authority would operate <lb/>in his mind.&quot; <lb/>42. <lb/>The Supreme Court in re: Subramania Goundan v. State <lb/>of Madras 2 would hold:-<lb/>&quot;14. The next question is whether there is <lb/>corroboration of the confession since it has been retracted. A <lb/>confession of a crime by a person, who has perpetrated it, is <lb/>usually the outcome of penitence and remorse and in normal <lb/>circumstances is the best evidence against the maker. The <lb/>question has very often arisen whether a retracted confession <lb/>may form the basis of conviction if believed to be true and <lb/>voluntarily made. For the purpose of arriving at this conclusion <lb/>the court has to take into consideration not only the reasons <lb/>given for making the confession or retracting it but the <lb/>attending facts and circumstances surrounding the same. It <lb/>may be remarked that there can be no absolute rule that a <lb/>retracted confession cannot be acted upon unless the same is <lb/>corroborated materially.&quot; <lb/>43. In re: Aloke Nath Dutta v. State of W.B. 3 the Supreme Court <lb/>would hold: <lb/>2 AIR 1958 SC 66 <lb/></body>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>&quot;113. The value of a retracted confession is now well known. <lb/>The court must be satisfied that the confession at the first instance <lb/>is true and voluntary. (See Subramania Goundan v. State of Madras <lb/>[AIR 1958 SC 66 : 1958 Cri LJ 238] and Pyare Lal Bhargava v. State <lb/>of Rajasthan [AIR 1963 SC 1094 : (1963) 2 Cri LJ 178] .) <lb/>114. Caution and prudence in accepting a retracted <lb/>confession is an ordinary rule. (See Puran v. State of Punjab (I) [AIR <lb/>1953 SC 459 : 1953 Cri LJ 1925] .) Although if a retracted <lb/>confession is found to be corroborative in material particulars, it may <lb/>be the basis of conviction. (Balbir Singh v. State of Punjab [AIR 1957 <lb/>SC 216 : 1957 Cri LJ 481] ) <lb/>115. We may notice that in 1950s and 1960s corroborative <lb/>evidence in &quot;material particulars&quot; was the rule. (See Puran [AIR <lb/>1953 SC 459 : 1953 Cri LJ 1925] , Balbir Singh [AIR 1957 SC 216 : <lb/>1957 Cri LJ 481] and Nand Kumar v. State of Rajasthan [(1963) 2 <lb/>Cri LJ 702 (SC)] .) A distinctiveness was made in later years in <lb/>favour of &quot;general corroboration&quot; or &quot;broad corroboration&quot;. (See for <lb/>&quot;General Corroboration&quot; -State of Maharashtra v. Bharat <lb/>Chaganlal Raghani [(2001) 9 SCC 1 : 2002 SCC (Cri) 377] ; &quot;General <lb/>trend of Corroboration&quot; -Jameel Ahmed v. State of Rajasthan <lb/>[(2003) 9 SCC 673 : 2003 SCC (Cri) 1853] and &quot;Broad Corroboration&quot; <lb/>-Parmananda Pegu v. State of Assam [(2004) 7 SCC 779 : 2004 <lb/>SCC (Cri) 2081 : AIR 2004 SC 4197] .) <lb/>116. Whatever be the terminology used, one rule is almost <lb/>certain that no judgment of conviction shall be passed on an <lb/>uncorroborated retracted confession. The court shall consider the <lb/>materials on record objectively in regard to the reasons for <lb/>retraction. It must arrive at a finding that the confession was truthful <lb/>and voluntary. Merit of the confession being the voluntariness and <lb/>truthfulness, the same, in no circumstances, should be <lb/>compromised. We are not oblivious of some of the decisions of this <lb/>Court which proceeded on the basis that conviction of an accused on <lb/>the basis of a retracted confession is permissible but only if it is <lb/></body>

			<page>3 (2007) 12 SCC 230 <lb/>30 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>found that retraction made by the accused was wholly on a false <lb/>premise. (See Balbir Singh [AIR 1957 SC 216 : 1957 Cri LJ 481] .) <lb/>117. There cannot, however, be any doubt or dispute that <lb/>although retracted confession is admissible, the same should be <lb/>looked at with some amount of suspicion -a stronger suspicion <lb/>than that which is attached to the confession of an approver who <lb/>leads evidence in the court.&quot; <lb/>44. It would be apposite to point out that Suren Rai had <lb/>voluntarily given his confession before the Learned Magistrate <lb/>before whom he candidly stated that he wanted to make the <lb/>confession because he had committed the offence. Various <lb/>opportunities would be provided by the Learned Judicial <lb/>Magistrate in the form of questions inquiring about any direct <lb/>or indirect pressure, influence, hope or lure from the police or <lb/>anyone else to Suren Rai and on each such occasion he would <lb/>candidly reply with an emphatic &quot;no&quot;. The confession was <lb/>recorded by the Learned Judicial Magistrate on 10.06.2013. <lb/>The charges were framed on 23.05.2014. 11 witnesses were <lb/>examined including the Investigating Officer during the trial. <lb/>On the closure of evidence, the examination of Suren Rai, as <lb/>an accused, would be conducted on 30.07.2015 and <lb/>16.02.2016 more than a year after the framing of charges <lb/>against him. Suren Rai sought to retract his confession only at <lb/>the time of recording his statement under Section 313 Cr.P.C. <lb/>The reason, Suren Rai would assign, for retracting his <lb/>confession is that he made his confession being pressurised by <lb/></body>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>the Investigating Officer. There are no specific details of how <lb/>the Investigating Officer exerted pressure on Suren Rai in his <lb/>explanation. The Investigating Officer was cross-examined by <lb/>the defence. There is not even a denial of having confessed <lb/>before the Learned Judicial Magistrate in the cross-<lb/>examination of the Investigating Officer. If there was any kind <lb/>of pressure exerted by the Investigating Officer due to which <lb/>Suren Rai would volunteer to give his confession to the <lb/>Learned Judicial Magistrate it was incumbent upon the <lb/>defence to cross-examine the Investigating Officer regarding <lb/>the specific details of the alleged pressure exerted by him to <lb/>elicit the truth of the allegation, which was not done. In his <lb/>subsequent examination under Section 313 Cr.P.C. the <lb/>Respondent would also be asked: &quot;3. As per P.W.3, after <lb/>recording the statement same was read over and explained to <lb/>you which was admitted by you to be true and correct. Exhibit <lb/>10 is your statement recorded by her under Section 164 Cr.P.C. <lb/>What have you to say?&quot; The Respondent would answer: &quot;It is <lb/>true&quot;. In view of the same it is unequivocally clear that the <lb/>allegation of the confession not being voluntarily and made <lb/>only after pressure was exerted by the Investigating Officer <lb/>was an afterthought of the defence far too late in the day to <lb/>invoke any further and deeper consideration. However, as <lb/>adverted before, since an issue of substantial importance that <lb/>oath having been administered the confession must be <lb/></body>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>discarded had been raised by Mr. B. Sharma this Court would <lb/>refer the issue before the Full Bench. A Full Bench of this <lb/>Court in re: State of Sikkim v. Suren Rai (supra) would inter-alia <lb/>hold:-<lb/>&quot;126. It is also evident that on examination of Section <lb/>164(5) Cr.P.C. administering of oath to an accused while <lb/>recording confession without anything more may lead to an <lb/>inference that the confession was not voluntary. However, <lb/>there could be stray cases in which the confessions had been <lb/>recorded in full and complete compliance of the mandate of <lb/>Section 164 and 281 Cr.P.C and that the confession was <lb/>voluntary and truthful and no oath may have been actually <lb/>administered but inspite of the same the confession was <lb/>recorded in the prescribed form for recording deposition or <lb/>statement of witness giving an impression that oath was <lb/>administered upon the accused. If the Court before which such <lb/>document is tendered finds that it was so, Section 463 Cr.P.C <lb/>would be applicable and the Court shall take evidence of non-<lb/>compliance of Section 164 and 281 Cr.P.C. to satisfy itself that <lb/>in fact it was so and if satisfied about the said fact is also <lb/>satisfied that the failure to record the otherwise voluntary <lb/>confession was not in the proper form only and did not injure <lb/>the accused the confession may be admitted in evidence. We <lb/>answer the second question accordingly.&quot; <lb/>45. Admittedly this issue was not raised before the trial <lb/>Court. Admittedly again no questions were asked to the <lb/>Learned Judicial Magistrate who recorded the confession <lb/>about the administration of oath nor any explanation sought. <lb/>The record of the confession clearly reflects that the confession <lb/>was recorded in the &quot;Form for recording deposition&quot;. The issue <lb/>not having been raised specifically before the Court it is <lb/>evident that the Court has not taken evidence under Section <lb/>463 Cr.P.C. After the Full Bench of this Court rendered his <lb/>judgment on the issue of administration of oath to an accused <lb/>the matter would be listed for hearing to give an opportunity to <lb/></body>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>the Appellant as well as the Respondent to make submissions <lb/>on the effect of the said judgment. At the said hearing held on <lb/>11.04.2018 Mr. Karma Thinlay would submit that a bare <lb/>perusal of the confession recorded under Section 164 Cr.P.C. <lb/>makes it clear that oath was not actually administered upon <lb/>the Respondent and the words &quot;taken on oath solemn <lb/>affirmation&quot; was part of a pre-typed &quot;form or recording <lb/>deposition&quot; and as such in view of paragraph 126 of the said <lb/>judgment rendered by the Full Bench of this Court it would be <lb/>important to remit the matter to the Court of the Learned <lb/>Sessions Judge for the limited purpose of taking evidence of <lb/>non-compliance of Section 164 and 281 Cr.P.C. On hearing <lb/>the parties this Court would direct that the case papers be <lb/>remitted to the Court of the Learned Sessions Judge for <lb/>examining whether oath was actually administered upon the <lb/>Respondent by the Learned Magistrate while recording his <lb/>confession. The Learned Sessions Judge would re-examine the <lb/>Learned Magistrate now Learned Chief Judicial Magistrate, <lb/>giving an opportunity to the Respondent to cross-examine the <lb/>Learned Chief Judicial Magistrate and thereafter give further <lb/>opportunity to the Respondent to explain the circumstances <lb/>under Section 313 Cr.P.C. pursuant to which the records <lb/>would be placed before this Court. The Appellant as well as the <lb/>Respondent would be re-heard on 30.05.2018. Mr. Karma <lb/>Thinley would submit that the evidence of the Learned Chief <lb/></body>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>Judicial Magistrate would make it evident that oath was in fact <lb/>not administered upon the Respondent and the confessional <lb/>statement was voluntary. Mr. B. Sharma to the contrary would <lb/>submit that in view of the judgement of the Full Bench of this <lb/>Court the Learned Chief Judicial Magistrate stated that she <lb/>had not actually administered oath although the records of the <lb/>examination would reveal that oath was actually administered. <lb/>He would further submit that in view of the documentary <lb/>evidence which records that oath was administered there was <lb/>no question of taking oral evidence and the said oral evidence <lb/>would thus have little evidentiary value. He would draw the <lb/>attention of this Court to Sections 91 and 94 of the Evidence <lb/>Act, 1872. Mr. B. Sharma&apos;s submission on exclusion of oral <lb/>evidence is in ignorance of Section 463 Cr.P.C. A perusal of the <lb/>cross-examination of the Learned Chief Judicial Magistrate <lb/>would disclose that the defence had not cross-examined her on <lb/>the allegation made before us that her evidence was the result <lb/>of the judgment of the Full Bench which is impermissible. <lb/>Ambiguities, <lb/>peculiarities <lb/>in <lb/>expression <lb/>and <lb/>the <lb/>inconsistencies between the written words and the existing <lb/>facts can also be explained by intrinsic evidence. The <lb/>deposition of the Learned Magistrate dated 26.04.2018 makes <lb/>it abundantly clear that oath had in fact not been <lb/>administered upon the Respondent while recording the <lb/></body>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>confession. It is thus quite evident that this Court must <lb/>examine the confession statement. <lb/>Disclosure statement (Exhibit 14) <lb/>46. The disclosure statement dated 24.05.2013 is recorded in <lb/>Nepali. It is signed by Suren Rai, the Investigating Officer and <lb/>two witnesses, Bhadrey Biswakarma and Dhiraj Rai. The <lb/>Investigating Officer has proved his signature thereon. So have <lb/>the two witnesses. <lb/>47. The disclosure statement of Suren Rai states that on the <lb/>night of 23.05.2013 he and the deceased had a fight after <lb/>which he took out the &quot;khukuri&quot; he had and hit him from <lb/>behind after which Suren Rai hid the &quot;khukuri&quot; close to the <lb/>house of Padma &quot;kopa&quot; (grandfather in the Rai language). <lb/>Suren Rai also stated that he could show the &quot;khukuri&quot; to the <lb/>police in the presence of witnesses. <lb/>48. <lb/>Both Bhadrey Bishwakarma and Dhiraj Rai have <lb/>deposed that on 24.05.2013 one Police Personnel of Naya <lb/>Bazar Police Station recorded the statement of Suren Rai <lb/>wherein he stated that he has concealed the weapon of offence <lb/>i.e., &quot;khukuri&quot; near the house of Padam Kumar Rai. The said <lb/>two witnesses also deposed that the disclosure statement was <lb/>the statement given by Suren Rai. The said two witnesses also <lb/>deposed about how Suren Rai took the Police Personnel and <lb/></body>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>them near the house of Padam Kumar Rai and the subsequent <lb/>discovery of the &quot;khukuri&quot; at his instance. However, during <lb/>their cross-examination they stated that the disclosure <lb/>statement was prepared by the Police only after the Suren Rai <lb/>was asked by the police to make statement regarding the <lb/>weapon of offence. The Learned Sessions Judge would take <lb/>exception of the fact that the said two witnesses deposed that <lb/>the disclosure statement was prepared by the police only after <lb/>Suren Rai was asked to make a statement. This exception, to <lb/>our mind is not correct as merely asking an accused to make a <lb/>statement without anything more cannot lead to any negative <lb/>inference. However, the said two witnesses would also state <lb/>that the statement was not voluntary. The said two witnesses <lb/>were not declared hostile on this aspect and cross-examined <lb/>by the prosecution. The prosecution is bound by their evidence <lb/>that the disclosure statement was not voluntary. <lb/>49. The submission of the defence found favour with the <lb/>Learned Sessions Judge who would hold the disclosure <lb/>statement not proved. On perusal of the depositions of the <lb/>seizure witnesses it is seen that both of them deposed that the <lb/>disclosure statement was not the voluntary statement of Suren <lb/>Rai. <lb/>50. The question which therefore falls for consideration is <lb/>whether a disclosure statement is required to be voluntary? <lb/></body>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>51. Section 27 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 provides:-<lb/>&quot;27. How much of information received from <lb/>accused may be proved.-Provided that, when any fact is <lb/>deposed to as discovered in consequence of information <lb/>received from a person accused of any offence, in the custody <lb/>of a police officer, so much of such information, whether it <lb/>amounts to a confession or not, as relates distinctly to the fact <lb/>thereby discovered, may be proved.&quot; <lb/>52. Section 25 and 26 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 are <lb/>also important for the purpose of understanding Section 27 <lb/>thereof and thus reproduced herein below:-<lb/>&quot;25. Confession to police officer not to be proved.-<lb/>No confession made to a police officer, shall, be proved as <lb/>against a person accused of any offence.&quot; <lb/>&quot;26. Confession by accused while in custody of <lb/>police not to be proved against him. No confession made <lb/>by any person whilst he is in the custody of a police officer, <lb/>unless it be made in the immediate presence of a Magistrate, <lb/>shall be proved as against such person. <lb/>Explanation.-In this section &quot;Magistrate&quot; does not <lb/>include the head of a village discharging magisterial functions <lb/>in the Presidency of Fort St. George or elsewhere, unless such <lb/>headman is a Magistrate exercising the powers of a <lb/>Magistrate under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1882 (10 of <lb/>1882).&quot; <lb/>53. Sir John Beaumont, in re: Pulukuri Kottaya and others v. <lb/>The King Emperor 4 would hold that Section 27 of the Indian <lb/>Evidence Act, 1872 seems to be based on the view that if a fact <lb/>is actually discovered in consequence of information given, <lb/>some guarantee is afforded thereby that the information was <lb/>true, and accordingly can be safely allowed to be given in <lb/>evidence. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">4 AIR 1947 PC 67 <lb/></note>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>54. In re: State of Maharashtra v. Damu 5 , the Supreme Court <lb/>would hold: <lb/>&quot;35. The basic idea embedded in Section 27 of the <lb/>Evidence Act is the doctrine of confirmation by subsequent <lb/>events. The doctrine is founded on the principle that if any fact <lb/>is discovered in a search made on the strength of any <lb/>information obtained from a prisoner, such a discovery is a <lb/>guarantee that the information supplied by the prisoner is <lb/>true. The information might be confessional or non-inculpatory <lb/>in nature, but if it results in discovery of a fact it becomes a <lb/>reliable information. Hence the legislature permitted such <lb/>information to be used as evidence by restricting the <lb/>admissible portion to the minimum. It is now well settled that <lb/>recovery of an object is not discovery of a fact envisaged in the <lb/>section. The decision of the Privy Council in Pulukuri Kottaya <lb/>v. Emperor is the most quoted authority for supporting the <lb/>interpretation that the &quot;fact discovered&quot; envisaged in the <lb/>section embrace the place from which the object was <lb/>produced, the knowledge of the accused as to it, but the <lb/>information given must relate distinctly to that effect.&quot; <lb/>55. The only portion of the disclosure statement which is <lb/>admissible is the statement of Suren Rai that he had hidden <lb/>the &quot;khukuri&quot; near the house of Padma Kumar Rai and he can <lb/>show the same to the police in the presence of witnesses which <lb/>is covered by Section 27 of the Evidence Act, 1872. The rest of <lb/>the disclosure statement is in-admissible, being confessional <lb/>and prohibited by Section 25 and 26 of the Indian Evidence <lb/>Act, 1872. <lb/>56. In re: Pulukuri Kottaya (supra) the Privy Council would <lb/>hold: <lb/>&quot;S. 27, which is not artistically worded, provides <lb/>an exception to the prohibition imposed by the preceding <lb/>section and enables certain statements made by a <lb/>person in police custody to be proved. The condition <lb/></body>

			<page>5 (2000) 6 SCC 269 <lb/>39 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>necessary to bring the section into operation is that the <lb/>discovery of a fact in consequence of information <lb/>received from a person accused of any offence in the <lb/>custody of a Police officer must be deposed to, and <lb/>thereupon so much of the information as relates <lb/>distinctly to the fact thereby discovered may be proved. <lb/>The section seems to be based on the view that if a fact <lb/>is actually discovered in consequence of information <lb/>given, some guarantee is afforded thereby that the <lb/>information was true, and accordingly can be safely <lb/>allowed to be given in evidence; but clearly the extent of <lb/>the information admissible must depend on the exact <lb/>nature of the fact discovered to which such information <lb/>is required to relate. Normally the section is brought into <lb/>operation when a person in police custody produces <lb/>from some place of concealment some object, such as a <lb/>dead body, a weapon, or ornaments, said to be <lb/>connected with the crime of which the informant is <lb/>accused. Mr. Megaw, for the Crown, has argued that in <lb/>such a case the &quot;fact discovered&quot; is the physical object <lb/>produced, and that any information which relates <lb/>distinctly to that object can be proved. Upon this view <lb/>information given by a person that the body produced is <lb/>that of a person murdered by him, that the weapon <lb/>produced is the one used by him in the commission of a <lb/>murder, or that the ornaments produced were stolen in <lb/>a dacoity would all be admissible. If this be the effect of <lb/>S. 27, little substance would remain in the ban imposed <lb/>by the two preceding sections on confessions made to <lb/>the police, or by persons in police custody. That ban <lb/>was presumably inspired by the fear of the legislature <lb/>that a person under police influence might be induced to <lb/>confess by the exercise of undue pressure. But if all that <lb/>is required to lift the ban be the inclusion in the <lb/>confession of information, relating to an object <lb/>subsequently produced, it seems reasonable to suppose <lb/>that the pursuasive powers of the police will prove equal <lb/>to the occasion, and that in practice the ban will lose its <lb/>effect. On normal principles of construction their <lb/>Lordships think that the proviso to S. 26, added by S. <lb/>27, should not be held to nullify the substance of the <lb/>section. ............................................&quot; <lb/>57. It is not the case of the defence that Suren Rai did not <lb/>make the disclosure statement or that he did not sign on it. <lb/>However, the defence would contend that the disclosure <lb/>statement was not given by Suren Rai &quot;voluntarily&quot;. Bhadrey <lb/>Bishwakarma and Dhiraj Rai have clearly deposed that the <lb/>disclosure statement was not given &quot;voluntarily&quot;. <lb/></body>

			<page>40 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>58. In re: State of Maharashtra v. Suresh 6 the Supreme Court <lb/>would hold: <lb/>&quot;26. We too countenance three possibilities when an <lb/>accused points out the place where a dead body or an <lb/>incriminating material was concealed without stating that it <lb/>was concealed by himself. One is that he himself would have <lb/>concealed it. Second is that he would have seen somebody <lb/>else concealing it. And the third is that he would have been <lb/>told by another person that it was concealed there. But if the <lb/>accused declines to tell the criminal court that his knowledge <lb/>about the concealment was on account of one of the last two <lb/>possibilities the criminal court can presume that it was <lb/>concealed by the accused himself. This is because the <lb/>accused is the only person who can offer the explanation as to <lb/>how else he came to know of such concealment and if he <lb/>chooses to refrain from telling the court as to how else he <lb/>came to know of it, the presumption is a well-justified course <lb/>to be adopted by the criminal court that the concealment was <lb/>made by himself. Such an interpretation is not inconsistent <lb/>with the principle embodied in Section 27 of the Evidence Act.&quot; <lb/>59. Relying upon the Judgment of the Supreme Court <lb/>reported in re: Raja (supra) (paragraph 15 to <lb/>17) and <lb/>emphasizing on the use of the word &quot;obtained&quot; Mr. Karma <lb/>Thinlay, would argue that the disclosure statement does <lb/>not <lb/>necessary <lb/>have <lb/>to <lb/>be <lb/>voluntary. The relevant <lb/>paragraphs of the said judgment are extracted herein below:-<lb/>&quot;15. Another circumstance that has been proven is <lb/>about the recovery of knife, bloodstained clothes <lb/>and the ashes of the burnt blanket. The seizure <lb/>witnesses Sukha PW 7 and Nanak PW 9 have <lb/></body>

			<page>6 (2000) 1 SCC 471 <lb/>41 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>proven the seizure. It is submitted by the learned <lb/>counsel for the appellant that the police had <lb/>recorded the confessional statement of the <lb/>appellant-accused at the police <lb/>custody and <lb/>thereafter, as alleged, had <lb/>recovered certain <lb/>things which really do not render any assistance to <lb/>the prosecution, for the confession recorded before <lb/>the police officer is inadmissible. That apart, the <lb/>accused had advanced the plea that the articles <lb/>and the weapon were planted by the investigating <lb/>agency. <lb/>16. To appreciate the said submission in proper <lb/>perspective, we may profitably reproduce a <lb/>passage from State of U.P. v. Deoman Upadhyaya 6 <lb/>:AIR p. 1129, para 7) <lb/>&quot;7.. ... The expression, &apos;accused of any <lb/>offence&apos; in Section 27, as in Section 25, is <lb/>also descriptive of the person concerned i.e. <lb/>against a person who is accused of an <lb/>offence. <lb/>Section 27 renders provable <lb/>certain statements made by him while he <lb/>was in the custody of a police officer. <lb/>Section 27 is founded on the principle that <lb/>even though the evidence relating to <lb/>confessional or other statements made by a <lb/>person, whilst he is in the custody of a <lb/>police officer, is tainted and therefore <lb/>inadmissible, if the truth of the information <lb/>given by him is assured by the discovery of <lb/>a fact, it may be presumed to be untainted <lb/>and is therefore declared provable insofar <lb/>as it distinctly relates to the fact thereby <lb/>discovered. Even though Section 27 is in <lb/>the form of a proviso to Section 26, the two <lb/>sections do not necessarily deal with the <lb/>evidence of the same character. The ban <lb/>imposed by Section 26 is against the proof <lb/></body>

			<page>42 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>of confessional statements. Section 27 is <lb/>concerned with the proof of information <lb/>whether it amounts to a confession or not, <lb/>which leads to discovery of facts. By <lb/>Section 27, even if a fact is deposed to as <lb/>discovered in consequence of information <lb/>received, only that much of the information <lb/>is admissible as distinctly relates to the <lb/>fact discovered.&quot; <lb/>&quot;17. In State of Maharashtra v. Damu [State of <lb/>Maharashtra v. Damu, (2000) 6 SCC 269 : 2000 <lb/>SCC (Cri) 1088], while dealing with the <lb/>fundamental facet of Section 27 of the Evidence <lb/>Act, the Court observed that the basic idea <lb/>embedded in the said provision is the doctrine of <lb/>confession by subsequent events, which is founded <lb/>on the principle that if any fact is discovered in a <lb/>search made on the strength of any information <lb/>obtained from a prisoner, such a discovery is a <lb/>guarantee that the information supplied by the <lb/>prisoner is true. It further stated that the <lb/>information might be confessional or non-<lb/>inculpatory in nature, but if it results in discovery <lb/>of a fact it becomes a reliable information and, <lb/>therefore, <lb/>the <lb/>legislature <lb/>permitted <lb/>such <lb/>information to be used as evidence by restricting <lb/>the admissible portion to the minimum…..&quot; <lb/>[Emphasis supplied] <lb/>60. In re: State of Maharashtra v. Damu (supra) after the arrest <lb/>of accused no. 3 therein, he would tell the Investigating Officer <lb/>that the dead body of the deceased was thrown in the canal. <lb/>The said statement was not found admissible as the dead body <lb/>was not recovered. On reconsideration the Supreme Court <lb/></body>

			<page>43 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>would find that pursuant to the said statement and the offer <lb/>made by the said accused that he would point out the spot, he <lb/>was taken to the spot and there the Investigating Officer found <lb/>a broken piece of glass lying on the ground which was picked <lb/>up by him. A motorcycle was also recovered from the house of <lb/>accused no. 2 and its tail lamp was found broken and one <lb/>piece missing. The broken piece of glass recovered on the <lb/>ground from the spot pointed out by accused no. 3 was placed <lb/>on the broken situs of the tail lamp of the motorcycle it fitted <lb/>the space and the Investigating Officer had no doubt that the <lb/>said glass piece was originally part of the tail lamp of that <lb/>motorcycle. It is in this context that the Supreme Court would <lb/>hold what was reproduced in re: Raja (supra) in paragraph 17 of <lb/>the said judgment. The Supreme Court was not called upon to <lb/>examine whether a disclosure statement was required to be <lb/>voluntary. <lb/>61. In re: Selvi v. State of Karnataka 7 the Supreme Court <lb/>would hold: <lb/>&quot;133...... However, Section 27 of the Evidence Act <lb/>incorporates the &quot;theory of confirmation by subsequent facts&quot; <lb/>i.e. statements made in custody are admissible to the extent <lb/>that they can be proved by the subsequent discovery of facts. <lb/>It is quite possible that the content of the custodial statements <lb/>could directly lead to the subsequent discovery of relevant <lb/>facts rather than their discovery through independent means. <lb/>Hence such statements could also be described as those <lb/></body>

			<page>7 (2010) 7 SCC 263 <lb/>44 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>which &quot;furnish a link in the chain of evidence&quot; needed for a <lb/>successful prosecution. This provision reads as follows: <lb/>&quot;27. How much of information received from accused <lb/>may be proved.-Provided that, when any fact is <lb/>deposed to as discovered in consequence of information <lb/>received from a person accused of any offence, in the <lb/>custody of a police officer, so much of such information, <lb/>whether it amounts to a confession or not, as relates <lb/>distinctly to the fact thereby discovered, may be <lb/>proved.&quot; <lb/>134. This provision permits the derivative use of <lb/>custodial statements in the ordinary course of events. In <lb/>Indian law, there is no automatic presumption that the <lb/>custodial statements have been extracted through compulsion. <lb/>In short, there is no requirement of additional diligence akin to <lb/>the administration of Miranda [16 L Ed 2d 694 : 384 US 436 <lb/>(1965)] warnings. However, in circumstances where it is <lb/>shown that a person was indeed compelled to make <lb/>statements while in custody, relying on such testimony as <lb/>well as its derivative use will offend Article 20(3).&quot; <lb/>[Emphasis supplied] <lb/>62. The word &quot;voluntarily&quot; has not been defined in the Cr. <lb/>P.C. Section 2 (y) Cr.P.C. however, provides: <lb/>&quot;(y). Words an expressions used herein and not defined but <lb/>defined in the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) have the <lb/>meanings respectively assigned to them in that Code.&quot; <lb/>63. Section 39 of the IPC provides: <lb/>&quot;39. &quot;Voluntarily&quot;.-A person is said to cause an effect <lb/>&quot;voluntarily&quot; when he causes it by means whereby he <lb/>intended to cause it, or by means which, at the time of <lb/>employing those means, he knew or had reason to believe to <lb/>be likely to cause it.&quot; <lb/>64. The word &quot;involuntary&quot; has been defined in the Black&apos;s <lb/>Law Dictionary, 10 th Edition to mean: <lb/></body>

			<page>45 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>&quot;Involuntary, adj.(15c) Not resulting from a free and <lb/>unrestrained choice; not subject to control by the will.&quot; <lb/>65. The Supreme Court in re: Rammi alias Rameshwar v. State <lb/>of M.P. 8 would hold: <lb/>&quot;11. Regarding the recovery of weapons, the prosecution <lb/>could utilise statements attributed to the accused on the basis <lb/>of which recovery of certain weapons was affected. Section 27 <lb/>of the Evidence Act permits so much of information which lead <lb/>to the discovery of a fact to be admitted in evidence. Here the <lb/>fact discovered by the police was that the accused had hidden <lb/>the bloodstained weapons. In that sphere what could have <lb/>been admitted in evidence is only that part of the information <lb/>which the accused had furnished to the police officer and <lb/>which led to the recovery of the weapons. <lb/>12. True, such information is admissible in evidence <lb/>under Section 27 of the Evidence Act, but admissibility alone <lb/>would not render the evidence, pertaining to the above <lb/>information, reliable. While testing the reliability of such <lb/>evidence the court has to see whether it was voluntarily stated <lb/>by the accused.&quot; <lb/>[Emphasis supplied] <lb/>66. A Constitutional Bench of the Supreme Court, as far <lb/>back as in the year 1961, would clearly hold in re: State of <lb/>Bombay v. Kathi Kalu Oghat 9 held:-<lb/>&quot;(13) ........ It was held by this court that S. 27 of the Evidence <lb/>Act did not offend Art. 14 of the Constitution and was, <lb/>therefore, &apos;intra vires&apos;. But the question whether it was <lb/>unconstitutional because it contravened the provisions of cl. (3) <lb/>of Art. 20 was not considered in that case. That question may, <lb/>therefore, be treated as an open one. The question has been <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">8 (1999) 8 SCC 649 <lb/>9 AIR 1961 SC 1808 <lb/></note>

			<page>46 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>raised in one of the cases before us and has, therefore, to be <lb/>decided. The information given by an accused person to a <lb/>police officer leading to the discovery of a fact which may or <lb/>may not prove incriminatory has been made admissible in <lb/>evidence by that section. If it is not incriminatory of the person <lb/>giving the information, the question does not arise. It can arise <lb/>only when it is of an incriminatory character so far as the giver <lb/>of the information is concerned. If the self incriminatory <lb/>information has been given by an accused person without any <lb/>threat, that will be admissible in evidence and that will not be <lb/>hit by the provisions of cl. (3) of Art. 20 of the Constitution for <lb/>the reason that there has been no compulsion. It must, <lb/>therefore, be held that the provisions of S. 27 of the Evidence <lb/>Act are not within the prohibition aforesaid, unless compulsion <lb/>had been used in obtaining the information.&quot; <lb/>[Emphasis supplied] <lb/>67. A Division Bench of this Court also had occasion to <lb/>examine whether a disclosure statement under Section 27 of <lb/>the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 was required to be voluntary <lb/>and in re: Kishore Thapa v. State of Sikkim 10 would hold: <lb/>&quot;14. As can be seen from the above, Section 27 is an <lb/>exception made to Section 25 and 26 in as much as the <lb/>information received from a person accused of an <lb/>offence, in the custody of a police officer, so much of <lb/>such information, as relates distinctly to the facts <lb/>thereby discovered may be which proved. In other <lb/>words, subject to the provisions contained in Sections <lb/>24, 25 and 26, information disclosed by a person, <lb/>whether it amounts to confession or not, would be <lb/>relevant only the factum of discovery and nothing more. <lb/>However, the pre-condition for a statement to be <lb/></body>

			<page>10 2010 SCC OnLine Sikk 10 <lb/>47 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>admissible under Section 27 is that it should have been <lb/>made voluntarily bereft of threat or coercion.&quot; <lb/>[Emphasis supplied] <lb/>68. Section 27 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 makes <lb/>information received from a person accused of any offence <lb/>even if in the custody of Police Officer and whether it amounts <lb/>to confession or not admissible to the extent it relates <lb/>distinctly to the fact thereby discovered in consequence of <lb/>information received from the said person. <lb/>69. The question raised in the present case is not merely <lb/>whether the recording of a disclosure statement in the custody <lb/>of police officer is inadmissible but whether the recording of a <lb/>disclosure statement in the custody of police officer and <lb/>admittedly made not voluntarily is admissible in evidence. In <lb/>view of the judgment of the Supreme Court in re: State of <lb/>Bombay v. Kathi Kalu Oghat (supra), Selvi v. State of Karnataka <lb/>(supra), Rammi alias Rameshwar v. State of M.P (supra) and the <lb/>Division Bench of this Court in re: Kishore Thapa v. State of <lb/>Sikkim (supra), it is unequivocally clear that the disclosure <lb/>statement is required to be voluntary in order to be <lb/>admissible. Involuntariness has an element of compulsion <lb/>which has been held prohibited although the mere recording of <lb/>the disclosure statement in the custody of police would not <lb/></body>

			<page>48 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>make it inadmissible. The disclosure statement, therefore, is <lb/>required to be kept out of consideration. <lb/>Seizure of Khukuri (vide Exhibit-15). <lb/>70. <lb/>The Learned Sessions Judge would hold: &quot;As per the <lb/>evidence of the witnesses the articles were seized by the police <lb/>from open place, accessible to all.&quot; The Learned Sessions <lb/>Judge would further hold: &quot;the evidence of witnesses does not <lb/>connect the accused with seizure articles i.e. M.O.XIV. There are <lb/>contradiction in the evidence of PW-9, Exhibit-14 and Exhibit-<lb/>15.&quot; M.O.XIV was the &quot;khukuri&quot;. Bhadrey Bishwakarma and <lb/>Dhiraj Rai would depose, in cross-examination, that the <lb/>alleged &quot;Khukuri&quot; was lying in an open place and everyone <lb/>could clearly see the place where alleged &quot;khukuri&quot; was lying. <lb/>Surely, it could not be a logical argument that merely because <lb/>the &quot;khukuri&quot;, was found in an open space it was not <lb/>admissible in evidence or in all crimes, the criminals would be <lb/>well advised not to hide the weapon of offence and leave it in <lb/>open spaces. The Supreme Court in Anter Singh v. State of <lb/>Rajasthan 11 would hold:-<lb/>&quot;10. ............. Though recovery from an open space may <lb/>not always render it vulnerable, it would depend upon the <lb/>factual situation in a given case and the truthfulness or <lb/>otherwise of such claim. ............&quot; <lb/></body>

			<page>11 (2004) 10 SCC 657 <lb/>49 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>71. In re: Yakub Abdul Razak Memon v. State of Maharashtra 12 <lb/>the Supreme Court would hold: <lb/>&quot;1706. In State of H.P. v. Jeet Singh [(1999) 4 SCC 370 <lb/>: 1999 SCC (Cri) 539] this Court dealt with the issue of <lb/>recovery from the public place and held: (SCC p. 377, para 21) <lb/>&quot;21. The conduct of the accused has some <lb/>relevance in the analysis of the whole circumstances <lb/>against him. PW 3 Santosh Singh, a member of the <lb/>Panchayat hailing from the same ward, said in his <lb/>evidence that he reached Jeet Singh&apos;s house at 6.15 <lb/>a.m. on hearing the news of that tragedy and then <lb/>accused Jeet Singh told him that Sudarshana <lb/>complained of pain in the liver during the early morning <lb/>hours. But when the accused was questioned by the <lb/>trial court under Section 313 of the Code of Criminal <lb/>Procedure, he denied having said so to PW 3 and <lb/>further said, for the first time, that he and Sudarshana <lb/>did not sleep in the same room but they slept in two <lb/>different rooms. Such a conduct on the part of the <lb/>accused was taken into account by the Sessions Court <lb/>in evaluating the incriminating circumstance spoken to <lb/>by PW 10 that they were in the same room on the <lb/>fateful night. We too give accord to the aforesaid <lb/>approach made by the trial court.&quot; <lb/>1707. Similarly, in State of Maharashtra v. Bharat <lb/>Fakira Dhiwar [(2002) 1 SCC 622 : 2002 SCC (Cri) 217] , this <lb/>Court held: (SCC p. 629, para 22) <lb/>&quot;22. In the present case the grinding stone was <lb/>found in tall grass. The pants and underwear were <lb/>buried. They were out of visibility of others in normal <lb/>circumstances. Until they were disinterred, at the <lb/>instance of the respondent, their hidden state had <lb/>remained unhampered. The respondent alone knew <lb/></body>

			<page>12 (2013) 13 SCC 1 <lb/>50 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>where they were until he disclosed it. Thus we see no <lb/>substance in this submission also.&quot; <lb/>1708. In view of the above, it cannot be accepted that a <lb/>recovery made from an open space or a public place which <lb/>was accessible to everyone, should not be taken into <lb/>consideration for any reason. The reasoning behind it, is that, <lb/>it will be the accused alone who will be having knowledge of <lb/>the place, where a thing is hidden. The other persons who had <lb/>access to the place would not be aware of the fact that an <lb/>accused, after the commission of an offence, had concealed <lb/>contraband material beneath the earth, or in the garbage. <lb/>xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx <lb/>1793. The submission made by Mr Mushtaq Ahmad, <lb/>learned counsel appearing on behalf of the appellant that the <lb/>recovery was made from a public place and, therefore, could <lb/>not be relied upon and cannot be accepted, as it is the <lb/>accused alone on whose disclosure statement the recovery <lb/>was made and it is he alone, who is aware of the place he <lb/>has hidden the same. It cannot be presumed that the other <lb/>persons having access to the place would be aware that some <lb/>accused after the commission of an offence has concealed the <lb/>contraband material beneath the earth or in the garbage. <lb/>1794. In State of H.P. v. Jeet Singh [(1999) 4 SCC 370 : <lb/>1999 SCC (Cri) 539] , this Court held: (SCC p. 378, para 26) <lb/>&quot;26. There is nothing in Section 27 of the <lb/>Evidence Act which renders the statement of the <lb/>accused inadmissible if recovery of the articles was <lb/>made from any place which is &apos;open or accessible to <lb/>others&apos;. It is a fallacious notion that when recovery of <lb/>any incriminating article was made from a place which <lb/>is open or accessible to others, it would vitiate the <lb/>evidence under Section 27 of the Evidence Act. Any <lb/>object can be concealed in places which are open or <lb/>accessible to others.&quot; <lb/></body>

			<page>51 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>72. The said Bhadrey Bishwakarma and Dhiraj Rai were re-<lb/>examined. They would prove that the &quot;khukuri&quot; was the same <lb/>&quot;khukuri&quot; seized in their presence vide the Property Seizure <lb/>Memo (exhibit-15). <lb/>73. The recovery of the &quot;khukuri&quot; from near the place of <lb/>occurrence as well as its seizure vide Property Seizure Memo <lb/>(exhibit-15) cannot be doubted. It is important that it is not <lb/>the defence case that the &quot;khukuri&quot; recovered from near the <lb/>place of occurrence was planted by the police. Two questions <lb/>still remain to be answered. Firstly whether the prosecution <lb/>has been able to connect the &quot;khukuri&quot; to the crime? Secondly <lb/>whether the Learned Sessions Judges hesitation to rely upon <lb/>the same due to the fact that the seizure witnesses deposed <lb/>that the Property Seizure Memo (exhibit-15) was prepared after <lb/>they were asked to make the statement, is correct? The fact <lb/>that the &quot;khukuri&quot; was seized near the place of occurrence in <lb/>front of the kitchen of Padam Kumar has been proved. The <lb/>existence of the blood stained &quot;khukuri&quot; cannot also be <lb/>doubted merely because the two seizure witnesses stated that <lb/>the said &quot;khukuri&quot; was recovered after the involuntary <lb/>statement of Suren Rai. The Property Seizure Memo (exhibit <lb/>15) would clearly reflect that the said &quot;khukuri&quot; had blood <lb/>stains on it. Dr. O.T. Lepcha would opine that the cause of <lb/>death, to the best of his knowledge and belief, was due to <lb/></body>

			<page>52 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>fracture with resection of the spinal cord as a result of a <lb/>sharp, moderately heavy weapon homicidal in nature. The <lb/>Investigating Officer would state that the &quot;khukuri&quot; seized from <lb/>the place of occurrence has been sent to CFSL, Kolkatta for <lb/>analysis and examination and the said report would be <lb/>received and placed before the Court through supplementary <lb/>charge-sheet. Dr. Anil Kumar Sharma, would depose that the <lb/>said &quot;khukuri&quot; with large reddish brown stain on the metallic <lb/>part with wooden handle contained in a sealed cloth packet <lb/>was received by him. He would depose that a portion of the <lb/>&quot;khukuri&quot; was examined for the presence of human blood by <lb/>Tetramethyl Benzidine and anti-human Haemoglobin test and <lb/>human blood could be detected therein. The aforesaid <lb/>evidences would cogently and clearly prove that the &quot;khukuri&quot; <lb/>with suspected blood stains had been seized from near the <lb/>place of occurrence and the said &quot;khukuri&quot; was found, in fact, <lb/>to be stained with human blood. The CFSL, Report (exhibit-26) <lb/>would also record the examination of &quot;One metallic knife with <lb/>wooden handle stated to be khukuri of length 18 inches <lb/>approx&quot;. Unfortunately, the genetic profiles from the blood <lb/>stains on the &quot;khukuri&quot; could not be developed after repeated <lb/>experiments which could be due to minute and/or highly <lb/>degraded DNA material. In re: Raja (supra) the Supreme Court <lb/>would observe:-<lb/></body>

			<page>53 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>&quot;19. Another circumstance which has been taken note of by <lb/>the High Court is that the bloodstained clothes and the weapon, the <lb/>knife, were sent to the Forensic Science Laboratory. The report <lb/>obtained from the laboratory clearly shows that bloodstains were <lb/>found on the clothes and the knife. True it is, there has been no <lb/>matching of the blood group. However, that would not make a <lb/>difference in the facts of the present case. The accused has not <lb/>offered any explanation as to how the human blood was found on <lb/>the clothes and the knife. In this regard, a passage from John <lb/>Pandian v. State [John Pandian v. State, (2010) 14 SCC 129 : (2011) <lb/>3 SCC (Cri) 550] is worth reproducing: (SCC p. 153, para 57) <lb/>&quot;57. … The discovery appears to be credible. It has <lb/>been accepted by both the courts below and we find no reason <lb/>to discard it. This is apart from the fact that this weapon was <lb/>sent to the forensic science laboratory (FSL) and it has been <lb/>found stained with human blood. Though the blood group <lb/>could not be ascertained, as the results were inconclusive, the <lb/>accused had to give some explanation as to how the human <lb/>blood came on this weapon. He gave none. This discovery <lb/>would very positively further the prosecution case.&quot; <lb/>In view of the aforesaid, there is no substantial reason not to <lb/>accept the recovery of the weapon used in the crime. It is also apt to <lb/>note here that Dr N.K. Mittal PW 1, has clearly opined that the <lb/>injuries on the person of the deceased could be caused by the knife <lb/>and the said opinion has gone unrebutted.&quot; <lb/>74. Padam Kumar Rai would tell the Court that the police <lb/>also recovered the weapon of offence &quot;khukuri&quot; which was <lb/>given by him to Suren Rai and the deceased for cutting logs. <lb/>This fact is vital. The defence would not deny this statement <lb/>but only assert that the said &quot;khukuri&quot; was not shown to him <lb/>in Court. Although the defence would deny the recovery of <lb/>&quot;khukuri&quot; at the instance of Suren Rai it would assert that the <lb/>said &quot;khukuri&quot; was lying at an open place through the cross-<lb/>examination of Bhadrey Bishwakarma and Dhiraj Rai. Both <lb/>the aforesaid witnesses would identify the &quot;khukuri&quot; as the one <lb/>seized under Property Seizure Memo (exhibit-15). The Property <lb/></body>

			<page>54 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>Seizure Memo (exhibit-15) would be prepared at the place of <lb/>occurrence. <lb/>75. In re: Prithipal Singh v. State of Punjab 13 the Supreme <lb/>Court would hold: <lb/>&quot;Burden of proof under Section 106 <lb/>53. In State of W.B. v. Mir Mohammad Omar [(2000) 8 SCC <lb/>382 : 2000 SCC (Cri) 1516 : AIR 2000 SC 2988] this Court held that <lb/>if fact is especially in the knowledge of any person, then burden of <lb/>proving that fact is upon him. It is impossible for the prosecution to <lb/>prove certain facts particularly within the knowledge of the accused. <lb/>Section 106 is not intended to relieve the prosecution of its burden to <lb/>prove the guilt of the accused beyond reasonable doubt. But the <lb/>section would apply to cases where the prosecution has succeeded <lb/>in proving facts from which a reasonable inference can be drawn <lb/>regarding the existence of certain other facts, unless the accused by <lb/>virtue of his special knowledge regarding such facts, failed to offer <lb/>any explanation which might drive the court to draw a different <lb/>inference. Section 106 of the Evidence Act is designed to meet <lb/>certain exceptional cases, in which, it would be impossible for the <lb/>prosecution to establish certain facts which are particularly within <lb/>the knowledge of the accused. (See also Shambhu Nath Mehra v. <lb/>State of Ajmer [AIR 1956 SC 404 : 1956 Cri LJ 794] , Sucha Singh v. <lb/>State of Punjab [(2001) 4 SCC 375 : 2001 SCC (Cri) 717 : AIR 2001 <lb/>SC 1436] and Sahadevan v. State [(2003) 1 SCC 534 : 2003 SCC <lb/>(Cri) 382 : AIR 2003 SC 215] .)&quot; <lb/>76. Under Section 106 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 <lb/>when any fact is especially within the knowledge of any <lb/>person, the burden of proving the fact is upon him. The only <lb/>person who could throw light on how the &quot;khukuri&quot; which was <lb/>admittedly given to Suren Rai and the deceased by Padam <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">13 (2012) 1 SCC 10 <lb/></note>

			<page>55 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>Kumar Rai was found blood stained with human blood in the <lb/>open space near the place of occurrence, is Suren Rai, since <lb/>the other was hacked to death. No such explanation is <lb/>forthcoming. <lb/>77. The Learned Sessions Judge would hesitate to rely upon <lb/>the seizure of the &quot;khukuri&quot; vide Property Seizure Memo <lb/>(exhibit-15) due to discrepancy in the time in the said memo, <lb/>the disclosure statement and the evidence of Dhiraj Rai who <lb/>stated that the alleged &quot;khukuri&quot; was seized about 10 a.m. The <lb/>disclosure statement would be recorded at Naya Bazar Police <lb/>Station. Disclosure statement would record the date of <lb/>recording the disclosure as 24.05.2013 and the time 1255 hrs. <lb/>The Property Seizure Memo (exhibit-15) would record the place <lb/>of seizure as &quot;in front of the kitchen of Shri Padam Kumar Rai&apos;s <lb/>residence&quot; at &quot;Okherbotey, Zoom, West Sikkim&quot;, the date of <lb/>seizure as 24.05.2013 and the time as 1325. The disclosure <lb/>statement being recorded at Naya Bazar and the seizure of the <lb/>&quot;khukuri&quot; having taken place at Okherbotey there was bound <lb/>to be difference in the time. Dhiraj Rai in his cross-<lb/>examination, however, would state: &quot;Alleged khukuri and other <lb/>material exhibits were seized at about 10 a.m. on the relevant <lb/>day&quot;. The evidence of Dhiraj Rai would be recorded on <lb/>19.05.2015. <lb/></body>

			<page>56 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>78. In re: State of U.P. v. Santosh Kumar 14 the Supreme Court <lb/>would hold: <lb/>&quot;24. In any criminal case where statements are recorded after <lb/>a considerable lapse of time, some inconsistencies are bound to <lb/>occur. But it is the duty of the court to ensure that the truth prevails. <lb/>If on material particulars, the statements of prosecution witnesses <lb/>are consistent, then they cannot be discarded only because of minor <lb/>inconsistencies.&quot; <lb/>79. The Supreme Court in re: Om Prakash v. State of <lb/>Haryana 15 would hold: <lb/>&quot;Every small discrepancy or minor contradictions which may <lb/>erupt in the statements of a witness because of lapse of time, <lb/>keeping in view the educational and other background of the <lb/>witness, cannot be treated as fatal to the case of the prosecution. <lb/>The court must examine the statement in its entirety, correct <lb/>prospective and in light of the attendant circumstances brought on <lb/>record by the prosecution.&quot; <lb/>80. We are of the view that the minor discrepancy of the <lb/>exact time of recovery of the &quot;khukuri&quot; is explainable and can <lb/>be overlooked. The time of seizure as provided by Dhiraj Rai <lb/>was an approximate time and not an exact time that too after <lb/>a gap of two years. Thus, although we are hesitant to rely <lb/>upon the disclosure statement because it has been said to be <lb/>involuntary, the recovery of the blood stained &quot;khukuri&quot; from <lb/>the front of the kitchen of Padam Kumar Rai&apos;s residence and <lb/>close to the place of occurrence which was within the holding <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">14 (2009) 9 SCC 626 <lb/>15 (2011) 14 SCC 309 <lb/></note>

			<page>57 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>of Padam Kumar Rai cannot be doubted. Further, the failure of <lb/>Suren Rai to explain how the &quot;khukuri&quot; given to him and the <lb/>deceased would be found blood stained in an open place close <lb/>to the place of occurrence admittedly occupied by him and the <lb/>deceased till the night before provides a vital link to the chain <lb/>of circumstances. More so when Suren Rai failed to deny the <lb/>fact that the said &quot;khukuri&quot; had been given to him and the <lb/>deceased for cutting logs by Padam Kumar Rai when <lb/>specifically put to him by the Learned Sessions Judge at the <lb/>time of his examination under Section 313 Cr.P.C. <lb/>Evidence of Padam Kumar Rai, Bhadrey Bishwakarma and <lb/>Dhiraj Rai. <lb/>81. The Learned Sessions Judge would hold that: &quot;On deep <lb/>consideration of the evidence of P.W.5, P.W.8 and P.W.9, their <lb/>presence become totally doubtful. If they were present together <lb/>at the P.O. then why P.W.5 did not know about the statement <lb/>made by the accused.&quot; The solitary reason on which the <lb/>Learned Sessions Judge would brush aside the evidence of the <lb/>three witnesses was on the above ground. Padam Kumar Rai <lb/>would be the sole witness present in the vicinity where the <lb/>crime was committed and therefore not only a natural witness <lb/>but also a vital witness. Bhadrey Bishwakarma and Dhiraj Rai <lb/>would be witnesses to the purported disclosure statement, <lb/>seizures, as well as the inquest. Padam Kumar Rai in cross-<lb/></body>

			<page>58 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>examination would state: &quot;It is true that accused person did not <lb/>confess anything before me. It is true that I cannot say what <lb/>statement was given by the accused before the police. It is true <lb/>that Dhiraj Rai and Bhadrey Bishwakarma Panchayat Member <lb/>were accompanying me throughout the investigation process on <lb/>24.05.2013.&quot; (Emphasis supplied). It was not the case of the <lb/>prosecution that Suren Rai confessed before Padam Kumar <lb/>Rai. Padam Kumar Rai was not a witness to the disclosure <lb/>statement or any confessional statement. Padam Kumar Rai <lb/>would clearly depose that he cannot say what statement was <lb/>given before the police by Suren Rai. The disclosure statement <lb/>would be purportedly recorded in the presence of Bhadrey <lb/>Bishwakarma and Dhiraj Rai at the Naya Bazar Police Station <lb/>and not at the place of occurrence i.e. Okherbotey, Zoom, West <lb/>Sikkim. Both the witnesses would clearly state that the <lb/>disclosure statement was made by Suren Rai in their <lb/>presence. It is a completely different matter that we hesitate to <lb/>rely upon the disclosure statement because of the fact that <lb/>both the said witnesses would state that it was not voluntary. <lb/>Bhadrey Bishwakarma in cross-examination would state that: <lb/>&quot;one Padam Kr. Rai was with us on the relevant day.&quot; Bhadrey <lb/>Bishwakarma would not be asked whether Padam Kr. Rai was <lb/>near him when Suren Rai confessed. Dhiraj Rai would not <lb/>even be asked about the presence of Padam Kumar Rai. In <lb/>such circumstances, it is quite evident the defence was trying <lb/></body>

			<page>59 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>to steal a march by the afore-quoted general statement of <lb/>Padam Kumar Rai obviously made on the suggestion of the <lb/>defence. On examination of the depositions of the said three <lb/>witnesses in its entirety, correct prospective and in light of the <lb/>attendant circumstances brought on record by the prosecution <lb/>we are of the view that the same are consistent and brooks no <lb/>hesitation to receive them in evidence. <lb/>Last seen theory <lb/>82. In re: Mohibur Rehman v. State of Assam 16 the Supreme <lb/>Court would hold that there must be a close proximity <lb/>between the events of accused last seen together with <lb/>deceased and the factum of death. This was a case in which <lb/>the dead body was recovered 14 days after the date on which <lb/>the deceased was last seen in the company of the accused. <lb/>83. In re: Sahadevan v. State 17 the Supreme Court would hold: <lb/>&quot;19. The last circumstance relied on by the courts <lb/>below pertains to the stand taken by the appellants in the trial <lb/>as to parting company with Vadivelu. Here we must notice <lb/>that as discussed hereinabove, the prosecution has <lb/>established the fact that Vadivelu was seen in the company of <lb/>the appellants from the morning of 5-3-1985 till at least 5 p.m. <lb/>on the same day, when he was brought to his house and <lb/>thereafter his dead body was found in the morning of 6-3-<lb/>1985. Therefore, it has become obligatory on the appellants to <lb/>satisfy the court as to how, where and in what manner <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">16 (2002) 6 SCC 715 <lb/>17 (2003) 1 SCC 534 <lb/></note>

			<page>60 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>Vadivelu parted company with them. This is on the principle <lb/>that a person who is last found in the company of another, if <lb/>later found missing, then the person with whom he was last <lb/>found has to explain the circumstances in which they parted <lb/>company. In the instant case the appellants have failed to <lb/>discharge this onus. In their statement under Section 313 <lb/>CrPC they have not taken any specific stand whatsoever. In <lb/>the evidence of PW 25, it is elicited that on 5-3-1985 in the <lb/>afternoon when Vadivelu was produced before the said <lb/>witness, he after interrogation allowed Vadivelu to go, but <lb/>then it is found from his evidence that he instructed A-1 to <lb/>keep a watch over Vadivelu. In such circumstances, it was <lb/>incumbent upon A-1 to have explained to the court in what <lb/>circumstances they parted company. He has not given any <lb/>explanation in this regard. On the contrary, the prosecution <lb/>has established the fact that on the very day at about 5 p.m., <lb/>Vadivelu was brought to the house of PW 1 by the appellants <lb/>which was seen by PW 5. This part of the evidence of PW 5 <lb/>has gone unchallenged in the cross-examination and, <lb/>therefore, we will have to proceed on the basis that, what is <lb/>stated by PW 5 in this regard is true. If that be so, the <lb/>prosecution has established the fact that on 5-3-1985 at 5 <lb/>p.m. Vadivelu was still in the company of these appellants <lb/>and, therefore, in the absence of any specific explanation from <lb/>the appellants in this regard, and in view of the other <lb/>incriminating circumstances against the appellants having <lb/>been proved by the prosecution, an adverse inference will <lb/>have to be drawn against these appellants as to their part in <lb/>the missing of Vadivelu. At this point, it may be relevant to <lb/>note that though no specific stand has been taken by the <lb/>appellants as to their parting company with Vadivelu, in their <lb/>statement under Section 313 CrPC, it is seen from the <lb/>evidence of PWs 1 and 5 that A-1 told the said witnesses on <lb/>the night intervening between 5-3-1985 and 6-3-1985 that <lb/>Vadivelu had escaped from the police station when he was <lb/>allowed to sleep in the verandah of the police station. This <lb/>explanation given by A-1 to PW 1 which was also heard by <lb/>PWs 5 and 14, clearly shows that the same is totally false <lb/></body>

			<page>61 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>and obviously was an excuse made by the appellants to <lb/>conceal the true facts and, therefore, this circumstance of A-1 <lb/>making a false statement to PW 1 can also be taken as a <lb/>circumstance against the appellants, in establishing the <lb/>appellants&apos; guilt. This Court in more than one case has held, <lb/>that if the prosecution, based on reliable evidence, establishes <lb/>that the missing person was last seen in the company of the <lb/>accused and was never seen thereafter, it is obligatory on the <lb/>accused to explain the circumstances in which the missing <lb/>person and the accused parted company. (See Joseph v. State <lb/>of Kerala [(2000) 5 SCC 197 : 2000 SCC (Cri) 926] .) Therefore, <lb/>we are in agreement with the finding of the courts below that <lb/>Circumstance 7 also stands established against the <lb/>appellants.&quot; <lb/>[Emphasis supplied] <lb/>84. The Supreme Court in re: Shyamal Ghosh v. State of W.B. 18 <lb/>would hold: <lb/>&quot;73. Application of the &quot;last seen theory&quot; requires a <lb/>possible link between the time when the person was last seen <lb/>alive and the fact of the death of the deceased coming to light. <lb/>There should be a reasonable proximity of time between these <lb/>two events. This proposition of law does not admit of much <lb/>excuse but what has to be seen is that this principle is to be <lb/>applied depending upon the facts and circumstances of a <lb/>given case. This Court in para 21 of Yusuf case [(2011) 11 <lb/>SCC 754 : (2011) 3 SCC (Cri) 620] while referring to Mohd. <lb/>Azad v. State of W.B. [(2008) 15 SCC 449 : (2009) 3 SCC (Cri) <lb/>1082] and State v. Mahender Singh Dahiya [(2011) 3 SCC 109 <lb/>: (2011) 1 SCC (Cri) 821] , held as under: (Yusuf case [(2011) <lb/>11 SCC 754 : (2011) 3 SCC (Cri) 620] , SCC pp. 760-61) <lb/>&quot;21. The last seen theory comes into play where <lb/>the time gap between the point of time when the <lb/></body>

			<page>18 (2012) 7 SCC 646 <lb/>62 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>accused and the deceased were last seen alive and <lb/>when the deceased is found dead is so small that <lb/>possibility of any person other than the accused being <lb/>the author of the crime becomes impossible. (Vide Mohd. <lb/>Azad v. State of W.B. [(2008) 15 SCC 449 : (2009) 3 <lb/>SCC (Cri) 1082] and State v. Mahender Singh Dahiya <lb/>[(2011) 3 SCC 109 : (2011) 1 SCC (Cri) 821] .)&quot; <lb/>74. The reasonableness of the time gap is, therefore, of <lb/>some significance. If the time gap is very large, then it is not <lb/>only difficult but may even not be proper for the court to infer <lb/>that the accused had been last seen alive with the deceased <lb/>and the former, thus, was responsible for commission of the <lb/>offence. The purpose of applying these principles, while <lb/>keeping the time factor in mind, is to enable the court to <lb/>examine that where the time of last seen together and the time <lb/>when the deceased was found dead is short, it inevitably <lb/>leads to the inference that the accused person was <lb/>responsible for commission of the crime and the onus was on <lb/>him to explain how the death occurred.&quot; <lb/>[Emphasis supplied] <lb/>85. In re: Dharam Deo Yadav v. State of U.P. 19 the Supreme <lb/>Court would hold: <lb/>&quot;19. It is trite law that a conviction cannot be recorded <lb/>against the accused merely on the ground that the accused <lb/>was last seen with the deceased. In other words, a conviction <lb/>cannot be based on the only circumstance of last seen <lb/>together. The conduct of the accused and the fact of last seen <lb/>together plus other circumstances have to be looked into. <lb/>Normally, last seen theory comes into play when the time gap, <lb/>between the point of time when the accused and the deceased <lb/>were seen last alive and when the deceased is found dead, is <lb/>so small that the possibility of any person other than the <lb/>accused being the perpetrator of the crime becomes <lb/></body>

			<page>19 (2014) 5 SCC 509 <lb/>63 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>impossible. It will be difficult in some cases to positively <lb/>establish that the deceased was last seen with the accused <lb/>when there is a long gap and possibility of other persons <lb/>coming in between exists. However, if the prosecution, on the <lb/>basis of reliable evidence, establishes that the missing person <lb/>was seen in the company of the accused and was never seen <lb/>thereafter, it is obligatory on the part of the accused to explain <lb/>the circumstances in which the missing person and the <lb/>accused parted company. Reference may be made to the <lb/>judgment of this Court in Sahadevan v. State [(2003) 1 SCC <lb/>534 : 2003 SCC (Cri) 382] . In such a situation, the proximity <lb/>of time between the event of last seen together and the <lb/>recovery of the dead body or the skeleton, as the case may be, <lb/>may not be of much consequence. PWs 1, 2, 3, 5, 9 and 10 <lb/>have all deposed that the accused was last seen with Diana. <lb/>But, as already indicated, to record a conviction, that itself <lb/>would not be sufficient and the prosecution has to complete <lb/>the chain of circumstances to bring home the guilt of the <lb/>accused.&quot; <lb/>[Emphasis supplied] <lb/>86. In the present case the evidence of Padam Kumar Rai <lb/>would clearly prove that Suren Rai was last seen with the <lb/>deceased in the temporary shed a little latter after 8.00 p.m. <lb/>on 23.05.2013. The dead body of the deceased was then <lb/>discovered by Padam Kumar Rai the very next day on <lb/>24.05.2013 at 6.00 a.m. barely ten hours later in the <lb/>temporary shed in which, admittedly, both the deceased and <lb/>Suren Rai were last residing together. In fact it is even the <lb/>defence case that Suren Rai was with the deceased till 8.30 <lb/>p.m. on 23.05.2013. Suren Rai would admit in his statement <lb/>under Section 313 Cr.P.C. that he was with the deceased at <lb/></body>

			<page>64 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>the place of occurrence till 8.30 pm on 23.05.2013. Padam <lb/>Kumar Rai would clearly depose that after Suren Rai left his <lb/>house he went off to sleep as it was raining. This is an <lb/>important fact. The defence would not even attempt to deny <lb/>this fact. The defence would not be able to tarnish Padam <lb/>Kumar Rai&apos;s deposition. In fact through Padam Kumar Rai&apos;s <lb/>cross-examination the defence would assert that Suren Rai <lb/>had appeared before Padam Kumar Rai at around 8.30 p.m. <lb/>The only person who was present in the vicinity of the place of <lb/>occurrence was Padam Kumar Rai. However, from the <lb/>evidence adduced it is certain that Padam Kumar Rai was <lb/>asleep when the crime was perpetrated. The defence would not <lb/>even try to point a needle of suspicion towards Padam Kumar <lb/>Rai and suggest instead, in his cross-examination, that there <lb/>was &quot;some other person&quot; in the temporary shed of Suren Rai <lb/>and the deceased. The only person who could have named the <lb/>said &quot;some other person&quot; is Suren Rai as the other is dead. It is <lb/>quite obvious that this is a false defence. The fact that when <lb/>Suren Rai left the house of Padam Kumar Rai it would be <lb/>raining and Padam Kumar Rai would go to sleep was <lb/>specifically put to Suren Rai by the Learned Sessions Judge <lb/>and in reply thereof Suren Rai in his statement under Section <lb/>313 Cr.P.C. would admit it to be true. It is evident that there is <lb/>proximity of both time and place in the present case. The time <lb/>gap between the point of time when Suren Rai and the <lb/></body>

			<page>65 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>deceased was seen together and deceased alive then and when <lb/>the deceased was found dead within a period of just about 10 <lb/>hours, all of it in the middle of the rainy night at a remote <lb/>village-Okherbotey, Zoom, West Sikkim, is so small that the <lb/>possibility of any other person other than Suren Rai being the <lb/>perpetrator of the crime would become impossible. It is also <lb/>admitted that immediately prior to the death of the deceased <lb/>there was a quarrel between the deceased and Suren Rai. <lb/>87. It is trite that the circumstance of last seen together <lb/>cannot by itself form the basis of holding the accused guilty of <lb/>the offence. <lb/>However, where the other links would be <lb/>satisfactorily made out and the circumstances would point to <lb/>the guilt of the accused, the circumstance of last seen together <lb/>and absence of explanation would provide an additional link <lb/>which would complete the chain. <lb/>88. <lb/>The Learned Sessions Judge would rely upon the <lb/>statement of Padam Kumar Rai in cross-examination to hold <lb/>that his statement does not lend full support to the <lb/>prosecution case. The said statement is:-<lb/>&quot;………It is true that when the accused appeared before me at <lb/>around 8.30 pm at my house and thereafter, I cannot say whether <lb/>he left towards his temporary shed or somewhere else.&quot; <lb/>89. <lb/>The evidence of Padam Kumar Rai would establish that <lb/>on the fateful night of 23.05.2013 Suren Rai and the deceased <lb/></body>

			<page>66 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>were together after 08.00 pm at the temporary shed in which <lb/>both Suren Rai and the deceased, admittedly, were residing till <lb/>the fateful day. Padam Kumar Rai would also state that after <lb/>he met the deceased and Suren Rai in the temporary shed, he <lb/>returned home and &quot;Suren Rai came following me&quot;. In cross-<lb/>examination, Padam Kumar Rai would thus concede that he <lb/>could not say whether Suren Rai went towards his temporary <lb/>shed or somewhere else. It would be because of this statement <lb/>of Padam Kumar Rai that the Learned Sessions Judge would <lb/>find it unsafe to rely on the last seen theory. What Padam <lb/>Kumar Rai said was absolutely truthful; how could he have <lb/>known where Suren Rai went after they parted? The Learned <lb/>Sessions Judge was required to examine what happened after <lb/>they parted instead of dismissing the last seen theory, which <lb/>in fact, was even admitted by Suren Rai in his statement <lb/>under Section 313 Cr.P.C. Being last seen with the deceased, <lb/>Suren Rai had sought to explain under what circumstances he <lb/>had parted ways with the deceased who had been residing <lb/>with him till that fateful night in his statement under Section <lb/>313 Cr.P.C. The relevant questions and answers are <lb/>reproduced herein:-<lb/>&quot;Q.No.14. It is in the evidence of PW-5 Shri Padam Kr. Rai that he <lb/>knows you. He is a resident of Zoom. At the relevant time, you were <lb/>hired by him to work as a lumberjack at his house. Along with you, <lb/>deceased Monit Rai also worked with you. About 100 meters away <lb/>from his house, you and the deceased had build a temporary shed <lb/></body>

			<page>67 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>with plastic and GIS sheets and the same could be seen from the <lb/>Veranda of his house. <lb/>What have you to say? <lb/>Ans. It is true. <lb/>Q.No.15. PW-5 deposed that on 23.05.2013, around 8 pm, you came <lb/>to his house and requested him to pacify the deceased Monit Rai as <lb/>he was provoking you into a fight regarding his mobile phone. He <lb/>told you that he will be coming later and after some time, he went <lb/>to your temporary shed and saw that you were having your meal <lb/>and deceased Monit Rai was sitting inside the temporary shed. He <lb/>asked both of you about the matter and he was told that deceased <lb/>Monit Rai had misplaced his mobile phone and was blaming for it. <lb/>What have you to say? <lb/>Ans. It is true. <lb/>Q.No.16. PW-5 deposed that he told both of you, not to fight over <lb/>such things and look for the mobile phone as it could be misplaced <lb/>somewhere and could be found later. Accordingly, he went to his <lb/>house and you came following him and he again asked you whether <lb/>you found the mobile phone. Thereafter, you left his house and it <lb/>started raining heavily he went to sleep. <lb/>What have you to say? <lb/>Ans. It is true. <lb/>xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx <lb/>Q.No.58. Do you have any statements to make in your defense? <lb/>Ans:-I am innocent and I did not commit any offence. I humbly <lb/>submitted that on the relevant night when I requested the <lb/>complainant twice for settlement of dispute between me and the <lb/>deceased (Monit Rai) but the complainant did not take positive steps <lb/>and I was continuously harassed and threatened by the deceased <lb/>Monit Rai to kill and due to the fear I left for Karmatand around 8.30 <lb/>pm on 23.05.2013 and as such, I have no knowledge about the <lb/>murder of the deceased Monit Rai.&quot; <lb/>90. Section 313 Cr.P.C is an important section of the Code of <lb/>Criminal Procedure. Section 313 Cr.P.C requires the Court to <lb/>put questions to the accused for the purpose of enabling the <lb/>accused &quot;personally&quot; to explain any circumstances appearing <lb/></body>

			<page>68 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>in the evidence against him. The section enables a direct <lb/>interaction between the Court and the accused for the sole <lb/>purpose of allowing the accused to provide his explanation to <lb/>each and every incriminating circumstance appearing in the <lb/>evidence. The statement is not to be taken on oath which is <lb/>prohibited under sub-section (3) thereof. The accused shall not <lb/>render himself liable to punishment by refusing to answer <lb/>such questions, or by giving false answers to them. The <lb/>answers, however, given by the accused may be taken into <lb/>consideration in such enquiry or trial, and put in evidence for <lb/>or against him in any other enquiry into, or trial for, any other <lb/>offence which such answers may tend to show that he had <lb/>committed. Under Section 313 Cr.P.C the accused has a duty <lb/>to furnish explanation in his statement regarding any <lb/>incriminating material that has been produced against him. It <lb/>is not sufficient compliance with the section to generally ask <lb/>the accused what he has to say after having heard the <lb/>prosecution evidence. Every material circumstance must be <lb/>questioned separately. Providing fair, proper and sufficient <lb/>opportunity to the accused to explain the circumstances <lb/>appearing against him should be the whole object of the Court <lb/>in compliance with Section 313 Cr.P.C. The Court must be <lb/>particularly sensitive when the accused is ignorant or illiterate <lb/>and may not understand the language of Court. The questions <lb/>must be simple and understandable even to an illiterate and <lb/></body>

			<page>69 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>ignorant of the law. Preferably the Court should avoid using <lb/>legal language and keep the questions simple especially while <lb/>dealing with people who are uneducated, illiterate, ignorant or <lb/>simple. The question should be short and each new <lb/>incriminating fact must be separately put to the accused. If <lb/>the accused is unable to understand the language of the <lb/>Court, the Court must translate the question in the language <lb/>understood by the accused. It is obligatory on the accused <lb/>while being examined to furnish explanation with respect to <lb/>incriminating circumstances against him and the Court is <lb/>duty bound to note such explanation even in a case of <lb/>circumstantial evidence. Section 313 Cr.P.C. was enacted for <lb/>the benefit of the accused. <lb/>91. It is trite that in a case like the present one where the <lb/>various links as stated above have been satisfactorily made <lb/>out and the circumstances point to the appellant as the <lb/>probable assailant, with reasonable definiteness and in <lb/>proximity to the deceased as regards time and situation, his <lb/>failure to offer any explanation, which if accepted, though not <lb/>proved, would afford a reasonable basis for a conclusion on <lb/>the entire case consistent with his innocence, such absence of <lb/>explanation or false explanation would itself be an additional <lb/>link which completes the chain. <lb/></body>

			<page>70 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>92. The failure of the accused to offer any explanation in his <lb/>Section 313 Cr.P.C. statement alone would not be sufficient to <lb/>establish the charge against the accused. The Court can, <lb/>however, rely on a portion of the statement of the accused and <lb/>find him guilty in consideration of other evidence against him. <lb/>The accused has a right to maintain silence during <lb/>examination <lb/>or <lb/>completely <lb/>deny <lb/>the <lb/>incriminating <lb/>circumstance but in such an event adverse inference could be <lb/>drawn against him. <lb/>93. Suren Rai has accepted as true substantially all the <lb/>deposition of Padam Kumar Rai till Suren Rai left the house of <lb/>Padam Kumar Rai on the fateful night. In fact in his <lb/>explanation to what transpired after Suren Rai left the house <lb/>of Padam Kumar Rai, Suren Rai would state that since Padam <lb/>Kumar Rai did not take positive steps to settle the dispute <lb/>between him and the deceased and as he was continuously <lb/>harassed and threatened by the deceased to kill, due to fear, <lb/>he left for Karmatar around 08.30 pm on 23.05.2013. Suren <lb/>Rai&apos;s explanation, however, does not inspire confidence. <lb/>Admittedly, Suren Rai was there at the scene of crime till <lb/>08.30 pm on 23.05.2013. Suren Rai also admits his arrest the <lb/>very next day. Suren Rai&apos;s arrest at Karmatar is cogently <lb/>proved by the evidence of two Police Officers, Constable <lb/>Topden Lepcha and Home guard Yamnath Sharma on <lb/></body>

			<page>71 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>24.05.2015 as well as the arrest Memo (exhibit-24) proved by <lb/>the Investigating Officer. At the time of the arrest on <lb/>24.05.2013 at 1245 hours it would be proved that three <lb/>wearing apparels had been seized from Suren Rai in the <lb/>presence of Dhiraj Rai and Bhadrey Biswakarma when he was <lb/>brought from Karmatar to Naya Bazar Police Station. <lb/>94. <lb/>The aforesaid three items were seized vide Property <lb/>Seizure Memo (exhibit-19) duly signed by the Investigating <lb/>Officer as well as the aforesaid two witnesses. The defence, <lb/>quite clearly, would not be able to demolish the aforesaid <lb/>seizure. The Investigating Officer, Dhiraj Rai and Bhadrey <lb/>Biswakarma would cogently prove it. <lb/>95. Suren Rai, however, would provide no explanation to this <lb/>circumstance appearing against him, although, he would be <lb/>the only person who would have been able to explain the same <lb/>when the question is put to him. Suren Rai would simply deny <lb/>it by saying: &quot;it is not true&quot; when the specific circumstance is <lb/>put to him by the Learned Sessions Judge under Section 313 <lb/>Cr.P.C. The said three wearing apparels seized vide property <lb/>seizure memo (exhibit-19) were sent for forensic examination <lb/>to CFSL, Kolkata for its examination. The Investigating Officer <lb/>also collected blood sample of Suren Rai vide requisition letter <lb/>(exhibit-11). The result of the forensic examination would be <lb/>placed before the Court through Dr. Anil Kumar Sharma who <lb/></body>

			<page>72 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>would prove the Forensic Examination Report dated <lb/>29.06.2015 (exhibit-25). <lb/>96. <lb/>The Forensic Examination Report (exhibit-26) would <lb/>opine about the said three wearing apparels seized from the <lb/>possession of Suren Rai at the Naya Bazar Police Station vide <lb/>Property Seizure Memo (exhibit-19). The result of the <lb/>examination would reflect that the soil particles found in the <lb/>blue faded jeans of Suren Rai seized after his arrest were <lb/>found to be similar to the sample soil particles collected from <lb/>the place of occurrence seized vide (exhibit-18). The Forensic <lb/>Examination Report dated 29.06.2015 (exhibit-25) would <lb/>opine that human blood could be detected in the said wearing <lb/>apparels seized from Suren Rai. It would also be opined that <lb/>the blood stains in the black T-shirt and the blue jeans pant <lb/>were of Suren Rai. Suren Rai would be examined by Dr. S. N. <lb/>Adhikari at PHC Jorethang, South Sikkim on 24.05.2013 at <lb/>12.40 p.m. His examination would reveal that Suren Rai had <lb/>no injuries. The Learned Sessions Judge would observe that: <lb/>&quot;If there was such fight between the accused and the deceased <lb/>one day prior to the incident, the accused would have sustained <lb/>some injury&quot;. It is not necessary that in every fight there must <lb/>be injury sustained by both the parties. However, what is vital <lb/>is that it would be proved that at the time of his arrest Suren <lb/>Rai was in possession of his blood stained wearing apparels <lb/></body>

			<page>73 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>which would also be seized. It was incumbent upon Suren Rai <lb/>to explain how he was in possession of his blood stained <lb/>wearing apparels on 24.05.2013, the day of his arrest, when <lb/>he clearly denied any physical brawl between him and the <lb/>deceased in the intervening night of 23.05.2013 and <lb/>24.05.2013 when admittedly they had quarrelled over a mobile <lb/>phone. In re: Gajanan Dashrath Kharate v. State of <lb/>Maharashtra 20 the Supreme Court would hold: <lb/>&quot;13. As seen from the evidence, appellant Gajanan and <lb/>his father Dashrath and mother Mankarnabai were living <lb/>together. On 7-4-2002, mother of the appellant-accused had <lb/>gone to another Village Dahigaon. The prosecution has proved <lb/>presence of the appellant at his home on the night of 7-4-<lb/>2002. Therefore, the appellant is duty-bound to explain as to <lb/>how the death of his father was caused. When an offence like <lb/>murder is committed in secrecy inside a house, the initial <lb/>burden to establish the case would undoubtedly be upon the <lb/>prosecution. In view of Section 106 of the Evidence Act, there <lb/>will be a corresponding burden on the inmates of the house to <lb/>give cogent explanation as to how the crime was committed. <lb/>The inmates of the house cannot get away by simply keeping <lb/>quiet and offering no explanation on the supposed premise <lb/>that the burden to establish its case lies entirely upon the <lb/>prosecution and there is no duty at all on the accused to offer. <lb/>On the date of the occurrence, when the accused and his <lb/>father Dashrath were in the house and when the father of the <lb/>accused was found dead, it was for the accused to offer an <lb/>explanation as to how his father sustained injuries. When the <lb/>accused could not offer any explanation as to the homicidal <lb/>death of his father, it is a strong circumstance against the <lb/>accused that he is responsible for the commission of the crime. <lb/></body>

			<page>20 (2016) 4 SCC 604 <lb/>74 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>14. In Trimukh Maroti Kirkan v. State of Maharashtra <lb/>[Trimukh Maroti Kirkan v. State of Maharashtra, (2006) 10 <lb/>SCC 681 : (2007) 1 SCC (Cri) 80] , it was held as under: (SCC <lb/>pp. 694-95, para 22) <lb/>&quot;22. Where an accused is alleged to have <lb/>committed the murder of his wife and the prosecution <lb/>succeeds in leading evidence to show that shortly <lb/>before the commission of crime they were seen together <lb/>or the offence takes place in the dwelling home where <lb/>the husband also normally resided, it has been <lb/>consistently held that if the accused does not offer any <lb/>explanation how the wife received injuries or offers an <lb/>explanation which is found to be false, it is a strong <lb/>circumstance which indicates that he is responsible for <lb/>commission of the crime. In Nika Ram v. State of H.P. <lb/>[Nika Ram v. State of H.P., (1972) 2 SCC 80 : 1972 SCC <lb/>(Cri) 635] it was observed that the fact that the accused <lb/>alone was with his wife in the house when she was <lb/>murdered there with &quot;khukhri&quot; and the fact that the <lb/>relations of the accused with her were strained would, <lb/>in the absence of any cogent explanation by him, point <lb/>to his guilt. In Ganeshlal v. State of Maharashtra <lb/>[Ganeshlal v. State of Maharashtra, (1992) 3 SCC 106 : <lb/>1993 SCC (Cri) 435] the appellant was prosecuted for <lb/>the murder of his wife which took place inside his <lb/>house. It was observed that when the death had <lb/>occurred in his custody, the appellant is under an <lb/>obligation to give a plausible explanation for the cause <lb/>of her death in his statement under Section 313 CrPC. <lb/>The mere denial of the prosecution case coupled with <lb/>absence of any explanation was held to be inconsistent <lb/>with the innocence of the accused, but consistent with <lb/>the hypothesis that the appellant is a prime accused in <lb/>the commission of murder of his wife. In State of U.P. v. <lb/>Ravindra Prakash Mittal [State of U.P. v. Ravindra <lb/>Prakash Mittal, (1992) 3 SCC 300 : 1992 SCC (Cri) 642] <lb/>the medical evidence disclosed that the wife died of <lb/></body>

			<page>75 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>strangulation during late night hours or early morning <lb/>and her body was set on fire after sprinkling kerosene. <lb/>The defence of the husband was that the wife had <lb/>committed suicide by burning herself and that he was <lb/>not at home at that time. The letters written by the wife <lb/>to her relatives showed that the husband ill-treated her <lb/>and their relations were strained and further the <lb/>evidence showed that both of them were in one room in <lb/>the night. It was held that the chain of circumstances <lb/>was complete and it was the husband who committed <lb/>the murder of his wife by strangulation and accordingly <lb/>this Court reversed the judgment of the High Court <lb/>acquitting the accused and convicted him under Section <lb/>302 IPC. In State of T.N. v. Rajendran [State of T.N. v. <lb/>Rajendran, (1999) 8 SCC 679 : 2000 SCC (Cri) 40] the <lb/>wife was found dead in a hut which had caught fire. <lb/>The evidence showed that the accused and his wife <lb/>were seen together in the hut at about 9.00 p.m. and <lb/>the accused came out in the morning through the roof <lb/>when the hut had caught fire. His explanation was that <lb/>it was a case of accidental fire which resulted in the <lb/>death of his wife and a daughter. The medical evidence <lb/>showed that the wife died due to asphyxia as a result <lb/>of strangulation and not on account of burn injuries. It <lb/>was held that there cannot be any hesitation to come to <lb/>the conclusion that it was the accused (husband) who <lb/>was the perpetrator of the crime.&quot; <lb/>Same view was reiterated by this Court in State of Rajasthan <lb/>v. Parthu [State of Rajasthan v. Parthu, (2007) 12 SCC 754: <lb/>(2009) 3 SCC (Cri) 507].&quot; <lb/>97. Under Section 106 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 <lb/>Suren Rai was required to discharge the burden of proving the <lb/>said fact especially within his knowledge. Suren Rai has <lb/>offered no such explanations. The presence of blood stains in <lb/></body>

			<page>76 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>Suren Rai&apos;s wearing apparels seized at the time of his arrest <lb/>shortly after the crime is surely a circumstance against him <lb/>which remained unexplained. The cumulative effect of the <lb/>admitted fact of the quarrel between Suren Rai and the <lb/>deceased, the fact that Suren Rai failed to explain the <lb/>incriminating circumstance of human blood in his wearing <lb/>apparels seized at the time of his arrest on 24.05.2013 itself, <lb/>the fact that Suren Rai made a false defence of an unknown: <lb/>&quot;some other person&quot;, the impossibility of: &quot;some other person&quot; <lb/>or even Padam Kumar Rai being even a suspect along with the <lb/>fact that Suren Rai was admittedly last seen with the deceased <lb/>at 8.30 p.m. in the temporary shed i.e. the place of occurrence <lb/>on 23.05.2013 and in spite of all these Suren Rai would offer <lb/>no reasonable explanation would itself be the additional vital <lb/>link in the chain of circumstances against Suren Rai all of <lb/>which, as stated above, had been cogently established. <lb/>98. The evidence produced by the prosecution and tested by <lb/>a detailed and intrusive cross-examination by the defence has <lb/>cogently established the following circumstances against <lb/>Suren Rai:-<lb/>(i) Suren Rai and the deceased had been hired by Padam <lb/>Kumar Rai to work as &quot;lumberjacks&quot; at his premises at <lb/>Zoom. <lb/>(ii) <lb/>Suren Rai and the deceased had built a temporary shed with <lb/>plastic and GIS sheets close to Padam Kumar Rai&apos;s house. <lb/></body>

			<page>77 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>(iii) <lb/>On 23.05.2013 around 8 p.m. Suren Rai went to Padam <lb/>Kumar Rai&apos;s house and requested him to pacify the deceased <lb/>as he was provoking him into a fight regarding his mobile <lb/>phone. This circumstance provides the animus nocendi or <lb/>the intention to harm for Suren Rai to commit the offence. <lb/>(iv) <lb/>Padam Kumar Rai visited the temporary shed after sometime <lb/>and found Suren Rai and the deceased together inside the <lb/>temporary shed. The deceased was alive then. <lb/>(v) <lb/>A little while later, Suren Rai came to the house of Padam <lb/>Kumar Rai who asked him about the mobile. It was raining <lb/>heavily that night. Suren Rai left Padam Kumar Rai&apos;s house <lb/>after which Padam Kumar Rai went off to sleep. This was the <lb/>time when Suren Rai was last seen. <lb/>(vi) <lb/>Next morning at 6 a.m. when Padam Kumar Rai discovered <lb/>the dead body of the deceased and the GIS sheet used to <lb/>make the temporary shed splattered with blood, Suren Rai <lb/>was not there without informing his hirer, Padam Kumar Rai. <lb/>(vii) The FIR was lodged by Padam Kumar Rai on 24.05.2013 at <lb/>8.45 a.m. to 9 a.m. <lb/>(viii) Suren Rai was arrested from Karmatar School ground, <lb/>Darjeeling and brought to the Naya Bazar Police Station on <lb/>24.05.2013 and formally arrested at the Naya Bazar Police <lb/>Station at 1250 hrs. <lb/>(ix) <lb/>At the time of his arrest three wearing apparels of Suren Rai, <lb/>all of them blood stained, were seized by the Investigating <lb/>Officer. The blood stains on the said wearing apparel were <lb/>found to be that of Suren Rai on forensic examination. Save <lb/>a bald denial, Suren Rai failed to provide a convincing <lb/>explanation to his blood in his wearing apparels including <lb/>his underwear. If there was no physical brawl Suren Rai had <lb/>got into there was no reason for the blood to be found. <lb/>(x) <lb/>The soil particles found in the blue jean pant seized from <lb/>Suren Rai after his arrest matched the soil particles from the <lb/>place of occurrence. <lb/></div>

			<page>78 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>(xi) <lb/>After the arrest of Suren Rai a blood stained &quot;khukuri&quot; which <lb/>was give to Suren Rai and the deceased was recovered from <lb/>outside the kitchen of Padam Kumar Rai close to the <lb/>temporary shed where the deceased suffered:-(1) multiple <lb/>gaping chop wounds over the back of the neck situated <lb/>below the skull involving the neck and the back; (2) chop <lb/>wound 12 x 2 cm x bone situated over the posterior aspect of <lb/>neck, 1.8 cms behind the right ear involving the scalp, bone <lb/>and direct downward and outward; (3) chop wound 11 x 2 <lb/>cms, 1.8 cms below the first injury directed downwards <lb/>involving skin muscle and second and third cervical <lb/>vertebrae; (4) chop wound, 21 x 2.8 cms situated at 2.5 cms <lb/>below injury No. 2 and extended up to the lower angle of <lb/>mandible. The wound involved the skin, muscle, vessels and <lb/>the spinal cord, which clean cut with fracture of second <lb/>cervical vertebrae; (5) Spindal shaped injury 15 x 4.5 cms x <lb/>bone covering the right shoulder with underline fracture of <lb/>shoulder joint and; (6) Spindal shaped injury 2 x 1.5 cms <lb/>involving skin, muscle and bone over the right upper back <lb/>situated 4.5 cms below and middle to injury No.5. The <lb/>medical opinion opined that the cause of death was due to <lb/>fracture and resection of the spinal cord as a result of a <lb/>sharp, moderately heavy weapon homicidal in nature. <lb/>(xii) The failure of Suren Rai to convincingly explain the <lb/>circumstances appearing in evidence against him including <lb/>the fact that admittedly he was last seen with the deceased <lb/>at around 8:30 p.m. on 23.05.2013 barely 10 hours before <lb/>the dead body of the deceased was discovered and the blood <lb/>being noticed and proved on his wearing apparels seized at <lb/>the time of the arrest after 6 hours 45 minutes of the <lb/>discovery of the dead body of the deceased brutally hacked to <lb/>death. <lb/>99. This is a case of circumstantial evidence as said before. <lb/>We have re-examined the entire case and marshalled the <lb/>evidence and documents on record. We are constrained to hold <lb/></body>

			<page>79 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>that the Learned Sessions Judges conclusion and the <lb/>consequential judgment of acquittal is not at all a possible or <lb/>plausible view. Each of the other circumstances, as held <lb/>above, having been conclusively proved by the prosecution, we <lb/>are of the view that the only gap in the chain of circumstances <lb/>has been conclusively filled by the aforesaid evidence and <lb/>circumstances. The factum of Suren Rai being last seen <lb/>together with the deceased, the blood on his wearing apparels, <lb/>soil particles in his blue jeans pant matching the soil at the <lb/>place of occurrence, the recovery of human blood stained <lb/>&quot;khukuri&quot;, definitely a sharp, moderately heavy weapon (which <lb/>has been cogently proved to have caused the death of the <lb/>deceased) given by Padam Kumar Rai to Suren Rai and the <lb/>deceased for cutting wood on 24.05.2013 from near the place <lb/>of occurrence itself are strong circumstances against Suren <lb/>Rai directly connecting him to the crime. Suren Rai&apos;s failure to <lb/>convincingly explain the incriminating circumstances as above <lb/>including the factum of his being last seen together, together <lb/>with the fact that there was a short gap would eventually lead <lb/>to the inference that Suren Rai was responsible for the crime <lb/>against the deceased and it was incumbent upon Suren Rai to <lb/>explain how the death occurred. His failure to do so fortifies <lb/>our conclusion of guilt of Suren Rai. There is no one else in the <lb/>same circumstance with even a remote possibility of the same <lb/>motive. All the proved facts are consistent only with the <lb/></body>

			<page>80 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>hypothesis of the guilt of Suren Rai and no other. The <lb/>circumstances are of conclusive nature and exclude every <lb/>possible hypothesis except that it is Suren Rai and Suren Rai <lb/>alone who is guilty of the crime. The chain of evidence is <lb/>complete. We, thus, hold that the view adopted by the Learned <lb/>Sessions Judge is not a reasonable one in the conclusion <lb/>reached by it and does not have its ground well set out on the <lb/>materials on record. The judgment passed by the Learned <lb/>Sessions Judge acquitting Suren Rai is not only unreasonable <lb/>but palpably wrong, manifestly erroneous and demonstrably <lb/>unsustainable. <lb/>100. The confessional statement of Suren Rai would disclose <lb/>that Suren Rai and the deceased would consume alcohol in <lb/>their temporary shed at around 2100 hours. They would get a <lb/>little intoxicated. The deceased would go out for a while and <lb/>return after having consumed more alcohol and start <lb/>provoking Suren Rai into a fight. The deceased would then <lb/>hurl a &quot;khukuri&quot; at him. Suren Rai would believe that this <lb/>assault was to kill him. Suren Rai would dodge himself, take <lb/>the &quot;khukuri&quot; from the deceased and use it to give three fatal <lb/>blows on the neck of the deceased. Suren Rai would stay in <lb/>the temporary shed for half an hour more till which time the <lb/>decease would be still alive and thereafter he would run off <lb/>towards Naya Bazar. <lb/></body>

			<page>81 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>101. Section 96 IPC, 1860 provides:-<lb/>&quot;96. Things done in private defence. -Nothing is an <lb/>offence which is done in the exercise of the right of private <lb/>defence.&apos;&apos; <lb/>102. Section 97 IPC, 1860 provides:-<lb/>&quot;97. Right of private defence of the body and of <lb/>property.-Every person has a right, subject to the restrictions <lb/>contained in section 99, to defend-<lb/>First.-His own body, and the body of any other person, <lb/>against any offence affecting the human body; <lb/>Secondly.-The property, whether movable or immovable, of <lb/>himself or of any other person, against any act which is an <lb/>offence falling under the definition of theft, robbery, mischief or <lb/>criminal trespass, or which is an attempt to commit theft, <lb/>robbery, mischief or criminal trespass.&apos;&apos; <lb/>103. Section 99 IPC, 1860 provides:-<lb/>&quot;99. Acts against which there is no right of private <lb/>defence.-There is no right of private defence against an act <lb/>which does not reasonably cause the apprehension of death or <lb/>of grievous hurt, if done, or attempted to be done, by a public <lb/>servant acting in good faith under colour of his office, though <lb/>that act, may not be strictly justifiable by law. <lb/>There is no right of private defence against an act which <lb/>does not reasonably cause the apprehension of death or of <lb/>grievous hurt, if done, or attempted to be done, by the direction <lb/>of a public servant acting in good faith under colour of his <lb/>office, though that direction may not be strictly justifiable by <lb/>law. <lb/></body>

			<page>82 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>There is not right of private defence in cases in which <lb/>there is time to have recourse to the protection of the public <lb/>authorities. <lb/>Extent to which the right may be exercised.-The right of <lb/>private defence in no case extends to the inflicting of more <lb/>harm than it is necessary to inflict for the purpose of defence. <lb/>Explanation 1.-A person is not deprived of the right of <lb/>private defence against an act done, or attempted to be done, <lb/>by a public servant, so such, unless he knows or has reason <lb/>to believe, that the person doing the act is such public servant. <lb/>Explanation 2.-A person is not deprived of the right or <lb/>private defence against an act done, or attempted to be done, <lb/>by the direction of a public servant, unless he knows, or has <lb/>reason to believe, that the person doing the act is acting by <lb/>such direction, or unless such person states the authority <lb/>under which he acts, or if he has authority in writing, unless <lb/>he produces such authority, if demanded.&apos;&apos; <lb/>104. Section 100 IPC, 1860 provides:-<lb/>&quot;100. When the right of private defence of the body <lb/>extends to causing death.-The right of private defence of the <lb/>body extends, under the restrictions mentioned in the last <lb/>preceding section, to the voluntary causing of death or of any <lb/>other harm to the assailant, if the offence which occasions the <lb/>exercise of the right be of any of the descriptions hereinafter <lb/>enumerated, namely:--<lb/>First.--Such an assault as may reasonably cause the <lb/>apprehension that death will otherwise be the consequence of <lb/>such assault; <lb/>Secondly.--Such an assault as may reasonably cause the <lb/>apprehension that grievous hurt will otherwise be the <lb/>consequence of such assault; <lb/>Thirdly.--An assault with the intention of committing rape; <lb/>Fourthly.--An assault with the intention of gratifying unnatural <lb/>lust; <lb/></body>

			<page>83 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>Fifthly.--An assault with the intention of kidnapping or <lb/>abducting; <lb/>Sixthly.--An assault with the intention of wrongfully confining a <lb/>person, under circumstances which may reasonably cause him <lb/>to apprehend that he will be unable to have recourse to the <lb/>public authorities for his release. <lb/>[Seventhly.--An act of throwing or administering acid or an <lb/>attempt to throw or administer acid which may reasonably <lb/>cause the apprehension that grievous hurt will otherwise be the <lb/>consequence of such act.]&apos;&apos; <lb/>105. Section 102 IPC, 1860 provides:-<lb/>&quot;102. Commencement and continuance of the right of <lb/>private defence of the body.-The right of private defence of <lb/>the body commences as soon as a reasonable apprehension of <lb/>danger to the body arises from an attempt or threat to commit <lb/>the offence though the offence may not have been committed; <lb/>and it continues as long as such apprehension of danger to the <lb/>body continues.&apos;&apos; <lb/>106. In re: Laxman Singh v. Poonam Singh 21 the Supreme Court <lb/>would hold:-<lb/>&quot;6. The only question which needs to be considered is the <lb/>alleged exercise of the right of private defence. Section 96 IPC <lb/>provides that nothing is an offence which is done in the <lb/>exercise of the right of private defence. The section does not <lb/>define the expression &quot;right of private defence&quot;. It merely <lb/>indicates that nothing is an offence which is done in the <lb/>exercise of such right. Whether in a particular set of <lb/>circumstances, a person acted in the exercise of the right of <lb/>private defence is a question of fact to be determined on the <lb/>21 <lb/>(2004) 10 SCC 94 <lb/></body>

			<page>84 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>facts and circumstances of each case. No test in the abstract <lb/>for determining such a question can be laid down. In <lb/>determining this question of fact, the court must consider all <lb/>the surrounding circumstances. It is not necessary for the <lb/>accused to plead in so many words that he acted in self-<lb/>defence. If the circumstances show that the right of private <lb/>defence was legitimately exercised, it is open to the court to <lb/>consider such a plea. In a given case the court can consider it <lb/>even if the accused has not taken it, if the same is available to <lb/>be considered from the material on record. Under Section 105 <lb/>of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (in short &quot;the Evidence Act&quot;), <lb/>the burden of proof is on the accused, who sets off the plea of <lb/>self-defence, and, in absence of proof, it is not possible for the <lb/>court to presume the truth of the plea of self-defence. The court <lb/>shall presume the absence of such circumstances. It is for the <lb/>accused to place necessary material on record either by <lb/>himself adducing positive evidence or by eliciting necessary <lb/>facts from the witnesses examined for the prosecution. An <lb/>accused taking the plea of the right of private defence is not <lb/>required to call evidence; he can establish his plea by <lb/>reference to circumstances transpiring from the prosecution <lb/>evidence itself. The question in such a case would be a <lb/>question of assessing the true effect of the prosecution <lb/>evidence, and not a question of the accused discharging any <lb/>burden. Where the right of private defence is pleaded, the <lb/>defence must be a reasonable and probable version satisfying <lb/>the court that the harm caused by the accused was necessary <lb/>for either warding off the attack or for forestalling the further <lb/>reasonable apprehension from the side of the accused. The <lb/>burden of establishing the plea of self-defence is on the <lb/>accused and the burden stands discharged by showing <lb/>preponderance of probabilities in favour of that plea on the <lb/>basis of the material on record. (See Munshi Ram v. Delhi <lb/>Admn. [AIR 1968 SC 702 : 1968 Cri LJ 806] , State of Gujarat <lb/>v. Bai Fatima [(1975) 2 SCC 7 : 1975 SCC (Cri) 384 : AIR 1975 <lb/>SC 1478] , State of U.P. v. Mohd. Musheer Khan [(1977) 3 SCC <lb/>562 : 1977 SCC (Cri) 565 : AIR 1977 SC 2226] and Mohinder <lb/>Pal Jolly v. State of Punjab [(1979) 3 SCC 30 : 1979 SCC (Cri) <lb/></body>

			<page>85 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>635 : AIR 1979 SC 577] .) Sections 100 to 101 define the <lb/>extent of the right of private defence of body. If a person has a <lb/>right of private defence of body under Section 97, that right <lb/>extends under Section 100 to causing death if there is <lb/>reasonable apprehension that death or grievous hurt would be <lb/>the consequence of the assault. The oft-quoted observation of <lb/>this Court in Salim Zia v. State of U.P. [(1979) 2 SCC 648 : <lb/>1979 SCC (Cri) 568 : AIR 1979 SC 391] runs as follows: (SCC <lb/>p. 654, para 9) <lb/>&quot;It is true that the burden on an accused person to <lb/>establish the plea of self-defence is not as onerous as the one <lb/>which lies on the prosecution and that while the prosecution is <lb/>required to prove its case beyond reasonable doubt, the <lb/>accused need not establish the plea to the hilt and may <lb/>discharge his onus by establishing a mere preponderance of <lb/>probabilities either by laying basis for that plea in the cross-<lb/>examination of prosecution witnesses or by adducing defence <lb/>evidence.&quot; <lb/>The accused need not prove the existence of the right of <lb/>private defence beyond reasonable doubt. It is enough for him <lb/>to show as in a civil case that the preponderance of <lb/>probabilities is in favour of his plea.&quot; <lb/>107. In view of the categorical confession of Suren Rai that it <lb/>was he who had assaulted the deceased thrice with a <lb/>&quot;khukuri&quot; after he was provoked to a fight and hurled the <lb/>&quot;khukuri&quot; at him by the deceased, although Mr. B. Sharma has <lb/>raised the plea of private defence during the hearing of the <lb/>present appeal as an alternative argument, it is considered <lb/>necessary to examine the same. <lb/></body>

			<page>86 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>108. In re: Darshan Singh v. State of Punjab 22 the Supreme <lb/>Court would hold: <lb/>&quot;58. The following principles emerge on scrutiny of the <lb/>following judgments: <lb/>(i) Self-preservation is the basic human instinct and is duly <lb/>recognised by the criminal jurisprudence of all civilised <lb/>countries. All free, democratic and civilised countries recognise <lb/>the right of private defence within certain reasonable limits. <lb/>(ii) The right of private defence is available only to one who is <lb/>suddenly confronted with the necessity of averting an <lb/>impending danger and not of self-creation. <lb/>(iii) A mere reasonable apprehension is enough to put the right <lb/>of self-defence into operation. In other words, it is not <lb/>necessary that there should be an actual commission of the <lb/>offence in order to give rise to the right of private defence. It is <lb/>enough if the accused apprehended that such an offence is <lb/>contemplated and it is likely to be committed if the right of <lb/>private defence is not exercised. <lb/>(iv) The right of private defence commences as soon as a <lb/>reasonable apprehension arises and it is coterminous with the <lb/>duration of such apprehension. <lb/>(v) It is unrealistic to expect a person under assault to <lb/>modulate his defence step by step with any arithmetical <lb/>exactitude. <lb/>(vi) In private defence the force used by the accused ought not <lb/>to be wholly disproportionate or much greater than necessary <lb/>for protection of the person or property. <lb/>(vii) It is well settled that even if the accused does not plead <lb/>self-defence, it is open to consider such a plea if the same <lb/>arises from the material on record. <lb/></body>

			<page>22 (2010) 2 SCC 333 <lb/>87 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>(viii) The accused need not prove the existence of the right of <lb/>private defence beyond reasonable doubt. <lb/>(ix) The Penal Code confers the right of private defence only <lb/>when that unlawful or wrongful act is an offence. <lb/>(x) A person who is in imminent and reasonable danger of <lb/>losing his life or limb may in exercise of self-defence inflict any <lb/>harm even extending to death on his assailant either when the <lb/>assault is attempted or directly threatened.&quot; <lb/>109. Padam Kumar Rai would clearly depose that Suren Rai, <lb/>at around 8.00 p.m. on 23.05.2013, would request him to <lb/>pacify the deceased as he was provoking him into a fight <lb/>regarding his mobile phone. Padam Kumar Rai would also <lb/>depose that Suren Rai had come following him to his house <lb/>after he had gone to the temporary shed and told them not to <lb/>fight and look for the mobile instead, when he would ask <lb/>Suren Rai whether the mobile had been found. The fact that <lb/>the deceased had lost his mobile and was blaming Suren Rai <lb/>for it is evident from the deposition of Padam Kumar Rai. The <lb/>fact there was an altercation between the deceased and Suren <lb/>Rai is also evident. We have found that the confession to be <lb/>true and voluntary. We have also found that the retraction was <lb/>an afterthought and had no basis. The judicial confession of <lb/>Suren Rai discloses that the deceased had provoked him to a <lb/>fight. This confessional statement corroborates the evidence of <lb/>Padam Kumar Rai that Suren Rai had complained to him <lb/></body>

			<page>88 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>about the deceased provoking him to a fight. Although we are <lb/>aware that a retracted confession if found to be corroborative <lb/>in material particulars it may be the basis of conviction we are <lb/>also alive to the rule that no judgment of conviction shall be <lb/>passed on an uncorroborated retracted confession. We are also <lb/>alive to the rule that although retracted confession is <lb/>admissible, the same should be looked at with some amount of <lb/>suspicion-a stronger suspicion then that which is attached to <lb/>the confession of an approver who leads evidence in the Court. <lb/>In the circumstances, we examine the confession for the <lb/>limited purpose of examining the alternative plea of Mr. B. <lb/>Sharma of the right of private defence. Suren Rai in his <lb/>confession would state that the deceased, after provoking him <lb/>to a fight, had hurled the &quot;khukuri&quot; at him with the intention <lb/>to kill him. Suren Rai would also state in his confession that <lb/>he took the &quot;khukuri&quot; from the deceased. It is evident that, <lb/>therefore, the &quot;khukuri&quot; was no longer with the deceased. <lb/>110. The Supreme Court in re: Buta Singh v. State of Punjab 23 <lb/>would hold: <lb/>&quot;A person who is apprehending death or bodily injury cannot <lb/>weigh in golden scales on the spur of the moment and in the heat of <lb/>circumstances, the number of injuries required to disarm the <lb/>assailant who are armed with weapons. In moments of excitement <lb/>and disturbed mental equilibrium it is often difficult to expect the <lb/>parties to preserve composure and use only so much force in <lb/>retaliation commensurate with the danger apprehended to him. <lb/></body>

			<page>23 (1991) 12 SCC 612 <lb/>89 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>Where assault is imminent by use of force, it would be lawful to <lb/>repel the force in self-defence and the right of private defence <lb/>commences, as soon as the threat becomes so imminent. Such <lb/>situations have to be pragmatically viewed and not with high-<lb/>powered spectacles or microscopes to detect slight or even marginal <lb/>overstepping. Due weightage has to be given to, and hypertechnical <lb/>approach has to be avoided in considering what happens on the <lb/>spur of the moment on the spot and keeping in view normal human <lb/>reaction and conduct, where self-preservation is the paramount <lb/>consideration. But, if the fact situation shows that in the guise of <lb/>self-preservation, what really has been done is to assault the <lb/>original aggressor, even after the cause of reasonable apprehension <lb/>has disappeared, the plea of right of private defence can legitimately <lb/>be negative. The court dealing with the plea has to weigh the <lb/>material to conclude whether the plea is acceptable. It is essentially <lb/>a finding of fact.&quot; <lb/>111. Dr. O. T. Lepcha who conducted the post-mortem would <lb/>find six anti-mortem injuries on the deceased as stated above. <lb/>Each of the said injuries are severe and in the neck region. <lb/>Section 102 of IPC provides that the right of private defence of <lb/>the body commences as soon as a reasonable apprehension of <lb/>danger to the body arises from an attempt or threat to commit <lb/>the offence though the offence may not have been committed; <lb/>and it continues as long as such apprehension of danger to <lb/>the body continues. The moment Suren Rai had taken the <lb/>&quot;khukuri&quot; from the deceased the threat was over. It may be <lb/>true that in the spur of the moment, and in view of the <lb/>provocation, the attempted assault by the deceased with a <lb/>&quot;khukuri&quot; and his apprehension of the imminent danger on his <lb/></body>

			<page>90 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>life, Suren Rai may have taken the &quot;khukuri&quot; and assaulted <lb/>the deceased. It is true that it is unrealistic to expect a person <lb/>under assault to modulate his defence step by step with an <lb/>arithmetical exactitude. However, the multiple and severe anti-<lb/>mortem injuries on the deceased coupled with the fact that <lb/>Suren Rai after commission of the act ran away from the scene <lb/>of the crime even while the deceased would be still alive <lb/>makes it unequivocally clear that Suren Rai had exceeded his <lb/>right of self defence. <lb/>112. Section 299 IPC, 1860 provides:-<lb/>&quot;299. Culpable homicide.-Whoever causes death by <lb/>doing an act with the intention of causing death, or with the <lb/>intention of causing such bodily injury as is likely to cause <lb/>death, or with the knowledge that he is likely by such act to <lb/>cause death, commits the offence of culpable homicide.&quot; <lb/>113. Section 300 IPC, 1860 provides:-<lb/>&quot;300. Murder.-Except in the cases hereinafter <lb/>excepted, culpable homicide is murder, if the act by which the <lb/>death is caused is done with the intention of causing death, <lb/>or-<lb/>(Secondly) -If it is done with the intention of causing <lb/>such bodily injury as the offender knows to be likely to cause <lb/>the death of the person to whom the harm is caused, or-<lb/>(Thirdly) -If it is done with the intention of causing <lb/>bodily injury to any person and the bodily injury intended to <lb/>be inflicted is sufficient in the ordinary course of nature to <lb/>cause death, or-<lb/>(Fourthly) -If the person committing the act knows <lb/>that it is so imminently dangerous that it must, in all <lb/></body>

			<page>91 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>probability, cause death or such bodily injury as is likely to <lb/>cause death, and commits such act without any excuse for <lb/>incurring the risk of causing death or such injury as <lb/>aforesaid.&quot; <lb/>Exception 1.-When culpable homicide is not <lb/>murder.-Culpable homicide is not murder if the offender, <lb/>whilst deprived of the power of self-control by grave and <lb/>sudden provocation, causes the death of the person who gave <lb/>the provocation or causes the death of any other person by <lb/>mistake or accident. <lb/>The above exception is subject to the following <lb/>provisos:-<lb/>(First) -That the provocation is not sought or <lb/>voluntarily provoked by the offender as an excuse for killing or <lb/>doing harm to any person. <lb/>(Secondly) -That the provocation is not given by <lb/>anything done in obedience to the law, or by a public servant <lb/>in the lawful exercise of the powers of such public servant. <lb/>(Thirdly) -That the provocation is not given by <lb/>anything done in the lawful exercise of the right of private <lb/>defence. <lb/>Explanation.-Whether the provocation was grave and <lb/>sudden enough to prevent the offence from amounting to <lb/>murder is a question of fact <lb/>Exception 2.-Culpable homicide is not murder if the <lb/>offender, in the exercise in good faith of the right of private <lb/>defence of person or property, exceeds the power given to him <lb/>by law and causes the death of the person against whom he <lb/>is exercising such right of defence without premeditation, and <lb/>without any intention of doing more harm than is necessary <lb/>for the purpose of such defence. Illustration Z attempts to <lb/>horsewhip A, not in such a manner as to cause grievous hurt <lb/>to A. A draws out a pistol. Z persists in the assault. A <lb/>believing in good faith that he can by no other means prevent <lb/></body>

			<page>92 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>himself from being horsewhipped, shoots Z dead. A has not <lb/>committed murder, but only culpable homicide. <lb/>Exception 3.-Culpable homicide is not murder if the <lb/>offender, being a public servant or aiding a public servant <lb/>acting for the advancement of public justice, exceeds the <lb/>powers given to him by law, and causes death by doing an <lb/>act which he, in good faith, believes to be lawful and <lb/>necessary for the due discharge of his duty as such public <lb/>servant and without ill-will towards the person whose death <lb/>is caused. <lb/>Exception 4.-Culpable homicide is not murder if it is <lb/>committed without premeditation in a sudden fight in the heat <lb/>of passion upon a sudden quarrel and without the offender <lb/>having taken undue advantage or acted in a cruel or unusual <lb/>manner. Explanation.-It is immaterial in such cases which <lb/>party offers the provocation or commits the first assault. <lb/>Exception 5.-Culpable homicide is not murder when <lb/>the person whose death is caused, being above the age of <lb/>eighteen years, suffers death or takes the risk of death with <lb/>his own consent.&quot; <lb/>114. In re: Suresh Singhal v. State (Delhi Administration) 24 the <lb/>Supreme Court would examine the case in which the accused <lb/>had exceeded the right of private defence. In the said case the <lb/>accused, Suresh Singhal was sought to be strangulated by the <lb/>deceased. Suresh Singhal would reach for his revolver, upon <lb/>which the deceased would release him and turn around to run <lb/>away. At this point the accused would shoot him, either still <lb/>lying down or having got up. The Supreme Court would hold <lb/>that the accused had reasonably apprehended danger to his <lb/></body>

			<page>24 (2017) 2 SCC 737 <lb/>93 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>life on being strangulated which would be reasonable <lb/>apprehension to put the right of self defence into operation. In <lb/>such situation on the face of imminent and reasonable danger <lb/>of losing life or limb the accused may in exercise of self defence <lb/>inflict any harm even extending to death on his assailant. The <lb/>Supreme Court would find that the accused had been put in <lb/>such a position. The Supreme Court would, however, hold that <lb/>the accused had exceeded the power given to him by law in <lb/>order to defend himself although the exercise of the right was <lb/>in good faith, in his own defence and without premeditation. <lb/>The Supreme Court would, thus, hold that the homicide does <lb/>not amount to murder in view of exception 2 of Section 300 <lb/>IPC, 1860 and that the homicide falls within exception 4 of <lb/>Section 300 IPC, 1860 and does not amount to murder. In <lb/>such circumstances the Supreme Court would hold:-<lb/>&quot;32. In these circumstances, we are of the view that Suresh <lb/>Singhal is undoubtedly guilty of causing death to Shyam Sunder <lb/>with the intention of causing death or of causing such bodily injury <lb/>as is likely to cause death and therefore guilty of the offence under <lb/>Section 304 IPC. We are informed that the appellant has already <lb/>undergone a sentence of 13½ years as on date. We thus sentence <lb/>him to the period already undergone.&quot; <lb/>115. In re: Naveen Chandra v. State of Uttaranchal 25 the <lb/>Supreme Court would examine a situation where the accused <lb/>would while exercising his right of private defence, exceeded by <lb/></body>

			<page>25 (2009) 16 SCC 449 <lb/>94 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>continuing attacks after threat to life had seized. The Supreme <lb/>Court would draw the distinction between the first and the <lb/>fourth exception of Section 300 IPC thus: <lb/>&quot;12. &quot;17. The Fourth Exception of Section 300 IPC covers acts <lb/>done in a sudden fight. The said exception deals with a case of <lb/>prosecution (sic provocation) not covered by the First Exception, after <lb/>which its place would have been more appropriate. The exception is <lb/>founded upon the same principle, for in both there is absence of <lb/>premeditation. But, while in the case of Exception 1 there is total <lb/>deprivation of self-control, in case of Exception 4, there is only that <lb/>heat of passion which clouds men&apos;s sober reason and urges them to <lb/>deeds which they would not otherwise do. There is provocation in <lb/>Exception 4 as in Exception 1; but the injury done is not the direct <lb/>consequence of that provocation. In fact, Exception 4 deals with <lb/>cases in which notwithstanding that a blow may have been struck, <lb/>or some provocation given in the origin of the dispute or in whatever <lb/>way the quarrel may have originated, yet the subsequent conduct of <lb/>both parties puts them in respect of guilt upon equal footing. A <lb/>&apos;sudden fight&apos; implies mutual provocation and blows on each side. <lb/>The homicide committed is then clearly not traceable to unilateral <lb/>provocation, nor in such cases could the whole blame be placed on <lb/>one side. For if it were so, the exception more appropriately <lb/>applicable would be Exception 1. <lb/>18. The help of Exception 4 can be invoked if death is caused <lb/>(a) without premeditation; (b) in a sudden fight; (c) without the <lb/>offender&apos;s having taken undue advantage or acted in a cruel or <lb/>unusual manner; and (d) the fight must have been with the person <lb/>killed. To bring a case within Exception 4, all the ingredients <lb/>mentioned in it must be found. It is to be noted that the &apos;fight&apos; <lb/>occurring in Exception 4 to Section 300 IPC is not defined in IPC. It <lb/>takes two to make a fight. Heat of passion requires that there must <lb/>be no time for the passions to cool down and in this case, the parties <lb/>had worked themselves into a fury on account of the verbal <lb/>altercation in the beginning. A fight is a combat between two and <lb/>more persons whether with or without weapons. It is not possible to <lb/></body>

			<page>95 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>enunciate any general rule as to what shall be deemed to be a <lb/>sudden quarrel. It is a question of fact and whether a quarrel is <lb/>sudden or not must necessarily depend upon the proved facts of <lb/>each case. For the application of Exception 4, it is not sufficient to <lb/>show that there was a sudden quarrel and there was no <lb/>premeditation. It must further be shown that the offender has not <lb/>taken undue advantage or acted in a cruel or unusual manner. The <lb/>expression &apos;undue advantage&apos; as used in the provision means <lb/>&apos;unfair advantage&apos;. <lb/>19. Where the offender takes undue advantage or has acted <lb/>in a cruel or unusual manner, the benefit of Exception 4 cannot be <lb/>given to him. If the weapon used or the manner of attack by the <lb/>assailant is out of all proportion, that circumstance must be taken <lb/>into consideration to decide whether undue advantage has been <lb/>taken. In Kikar Singh v. State ofRajasthan [(1993) 4 SCC 238 : 1993 <lb/>SCC (Cri) 1156 : AIR 1993 SC 2426] it was held that if the accused <lb/>used deadly weapons against the unarmed man and struck a blow <lb/>on the head it must be held that by using the blows with the <lb/>knowledge that they were likely to cause death he had taken undue <lb/>advantage. In the instant case blows on vital parts of unarmed <lb/>persons were given with brutality. The abdomens of two deceased <lb/>persons were ripped open and internal organs had come out. In view <lb/>of the aforesaid factual position, Exception 4 to Section 300 IPC has <lb/>been rightly held to be inapplicable.&quot; <lb/>The above position was highlighted in Babulal Bhagwan <lb/>Khandare v. State of Maharashtra [(2005) 10 SCC 404 : 2005 SCC <lb/>(Cri) 1553] , at SCC pp. 410-11, paras 17-19. <lb/>13. Considering the background facts in the backdrop of the <lb/>legal principles as set out above, the inevitable conclusion is that <lb/>Fourth Exception to Section 300 IPC does not apply&quot; <lb/>116. In re: Naveen Chandra (supra) was a case in which the <lb/>Trial Court had convicted the accused under Section 302 IPC <lb/>and awarded the death sentence which led to a reference <lb/></body>

			<page>96 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>before the High Court for confirmation in terms of Section 366 <lb/>Cr.P.C. The High Court converted the death sentence to life <lb/>imprisonment partly allowing the appeal. The case would <lb/>relate to an altercation between two sets of family members. It <lb/>was alleged that the appellant before the Supreme Court, <lb/>Naveen Chandra rushed and injured the deceased on his head <lb/>with a &quot;khukuri&quot;. When the Appellant would be asked to spare <lb/>the deceased the Appellant would attack the said persons too <lb/>and injured them. The deceased would succumb to his injuries <lb/>on the spot. <lb/>117. We find that the deceased had blamed Suren Rai for the <lb/>loss of his mobile. We also find that the deceased had more <lb/>than once provoked Suren Rai. Considering the confession of <lb/>Suren Rai it seems that the deceased had provoked Suren Rai <lb/>into a fight and hurled a &quot;khukuri&quot; at him on which Suren Rai <lb/>had grabbed the &quot;khukuri&quot; from him and assaulted the <lb/>deceased multiple times and severely which caused the death <lb/>of the deceased. There was reasonable apprehension of danger <lb/>to Suren Rai&apos;s life which would put the right of self defence <lb/>into operation giving him the right to inflict any harm even <lb/>extending to death. The multiple and gaping chop wounds on <lb/>the back of the neck, below the skull causing the six severe <lb/>anti-mortem injuries with the &quot;khukuri&quot;, a sharp moderately <lb/>heavy weapon and his running away whilst the deceased was <lb/></body>

			<page>97 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>still alive makes us firmly believe that Suren Rai exceeded the <lb/>power given to him by law in order to defend himself although <lb/>the exercise of the right, quite clearly, was done whilst <lb/>deprived of the power of self control by grave and sudden <lb/>provocation in his own defence and without premeditation. <lb/>The homicide therefore does not amount to murder in view of <lb/>exception 1 of Section 300 IPC, 1860. We are of the view that <lb/>Suren Rai is guilty of causing death of the deceased with the <lb/>intention of causing death or of causing such bodily injury as <lb/>is likely to cause death and therefore guilty of the offence <lb/>under Section 304 IPC, 1860. Resultantly, Suren Rai is <lb/>convicted for the offence of culpable homicide not amounting <lb/>to murder under paragraph 1 of Section 304 IPC, 1860. The <lb/>appeal against conviction is allowed. The acquittal of the <lb/>Respondent vide impugned judgment dated 29.02.2016 passed <lb/>by the Learned Sessions Judge, West Sikkim at Gyalshing is <lb/>set aside. <lb/>118. As this Court is reversing a judgment of acquittal in <lb/>favour of the Respondent and convicting him we deem it <lb/>appropriate to grant a hearing to the Respondent on the <lb/>quantum of sentence. Accordingly the Respondent shall be <lb/>produced before this Court on 11.06.2018 and heard on the <lb/>quantum of sentence. <lb/></body>

			<page>98 <lb/></page>

			<body>Crl. Appeal No. 17 of 2016 <lb/>State of Sikkim vs. Suren Rai <lb/>119. Certified copies of this judgment shall be furnished free <lb/>of cost to the Respondent and also forwarded to the Court of <lb/>the Learned Sessions Judge, West Sikkim at Gyalshing <lb/>forthwith. <lb/>Sd/-<lb/>Sd/-<lb/>(Bhaskar Raj Pradhan) <lb/>(Meenakshi Madan Rai) <lb/>Judge <lb/>Judge <lb/>04.06.2018 <lb/>04.06.2018 <lb/>Approved for reporting: yes. <lb/>to <lb/>Internet: yes. </body>


	</text>
</tei>
