<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			RSA 346/2016
			<lb />
			Page 1 of 7
			<lb />
			$~1
			<lb />
			*
			<lb />
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF DELHI AT NEW DELHI
			<lb />
			%
			<lb />
			Date of Decision: December 02, 2016
			<lb />
			+
			<lb />
			RSA 346/2016
			<lb />
			GYAN CHAND
			<lb />
			..... Appellant
			<lb />
			Through: Mr.N.K.Aggarwal &amp; Ms.Nupur
			<lb />
			Sachdeva, Advocates with appellant in
			<lb />
			person
			<lb />
			versus
			<lb />
			KAMLESH
			<lb />
			..... Respondent
			<lb />
			Through: Mr.Deepak Gupta, Advocate with
			<lb />
			Mr.Ankush Sharma &amp; Mr.Gaurav
			<lb />
			Dhakar, Advocates
			<lb />
		</front>

		<body>
			CORAM:
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MS. JUSTICE PRATIBHA RANI
			<lb />
			JUDGMENT (Oral)
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			This Regular Second Appeal under Section 100 of the Code of Civil
			<lb />
			Procedure has been filed against the concurrent judgment of the Courts
			<lb />
			below i.e. of the First Appellate Court dated 16 th September, 2016 and of the
			<lb />
			trial Court dated 11 th December, 2014 whereby the suit of the plaintiff in
			<lb />
			respect of the possession has been decreed under Order XII Rule 6 CPC.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			After the notice of the appeal was sent to the Respondent, LCR was
			<lb />
			also requisitioned.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			At the stage of hearing, the thrust of argument on behalf of the
			<lb />
			appellant was that instead of passing a decree under Order XII Rule 6 CPC
			<lb />
			on the basis of admission in the written statement, it has been passed on the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			RSA 346/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 2 of 7
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			basis of rectification deed which has been filed subsequently by the
			<lb />
			respondent/plaintiff. Thus, it has been urged by the appellant that the
			<lb />
			findings of the Courts below suffer from perversity.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Following substantial question of law was formulated in this case on
			<lb />
			21 st November 2016:-
			<lb />
			&quot;Whether the findings of the Courts below being not based on
			<lb />
			admission are perverse?&quot;
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			Learned counsel for the appellant, Mr.N.K.Aggarwal has submitted
			<lb />
			that the suit in respect of the relief of the possession could not have been
			<lb />
			decreed by the learned trial Court in view of the preliminary objection raised
			<lb />
			in the written statement disputing the ownership of the plaintiff or she having
			<lb />
			any right title or interest in the suit property. Learned counsel for the
			<lb />
			appellant has further submitted that in the written statement there was no
			<lb />
			admission in respect of the Shop No.4 for the reason that suit was not
			<lb />
			instituted in respect of Shop No.4 which was in his tenancy. Learned counsel
			<lb />
			for the appellant has also contended that the respondent/plaintiff purchased
			<lb />
			shop Nos.2 and 3. When the case was listed for orders on the application
			<lb />
			under Order XII Rule 6 CPC the clarification was sought by the Court and
			<lb />
			the rectification deed was filed which could not have been taken into
			<lb />
			consideration by the Court for decreeing the suit for possession under Order
			<lb />
			XII Rule 6 CPC. It has been further contended that in the absence of any
			<lb />
			admission about the relationship of the landlord and tenant between the
			<lb />
			parties in respect of Shop No.4 in tenancy of the respondent, learned trial
			<lb />
			Court could not have passed the decree for possession in respect of the
			<lb />
			tenanted shop.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			On behalf of the respondent Mr.Deepak Gupta, Advocate has
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			RSA 346/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 3 of 7
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			submitted that even if the rectification deed in respect of private number of
			<lb />
			shop in property bearing No.B-11, Gulab Bagh, Village Nawada, Delhi-
			<lb />
			110059 is excluded, there is clear cut admission in the written statement not
			<lb />
			only about the relationship of landlady and tenant between the parties but
			<lb />
			also that the appellant had deposited the rent under Section 27 of Delhi Rent
			<lb />
			Control Act taking the plea that the landlady was not accepting the rent.
			<lb />
			Mr.Deepak Gupta, Advocate has further contended that irrespective of the
			<lb />
			fact that rectification deed mentioned the private number for the shop to be 4
			<lb />
			whereas the sale documents in favour of the respondent are in respect of
			<lb />
			private shop Nos.2 and 3, the identity of the property is not in dispute and
			<lb />
			the suit property i.e. the shop in tenancy of the appellant was correctly
			<lb />
			shown in red in the site plan annexed with the plaint copy of which was
			<lb />
			supplied to the appellant/defendant. In the written statement the correctness
			<lb />
			of the site plan was not disputed. Thus, irrespective of the discrepancy, if any
			<lb />
			about the private numbers given to the shop in the sale documents or the
			<lb />
			rectification deed, so far as the appellant is concerned he was tenant in
			<lb />
			respect of one shop only which was duly identified and described in the site
			<lb />
			plan. In respect of that shop decree for possession has been passed in view of
			<lb />
			the admission by him in the written statement. Mr. Deepak Gupta, Advocate
			<lb />
			has also submitted that the provisions of Delhi Rent Control Act do not
			<lb />
			apply to the area where the suit property is situated. Thus, a suit for
			<lb />
			possession has been filed which has been rightly decreed on the basis of
			<lb />
			admission made in the written statement. Even the possession of the suit
			<lb />
			property has already been taken by the respondent/plaintiff in execution
			<lb />
			proceedings.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			In support of above submissions, learned counsel for the respondent
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			RSA 346/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 4 of 7
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			has referred to the decision of Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Payal Vision Ltd.
			<lb />
			Vs. Radhika Chaudhary, 2012 Law Suit (SC) 605 wherein the decision in
			<lb />
			Anar Devi (Smt.) Vs. Nathu Ram, 1994 4 SCC 250 has been followed. In
			<lb />
			respect of discrepancy about the private shop number in property No. B-11,
			<lb />
			Gulab Bagh, Village Nawada, Delhi-110059, learned counsel for the
			<lb />
			respondent has relied upon the decision of this Court in Vijay Kumar
			<lb />
			Sharma Vs. Manoj Kumar Garg, RSA No.179/2016 decided on 20 th July,
			<lb />
			2016.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			While examining the findings of the Courts below, as to whether the
			<lb />
			same are based on the basis of admission made in the written statement, the
			<lb />
			rectification deed has been excluded from the consideration zone. Now the
			<lb />
			only aspect that requires consideration is whether the judgments passed by
			<lb />
			the Courts below under Order XII Rule 6 CPC can be termed as perverse. In
			<lb />
			the Civil Suit No.60/14 in para no.1 and 2 of the plaint the
			<lb />
			respondent/plaintiff claimed herself to be the owner of property No.11, B-
			<lb />
			Block, Area Gulabi Bagh, Village Nawada, Bindapur, Delhi-110059. Para
			<lb />
			no.3 of the plaint reads as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;3. That the defendant was inducted as a tenant by the
			<lb />
			plaintiff&apos;s predecessor, for a portion (one &apos;shop&apos;) admeasuring
			<lb />
			about &quot;5&quot; X &quot;12&quot; (approximately), (correct measurement can
			<lb />
			only be filed after a proper inspection of the premises in suit, as
			<lb />
			the plaintiff is not permitted to enter in the premises in suit for
			<lb />
			the purposes of preparing site plan), on the ground floor
			<lb />
			forming part of the property bearing No.B-11, area known as
			<lb />
			Gulab Bagh, Village Nawada, New Delhi-110059 (morefully
			<lb />
			shown bounded by red colour in the rough site plan of the
			<lb />
			property), hereinafter called the suit property. Now a monthly
			<lb />
			rent of the said tenanted accommodation is ₹850/-per month
			<lb />
			(Rupees Eight Hundred and Fifty only) excluding other charges
			<lb />
			for purposes of carrying out business activities. Site plan of the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			RSA 346/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 5 of 7
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			property annexed herewith as Annexure-&quot;A&quot;.&quot;
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			Corresponding para of the written statement reads as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;That the contents of corresponding para 3 of suit on merits is
			<lb />
			admitted. However, it is specifically denied that the defendant
			<lb />
			has ever denied the lawful owner to inspect the property at
			<lb />
			legitimate working hours of the day.&quot;
			<lb />
			10. On page No.11 in para No.7 of the written statement the
			<lb />
			appellant/defendant has pleaded that he had been regularly tendering the rent
			<lb />
			to the plaintiff but the plaintiff had been refusing to accept the same thereby
			<lb />
			compelling the appellant/defendant to regularly deposit the same before the
			<lb />
			Rent Controller and there was no arrears towards rent.
			<lb />
			11. Service of notice dated 21 st March, 2014 terminating the tenancy has
			<lb />
			been held to be proved by the learned trial Court as the same was replied
			<lb />
			dated 3 rd April, 2014. It has been held that even if the period of 15 days is
			<lb />
			calculated from the date of reply i.e. 3 rd April, 2014 as required under
			<lb />
			Section 106 of the Transfer of Property Act, the possession of the
			<lb />
			appellant/defendant became unauthorized with effect from 19 th April, 2014.
			<lb />
			Thus on the basis of admission a decree for possession was passed in respect
			<lb />
			of the shop as shown red in the site plan under Order XII Rule 6 CPC.
			<lb />
			12. The First Appellate Court dismissed the appeal noting the following
			<lb />
			facts:-
			<lb />
			(i)
			<lb />
			The tenant failed to bring on record any notification that provisions of
			<lb />
			Delhi Rent Control Act extends to the area where the suit property is
			<lb />
			situated.
			<lb />
			(ii) The service of legal notice dated 21 st March, 2014 is per se apparent as
			<lb />
			the same was replied on 3 rd April, 2014.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			RSA 346/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 6 of 7
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			(iii) There is admission on behalf of the appellant/tenant that he attorned in
			<lb />
			favour of the respondent/plaintiff who purchased the property vide registered
			<lb />
			sale deed.
			<lb />
			13. Even as per the admission of the appellant/tenant he had been
			<lb />
			depositing rent under Section 27 of Delhi Rent Control Act in favour of the
			<lb />
			respondent/plaintiff which is sufficient to show her right and interest in the
			<lb />
			tenanted premises. The tenant is estopped from challenging the title of the
			<lb />
			landlord.
			<lb />
			14. Finding no illegality or infirmity in the order passed by the learned
			<lb />
			trial Court, the First Appellate Court dismissed the appeal.
			<lb />
			15. The legal position is well settled that for a litigant the first appeal is a
			<lb />
			matter of right. The First Appellate Court is empowered to re-appreciate the
			<lb />
			entire evidence in the light of arguments and can substitute its own findings
			<lb />
			of the fact and finding of law if the First Appellate Court is of the opinion
			<lb />
			that the findings of the trial Court are not in accordance with law or not
			<lb />
			based on facts. However, the second appeal would lie only when substantial
			<lb />
			question of law is involved. The order passed by the learned trial Court and
			<lb />
			affirmed by the learned First Appellate Court is based on admission made by
			<lb />
			the appellant in the written statement. Irrespective of the private number
			<lb />
			given to the shop situated in property No. B-11, Gulab Bagh, Village
			<lb />
			Nawada, Delhi-110059, in the written statement in para no.3 correctness of
			<lb />
			the site plan is admitted. The relationship of landlady and tenant between the
			<lb />
			parties as well attornment in favour of the plaintiff who purchased the
			<lb />
			property through registered sale deed was not disputed by the
			<lb />
			appellant/tenant. He even deposited rent in favour of respondent/plaintiff by
			<lb />
			taking recourse to the provisions of Section 27 of Delhi Rent Control Act
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			RSA 346/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 7 of 7
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			and pleaded specifically in the written statement that he is not in arrears of
			<lb />
			rent. Since the provisions of Delhi Rent Control Act are not applicable to the
			<lb />
			area where the suit property is situated, the landlord was required to serve a
			<lb />
			notice under Section 106 of the Transfer of Property Act which requirement
			<lb />
			has been duly complied with in this case.
			<lb />
			16. Thus the concurrent findings of the Courts below are based on the
			<lb />
			admission made in the written statement while passing a decree for
			<lb />
			possession under Order XII Rule 6 CPC. The impugned order does not suffer
			<lb />
			from perversity.
			<lb />
			17. The Regular Second Appeal is dismissed.
			<lb />
			18. No costs.
			<lb />
			CM No.42891/2016
			<lb />
			Dismissed as infructuous.
			<lb />
			PRATIBHA RANI, J.
			<lb />
			DECEMBER 02, 2016
			<lb />
			&apos;pg&apos;
		</body>


	</text>
</tei>