<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">

		<page>
			1
			<lb />
		</page>

		<front>
			THE HIGH COURT OF SIKKIM : GANGTOK
			<lb />
			(Civil Extraordinary Jurisdiction)
			<lb />
			DATED : 25 th January, 2021
			<lb />
			-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------
			<lb />
			SINGLE BENCH : THE HON&apos;BLE MRS. JUSTICE MEENAKSHI MADAN RAI, JUDGE
			<lb />
			-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------
			<lb />
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			0
			<lb />
			Petitioners
			<lb />
			: Sushil Pradhan and Others
			<lb />
			versus
			<lb />
			Respondents : State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
			Petitioner under Article 226 of the
			<lb />
			Constitution of India
			<lb />
			-------------------------------------------------------------------
			<lb />
			Appearance
			<lb />
			Mr. A. Moulik, Senior Advocate with Ms. K.D. Bhutia and Mr. Ranjit
			<lb />
			Prasad, Advocates, for the Petitioners.
			<lb />
			Dr. (Mrs.) Doma T. Bhutia and Mr. Sudesh Joshi, Additional Advocate
			<lb />
			Generals with Mr. S.K. Chettri, Additional Government Advocate and
			<lb />
			Mr. Sujan Sunwar, Assistant Government Advocate, for Respondents
			<lb />
			No.1 to 3.
			<lb />
			Mr. Karma Thinlay, Senior Advocate for Respondents No.4 to 6.
			<lb />
			Mr. J.B. Pradhan, Senior Advocate with Mr. T.R. Barfungpa and Ms.
			<lb />
			Yangchen Doma Gyatso, Advocates for Respondents No.7 to 17.
			<lb />
			-------------------------------------------------------------------
			<lb />
		</front>

		<body>
			J U D G M E N T
			<lb />
			Meenakshi Madan Rai, J.
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			The discontentment of the Petitioners arises on account
			<lb />
			of their appointment and retention on Officiating basis from
			<lb />
			08.05.2008 in the posts of Accounts Officers despite alleged
			<lb />
			existing Substantive vacancies, confirming them in the posts only
			<lb />
			on 16.03.2013, thus, depriving them of regular Promotion and
			<lb />
			Service Seniority, as against the Respondents No.7 to 17 directly
			<lb />
			recruited as Accounts Officers in January/February, 2009, who
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			2
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			have been ranked higher than the Petitioners in the inter se
			<lb />
			Seniority.
			<lb />
			1.(a)
			<lb />
			They are further aggrieved that the Respondents No.4,
			<lb />
			5 and 6, who had appeared in the same Departmental Examination
			<lb />
			as them in the year 1997, were promoted on 24.12.1997 as Senior
			<lb />
			Accountants from the Panel prepared for such Promotion. On
			<lb />
			05.02.2005, the same Respondents were further promoted as
			<lb />
			Accounts Officers on Officiating capacity while the Petitioners No.1,
			<lb />
			2 and 8 despite possessing similar requisite qualifying years of
			<lb />
			Service, were excluded citing lack of vacancy. The said
			<lb />
			Respondents were promoted on Substantive capacity as Accounts
			<lb />
			Officers on 21.01.2009 and as Senior Accounts Officers on
			<lb />
			Officiating basis on 11.02.2011. The Petitioners No.1 and 2 were
			<lb />
			promoted as Senior Accountants in 1998, the Petitioner No.8 in
			<lb />
			1999 and the remaining Petitioners only on 27.06.2000.
			<lb />
			1.(b)
			<lb />
			It is the Petitioners&apos; case that they were, in fact,
			<lb />
			eligible for Promotion as Accounts Officers in 2004-2006 itself,
			<lb />
			having then put in the requisite years of Service required by the
			<lb />
			Rules as Senior Accountants. When the Cadre strength of Accounts
			<lb />
			Officers was 77 (seventy-seven), there were adequate vacancies to
			<lb />
			accommodate them in Substantive capacity, which would have
			<lb />
			made them seniors to the 11 (eleven) Direct Recruits who were
			<lb />
			appointed in January/February, 2009, allegedly from the same
			<lb />
			Cadre strength of 77 (seventy-seven) and promoted as Officiating
			<lb />
			Senior Accounts Officers on 11.01.2013 after only four years of
			<lb />
			Service, as against the required number of six years, mandated by
			<lb />
			the Rules. In December, 2008, the Cadre strength was increased
			<lb />
			from 77 (seventy-seven) to 103 (one hundred and three), resulting
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			3
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			in 26 (twenty-six) new vacancies but it was only on 16.03.2013,
			<lb />
			that the Petitioners were confirmed in the Substantive posts of
			<lb />
			Accounts Officers. The Petitioners No.1, 2 and 8 along with one
			<lb />
			M.R. Chettri, were promoted as Senior Accounts Officers on
			<lb />
			Officiating capacity on 22.05.2014, leaving out the remaining
			<lb />
			Petitioners who possessed the requisite qualification and merit.
			<lb />
			1.(c)
			<lb />
			The Petitioners speculate that had they been promoted
			<lb />
			as Accounts Officers in 2004-2006, by 2013, they could well have
			<lb />
			been promoted as Senior Accounts Officers in the 12 (twelve)
			<lb />
			vacancies in the said posts, but vide a Notification dated
			<lb />
			21.06.2013, these 12 (twelve) posts were downgraded to that of
			<lb />
			Accounts Officers, allegedly for the purpose of appointing Direct
			<lb />
			Recruits as Accounts Officers. Ultimately, no Direct Recruit came to
			<lb />
			be appointed to the downgraded posts but were then filled by way
			<lb />
			of Promotion. Thus, the policy of Promotions adopted by the State-
			<lb />
			Respondents No.1, 2 and 3 has been prejudicial to the Petitioners.
			<lb />
			On approaching the Respondent No.3, their prayers were declined,
			<lb />
			while steps taken by the Respondent No.1 to mitigate their
			<lb />
			grievances on their request led to their confirmation in March,
			<lb />
			2013, by which time, the Respondents No.7 to 17 had already
			<lb />
			stolen a march against them in terms of Seniority. That, although
			<lb />
			Petitioners No.2 and 3 have retired during the pendency of the
			<lb />
			instant Writ Petition, they seek enforcement of their legal rights.
			<lb />
			1.(d)
			<lb />
			Hence, the prayers in the Petition, as extracted
			<lb />
			hereinbelow;
			<lb />
			&quot;(i)
			<lb />
			A Rule upon the Government respondents to show-
			<lb />
			cause as to why the petitioners&quot; seniority in the rank
			<lb />
			of A.O. and Sr.A.O. shall not be protected and they
			<lb />
			be declared as seniors to the directly recruited
			<lb />
			respondent nos.7 to 17 with all service benefits in
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			4
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			the rank of A.O. and Sr.A.O. and upon hearing the
			<lb />
			parties to make the Rule absolute;
			<lb />
			(ii)
			<lb />
			A writ or order or direction or declaration that the
			<lb />
			petitioners are seniors to the respondent nos.7 to
			<lb />
			17 i.e. directly recruited A.O. and in the seniority list
			<lb />
			the petitioners&quot; name be incorporated above those
			<lb />
			of respondent nos.7 to 17 in the said rank of A.O.;
			<lb />
			(iii)
			<lb />
			A writ or order or direction or declaration that the
			<lb />
			three petitioners namely petitioner nos.1, 2 and 8
			<lb />
			be deemed to be promoted as Sr.A.O. on the same
			<lb />
			date when respondent nos.7 to 17 were promoted
			<lb />
			as Sr.A.O. on officiating capacity with all service
			<lb />
			benefits;
			<lb />
			(iv)
			<lb />
			A writ or order or direction or declaration that the
			<lb />
			petitioners who were promoted as A.O. in
			<lb />
			substantive capacity on 16/3/13 be deemed to have
			<lb />
			promoted as such on 08/5/2008 when they were
			<lb />
			promoted as A.O. in officiating capacity without
			<lb />
			service benefits;
			<lb />
			(v)
			<lb />
			A writ or order or direction or declaration that the
			<lb />
			12 numbers of posts of Sr.A.O. which were
			<lb />
			downgraded vide Office Order dated 21/6/13
			<lb />
			(Annexure-P9) shall be set aside, quashed and
			<lb />
			cancelled.
			<lb />
			(vi)
			<lb />
			A writ or order or direction or declaration that the
			<lb />
			petitioners shall be given all benefits of service in
			<lb />
			the respective rank of A.O. and Sr. A.O. and they be
			<lb />
			placed senior over the respondent nos.7 to 17 in the
			<lb />
			seniority list in the said rank of A.O. and Sr.A.O.
			<lb />
			(vii)
			<lb />
			A writ or order or direction or declaration that the
			<lb />
			petitioners shall be given all benefits of service in
			<lb />
			the respective rank of A.O. and Sr.A.O. and they be
			<lb />
			placed in the seniority list above those of the
			<lb />
			respondent nos.7 to 17 in both the ranks.
			<lb />
			(viii) A writ or order or direction or declaration that the
			<lb />
			remaining seven petitioners namely petitioner nos.3
			<lb />
			to 7, 9 and 10 be also promoted in the rank of
			<lb />
			Sr.A.O. in substantive capacity before those of
			<lb />
			respondent nos.7 to 17;
			<lb />
			(ix)
			<lb />
			A writ or order or direction or declaration to follow
			<lb />
			the process of appointment/promotion between the
			<lb />
			petitioners and the respondent nos.7 to 17 on 50:50
			<lb />
			ratio i.e. 50% for inservice candidates i.e.
			<lb />
			petitioners and 50% for direct recruits i.e. the
			<lb />
			respondent nos.7 to 17.
			<lb />
			(ix)(a)
			<lb />
			A writ or order or direction or declaration
			<lb />
			declaring that the petitioner nos.2 and 3
			<lb />
			even after retirement in the service shall be
			<lb />
			entitled to get their legal rights pertaining to
			<lb />
			their incidental reliefs/service benefits which
			<lb />
			they would have got prior to their retirement
			<lb />
			in the event the petitioners succeed in the
			<lb />
			instant writ petition.
			<lb />
			(x)……………
			<lb />
			(xi)……………&quot;
			<lb />
			2.(i)
			<lb />
			While denying and disputing the averments of the
			<lb />
			Petitioners, the State-Respondents No.1, 2 and 3, in their joint
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			5
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			Counter-Affidavit, sought to explain that on 03.06.2003, the Cadre
			<lb />
			strength of the Accounts Officers were increased from 75 (seventy-
			<lb />
			five) to 77 (seventy-seven). On the date of Cadre revision in
			<lb />
			December, 2008, 31 (thirty-one) persons were occupying the posts
			<lb />
			of Accounts Officers while 46 (forty-six) posts were vacant. 23
			<lb />
			(twenty-three) posts were to be filled by Direct Recruitment
			<lb />
			through Open Competitive Examination and 23 (twenty-three) by
			<lb />
			way of Promotion. Therefore, against the 23 (twenty-three) posts
			<lb />
			for Promotees, in fact, 55 (fifty-five) Officers were promoted and
			<lb />
			all were senior in rank to the Petitioners. No Direct Recruitment to
			<lb />
			the post of Accounts Officers in the 23 (twenty-three) vacant posts
			<lb />
			meant for Direct Recruits, took place during the said period, the
			<lb />
			last Direct Recruitment having been made in May, 2003. It was
			<lb />
			only on 16.07.2007 that the Respondent No.3 forwarded a
			<lb />
			requisition to the Sikkim Public Service Commission (for short
			<lb />
			&quot;SPSC&quot;), for filling up 11 (eleven) posts of Accounts Officers under
			<lb />
			the Sikkim Finance and Accounts Service Rules, 1978 (for brevity
			<lb />
			&quot;Rules of 1978&quot;) by Direct Recruitment. Pending this proposal, 17
			<lb />
			(seventeen) Senior Accountants were promoted as Accounts
			<lb />
			Officers in Officiating capacity on 08.05.2008, subject to the
			<lb />
			conditions that the Officiating Promotion shall not confer any right
			<lb />
			for regular Promotion and shall not be counted towards Seniority
			<lb />
			and their regular Promotion shall be made on the recommendation
			<lb />
			of the SPSC, which were accepted by the Petitioners without
			<lb />
			demur. The amendment of the Rules of 1978 on 15.12.2008,
			<lb />
			increased the Cadre strength of Accounts Officers from 77
			<lb />
			(seventy-seven) to 103 (one hundred and three). On 08.04.2008,
			<lb />
			prior to the above amendment, the SPSC invited applications for
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			6
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			filling up of 11 (eleven) posts of Accounts Officers, consequently 11
			<lb />
			(eleven) Direct Recruits came to be appointed vide Orders dated
			<lb />
			31.01.2009, 02.02.2009 and 04.02.2009. Thus, the appointment of
			<lb />
			Respondents No.7 to 17 was against the Direct Recruitment Quota
			<lb />
			of 50 per cent of the Rules of 1978 and having been appointed in
			<lb />
			Substantive capacity, were made senior to the Petitioners who
			<lb />
			were promoted on Officiating capacity, as 20 (twenty) Officers
			<lb />
			senior to them were already working in Officiating capacity. That,
			<lb />
			Rule 24 Sub Clause 5 of the Sikkim Finance Accounts Service
			<lb />
			(Amendment) Rules, 1986 (hereinafter &quot;Rules of 1986&quot;) provides
			<lb />
			for Rota Quota but the Government had considered the Promotion
			<lb />
			of Senior Accountants to the post of Accounts Officers from
			<lb />
			December, 2003 to June, 2007, duly utilizing Direct Recruitment
			<lb />
			Quota either on Officiating basis and then in Substantive capacity,
			<lb />
			or against Substantive capacity as and when vacancy existed, or
			<lb />
			against anticipated vacancies.
			<lb />
			(ii)
			<lb />
			Countering the allegation of the Petitioners being made
			<lb />
			junior to Respondents No.4, 5 and 6, it was explained that they
			<lb />
			were placed at Serial Nos.1, 2 and 3 amongst 19 (nineteen)
			<lb />
			candidates in the Departmental Examination held for Promotion
			<lb />
			which was subject to availability of vacancies, which occurred on
			<lb />
			24.12.1997. The validity of the Panel was extended up to
			<lb />
			31.12.1999 and the Petitioners No.1, 2 and 3 were promoted as
			<lb />
			Senior Accountants on 31.12.1998. Similarly, one D.R. Pradhan
			<lb />
			and the Petitioner No.8, were promoted on 22.05.1999. On
			<lb />
			14.06.1999, the Petitioners No.3, 4, 6, 7 and 9 submitted a
			<lb />
			Petition to the Government seeking extension of the Panel till
			<lb />
			finalization of anticipated vacancies of Senior Accountants. On due
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			7
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			consideration by the Government, these persons also came to be
			<lb />
			promoted as Senior Accountants on 27.06.2000. That, the Petition
			<lb />
			deserves a dismissal on grounds of delay and laches, as the Orders
			<lb />
			of the Petitioners pertaining to Officiating capacity was issued in
			<lb />
			2008 while the Writ Petition was filed only in 2016.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			The Respondents No.4, 5 and 6 filed their respective
			<lb />
			Counter-Affidavits which, in sum and substance, were similar to
			<lb />
			each other and substantially reiterated the facts as set out in the
			<lb />
			Counter-Affidavit of the Respondents No.1, 2 and 3.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Respondents No.7 to 17, while denying and disputing
			<lb />
			the allegations made in the Writ Petition, reiterated the position of
			<lb />
			Quota and Rota as spelt out by the State-Respondents No.1, 2 and
			<lb />
			3 and averred that the prayers in the Petition are misconceived and
			<lb />
			liable to be rejected by this Court as also the Writ Petition.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			In Rejoinder, the Petitioners elucidated that by the time
			<lb />
			the Cadre was revised in the month of December 2008, around 14
			<lb />
			(fourteen) people had retired/expired which has not been
			<lb />
			addressed by the State-Respondents as they were aware that the
			<lb />
			Petitioners could well have been accommodated in the said 14
			<lb />
			(fourteen) vacancies. The names of the 14 (fourteen) persons who
			<lb />
			had retired/expired between 2003 to December 2008, were also
			<lb />
			detailed in the Rejoinder.
			<lb />
			6.(i)
			<lb />
			Advancing his arguments for the Petitioners, Learned
			<lb />
			Senior Counsel Mr. A. Moulik, while reiterating the averments made
			<lb />
			in the Writ Petition and the Rejoinder, contended that the State-
			<lb />
			Respondents have attempted to prove that the Promotion of the
			<lb />
			Petitioners as Accounts Officers in Officiating capacity was merely a
			<lb />
			stop gap arrangement and a fortuitous appointment as such, their
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			8
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			past Services could not be counted for the purposes of rendering
			<lb />
			them senior to the private Respondents. Relying on the decision in
			<lb />
			D.R. Nim vs. Union of India 1 , it was canvassed that the Petitioners
			<lb />
			have worked in the post of Accounts Officers for several years and
			<lb />
			have never been reverted, hence they are entitled to Seniority
			<lb />
			from 08.05.2008, the date of their Officiating Orders in the posts of
			<lb />
			Accounts Officers. It was further contended that the Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Supreme Court has held in Rudra Kumar Sain and Others vs. Union of
			<lb />
			India and Others 2 that if an appointment is made to meet a
			<lb />
			particular contingency and for a specific period, then such an
			<lb />
			appointment is ad hoc or stop gap. On the other hand, if the post is
			<lb />
			created to meet a sudden and temporary situation then the
			<lb />
			appointment is fortuitous but these criterion are not attracted in
			<lb />
			the Order of the Petitioners, dated 08.05.2008. Drawing support
			<lb />
			from the decision in O.P. Singla and Another vs. Union of India and
			<lb />
			Others 3 , Learned Senior Counsel next contended that as per the
			<lb />
			said ratio, if a temporary employee works for five to twelve years
			<lb />
			continuously and the Appointment Order reads as &quot;Until further
			<lb />
			orders&quot; then such appointment cannot be termed as ad hoc or
			<lb />
			fortuitous or stop gap, so also is the case of the Petitioners. That,
			<lb />
			the two conditions laid out in the Officiating Promotion Order dated
			<lb />
			08.05.2008 were mere requirements. The Petitioners had indeed
			<lb />
			completed 6 (six) years of Service as Senior Accountants as
			<lb />
			required by the relevant Rules, making them eligible for Promotion
			<lb />
			as Accounts Officers in 2004/2006 itself. However, the Petitioners
			<lb />
			continued as Officiating Accounts Officers for years together due to
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			1 AIR 1967 SC 1301
			<lb />
			2 (2000) 8 SCC 25
			<lb />
			3 (1984) 4 SCC 450
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			9
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place='headnote'>
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			inaction and negligence of the State-Respondents, thus the
			<lb />
			Petitioners have the right to claim Seniority over the private
			<lb />
			Respondents. On this count, reliance was placed on Baleshwar Dass
			<lb />
			and Others vs. State of U.P. and Others 4 .
			<lb />
			(ii)
			<lb />
			Canvassing the contention that there were sufficient
			<lb />
			vacancies in the Substantive posts in which the Petitioners could
			<lb />
			have been promoted on 08.05.2008 itself, Learned Senior Counsel
			<lb />
			pointed out that there were 10 (ten) vacancies in the rank of
			<lb />
			Accounts Officer when the Petitioners were promoted on Officiating
			<lb />
			basis on 08.05.2008, as the State-Respondents have claimed at
			<lb />
			Paragraph &quot;5(d)&quot; of their Counter-Affidavit that there were 46
			<lb />
			(forty-six) vacancies as on 01.07.2003 in the rank of Accounts
			<lb />
			Officer to be filled up, out of which 9 (nine) posts were filled up on
			<lb />
			19.12.2003, another 19 (nineteen) posts were filled up on
			<lb />
			20.02.2004 and 8 (eight) vacancies were filled up on 08.06.2006.
			<lb />
			Thus, up to 08.05.2008, only 36 (thirty-six) vacancies out of 46
			<lb />
			(forty-six) were filled up in the Substantive capacity and 10 (ten)
			<lb />
			vacancies were yet to be filled. Hence, it was erroneous to state
			<lb />
			that when the 10 (ten) Petitioners were promoted as Accounts
			<lb />
			Officers (Officiating), there was no vacancy.
			<lb />
			(iii)
			<lb />
			It was further contended that as on 03.06.2003, the
			<lb />
			Cadre Strength of Accounts Officers was 77 (seventy-seven) for
			<lb />
			which reliance was placed on Annexure R-2. As on 01.07.2003, the
			<lb />
			vacancies to be filled up out of 77 (seventy-seven) posts was 46
			<lb />
			(forty-six) for which, attention of this Court was invited to
			<lb />
			Annexure R-3. That, vide Annexure R-11 dated 15.12.2008, the
			<lb />
			Cadre Strength of Accounts Officers was increased from 77
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place='footnote'>
			4 (1980) 4 SCC 226
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			10
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			(seventy-seven) to 103 (one hundred and three) thereby creating
			<lb />
			26 (twenty-six) new posts. Hence, as on the said date, total
			<lb />
			vacancies amounted to 72 (seventy-two) by adding the 46 (forty-
			<lb />
			six) existing vacancies and 26 (twenty-six) newly created posts.
			<lb />
			That, 9 (nine) Senior Accountants were promoted as Accounts
			<lb />
			Officers on Substantive basis of which, 4 (four) retired/died before
			<lb />
			the Petitioners were promoted on 08.05.2008. Thereafter on
			<lb />
			20.02.2004, 19 (nineteen) Senior Accountants were promoted as
			<lb />
			Accounts Officers in Substantive capacity out of which, 8 (eight)
			<lb />
			persons retired. Vide Order dated 23.02.2004, 22 (twenty-two)
			<lb />
			persons were promoted as Accounts Officers who were later
			<lb />
			absorbed in Substantive posts vide different Orders through the
			<lb />
			years 2006, 2008 and 2009. Thus, out of the 72 (seventy-two)
			<lb />
			vacancies existing till 15.12.2008, 56 (fifty-six) vacancies were
			<lb />
			filled by 21.01.2009 and 16 (sixteen) vacancies were yet to be
			<lb />
			filled. That, the recruitment of Respondents No.7 to 17 was against
			<lb />
			non-existent vacancies. That, the 20 (twenty) senior most
			<lb />
			Accounts Officers had to be promoted out of the 26 (twenty-six)
			<lb />
			new vacancies of which, 6 (six) vacancies then remained in hand,
			<lb />
			in which Respondents No.7 to 17 could not be accommodated
			<lb />
			besides, the State-Respondents have not addressed the death or
			<lb />
			retirement of 14 (fourteen) Accounts Officers up to the end of
			<lb />
			2008, thereby creating vacancies by 2008 in addition to the stated
			<lb />
			72 (seventy-two) vacancies.
			<lb />
			(iv)
			<lb />
			That, the delay in approaching the Court is on account
			<lb />
			of the absence of any Seniority List and that there is still no
			<lb />
			Confirmation List as on date. On the point of delay, reliance was
			<lb />
			placed on Ram Nath Sao alias Ram Nath Sahu and Others vs.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			11
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			Gobardhan Sao and Others 5 . Relying on proposition &quot;(B)&quot; of
			<lb />
			Paragraph &quot;47&quot; of the ratio in Direct Recruit Class II Engineering
			<lb />
			Officers&apos; Association vs. State of Maharashtra and Others 6 , Learned
			<lb />
			Senior Counsel for the Petitioners submitted that in terms thereof,
			<lb />
			in the instant matter, even assuming that the initial appointment
			<lb />
			was not made by following the procedure prescribed, the
			<lb />
			Petitioners continued in Service uninterruptedly till regularization in
			<lb />
			accordance with the Rules, therefore the period of Officiating
			<lb />
			Service ought to be counted towards Seniority vis-à-vis the
			<lb />
			Respondents No.7 to 17. The Petitioners could have been
			<lb />
			confirmed in 2006 and 2008 in the existing vacancies. The
			<lb />
			Petitioners have been deprived of Promotion in their right time and
			<lb />
			have been kept on Officiating basis when they are entitled to
			<lb />
			Seniority over the Respondents No.7 to 17. Garnering strength
			<lb />
			from the ratio of Narender Chadha vs. Union of India 7 , it was stated
			<lb />
			that the Petitioners&apos; case is comparable to the said ratio as the
			<lb />
			Petitioners were qualified to fill the posts. To further reinforce his
			<lb />
			submissions, reliance was placed on the decisions in S.B.
			<lb />
			Patwardhan and Another vs. State of Maharashtra and Others 8 , Pran
			<lb />
			Krishna Goswami and Others vs. State of West Bengal and Others 9 , G.K.
			<lb />
			Dudani and Others vs. S.D. Sharma and Others 10 , G.C. Gupta and Others
			<lb />
			vs. N.K. Pandey and Others 11 , M.V. Krishna Rao and Others vs. Union of
			<lb />
			India and Others 12 and State of W.B. and Others vs. Aghore Nath Dey
			<lb />
			and Others 13 .
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			5 AIR 2002 SC 1201
			<lb />
			6 (1990) 2 SCC 715
			<lb />
			7 (1986) 2 SCC 157
			<lb />
			8 (1977) 3 SCC 399
			<lb />
			9 AIR 1985 SC 1605
			<lb />
			10 AIR 1986 SC 1455
			<lb />
			11 (1988) 1 SCC 316
			<lb />
			12 (1994) Supp 3 SCC 553
			<lb />
			13 (1993) 3 SCC 371
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			12
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place='headnote'>
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			7.
			<lb />
			Learned Additional Advocate General, Dr. (Mrs.) Doma
			<lb />
			T. Bhutia, for the State-Respondents No.1 to 3, per contra,
			<lb />
			contended that once the Petitioners have accepted the Officiating
			<lb />
			Promotion along with the conditions therein without demur, it
			<lb />
			tantamounts to their acceptance of the conditions and hence, they
			<lb />
			have waived their rights pertaining to Seniority as they failed to
			<lb />
			raise any issue on this point, at the relevant time. Towards this
			<lb />
			point, reliance was placed on P.S. Gopinathan vs. State of Kerala and
			<lb />
			Others 14 . Drawing strength from the ratio in Rajen Kumar Chettri vs.
			<lb />
			State of Sikkim and Others 15 , it was contended that the Petition has
			<lb />
			been filed belatedly and for this reason, cannot be sustained. That,
			<lb />
			there were no vacancies in the Quota for Promotees when the
			<lb />
			Petitioners were promoted on Officiating basis and their claim for
			<lb />
			Seniority is unsubstantiated and stale. On this count, reliance was
			<lb />
			placed on B.S. Sheshagiri Setty and Others vs. State of Karnataka and
			<lb />
			Others 16 . That, Seniority can be reckoned only from the date that
			<lb />
			the Petitioners entered the Service in Substantive posts and not
			<lb />
			retrospectively. Contending that the Promotees cannot be
			<lb />
			accommodated in the Quota meant for the Direct Recruits, thus
			<lb />
			resulting in the Officiating Promotion of the Petitioners, reliance
			<lb />
			was placed on Nani Sha and Others vs. State of Arunachal Pradesh and
			<lb />
			Others 17 . That, the Petition is hit by laches and delay, this aspect of
			<lb />
			the argument was buttressed by Union of India and Others vs. M.K.
			<lb />
			Sarkar 18 . Relying on the facts and circumstances as detailed in the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			14 (2008) 7 SCC 70
			<lb />
			15 2019 SCC OnLine Sikk 202
			<lb />
			16 (2016) 2 SCC 123
			<lb />
			17 (2007) 15 SCC 406
			<lb />
			18 (2010) 2 SCC 59
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			13
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place='headnote'>
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			Counter-Affidavit, it was contended that the Petition deserves a
			<lb />
			dismissal.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			Learned Senior Advocate Mr. Karma Thinlay, for
			<lb />
			Respondents No.4, 5 and 6 reiterated and relied on the averments
			<lb />
			made in their Return and submitted that they were promoted as
			<lb />
			Accounts Officers on Officiating capacity in the year 2005 and were
			<lb />
			confirmed in the year 2009. That, should the Petitioners be granted
			<lb />
			reliefs in terms of Seniority from 2008, the cascading effect
			<lb />
			thereon would be to the benefit of the Respondents No.4, 5 and 6,
			<lb />
			who would also then be eligible for Seniority from the year 2005.
			<lb />
			That, 46 (forty-six) vacant posts of Accounts Officers existed in
			<lb />
			2003 and the Officiating Order of the Respondents No.4, 5 and 6
			<lb />
			was issued when the 46 (forty-six) posts were vacant. In fact, out
			<lb />
			of the 77 (seventy-seven) posts of Accounts Officers at the
			<lb />
			relevant time, 31 (thirty-one) were filled and against the 46 (forty-
			<lb />
			six) vacancies, Respondents No.4, 5 and 6 had been appointed on
			<lb />
			Officiating basis on 05.02.2005 and confirmed on 21.01.2009.
			<lb />
			Respondents No.4, 5 and 6 are therefore senior to the Petitioners.
			<lb />
			That, the Petition being devoid of merit ought to be dismissed.
			<lb />
			9.(i)
			<lb />
			Learned Senior Advocate Mr. J.B. Pradhan, on behalf of
			<lb />
			Respondents No.7 to 17, building his arguments on the edifice of
			<lb />
			Rule 24 (5) of the Rules of 1986, pointed out that the said Rule
			<lb />
			provides that the relative Seniority inter se of persons recruited to
			<lb />
			the Service through Competitive Examination and by Promotion,
			<lb />
			shall be determined according to the rotation of vacancies between
			<lb />
			Direct Recruits and Promotees which shall be based on the Quotas
			<lb />
			of vacancies reserved for Direct Recruitment and Promotion
			<lb />
			respectively. That, the said Rule also provides in the &quot;Explanation&quot;
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			14
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			that &quot;a Roster shall be maintained based on the reservation for Direct
			<lb />
			Recruitment and Promotion in the Rules, which shall be as follows; (1)
			<lb />
			Promotion (2) Direct Recruitment (3) Promotion (4) Direct Recruitment
			<lb />
			and so on. Appointment shall be made in accordance with this Roster and
			<lb />
			Seniority determined accordingly.&quot; Therefore, the Petitioners cannot
			<lb />
			be promoted in the Quota of the Direct Recruits, in excess to their
			<lb />
			own Quota. That, this position is fortified by Schedule II to the
			<lb />
			same Rules, which provides for 50 per cent by Direct Recruitment
			<lb />
			through Open Competitive Examination and 50 per cent by
			<lb />
			Promotion
			<lb />
			through
			<lb />
			Limited
			<lb />
			Departmental
			<lb />
			Competitive
			<lb />
			Examination/Deputation/Re-employment.
			<lb />
			Attention
			<lb />
			was
			<lb />
			also
			<lb />
			invited to Rules 6 and 16 of the Rules supra. That, as per the Office
			<lb />
			Note Sheet dated 30.06.2003, out of 77 (seventy-seven) numbers
			<lb />
			of Posts of Accounts Officers in the Junior Grade in the year 2003,
			<lb />
			46 (forty-six) Posts were vacant. In terms of Schedule II of the
			<lb />
			Rules of 1986, 46 (forty-six) Posts were to be equally divided
			<lb />
			between Promotees and Direct Recruits, however, between the
			<lb />
			years 2003 up to 2008, no appointments by way of Direct
			<lb />
			Recruitment were made, whereas the 23 (twenty-three) posts for
			<lb />
			Promotees was duly filled up and exceeded as well. Learned Senior
			<lb />
			Counsel contended that when the Petitioners were promoted on
			<lb />
			Officiating basis on 08.05.2008, there was no Substantive posts
			<lb />
			neither were the Rules relaxed then by any executive Order. It was
			<lb />
			only on 19.05.2012 that a Notification pertaining to relaxation of
			<lb />
			Rules was published. The State-Respondent No.3 sent the Letter of
			<lb />
			recommendation for appointment of the Petitioners only on
			<lb />
			13.09.2012 to the SPSC, upon which the Departmental Promotion
			<lb />
			Committee of the SPSC convened on 24.01.2013 and accepted the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			15
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			recommendations. The Petitioners were then promoted to the
			<lb />
			Substantive posts of Accounts Officers only after 24.01.2013,
			<lb />
			whereas the Respondents No.7 to 17 were appointed in
			<lb />
			Substantive posts between 31.01.2009 to 04.02.2009 thereby
			<lb />
			rendering them senior to the Petitioners in terms of Rule 24 supra.
			<lb />
			Inviting the attention of this Court to the ratio in State of W.B. and
			<lb />
			Others vs. Aghore Nath Dey and Others (supra) wherein the dispute
			<lb />
			arose as a result of Promotions being made in excess of the
			<lb />
			Promotees Quota in the case of the surplus Promotees, it was
			<lb />
			contended that even if it is to be presumed that the Rules were
			<lb />
			relaxed, the relaxation can only be effective from the date of
			<lb />
			issuance of Notification by the Government in this context, i.e. in
			<lb />
			the case of the Petitioners from 19.05.2012, if not from
			<lb />
			16.03.2013 which is the correct approach and would still render
			<lb />
			them subordinate to Respondents No.7 to 17.
			<lb />
			(ii)
			<lb />
			That, the amendments to the Rules of 1978, notified on
			<lb />
			25.02.1987, are relevant which provides at Rule 6 that competitive
			<lb />
			examination was to be held by the Commission and the number of
			<lb />
			vacancies to be filled up by Promotion, Deputation or Re-
			<lb />
			employment in one year, would not exceed 50 per cent of the total
			<lb />
			number of vacancies to be filled in that year. Pointing to the
			<lb />
			alleged incongruities in the grounds raised by the Petitioners, more
			<lb />
			especially in Grounds No.1, 2, 5, 8 and 11, Learned Senior Counsel
			<lb />
			contended that the Petitioners have approached the Court
			<lb />
			belatedly as they seek to challenge the appointment of
			<lb />
			Respondents No.7 to 17 after a period of 8 (eight) years of their
			<lb />
			appointment as Accounts Officers and that of Respondents No.4 to
			<lb />
			6 after a period of 19 (nineteen) years from the date they were
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			16
			<lb />
		</page>
		>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			appointed as Senior Accountants. That apart, it was a rather
			<lb />
			strange proposition that the Petitioners were claiming Service
			<lb />
			Seniority from the date of their Officiating Service despite the clear
			<lb />
			conditions specified in their Orders. These Orders were unassailed
			<lb />
			before the concerned authorities thereby barring the Petition by the
			<lb />
			principles of Waiver, Estoppel and Acquiescence, to buttress this
			<lb />
			submission reliance was placed on P.S. Gopinathan (supra) and M.P.
			<lb />
			Palanisamy and Others vs. A. Krishnan and Others 19 . Besides, the
			<lb />
			Petitioners cannot pick and choose parts of the Order favourable to
			<lb />
			them and reject the others, as held in M.P. Palanisamy (supra).
			<lb />
			That, the Rota Quota Rule was not broken but procedure
			<lb />
			prescribed therein was not followed, thus to utilize the Rota Quota
			<lb />
			Rule, the Notification pertaining to relaxation of Rules was issued
			<lb />
			on 19.05.2012 to enable regularization of the appointment of the
			<lb />
			Petitioners. That, in fact, the Rota Quota Rule breaks down only
			<lb />
			when efforts are made by the Government through advertisement
			<lb />
			inviting candidates for Direct Recruitment but fails to get
			<lb />
			candidates making such appointments an impossibility. It is then
			<lb />
			that the Government has to derive a method to deviate and see
			<lb />
			how the posts can be filled up. The Government is thus under an
			<lb />
			obligation to establish by documentary evidence that there were no
			<lb />
			suitable candidates for appointment by Direct Recruitment.
			<lb />
			Paragraph &quot;5 (e)&quot; of the State-Respondents&apos; Counter-Affidavit
			<lb />
			indicates that no such effort was made. On this count, succour was
			<lb />
			drawn from the ratio in Suraj Parkash Gupta and Others vs. State of &amp;K and Others 20 and N.K. Chauhan and Others vs. State of Gujarat and
			<lb />
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			J19 (2009) 6 SCC 428
			<lb />
			20 (2000) 7 SCC 561
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			17
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place='headnote'>
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			Others 21 . Further, support was garnered from the ratio in Union of
			<lb />
			India vs. Dharam Pal and Others 22 wherein it was observed that
			<lb />
			where the initial appointment is only ad hoc and not according to
			<lb />
			Rules and made as a stop gap arrangement, the period of
			<lb />
			Officiation in such post cannot be taken into account for
			<lb />
			considering the Seniority. That, even assuming that there were
			<lb />
			vacancies for the purposes of Promotion, the Petitioners were to
			<lb />
			have adhered to the procedure of appearing for Departmental
			<lb />
			Examinations and thereafter obtaining the recommendation of the
			<lb />
			SPSC, this was not done. Inviting the attention of this Court to
			<lb />
			Keshav Chandra Joshi and Others vs. Union of India and Others 23 and
			<lb />
			Samdup Tshering Bhutia vs. State of Sikkim and Others 24 , it was
			<lb />
			canvassed that the Officiating Promotion of the Petitioners was
			<lb />
			fortuitous appointments and the Direct Recruit Quota on which
			<lb />
			they were promoted, has to invariably revert back to the Direct
			<lb />
			Recruits for the next appointments. That, the Petitioners have
			<lb />
			themselves accepted by averments made in their Rejoinder that
			<lb />
			other Accounts Officers similarly circumstanced as them, were
			<lb />
			promoted in Substantive Capacity in the vacancies meant for both
			<lb />
			Promotees and Direct Recruits. Relying on the ratio of Direct Recruit
			<lb />
			Class II Engineering Officers&apos; Association (supra), Learned Senior
			<lb />
			Counsel advanced the contention that the case of the Petitioners
			<lb />
			falls under the corollary of Proposition &quot;(A)&quot; in Paragraph &quot;47&quot;
			<lb />
			therein and not under proposition &quot;(B)&quot;, as advanced by Learned
			<lb />
			Senior Counsel for the Petitioners. That, in view of the grounds
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			21 (1977) 1 SCC 308
			<lb />
			22 (2009) 4 SCC 170
			<lb />
			23 (1992) Supp 1 SCC 272
			<lb />
			24 2017 SCC OnLine Sikk 153
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			18
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			canvassed, the Petition being devoid of merit deserves to be
			<lb />
			dismissed.
			<lb />
			10.
			<lb />
			In rebuttal, Learned Senior Counsel for the Petitioners,
			<lb />
			while agreeing with Learned Senior Counsel for Respondents No.7
			<lb />
			to 17 that the Rota Quota Rule had not broken down, submitted
			<lb />
			that initially due to filling up of the posts of Direct Recruits by the
			<lb />
			Promotees, there was a breakdown of the Rota Quota Rule but
			<lb />
			these appointments were subsequently regularized restoring the
			<lb />
			Rota Quota. That, no condition in the Officiating Order debarred
			<lb />
			the Petitioners from claiming Seniority from the date of Promotion
			<lb />
			in their Officiating capacity once they were regularized in the
			<lb />
			Substantive posts. That, the settled position of law is as laid down
			<lb />
			in Direct Recruit Class II Engineering Officers&apos; Association (supra) by
			<lb />
			the Constitution Bench and this is applicable to the Petitioners&apos;
			<lb />
			case. That, the ratio in Samdup Tshering Bhutia (supra) relied on by
			<lb />
			the Respondents No.7 to 17, is not relevant in the instant matter
			<lb />
			as the Court was not informed of the correct factual position and
			<lb />
			its conclusion for arriving at the finding that the appointment was
			<lb />
			fortuitous, was sans reasons. The question of the Petitioners
			<lb />
			accepting the Officiating Promotion without demur does not arise,
			<lb />
			they being mere employees and the State-Respondents were
			<lb />
			required to look after their welfare. That, the case of M.P.
			<lb />
			Palanisamy (supra) relied on by the Respondents No.7 to 17, is
			<lb />
			distinguishable from the instant facts and not applicable to the
			<lb />
			Petitioners&apos; case as also the ratio in P.S. Gopinathan (supra) and
			<lb />
			hence the Petitioners are deserving of the reliefs prayed for.
			<lb />
			11.
			<lb />
			The rival submissions of Learned Counsel for the
			<lb />
			parties were heard in extenso by me and given due consideration.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			19
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			The decisions relied on by Learned Counsel for the parties have
			<lb />
			also been perused as also the pleadings and all documents on
			<lb />
			record.
			<lb />
			12.
			<lb />
			The only question that falls for consideration before
			<lb />
			this Court is;
			<lb />
			Whether the fitment of Seniority determined by the
			<lb />
			Department vis-à-vis the Petitioners and the
			<lb />
			Respondents No.7 to 17, was in accordance with the
			<lb />
			Rules?
			<lb />
			13.(i)
			<lb />
			To assess with clarity the grievances of the Petitioners,
			<lb />
			it is essential to briefly refer to the Rules which govern them. The
			<lb />
			Sikkim Subordinate Accounts Service Rules, 1984 was notified on
			<lb />
			28.01.1985 and governs the posts of Accounts Clerk, Junior
			<lb />
			Accountant, Accountant and Senior Accountant. The Petitioners
			<lb />
			were initially appointed in Service under these Rules. The Rules of
			<lb />
			1978, notified on 30.04.1979, governs the appointment of
			<lb />
			Accounts Officers and Senior Accounts Officers consisting of three
			<lb />
			Grades i.e. Junior, Senior and Selection Grades. The said Rules
			<lb />
			comprised of thirteen Clauses including Rule 13 which is the
			<lb />
			interpretation Clause. Rule 3 provided inter alia for &quot;Constitution of
			<lb />
			Service&quot;, Rule 4 was for &quot;Appointments and Postings,&quot; Rule 5 detailed
			<lb />
			&quot;Initial Constitution of the Service,&quot; Rule 6 laid down the &quot;Method of
			<lb />
			Recruitment to the Service,&quot; Rule 7 was concerned with &quot;Qualification
			<lb />
			for Appointment,&quot; Rule 8 dealt with &quot;Constitution of Selection
			<lb />
			Committees.&quot; The Committee was to comprise of the Chairman,
			<lb />
			Sikkim Public Service Commission or his nominee, the Chief
			<lb />
			Secretary to the Government, the Finance Secretary and the
			<lb />
			Establishment Secretary to the Government and was entrusted
			<lb />
			with the task of grading persons mentioned in Rule 5, for
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			20
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			absorption in the various Grades of the Service and under Sub Rule
			<lb />
			(4) of Rule 6. The Committee was also to make recommendations
			<lb />
			for Direct Recruitments under Clause (i) of Rule 6 or Sub Rule (4)
			<lb />
			of Rule 6. Promotion of persons mentioned in Rule 6 (1) (iv) was
			<lb />
			also vested on the Committee. The recommendations of the
			<lb />
			Committee, as finally approved by the Commission, was to be
			<lb />
			forwarded to the Government along with all other papers sent to
			<lb />
			the Selection Committee. Rule 9 elucidated the &quot;Training, Probation
			<lb />
			and Confirmation&quot; of persons appointed, while Rule 10 laid the
			<lb />
			details of how &quot;Seniority&quot; was to be computed and provided that the
			<lb />
			persons deemed to have been appointed to the Service under Rule
			<lb />
			5 was to rank as senior to all those who may be appointed under
			<lb />
			Rule 6 and that, &quot;The inter-se seniority of direct recruits and promotees
			<lb />
			shall be in the order in which their names appear in the merit/select list.
			<lb />
			As for seniority between promotees and direct recruits, persons promoted
			<lb />
			in one year shall rank senior to persons recruited direct in that year.&quot;
			<lb />
			Schedule I to the Rules detailed the strength and composition and
			<lb />
			designation of posts. It indicated 29 (twenty-nine) posts then in
			<lb />
			the Junior Grade i.e. that of Accounts Officers.
			<lb />
			(ii)
			<lb />
			The Rules came to be amended several times in the
			<lb />
			interregnum and twice in 1986, one vide Notification No.15/Fin.
			<lb />
			dated 11.03.1986 and vide Notification No.20/Fin. dated
			<lb />
			25.02.1987. Vide the amendment on 25.02.1987, the sanctioned
			<lb />
			strength of Accounts Officers was shown to be 43 (forty-three) in
			<lb />
			Schedule I. Rules 6 and 16 of the amended Rules are extracted
			<lb />
			hereinbelow;
			<lb />
			&quot;Amendment of rules
			<lb />
			6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13.
			<lb />
			In the said rules, for rules 6,
			<lb />
			7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12 and 13,
			<lb />
			following
			<lb />
			rules
			<lb />
			shall
			<lb />
			be
			<lb />
			substituted, namely:-
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			21
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			&quot;6. Method of Recruitment to the Service -(1)
			<lb />
			Subject to the provision of rules 5, recruitment to
			<lb />
			the Service shall, after the appointed day, be
			<lb />
			made by the following methods, namely:-
			<lb />
			(i)
			<lb />
			Competitive Examination to be held by the
			<lb />
			Commission.
			<lb />
			(ii)
			<lb />
			Obtaining the services of any employee of the
			<lb />
			Central Government or other State Governments.
			<lb />
			(iii) Promotion
			<lb />
			from
			<lb />
			among
			<lb />
			persons
			<lb />
			holding
			<lb />
			substantive appointment in Grade I mentioned in
			<lb />
			Schedule II to the Sikkim Sub-ordinate
			<lb />
			Accounts
			<lb />
			Service Rules, 1984.
			<lb />
			(iv) Re-employment, after retirement of any person,
			<lb />
			who in the opinion of the Government is suitable for
			<lb />
			such re-employment.
			<lb />
			2. (i) Government shall ordinarily decide in each
			<lb />
			year the number of vacancies in the Service to be
			<lb />
			filled in that year by direct recruitment and
			<lb />
			also the number to be filled by promotion or by
			<lb />
			any other method mentioned in sub-rule (1).
			<lb />
			(ii) The number of vacancies to be filled up by
			<lb />
			promotion, deputation or re-employment in any
			<lb />
			one year shall not exceed 50 per cent of the
			<lb />
			total number of vacancies to be filled in that
			<lb />
			year.&quot;
			<lb />
			……………………………………………………………………………………
			<lb />
			16. RECRUITMENT BY PROMOTION
			<lb />
			(1)
			<lb />
			……………………………………………………………………………………
			<lb />
			(2)
			<lb />
			The Government shall, every year for the purpose of
			<lb />
			promotion to the Service under Clause (iii) of sub-
			<lb />
			rule (1) of rule 6, prepare a list of names of persons
			<lb />
			in order of seniority who have, on the first day of
			<lb />
			that year, completed not less than six years of
			<lb />
			continuous service under the Government in a
			<lb />
			post included in Grade I mentioned in the Schedule
			<lb />
			II appended to the Sikkim Subordinate Accounts
			<lb />
			Service Rules, 1984.
			<lb />
			(3)
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			Government
			<lb />
			shall
			<lb />
			forward
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Commission the list of persons referred to in
			<lb />
			sub-rule (2) of this rule together with their
			<lb />
			character rolls and service records for the preceding
			<lb />
			five years indicating the anticipated number of
			<lb />
			vacancies to be filled by promotion in course of
			<lb />
			the period of 12 months commencing from the
			<lb />
			date of preparation of the list.
			<lb />
			(4)
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			Commission
			<lb />
			after
			<lb />
			satisfying
			<lb />
			themselves
			<lb />
			that the records and information complete in all
			<lb />
			respects have been received, shall convene a
			<lb />
			meeting
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Promotion
			<lb />
			Committee.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			Committee shall prepare a final list of persons
			<lb />
			who are found to be suitable for promotion to
			<lb />
			the Service on an overall relative assessment of
			<lb />
			their service records and interview.
			<lb />
			(5)
			<lb />
			The number of persons to be included in the list
			<lb />
			shall not exceed twice the number of vacancies to
			<lb />
			be filled by promotion.
			<lb />
			(6)
			<lb />
			The Commission shall forward the final list
			<lb />
			prepared under sub-rule (4) of this rule to the
			<lb />
			Government along with all the character rolls
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			service
			<lb />
			records
			<lb />
			received
			<lb />
			from
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Government.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			22
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			(7)
			<lb />
			The list shall ordinarily be in force for a period of
			<lb />
			twelve
			<lb />
			months
			<lb />
			from
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			date
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			recommendation of the Commission.
			<lb />
			(8)
			<lb />
			Appointment of persons included in the list to
			<lb />
			the service shall be made by the Government in the
			<lb />
			order in which the names of persons appear in the
			<lb />
			list.
			<lb />
			(9)
			<lb />
			It shall not be ordinarily necessary to consult
			<lb />
			the Commission before each appointment is
			<lb />
			made unless during the period of 12 months
			<lb />
			from the date of recommendation of the
			<lb />
			Commission there occurs
			<lb />
			deterioration in the
			<lb />
			work of the person which in the opinion of the
			<lb />
			Government,
			<lb />
			is
			<lb />
			such
			<lb />
			as
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			render
			<lb />
			him
			<lb />
			unsuitable for appointment to the service.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			(iii)
			<lb />
			Schedule II referred to in Rule 16 (2) supra details the
			<lb />
			&quot;Designation of Posts,&quot; &quot;Method of Recruitment&quot; and &quot;Eligibility
			<lb />
			Conditions&quot; of Selection Grade I, Selection Grade II, Senior Grade
			<lb />
			and Junior Grade. So far as the Junior Grade is concerned, it
			<lb />
			includes Accounts Officer/Accounts-cum-Administrative Officer/
			<lb />
			Audit Officer and the &quot;Method of Recruitment&quot; is shown to be 50 per
			<lb />
			cent by Direct Recruitment through Open Competitive Examination
			<lb />
			and 50 per cent by Promotion through a Limited Departmental
			<lb />
			Competitive
			<lb />
			Examination/Deputation/Re-employment.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			&quot;Eligibility Conditions&quot; for Promotion is reflected as follows,
			<lb />
			&quot;SCHEDULE -II
			<lb />
			……………………………………………………………………………………….
			<lb />
			By Promotion: Persons holding posts in Grade-I of
			<lb />
			the Sikkim Subordinate Accounts Service with at least 6
			<lb />
			years of service in the grade. The promotion shall be made
			<lb />
			on the basis of seniority-cum-merit.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			14.
			<lb />
			From a reading of the above Rules, it emerges that the
			<lb />
			posts of Accounts Officers were to be filled by way of Promotion
			<lb />
			and Direct Recruitment in the ratio of 50:50 each. The Petitioners
			<lb />
			were qualified as per the Rules in 2004-2006 as well as on
			<lb />
			08.05.2008, to be considered for Promotion as Accounts Officers.
			<lb />
			The Rules extracted supra required the State-Respondents to
			<lb />
			decide in each year, the number of vacancies in the Service to be
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			23
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			filled in that year by Direct Recruitment and Promotion and to take
			<lb />
			steps after assessing the vacancy, viz., including recommending
			<lb />
			the names of the Service holders for Promotion to Substantive
			<lb />
			Posts. The State-Respondents failed to comply with this
			<lb />
			requirement of the Rules nor were Examinations for either criteria
			<lb />
			held, as mandated. From the records available before this Court, it
			<lb />
			is clear that the procedure prescribed for recruitment was not
			<lb />
			adhered to by the State-Respondents which has, in fact, led to the
			<lb />
			heartburning amongst the Petitioners and the Direct Recruits
			<lb />
			concerning their inter se Seniority. Besides failing to take steps as
			<lb />
			enunciated hereinabove, the Government has not prepared a List
			<lb />
			of names of persons in order of Seniority (as per Rules) who have,
			<lb />
			on the first day of that year, completed not less than 6 (six) years
			<lb />
			of continuous Service as Senior Accountants nor was the List of
			<lb />
			such persons forwarded to the Commission along with the relevant
			<lb />
			documents. The anticipated number of vacancies to be filled by
			<lb />
			Promotion in the course of the period of 12 (twelve) months,
			<lb />
			commencing from the date of preparation of the List was not
			<lb />
			indicated as well. In the absence of necessary steps by the
			<lb />
			Government, it is evident that the Commission was not in a
			<lb />
			position to take consequential steps and convene a meeting of the
			<lb />
			Promotion Committee who had been vested with the responsibility
			<lb />
			of preparing a final List of persons found to be suitable for
			<lb />
			Promotion to the higher Service on an overall relative assessment
			<lb />
			of their Service Records and interview.
			<lb />
			15.(i)
			<lb />
			The State-Respondents have failed to enlighten this
			<lb />
			Court on the number of posts filled vide the two channels till 2009.
			<lb />
			Clearly, the Rules have been ignored and sidelined by the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			24
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			Government and appointments to the posts of Accounts Officers
			<lb />
			made by Promotion only. By their own admission, Direct
			<lb />
			Recruitment had been kept in abeyance from December, 2003 to
			<lb />
			2007 and the post of Accounts Officer in the Junior Grade was filled
			<lb />
			only by Promotion. While considering the conduct of the State-
			<lb />
			Respondents, it is apposite to refer to the observations made by
			<lb />
			the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Keshav Chandra Joshi (supra),
			<lb />
			wherein the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court while faced with, once again
			<lb />
			the proposition of reckoning inter se Seniority, was alive to the
			<lb />
			lackadaisical attitude of the Government and inter alia held as
			<lb />
			follows;
			<lb />
			&quot;22. In a democracy governed by rule of law, it is
			<lb />
			necessary for the appropriate governance of the country
			<lb />
			that the political executive should have the support of an
			<lb />
			efficient bureaucracy. Our Constitution enjoins upon the
			<lb />
			executive and charges the legislature to lay down the policy
			<lb />
			of administration in the light of the directive principles. The
			<lb />
			executive should implement them to establish the
			<lb />
			contemplated egalitarian social order envisaged in the
			<lb />
			preamble of the Constitution.
			<lb />
			……………………………………………………………………………………
			<lb />
			24. It is notorious that confirmation of an employee
			<lb />
			in a substantive post would take place long years after the
			<lb />
			retirement. An employee is entitled to be considered for
			<lb />
			promotion on regular basis to a higher post if he/she is an
			<lb />
			approved probationer in the substantive lower post. An
			<lb />
			officer appointed by promotion in accordance with Rules
			<lb />
			and within quota and on declaration of probation is entitled
			<lb />
			to reckon his seniority from the date of promotion and the
			<lb />
			entire length of service, though initially temporary, shall be
			<lb />
			counted for seniority. Ad hoc or fortuitous appointments on
			<lb />
			a temporary or stop gap basis cannot be taken into account
			<lb />
			for the purpose of seniority, even if the appointee was
			<lb />
			subsequently qualified to hold the post on a regular basis.
			<lb />
			To give benefit of such service would be contrary to
			<lb />
			equality enshrined in Article 14 read with Article 16(1) of
			<lb />
			the Constitution as unequals would be treated as equals.
			<lb />
			………&quot;
			<lb />
			A similar attitude of the concerned Departments as indicated
			<lb />
			above, are reflected even in the facts and circumstances of the
			<lb />
			instant case by the nonchalant circumvention of the Rules by the
			<lb />
			State-Respondents. Besides, sloth takes away a man&apos;s welfare.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			25
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			(ii)
			<lb />
			Rule 24 of the amended Rules of 1986 provides for
			<lb />
			&quot;Seniority&quot; and reads inter alia as follows;
			<lb />
			&quot;24. SENIORITY:
			<lb />
			(1) The persons deemed to have been appointed to the
			<lb />
			Service under rule 5 shall rank as senior to all those who
			<lb />
			may be appointed under rule 6:
			<lb />
			Provided that………………………………………………………………
			<lb />
			(2)
			<lb />
			…………………
			<lb />
			(3) The seniority inter-se of the persons recruited to the
			<lb />
			Service through competitive examination shall be in the
			<lb />
			same order in which their names appear in the merit list
			<lb />
			forwarded by the Commission under sub-rule (4) of rule 7.
			<lb />
			(4) The seniority inter-se of the persons appointed to the
			<lb />
			Service by promotion shall be in the same order in which
			<lb />
			their names appear in the list prepared under sub-rule (4)
			<lb />
			of rule 16 and forwarded by the Commission to the
			<lb />
			Government.
			<lb />
			(5) The relative seniority inter-se of persons recruited to
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Service
			<lb />
			through
			<lb />
			competitive
			<lb />
			examination
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			appointed to the Service by promotion shall be determined
			<lb />
			according to the rotation of vacancies between direct
			<lb />
			recruits and promotees which shall be based on the quotas
			<lb />
			of vacancies reserved for direct recruitment and promotion
			<lb />
			respectively in these rules.
			<lb />
			Explanation:-A roster shall be maintained based on the
			<lb />
			reservation for direct recruitment and promotion in these
			<lb />
			rules. The roster shall run as follows:-
			<lb />
			(1)
			<lb />
			Promotion, (2) Direct Recruitment, (3) Promotion,
			<lb />
			(4) Direct Recruitment and so on.
			<lb />
			Appointment shall be made in accordance with this
			<lb />
			roster and seniority determined accordingly.
			<lb />
			(6) Notwithstanding anything contained in rules 5 and 6,
			<lb />
			the seniority of persons mentioned in the third proviso to
			<lb />
			rule 5 and in clause (ii) of sub-rule (1) of rule 6, who are
			<lb />
			absorbed in the Service shall be such as may be
			<lb />
			determined by Government in each case.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			(iii)
			<lb />
			These Rules, for the first time provided for a Roster
			<lb />
			System, for recruitment. Schedule II to the Rules elucidates that
			<lb />
			the Junior Grade comprising of Accounts Officers, is to be filled 50
			<lb />
			per cent by Direct Recruitment through Open Competitive
			<lb />
			Examination and 50 per cent by Promotion through Limited
			<lb />
			Departmental
			<lb />
			Competitive
			<lb />
			Examination/Deputation/Re-
			<lb />
			employment. At this juncture, it is worth noticing that the State-
			<lb />
			Respondents have not explained as to how the rotation of the
			<lb />
			Quota is fixed, is it to be construed as the Promotees getting the
			<lb />
			first, third and fifth of the vacancies that occur or was it by way of
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			26
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			entitlement of half the vacancies? The facts placed before this
			<lb />
			Court by the State-Respondents in this context, are opaque and do
			<lb />
			not reflect the method adopted by them. There is an absence of
			<lb />
			data to indicate the Quota Rota adopted up to May, 2003, when
			<lb />
			the last Direct Recruitment to the post of Accounts Officer allegedly
			<lb />
			took place.
			<lb />
			(iv)
			<lb />
			In 1988, the Rules were further amended and notified
			<lb />
			on 11.08.1988. Serial number &quot;2&quot; reads as follows;
			<lb />
			&quot;2. Rules 6 Method of recruitment to the Service:
			<lb />
			In clause (iii) of sub-rule (i) of this rule add the following
			<lb />
			words at the end of the sentence:-&quot;to be held by the
			<lb />
			Commission.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			&quot;Schedule I&quot; of the existing Schedule was substituted by a new
			<lb />
			Schedule. As already pointed out, the Commission&apos;s hands were
			<lb />
			evidently tied in the absence of necessary and timely steps by the
			<lb />
			Government in terms of Rules 6 and 16 supra. By a Notification
			<lb />
			dated 29.06.1996, amending the Rules further, the post of
			<lb />
			Accounts Officer was indicated to be 73 (seventy-three). On
			<lb />
			26.08.1998, another amendment took place which stated inter alia
			<lb />
			as follows;
			<lb />
			&quot;Amendment
			<lb />
			of Schedule II.
			<lb />
			2. In the Sikkim Finance and Accounts
			<lb />
			Service Rules, 1978, in Schedule-II,
			<lb />
			for the post of Accounts Officer/
			<lb />
			Assistant
			<lb />
			Director/Accounts-cum-
			<lb />
			Administrative Officer/Audit Officer,
			<lb />
			under
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			heading
			<lb />
			method
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			recruitment, for the figures and words
			<lb />
			&quot;66% by direct recruitment and 34% by
			<lb />
			promotion&quot;, the figures and words
			<lb />
			&quot;50% by direct recruitment and &quot;50%
			<lb />
			by promotion&quot; shall be substituted
			<lb />
			respectively.&quot;
			<lb />
			(v)
			<lb />
			Indeed, this amendment is superfluous, as the
			<lb />
			amended Rules of 1986, notified on 25.02.1985, at Schedule II,
			<lb />
			already indicated 50 per cent by Promotion and 50 percent by
			<lb />
			Direct Recruitment, besides, a careful scrutiny of the Rules placed
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			27
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			before this Court, nowhere indicates &quot;66 per cent by Direct
			<lb />
			Recruitment and 34 per cent by Promotion.&quot; On 05.09.2001, vide a
			<lb />
			Notification of the same date, further amendment was made to the
			<lb />
			Rules which provided that &quot;……in Schedule II, in serial No.4, under the
			<lb />
			column eligibility conditions for the figure &quot;8; the figure &quot;6&quot; shall be
			<lb />
			substituted&quot; which meant that Senior Accountants, would be eligible
			<lb />
			for Promotion to the post of Accounts Officers on putting in 6 (six)
			<lb />
			years of qualifying service instead of 8 (eight) years, as previously
			<lb />
			required. The Petitioners thus were in the zone of consideration for
			<lb />
			Promotion having indubitably completed 6 (six) years of Service as
			<lb />
			Senior Accountants by 2004/2006. On 03.06.2003, another
			<lb />
			amendment came to be made in the Rules vide which the post of
			<lb />
			Accounts Officer was increased to 77 (seventy-seven). However, as
			<lb />
			already pointed out, the State-Respondents were loath to take
			<lb />
			timely steps although the Rules made adequate provisions.
			<lb />
			16.(i)
			<lb />
			Notably, vide Notification dated 09.12.2003, the Rules
			<lb />
			of 1978 were further amended whereby &quot;Rule 28,&quot; a provision for
			<lb />
			relaxation of the Rules, was inserted. The said Rule reads as
			<lb />
			follows;
			<lb />
			&quot;28. Power to relax:-Where the Government is of
			<lb />
			the opinion that it is necessary or expedient so to do, it
			<lb />
			may, by order, for reasons to be recorded in writing, relax
			<lb />
			any of the provisions of these rules with respect to any
			<lb />
			class or category or persons or post.&quot;
			<lb />
			(ii)
			<lb />
			The Rules of 1978 (unamended) contained no powers
			<lb />
			of relaxation save to the extent that in Rule 9, the Governor was
			<lb />
			given the prerogative of extending the period of probation of the
			<lb />
			Direct Recruits and the Promotees at his discretion, for any
			<lb />
			particular case or cases and was also empowered to exempt for
			<lb />
			reasons to be recorded from passing the Examination. On the point
			<lb />
			of relaxation and inter se Seniority, we may relevantly refer to the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			 28
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			decision in G.S. Lamba and Others vs. Union of India and Others 25
			<lb />
			decided by a two Judge Bench of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court
			<lb />
			wherein the relevant Rules provided for recruitment to the Indian
			<lb />
			Foreign Service from three different Services viz., (i) Direct
			<lb />
			Recruitment by Competitive Examination, (ii) Substantive
			<lb />
			appointment of persons included in the select list promoted on the
			<lb />
			basis of a Limited Competitive Examination and (iii) Promotion on
			<lb />
			the basis of Seniority. One of the Rules provided that a recruitment
			<lb />
			should be made from the above sources on the following basis: (i)
			<lb />
			One-sixth of the Substantive vacancies to be filled in by Direct
			<lb />
			Recruitment, (ii) 33 1/3 per cent of the remaining five-sixth of the
			<lb />
			vacancies to be filled on the basis of results of Limited Competitive
			<lb />
			Examinations, and (iii) the remaining vacancies to be filled in by
			<lb />
			Promotion on the basis of Seniority. The Hon&apos;ble Court found that
			<lb />
			the Direct Recruitment had not been made for years, Limited
			<lb />
			Competitive Examination had also not been held for years and
			<lb />
			Promotions from the select list had been made in excess of the
			<lb />
			Quota. Thus, there was enormous departure from the Rules of
			<lb />
			recruitment in making appointments over several years. The
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Court was of the view that the situation was similar to the
			<lb />
			situation in two other earlier cases viz., A. Janardhana vs. Union of
			<lb />
			India and Others 26 and O.P. Singla (supra). It was opined that in the
			<lb />
			circumstances, it should be presumed that the excess appointment
			<lb />
			by Promotion had been made in relaxation of the Rules since there
			<lb />
			was power to relax the Rules. The Hon&apos;ble Court held inter alia as
			<lb />
			follows;
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place='footnote'>
			25 (1985) 2 SCC 604
			<lb />
			26 (1983) 3 SCC 601
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			29
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			&quot;27. ……………………Therefore assuming there
			<lb />
			was failure to consult the Union Public Service
			<lb />
			Commission before exercising the power to relax the
			<lb />
			mandatory quota rule and further assuming that the
			<lb />
			posts in integrated Grade II and III were within the
			<lb />
			purview of the Union Public Service Commission and
			<lb />
			accepting for the time being that the Commission
			<lb />
			was not consulted before the power to relax the rule
			<lb />
			was exercised yet the action taken would not be
			<lb />
			vitiated nor would it furnish any help to Union of
			<lb />
			India which itself cannot take any advantage of its
			<lb />
			failure to consult the Commission. Therefore it can
			<lb />
			be safely stated that the enormous departure from
			<lb />
			the quota rule year to year permits an inference
			<lb />
			that the departure was in exercise of the power of
			<lb />
			relaxing the quota rule conferred on the controlling
			<lb />
			authority. Once there is power to relax the
			<lb />
			mandatory quota rule, the appointments made in
			<lb />
			excess of the quota from any given source would
			<lb />
			not be illegal or invalid but would be valid and legal
			<lb />
			as held by this Court in N.K. Chauhan v. State of
			<lb />
			Gujarat [(1977) 1 SCC 308 : (1977) 1 SCR 1037 :
			<lb />
			1977 SCC (L&amp;S) 127] . Therefore the promotion of
			<lb />
			the promotees was regular and legal both on
			<lb />
			account of the fact that it was made to meet the
			<lb />
			exigencies of service in relaxation of the mandatory
			<lb />
			quota rule and the substantive vacancies in
			<lb />
			service.&quot;
			<lb />
			(iii)
			<lb />
			Similarly, in Narender Chadha (supra) decided by a two
			<lb />
			Judge Bench of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court, the question therein
			<lb />
			was of inter se Seniority between Direct Recruits and Promotees.
			<lb />
			Evidently, ad hoc or ex gratia Promotions were made in large
			<lb />
			numbers from feeder posts to continuously fill several vacancies
			<lb />
			allocated for Direct Recruits while only few Direct Recruitments
			<lb />
			were made in deliberate derogation of the Quota Rule. The
			<lb />
			Promotees, however, had continued in their ad hoc posts for fifteen
			<lb />
			to twenty years without being reverted to their original posts and
			<lb />
			without their right to hold the Promotion posts being questioned.
			<lb />
			The Departmental Promotion Committee, which was required to
			<lb />
			meet annually, in accordance with Rules and instructions, met only
			<lb />
			thrice in nineteen years and selected for Promotion only those
			<lb />
			Promotees who had four years of regular Service in their feeder
			<lb />
			posts, as on a specified date of several years back. The Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Supreme Court held that Articles 14 and 16 of the Constitution
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			30
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			were violated and all Promotees were entitled to regular Promotion.
			<lb />
			The Seniority of the Promotees including those selected by the
			<lb />
			Departmental Promotion Committee, was to be reckoned with
			<lb />
			effect from the dates of their continuous officiation in the
			<lb />
			Promotion posts. It was observed inter alia as follows;
			<lb />
			&quot;15. At one stage it was argued before us on behalf
			<lb />
			of some of the respondents that the petitioners who have
			<lb />
			not been appointed in accordance with Rule 8(1)(a)(ii)
			<lb />
			could not be treated as members of the Indian Economic
			<lb />
			Service or of the Indian Statistical Service at all and hence
			<lb />
			there was no question of determining the question of
			<lb />
			seniority as between the petitioners and the direct recruits.
			<lb />
			This argument has got to be rejected. It is true that the
			<lb />
			petitioners were not promoted by following the actual
			<lb />
			procedure prescribed under Rule 8(1)(a)(ii) but the fact
			<lb />
			remains that they have been working in posts included in
			<lb />
			Grade IV from the date on which they were appointed to
			<lb />
			these posts. The appointments are made in the name of the
			<lb />
			President by the competent authority. They have been
			<lb />
			continuously holding these posts. They are being paid all
			<lb />
			along the salary and allowances payable to incumbents of
			<lb />
			such posts. They have not been asked to go back to the
			<lb />
			posts from which they were promoted at any time since the
			<lb />
			dates of their appointment. The order of promotion issued
			<lb />
			in some cases show that they are promoted in the direct
			<lb />
			line of their promotion. It is expressly admitted that the
			<lb />
			petitioners have been allowed to hold posts included in
			<lb />
			Grade IV of the aforesaid services, though on an ad hoc
			<lb />
			basis. ……………………………………………. But in a case of the kind
			<lb />
			before us where persons have been allowed to function in
			<lb />
			higher posts for 15 to 20 years with due deliberation it
			<lb />
			would be certainly unjust to hold that they have no sort of
			<lb />
			claim to such posts and could be reverted unceremoniously
			<lb />
			or treated as persons not belonging to the Service at all,
			<lb />
			particularly where the Government is endowed with the
			<lb />
			power to relax the rules to avoid unjust results. In the
			<lb />
			instant case the Government has also not expressed its
			<lb />
			unwillingness to continue them in the said posts. The other
			<lb />
			contesting respondents have also not urged that the
			<lb />
			petitioners should be sent out of the said posts. The only
			<lb />
			question agitated before us relates to the seniority as
			<lb />
			between the petitioners and the direct recruits and such a
			<lb />
			question can arise only where there is no dispute regarding
			<lb />
			the entry of the officers concerned into the same grade. In
			<lb />
			the instant case there is no impediment even under the
			<lb />
			Rules to treat these petitioners and others who are
			<lb />
			similarly situated as persons duly appointed to the posts in
			<lb />
			Grade IV because of the enabling provision contained in
			<lb />
			Rule 16 thereof. ………………………………………………………………..….
			<lb />
			…………………………………………………………….………………………………….
			<lb />
			17. ……………….Therefore it can be safely stated that
			<lb />
			the enormous departure from the quota rule year to year
			<lb />
			permits an inference that the departure was in exercise of
			<lb />
			the power of relaxing the quota rule conferred on the
			<lb />
			controlling authority. Once there is power to relax the
			<lb />
			mandatory quota rule, the appointments made in excess of
			<lb />
			the quota from any given source would not be illegal or
			<lb />
			invalid but would be valid and legal as held by this Court
			<lb />
			in N.K. Chauhan v. State of Gujarat…………..&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			31
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			(iv)
			<lb />
			On the bedrock of the principle expounded above, while
			<lb />
			considering the admitted departure from the Quota Rule and
			<lb />
			prescribed procedure of recruitment in the instant matter, it is a
			<lb />
			safe assumption that the appointments of the Petitioners if made in
			<lb />
			excess of the Service Quota were valid and legal in view of the
			<lb />
			existence of the Relaxation Clause at Rule 28 of the amended Rules
			<lb />
			of 1986. A presumption thus arises that Rule 28 was invoked
			<lb />
			legalizing and validating the Promotion of the Petitioners. I cannot
			<lb />
			bring myself to agree with the submissions of Learned Senior
			<lb />
			Counsel for Respondents No.7 to 17 that the relaxation would only
			<lb />
			come into effect from the date of Notification i.e. 19.05.2012, if not
			<lb />
			from 16.03.2013, the date of confirmation, for the reason that the
			<lb />
			Notification firstly does not specify the date of such relaxation,
			<lb />
			besides, Rule 28 was inserted vide the amendment dated
			<lb />
			09.12.2003 and therefore in existence when the Officiating Orders
			<lb />
			were issued on 08.05.2008. Thus, the inevitable conclusion is that
			<lb />
			the Relaxation Clause was invoked and effective from the date the
			<lb />
			Officiating appointment of the Petitioners were made to the posts
			<lb />
			of Accounts Officers i.e. from 08.05.2008. Conditions &quot;1&quot; and &quot;2&quot;
			<lb />
			inserted in the Officiating Order of the Petitioners are sans reasons,
			<lb />
			no Rules make provisions for insertion of such conditions.
			<lb />
			17.(i)
			<lb />
			Relevantly, the impact and purpose of the word
			<lb />
			&quot;Officiating&quot; in the case at hand, is to be considered. The
			<lb />
			Officiating Order, dated 08.05.2008, states that the Petitioners are
			<lb />
			promoted as Accounts Officers in Officiating capacity and the
			<lb />
			Officiating Promotion shall be subject to the following conditions:
			<lb />
			&quot;1.
			<lb />
			The officiating promotion shall not confer any right
			<lb />
			for regular promotion and shall not be counted
			<lb />
			towards seniority.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			32
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.30 of 2016
			<lb />
			Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
			<lb />
		</note>

				<body>
					2.
					<lb />
					Their regular promotion shall be made on the
					<lb />
					recommendation of the Sikkim Public Service
					<lb />
					Commission.&quot;
					<lb />
					Since the Rules of 1978 do not define &quot;Officiating,&quot; we may refer to
					<lb />
					the Sikkim Government Service Rules, 1974 which, in Chapter II,
					<lb />
					Rule 13 provides as follows:-
					<lb />
					&quot;(13) &apos;Officiating appointment&apos;.-A Government
					<lb />
					Servant is said to be holding an officiating appointment
					<lb />
					when he performs the duties of a vacant or newly created
					<lb />
					temporary post on which no Government Servant holds a
					<lb />
					lien without completing the minimum number of qualifying
					<lb />
					years of service as may have been or as may be prescribed
					<lb />
					by the Government from time to time.&quot;
					<lb />
					(ii)
					<lb />
					Rule 39 of the Sikkim Government Service Rules, 1974
					<lb />
					reads inter alia thus;
					<lb />
					&quot;39. Officiating appointment.-
					<lb />
					(1) A Government Servant may be appointed to
					<lb />
					officiate in a post carrying a higher time scale of pay if the
					<lb />
					vacancy is for a period exceeding one year
					<lb />
					(2) …………
					<lb />
					(3) Officiating appointment shall continue till the
					<lb />
					Government Servant completes the minimum qualifying
					<lb />
					number of years as may have been or may be prescribed
					<lb />
					by the Government from time to time.&quot;
					<lb />
					(iii)
					<lb />
					Therefore, it is understood that a person appointed on
					<lb />
					Officiating basis is essentially a Government servant who has not
					<lb />
					completed the minimum number of qualifying years of Service
					<lb />
					prescribed by the Government from time to time and in a post
					<lb />
					which carries a higher time scale of pay, if the vacancy is for a
					<lb />
					period exceeding one year. The qualification necessary for the
					<lb />
					Petitioners to be considered for Promotion from Senior Accountant
					<lb />
					to Accounts Officer is 6 (six) years of continuous Service in the
					<lb />
					rank of Senior Accountant. It is not the case of the State-
					<lb />
					Respondents that the Petitioners had not completed the qualifying
					<lb />
					years of Service or were lacking in any other field, which would
					<lb />
					render them eligible only for Officiating Promotion. That, having
					<lb />
					been said, while considering condition number &quot;1.&quot; of the
					<lb />
					Officiating Order, dated 08.05.2008, it is in the first instance,
					<lb />
				</body>

				<page>
					33
					<lb />
				</page>

				<note place="headnote">
					WP(C) No.30 of 2016
					<lb />
					Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
					<lb />
				</note>

				<body>
					unfathomable since it states that the Officiating Promotion shall not
					<lb />
					confer any right for regular Promotion, in such a circumstance, is it
					<lb />
					to be construed that despite the person having put in the required
					<lb />
					years of Service, all other qualifications being met and Substantive
					<lb />
					vacant posts existing, he would still be deprived of his regular
					<lb />
					Promotion and would be sentenced to suffer the whims of the
					<lb />
					State-Respondents? The second condition provides that regular
					<lb />
					Promotion can be made on the recommendation of the SPSC, this
					<lb />
					condition obviously would be contingent upon the action of the
					<lb />
					State-Respondents in terms of Rule 16 (extracted supra) of the
					<lb />
					amended Rules of 1986, notified on 11.03.1986. The Petitioners
					<lb />
					cannot be answerable for the procrastination or indolence of the
					<lb />
					State-Respondents, thereby depriving them of timely Promotions,
					<lb />
					of course subject to fulfillment of all other requisite conditions. The
					<lb />
					uncertainty of confirmation is surely not a reflection of the
					<lb />
					inefficiency of the Petitioners.
					<lb />
					18.
					<lb />
					Related to this would be the question of vacancy in the
					<lb />
					posts of Accounts Officer. On this aspect, the averments in the
					<lb />
					Counter-Affidavit are at best nebulous and fail to address the real
					<lb />
					issues pertaining to vacancy as emanates from the discussions
					<lb />
					which follow. No reasonable explanation was offered as to why the
					<lb />
					Petitioners were promoted only on Officiating capacity, besides
					<lb />
					which, a confirmed Seniority List as on date, is not exhibited.
					<lb />
					Although the State-Respondents would argue that the 11 (eleven)
					<lb />
					Direct Recruits had been appointed in the year 2009 against the 23
					<lb />
					(twenty-three) vacancies that existed for Direct Recruits at the
					<lb />
					relevant time, however, Annexure R-15 (collectively) provides that
					<lb />
					there was a proposal on 30.06.2003 for filling up of 23 (twenty-
					<lb />
				</body>

				<page>
					34
					<lb />
				</page>

				<note place="headnote">
					WP(C) No.30 of 2016
					<lb />
					Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
					<lb />
				</note>

				<body>
					three) posts by Departmental Competitive Examination via
					<lb />
					Promotion. Thereafter, again in 2003, a proposal was placed for
					<lb />
					filling up of 18 (eighteen) Posts of Accounts Officers by Direct
					<lb />
					Recruitment, however, vide Letter dated 22.11.2003, Annexure R-
					<lb />
					15/5 (collectively), it was stated that the Department had already
					<lb />
					forwarded the proposal for filling up of 18 (eighteen) Posts of
					<lb />
					Accounts Officers by Promotion and a request was made to the
					<lb />
					Rule Section to allot the Roster Points. Therefore, the Office Notes
					<lb />
					reveal that for the post of 23 (twenty-three) alleged vacancies of
					<lb />
					Direct Recruits, 18 (eighteen) posts were also proposed to be filled
					<lb />
					by Promotion. The Office Notes further reveal that on 12.10.2004,
					<lb />
					the Chief Minister convened a meeting in which he directed that 10
					<lb />
					(ten) new posts of Accounts Officers be created. On 19.05.2007,
					<lb />
					another Office Note reveals that there were 12 (twelve) posts of
					<lb />
					Accounts Officers which were proposed to be filled through Direct
					<lb />
					Recruitment against anticipated vacancy. In the light of what has
					<lb />
					ensued in the concerned Department, as also the Order of the
					<lb />
					Chief Minister, it is evident that the contention of the State-
					<lb />
					Respondents that the Direct Recruits in 2009 were being filled from
					<lb />
					the 23 (twenty-three) vacant posts of the 46 (forty-six) posts, are
					<lb />
					erroneous and not buttressed by documentary evidence. The
					<lb />
					vacancies that arose out of the death and retirements and the
					<lb />
					allocation of such vacancies to the Quota and Rota, have not been
					<lb />
					responded to at all by the State-Respondents.
					<lb />
					19.(i)
					<lb />
					Turning my attention now to the Quota Rota Rule, in
					<lb />
					N.K. Chauhan (supra), the question that fell for consideration was
					<lb />
					whether the 50:50 ratio as between Direct Recruits and Promoted
					<lb />
					hands was subject to the saving clause &quot;as far as practicable.&quot; It
					<lb />
				</body>

				<page>
					35
					<lb />
				</page>

				<note place="headnote">
					WP(C) No.30 of 2016
					<lb />
					Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
					<lb />
				</note>

				<body>
					was observed that the Government must give proof that it was not
					<lb />
					practicable for the State to recruit from the open market qualified
					<lb />
					persons through the specialized agency of the Public Service
					<lb />
					Commission. If it does not succeed despite honest and serious
					<lb />
					efforts, it qualifies for departure from the Rule. It was inter alia
					<lb />
					held as follows;
					<lb />
					&quot;27. ………………………The
					<lb />
					straightforward
					<lb />
					answer
					<lb />
					seems to us to be that the State, in tune with the mandate
					<lb />
					of the rule, must make serious effort to secure hands to fill
					<lb />
					half the number of vacancies from the open market. If it
					<lb />
					does not succeed, despite honest and serious effort, it
					<lb />
					qualifies for departure from the rule. ……………………………The
					<lb />
					short test, therefore, is to find out whether the
					<lb />
					government, in the present case, has made effective
					<lb />
					efforts, doing all that it reasonably can, to recruit from the
					<lb />
					open market necessary numbers of qualified hands. ………&quot;
					<lb />
					(ii)
					<lb />
					In Suraj Parkash Gupta (supra), it was held inter alia as
					<lb />
					follows;
					<lb />
					&quot;38. That in such situations there can be no
					<lb />
					breakdown of the quota rule is clear from the decided
					<lb />
					cases. In N.K. Chauhan v. State of Gujarat [(1977) 1 SCC
					<lb />
					308 : 1977 SCC (L&amp;S) 127] the rule said that &quot;as far as
					<lb />
					practicable&quot;, the quota must be followed. Krishna Iyer, J.
					<lb />
					said that there must be evidence to show that effort was
					<lb />
					made to fill up the direct recruitment quota. It must be
					<lb />
					positively proved that it was not feasible, nor practicable to
					<lb />
					get direct recruits. The reason should not be
					<lb />
					&quot;procrastinatory&quot;.
					<lb />
					In Syed
					<lb />
					Khalid
					<lb />
					Rizvi v. Union
					<lb />
					of
					<lb />
					India [1993 Supp (3) SCC 575 : 1994 SCC (L&amp;S) 84 :
					<lb />
					(1994) 26 ATC 192] it was held that mere non-preparation
					<lb />
					of select list does not amount to collapse of the quota rule.
					<lb />
					In M.S.L. Patil v. State of Maharashtra [(1996) 11 SCC
					<lb />
					361] it was held that mere omission to prepare lists did not
					<lb />
					amount to breakdown of quota rule.&quot;
					<lb />
					(iii)
					<lb />
					Therefore, both the ratio of N.K. Chauhan and Suraj
					<lb />
					Parkash Gupta (supra), lay down that the Quota Rule is not broken
					<lb />
					down until serious efforts are made by the Government to recruit
					<lb />
					from the open market. In the instant case, right from the inception
					<lb />
					of the Rules and several amendments thereof, the State-
					<lb />
					Respondents have not been able to establish before this Court that
					<lb />
					the Quota Rule was ever adhered to, however, the Rules do exist
					<lb />
					providing for methods of recruitment for Direct Recruits and
					<lb />
				</body>

				<page>
					36
					<lb />
				</page>

				<note place="headnote">
					WP(C) No.30 of 2016
					<lb />
					Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
					<lb />
				</note>

				<body>
					Promotees but no effort has been shown to have been made by the
					<lb />
					Government to recruit from the open market. On the touchstone of
					<lb />
					the principles enunciated in N.K. Chauhan and Suraj Parkash Gupta
					<lb />
					(supra), the Quota Rule thus cannot be said to have broken down.
					<lb />
					In Direct Recruit Class II Engineering Officers&apos; Association (supra), the
					<lb />
					Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court was also of the opinion that although the
					<lb />
					Rules fixed the Quota of the appointees from two sources and were
					<lb />
					meant to be followed but that if it becomes impractical to act upon
					<lb />
					it, it is no use insisting that the authorities must continue to give
					<lb />
					effect to it. That, on the Quota Rule not being followed, brings
					<lb />
					about its natural demise and there is no meaning in pretending
					<lb />
					that it is still vibrant with life. In such a situation, if appointments
					<lb />
					from one source are made in excess of a Quota, but in a regular
					<lb />
					manner and after following the prescribed procedure, there is no
					<lb />
					reason to push down the appointees below the recruits from the
					<lb />
					other source who are inducted in the Service subsequently. That,
					<lb />
					where the Rules permit the authorities to relax the provision
					<lb />
					relating to the Quota, ordinarily a presumption should be raised
					<lb />
					that there was such Relaxation when there is a deviation from the
					<lb />
					Quota Rules. Despite the Quota Rule not having broken down in
					<lb />
					the instant case, the safety net of Rule 28 inserted in the Rules on
					<lb />
					09.12.2003, has come into play, as already elaborately discussed,
					<lb />
					making the appointments of the Petitioners as Accounts Officers
					<lb />
					valid and legal.
					<lb />
					20.(i)
					<lb />
					In the light of the above position, it is imperative to
					<lb />
					discuss here as to how the inter se Seniority between the
					<lb />
					Petitioners and the Respondents No.7 to 17 was to be settled.
					<lb />
					Relevant reference may be made to the observation in D.R. Nim
					<lb />
				</body>

				<page>
					37
					<lb />
				</page>

				<note place="headnote">
					WP(C) No.30 of 2016
					<lb />
					Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
					<lb />
				</note>

				<body>
					(supra), wherein it was held that when an Officer had worked
					<lb />
					continuously for a long period (as in that case for nearly fifteen to
					<lb />
					twenty years) in a post and had never been reverted, it cannot be
					<lb />
					held that the Officer&apos;s continuous Officiation was a mere temporary
					<lb />
					or local or stop gap arrangement even though the Order of
					<lb />
					appointment may state so. In such circumstances, the entire
					<lb />
					period of Officiation was to be counted for Seniority, any other
					<lb />
					view would be arbitrary and violative of Articles 14 and 16 (1) of
					<lb />
					the Constitution because the temporary Service in the post in
					<lb />
					question is not for a short period intended to meet some emergent
					<lb />
					or unforeseen circumstance. The ratio in S.B. Patwardhan (supra),
					<lb />
					may also be referred to. The pivotal question for consideration
					<lb />
					before a three Judge Bench of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court was
					<lb />
					whether Departmental Promotees and Direct Recruits appointed as
					<lb />
					Deputy Engineers in the Engineering Services of the Governments
					<lb />
					of Maharashtra and Gujarat, belonged to the same Class so that
					<lb />
					they may be treated with an even hand or whether they belonged
					<lb />
					to different Classes or categories and can justifiably be treated
					<lb />
					unequally. The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court observed that concededly,
					<lb />
					they were being treated unequally in the matter of Seniority
					<lb />
					because whereas, Promotees rank for Seniority from the date of
					<lb />
					their confirmation, the Seniority of Direct Recruits is reckoned from
					<lb />
					the date of their initial appointment. That, a Promotee ranks below
					<lb />
					the Direct Recruit even if he has officiated continuously as a
					<lb />
					Deputy Engineer for years before the appointment of the Direct
					<lb />
					Recruit is made and even if he, the Promotee, could have been
					<lb />
					confirmed in an available Substantive vacancy before the
					<lb />
					appointment of the Direct Recruit. After due consideration of the
					<lb />
				</body>

				<page>
					38
					<lb />
				</page>

				<note place="headnote">
					WP(C) No.30 of 2016
					<lb />
					Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
					<lb />
				</note>

				<body>
					relevant Rules, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court was pleased to opine
					<lb />
					inter alia as follows;
					<lb />
					&quot;39. If officiating Deputy Engineers belong to
					<lb />
					Class II cadre as much as direct recruits do and if
					<lb />
					the quota system cannot operate upon their
					<lb />
					respective confirmation in that cadre, is there any
					<lb />
					valid basis for applying different standards to the
					<lb />
					members of the two groups for determining their
					<lb />
					seniority? Though drawn from two different sources,
					<lb />
					the direct recruits and promotees constitute in the
					<lb />
					instant case a single integrated cadre. They
					<lb />
					discharge
					<lb />
					identical
					<lb />
					functions,
					<lb />
					bear
					<lb />
					similar
					<lb />
					responsibilities and acquire an equal amount of
					<lb />
					experience in their respective assignments. And yet
					<lb />
					clause (iii) of Rule 8 provides that probationers
					<lb />
					recruited during any year shall in a bunch be treated
					<lb />
					as senior to promotees confirmed in that year. The
					<lb />
					plain arithmetic of this formula is that a direct
					<lb />
					recruit appointed on probation, say in 1966, is to be
					<lb />
					regarded as senior to a promotee who was
					<lb />
					appointed as an officiating Deputy Engineer, say in
					<lb />
					1956, but was confirmed in 1966 after continuous
					<lb />
					officiation till then. This formula gives to the direct
					<lb />
					recruit even the benefit of his one year&apos;s period of
					<lb />
					training and another year&apos;s period of probation for
					<lb />
					the purposes of seniority and denies to promotees
					<lb />
					the benefit of their long and valuable experience. If
					<lb />
					there was some intelligible ground for this
					<lb />
					differentiation bearing nexus with efficiency in public
					<lb />
					services, it might perhaps have been possible to
					<lb />
					sustain such a classification. ……………… It is on the
					<lb />
					record of these writ petitions that officiating Deputy
					<lb />
					Engineers were not confirmed even though
					<lb />
					substantive vacancies were available in which they
					<lb />
					could have been confirmed. It shows that
					<lb />
					confirmation does not have to conform to any set
					<lb />
					rules and whether an employee should be confirmed
					<lb />
					or not depends on the sweet will and pleasure of the
					<lb />
					government.
					<lb />
					…………………………………………………………………………………
					<lb />
					43. Rule 8(ii) in the instant case adopts the
					<lb />
					seniority-cum-merit test for preparing the statewise
					<lb />
					Select List of seniority. And yet clause (iii) rejects
					<lb />
					the test of merit altogether. The vice of that clause
					<lb />
					is that it leaves the valuable right of seniority to
					<lb />
					depend upon the mere accident of confirmation.
					<lb />
					That, under Articles 14 and 16 of the Constitution, is
					<lb />
					impermissible and therefore we must strike down
					<lb />
					Rule 8 (iii) as being unconstitutional.
					<lb />
					…………………………………….……………………………………………
					<lb />
					48. Rules 33, insofar as it makes seniority
					<lb />
					dependent upon the fortuitous circumstance of
					<lb />
					confirmation, is open to the same objection as Rule
					<lb />
					8(iii) of the 1960 Rules and must be struck down for
					<lb />
					identical reasons.
					<lb />
					…………………………………………………….……………………………
					<lb />
					51. We
					<lb />
					are
					<lb />
					not
					<lb />
					unmindful
					<lb />
					of
					<lb />
					the
					<lb />
					administrative difficulties in evolving a code of
					<lb />
					seniority which will satisfy all conflicting claims. But
					<lb />
					care ought to be taken to avoid a clear
					<lb />
					transgression of the equality clauses of the
					<lb />
					Constitution. ……………………… We however hope that
					<lb />
					the Government will bear in mind the basic principle
					<lb />
					that if a cadre consists of both permanent and
					<lb />
				</body>

				<page>
					39
					<lb />
				</page>

				<note place="headnote">
					WP(C) No.30 of 2016
					<lb />
					Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
					<lb />
				</note>

				<body>
					temporary employees, the accident of confirmation
					<lb />
					cannot be an intelligible criterion for determining
					<lb />
					seniority as between direct recruits and promotees.
					<lb />
					All other factors being equal, continuous officiation
					<lb />
					in a non-fortuitous vacancy ought to receive due
					<lb />
					recognition in determining rules of seniority as
					<lb />
					between persons recruited from different sources,
					<lb />
					so long as they belong to the same cadre, discharge
					<lb />
					similar functions and bear similar responsibilities.
					<lb />
					……………………&quot;
					<lb />
					(emphasis supplied)
					<lb />
					(ii)
					<lb />
					In Direct Recruit Class II Engineering Officers&apos; Association
					<lb />
					(supra), a Constitution Bench of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court was in
					<lb />
					agreement with the Patwardhan case (supra), and held inter alia
					<lb />
					therein as follows;
					<lb />
					&quot;13. When the cases were taken up for
					<lb />
					hearing before us, it was faintly suggested that the
					<lb />
					principle laid down in Patwardhan case [(1977) 3
					<lb />
					SCC 399: 1977 SCC (L&amp;S) 391: (1977) 3 SCR 775]
					<lb />
					was unsound and fit to be overruled, but no attempt
					<lb />
					was made to substantiate the plea. We were taken
					<lb />
					through the judgment by the learned counsel for the
					<lb />
					parties more than once and we are in complete
					<lb />
					agreement with the ratio decidendi, that the period
					<lb />
					of continuous officiation by a government servant,
					<lb />
					after his appointment by following the rules
					<lb />
					applicable for substantive appointments, has to be
					<lb />
					taken into account for determining his seniority;
					<lb />
					and seniority cannot be determined on the sole test
					<lb />
					of
					<lb />
					confirmation,
					<lb />
					for,
					<lb />
					as
					<lb />
					was
					<lb />
					pointed out,
					<lb />
					confirmation is one of the inglorious uncertainties
					<lb />
					of government service depending neither on
					<lb />
					efficiency of the incumbent nor on the availability of
					<lb />
					substantive vacancies. The principle for deciding
					<lb />
					inter se seniority has to conform to the principles of
					<lb />
					equality spelt out by Articles 14 and 16. If an
					<lb />
					appointment is made by way of stop-gap
					<lb />
					arrangement, without considering the claims of all
					<lb />
					the eligible available persons and without following
					<lb />
					the rules of appointment, the experience on such
					<lb />
					appointment cannot be equated with the experience
					<lb />
					of a regular appointee, because of the qualitative
					<lb />
					difference in the appointment. To equate the two
					<lb />
					would be to treat two unequals as equal which
					<lb />
					would violate the equality clause. But if the
					<lb />
					appointment is made after considering the claims of
					<lb />
					all eligible candidates and the appointee continues
					<lb />
					in the post uninterruptedly till the regularisation of
					<lb />
					his service in accordance with the rules made for
					<lb />
					regular substantive appointments, there is no
					<lb />
					reason to exclude the officiating service for the
					<lb />
					purpose of seniority. Same will be the position if the
					<lb />
					initial appointment itself is made in accordance with
					<lb />
					the rules applicable to substantive appointments as
					<lb />
					in the present case. To hold otherwise will be
					<lb />
					discriminatory
					<lb />
					and
					<lb />
					arbitrary.
					<lb />
					……………………………………………………………………….……
					<lb />
					16. …….……We are not in a position to agree
					<lb />
					with the learned counsel that the rules indicate that
					<lb />
					the officiating posts were not included in the cadre
					<lb />
					of the Deputy Engineers. It is true that the use of
					<lb />
				</body>

				<page>
					40
					<lb />
				</page>

				<note place="headnote">
					WP(C) No.30 of 2016
					<lb />
					Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
					<lb />
				</note>

				<body>
					word &quot;promotions&quot; in Rule 8(i) of the 1960 Rules is
					<lb />
					not quite appropriate, but that by itself cannot lead
					<lb />
					to the conclusion that the officiating Deputy
					<lb />
					Engineers formed a class inferior to that of the
					<lb />
					permanent Engineers. ………………………………….…..
					<lb />
					17. This
					<lb />
					question
					<lb />
					was
					<lb />
					considered
					<lb />
					in Patwardhan case [(1977) 3 SCC 399: 1977 SCC
					<lb />
					(L&amp;S) 391: (1977) 3 SCR 775] at considerable
					<lb />
					length, and a categorical finding against the direct
					<lb />
					recruits was arrived at, which has been followed for
					<lb />
					the last more than a decade, in many cases arising
					<lb />
					between members of Maharashtra and Gujarat
					<lb />
					Engineering Services. The question is of vital
					<lb />
					importance affecting a very large number of officers
					<lb />
					in the departments concerned and many disputes
					<lb />
					have been settled by following the judgment
					<lb />
					in Patwardhan case [(1977) 3 SCC 399: 1977 SCC
					<lb />
					(L&amp;S) 391: (1977) 3 SCR 775]. In such a situation it
					<lb />
					is not expedient to depart from the decision lightly.
					<lb />
					It is highly desirable that a decision, which concerns
					<lb />
					a large number of government servants in a
					<lb />
					particular Service and which has been given after
					<lb />
					careful consideration of the rival contentions, is
					<lb />
					respected rather than scrutinised for finding out any
					<lb />
					possible error. It is not in the interest of the Service
					<lb />
					to unsettle a settled position every now and then.
					<lb />
					……………….&quot;
					<lb />
					(emphasis supplied)
					<lb />
					In sum and substance, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court summarized the
					<lb />
					points as follows;
					<lb />
					&quot;47. To sum up, we hold that:
					<lb />
					(A) Once an incumbent is appointed to a
					<lb />
					post according to rule, his seniority has to be
					<lb />
					counted from the date of his appointment and not
					<lb />
					according to the date of his confirmation.
					<lb />
					The corollary of the above rule is that where
					<lb />
					the initial appointment is only ad hoc and not
					<lb />
					according to rules and made as a stop-gap
					<lb />
					arrangement, the officiation in such post cannot be
					<lb />
					taken into account for considering the seniority.
					<lb />
					(B) If the initial appointment is not made by
					<lb />
					following the procedure laid down by the rules but
					<lb />
					the appointee continues in the post uninterruptedly
					<lb />
					till the regularisation of his service in accordance
					<lb />
					with the rules, the period of officiating service will
					<lb />
					be counted.
					<lb />
					(C) When appointments are made from more
					<lb />
					than one source, it is permissible to fix the ratio for
					<lb />
					recruitment from the different sources, and if rules
					<lb />
					are framed in this regard they must ordinarily be
					<lb />
					followed strictly.
					<lb />
					(D) If it becomes impossible to adhere to the
					<lb />
					existing quota rule, it should be substituted by an
					<lb />
					appropriate rule to meet the needs of the situation.
					<lb />
					In case, however, the quota rule is not followed
					<lb />
					continuously for a number of years because it was
					<lb />
					impossible to do so the inference is irresistible that
					<lb />
					the quota rule had broken down.
					<lb />
				</body>

				<page>
					41
					<lb />
				</page>

				<note place="headnote">
					WP(C) No.30 of 2016
					<lb />
					Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
					<lb />
				</note>

				<body>
					(E) Where the quota rule has broken down
					<lb />
					and the appointments are made from one source in
					<lb />
					excess of the quota, but are made after following
					<lb />
					the procedure prescribed by the rules for the
					<lb />
					appointment, the appointees should not be pushed
					<lb />
					down below the appointees from the other source
					<lb />
					inducted in the service at a later date.
					<lb />
					(F) Where the rules permit the authorities to
					<lb />
					relax the provisions relating to the quota, ordinarily
					<lb />
					a presumption should be raised that there was such
					<lb />
					relaxation when there is a deviation from the quota
					<lb />
					rule.
					<lb />
					(G) The quota for recruitment from the
					<lb />
					different sources may be prescribed by executive
					<lb />
					instructions, if the rules are silent on the subject.
					<lb />
					(H) If the quota rule is prescribed by an
					<lb />
					executive
					<lb />
					instruction,
					<lb />
					and
					<lb />
					is
					<lb />
					not
					<lb />
					followed
					<lb />
					continuously for a number of years, the inference is
					<lb />
					that the executive instruction has ceased to remain
					<lb />
					operative.
					<lb />
					(I) The posts held by the permanent Deputy
					<lb />
					Engineers as well as the officiating Deputy
					<lb />
					Engineers under the State of Maharashtra belonged
					<lb />
					to the single cadre of Deputy Engineers.
					<lb />
					(J) The decision dealing with important
					<lb />
					questions concerning a particular service given after
					<lb />
					careful consideration should be respected rather
					<lb />
					than scrutinised for finding out any possible error. It
					<lb />
					is not in the interest of Service to unsettle a settled
					<lb />
					position.
					<lb />
					With respect to Writ Petition No. 1327 of
					<lb />
					1982, we further hold:
					<lb />
					(K) That a dispute raised by an application
					<lb />
					under Article 32 of the Constitution must be held to
					<lb />
					be barred by principles of res judicata including the
					<lb />
					rule of constructive res judicata if the same has
					<lb />
					been earlier decided by a competent court by a
					<lb />
					judgment which became final.&quot;
					<lb />
					(emphasis supplied)
					<lb />
					21.(i)
					<lb />
					Admittedly, the Promotion of the Petitioners was not
					<lb />
					made by following the procedure prescribed but they did fulfill the
					<lb />
					criteria mandated by the Rules. Being thus eligible under the said
					<lb />
					Rules, they could well have been considered for Promotion on
					<lb />
					completion of required period in the posts of Senior Accountants
					<lb />
					but for the passivity of the State-Respondents. Now, would the
					<lb />
					term &quot;ad hoc&quot; as emanates in the corollary of proposition &quot;A&quot; of
					<lb />
					the ratio in Direct Recruit Class II Engineering Officers&apos; Association
					<lb />
					(supra), be applicable to the case of the Petitioners. In Rudra Kumar
					<lb />
					Sain (supra), a Constitution Bench of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court
					<lb />
				</body>

				<page>
					42
					<lb />
				</page>

				<note place="headnote">
					WP(C) No.30 of 2016
					<lb />
					Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
					<lb />
				</note>

				<body>
					was considering the question of inter se Seniority between Direct
					<lb />
					Recruits and Promotees in the Delhi Higher Judicial Service and
					<lb />
					while examining the term &quot;ad hoc&quot; held inter alia as follows;
					<lb />
					&quot;16. ………………In Black&apos;s Law Dictionary, the
					<lb />
					expression &quot;fortuitous&quot; means &quot;occurring by
					<lb />
					chance&quot;, &quot;a fortuitous event may be highly
					<lb />
					unfortunate&quot;. It thus, indicates that it occurs only by
					<lb />
					chance or accident, which could not have been
					<lb />
					reasonably foreseen. The expression &quot;ad hoc&quot;
					<lb />
					in Black&apos;s Law Dictionary, means &quot;something which
					<lb />
					is formed for a particular purpose&quot;. The expression
					<lb />
					&quot;stopgap&quot; as per Oxford Dictionary, means &quot;a
					<lb />
					temporary way of dealing with a problem or
					<lb />
					satisfying a need&quot;.
					<lb />
					17. In Oxford Dictionary, the word &quot;ad hoc&quot;
					<lb />
					means for a particular purpose; specially. In the
					<lb />
					same dictionary, the word &quot;fortuitous&quot; means
					<lb />
					happening by accident or chance rather than design.
					<lb />
					18. In P.
					<lb />
					Ramanatha
					<lb />
					Aiyar&apos;s
					<lb />
					Law
					<lb />
					Lexicon (2nd Edn.) the word &quot;ad hoc&quot; is described
					<lb />
					as: &quot;For particular purpose. Made, established,
					<lb />
					acting or concerned with a particular (sic) and or
					<lb />
					purpose.&quot; The meaning of word &quot;fortuitous event&quot; is
					<lb />
					given as &quot;an event which happens by a cause which
					<lb />
					we cannot resist; one which is unforeseen and
					<lb />
					caused by superior force, which it is impossible to
					<lb />
					resist; a term synonymous with Act of God&quot;.
					<lb />
					19. ……………………If the appointment order
					<lb />
					itself indicates that the post is created to meet a
					<lb />
					particular temporary contingency and for a period
					<lb />
					specified in the order, then the appointment to such
					<lb />
					a post can be aptly described as &quot;ad hoc&quot; or
					<lb />
					&quot;stopgap&quot;. If a post is created to meet a situation
					<lb />
					which has suddenly arisen on account of happening
					<lb />
					of some event of a temporary nature then the
					<lb />
					appointment of such a post can aptly be described
					<lb />
					as &quot;fortuitous&quot; in nature. ………………………&quot;
					<lb />
					(ii)
					<lb />
					The Officiating Orders of the Petitioners do not indicate
					<lb />
					that the posts were created to meet a particular temporary
					<lb />
					contingency and for a period specified nor is it the case of the
					<lb />
					State-Respondents that the post was created to meet a situation
					<lb />
					which had suddenly arisen on account of the happening of some
					<lb />
					event of a temporary nature to describe the appointment of the
					<lb />
					Petitioners as fortuitous. The Petitioners were in the posts of
					<lb />
					Accounts Officers from 08.05.2008 till their confirmation on
					<lb />
					16.03.2013 and therefore cannot be said to be for a short period
					<lb />
					intended to meet emergent or unforeseen circumstances. In fact,
					<lb />
				</body>

				<page>
					43
					<lb />
				</page>

				<note place="headnote">
					WP(C) No.30 of 2016
					<lb />
					Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
					<lb />
				</note>

				<body>
					only two whimsical conditions have been inserted in the Officiating
					<lb />
					Order, which also do not lay down that they would be reverted to
					<lb />
					their posts of Senior Accountants nor are the conditions fortified by
					<lb />
					any Rules. No conditions were attached to their Officiating
					<lb />
					Promotion regarding obtainment of qualification at a later date or
					<lb />
					reversion to the earlier posts, except the two conditions as already
					<lb />
					extracted hereinabove sans explanation as to whether there were
					<lb />
					Substantive vacancies or not. The appointment does not specify
					<lb />
					that it was made in the exigencies of service or on ad hoc or stop
					<lb />
					gap to meet a sudden temporary situation requiring en masse
					<lb />
					Promotions to define it as fortuitous. It is settled law that where
					<lb />
					the initial appointment is only ad hoc and not according to Rules
					<lb />
					and made as a stop gap arrangement, the period of Officiation to
					<lb />
					the said post cannot be taken into account for considering
					<lb />
					Seniority. In the instant case, however, the well-settled principle of
					<lb />
					law as propounded by the ratio in Direct Recruit Class II Engineering
					<lb />
					Officers&apos; Association (supra) is applicable viz., that an employee
					<lb />
					appointed to a post according to Rules would be entitled to get his
					<lb />
					Seniority reckoned from the date of his appointment and not from
					<lb />
					the date of its confirmation. It is but trite to remark that without
					<lb />
					State action in terms of the prescribed procedure, the Petitioners
					<lb />
					could not have volunteered to take the Limited Departmental
					<lb />
					Competitive Examination.
					<lb />
					(iii)
					<lb />
					In Vireshwar Singh and Others vs. Municipal Corporation of
					<lb />
					Delhi and Others 27 , the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court observed inter alia as
					<lb />
					follows;
					<lb />
				</body>

				<note place='footnote'>
					27 (2014) 10 SCC 360
					<lb />
				</note>

				<page>
					44
					<lb />
				</page>

				<note place="headnote">
					WP(C) No.30 of 2016
					<lb />
					Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
					<lb />
				</note>

				<body>
					&quot;15. It is the view expressed in Narender
					<lb />
					Chadha [Narender Chadha v. Union of India, (1986) 2 SCC
					<lb />
					157 : 1986 SCC (L&amp;S) 226] which would require a close
					<lb />
					look as Keshav Chandra Joshi [1992 Supp (1) SCC 272 :
					<lb />
					1993 SCC (L&amp;S) 694 : (1993) 24 ATC 545] is a mere
					<lb />
					reiteration of the said view. In Narender Chadha [Narender
					<lb />
					Chadha v. Union of India, (1986) 2 SCC 157 : 1986 SCC
					<lb />
					(L&amp;S) 226] the lis between the parties was the one relating
					<lb />
					to counting of ad hoc service rendered by the promotees
					<lb />
					for the purpose of computation of seniority qua the direct
					<lb />
					recruits. The basis of the decision to count long years of ad
					<lb />
					hoc service for the purpose of seniority is to be found more
					<lb />
					in the peculiar facts of the case as noted in para 20 of the
					<lb />
					Report than on any principle of law of general application.
					<lb />
					However, in paras 15-19 of the Report a deemed relaxation
					<lb />
					of the rules of appointment and the wide sweep of the
					<lb />
					power to relax the provisions of the rules, as it existed at
					<lb />
					the relevant point of time, appears to be the basis for
					<lb />
					counting of the ad hoc service for the purpose of seniority.
					<lb />
					16. The
					<lb />
					principle
					<lb />
					laid
					<lb />
					down
					<lb />
					in Narender
					<lb />
					Chadha [Narender Chadha v. Union of India, (1986) 2 SCC
					<lb />
					157 : 1986 SCC (L&amp;S) 226] was approved by the
					<lb />
					Constitution Bench in Direct Recruit Class II [Direct Recruit
					<lb />
					Class II Engg. Officers&apos; Assn. v. State of Maharashtra,
					<lb />
					(1990) 2 SCC 715 : 1990 SCC (L&amp;S) 339 : (1990) 13 ATC
					<lb />
					348] as the promotion of the officers on ad hoc basis was
					<lb />
					found to be &quot;without following the procedure laid down
					<lb />
					under the Rules&quot;. That apart, what was approved in Direct
					<lb />
					Recruit Class II [Direct Recruit Class II Engg. Officers&apos;
					<lb />
					Assn. v. State of Maharashtra, (1990) 2 SCC 715 : 1990
					<lb />
					SCC (L&amp;S) 339 : (1990) 13 ATC 348] is in the following
					<lb />
					terms: (SCC p. 726, para 13)
					<lb />
					&quot;13. … We, therefore, confirm the
					<lb />
					principle of counting towards seniority the
					<lb />
					period of continuous officiation following
					<lb />
					an appointment made in accordance with
					<lb />
					the
					<lb />
					rules
					<lb />
					prescribed for
					<lb />
					regular
					<lb />
					substantive appointments in the service.&quot;
					<lb />
					……………&quot;
					<lb />
					The law on the point of Seniority qua the appointments made in
					<lb />
					excess to the Quotas and the principle of computing the Seniority
					<lb />
					is thus clearly laid down, further, as expressed in the ratio of Direct
					<lb />
					Recruit Class II Engineering Officers&apos; Association (supra), it is not in
					<lb />
					the interest of the Service to unsettle a settled position now and
					<lb />
					then.
					<lb />
					(iv)
					<lb />
					We may, therefore now look at the propositions put
					<lb />
					forth in Direct Recruits case supra. Learned Senior Counsel for
					<lb />
					Respondents No.7 to 17 relied on proposition &quot;(A)&quot; while Learned
					<lb />
					Senior Counsel for the Petitioners relied on proposition &quot;(B)&quot;. From
					<lb />
					the discussions made hereinabove, it can be culled out that the
					<lb />
				</body>

				<page>
					45
					<lb />
				</page>

				<note place="headnote">
					WP(C) No.30 of 2016
					<lb />
					Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
					<lb />
				</note>

				<body>
					Petitioners continued in the posts until regularization of their
					<lb />
					Service in accordance with the Rules. Thus, the case of the
					<lb />
					Petitioners squarely falls under proposition &quot;(B)&quot; enunciated in
					<lb />
					Direct Recruit Class II Engineering Officers&apos; Association supra. At the
					<lb />
					same time, it is worth noticing propositions &quot;(D)&quot; and &quot;(F)&quot; of the
					<lb />
					same ratio wherein at &quot;(D)&quot; it was held that if it becomes
					<lb />
					impossible to adhere to the existing Quota Rule, it should be
					<lb />
					substituted by an appropriate Rule to meet the needs of the
					<lb />
					situation. In case, however, the Quota Rule is not followed
					<lb />
					continuously for a number of years because it was impossible to
					<lb />
					do so, the inference is irresistible that the Quota Rule had broken
					<lb />
					down. It may be explained here that the word &quot;impossible&quot; has to
					<lb />
					be construed in this context in terms of the decision of the Hon&apos;ble
					<lb />
					Supreme Court in N.K. Chauhan and Suraj Parkash Gupta (supra). No
					<lb />
					effort of the State-Respondents to recruit directly is established
					<lb />
					herein as already discussed. Proposition &quot;F&quot; of Direct Recruit Class II
					<lb />
					Engineering Officers&apos; Association 1990 (2) SCC 715 supra provides that
					<lb />
					where the Rules permit the authorities to relax the provisions
					<lb />
					relating to the Quota, ordinarily a presumption should be raised
					<lb />
					that there was such relaxation when there is a deviation from the
					<lb />
					Quota Rule. The Relaxation Clause at Rule 28 of the Rules is
					<lb />
					assumed to have been invoked when deviation from the Quota
					<lb />
					Rule was made.
					<lb />
					22.
					<lb />
					In conclusion, it must be remarked that no case fits
					<lb />
					with mathematical or clockwork precision to a previously decided
					<lb />
					case. The facts of each case are peculiar in their own details. Thus,
					<lb />
					it is only reasonable that the Courts apply the principles laid down
					<lb />
					by the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court, similar to those requiring
					<lb />
				</body>

				<page>
					46
					<lb />
				</page>

				<note place="headnote">
					WP(C) No.30 of 2016
					<lb />
					Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
					<lb />
				</note>

				<body>
					determination before them. It is worth remarking at this juncture
					<lb />
					that the Petitioners had also agitated the point that the Direct
					<lb />
					Recruits appointed in January, 2009 were promoted on Officiating
					<lb />
					basis as Senior Accounts Officers even before completion of the
					<lb />
					qualifying years of Service as Accounts Officers, and that 12
					<lb />
					(twelve) posts of Senior Accounts Officers to that of Accounts
					<lb />
					Officers were downgraded for the alleged purposes of Direct
					<lb />
					Recruitments which were subsequently then filled by Promotions.
					<lb />
					No light has been shed on these circumstances by the State-
					<lb />
					Respondents.
					<lb />
					23.
					<lb />
					So far as the grievance of the Petitioners against the
					<lb />
					Respondents No.4, 5 and 6 are concerned, in the first instance,
					<lb />
					they had appeared in the Departmental Examination in the year
					<lb />
					1997 for Promotion from the posts of Accountants to Senior
					<lb />
					Accountants and were ranked in the first, second and third place
					<lb />
					amongst 19 (nineteen) candidates in the Panel prepared for such
					<lb />
					Promotion. In such circumstances, in my considered opinion,
					<lb />
					nothing irregular emanates on their selection and consequent
					<lb />
					Promotions.
					<lb />
					24.
					<lb />
					The foregoing detailed discussions thus soundly
					<lb />
					answers the question that fell for consideration before this Court.
					<lb />
					25.
					<lb />
					So far as the question of delay is concerned, the
					<lb />
					Petitioners are employees of the State-Respondents and bound by
					<lb />
					official discipline. In the absence of any Confirmation List
					<lb />
					pertaining to Seniority, it was not for the Petitioners to have run to
					<lb />
					the Court at the drop of a hat. In my considered opinion, there is
					<lb />
					no negligence or inaction on the part of the Petitioners or want of
					<lb />
					bona fides. The expectation of the Petitioners was that the State-
					<lb />
				</body>

				<page>
					47
					<lb />
				</page>

				<note place="headnote">
					WP(C) No.30 of 2016
					<lb />
					Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
					<lb />
				</note>

				<body>
					Respondents would treat them fairly and when such action was not
					<lb />
					forthcoming, the Petitioners were constrained to seek redressal
					<lb />
					from the Court. The Courts cannot always take a pedantic and
					<lb />
					hyper technical view on the point of delay, which ought not to be
					<lb />
					an obstacle in the exercise of the Courts&apos; discretion to mete out
					<lb />
					even handed justice to all concerned.
					<lb />
					26.
					<lb />
					While on the issue of waiver and acquiescence, I am
					<lb />
					inclined to agree with the submissions of Learned Counsel for the
					<lb />
					Petitioners that the ratio of P.S. Gopinathan and M.P. Palanisamy
					<lb />
					(supra) relied on by Learned Counsel for Respondents No.7 to 17,
					<lb />
					are distinguishable from the instant case. In P.S. Gopinathan
					<lb />
					(supra), the relief was not granted to the Appellant as the position
					<lb />
					therein was that the Appellant was well aware of the
					<lb />
					&quot;35..……..mistaken belief of the High Court in appointing and posting him
					<lb />
					as a temporary employee. …&quot; to which he raised no objection and did
					<lb />
					so only subsequently. In M.P. Palanisamy (supra), the contention of
					<lb />
					the Appellants was that they had all the qualifications for holding
					<lb />
					the posts of Post Graduate Assistants when they were appointed
					<lb />
					under the relevant Rules and there was no break in Service to
					<lb />
					which they were ultimately regularized in 1988. They were placed
					<lb />
					below in Seniority to those who were selected in 1986. It was
					<lb />
					found inter alia as follows;
					<lb />
					&quot;29. ……………however, it must be borne in
					<lb />
					mind that though the appellants herein had the necessary
					<lb />
					qualifications at the time of their initial appointment under
					<lb />
					Rule 10(a)(i)(1) and though they were subsequently
					<lb />
					regularised also, the regularisation was conditional
					<lb />
					regularisation, which was done way back in 1988. The
					<lb />
					condition regarding the seniority was explicit in the said
					<lb />
					regularisation, which is clear from a mere reading of GOMs
					<lb />
					No. 1813. …………...&quot;
					<lb />
				</body>

				<page>
					48
					<lb />
				</page>

				<note place="headnote">
					WP(C) No.30 of 2016
					<lb />
					Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
					<lb />
				</note>

				<body>
					The Appellants therein raised the issue in 1994 and thereafter
					<lb />
					when the Seniority prayed for by them was refused, they bore it in
					<lb />
					silence and raised the matter again only in 2003. That apart, it is
					<lb />
					worth considering that in N.K. Chauhan (supra), the Hon&apos;ble
					<lb />
					Supreme Court had also observed inter alia as follows;
					<lb />
					&quot;36. …………….….But we should not forget that
					<lb />
					seniority is the manifestation of official experience, -the
					<lb />
					process of metabolism of service, over the years, of civil
					<lb />
					servants, by the administration -and, therefore, it is
					<lb />
					appropriate that as far as possible he who has actually
					<lb />
					served longer benefits better in the future. ………….&quot;
					<lb />
					27.
					<lb />
					The Rule of law cannot be anathema to the State-
					<lb />
					Respondents, it demands obedience and exists to check arbitrary
					<lb />
					exercise of power which otherwise conceives chaos, as exhibited in
					<lb />
					the facts and circumstances herein. The fate of the Petitioners have
					<lb />
					been left to the vagaries of executive indecisions leading to
					<lb />
					violation of Articles 14 and 16 of the Constitution of India.
					<lb />
					28.
					<lb />
					Considering the entirety of the facts and circumstances
					<lb />
					and for the reasons discussed supra and in terms of the well
					<lb />
					settled position of law in the ratiocinations relied upon, it is hereby
					<lb />
					ordered as follows:
					<lb />
					(i)
					<lb />
					The Petitioners shall be accorded Seniority with
					<lb />
					effect from the date of their Officiating Promotion
					<lb />
					i.e. 08.05.2008 as Accounts Officers with all benefits
					<lb />
					of Service;
					<lb />
					(ii)
					<lb />
					The consequent Seniority of the Petitioners in their
					<lb />
					subsequent senior posts shall be computed in terms
					<lb />
					of the directions supra;
					<lb />
					(iii)
					<lb />
					A Seniority List shall be prepared by the State-
					<lb />
					Respondents on the above basis, to rule out
					<lb />
				</body>

				<page>
					49
					<lb />
				</page>

				<note place="headnote">
					WP(C) No.30 of 2016
					<lb />
					Sushil Pradhan and Others vs. State of Sikkim and Others
					<lb />
				</note>

				<body>
					prejudice to the Petitioners and ensure equity to all,
					<lb />
					thereby, toeing the line of Articles 14 and 16 of the
					<lb />
					Constitution and thus satisfying the test of
					<lb />
					constitutionality;
					<lb />
					(iv)
					<lb />
					The Petitioners No.2 and 3 who have retired during
					<lb />
					the pendency of the instant Writ Petition are entitled
					<lb />
					to receive the same benefits as granted to the
					<lb />
					Petitioners herein, during their time in Service, for
					<lb />
					the purposes of their retirement benefits.
					<lb />
					(v)
					<lb />
					No Orders need be issued with regard to
					<lb />
					Respondents No.4, 5 and 6 in view of the foregoing
					<lb />
					discussions pertaining to their Promotions, they are
					<lb />
					at liberty to approach the State-Respondents for
					<lb />
					redressal of any grievances.
					<lb />
					29.
					<lb />
					The Writ Petition stands disposed of with the above
					<lb />
					directions.
					<lb />
					30.
					<lb />
					No order as to costs.
					<lb />
					( Meenakshi Madan Rai )
					<lb />
					Judge
					<lb />
					25.01.2021
					<lb />
				</body>

				<note place='footnote'>
					ml
					<lb />
					Approved for reporting : Yes
				</note>


	</text>
</tei>