<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<page>
			1
			<lb />
		</page>

		<front>
			THE HIGH COURT OF SIKKIM : GANGTOK
			<lb />
			(Criminal Appeal Jurisdiction)
			<lb />
			DATED : 13 th October, 2018
			<lb />
			---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
			<lb />
			DIVISION BENCH : THE HON&apos;BLE ACTING CHIEF JUSTICE MRS. JUSTICE MEENAKSHI MADAN RAI
			<lb />
			THE HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE BHASKAR RAJ PRADHAN, JUDGE
			<lb />
			---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
			<lb />
			Crl. A. No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Appellant
			<lb />
			:
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack
			<lb />
			versus
			<lb />
			Respondent
			<lb />
			:
			<lb />
			State of Sikkim
			<lb />
			Appeal under Section 374(2)
			<lb />
			of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973
			<lb />
			-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
			<lb />
			Appearance
			<lb />
			Ms. Puja Lamichaney, Advocate (Legal Aid Counsel).
			<lb />
			Mr. Karma Thinlay, Mr. Thinlay Dorjee Bhutia, Additional Public
			<lb />
			Prosecutors with Mr. S. K. Chettri and Mrs. Pollin Rai, Assistant
			<lb />
			Public Prosecutor.
			<lb />
			------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
			<lb />
		</front>

		<body>
			J U D G M E N T
			<lb />
			Meenakshi Madan Rai, ACJ
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			The Learned Special Judge, Protection of Children from
			<lb />
			Sexual Offences (POCSO) Act, 2012, East Sikkim, at Gangtok,
			<lb />
			convicted the Appellant under Section 5(l) punishable under Section
			<lb />
			6 of the Protection of Children from Sexual Offences Act, 2012 (for
			<lb />
			short the -POCSO Act‖), vide its impugned Judgment dated 19-09-
			<lb />
			2017. The impugned Order on Sentence dated 20-09-2017
			<lb />
			sentenced the Appellant to undergo rigorous imprisonment for a
			<lb />
			period of ten years and to pay a fine of Rs.2,000/-(Rupees two
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			2
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place='headnote'>
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			thousand) only, for the offence aforestated, with a default clause of
			<lb />
			imprisonment.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Aggrieved, the Appellant is before this Court, inter alia,
			<lb />
			on grounds that the seizure of Exhibit 7 the Birth Certificate of the
			<lb />
			Victim, remained unproved, the date of birth of the Victim has not
			<lb />
			been established as the contents of Exhibit 7 were not proved by
			<lb />
			any witness of the Prosecution. That, it is now settled law as to how
			<lb />
			the age of a Victim is to be assessed and none of the parameters as
			<lb />
			laid down in Mahadeo s/o Kerba Maske vs. State of Maharashtra and
			<lb />
			Another 1 have been complied with although witnesses being P.W.7,
			<lb />
			P.W.8 and P.W.9 were examined with regard to the Birth Certificate.
			<lb />
			P.W.2, the mother of the Victim, from whose possession the Birth
			<lb />
			Certificate was allegedly seized has made no mention of such
			<lb />
			seizure neither has she testified about the age of the Victim to
			<lb />
			establish that she was a minor. The Register containing the entry, if
			<lb />
			at all, of the date of birth of the Victim was not furnished before the
			<lb />
			Learned Trial Court. That apart, it is also evident from Exhibit 8 the
			<lb />
			FIR, that the father of the Victim had in fact lodged a Complaint on
			<lb />
			25-05-2016 (May 2016) informing the Police that his daughter, the
			<lb />
			Victim, aged 15, was missing since 24-04-2016 (April 2016) at 2.30
			<lb />
			p.m. which, however, was not reduced in writing but merely entered
			<lb />
			as a Diary Report and the case taken up as one under -Missing
			<lb />
			Children‖ being Case No.17/2016 dated 25-05-2016. The Learned
			<lb />
			Trial Court failed to appreciate that the evidence furnished before it
			<lb />
			did not prove that the Victim was a child as defined under Section
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place='footnote'>
			1 (2013) 14 SCC 637
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			3
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			2(d) of the POCSO Act. That, material discrepancies have occurred
			<lb />
			in the evidence of the Prosecution, as P.W.9 ASI Tek Bahadur
			<lb />
			Chettri and P.W.15 PI Ajay Rai were not able to prove the date of
			<lb />
			lodging of the FIR and the date when the Victim was alleged to have
			<lb />
			gone missing. The Section 164 Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973
			<lb />
			(for short -Cr.P.C.‖) statement of the Victim was incorrectly
			<lb />
			considered as substantive evidence by the Learned Trial Court, while
			<lb />
			the Victim was unable to prove that her statement was recorded
			<lb />
			under the said provision. Exhibit 12 the Medical Report of the Victim
			<lb />
			and Exhibit 15 the Report of the Regional Forensic Science
			<lb />
			Laboratory (RFSL), Sikkim, have not supported the Prosecution case
			<lb />
			of penetrative sexual assault. This evidence nevertheless was relied
			<lb />
			on by the Prosecution and the embellished and uncorroborated
			<lb />
			testimony of the Victim was duly considered by the Learned Trial
			<lb />
			Court. That, reliance has been placed on the statements of P.W.9
			<lb />
			and P.W.16 who are both Investigating Officers (I.O.) which is
			<lb />
			impermissible. That, the Learned Trial Court failed to consider the
			<lb />
			claim of juvenility raised by the Appellant before the Court and erred
			<lb />
			in ignoring the principles laid down by Section 114(g) of the Indian
			<lb />
			Evidence Act, 1872 (for short the -Evidence Act‖), when material
			<lb />
			witnesses and evidence were not produced by the Prosecution such
			<lb />
			as the father of the Victim and the FIR lodged by him. Hence, in
			<lb />
			view of the aforesaid circumstances the impugned Judgment and
			<lb />
			Order on Sentence deserves to be set aside and the Appellant
			<lb />
			acquitted of the Charges.
		</body>

		<page>
			4
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place='headnote'>
			<lb />
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			3.
			<lb />
			Resisting the stand of learned Counsel for the Appellant,
			<lb />
			learned Assistant Public Prosecutor would contend that the
			<lb />
			Prosecution has without doubt proved the age of the Victim as
			<lb />
			Exhibit 7, the Birth Certificate of the Victim, being an official
			<lb />
			document is admissible in evidence. The date of birth of the Victim
			<lb />
			on the Exhibit is reflected as -14-09-2001‖ thereby making her 15
			<lb />
			years at the time of the incident, i.e., 25-05-2016. That, the claim
			<lb />
			of juvenility by the Appellant deserves no consideration as Exhibit 5
			<lb />
			his Ossification Test would clearly indicate that his approximate
			<lb />
			bone age as per the Radiologist is above 20 years of age. That, the
			<lb />
			Learned Trial Court has correctly considered the statement of the
			<lb />
			Victim recorded under Section 164 of the Cr.P.C. which corroborated
			<lb />
			the evidence given by her in the Court. Exhibit 12, the Medical
			<lb />
			Report of the Victim, is testimony to the fact that the hymen of the
			<lb />
			Victim was ruptured establishing the offence of rape and of
			<lb />
			penetrative sexual assault. That, there are no anomalies with
			<lb />
			regard to the facts emerging in Exhibit 8 the FIR lodged by P.W.9
			<lb />
			hence, no error emanates in the Prosecution case as well as the
			<lb />
			impugned Judgment and Order on Sentence of the Learned Trial
			<lb />
			Court. The Appeal thereby warrants dismissal.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			The rival submissions put forth by learned Counsel for
			<lb />
			the parties were heard in extenso. The evidence and documents on
			<lb />
			records have also been meticulously perused by us.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			We may briefly traverse the facts of the case as per the
			<lb />
			Prosecution for clarity in the matter. P.W.9, Assistant Sub-Inspector
			<lb />
			(ASI) Tek Bahadur Chettri of Singtam Police Station, received a
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			5
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			Complaint from the father of the Victim on 25-05-2016, to the effect
			<lb />
			that his daughter, aged 15 years, was missing since 24-04-2016
			<lb />
			from 2.30 p.m. This information was recorded as a -Diary Report‖ at
			<lb />
			the Singtam Police Station the same day, as can be drawn from the
			<lb />
			details at Exhibit 8 FIR lodged by P.W.9, ASI Tek Bahadur Chettri.
			<lb />
			The Complaint of the father was registered as MC (Missing Children)
			<lb />
			Case No.17/2016 dated 25-05-2016 at the Singtam Police Station
			<lb />
			and endorsed to P.W.9 for investigation. P.W.9 (I.O.) suspecting
			<lb />
			that the missing child could be with the Appellant, kept the mobile
			<lb />
			number of the Appellant on surveillance which traced him to a
			<lb />
			village ‗Kawli&apos;, District Baksa, Assam. P.W.9 contacted the NGO
			<lb />
			(Impulse) at the said place, who traced the alleged Victim to the
			<lb />
			home of the Appellant. She was handed over to the Tamalpur Police
			<lb />
			Station. P.W.9 recorded the facts and submitted it before the
			<lb />
			Station House Officer, Singtam Police Station on 06-05-2016 which
			<lb />
			was registered as FIR, Exhibit 8, bearing No.21/2016 dated 06-05-
			<lb />
			2016. The missing case was converted into one under Sections
			<lb />
			363/365 of the Indian Penal Code, 1860 (for short -IPC‖) and
			<lb />
			registered against the Appellant and endorsed to Sub-Inspector
			<lb />
			Sonam Thendup Bhutia, P.W.16 for investigation. The Appellant was
			<lb />
			arrested in Assam on 08-05-2016 on a Non-Bailable Warrant of
			<lb />
			Arrest issued by the Learned Chief Judicial Magistrate, East at
			<lb />
			Gangtok, and produced under transit warrant issued by the Learned
			<lb />
			Judicial Magistrate, Nalbari. The Victim was also brought from the
			<lb />
			same place and forwarded for medical examination to the Singtam
			<lb />
			District Hospital, while the Appellant was forwarded to the Juvenile
			<lb />
			Observation Home by the Principal Magistrate, Juvenile Justice
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			6
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			Board, North at Mangan, due to lack of proof of age. An Ossification
			<lb />
			Test of the Appellant was conducted which determined his age as
			<lb />
			twenty years following which he was remanded to judicial custody.
			<lb />
			Case Exhibits were forwarded to RFSL, Saramsa, for chemical
			<lb />
			analysis.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			Investigation unravelled that the Appellant who was
			<lb />
			working as a plumber in Singtam met the Victim at her school there
			<lb />
			in February 2016 where they got acquainted with each other and fell
			<lb />
			in love. The Appellant thereafter sexually assaulted the minor
			<lb />
			Victim several times below the school jungle. The brother of the
			<lb />
			Victim, P.W.4 had seen her talking to the Appellant on one occasion
			<lb />
			and reprimanded her, two days later the Appellant and the Victim
			<lb />
			met again and the Appellant suggested that the Victim elope with
			<lb />
			him. The same night they eloped, left for Siliguri and reached
			<lb />
			Jaigaon, where they met the Appellant&apos;s mother. She expressed her
			<lb />
			displeasure at the Appellant bringing home a school going child
			<lb />
			fearing legal consequences. Consequently, the Appellant took the
			<lb />
			minor Victim to his brother&apos;s house in Baksa, Assam, where they
			<lb />
			stayed and allegedly had sexual intercourse twice. On completion of
			<lb />
			investigation, finding a prima facie case Charge-Sheet was
			<lb />
			submitted against the Appellant under Sections 363/365/376 of the
			<lb />
			IPC read with Section 4 of the POCSO Act.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			The Learned Trial Court on consideration of the prima
			<lb />
			facie materials framed Charges against the Appellant under Sections
			<lb />
			363, 366 and 376(2)(n) of the IPC read with Section 5(l) of the
			<lb />
			POCSO Act, punishable under Section 6 and directed trial on the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			7
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			plea of -not guilty‖ by the Appellant. The Prosecution furnished
			<lb />
			sixteen witnesses including the I.O. of the case. On completion of
			<lb />
			evidence the Appellant was examined under Section 313 of the
			<lb />
			Cr.P.C., the final arguments heard and the impugned Judgment and
			<lb />
			the Order on Sentence pronounced.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			The questions that now plague this Court and require
			<lb />
			determination are;
			<lb />
			(i)
			<lb />
			Whether two First Information Reports can exist in one
			<lb />
			case?
			<lb />
			(ii)
			<lb />
			Whether the Prosecution was able to establish that the
			<lb />
			Victim was a child, as defined under Section 2(d) of the
			<lb />
			POCSO Act?
			<lb />
			(iii) Whether the Appellant was a -child in conflict with law‖
			<lb />
			and had not completed eighteen years of age on the
			<lb />
			date of commission of the offence?
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			While answering the first question the provision of
			<lb />
			Section 154 of the Cr.P.C. is extracted hereinbelow for easy
			<lb />
			reference which we may briefly examine to assess what the
			<lb />
			provision entails. Section 154 of the Cr.P.C. pertains to information
			<lb />
			in cognizable cases and provides that;
			<lb />
			&quot;154. Information in cognizable cases.-(1)
			<lb />
			Every information relating to the commission of a
			<lb />
			cognizable offence, if given orally to an officer in
			<lb />
			charge of a police station, shall be reduced to writing
			<lb />
			by him or under his direction, and can be read over to
			<lb />
			the informant; and every such information, whether
			<lb />
			given in writing or reduced to writing as aforesaid, shall
			<lb />
			be signed by the person giving it, and the substance
			<lb />
			thereof shall be entered in a book to be kept by such
			<lb />
			officer in such form as the State Government may
			<lb />
			prescribe in this behalf.
			<lb />
			……………………………………………………………..
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			8
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			(2) A copy of the information as recorded under
			<lb />
			sub-section (1) shall be given forthwith, free of cost, to
			<lb />
			the informant.
			<lb />
			……………………………………………………………..&quot;
			<lb />
			10.
			<lb />
			The term -First Information‖ has not been defined in the
			<lb />
			Code nor is there any mention of such a term however it is now a
			<lb />
			settled position that information given to a police officer concerning
			<lb />
			an offence means something in the nature of a complaint or
			<lb />
			accusation. It may well be information of a crime which sets the
			<lb />
			criminal law justice system in motion. The provisions of Section 154
			<lb />
			of the Cr.P.C. are mandatory and the concerned Police Officer is
			<lb />
			duty bound to register the case on the basis of information
			<lb />
			disclosing cognizable offence, this was held in Ramesh Kumari vs.
			<lb />
			State (N.C.T. of Delhi) and Others
			<lb />
			2 . Thus, the condition which is sine
			<lb />
			qua non for recording a First Information Report is that, there must
			<lb />
			be information, which must disclose a cognizable offence before the
			<lb />
			Officer-in-Charge of the Police Station. Upon receipt of such
			<lb />
			information, the law requires the police officer to reduce the
			<lb />
			information in writing if given orally which shall be read over to the
			<lb />
			informant. Where such information is a written complaint or one
			<lb />
			which has been reduced to writing it shall be signed by the person
			<lb />
			giving the information. The substance of the information is to be
			<lb />
			entered in a book to be kept by such Officer in terms of the rules
			<lb />
			prescribed by the Government. The Section also requires that a copy
			<lb />
			of the information so recorded under Sub-Section (1) shall be given
			<lb />
			free of cost to the informant. It is thus incumbent upon the Officer
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place='footnote'>
			2 AIR 2006 SC 1322
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			9
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			at the Police Station to record a Complaint when a cognizable
			<lb />
			offence is reported and treat it as an FIR. This discussion puts into
			<lb />
			place the requirements of Section 154 of the Cr.P.C.
			<lb />
			11.
			<lb />
			According to P.W.9, on 25-05-2016, the father of the
			<lb />
			Victim filed a Missing Child Report at the Singtam Police Station
			<lb />
			regarding his minor daughter who went missing from the afternoon
			<lb />
			of 24-05-2016. The Missing Child Report was registered at Singtam
			<lb />
			Police Station as MC Case No.17 of 2016, dated 25-05-2016. It is
			<lb />
			pertinent to point out that the records of the case are bereft of this
			<lb />
			Report. The father of the Victim who allegedly lodged the report is
			<lb />
			notably not a Prosecution witness for reasons best known to the
			<lb />
			Prosecution which leads this Court to draw an adverse inference
			<lb />
			under Section 114(g) of the Indian Evidence Act. On this aspect of
			<lb />
			the report filed by the Victim&apos;s father, we may also consider the
			<lb />
			evidence of P.W.2 the Victim&apos;s mother. Her evidence to the contrary
			<lb />
			is that the Victim child went missing since 24-04-2016, thereafter,
			<lb />
			she tried to locate her and informed the Singtam Police Station that
			<lb />
			her daughter was missing. Her cross-examination would reveal that
			<lb />
			she had lodged a written missing report at the Singtam Police
			<lb />
			Station. This written report also finds no place in the records of the
			<lb />
			Prosecution case. P.W.2 has further specified in her evidence that
			<lb />
			on 05-05-2016 that her son received a telephone call on his mobile
			<lb />
			from the Appellant who informed him that his name was Jack
			<lb />
			Tamang and that the Victim was with him in Gangtok. When the
			<lb />
			Police recorded her statement she informed the Police about the
			<lb />
			information received by her son on his cell phone from the said
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			10
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			Jack. Now, when we revisit Exhibit 8 the report of P.W.9 inter alia
			<lb />
			reads as follows;
			<lb />
			&quot;………………………………………………………….…………………….
			<lb />
			B. B. …………….. East Sikkim had lodged a diary
			<lb />
			report on 25/05/2016, to the effect that his daughter
			<lb />
			H………. aged 15 was missing since 24.04.2016 at 2.30
			<lb />
			p.m. …………………&quot;.
			<lb />
			This is contrary to his evidence where he states that the
			<lb />
			Victim&apos;s father had told him that the child was missing from the
			<lb />
			afternoon of 24-05-2016. At the same time it is relevant to notice
			<lb />
			that Exhibit 8 corroborates the evidence of P.W.2 who has stated
			<lb />
			that the Victim was missing from the afternoon of 24-04-2016.
			<lb />
			12.
			<lb />
			Exhibit 8 is said to be recorded on 06-05-2016 but if the
			<lb />
			Victim&apos;s father lodged a Diary Report only on 25-05-2016 as
			<lb />
			reflected in Exhibit 8 then how was it possible for P.W.9 to make a
			<lb />
			GD Entry on 06-05-2016, viz.; prior in time. This is indeed baffling
			<lb />
			and mind boggling. What can thus be culled out from the records is
			<lb />
			that the child went missing on 24-04-2016, P.W.2 as per her lodged
			<lb />
			a report at the Singtam Police Station. This was not recorded.
			<lb />
			P.W.16 the I.O. of the instant case would admit that the Victim&apos;s
			<lb />
			mother filed a missing report in connection with the Victim going
			<lb />
			missing. He also admitted that he has not filed the records of the
			<lb />
			enquiry into the missing report along with the Charge-Sheet or the
			<lb />
			missing report filed by the Victim&apos;s mother. Apparently the Police
			<lb />
			lost track of who was the Complainant or the date when the Victim
			<lb />
			went missing. P.W.15, the SHO Singtam P.S. also in tandem with
			<lb />
			the evidence of P.W.9 states that the Victim&apos;s father lodged a
			<lb />
			missing report on 25-05-2016 to the effect that his daughter was
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			11
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			missing from 24-05-2016 but strangely enough goes on to state
			<lb />
			that based on such missing report an enquiry was made by P.W.9 on
			<lb />
			06-05-2016. The Prosecution would indeed have us believe in the
			<lb />
			limerick of the young lady named Bright, whose speed was faster
			<lb />
			than light, she set out one day in a relative way and returned on the
			<lb />
			previous night. In view of the anomalies arising in the Prosecution
			<lb />
			case it is evident that efforts are being made by P.W.9, P.W.15 and
			<lb />
			P.W.16 to suppress their follies in the instant matter resulting in a
			<lb />
			preposterous situation.
			<lb />
			13.
			<lb />
			The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Amitbhari Anilchandra Shah
			<lb />
			vs. Central Bureau of Investigation and Another 3 was dealing with the
			<lb />
			question of two FIRs lodged in the matter and would hold as follows;
			<lb />
			&quot;58.5. The first information report is a report which
			<lb />
			gives first information with regard to any offence.
			<lb />
			There cannot be second FIR in respect of the same
			<lb />
			offence/event
			<lb />
			because
			<lb />
			whenever
			<lb />
			any
			<lb />
			further
			<lb />
			information is received by the investigating agency, it
			<lb />
			is always in furtherance of the first FIR.
			<lb />
			58.6. In the case on hand, as explained in the
			<lb />
			earlier paragraphs, in our opinion, the second FIR was
			<lb />
			nothing but a consequence of the event which had
			<lb />
			taken place on 25-11-2005/26-11-2005. We have
			<lb />
			already concluded that this Court having reposed faith
			<lb />
			in CBI accepted their contention that Tulsiram Prajapati
			<lb />
			encounter is a part of the same chain of events in
			<lb />
			which Sohrabuddin and Kausarbi were killed and
			<lb />
			directed CBI to -take up‖ the investigation.
			<lb />
			…………………………………………………………..
			<lb />
			60. In view of the above discussion and conclusion,
			<lb />
			the second FIR dated 29-4-2011 being RC No.
			<lb />
			3(S)/2011/Mumbai filed by CBI is contrary to the
			<lb />
			directions issued in judgment and order dated 8-4-
			<lb />
			2011 by this Court in Narmada Bai v. State of
			<lb />
			Gujarat [(2011) 5 SCC 79 : (2011) 2 SCC (Cri) 526]
			<lb />
			and accordingly the same is quashed. As a
			<lb />
			consequence, the charge-sheet filed on 4-9-2012, in
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			3 (2013) 6 SCC 348
			<lb />
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			12
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place='headnote'>
			<lb />
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			pursuance of the second FIR, be treated as a
			<lb />
			supplementary charge-sheet in the first FIR. It is made
			<lb />
			clear that we have not gone into the merits of the
			<lb />
			claim of both the parties and it is for the trial court to
			<lb />
			decide the same in accordance with law. Consequently,
			<lb />
			Writ Petition (Crl.) No. 149 of 2012 is allowed. Since
			<lb />
			the said relief is applicable to all the persons arrayed
			<lb />
			as accused in the second FIR, no further direction is
			<lb />
			required in Writ Petition (Crl.) No. 5 of 2013.&quot;
			<lb />
			14.
			<lb />
			In Anju Chaudhary vs. State of Uttar Pradesh and Another 4
			<lb />
			the Supreme Court would again consider the question of a second
			<lb />
			FIR in respect of the same offence or incident forming part of the
			<lb />
			same transaction as contained in the first FIR and discuss its
			<lb />
			permissibility.
			<lb />
			&quot;14. On the plain construction of the language
			<lb />
			and scheme of Sections 154, 156 and 190 of the Code,
			<lb />
			it cannot be construed or suggested that there can be
			<lb />
			more than one FIR about an occurrence. However, the
			<lb />
			opening words of Section 154 suggest that every
			<lb />
			information relating to commission of a cognizable
			<lb />
			offence shall be reduced into writing by the officer-in-
			<lb />
			charge of a police station. This implies that there has
			<lb />
			to be the first information report about an incident
			<lb />
			which constitutes a cognizable offence. The purpose of
			<lb />
			registering an FIR is to set the machinery of criminal
			<lb />
			investigation into motion, which culminates with filing
			<lb />
			of the police report in terms of Section 173(2) of the
			<lb />
			Code. It will, thus, be appropriate to follow the settled
			<lb />
			principle that there cannot be two FIRs registered for
			<lb />
			the same offence. However, where the incident is
			<lb />
			separate; offences are similar or different, or even
			<lb />
			where the subsequent crime is of such magnitude that
			<lb />
			it does not fall within the ambit and scope of the FIR
			<lb />
			recorded first, then a second FIR could be registered.
			<lb />
			The most important aspect is to examine the inbuilt
			<lb />
			safeguards provided by the legislature in the very
			<lb />
			language of Section 154 of the Code. These safeguards
			<lb />
			can be safely deduced from the principle akin to double
			<lb />
			jeopardy, rule of fair investigation and further to
			<lb />
			prevent abuse of power by the investigating authority
			<lb />
			of the police. Therefore, second FIR for the same
			<lb />
			incident cannot be registered. Of course, the
			<lb />
			investigating agency has no determinative right. It is
			<lb />
			only a right to investigate in accordance with the
			<lb />
			provisions of the Code. The filing of report upon
			<lb />
			completion of investigation, either for cancellation or
			<lb />
			alleging commission of an offence, is a matter which
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place='footnote'>
			4 (2013) 6 SCC 384
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			13
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			once filed before the court of competent jurisdiction
			<lb />
			attains a kind of finality as far as police is concerned,
			<lb />
			may be in a given case, subject to the right of further
			<lb />
			investigation but wherever the investigation has been
			<lb />
			completed and a person is found to be prima facie
			<lb />
			guilty of committing an offence or otherwise, re-
			<lb />
			examination by the investigating agency on its own
			<lb />
			should not be permitted merely by registering another
			<lb />
			FIR with regard to the same offence. If such protection
			<lb />
			is not given to a suspect, then possibility of abuse of
			<lb />
			investigating powers by the police cannot be ruled out.
			<lb />
			It is with this intention in mind that such interpretation
			<lb />
			should be given to Section 154 of the Code, as it would
			<lb />
			not only further the object of law but even that of just
			<lb />
			and fair investigation. More so, in the backdrop of the
			<lb />
			settled
			<lb />
			canons
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			criminal
			<lb />
			jurisprudence,
			<lb />
			reinvestigation or de novo investigation is beyond the
			<lb />
			competence of not only the investigating agency but
			<lb />
			even that of the learned Magistrate. The courts have
			<lb />
			taken this view primarily for the reason that it would
			<lb />
			be opposed to the scheme of the Code and more
			<lb />
			particularly Section 167(2) of the Code. (Ref. Reeta
			<lb />
			Nag v. State of W.B. [(2009) 9 SCC 129 : (2009) 3 SCC (Cri)
			<lb />
			1051] and Vinay Tyagi v. Irshad Ali [(2013) 5 SCC 762] of
			<lb />
			the same date.)&quot;
			<lb />
			The above ratio make it crystal clear that there cannot be two
			<lb />
			FIRs for the same offence. Although two FIRs have not been
			<lb />
			exhibited herein the evidence on record indeed leads one to such
			<lb />
			conclusion. The Missing Report is actually the FIR being prior in
			<lb />
			time to Exhibit 8 which in sum and substance is a report of steps
			<lb />
			taken by P.W.9 pursuant to the Missing Report. Exhibit 8 surely
			<lb />
			does not classify as an FIR.
			<lb />
			The matter being riddled with
			<lb />
			anomalies, lacking clarity about the lodging of an FIR is therefore
			<lb />
			untenable in the eyes of law.
			<lb />
			15.
			<lb />
			The next question which is indeed the core issue at hand
			<lb />
			is taken up for consideration. Exhibit 7 the Birth Certificate of the
			<lb />
			Victim is said to have been issued from the District Hospital,
			<lb />
			Singtam, recorded as the place of birth of the Victim. Has this
			<lb />
			document been established in terms of the required legal
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			14
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			parameters? In our considered opinion, the answer would be in the
			<lb />
			negative. Learned Counsel for the State-Respondent would contend
			<lb />
			that the document is a public document requiring no proof. In this
			<lb />
			context, we may refer to Section 35 of the Evidence Act, which
			<lb />
			reads as follows;
			<lb />
			&quot;35. Relevancy of entry in public record or
			<lb />
			an electronic record made in performance of
			<lb />
			duty.-An entry in any public or other official book,
			<lb />
			register or record or any electronic record, stating a
			<lb />
			fact in issue or relevant fact, and made by a public
			<lb />
			servant in the discharge of his official duty, or by any
			<lb />
			other person in performance of a duty specially
			<lb />
			enjoined by the law of the country in which such book,
			<lb />
			register, or record or an electronic record is kept, is
			<lb />
			itself a relevant fact.&quot;
			<lb />
			16.
			<lb />
			Section 35 requires the following conditions to be
			<lb />
			fulfilled before a document can be held to be admissible under this
			<lb />
			Section;
			<lb />
			(i)
			<lb />
			The document must be in the nature of an entry in any
			<lb />
			public or other official book, register or record;
			<lb />
			(ii) It must state a fact in issue or a relevant fact; and
			<lb />
			(iii) The entry must be made by a public servant in the
			<lb />
			discharge of his official duties, or in performance of his
			<lb />
			duties.
			<lb />
			[State of Bihar vs. Radha Krishna Singh and Others 5 ]
			<lb />
			Such entries however must be established by necessary
			<lb />
			evidence. In addition to which the entries must be made by or
			<lb />
			under the direction of the person whose duty it is to make them at
			<lb />
			the relevant time. It is essential to show that the document was
			<lb />
			prepared by the public servant in the discharge of his official duty.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place='footnote'>
			5 (1983) 3 SCC 118
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			15
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			17.
			<lb />
			Section 74 of the Evidence Act defines what public
			<lb />
			documents are and reads as follows;
			<lb />
			&quot;74.
			<lb />
			Public
			<lb />
			documents.-The
			<lb />
			following
			<lb />
			documents are public documents:-
			<lb />
			(1) Documents forming the acts, or records of
			<lb />
			the acts-
			<lb />
			(i) of the sovereign authority,
			<lb />
			(ii) of official bodies and tribunals, and
			<lb />
			(iii) of public officers, legislative, judicial and
			<lb />
			executive, of any part of India or of the
			<lb />
			Commonwealth, or of a foreign country;
			<lb />
			(2) Public records kept in any State of private
			<lb />
			documents.&quot;
			<lb />
			18.
			<lb />
			In Madan Mohan Singh and Others vs. Rajni Kant and
			<lb />
			Another 6 distinguishing between the admissibility of a document and
			<lb />
			its probative value, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court would explain as
			<lb />
			follows;
			<lb />
			&quot;18. Therefore, a document may be admissible,
			<lb />
			but as to whether the entry contained therein has any
			<lb />
			probative value may still be required to be examined in
			<lb />
			the facts and circumstances of a particular case. The
			<lb />
			aforesaid legal proposition stands fortified by the
			<lb />
			judgments of this Court in Ram Prasad Sharma v. State
			<lb />
			of Bihar [(1969) 2 SCC 359 : AIR 1970 SC 326], Ram
			<lb />
			Murti v. State of Haryana [(1970) 3 SCC 21 : 1970 SCC (Cri)
			<lb />
			371 : AIR 1970 SC 1029], Dayaram v. Dawalatshah [(1971)
			<lb />
			1 SCC 358 : AIR 1971 SC 681], Harpal Singh v. State of H.P.
			<lb />
			[(1981) 1 SCC 560 : 1981 SCC (Cri) 208 : AIR 1981 SC
			<lb />
			361], Ravinder Singh Gorkhi v. State of U.P. [(2006) 5
			<lb />
			SCC 584 : (2006) 2 SCC (Cri) 632], Babloo Pasi v. State of
			<lb />
			Jharkhand [(2008) 13 SCC 133 : (2009) 3 SCC (Cri) 266], Desh
			<lb />
			Raj v. Bodh Raj [(2008) 2 SCC 186 : AIR 2008 SC 632]
			<lb />
			and Ram Suresh Singh v. Prabhat Singh [(2009) 6 SCC 681
			<lb />
			: (2010) 2 SCC (Cri) 1194]. In these cases, it has been held
			<lb />
			that even if the entry was made in an official record by
			<lb />
			the official concerned in the discharge of his official
			<lb />
			duty, it may have weight but still may require
			<lb />
			corroboration by the person on whose information the
			<lb />
			entry has been made and as to whether the entry so
			<lb />
			made has been exhibited and proved. The standard of
			<lb />
			proof required herein is the same as in other civil and
			<lb />
			criminal cases.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			6 (2010) 9 SCC 209
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			16
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			19. Such entries may be in any public document
			<lb />
			i.e. school register, voters&apos; list or family register
			<lb />
			prepared under the Rules and Regulations, etc. in
			<lb />
			force, and may be admissible under Section 35 of the
			<lb />
			Evidence Act as held in Mohd. Ikram Hussain v. State
			<lb />
			of U.P. [AIR 1964 SC 1625 : (1964) 2 Cri LJ 590] and Santenu
			<lb />
			Mitra v. State of W.B. [(1998) 5 SCC 697 : 1998 SCC (Cri)
			<lb />
			1381 : AIR 1999 SC 1587].
			<lb />
			20. So far as the entries made in the official
			<lb />
			record by an official or person authorised in
			<lb />
			performance of official duties are concerned, they may
			<lb />
			be admissible under Section 35 of the Evidence Act but
			<lb />
			the court has a right to examine their probative value.
			<lb />
			The authenticity of the entries would depend on whose
			<lb />
			information such entries stood recorded and what was
			<lb />
			his source of information. The entries in school
			<lb />
			register/school leaving certificate require to be proved
			<lb />
			in accordance with law and the standard of proof
			<lb />
			required in such cases remained the same as in any
			<lb />
			other civil or criminal cases.
			<lb />
			21. For determining the age of a person, the
			<lb />
			best evidence is of his/her parents, if it is supported by
			<lb />
			unimpeachable documents. In case the date of birth
			<lb />
			depicted in the school register/certificate stands belied
			<lb />
			by the unimpeachable evidence of reliable persons and
			<lb />
			contemporaneous documents like the date of birth
			<lb />
			register of the Municipal Corporation, government
			<lb />
			hospital/nursing home, etc., the entry in the school
			<lb />
			register is to be discarded. (Vide Brij Mohan
			<lb />
			Singh v. Priya Brat Narain Sinha [AIR 1965 SC 282], Birad
			<lb />
			Mal Singhvi v. Anand Purohit [1988 Supp SCC 604 : AIR
			<lb />
			1988 SC 1796], Vishnu v. State of Maharashtra [(2006) 1
			<lb />
			SCC 283 : (2006) 1 SCC (Cri) 217] and Satpal Singh v. State
			<lb />
			of Haryana [(2010) 8 SCC 714 : JT (2010) 7 SC 500] .)
			<lb />
			22. If a person wants to rely on a particular date
			<lb />
			of birth and wants to press a document in service, he
			<lb />
			has to prove its authenticity in terms of Section 32(5)
			<lb />
			or Sections 50, 51, 59, 60 and 61, etc. of the Evidence
			<lb />
			Act by examining the person having special means of
			<lb />
			knowledge, authenticity of date, time, etc. mentioned
			<lb />
			therein. (Vide Updesh Kumar v. Prithvi Singh [(2001) 2
			<lb />
			SCC 524 : 2001 SCC (Cri) 1300 : 2001 SCC (L&amp;S) 1063]
			<lb />
			and State of Punjab v. Mohinder Singh [(2005) 3 SCC 702
			<lb />
			: AIR 2005 SC 1868] .)&quot;
			<lb />
			[emphasis supplied]
			<lb />
			19.
			<lb />
			In the case at hand, the Prosecution furnished Exhibit 7
			<lb />
			as the Birth Certificate of the Victim. P.W.7 and P.W.8 were
			<lb />
			produced by the Prosecution as witnesses to the seizure of the
			<lb />
			document. P.W.7 testified that the Police prepared a Property
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			17
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			Seizure Memo and seized the Birth Certificate from the Victim&apos;s
			<lb />
			mother, who had produced it at the Singtam Police Station. P.W.8
			<lb />
			the second witness for the Seizure of Exhibit 7 would however state
			<lb />
			that he was called by the Victim&apos;s mother, P.W.2 to the Police
			<lb />
			Station in connection with the case relating to the Victim. According
			<lb />
			to him, the Police prepared Seizure Memo, Exhibit 6 and requested
			<lb />
			him to sign on the said document which he complied with. His
			<lb />
			specific testimony is that he did not see the Birth Certificate, Exhibit
			<lb />
			7, which was shown to him in the Court on the day his evidence was
			<lb />
			recorded, although he identified Exhibit 6 and his signature thereon
			<lb />
			as Exhibit 6(b). He however deposed that the contents of Exhibit 6
			<lb />
			were not read over and explained to him. The evidence of P.W.9
			<lb />
			ASI Tek Bahadur Chettri reveals that he had seized the Birth
			<lb />
			Certificate from the -legal guardian‖ of the Victim at the Singtam
			<lb />
			Police Station. The witness reveals the said -legal guardian‖ to be
			<lb />
			the father of the Victim. The anomaly that arises in the evidence of
			<lb />
			P.W.7 and P.W.9 is that, according to P.W.9, Exhibit 6(d) and 6(e)
			<lb />
			are the signatures of the father of the Victim from whom he had
			<lb />
			seized the Birth Certificate, Exhibit 7. This is in contradiction to the
			<lb />
			evidence of P.W.7 according to whom it was seized from the mother
			<lb />
			of the Victim. In this context when we examine the evidence of
			<lb />
			P.W.2, the Victim&apos;s mother she has made no claim that Exhibit 7
			<lb />
			was seized from her or that she had furnished Exhibit 7 at the Police
			<lb />
			Station. Infact her evidence is silent with regard to Exhibit 7 or on
			<lb />
			the aspect of the Victim&apos;s age. Although P.W.9 has identified Exhibit
			<lb />
			6(c) as his signature on Exhibit 6 and the signatures purportedly of
			<lb />
			the Victim&apos;s father, but no explanation was furnished as to why the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			18
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			father was not produced as a witness when besides being a seizure
			<lb />
			witness he was also the original Complainant as per P.W.9. Exhibit
			<lb />
			7 no doubt records the date of birth of the Victim as -14-09-2001‖
			<lb />
			but the origin of this document has remained an enigma. No
			<lb />
			Register of the Chief Registrar of Births and Deaths, Health &amp; Family
			<lb />
			Welfare Department, Government of Sikkim, was furnished to
			<lb />
			substantiate that the entries made in Exhibit 7 drew strength from
			<lb />
			the entries in the Register. No witness was forthcoming as the
			<lb />
			person who made the entries in either any Register or Exhibit 7.
			<lb />
			Confounding the above confusion is Exhibit 6 the Property Seizure
			<lb />
			Memo which at Sl. No.4 recorded that property (Exhibit 7) was
			<lb />
			seized on 25-04-2016 at 11.50 hours. The dates which appear
			<lb />
			below the signatures of the witnesses and P.W.9 all are reflected the
			<lb />
			date as -25-04-2016‖. The perpetual anomalies in the dates of the
			<lb />
			Prosecution case leads to doubts regarding its veracity and strikes at
			<lb />
			the root of the Prosecution case. Merely because Exhibit 7 is a
			<lb />
			document furnished by the Prosecution in support of their case it
			<lb />
			cannot be accepted as gospel truth without fortification by way of
			<lb />
			supporting evidence, sans examination of its probative value.
			<lb />
			20.
			<lb />
			It is also to be mentioned here that the matter at hand
			<lb />
			was registered on 06-05-2016, the Juvenile Justice (Care and
			<lb />
			Protection of Children) Act, 2015 (for short -Juvenile Justice Act‖),
			<lb />
			came into force on 15-01-2016, before the registration of the
			<lb />
			instant case. Section 94 of the Juvenile Justice Act provides for
			<lb />
			presumption and determination of age and reads as follows;
			<lb />
			&quot;94. Presumption and determination of age.─(1)
			<lb />
			Where, it is obvious to the Committee or the Board,
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			19
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			based on the appearance of the person brought before
			<lb />
			it under any of the provisions of this Act (other than for
			<lb />
			the purpose of giving evidence) that the said person is
			<lb />
			a child, the Committee or the Board shall record such
			<lb />
			observation stating the age of the child as nearly as
			<lb />
			may be and proceed with the inquiry under section 14
			<lb />
			or section 36, as the case may be, without waiting for
			<lb />
			further confirmation of the age.
			<lb />
			(2) In case, the Committee or the Board has
			<lb />
			reasonable grounds for doubt regarding whether the
			<lb />
			person brought before it is a child or not, the
			<lb />
			Committee or the Board, as the case may be, shall
			<lb />
			undertake the process of age determination, by
			<lb />
			seeking evidence by obtaining-
			<lb />
			(i) the date of birth certificate from the
			<lb />
			school, or the matriculation or equivalent
			<lb />
			certificate
			<lb />
			from
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			concerned
			<lb />
			examination Board, if available; and in
			<lb />
			the absence thereof;
			<lb />
			(ii) the
			<lb />
			birth
			<lb />
			certificate
			<lb />
			given
			<lb />
			by
			<lb />
			a
			<lb />
			corporation or a municipal authority or a
			<lb />
			panchayat;
			<lb />
			(iii) and only in the absence of (i) and (ii)
			<lb />
			above, age shall be determined by an
			<lb />
			ossification test or any other latest
			<lb />
			medical age determination test conducted
			<lb />
			on the orders of the Committee or the
			<lb />
			Board:
			<lb />
			Provided such age determination test conducted
			<lb />
			on the order of the Committee or the Board shall be
			<lb />
			completed within fifteen days from the date of such
			<lb />
			order.
			<lb />
			(3) The age recorded by the Committee or the
			<lb />
			Board to be the age of person so brought before it
			<lb />
			shall, for the purpose of this Act, be deemed to be the
			<lb />
			true age of that person.&quot;
			<lb />
			21.
			<lb />
			Although the said provision for is to gauge the age of a
			<lb />
			child in need of care and protection or a child in conflict with law and
			<lb />
			consequently for the use of the Child Welfare Committee constituted
			<lb />
			under Section 27 of the Juvenile Justice Act or the Juvenile Justice
			<lb />
			Board constituted under Section 4 of the Juvenile Justice Act,
			<lb />
			nevertheless this does not debar any Court from taking assistance of
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			20
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			the provisions of this Section to assess the age of the Victim by the
			<lb />
			methods prescribed therein.
			<lb />
			In Mahadeo (supra), the Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Supreme Court has held that;
			<lb />
			&quot;12. .......................................... Under Rule
			<lb />
			12(3)(b), it is specifically provided that only in the
			<lb />
			absence of alternative methods described under Rules
			<lb />
			12(3)(a)(i) to (iii), the medical option can be sought
			<lb />
			for. In the light of such a statutory rule prevailing for
			<lb />
			ascertainment of the age of a juvenile, in our
			<lb />
			considered opinion, the same yardstick can be rightly
			<lb />
			followed by the courts for the purpose of ascertaining
			<lb />
			the age of a victim as well.&quot;
			<lb />
			[emphasis supplied]
			<lb />
			22.
			<lb />
			Hence, if in the first instance the date of birth from the
			<lb />
			school or Matriculation Certificate of the child is unavailable then
			<lb />
			resort can be taken to a Birth Certificate given by a Corporation or a
			<lb />
			Municipal authority. It is only thereafter that the Prosecution can
			<lb />
			rely on the Ossification Test. As Exhibit 7 the Birth Certificate is of
			<lb />
			no assistance to the Prosecution and the Victim being a student of
			<lb />
			Class 7 did not possess a Matriculation Certificate the Ossification
			<lb />
			Test of the child could have been conducted. The provisions of the
			<lb />
			Section have not been complied with hence the Prosecution has
			<lb />
			failed to establish the first requirement of the case under POCSO
			<lb />
			Act, viz.; to establish that the Victim was below the age of 18 years
			<lb />
			as is the requisite provided under Section 2(d) of the POCSO Act.
			<lb />
			Thus, it is but apposite for this Court to reject Exhibit 7 as proof of
			<lb />
			age of the Victim which thereby remains unproved.
			<lb />
			23.
			<lb />
			That having been said, we may next address the
			<lb />
			question which pertains to the age of the Appellant and is of equal
			<lb />
			importance. P.W.16, the I.O. of the instant case revealed that in
			<lb />
			the course of his investigation, he filed a requisition Exhibit 24
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			21
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			before the Principal Magistrate, Juvenile Justice Board, North Sikkim
			<lb />
			at Mangan seeking permission to conduct Ossification Test in respect
			<lb />
			of the Appellant for determination of his age. The I.O. identified
			<lb />
			Exhibit 4 as the requisition of Dr. O. T. Lepcha for the Ossification
			<lb />
			Test and Exhibit 5 as the Ossification Test Report. Dr. O. T. Lepcha
			<lb />
			is not a witness herein. Pending the enquiry regarding the age of
			<lb />
			the Appellant, he was forwarded to the Juvenile Observation Home.
			<lb />
			Upon receipt of the Report he was remanded to Judicial Custody in
			<lb />
			connection with the Case vide Exhibit 26, his age having been
			<lb />
			indicated as above 20 years.
			<lb />
			24.
			<lb />
			P.W.6 Dr. K. Giri, the Principal Chief Consultant,
			<lb />
			Radiology, STNM Hospital, on receiving the requisition Exhibit 4 from
			<lb />
			Dr. O. T. Lepcha, the Medicolegal Specialist at STNM Hospital
			<lb />
			conducted Ossification Test of the Appellant. P.W.6 would give the
			<lb />
			following opinion after examining the Appellant;
			<lb />
			&quot;The following X-rays of Mangala Mishra were
			<lb />
			taken:
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			Right wrist AP
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Right elbow AP
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			Right knee AP
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Right shoulder AP
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			Right hip with crest AP
			<lb />
			The above x-rays were studied by me and I
			<lb />
			came to the conclusion that the approximate bone age
			<lb />
			of Mangala Mishra was above 20 years.
			<lb />
			Accordingly, I prepared the Bone Age Estimation
			<lb />
			Report, Exbt. 5, shown to me in the Court today under
			<lb />
			my signature Exbt.5(a).&quot;
			<lb />
			25.
			<lb />
			Exhibit 5 referred to by the Expert reads as follows;
			<lb />
			&quot;Bone age estimation
			<lb />
			Rt wrist AP -lower ends of radius &amp; ulna fused.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			22
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			Rt elbow AP -all centres fused.
			<lb />
			Rt knee AP -lower end of jemur fused.
			<lb />
			Rt shoulder AP -acromion &amp; coracoids fused.
			<lb />
			Rt hip and crest AP -iliac crest fused.
			<lb />
			Impr. Approx bone age above 20 years&quot;
			<lb />
			26.
			<lb />
			Pausing here for a minute, when we embark upon an
			<lb />
			examination of the evidence of this witness, it is clear in the first
			<lb />
			instance that his evidence would be covered by the provisions of
			<lb />
			Section 45 of the Evidence Act which deals with opinions of Experts.
			<lb />
			Medical evidence as is well settled is an opinion given by an Expert
			<lb />
			and deserves respect by the Court, however, this does not
			<lb />
			necessarily conclude as always being binding upon the Court. The
			<lb />
			Expert&apos;s evidence may be an opinion on facts such as a doctor
			<lb />
			giving his opinion as to the cause of a person&apos;s death or injury. But
			<lb />
			when calling an Expert&apos;s evidence the Prosecution must first
			<lb />
			establish the expertise of the witness by furnishing evidence to
			<lb />
			convince the Court that the witness is a competent witness. In State
			<lb />
			of Haryana vs. Bhagirath and others 7 the Supreme Court would hold as
			<lb />
			follows;
			<lb />
			&quot;15. The opinion given by a medical witness
			<lb />
			need not be the last word on the subject. Such an
			<lb />
			opinion shall be tested by the court. If the opinion is
			<lb />
			bereft of logic or objectivity, the court is not obliged to
			<lb />
			go by that opinion. After all opinion is what is formed in
			<lb />
			the mind of a person regarding a fact situation. If one
			<lb />
			doctor forms one opinion and another doctor forms a
			<lb />
			different opinion on the same facts it is open to the
			<lb />
			Judge to adopt the view which is more objective or
			<lb />
			probable. Similarly if the opinion given by one doctor is
			<lb />
			not consistent with probability the court has no liability
			<lb />
			to go by that opinion merely because it is said by the
			<lb />
			doctor. Of course, due weight must be given to
			<lb />
			opinions given by persons who are experts in the
			<lb />
			particular subject.&quot;
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place='footnote'>
			7 (1999) 5 SCC 96
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			23
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place="headnote">
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			27.
			<lb />
			On the bedrock of the principle so enunciated, the
			<lb />
			evidence of P.W.6 reveals that his expertise has not been
			<lb />
			established, the number of years he has put in as a Radiologist has
			<lb />
			not been alluded to raising a doubt about the competence of the
			<lb />
			witness. Added to that is the fact that the X-rays of the Appellant
			<lb />
			do not explain any circumstance pertaining to his age inasmuch as
			<lb />
			P.W.6 has failed to reveal what &quot;Right wrist AP, Right elbow AP,
			<lb />
			Right knee AP, Right shoulder AP and Right hip with Crest AP&quot;
			<lb />
			mean. It may be accepted medical terms but the Expert is without
			<lb />
			a doubt expected to clarify and elucidate the same to the
			<lb />
			understanding of the parties and the Court. This patently has been
			<lb />
			overlooked. Therefore, there is no basis for the Court to reach a
			<lb />
			finding as to the ground on which the Expert has reached his finding
			<lb />
			about the age of the Appellant and the satisfaction of the Court on
			<lb />
			this count is but nil. This evidence consequently cannot be taken
			<lb />
			into consideration. Undoubtedly the appearance of the Appellant
			<lb />
			was that of a minor prompting, the I.O. to file Exhibit 24 before the
			<lb />
			concerned Magistrate of the Juvenile Justice Board for age
			<lb />
			verification. The I.O. has failed to comply with the provisions of
			<lb />
			Section 94 of the Juvenile Justice Act. In such a circumstance, it is
			<lb />
			not possible to reach a final conclusion that the Appellant was
			<lb />
			indeed 20 years or above. In this aspect of the matter, useful
			<lb />
			reference may be made to the ratiocination of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme
			<lb />
			Court in Arnit Das vs. State of Bihar 8 in which while discussing
			<lb />
			authorities being Santenu Mitra vs. State of W.B. 9 , Bhola
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			8 (2000) 5 SCC 488
			<lb />
			9 (1998) 5 SCC 697
			<lb />
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			24
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
			<lb />
			Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
			<lb />
		</body>

			<body>
				Bhagat vs. State of Bihar 10 and Gopinath Ghosh vs. State of W.B. 11 and
				<lb />
				to a number of other decisions which we do not propose to
				<lb />
				catalogue separately would inter alia hold that generally speaking
				<lb />
				these cases are authorities for the propositions that;
				<lb />
				&quot;19. ……………………………………………………………….
				<lb />
				(i) the technicality of the accused having
				<lb />
				not claimed the benefit of the provisions of the
				<lb />
				Juvenile Justice Act at the earliest opportunity or
				<lb />
				before any of the courts below should not,
				<lb />
				keeping in view the intendment of the
				<lb />
				legislation, come in the way of the benefit being
				<lb />
				extended to the accused-appellant even if the
				<lb />
				plea was raised for the first time before this
				<lb />
				Court;
				<lb />
				(ii) a hypertechnical approach should not
				<lb />
				be adopted while appreciating the evidence
				<lb />
				adduced on behalf of the accused in support of
				<lb />
				the plea that he was a juvenile and if two views
				<lb />
				may be possible on the same evidence, the court
				<lb />
				should lean in favour of holding the accused to
				<lb />
				be a juvenile in borderline cases; and
				<lb />
				(iii) the provisions of the Act are
				<lb />
				mandatory
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				while
				<lb />
				implementing
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				provisions of the Act, those charged with
				<lb />
				responsibilities of implementation should show
				<lb />
				sensitivity and concern for a juvenile.
				<lb />
				……………………………………………………………………&quot;
				<lb />
				It may be added here that this pertains to the Juvenile Justice
				<lb />
				Act, 1986, but the same principles apply to the matter at hand.
				<lb />
				28.
				<lb />
				In Rajinder Chandra vs. State of Chhattisgarh and Another 12
				<lb />
				the Supreme Court would reiterate the principle laid down in Arnit
				<lb />
				Das (supra) and hold that while dealing with the question of
				<lb />
				determination of the age of the accused for the purpose of finding
				<lb />
				out whether he is a juvenile or not, a hypertechnical approach
				<lb />
			</body>

			<note place="footnote">
				10 (1997) 8 SCC 720
				<lb />
				11 1984 Supp SCC 228
				<lb />
				12 (2002) 2 SCC 287
				<lb />
				Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
				<lb />
			</note>

			<page>
				25
				<lb />
			</page>

			<body>
				Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
				<lb />
				Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
				<lb />
			</body>

				<body>
					should not be adopted while appreciating the evidence adduced on
					<lb />
					behalf of the accused in support of the plea that he was a juvenile.
					<lb />
					That if two views may be possible on the said evidence, the court
					<lb />
					should lean in favour of holding the accused to be a juvenile in
					<lb />
					borderline cases.
					<lb />
					29.
					<lb />
					In the case of the Appellant there is no evidence
					<lb />
					whatsoever at hand to gauge his age. Once a claim of juvenility or
					<lb />
					a doubt arose that the Appellant was a juvenile, the correct
					<lb />
					procedure to be adopted was the one detailed in Section 94 of the
					<lb />
					Juvenile Justice Act. P.W.7 under cross-examination has revealed
					<lb />
					that the Police seized the Voter I.D. Card of the Appellant, Exhibit
					<lb />
					24 substantiates this evidence. No reason obtains as to why it was
					<lb />
					eschewed as evidence. In the absence of conclusion proof of the age
					<lb />
					of the Appellant we lean in favour of the accused being a juvenile.
					<lb />
					30.
					<lb />
					No proof of the age of the Victim or the Appellant exists
					<lb />
					the Victim has admitted that she eloped with the Appellant of her
					<lb />
					own free will and consented to sexual intercourse. P.W.3 has stated
					<lb />
					that he saw the alleged Victim at the work site of the Appellant
					<lb />
					proving that she was there voluntarily. P.W.4 the Victim&apos;s brother
					<lb />
					had also seen the Victim talking to the Appellant behind a Masjid on
					<lb />
					account of which he gave her a beating at home. The Appellant in
					<lb />
					such circumstances cannot be saddled with the offence of
					<lb />
					penetrative sexual assault on the alleged Victim.
					<lb />
					31.
					<lb />
					In conclusion, we find that the Prosecution has failed to
					<lb />
					prove its case beyond a reasonable doubt.
					<lb />
				</body>

				<page>
					26
					<lb />
				</page>

				<note place="headnote">
					Crl.A.No.36 of 2017
					<lb />
					Mangala Mishra @ Dawa Tamang @ Jack vs. State of Sikkim
					<lb />
				</note>

				<body>
					32.
					<lb />
					The Appellant is acquitted of the offence under Section
					<lb />
					5(l) punishable under Section 6 of the POCSO Act. He be set at
					<lb />
					liberty forthwith, if not required in any other matter.
					<lb />
					33.
					<lb />
					Consequently, the impugned Judgment and Order on
					<lb />
					Sentence of the Learned Trial Court is set aside.
					<lb />
					34.
					<lb />
					Appeal is allowed.
					<lb />
					35.
					<lb />
					Fine, if any, deposited by the Appellant in terms of the
					<lb />
					impugned Order on Sentence, be reimbursed to him.
					<lb />
					36.
					<lb />
					No order as to costs.
					<lb />
					37.
					<lb />
					Copy of this Judgment be forwarded to the Learned Trial
					<lb />
					Court for information, along with its records.
					<lb />
				</body>

				<note place='footnote'>
					Sd/-
					<lb />
					Sd/-
					<lb />
					( Bhaskar Raj Pradhan )
					<lb />
					( Meenakshi Madan Rai )
					<lb />
					Judge
					<lb />
					Acting Chief Justice
					<lb />
					13-10-2018
					<lb />
					13-10-2018
					<lb />
					Approved for reporting : Yes
					<lb />
					Internet : Yes
					<lb />
					ds/bp
				</note>


	</text>
</tei>