<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<page>
			page 1 of 20
			<lb />
		</page>

		<front>
			W.A. No.02 of 2018
			<lb />
			(Sikkim University &amp; Anr. Vs. Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishnan Ananth &amp; Anr.)
			<lb />
			Page 1 of 20
			<lb />
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF SIKKIM : GANGTOK
			<lb />
			(Civil Appellate Jurisdiction)
			<lb />
			W.A. No. 02 of 2018
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			The Sikkim University,
			<lb />
			Represented through its Registrar,
			<lb />
			Sikkim University,
			<lb />
			Tadong, East Sikkim.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			The Vice Chancellor,
			<lb />
			Sikkim University,
			<lb />
			Tadong, East Sikkim.
			<lb />
			...Appellants
			<lb />
			Versus
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishna Ananth,
			<lb />
			Chair and Professor,
			<lb />
			School of Liberal Arts and Basic Sciences,
			<lb />
			Shri Ramsami Memorial University,
			<lb />
			Amravati, Neerukonda,
			<lb />
			Magalore Mandol,
			<lb />
			Guntur District, Mongola Giri,
			<lb />
			Andhra Pradesh-Pin Code-522502.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			The University Grant Commission (UGC),
			<lb />
			Represented through its Secretary,
			<lb />
			Bahadur Shah Zafar Marg,
			<lb />
			New Delhi-110002.
			<lb />
			...Respondents
			<lb />
			BEFORE
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE ARUP KUMAR GOSWAMI, C.J.
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE BHASKAR RAJ PRADHAN, J.
			<lb />
			For Appellants
			<lb />
			: Dr. Doma T. Bhutia and Mr. Manish Kumar Jain,
			<lb />
			Advocates.
			<lb />
			For Respondent No. 1 : Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishna Ananth, in-person.
			<lb />
			For Respondent No. 2 : Mr. Thinlay Dorjee Bhutia, Advocate.
			<lb />
			Date of Hearing
			<lb />
			: 27.02.2020.
			<lb />
			Date of Judgment
			<lb />
			:
			<lb />
		</front>

		<body>
			JUDGMENT
			<lb />
			(Arup Kumar Goswami, CJ.)
			<lb />
			This writ appeal is preferred against the judgment and order dated
			<lb />
			06.03.2018 passed by the learned Single Judge in W.P.(C) No. 47 of 2017,
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			page 2 of 20
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place='headnote'>
			W.A. No.02 of 2018
			<lb />
			(Sikkim University &amp; Anr. Vs. Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishnan Ananth &amp; Anr.)
			<lb />
			</note>
			<body>
				whereby the writ petition filed by the respondent no. 1 as writ petitioner was
				<lb />
				allowed.
				<lb />
				2.
				<lb />
				We have heard Dr. Doma T. Bhutia, learned counsel appearing for the
				<lb />
				appellants. We have also heard respondent no.1, who has appeared in-person,
				<lb />
				and Mr. Thinlay Dorjee Bhutia, learned counsel appearing for respondent no.2.
				<lb />
				3.
				<lb />
				The writ petitioner essentially raised a grievance regarding non-
				<lb />
				consideration of his case under Career Advancement Scheme (for short, CAS)
				<lb />
				of the Sikkim University from Stage-IV to Stage-V, i.e., from Associate
				<lb />
				Professor to Professor. According to him, though he fulfilled the eligibility
				<lb />
				criteria in terms of University Grants Commission (Minimum Qualifications for
				<lb />
				Appointment of Teachers and other Academic Staff in Universities and Colleges
				<lb />
				and other Measures for the Maintenance of Standards in Higher Education)
				<lb />
				Regulations, 2010 (for short, UGC Regulations), his case was not considered.
				<lb />
				4.
				<lb />
				For the present, to understand the core controversy, suffice it is to say
				<lb />
				that an e-mail was sent by the Registrar of the appellant University to the writ
				<lb />
				petitioner in connection with his CAS application informing him that though on
				<lb />
				scrutiny it was found that while he qualified on all other points, the Committee
				<lb />
				had observed that he had not attached with the application any documentary
				<lb />
				proof establishing the fact of his supervising award of Ph.D. and, accordingly,
				<lb />
				requesting him to send scanned copy of any documentary evidence of
				<lb />
				successfully supervising Ph.D. at the earliest. Stand of the University is that it
				<lb />
				is permissible for the university to prescribe norms over and above the UGC
				<lb />
				Regulations and that accordingly, additional criterion was laid down to the
				<lb />
				effect that Associate Professors shall be considered for promotion to the post of
				<lb />
				Professors under CAS only after they acquire the experience of guiding
				<lb />
				research scholars of Doctoral Level. The writ petitioner disputed laying down of
				<lb />
				the additional norm.
				<lb />
			</body>

			<page>
				page 3 of 20
				<lb />
			</page>

			<note place="headnote">
				W.A. No.02 of 2018
				<lb />
				(Sikkim University &amp; Anr. Vs. Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishnan Ananth &amp; Anr.)
				<lb />
			</note>

			<body>
				5.
				<lb />
				It will be relevant to note that 2 nd , 3 rd and 4 th amendment of UGC
				<lb />
				Regulations, which are relevant for the purpose of consideration of this appeal,
				<lb />
				came into effect on 13.06.2013, 04.05.2016 and 11.07.2016, respectively.
				<lb />
				6.
				<lb />
				By the 3 rd amendment of the UGC Regulations, 2010, amongst others,
				<lb />
				the existing Tables I to IX under Appendix-III of UGC Regulations, and the 2 nd
				<lb />
				amendment regarding computation of Academic Performance Indicator (API)
				<lb />
				score for appointment and promotion of teachers and other academic staff in
				<lb />
				the universities/colleges/institutions were amended and substituted by the
				<lb />
				revised Tables I to IX appended to 3 rd amendment regulations.
				<lb />
				7.
				<lb />
				Clause 6.4.8 of UGC Regulations, 2010 reads as follows:
				<lb />
				6.4.8.
				<lb />
				Associate Professor completing three years of service in
				<lb />
				stage 4 and possessing a Ph.D. Degree in the relevant
				<lb />
				discipline shall be eligible to be appointed and
				<lb />
				designated as Professor and be placed in the next
				<lb />
				higher grade (stage 5), subject to (a) satisfying the
				<lb />
				required credit points as per API based PBAS
				<lb />
				methodology provided in Table I-III of Appendix IV
				<lb />
				stipulated in these Regulations, and (b) an assessment
				<lb />
				by a duly constituted selection committee as suggested
				<lb />
				for the direct recruitment of Professor.
				<lb />
				Provided that no teachers other than those with a Ph.D.
				<lb />
				shall be promoted or appointed as Professor.
				<lb />
				8.
				<lb />
				Clause 6.0.2 of the UGC Regulations, 2010 was amended and substituted
				<lb />
				by the 2 nd amendment with the following clause:
				<lb />
				6.0.2.
				<lb />
				The Universities shall adopt these Regulations for
				<lb />
				selection committees and selection procedures through
				<lb />
				their respective statutory bodies incorporating the
				<lb />
				Academic
				<lb />
				Performance
				<lb />
				Indicator
				<lb />
				(API)
				<lb />
				based
				<lb />
				Performance Based Appraisal System (PBAS) at the
				<lb />
				institutional level for University Departments and their
				<lb />
				Constituent colleges/ affiliated colleges (Government/
				<lb />
				Government aided/ Autonomous/Private colleges) to be
				<lb />
				followed transparently in all the selection processes. An
				<lb />
				indicative PBAS template proforma for direct
				<lb />
			</body>

			<page>
				page 4 of 20
				<lb />
			</page>

			<note place="headnote">
				W.A. No.02 of 2018
				<lb />
				(Sikkim University &amp; Anr. Vs. Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishnan Ananth &amp; Anr.)
				<lb />
			</note>

			<body>
				recruitment and for Career Advancement Schemes
				<lb />
				(CAS) based on API based PBAS is annexed in
				<lb />
				Appendix III. The Universities may adopt the template
				<lb />
				proforma or may devise their own self-assessment cum
				<lb />
				performance appraisal forms for teachers. While
				<lb />
				adopting this, universities shall not change any of the
				<lb />
				categories or scores of the API given in Appendix-III.
				<lb />
				The universities can, if they wish so, increase the
				<lb />
				minimum required score or devise appropriate
				<lb />
				additional criteria for screening of candidates at any
				<lb />
				level of recruitment.
				<lb />
				(Emphasis ours)
				<lb />
				9.
				<lb />
				It is the case of the writ petitioner that as he was eligible for
				<lb />
				appointment and designation as Professor from 01.07.2016, he had submitted
				<lb />
				his application on 17.06.2016 in terms of the Appendix-III of 3 rd amendment of
				<lb />
				UGC Regulations. He had to re-submit his application on 01.03.2017 in view of
				<lb />
				a letter dated 27.02.2017 issued by appellant no. 2 requesting him to re-
				<lb />
				submit the application as the earlier application could not be located. After re-
				<lb />
				submission of his application on 01.03.2017, an e-mail dated 18.05.2017 was
				<lb />
				sent by the Internal Quality Assurance Cell, for short, &quot;IQAC&quot;, of the University
				<lb />
				requesting the writ petitioner to submit his application as per the format
				<lb />
				prescribed by the 4 th amendment of UGC Regulations, as API would have to be
				<lb />
				computed in terms of 4 th amendment of UGC Regulations. It was also observed
				<lb />
				in the said e-mail that the writ petitioner&quot;s application was in terms of the
				<lb />
				format of the 2 nd amendment. The writ petitioner by e-mail dated 19.07.2017,
				<lb />
				while questioning the authority of IQAC to deal with the subject as indicated in
				<lb />
				the e-mail dated 18.05.2017, also stated that as he had submitted his
				<lb />
				application on 17.06.2016, and date of eligibility of promotion claimed being
				<lb />
				01.07.2016, which is prior in point of time to coming into effect of the 4 th
				<lb />
				amendment of UGC Regulations, request made to him for applying on the
				<lb />
				format as prescribed in 4 th amendment was inappropriate. Thereafter, an e-
				<lb />
				mail dated 10.07.2017 was sent by the Registrar of the University, amongst
				<lb />
				others, to the writ petitioner informing that his application for CAS had been
				<lb />
			</body>

			<page>
				page 5 of 20
				<lb />
			</page>

			<note place='headnote'>
				W.A. No.02 of 2018
				<lb />
				(Sikkim University &amp; Anr. Vs. Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishnan Ananth &amp; Anr.)
				<lb />
			</note>

			<body>
				scrutinized and that while he qualified on all other points, the Committee had
				<lb />
				observed that no documentary proof was attached with the application
				<lb />
				establishing the fact of supervising award of Ph.D. and, accordingly, requesting
				<lb />
				him to send scanned copy of any documentary evidence of successfully
				<lb />
				supervising Ph.D. at the earliest. The petitioner replied back by his letters
				<lb />
				dated 10.07.2017 and 17.07.2017 stating that consistent stand of the
				<lb />
				University was that award of Ph.D. under one&quot;s supervision was not necessary
				<lb />
				for promotion as Professor under CAS. The petitioner came to learn that
				<lb />
				selection committee meetings were held after 31.07.2017 and in such
				<lb />
				meetings, applications of applicants who had submitted applications much later
				<lb />
				than the petitioner, had also been considered but the case of the petitioner
				<lb />
				was not considered.
				<lb />
				10. In the counter-affidavit filed by the respondent nos.1 and 2, a
				<lb />
				preliminary objection was taken to the effect that the writ petition suffers from
				<lb />
				non-joinder of necessary and proper party as the writ petitioner had not made
				<lb />
				the similarly situated persons parties though he had sought parity with other
				<lb />
				Professors who were promoted under CAS. Another preliminary objection was
				<lb />
				taken that in absence of any challenge made to the rule making power of the
				<lb />
				Statutory Authority, the norms laid down seeking evidence of having guided
				<lb />
				research scholars of Doctoral Level as a pre-requisite under CAS cannot be
				<lb />
				challenged. It is pleaded that it is permissible for the university to prescribe
				<lb />
				norms over and above the UGC Regulations and that accordingly, additional
				<lb />
				criterion was laid down to the effect that Associate Professors shall be
				<lb />
				considered for promotion to the post of Professors under CAS only after they
				<lb />
				acquire the experience of guiding research scholars of Doctoral Level. It is
				<lb />
				pleaded that only because the writ petitioner had completed three years as
				<lb />
				Associate Professor would not entitle him to be promoted under CAS, but the
				<lb />
				same would entitle him to be in the zone of consideration only. It is stated that
				<lb />
				the writ petitioner had the eligibility as per UGC Regulations, 2010 including 3 rd
				<lb />
			</body>

			<page>
				page 6 of 20
				<lb />
			</page>

			<note place="headnote">
				W.A. No.02 of 2018
				<lb />
				(Sikkim University &amp; Anr. Vs. Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishnan Ananth &amp; Anr.)
				<lb />
			</note>

			<body>
				and 4 th amendment up to 2016. The UGC Regulations including amendments
				<lb />
				made in the year 2016 had been adopted after approval was granted by the
				<lb />
				Executive Council in a meeting held on 10.06.2016. It is pleaded that the
				<lb />
				application submitted by the writ petitioner on 17.06.2016 was never actually
				<lb />
				received in the office files and therefore, the writ petitioner was directed to re-
				<lb />
				submit his application. It is stated that by the 4 th amendment, terms of API
				<lb />
				calculation were relaxed and list of UGC approved journals were expanded and
				<lb />
				accordingly, in order to give the benefit of amendment, the writ petitioner was
				<lb />
				directed to re-submit his application in good faith. Six candidates of various
				<lb />
				departments, who applied for promotion under CAS, were promoted to the
				<lb />
				post of Professors in their respective departments as they possessed evidence
				<lb />
				of guiding research scholars of Doctoral Level. It is also stated that a
				<lb />
				departmental enquiry against the petitioner for gaining illegal access and use
				<lb />
				of confidential document in the form of Annexure-P13 was under consideration.
				<lb />
				It is stated that the application stated to have been submitted by the
				<lb />
				petitioner, annexed as Annexure-P1, would itself demonstrate that none of
				<lb />
				Ph.D. Scholars under his supervision had completed their course.
				<lb />
				11. A reply affidavit was filed by the writ petitioner, stating, amongst others,
				<lb />
				that discretion conferred on the university to prescribe additional criteria for
				<lb />
				screening of candidates at any level of recruitment is limited to only direct
				<lb />
				recruitment and not to promotion under CAS. The petitioner disputed laying
				<lb />
				down of an additional norm requiring experience of guiding research at
				<lb />
				Doctoral Level and had contested the document at Annexure R-1 of affidavit of
				<lb />
				respondents no.1 and 2 stating that the letter head, on which contents of
				<lb />
				Annexure R-1 had been typed, had come to be used only from the month of
				<lb />
				August, 2017. It is asserted that no such decision was taken by the
				<lb />
				appropriate authority and, therefore, the Annexure R-1 document was not put
				<lb />
				in public domain. The petitioner also placed reliance on a Circular No.13/2017
				<lb />
				dated 07.03.2017, wherein while inviting applications for promotion under
				<lb />
			</body>

			<page>
				page 7  of 20
				<lb />
			</page>

			<note place="headnote">
				W.A. No.02 of 2018
				<lb />
				(Sikkim University &amp; Anr. Vs. Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishnan Ananth &amp; Anr.)
				<lb />
			</note>

			<body>
				CAS, additional criterion of experience of guiding research scholars to Ph.D.
				<lb />
				was not mentioned.
				<lb />
				12. In its affidavit, the respondent no.3 pleaded that Clause 6.0.2 of 2 nd
				<lb />
				amendment of the Principal UGC Regulations confers power on the universities
				<lb />
				to increase the minimum required score or devise appropriate additional
				<lb />
				criteria or screening of candidates at any level of recruitment and that
				<lb />
				promotion under CAS would have to be considered on the basis of Regulations
				<lb />
				which were in force on the date of eligibility and not on the date of interview.
				<lb />
				13. The learned Single Judge, on consideration of the pleadings and
				<lb />
				arguments of the parties, had noted that the following issues had arisen for
				<lb />
				consideration of the court:-
				<lb />
				&quot;11. What falls for consideration before this Court is;
				<lb />
				1.
				<lb />
				Whether the Petition suffers from non-joinder of necessary
				<lb />
				parties making it liable for dismissal?
				<lb />
				2.
				<lb />
				Whether the Respondents No. 1 and 2 are competent to
				<lb />
				prescribe any new criterion or qualification in addition to the
				<lb />
				criteria enumerated in Clause 6.4.8 of the UGC Regulations,
				<lb />
				2010 for promotion from Stage 4 to Stage 5 under the CAS,
				<lb />
				i.e. promotion from Associate Professor to the post of
				<lb />
				Professor?
				<lb />
				3.
				<lb />
				Whether the Petitioner is entitled to consideration for
				<lb />
				promotion from the Stage 4 to Stage 5 under CAS, having
				<lb />
				fulfilled the necessary criteria as laid down in Clause 6.4.8 of
				<lb />
				the UGC Regulations, 2010 and whether the 4 th amendment
				<lb />
				to the Regulations is applicable to his case?
				<lb />
				4.
				<lb />
				Whether relieving the Petitioner for another posting on lien,
				<lb />
				as per his request, would tantamount to waiving his rights to
				<lb />
				promotion?&quot;
				<lb />
			</body>

			<page>
				page 8 of 20
				<lb />
			</page>

			<note place="headnote">
				W.A. No.02 of 2018
				<lb />
				(Sikkim University &amp; Anr. Vs. Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishnan Ananth &amp; Anr.)
				<lb />
			</note>

			<body>
				14. In respect of the point no. 1 of the points for consideration, the learned
				<lb />
				Single Judge opined that when the writ petitioner had not sought for any relief
				<lb />
				against the six promoted candidates or the selection committee, the writ
				<lb />
				petition did not suffer from non-joinder of necessary parties.
				<lb />
				15. The learned Single Judge, in point no.2 for consideration as noted above,
				<lb />
				had held that in view of Clause 6.0.2 of the UGC Regulations as amended by
				<lb />
				the 2 nd Amendment, the appellant no. 1 is clothed with power to prescribe
				<lb />
				additional criteria over and above those set out in Clause 6.4.8 of the UGC
				<lb />
				Regulations for screening of candidates at any level of recruitment, which
				<lb />
				includes promotion, and thus, negating the challenge made by the writ
				<lb />
				petitioner that no additional criteria could have been prescribed by appellants
				<lb />
				no. 1 and 2 apart from those laid down in Clause 6.4.8 of the UGC Regulations
				<lb />
				for promotion from Stage-IV to Stage-V under the CAS. However, having
				<lb />
				concluded so, the learned Single Judge held that the additional criterion stated
				<lb />
				to have been laid down by the University was non-est in law. It was held that
				<lb />
				the document annexed as Annexure-I of the counter-affidavit of appellants
				<lb />
				no.1 and 2 wherein additional criterion that an Associate Professor shall be
				<lb />
				considered for promotion to the post of Professor under CAS only after
				<lb />
				acquiring the experience of guiding research at Doctoral level, was not even
				<lb />
				notified or circulated.
				<lb />
				16. The learned Single Judge repelled the argument advanced by the
				<lb />
				appellants that application dated 17.06.2016 submitted by the writ petitioner
				<lb />
				was never received by them. As the 4 th amendment of the UGC Regulations
				<lb />
				came into force with effect from 11.07.2016 and as the petitioner was held to
				<lb />
				be eligible before coming into force of the 4 th amendment, relying upon a
				<lb />
				public notice dated 21.11.2014 providing that promotion under CAS shall be
				<lb />
				governed by the UGC Regulations which are in operation on the date of
				<lb />
				eligibility and not on the date of interview, concluded that appellants no. 1 and
				<lb />
			</body>

			<page>
				page 9 of 20
				<lb />
			</page>

			<note place="headnote">
				W.A. No.02 of 2018
				<lb />
				(Sikkim University &amp; Anr. Vs. Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishnan Ananth &amp; Anr.)
				<lb />
			</note>

			<body>
				2 could not have required the writ petitioner to submit his application under
				<lb />
				the 4 th amendment.
				<lb />
				17. So far as the point no.4 of the points for consideration, as formulated by
				<lb />
				the learned Single Judge, is concerned, it will not be necessary to dilate on the
				<lb />
				issue as Dr. Doma T. Bhutia has submitted that she will not raise the issue as
				<lb />
				the writ petitioner had re-joined the University.
				<lb />
				18. Dr. Doma T. Bhutia, learned counsel for the appellants, has submitted
				<lb />
				that the learned Single Judge committed error of law in holding that Writ
				<lb />
				Petition did not suffer from non-joinder of parties. According to her, the six
				<lb />
				selected candidates were necessary parties as the writ petitioner had
				<lb />
				questioned his non-consideration for promotion and, therefore, for non-joinder
				<lb />
				of necessary parties, the Writ Petition is liable to be dismissed. She has
				<lb />
				submitted that all the six candidates had been considered for promotion as
				<lb />
				they had the additional norm, which is annexed as Annexure P-1 of the
				<lb />
				affidavit of the respondent no.1. The learned Single Judge was not correct in
				<lb />
				holding that there is no compliance of the provisions of Sikkim University Act,
				<lb />
				2006 (for short, the Act) while laying down the additional criterion and
				<lb />
				therefore, the same was non-est in the eyes of law. Learned counsel also
				<lb />
				submits that the learned Single Judge was not correct, in absence of any
				<lb />
				tangible materials on record, in accepting the argument of the writ petitioner
				<lb />
				that the aforesaid document was prepared for the purpose of the case by the
				<lb />
				University. Dr. Bhutia has drawn the attention of the Court to an application
				<lb />
				filed by the writ petitioner, registered as I.A. No.02/2019, for placing additional
				<lb />
				documents and on the basis of the objection filed thereto, contends that the
				<lb />
				documents sought to be relied upon by the writ petitioner ought not to be
				<lb />
				considered. She has also submitted that direction to consider the case of the
				<lb />
				writ petitioner for promotion under 4 th Amendment is also totally uncalled for
				<lb />
				as, by the time the writ petitioner had re-submitted his application on
				<lb />
				01.03.2017, 4 th Amendment had come into effect. Drawing attention to page
				<lb />
			</body>

			<page>
				page 10 of 20
				<lb />
			</page>

			<note place="headnote">
				W.A. No.02 of 2018
				<lb />
				(Sikkim University &amp; Anr. Vs. Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishnan Ananth &amp; Anr.)
				<lb />
			</note>

			<body>
				125 of the paper-book under the heading -&quot;Details of Ph.Ds Awarded&quot;, she has
				<lb />
				pointed out that it is evident there from that no scholar under the writ
				<lb />
				petitioner was awarded Ph.D., which is a requirement under the additional
				<lb />
				criterion laid down by the University. It is also contended that learned Single
				<lb />
				Judge granted reliefs which were not even prayed for. Accordingly, learned
				<lb />
				counsel submits that it is a fit case for interference with the judgment of the
				<lb />
				learned Single Judge.
				<lb />
				19. She has further submitted that though the case of the writ petitioner was
				<lb />
				considered because of an order dated 21.08.2019 passed in the instant appeal,
				<lb />
				the result is kept in a sealed cover as a departmental proceeding was initiated
				<lb />
				against the writ petitioner in the year 2019. Therefore, even otherwise, the
				<lb />
				result is required to be kept in sealed cover till the conclusion of the
				<lb />
				departmental proceeding. She has placed reliance on the judgments of the
				<lb />
				Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court in Maharashtra State Board of Secondary and
				<lb />
				Higher Secondary Education and Another Vs. Paritosh Bhupeshkumar
				<lb />
				Sheth and Others, reported in (1984) 4 SCC 27; Dalpat Abasaheb
				<lb />
				Solunke and Others Vs. Dr. B.S. Mahajan and Others, reported in (1990)
				<lb />
				1 SCC 305 and The Chancellor and Another Vs. Dr. Bijayananda Kar and
				<lb />
				Others, reported in (1994) 1 SCC 169.
				<lb />
				20.
				<lb />
				Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishna Ananth, who has appeared in person, has
				<lb />
				supported the impugned judgment and submits that he was aggrieved by the
				<lb />
				so-called additional criterion fixed by the University and, therefore, the learned
				<lb />
				Single Judge was correct in holding that the writ petition does not suffer from
				<lb />
				non-joinder of necessary parties. Referring to the Annexure-I of the counter-
				<lb />
				affidavit of respondent no.1 (appellant no.1 herein), he has submitted that the
				<lb />
				same is an undated document and was, at no point of time, circulated. He
				<lb />
				reiterates the submissions made before the learned Single Judge that the same
				<lb />
				is a manufactured document. He has submitted that the said document was
				<lb />
			</body>

			<page>
				page 11 of 20
				<lb />
			</page>

			<note place="headnote">
				W.A. No.02 of 2018
				<lb />
				(Sikkim University &amp; Anr. Vs. Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishnan Ananth &amp; Anr.)
				<lb />
			</note>

			<body>
				not in existence as otherwise if the aforesaid norm was really in force, there
				<lb />
				would have been no occasion for the University not to have mentioned the
				<lb />
				additional criterion purported to have been framed while inviting applications
				<lb />
				for CAS vide Circular No.13/2017 dated 07.03.2017. Rather, the said Circular
				<lb />
				refers to eligibility criteria, etc., as laid down by the UGC for promotion under
				<lb />
				CAS. Referring to page 125 of the paper-book, he submits that in absence of
				<lb />
				any requirement for guiding a scholar to Ph.D., learned counsel for the
				<lb />
				appellants is making a mountain out of a molehill. He submits that document
				<lb />
				itself indicates that information was called for with regard to Ph.D.
				<lb />
				submitted/awarded only because of the fact that 10 points are to be given for
				<lb />
				award of Ph.D. for each candidate and 7 points for submission of Ph.D. for
				<lb />
				each candidate. He has submitted that the notification dated 14.08.2018
				<lb />
				makes it abundantly clear and re-enforces the conclusion arrived at by the
				<lb />
				learned Single Judge that the additional criterion was not earlier notified by the
				<lb />
				University. It shows that the same was formally approved only on 29.06.2018.
				<lb />
				He has submitted that contention advanced by Dr. Bhutia that a disciplinary
				<lb />
				proceeding is pending and, therefore, no direction should be issued for his
				<lb />
				consideration of promotion under CAS or that the result should be kept in a
				<lb />
				sealed cover, is without any merit as he was illegally deprived of being
				<lb />
				considered way back in the year 2016. He submits that the disciplinary
				<lb />
				proceeding was initiated for extraneous consideration. He contends that
				<lb />
				submission of Dr. Bhutia that the learned Single Judge granted relief beyond
				<lb />
				what was prayed for, is without any merit and submits that, at any rate, the
				<lb />
				Court has power to mould relief depending upon the facts and circumstances of
				<lb />
				the case. He places reliance on the judgment of the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court in
				<lb />
				the case of Union of India and Others Vs. K.V. Jankiraman and Others,
				<lb />
				reported in (1991) 4 SCC 109.
				<lb />
				21. We have considered the submissions of the learned counsel for the parties and
				<lb />
				have perused the materials on record.
				<lb />
			</body>

			<page>
				page 12 of 20
				<lb />
			</page>

			<note place="headnote">
				W.A. No.02 of 2018
				<lb />
				(Sikkim University &amp; Anr. Vs. Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishnan Ananth &amp; Anr.)
				<lb />
			</note>

			<body>
				22. A necessary party is one in whose absence a writ petition cannot be effectively
				<lb />
				adjudicated. It is to be noted that no right of the selected candidates was sought to be
				<lb />
				impinged in the writ petition. The core question was whether an additional norm of
				<lb />
				eligibility was laid down at all by the University and if so, whether the same was done in
				<lb />
				accordance with law. The University and the Vice-Chancellor had been made parties and
				<lb />
				rightly so, as they are certainly necessary parties. Having regard to the contour of the
				<lb />
				controversy raised in the writ petition, the learned Single Judge was wholly justified in
				<lb />
				rejecting the preliminary objection that in absence of necessary party, the writ petition is
				<lb />
				liable to be dismissed.
				<lb />
				23. Relevant portion at page-125 of the paper-book, on which much reliance is placed
				<lb />
				by Dr. Bhutia, reads as follows:
				<lb />
				&quot;Details of Ph.Ds Awarded / submitted
				<lb />
				Name of the
				<lb />
				Scholar
				<lb />
				Title of the
				<lb />
				Thesis
				<lb />
				Submitted/
				<lb />
				Awarded
				<lb />
				Name
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				University
				<lb />
				Month
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				Year
				<lb />
				Points
				<lb />
				NA
				<lb />
				NA
				<lb />
				NA
				<lb />
				NA
				<lb />
				NA
				<lb />
				NA
				<lb />
				Total points over assessment period
				<lb />
				Note: (i)
				<lb />
				10 points / each candidates awarded.
				<lb />
				(ii)
				<lb />
				7 points for Ph.D submitted.&quot;
				<lb />
				24. Though it is apparent from the above that the writ petitioner had not guided any
				<lb />
				scholar to award of Ph.D., same does not indicate laying down of additional norm. It only
				<lb />
				indicates how points are to be awarded for award/submission of Ph.D.
				<lb />
				25.
				<lb />
				Orders of this Court dated 25.11.2019 indicated that the order dated 21.08.2019
				<lb />
				directing the University to consider the case of the writ petitioner within a period of four
				<lb />
				weeks was not complied with in letter and spirit. Subsequently, an affidavit was filed on
				<lb />
				behalf of the University, amongst others, indicating that the case of the writ petitioner was
				<lb />
				considered by the Selection Committee on 12.02.2020 and the decision of the Selection
				<lb />
				Committee was placed before the Executive Council. It was further stated that decision
				<lb />
				was kept in sealed cover as a disciplinary proceeding was pending against the writ
				<lb />
				petitioner. As there was substantial compliance of the order of the Division Bench dated
				<lb />
			</body>

			<page>
				page 13 of 20
				<lb />
			</page>

			<note place="headnote">
				W.A. No.02 of 2018
				<lb />
				(Sikkim University &amp; Anr. Vs. Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishnan Ananth &amp; Anr.)
				<lb />
			</note>

			<body>
				21.08.2019, it was noted in the order dated 20.02.2020 that these aspects would be
				<lb />
				considered in the final hearing of the appeal and accordingly, the appeal was heard.
				<lb />
				26. Annexure-1 of the counter-affidavit in opposition of the appellants reads as follows:
				<lb />
				&quot;Statement about Sikkim University norm for Professorship under
				<lb />
				CAS
				<lb />
				This is to state that Vice-chancellor of Sikkim University, for the sake of
				<lb />
				quality of higher education, has, since 2015, established a norm according to
				<lb />
				which an Associate Professor shall be considered for promotion to the post of
				<lb />
				Professor under Career Advancement Schemes only after acquiring the
				<lb />
				experience of guiding research at doctoral level, in addition to the norms
				<lb />
				established by the University Grants Commission under Section 26(1) of the
				<lb />
				UGC Act, 1956.
				<lb />
				The Vice-chancellor has established the above under Section 12(2) of the
				<lb />
				Sikkim University Act, 2006 (No. 10 of 2017).&quot;
				<lb />
				27. It is relevant to state that in the objection filed in I.A. No.02/2019, the
				<lb />
				appellant University had not disputed the documents. All that is said is that
				<lb />
				Annexures-A1 and A2 of I.A. No.02/2019 had come into effect post the date of
				<lb />
				judgment of the learned Single Judge and, therefore, the same should not be
				<lb />
				considered. Annexures-A3 and A4 are stated to be having no bearing with the
				<lb />
				instant case.
				<lb />
				28. This Court is of the considered opinion that there cannot be any
				<lb />
				impediment for a writ appellate Court to take note of a document in the
				<lb />
				interest of justice if the document, though subsequent in point of time, can
				<lb />
				throw light to the controversy.
				<lb />
				29. Annexure-A1 reads as follows:
				<lb />
				Notification -97/ 2018
				<lb />
				Subject:
				<lb />
				Policy for promotion under CAS for placement of Stage IV
				<lb />
				(Associate Professor) to Stage V (Professor)
				<lb />
				University has adopted UGC&quot;s Regulations on minimum qualification for
				<lb />
				appointment of teachers and other academic staff in University and
				<lb />
			</body>

			<page>
				page 14 of 20
				<lb />
			</page>

			<note place="headnote">
				W.A. No.02 of 2018
				<lb />
				(Sikkim University &amp; Anr. Vs. Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishnan Ananth &amp; Anr.)
				<lb />
			</note>

			<body>
				Colleges and measures for the maintenance of standard of higher
				<lb />
				education, 2010. University also adopted a policy of having successfully
				<lb />
				guided Ph.D as one of the requirements for promotion under CAS from
				<lb />
				Stage IV (Associate Professor) to Stage V (Professor). This was made
				<lb />
				known to all prospective candidates informally but was not notified by
				<lb />
				the University. Accordingly all those candidates who had successfully
				<lb />
				guided Ph.D after fulfillment of other conditions as prescribed in UGC
				<lb />
				Regulations were considered under CAS for placement from Stage IV to
				<lb />
				Stage V in 2017.
				<lb />
				The Executive Council in its 31 st meeting held on 29 th June 2018 formally
				<lb />
				approved the policy of the University of having successfully guided Ph.D
				<lb />
				(awarded) as one of the requirements for promotion under CAS for
				<lb />
				placement from Stage-IV (Associate Professor) to Stage-V (Professor).
				<lb />
				Moreover, the new UGC Regulations 2018 has also clearly mentioned the
				<lb />
				successfully guided Ph.D for promotion from Associate Professor to
				<lb />
				Professor.&quot;
				<lb />
				(Emphasis ours)
				<lb />
				30. Relevant portion of Annexure-A2 reads as follows:
				<lb />
				&quot;……………………… The Council was informed that the University
				<lb />
				has adopted a policy of having successfully guided Ph.D as one of
				<lb />
				the minimum requirements for promotion under CAS from Stage-4
				<lb />
				(Associate Professor) to Stage-5 (Professor). Though this policy
				<lb />
				has not been notified by the University but it was made known to
				<lb />
				all prospective candidates informally. As such all CAS cases from
				<lb />
				Stage-4 to Stage-5 in 2017 were considered and those having
				<lb />
				successfully guided Ph.D were placed in Stage-5 (Professor), after
				<lb />
				fulfillment of other conditions as prescribed in UGC&quot;s Regulation.
				<lb />
				Case of Dr. V. Krishna Ananth, Associate Professor could not be
				<lb />
				considered for placement at Stage-5 (Professor) as he did not fulfill
				<lb />
				the criteria of having successfully guided Ph.D. He thereafter
				<lb />
			</body>

			<page>
				page 15 of 20
				<lb />
			</page>

			<note place="headnote">
				W.A. No.02 of 2018
				<lb />
				(Sikkim University &amp; Anr. Vs. Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishnan Ananth &amp; Anr.)
				<lb />
			</note>

			<body>
				approached the High Court of Sikkim. Single bench of High Court
				<lb />
				though stated that the University is within its powers to lay down
				<lb />
				additional criteria, yet it ruled against the University as the policy
				<lb />
				of having successfully guided Ph.D had not been notified. However,
				<lb />
				University has filed a review petition for consideration of the matter
				<lb />
				by the Division Bench which has been accepted.
				<lb />
				The policy of having successfully guided Ph.D for CAS from
				<lb />
				Stage-4 to Stage-5 was kept as it is a mandatory criterion for
				<lb />
				direct recruitment at Associate Professor level as per UGC
				<lb />
				guidelines. But this guideline was not followed by the University for
				<lb />
				direct recruitment of Associate Professors from the beginning. To
				<lb />
				compensate the shortfall, the above policy for CAS from Stage-4 to
				<lb />
				Stage-5 was adopted.
				<lb />
				The Council after deliberations formally approved the policy
				<lb />
				of the University of having successfully guided Ph.D (Awarded) as
				<lb />
				one of the main requirements for promotion under CAS from
				<lb />
				Stage-4 (Associate Professor) to Stage-5 (Professor).
				<lb />
				(Emphasis ours)
				<lb />
				After adopting the resolution Dr. K.R. Rama Mohan, Dr. S.
				<lb />
				Manivannan and Dr. Subit Mukhopadhyay were asked to re-join the
				<lb />
				meeting.&quot;
				<lb />
				31. Relevant portion of Annexure-A3, a letter dated 13.09.2018, reads as follows:
				<lb />
				5.
				<lb />
				Withdrawal of Notification No. 97/2018: Notification No.
				<lb />
				97/2018 dated 14 th August 2018 has been issued in pursuance to the
				<lb />
				policy approved by the Executive Council in its 31 st meeting held on
				<lb />
				29 th June 2018 of having successfully guided PhD (awarded) as one of
				<lb />
				the requirements for promotion under CAS for placement from Stage-
				<lb />
				IV (Associate Professor) to Stage V (Professor). Notification of such a
				<lb />
			</body>

			<page>
				page 16 of 20
				<lb />
			</page>

			<note place="headnote">
				W.A. No.02 of 2018
				<lb />
				(Sikkim University &amp; Anr. Vs. Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishnan Ananth &amp; Anr.)
				<lb />
			</note>

			<body>
				policy was warranted as per the advice of our Counsels to place in the
				<lb />
				Division bench of Hon&apos;ble High Court.
				<lb />
				32. Annexure-A4 is a notification dated 18.07.2018, whereby UGC Regulations 2010
				<lb />
				was superseded. Annexure-A5 is a letter dated 07.08.2014 on the subject of officers
				<lb />
				performing current duties of a post which is issued by the Government of India, Ministry of
				<lb />
				Human Resource Development, Department of Higher Education.
				<lb />
				33. Going through the contents of the documents and as the authenticity of the
				<lb />
				documents are not questioned, we are of the opinion that it will be in the interest of
				<lb />
				justice to take note of Annexures-A1 to A4. However, we do not think Annexure-A5 is
				<lb />
				relevant.
				<lb />
				34. In Maharashtra State Board of Secondary and Higher Secondary
				<lb />
				Education (supra), the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court laid down that a bye-law
				<lb />
				cannot be struck down by Court unless it can be said that a bye-law is
				<lb />
				manifestly unjust, capricious, inequitable, or partial in its operation, it cannot
				<lb />
				be invalidated by the Court on the ground of unreasonableness. In Dalpat
				<lb />
				Abasaheb Solunke (supra), the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court laid down that it is
				<lb />
				not the function of the Court to hear appeals over the decisions of the
				<lb />
				Selection Committees or to scrutinize the relative merits of the candidates. In
				<lb />
				Dr. Bijayananda Kar (supra), the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court has held whether a
				<lb />
				candidate fulfils the requisite qualification or not is a matter which should be
				<lb />
				entirely left to be decided by the academic bodies.
				<lb />
				35. The application of propositions of law as laid down in the aforesaid
				<lb />
				judgments does not arise in the present case as what falls for consideration is
				<lb />
				whether the University had laid down an additional criterion for promotion
				<lb />
				under CAS from Stage-IV to Stage-V in addition to norms under UGC
				<lb />
				Regulations.
				<lb />
				36. It is virtually the admitted position that but for the additional criterion stated to
				<lb />
				have been laid down by the University, the writ petitioner had qualified in terms of the
				<lb />
				UGC regulations. Annexure-1 of the counter-affidavit of the respondents no. 1
				<lb />
			</body>

			<page>
				page 17 of 20
				<lb />
			</page>

			<note place="headnote">
				W.A. No.02 of 2018
				<lb />
				(Sikkim University &amp; Anr. Vs. Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishnan Ananth &amp; Anr.)
				<lb />
			</note>

			<body>
				and 2 is not dated. Given the importance of the issue, it is, to say the least,
				<lb />
				very surprising. Content of the same is very vague. It is not indicated when
				<lb />
				such an additional norm was &quot;established&quot; by the Vice Chancellor. All that is
				<lb />
				said is that the norm was &quot;established&quot; since 2015. That is the only document
				<lb />
				that was brought on record by the appellants relating to laying down of
				<lb />
				additional norm. There is an unequivocal admission in Annexures-A1 and A2
				<lb />
				that the additional norm was not notified by the University. It is also admitted
				<lb />
				therein that Executive Council approved the above policy only on 29.06.2018.
				<lb />
				In view of the above, this Court is of the unhesitant opinion that even if a
				<lb />
				policy laying down additional norm was formulated, without notifying the same
				<lb />
				and without due approval, it could not have been acted upon. It was in that
				<lb />
				context the learned Single Judge had noted that the same was non-est in law.
				<lb />
				The appellants have also failed to reconcile how Circular No.13/2017 dated
				<lb />
				07.03.2017, wherein while inviting applications for promotion under CAS,
				<lb />
				additional criterion of experience of guiding research scholars to Ph.D. was not
				<lb />
				mentioned, and Annexure-1 of the counter-affidavit of the appellants can stand
				<lb />
				together.
				<lb />
				37. The six candidates who had been promoted under CAS may not have
				<lb />
				questioned application of additional norm. That does not mean the writ
				<lb />
				petitioner has to follow suit. He can certainly articulate his grievance in
				<lb />
				accordance with law. When this Court has held that additional criterion could
				<lb />
				not have been applied during the relevant time when the application of the
				<lb />
				petitioner for CAS was initially under consideration, an argument cannot be
				<lb />
				countenanced that the eligibility of the writ petitioner cannot be considered on
				<lb />
				a lesser yardstick as compared to other candidates in the fray.
				<lb />
				38. There is an acknowledgement of receipt of the application dated
				<lb />
				17.06.2016 of the writ petitioner for CAS. By the letter dated 27.02.2017
				<lb />
				(Annexure P-5 of the writ petition) the Assistant Registrar of the University
				<lb />
				requested the writ petitioner to re-submit his application. The said letter
				<lb />
			</body>

			<page>
				page 18 of 20
				<lb />
			</page>

			<note place="headnote">
				W.A. No.02 of 2018
				<lb />
				(Sikkim University &amp; Anr. Vs. Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishnan Ananth &amp; Anr.)
				<lb />
			</note>

			<body>
				indicates that his application could not be located. There was no other
				<lb />
				communication in between with regard to the aforesaid subject. The learned
				<lb />
				Single Judge had, as noted earlier, not accepted the argument of the
				<lb />
				University that the application was not received. Learned counsel for the
				<lb />
				appellants has failed to show why the aforesaid conclusion of the learned
				<lb />
				Single Judge is wrong.
				<lb />
				39. The application dated 17.06.2016 was submitted prior to coming into
				<lb />
				force of 4 th Amendment of UGC Regulations. The stand of the University was
				<lb />
				that the writ petitioner was requested to re-submit his application in order to
				<lb />
				give benefit of 4 th Amendment. When the writ petitioner had qualified under
				<lb />
				the 2 nd Amendment and 3 rd Amendment, it is not understood why the benefit
				<lb />
				under the 4 th Amendment had to be given to the writ petitioner.
				<lb />
				40. The learned Single Judge issued the following directions:
				<lb />
				&quot;(a) The Respondents No.1 and 2 shall take steps to consider the
				<lb />
				promotion of the Petitioner from Stage 4 to Stage 5, in terms
				<lb />
				of the UGC Regulations, 2010, Clause 6.4.8 and any other
				<lb />
				relevant provision. While doing so, due consideration shall be
				<lb />
				taken of the observations in the e-mail dated July 10, 2017
				<lb />
				addressed to the Petitioner and one Dr. Sathyanarayanan
				<lb />
				from Mr. T.K. Kaul, Registrar, Sikkim University, wherein the
				<lb />
				Petitioner has been informed that he qualifies on all other
				<lb />
				points except the criterion added vide Annexure-I. No
				<lb />
				consideration whatsoever shall be attached to the impugned
				<lb />
				additional criterion inserted by the Respondent No.2 vide
				<lb />
				Annexure-I (Page 143 of the Paper-Book), viz. requiring
				<lb />
				supervising award of Ph.D., the same being non est in the
				<lb />
				eyes law.
				<lb />
				(b) The Respondents No. 1 and 2 shall consider the Application
				<lb />
				of the Petitioner for promotion under the 3 rd amendment
				<lb />
			</body>

			<page>
				page 19 of 20
				<lb />
			</page>

			<note place="headnote">
				W.A. No.02 of 2018
				<lb />
				(Sikkim University &amp; Anr. Vs. Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishnan Ananth &amp; Anr.)
				<lb />
			</note>

			<body>
				dated 4 th May, 2016 of the UGC Regulations, 2010 which are
				<lb />
				applicable to him and not under the 4 th amendment dated
				<lb />
				11 th July, 2016, which has no retrospective effect t.
				<lb />
				(b) All necessary steps shall be completed within sixty days
				<lb />
				hence.&quot;
				<lb />
				41. The writ petitioner essentially prayed for completing the process of
				<lb />
				consideration of his case for promotion from Stage-IV to Stage-V as per 3 rd
				<lb />
				Amendment of UGC Regulations. While deciding the aforesaid prayer, validity
				<lb />
				of the additional criterion as laid down in Annexure-1 of the counter-affidavit
				<lb />
				had arisen. Viewed in that context, it cannot be said that relief beyond prayer
				<lb />
				was granted by learned Single Judge. Even otherwise, it is well-settled that in
				<lb />
				the facts and circumstances of a case, a writ court will be justified to mould the
				<lb />
				relief for ends of justice.
				<lb />
				42. The appellants have not brought on record the charge memo though 4
				<lb />
				affidavits had been filed by them during the course of the appeal. The date of
				<lb />
				charge memo is also not mentioned. Dr. Bhutia had submitted that
				<lb />
				departmental proceeding was initiated in the year 2019. From the averments
				<lb />
				made in the affidavits and the documents annexed thereto it would appear that
				<lb />
				a disciplinary proceeding was initiated against the writ petitioner along with
				<lb />
				other members of a screening committee in respect of calculation of API score
				<lb />
				in respect of a candidate. The learned Single Judge had directed to consider
				<lb />
				the case of the writ petitioner by the order dated 06.03.2018 within 4 weeks.
				<lb />
				Prayer for stay of the judgment and order was rejected on 21.08.2019 with a
				<lb />
				further direction to consider the case of the writ petitioner within 4 weeks in
				<lb />
				terms of the order of the learned Single Judge. This order was not assailed in
				<lb />
				any forum. The order does not indicate that any submission was advanced that
				<lb />
				a disciplinary proceeding had been initiated against the writ petitioner. The
				<lb />
				developments after 21.08.2019 had already been noted in paragraph 25 of this
				<lb />
			</body>

			<page>
				page 20 of 20
				<lb />
			</page>

			<note place="headnote">
				W.A. No.02 of 2018
				<lb />
				(Sikkim University &amp; Anr. Vs. Dr. Vaidyanathan Krishnan Ananth &amp; Anr.)
				<lb />
			</note>

			<body>
				judgment. The counter-affidavit of the appellants dated 28.10.2017 goes to
				<lb />
				show that the 6 other applicants had been appointed as Professors by them.
				<lb />
				43. In K.V. Jankiraman (supra), it is laid down as follows:
				<lb />
				&quot;8. …………………………………………………………………………………
				<lb />
				The &quot;sealed cover procedure&quot; is adopted when an employee
				<lb />
				is due for promotion, increment etc. but disciplinary/criminal
				<lb />
				proceedings are pending against him at the relevant time and
				<lb />
				hence, the findings of his entitlement to the benefit are kept in a
				<lb />
				sealed cover to be opened after the proceedings in question are
				<lb />
				over. …………………………………….&quot;
				<lb />
				At the relevant time, there was no disciplinary proceeding pending against the
				<lb />
				writ petitioner and therefore, we are of the opinion that it is not a case where
				<lb />
				result should be kept in sealed cover.
				<lb />
				44. In view of the above discussions, we find no merit in the appeal and
				<lb />
				accordingly, the same is dismissed.
				<lb />
				45. No cost.
				<lb />
				Judge
				<lb />
				Chief Justice
			</body>


	</text>
</tei>