<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF KERALA AT ERNAKULAM
			<lb />
			PRESENT
			<lb />
			THE HONOURABLE MR.JUSTICE A.M.SHAFFIQUE
			<lb />
			&amp;
			<lb />
			THE HONOURABLE MR. JUSTICE GOPINATH P.
			<lb />
			THURSDAY, THE 07TH DAY OF JANUARY 2021 / 17TH POUSHA, 1942
			<lb />
			WP(C).No.27408 OF 2017(S)
			<lb />
			PETITIONER:
			<lb />
			M.K. SALIM
			<lb />
			AGED 61 YEARS, S/O. HAJI M.K. AHMEDKUNJU,HAJI
			<lb />
			MANZIL, MAIN ROAD, KOLLAM -691 001.
			<lb />
			BY ADV. SRI. M.K. SALIM (PARTY -IN -PERSON)
			<lb />
			RESPONDENTS:
			<lb />
			1
			<lb />
			STATE OF KERALA
			<lb />
			REPRESENTED BY CHIEF SECRETARY
			<lb />
			SECRETARIAT,THIRUVANANTHAPURAM-695001.
			<lb />
			2
			<lb />
			PRINCIPAL SECRETARY
			<lb />
			PORTS, SECRETARIAT, THIRUVANANTHAPURAM-695001.
			<lb />
			3
			<lb />
			MR.GAUTHAM ADANI
			<lb />
			CHAIRMAN, ADANI VIZHINJAM PORTS PVT LTD, 2ND
			<lb />
			FLOOR, VIPANCHIKA TOWERS,
			<lb />
			THYCAUD,THIRUVANANTHAPURAM. CORPORATE OFFICE:
			<lb />
			CHAIRMAN,ADANI HOUSE, NEAR MITHAKHAIL SIX
			<lb />
			ROADS,NAVARANGPURA, AHAMEDABAD, GUJARATH -380
			<lb />
			09
			<lb />
			4
			<lb />
			SHRI.OOMMENCHANDY
			<lb />
			MLA EX CHIEF MINISTER, PUTHUPALLY HOUSE,
			<lb />
			JAGATHY,THIRUVANANTHAPURAM -695 001.
			<lb />
			WP(C) No.27408/2017
			<lb />
			-:2:-
			<lb />
			5
			<lb />
			SHRI.K.BABU
			<lb />
			EX. MINISTER, KANNUVARAMPATHU HOUSE, SANSKRIT
			<lb />
			COLLEGE ROAD,
			<lb />
			THRIPUNITHURA, ERNAKULAM -682 031.
			<lb />
			6
			<lb />
			SUPERINTENDENT OF POLICE CBI
			<lb />
			COCHIN UNIT, KATHRIKADAVU KALOOR,
			<lb />
			ERNAKULAM -682 017.
			<lb />
			R1 AND R2 BY SRI.K.V.SOHAN, STATE ATTORNEY
			<lb />
			R5 BY ADV. SRI. PAUL C. THOMAS
			<lb />
			R5 BY ADV. SRI.C.S.AJITH PRAKASH
			<lb />
			R3 BY ADV. SRI.K.M.ANEESH
			<lb />
			R3 BY ADV. SRI.ADARSH KUMAR
			<lb />
			R3 BY ADV. SRI.BIJU VARGHESE ABRAHAM
			<lb />
			R5 BY ADV. SRI.BIJITH S.KHAN
			<lb />
			R5 BY ADV. SRI.M.BAIJU NOEL
			<lb />
			R4 BY ADV. SRI.K.P.DANDAPANI SR.
			<lb />
			R5 BY ADV. SRI.T.K.DEVARAJAN
			<lb />
			R3 BY ADV. SRI.DILEEP CHANDRAN
			<lb />
			R5 BY ADV. SRI.A.T.JOSE
			<lb />
			R4 BY ADV. SRI.MILLU DANDAPANI
			<lb />
			R4 BY ADV. SRI.ROSHEN.D.ALEXANDER
			<lb />
			BY ADV. SRI.K.SANTHOSH KUMAR KALIYANAM
			<lb />
			R3 BY ADV. SRI.SHASHANK DEVAN
			<lb />
			R6 BY ADV. SRI. SASTHAMANGALAM S. AJITHKUMAR,
			<lb />
			SPL.P.P. FOR C.B.I.
			<lb />
			THIS WRIT PETITION (CIVIL) HAVING BEEN FINALLY HEARD ON
			<lb />
			18-12-2020, THE COURT ON 7-1-2021 DELIVERED THE FOLLOWING:
			<lb />
			WP(C) No.27408/2017
			<lb />
			-:3:-
			<lb />
		</front>

		<body>
			J U D G M E N T
			<lb />
			Dated this the 7 th day of January, 2021
			<lb />
			Shaffique, J.
			<lb />
			Writ petition has been filed pro bono inter alia seeking the
			<lb />
			following reliefs.
			<lb />
			&quot;i) To issue a writ of mandamus order or direction to the
			<lb />
			Official respondents to take effective steps to protect the
			<lb />
			interest of the State by making necessary modifications in
			<lb />
			the agreement entered upon by the Kerala Government and
			<lb />
			ADANI Vizhinjam Harbour Seaport.
			<lb />
			ii) To issue an order or direction to the then Chief Minister,
			<lb />
			Shri. Oommen Chandy, Ports Minister Shri. K. Babu, Ports
			<lb />
			Minister to owe the responsibility for the loss to the State
			<lb />
			Government and for not protecting the State interest and to
			<lb />
			giving away all the benefits to the concessionaire running
			<lb />
			away with all the benefits as pointed out by the Accountant
			<lb />
			General and for responsible in catering the agreement and
			<lb />
			mainly responsible for the signing of the M.O.U and
			<lb />
			entrusting the decision only with the respondent no.1 &amp; 2
			<lb />
			who was the Principal Secretary, Ports, Kerala Government
			<lb />
			to take a decision against the interest of the State as
			<lb />
			pointed out by the C.A.G in all the meeting took place in
			<lb />
			Delhi for the sanctioning of the agreement between the
			<lb />
			State and ADANI GROUP.
			<lb />
			iii) To issue an order or direction to the 6 th respondent or
			<lb />
			any national investigating agency to probe into all the
			<lb />
			lapses and file charge sheet before this Hon&apos;ble Court within
			<lb />
			a stipulated time under the supervision of this Court to
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.27408/2017
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			-:4:-
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			probe whether any kickbacks were paid to anybody for
			<lb />
			entering into such an agreement with the Concessionaire
			<lb />
			which has put the State under heavy loss and the State
			<lb />
			interest are not taken care off as per the C.A.G report. An
			<lb />
			expert committee to be set up by the court to rectify the
			<lb />
			losses to the State through the M.O.U which to be altered
			<lb />
			accordingly.
			<lb />
			iv) To declare the enquiry commission constituted to probe
			<lb />
			the CAG findings may be dissolved as the CAG has
			<lb />
			equivalent powers of Judge of Supreme Court.&quot;
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			The substantial contention urged by the petitioner is
			<lb />
			that the Comptroller and Auditor General of India in its report has
			<lb />
			listed out several irregularities in the conditions incorporated in
			<lb />
			an agreement between the State of Kerala and Adani Ports
			<lb />
			Private Ltd., which were unfavourable to the State. But despite
			<lb />
			such reports, no action is taken by the Government to consider
			<lb />
			whether the agreement would protect the interest of the State
			<lb />
			and therefore he seeks appropriate modification to the
			<lb />
			agreement and to
			<lb />
			ensure proper enquiry being conducted
			<lb />
			through an appropriate agency into the kickbacks if any that
			<lb />
			would have passed on between the parties while entering into the
			<lb />
			agreement.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			The respondents have filed their counter affidavit
			<lb />
			denying the allegations. During the course of the proceedings,
			<lb />
			this Court had sought the response of the Government by an
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.27408/2017
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			-:5:-
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			interim order dated 13/9/2017. By yet another interim order
			<lb />
			dated 9/10/2017, it was observed that the State Government had
			<lb />
			appointed a Commission of Enquiry under the Commission of
			<lb />
			Enquiry Act, 1952, headed by a retired Judge of this Court as per
			<lb />
			notification dated 18/7/2019 and therefore, it is not appropriate
			<lb />
			to consider the matter while awaiting for the recommendation of
			<lb />
			the Commission. By a further interim order dated 15/3/2019, it
			<lb />
			was indicated by this Court that the commission of enquiry has
			<lb />
			finalised the report and it has to be placed before the State
			<lb />
			Legislature.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			When the above matter came up for hearing on
			<lb />
			18/12/2020, we heard Sri.M.K.Salim, the petitioner as party in
			<lb />
			person through video conferencing, learned State Attorney
			<lb />
			Sri.K.V.Sohan,
			<lb />
			Sri.K.P.Dandapani,
			<lb />
			learned
			<lb />
			Senior
			<lb />
			counsel
			<lb />
			appearing on behalf of the 4 th respondent, Sri.C.S.Ajith Prakash,
			<lb />
			learned counsel appearing on behalf of the 5 th respondent and
			<lb />
			Sri.Sasthamangalam S.Ajith Kumar, learned Special Public
			<lb />
			Prosecutor appearing on behalf of the 6 th respondent.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			The petitioner reiterated his contentions in the matter.
			<lb />
			The learned State Attorney placed before us Government letter
			<lb />
			dated 2/12/2020 sent by the Additional Chief Secretary to the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.27408/2017
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			-:6:-
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Director,
			<lb />
			Vigilance
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			Anti-Corruption
			<lb />
			Bureau,
			<lb />
			Thiruvananthapuram. The purport of the letter is that based on
			<lb />
			the Commission Report of Justice C.N.Ramachandran Nair and the
			<lb />
			infirmities which were pointed out, Government had decided to
			<lb />
			conduct vigilance enquiry and therefore sanction was given to
			<lb />
			conduct investigation under Section 17A of the Prevention of
			<lb />
			Corruption Act, 1988. The relevant portion of the said letter reads
			<lb />
			as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;xxx
			<lb />
			A Concession agreement has been entered into between
			<lb />
			the Government of Kerala and Adani Vizhinjam Port Private
			<lb />
			Limited for the construction of the Vizhinjam International
			<lb />
			Multi-purpose Seaport. lt is reported as per the references
			<lb />
			cited (copies enclosed) that actions as elaborated below
			<lb />
			have resulted in financial advantage to the Concessionaire,
			<lb />
			which were not conceived at the time of RFP.
			<lb />
			1. It was proposed to construct breakwater as per EPC
			<lb />
			(Engineering, Procurement and Construction) mode. This
			<lb />
			proposal was subsequently canceled and incorporated as a
			<lb />
			work to be carried-out by, the Concessionaire an amount of
			<lb />
			Rs. 1463 Crores. As the EPC tender was canceled, the
			<lb />
			market rate for the above project could not be worked out.
			<lb />
			It has resulted in huge benefit to Concessionaire.
			<lb />
			2. As per EPC proposal, the cost required for the
			<lb />
			completion of breakwater and Fishing harbour was Rs.747
			<lb />
			Crores, fixed by the Consultant. The same was increased
			<lb />
			to Rs.1463 crores. Though the cost of funded work was
			<lb />
			increased, since only one offer was received, the cost of the
			<lb />
			project was not meticulously analyzed and vetted at the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.27408/2017
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			-:7:-
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Government level and the cost seems to be without
			<lb />
			considering the actual requirement. This has also resulted
			<lb />
			in benefit to the Concessionaire.
			<lb />
			3. Extension of Concession period from 30 years to
			<lb />
			40 years against the provisions under the Model Concession
			<lb />
			Agreement has resulted in huge benefit to the
			<lb />
			Concessionaire.
			<lb />
			4. The construction of breakwater and Fishing
			<lb />
			Harbour as funded work, development of Port Estate, etc,
			<lb />
			were not originally contemplated at the tine of RFQ. This
			<lb />
			has also made for undue benefit to the Concessionaire.
			<lb />
			5. A comparative study of certain rates to ascertain
			<lb />
			the cost of funded works on DPR and Basic Engineering
			<lb />
			Report shows that rate calculated in the Concession
			<lb />
			agreement gives undue benefit to the Concessionaire.
			<lb />
			6. The rate of rock which is a substantial component
			<lb />
			of breakwater is based on the rates fixed by AECOM &amp; the
			<lb />
			rate assessed by the C&amp;AG on the rate fixed by HED shows
			<lb />
			huge difference. While fixing such rates no proper scrutiny
			<lb />
			has been made.
			<lb />
			I am directed to inform you that the Government
			<lb />
			have decided to conduct a Vigilance Enquiry on the above
			<lb />
			aspects. Accordingly, sanction is also given to conduct the
			<lb />
			Enquiry under Section 17A of the Prevention of Corruption
			<lb />
			Act,1988. I am also to request you to take expeditious
			<lb />
			steps to conduct the Vigilance Enquiry.&quot;
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			As far as the relief sought for by the petitioner is
			<lb />
			concerned, it is substantially met when the Government had
			<lb />
			ordered enquiry through a Commission who was a former Judge
			<lb />
			of this Court. On the basis of the report submitted by the
			<lb />
			Commission, the Vigilance Wing of the State had also been
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.27408/2017
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			-:8:-
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			directed to conduct investigation.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			In the light of the aforesaid factual situation, we do not
			<lb />
			think that there is any necessity to keep the matter pending as
			<lb />
			the grievance brought to the notice of the court to a certain
			<lb />
			extent had been taken care of by the Government itself while
			<lb />
			appointing a Commission of Enquiry as well as by directing a
			<lb />
			vigilance investigation to be held in the matter. Once the
			<lb />
			vigilance investigation is complete, the law shall take its own
			<lb />
			course.
			<lb />
			Therefore, we do not think that any further directions are
			<lb />
			required in the matter. Writ petition is disposed of taking note of
			<lb />
			the above facts.
			<lb />
			Sd/-
			<lb />
			A.M.SHAFFIQUE
			<lb />
			JUDGE
			<lb />
			Sd/-
			<lb />
			GOPINATH P.
			<lb />
			Rp
			<lb />
			JUDGE
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.27408/2017
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			-:9:-
			<lb />
		</page>

		<front>
			APPENDIX
			<lb />
			PETITIONER&apos;S EXHIBITS:
			<lb />
			EXHIBIT P1
			<lb />
			TRUE COPY OF THE MINUTES MEETING BY
			<lb />
			DEPARTMENT
			<lb />
			OF
			<lb />
			ECONOMIC
			<lb />
			AFFAIRS(PPP
			<lb />
			CELL) ON AUGUST 19TH , 2014.
			<lb />
			EXHIBIT P2
			<lb />
			TRUE COPY OF THE C.A G REPORT.
			<lb />
			EXHIBIT P3
			<lb />
			NEWS PAPER REPORTS ON THE C.A.G REPORT.
			<lb />
			RESPONDENT&apos;S EXHIBITS:
			<lb />
			EXHIBIT R4(A)
			<lb />
			TRUE COPY OF THE GO(MS) NO.36/2014/F&amp;PD
			<lb />
			DATED 12/05/2014.
			<lb />
			EXHIBIT R4(B)
			<lb />
			TRUE COPY OF THE REPLY DATED 03/07/2017
			<lb />
			ISSUED UNDER THE RTI ACT ALONG WITH THE
			<lb />
			ENCLOSED DOCUMENT.
			<lb />
			EXHIBIT R4(C)
			<lb />
			TRUE COPY OF THE LETTER WRITTEN BY THE
			<lb />
			4TH RESPONDENT TO THE COMPTROLLER AND
			<lb />
			AUDITOR GENERAL OF INDIA (CAG) BEARING
			<lb />
			REFERENCE
			<lb />
			NO.
			<lb />
			296/OC/17
			<lb />
			DATED
			<lb />
			09/06/2017.
			<lb />
			EXHIBIT R4(D)
			<lb />
			TRUE COPY OF THE GO(MS) NO.75/10/F&amp;PD
			<lb />
			DATED 18/10/2010.
			<lb />
			EXHIBIT R4(E)
			<lb />
			TRUE
			<lb />
			COPY
			<lb />
			OF
			<lb />
			THE
			<lb />
			GO(RT)
			<lb />
			NO.800/2010/F&amp;PD DATED 22/09/2010.
			<lb />
			EXHIBIT R4(F)
			<lb />
			TRUE COPY OF THE GO(MS) NO.26/2014/F&amp;PD
			<lb />
			DATED 31/03/2014.
			<lb />
			EXHIBIT R4(G)
			<lb />
			TRUE COPY OF THE MINUTES OF THE 23RD
			<lb />
			MEETING OF THE EMPOWERED COMMITTEE HELD
			<lb />
			ON 07/05/2015.
			<lb />
			EXHIBIT R4(H)
			<lb />
			TRUE COPY OF THE NOTE ON SELECTION
			<lb />
			PROCESS PUBLISHED IN THE WEBSITE OF
			<lb />
			VIZHINJAM INTERNATIONAL SEAPORT.
			<lb />
		</front>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) No.27408/2017
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			-:10:-
			<lb />
		</page>

		<front>
			EXHIBIT R4(I)
			<lb />
			TRUE COPY OF THE GO(MS) NO.35/2015/F&amp;PD
			<lb />
			DATED 13/07/2015.
			<lb />
			EXHIBIT R4(J)
			<lb />
			TRUE COPY OF THE ORDER DATED 03/02/2015
			<lb />
			ISSUED BY THE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA,
			<lb />
			MINISTRY OF FINANCE.
			<lb />
			EXHIBIT R4(K)
			<lb />
			TRUE
			<lb />
			COPY
			<lb />
			OF
			<lb />
			THE
			<lb />
			GO(MS()
			<lb />
			NO.15/2017/F&amp;PD DATED 18/07/2017.
			<lb />
			EXHIBIT R1(A)
			<lb />
			TRUE
			<lb />
			COPY
			<lb />
			OF
			<lb />
			THE
			<lb />
			GO(MS)
			<lb />
			NO.
			<lb />
			15/2017/F&amp;PD
			<lb />
			DATED
			<lb />
			18/07/2017
			<lb />
			APPOINTING THE COMMISSION ALONG WITH
			<lb />
			TERMS
			<lb />
			OF
			<lb />
			REFERENCE
			<lb />
			PUBLISHED
			<lb />
			ON
			<lb />
			20/07/2017.
			<lb />
			EXHIBIT R1(B)
			<lb />
			TRUE
			<lb />
			COPY
			<lb />
			OF
			<lb />
			THE
			<lb />
			GO(RT)
			<lb />
			NO.674/2017/F&amp;PD DATED 25/08/2017.
			<lb />
			EXHIBIT R1(C)
			<lb />
			TRUE COY OF THE GO(RT) NO.707/2017/F&amp;PD
			<lb />
			DATED 15/09/2017.
			<lb />
			True Copy
			<lb />
			PS to Judge
			<lb />
			Rp
		</front>


	</text>
</tei>