<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<page>
			1
			<lb />
		</page>

		<front>
			REPORTABLE
			<lb />
			IN THE SUPREME COURT OF INDIA
			<lb />
			CIVIL APPELLATE JURISDICTION
			<lb />
			CIVIL APPEAL NO. 7042 of 2019
			<lb />
			M/S LAUREATE BUILDWELL PVT. LTD.
			<lb />
			….APPELLANT (S)
			<lb />
			VERSUS
			<lb />
			CHARANJEET SINGH
			<lb />
			....RESPONDENT(S)
			<lb />
		</front>

		<body>
			ORDER
			<lb />
			S. RAVINDRA BHAT, J.
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			The appellant (hereafter called &quot;Laureate&quot; or &quot;the builder&quot;) is aggrieved by
			<lb />
			an order of the National Consumer Dispute Redressal Commission 1 (hereafter
			<lb />
			&quot;NCDRC&quot;). The respondent (hereafter &quot;the purchaser&quot;) had sought, through his
			<lb />
			complaint a direction against the builder, for refund of the consideration amount of
			<lb />
			₹1,93,70,883/-received by the latter, as consideration for sale of a flat along with
			<lb />
			interest @ 24% p.a. from the date different instalments were paid, as well as
			<lb />
			compensation and costs.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			The relevant facts are that one Ms. Madhabi Venkatraman (hereafter &quot;the
			<lb />
			original allottee&quot;) applied on 29.08.2012 for allotment of a residential flat (No. 7013,
			<lb />
			(hereafter &quot;the flat&quot;) admeasuring 4545 sq. ft., in Nectarine Tower &quot;PARX
			<lb />
			LAUREATE&quot; at Sector-108, Expressway, Noida. The flat was to be developed by
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place='footnote'>
			1
			<lb />
			In Consumer case No. 1183/2017, decided on 29-05-2019
			<lb />
			Digitally signed by
			<lb />
			Indu Marwah
			<lb />
			Date: 2021.07.22
			<lb />
			17:34:16 IST
			<lb />
			Reason:
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			2
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			the builder (Laureate). She paid the registration amount of ₹7,00,000/-. On
			<lb />
			16.10.2012, an allotment letter was issued to the original allottee, for the flat after
			<lb />
			deposit of ₹32,33,657/-out of the total sale consideration of ₹2,47,29,405/-.
			<lb />
			According to the allotment letter, the possession of the flat was to be handed over
			<lb />
			within 36 months (from the date of allotment letter) i.e., latest by 15.10.2015. The
			<lb />
			original allottee made payment to the tune of ₹1,55,89,329/-, for the first seven
			<lb />
			instalments as demanded by Laureate. On 16.02.2015, after noticing the slow pace of
			<lb />
			construction, the original allottee decided to sell the flat. The purchaser who was in
			<lb />
			search of a residential flat was approached by her through a broker. He was assured
			<lb />
			that the possession of the flat would be delivered on time, and he agreed to purchase
			<lb />
			the flat and paid an amount of 1,00,000/-as advance towards the total sale
			<lb />
			consideration of ₹1,55,89,329/-. The purchaser and the original allottee agreed that
			<lb />
			the balance amount of sale consideration would be paid on or before 15.10.2015 and
			<lb />
			further that the purchaser would pay the outstanding instalments beyond
			<lb />
			₹1,55,89,329/-directly after transfer of the flat to him. Demand letters for two
			<lb />
			instalments (Nos. 8 &amp; 9) were issued by Laureate and payment to the tune of ₹21,
			<lb />
			68,694/-was made by the original allottee.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			The purchaser alleged that possession was not delivered in October, 2015 as
			<lb />
			promised (in the allotment letter). He decided to wait for the possession and not to
			<lb />
			make any payment towards the sale; however, the original allottee insisted upon the
			<lb />
			execution of an agreement to sell and demanded payment of instalments, which she
			<lb />
			had made to the builder, stating that she could not wait any further and she would
			<lb />
			forfeit the earnest money and cancel the deal. The purchaser alleged that he made
			<lb />
			enquiries from the officials of the builder, who assured that the possession would be
			<lb />
			delivered by June 2016. Therefore, the purchaser, on 17.02.2016, entered into an
			<lb />
			agreement of sale with the original allottee, and paid an amount of ₹1,85,00,000/-.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			The original allottee on 02.04.2016, requested the builder to transfer the flat
			<lb />
			in favor of the respondent. The purchaser submitted an undertaking dated 01.04.2016
			<lb />
			duly signed and executed by him, to the builder, Laureate. Later, Laureate issued a
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			3
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			letter dated 09.05.2016 to the purchaser, confirming the payment of ₹1,93,70,883/-
			<lb />
			towards the purchase of the flat. Thereafter, the purchaser visited the site to acquaint
			<lb />
			himself with the extent of construction but he was denied entry to the construction
			<lb />
			site by the builder&apos;s employees citing security reasons and was informed that the
			<lb />
			work was in progress and possession would be delivered shortly. The purchaser
			<lb />
			alleges that he made telephonic inquiries from the office of the builder regarding
			<lb />
			possession, but unavailingly, without any result. He claims to have visited the
			<lb />
			builder&apos;s office in last week of January, 2017 and was informed that possession of
			<lb />
			the said flat could not be delivered till the end of year 2017.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			After this, the purchaser sought for refund of the amount paid, from the
			<lb />
			builder. On 08.03.2017, a legal notice was issued to the builder asking for refund of
			<lb />
			the amount of ₹1,93,70,883/-with interest @ 24% p.a. from the various dates of
			<lb />
			deposit, was sought by the purchaser, but in vain. He claims to have been shocked to
			<lb />
			receive the demand letter for the 11th instalment for ₹10,92,628/-. On refusal of the
			<lb />
			payment of instalment, the officials of the builder threatened the purchaser of
			<lb />
			cancellation and forfeiture of the amounts paid. It is in these circumstances, that the
			<lb />
			appellant approached the NCDRC, for direction to the builder to refund the entire
			<lb />
			sum of ₹1,93,70,883/-with interest at the rate of 24% from the respective dates when
			<lb />
			the instalments were paid to Laureate. In addition, ₹ 5,00,000/-as compensation and
			<lb />
			₹ 2,00,000/-as litigation expenses were sought along with other costs.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			The builder, Laureate denied the claim, stating that for the period 28.03.2013
			<lb />
			to January 2016, (i.e. 26 months), there was complete slowdown in the construction
			<lb />
			of the projects in all of NOIDA including the buildings in question, due to the order
			<lb />
			passed by National Green Tribunal (NGT) in OA/158/2013, and due to a notification
			<lb />
			issued by the Ministry of Environment, Forests and Climate Change. The original
			<lb />
			allottee was aware of the orders of the NGT, and the builder had sent several
			<lb />
			reminders for payment towards the instalments and finally issued a notice on
			<lb />
			17.10.2014 for cancellation of the Provisional Allotment of Flat No. 7013. It was
			<lb />
			alleged that in view of Clause 13(7) of the agreement neither Ms. Madhabi
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			4
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Venkatraman, the original allottee nor the purchaser-respondent who is endorsed by
			<lb />
			the original allottee was entitled to any amounts for delay in construction. It was also
			<lb />
			alleged that on 02.04.2016, the original allottee requested the builder to transfer flat
			<lb />
			No. 7013 in favour of the purchaser. The purchaser furnished an undertaking on
			<lb />
			01.04.2016 duly signed before the competent authority, which makes it clear that
			<lb />
			both the original allottee and the purchaser were aware of the order of the NGT and
			<lb />
			the delay in construction were beyond the control of the purchaser. Therefore, their
			<lb />
			right to claim compensation is construed to be waived in terms of Clause 13.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			The builder further alleged that on commencement of 18th floor and 20th
			<lb />
			floor roof slab, the 11th and 12th instalments were demanded from the Complainant
			<lb />
			and the same was not paid. Therefore, the builder had a right to cancel the allotment.
			<lb />
			It is only on account of the restrictive order dated 28.10.2013 passed by NGT on any
			<lb />
			construction within the radius of 10 kilometres from Okhla Bird Sanctuary, that the
			<lb />
			builder could not complete the project as the said project comes within the radius of
			<lb />
			10 kilometres. In view of clause 13(5), the builder was entitled for extension of time
			<lb />
			for offer of possession at such premises on account of force majeure conditions.
			<lb />
			Therefore, it is not liable to pay any compensation.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			The NCDRC, after considering the depositions of the parties, through
			<lb />
			affidavits, documentary evidence and the submissions of parties, noticed that the
			<lb />
			demand letter for the 11th instalment was dated 24.03.2017, whereas the promised
			<lb />
			date of delivery was 15.10.2015. That said letter stated that the construction stage &apos;on
			<lb />
			commencement of 18th floor roof slab&apos; of the tower had been achieved and therefore
			<lb />
			the 11th instalment was demanded to be paid. This showed that even as on
			<lb />
			24.03.2017, the construction of the said tower was incomplete. The commission
			<lb />
			considered that Receipt No. 306 dated 01.03.2016 shows that the original allottee had
			<lb />
			paid an amount of ₹5,29,000/-towards penal interest charged by the Developer at the
			<lb />
			rate of 24% per annum. The NCDRC rejected the plea that the original allottee was a
			<lb />
			defaulter. It thereafter allowed the complaint, reasoning as follows:
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			5
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			&quot;20. We find it a fit case to place reliance on the judgement of the
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Kolkata West International City Pvt. Ltd. Vs.
			<lb />
			Devasis Rudra, II (2019) CPJ 29 (SC), wherein the Hon&apos;ble Apex Court
			<lb />
			has clearly laid down that a flat purchaser cannot be made to wait
			<lb />
			indefinitely for seeking possession. Even in the instant case, though the
			<lb />
			promised date of delivery was way back in the year 2015, even as on
			<lb />
			date, the tower is far from completion.
			<lb />
			21. The Learned Counsel for the Complainant relied on the decision
			<lb />
			of this Commission dated 11.01.2019 in Manmeet Singh &amp; Anr. Vs.
			<lb />
			Unitech Hi-Tech Developers Ltd. &amp; Ors. (Consumer Complaint No.
			<lb />
			1285 of 2017), wherein this Commission has allowed refund of the
			<lb />
			principal amount with interest @ 10% p.a.
			<lb />
			22. For all the aforenoted reasons and the principal laid down by the
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Kolkata West International City Pvt. Ltd.
			<lb />
			(Supra) we are of the considered view that the Complaint be allowed in
			<lb />
			part and we direct the Developer to refund the amount deposited with
			<lb />
			the developer in respect of subject flat No. 7013 with interest @ 10%
			<lb />
			p.a. from the respective dates of deposit till the date of realisation
			<lb />
			together with the cost of ₹25,000/.&quot;
			<lb />
			Arguments of the parties
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			It is argued by Mr. Jayanth Mithras, learned senior counsel on behalf of the
			<lb />
			builder that the relief granted by NCDRC is unwarranted. Highlighting that the entire
			<lb />
			project had come to a standstill on account of an interim order by the NGT, the
			<lb />
			learned senior counsel stressed that these facts were within the knowledge of the
			<lb />
			original allottee as well as the purchaser. When they decided to purchase it in 2015, it
			<lb />
			was decided that the respondent would purchase the flat and step into the shoes of the
			<lb />
			original allottee. Learned senior counsel argued that given these circumstances, the
			<lb />
			respondent, as a prudent purchaser, could not have reasonably expected the
			<lb />
			construction to be completed till the interim orders were vacated and some time was
			<lb />
			allowed for the construction to be completed. Clearly, the purchaser was only an
			<lb />
			investor and was not interested in residing in the flat.
			<lb />
			10. Learned senior counsel submitted that barely a year after the transaction of
			<lb />
			stepping into the shoes of the original allottee -which was endorsed by the builder,
			<lb />
			the purchaser made an unreasonable demand for the refund of the entire amount. At
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			6
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			that point in time, the interim order of the NGT had been vacated. Quite naturally,
			<lb />
			therefore, the construction had started and the builder made the demand on
			<lb />
			23.04.2017 towards subsequent instalments which were not paid. Although the
			<lb />
			purchaser sent a legal notice prior to these demands, the fact remained that so long as
			<lb />
			he assumed responsibility as an allottee, he could not shy away from fulfilling the
			<lb />
			demand towards the instalments.
			<lb />
			11. Learned senior counsel argued that the purchaser could not claim the equities
			<lb />
			in the same manner that an original allottee could. In the present case, the original
			<lb />
			allottee had not paid the instalments in time and was constrained to pay penal interest
			<lb />
			-a fact noted by the NCDRC. In these circumstances, there were no equities
			<lb />
			compelling the NCDRC to grant any relief over and above a refund of compensation
			<lb />
			much less interest @ 10% from the period the deposits were made by the original
			<lb />
			allottee.
			<lb />
			12. Learned senior counsel submits that since the complainant was not the original
			<lb />
			allottee but a subsequent purchaser, he could not claim any interest. He relied upon
			<lb />
			two rulings of this Court in HUDA v. Raje Ram 2 and the recent judgment of this
			<lb />
			Court in Wing Commander Arifur Rahman Khan and Anr. v. DLF Southern Homes
			<lb />
			Pvt. Ltd. 3 . It is submitted that in both these cases, this Court had categorically ruled
			<lb />
			that when the allottee in a housing project transfers his or her rights in favour of
			<lb />
			another, such a third party cannot claim equities to the same extent as the original
			<lb />
			allottee, especially as regards a claim for interest. It was submitted by the learned
			<lb />
			senior counsel that there is a sound public policy rationale in support of such a rule
			<lb />
			which is that a subsequent purchaser is deemed to be aware of the nature of
			<lb />
			construction and the delay which occurred till the time he or she steps into the shoes
			<lb />
			of the allottee. The NCDRC overlooked these binding rulings and directed payment
			<lb />
			of interest for the entire period and clearly the respondent purchaser was not entitled
			<lb />
			to any interest at all.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place='footnote'>
			2
			<lb />
			2008 (17) SCC 407
			<lb />
			3
			<lb />
			2020 SCC Online 667 (SC)
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			7
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			13. Mr. M.L. Lahoty, learned counsel for the respondent urged this Court not to
			<lb />
			interfere with the findings and directions of the NCDRC. He highlighted that even if
			<lb />
			they were notified about the transfer by the original allottee in respect of the
			<lb />
			respondent, the builder had made demands towards penal interest, for various
			<lb />
			periods. A total amount of ₹ 5.9 lakhs was in fact paid during the period 01.03.2016
			<lb />
			to 18.04.2016. The builder was made aware of the agreement to sell when its
			<lb />
			endorsement with respect to the transfer was sought. Further, it was only after
			<lb />
			receiving the amounts towards the so-called penal interest that the endorsement letter
			<lb />
			was ultimately issued on 09.05.2016 by the builder. This clearly confirmed
			<lb />
			₹1,93,70,883/-was paid towards the flat. This endorsement letter also confirmed that
			<lb />
			the respondent purchaser would be entitled to the delivery of the flat.
			<lb />
			14. It is submitted that the purchaser had entered into an understanding and paid
			<lb />
			the amounts towards the previous instalments as well as settled the later penal
			<lb />
			interest component to the original allottee and also paid penal interest upto October
			<lb />
			2016. In these circumstances, it was not unreasonable for him to expect that project
			<lb />
			would be complete and the flat would be handed over at least in the first part of
			<lb />
			2017. However, upon visiting the site and noticing that there was practically no
			<lb />
			progress, the respondent/purchaser was constrained to move the NCDRC for the
			<lb />
			relief of direction of refunding the entire amount.
			<lb />
			15. Mr. Lahoty pointed to the findings and observations of the NCDRC which had
			<lb />
			noticed the facts that although the NGT&apos;s interim order had subsisted for a while, and
			<lb />
			the builder had taken shelter under it to say that construction could not take place, the
			<lb />
			record indicated that the builder had sought for instalments from the original allottee,
			<lb />
			including demanding penal interest. Given these facts, there were no equities in
			<lb />
			favour of the builder; it was not open to it to claim that force majeure conditions
			<lb />
			operated and prevented it from going ahead with the construction.
			<lb />
			16. It was submitted that upon the endorsement by the builder of all the
			<lb />
			transactions, and its acknowledgment, the purchaser had become entitled to seek
			<lb />
			delivery. There was no impediment in the purchaser claiming any kind of relief. Mr.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			8
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Lahoty submitted that if for instance, there were to be any defect or deficiency in
			<lb />
			service, the purchaser could not be discriminated against and an application or a
			<lb />
			plaint in that regard cannot be dismissed as not maintainable. Likewise, the mere fact
			<lb />
			that a subsequent purchaser steps into the shoes of an original allottee who might
			<lb />
			have at an earlier point of time sought allotment but because of the delay in the
			<lb />
			construction, being unable to withstand economic pressures withdrew, does not mean
			<lb />
			that the builder&apos;s default could be glossed over. Learned counsel urged that there is
			<lb />
			no rule or principle to support the judgment in Raje Ram (supra) or Wing
			<lb />
			Commander Arifur Rahman Khan and Anr. (supra) to say that subsequent purchasers
			<lb />
			should never be given the relief of interest on refunds. It was submitted that the
			<lb />
			refusal of the Court to grant relief have to be seen in the light of the peculiar
			<lb />
			circumstances of those cases.
			<lb />
			Analysis and Conclusions:
			<lb />
			17. The allotment letter dated 16.10.2012 assured the original allottee that the
			<lb />
			possession of the flat would be handed over within 36 months i.e. on or before
			<lb />
			15.10.2015. The original allotee made payment to the tune of ₹1,55,89,329/-,
			<lb />
			towards the first seven instalments as and when demanded. Apparently, the allottee
			<lb />
			due to her own compulsions could not continue to wait indefinitely for delivery of
			<lb />
			the flat, having regard to the slow pace of construction. She therefore felt compelled
			<lb />
			to sell the flat. It was then that the purchaser stepped in, and an agreement to sell
			<lb />
			was executed between the parties on 17.02.2016. The original allottee thereafter
			<lb />
			approached the builder, informing it that the purchaser had stepped into her shoes
			<lb />
			and would continue with the obligations, and was therefore entitled to possession.
			<lb />
			Significantly, the builder endorsed and even required the purchaser to execute the
			<lb />
			letter of undertaking, which he did.
			<lb />
			With this development, the builder
			<lb />
			acknowledged that the rights and entitlements of the original allottee relation to the
			<lb />
			flat were assumed by the purchaser, and signified its obligations, correspondingly to
			<lb />
			the purchaser, as the consumer.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			9
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			18. In the meanwhile, there was a slowdown in construction, apparently, on
			<lb />
			account of orders made by NGT. The builder alleged that the slowdown in
			<lb />
			construction was due to the NGT&apos;s interim orders. However, what transpired was
			<lb />
			that on 28.10.2013, the NGT imposed certain restrictions within 10 km radius of the
			<lb />
			Okhla Bird Sanctuary. The application before the NGT was disposed on 03.04.2014.
			<lb />
			Consequently, there were no directions after that date. A review application was filed
			<lb />
			before the NGT which remained pending for some time; however, even at that stage
			<lb />
			there were no interim orders requiring stoppage of construction. On 19.08.2015 the
			<lb />
			Ministry of Environment and Forests issued a notification. The appellant is unclear
			<lb />
			as to the effect of this notification; apparently, it did not impede construction; the
			<lb />
			notification was challenged. It is only on 05.07.2016, on account of an application
			<lb />
			preferred by an occupant of an adjoining area that the NGT directed the builder not
			<lb />
			to carry on with the construction. This, the builder informs in its appeal, was finally
			<lb />
			disposed of in January 2016.
			<lb />
			19. The facts set out in the preceding paragraph demonstrate that on the one hand
			<lb />
			the builder/appellant is not categorical with respect to the existence of interim orders
			<lb />
			enjoining it not to construct further. Rather, it appears that there was no construction
			<lb />
			of the project for about six months. However, despite this position, it continued to
			<lb />
			demand and received instalments. The purchaser entered the scene in 2016, waited
			<lb />
			for some time and demanded refund of the entire amount with interest from the dates
			<lb />
			that deposits were made. After receiving notice, the builder demanded further
			<lb />
			instalments. It was in this background that the purchaser approached the NCDRC
			<lb />
			successfully with the claim for refund. The claim for interest was allowed to the
			<lb />
			extent of 10% on the entire amounts deposited from the respective dates of deposits.
			<lb />
			20. The principal argument of the builder is the rights of a purchaser are not the
			<lb />
			same as an original allottee. The builder appellant cites Raje Ram and Arifur
			<lb />
			Rahman Khan (supra).In the first decision Raje Ram, this Court declined to grant
			<lb />
			interest on a refund claim made by a subsequent purchaser. The original allottee did
			<lb />
			not continue with the allotment; the statutory authority/developer HUDA re-allotted
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			10
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			the plot. The re-allottee then approached the consumer forum which directed refund
			<lb />
			with interest. This court was of the opinion that when the subsequent purchaser, i.e.
			<lb />
			the re-allottee stepped into the shoes of the original allottee, he was aware of the
			<lb />
			delay in handing over the possession which had occurred and therefore could no
			<lb />
			longer claim the time of the delay. In Arifur Rahman Khan (supra) several allottees
			<lb />
			approached the Court. This Court did not grant relief to the subsequent purchasers
			<lb />
			who stepped into the shoes of the original allottees, citing Raje Ram.
			<lb />
			21. The relevant discussion in Raje Ram is as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;14. The appellants challenged the said orders of the State Commission
			<lb />
			contending that no interest was payable. The National Consumer
			<lb />
			Disputes Redressal Commission by its non-speaking orders dated 27-8-
			<lb />
			2002, 30-9-2002 and 27-8-2002, disposed of the said revisions filed by
			<lb />
			the Development Authority, in terms of its earlier decision
			<lb />
			in HUDA v. Darsh Kumar [ RP No. 1197 of 1998 decided on 31-8-2001
			<lb />
			(NC)] by merely observing that it had upheld the award of interest up to
			<lb />
			18% per annum in similar circumstances. The National Commission did
			<lb />
			not refer to or consider the facts of these cases. The said orders are
			<lb />
			challenged in these appeals by special leave. The common issue in all
			<lb />
			these cases is whether interest could have been awarded against the
			<lb />
			appellant, and if so whether the rate of interest is excessive.
			<lb />
			15. The decision of the National Commission in Darsh Kumar [ RP No.
			<lb />
			1197 of 1998 decided on 31-8-2001 (NC)] , followed in the impugned
			<lb />
			orders, did not find favour of this Court in HUDA v. Darsh
			<lb />
			Kumar [(2005) 9 SCC 449] . This Court observed that (at SCC p. 451,
			<lb />
			para 7) where possession is given at the old rate, the party has got the
			<lb />
			benefit of escalation in price of land, and therefore, there cannot and
			<lb />
			should not be award of interest on the amounts paid by the allottee on
			<lb />
			the ground of delay in allotment. On the special facts of that case, this
			<lb />
			Court however awarded compensation for harassment/mental agony.
			<lb />
			16. The respondents in the three appeals are not the original allottees.
			<lb />
			They are re-allottees to whom reallotment was made by the appellant in
			<lb />
			the years 1994, 1997 and 1996 respectively. They were aware, when the
			<lb />
			plots were reallotted to them, that there was delay (either in forming the
			<lb />
			layout itself or delay in delivering the allotted plot on account of
			<lb />
			encroachment, etc). In spite of it, they took reallotment. Their cases
			<lb />
			cannot be compared to the cases of the original allottees who were
			<lb />
			made to wait for a decade or more for delivery and thus put to mental
			<lb />
			agony and harassment. They were aware that time for performance was
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			11
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			not stipulated as the essence of the contract and the original allottees
			<lb />
			had accepted the delay.&quot;
			<lb />
			22. In Arifur Rahman Khan, the court observed as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;43. Similarly, the three appellants who have transferred their title,
			<lb />
			right and interest in the apartments would not be entitled to the benefit
			<lb />
			of the present order since they have sold their interest in the apartments
			<lb />
			to third parties. The written submissions which have been filed before
			<lb />
			this Court indicate that &quot;the two buyers stepped into the shoes of the
			<lb />
			first buyers&quot; as a result of the assignment of rights and liabilities by the
			<lb />
			first buyer in favour of the second buyer. In HUDA v. Raje
			<lb />
			Ram [HUDA v. Raje Ram, (2008) 17 SCC 407 : (2009) 5 SCC (Civ)
			<lb />
			889] , this Court while holding that a claim of compensation for delayed
			<lb />
			possession by subsequent transferees is unsustainable, observed that:
			<lb />
			(SCC p. 410, para 16)
			<lb />
			&quot;16. The respondents in the three appeals are not the
			<lb />
			original allottees. They are re-allottees to whom
			<lb />
			reallotment was made by the appellant in the years 1994,
			<lb />
			1997 and 1996 respectively. They were aware, when the
			<lb />
			plots were reallotted to them, that there was delay (either
			<lb />
			in forming the layout itself or delay in delivering the
			<lb />
			allotted plot on account of encroachment, etc.). In spite of
			<lb />
			it, they took reallotment. Their cases cannot be compared
			<lb />
			to the cases of the original allottees who were made to
			<lb />
			wait for a decade or more for delivery and thus put to
			<lb />
			mental agony and harassment. They were aware that time
			<lb />
			for performance was not stipulated as the essence of the
			<lb />
			contract and the original allottees had accepted the
			<lb />
			delay.&quot;
			<lb />
			Even if the three appellants who had transferred their interest in the
			<lb />
			apartments had continued to agitate on the issue of delay of
			<lb />
			possession, we are not inclined to accept the submission that the
			<lb />
			subsequent transferees can step into the shoes of the original buyer for
			<lb />
			the purpose of benefiting from this order. The subsequent transferees
			<lb />
			in spite of being aware of the delay in delivery of possession the flats,
			<lb />
			had purchased the interest in the apartments from the original buyers.
			<lb />
			Further, it cannot be said that the subsequent transferees suffered any
			<lb />
			agony and harassment comparable to that of the first buyers, as a
			<lb />
			result of the delay in the delivery of possession in order to be entitled
			<lb />
			to compensation.&quot;
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			12
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			23. The builder does not deny that upon issuance of the endorsement letter, the
			<lb />
			purchaser not only stepped into the shoes of the original allottee but also became
			<lb />
			entitled to receive possession of the flat. There is no denial that the purchaser fulfils
			<lb />
			the description of the complainant/ consumer and is entitled to move any forum
			<lb />
			under the Consumer Protection Act for any deficiency in service. The question then
			<lb />
			is whether a subsequent purchaser is not entitled to similar treatment as the original
			<lb />
			allottee, and can be denied relief which otherwise the original allottee would have
			<lb />
			been entitled to, had she or he continued with the arrangement. An individual such
			<lb />
			as the original allottee, enters into an agreement to purchase the flat in an on-going
			<lb />
			project where delivery is promised. The terms of the agreement as well as the
			<lb />
			assurance by the builder are that the flat would be made available within a time-
			<lb />
			frame. It is commonplace that in a large number of such transactions, allottees are
			<lb />
			not able to finance the flat but seek advances and funds from banks or financial
			<lb />
			institutions, to which they mortgage the property. The mortgage pay-outs start
			<lb />
			initially after an agreed period, commencing in a span of about 15 to 24 months after
			<lb />
			the agreement. This would mean that in most cases, allottees start repaying the bank
			<lb />
			or financial institutions with instalments (mostly equated monthly instalments)
			<lb />
			towards the principal and the interest spread over a period of time, even before the
			<lb />
			flats are ready. If these facts are taken into consideration, prolongation of the project
			<lb />
			would involve serious economic repercussions upon such original allottees who are
			<lb />
			on the one hand compelled to pay instalments and, in addition, quite often -if she or
			<lb />
			he is in want of a house -also pay monthly rents. Such burdens become almost
			<lb />
			intolerable. It is at this point that an indefinite wait is impossible and allottees prefer
			<lb />
			to find purchasers who might step into their shoes. That such purchasers take over
			<lb />
			the obligations of the original allottee -either to pay the balance instalments or to
			<lb />
			wait for sometime, would not per se exclude them from the description of a
			<lb />
			consumer. All that then happens is that the consumer forum or commission -or
			<lb />
			even courts have to examine the relative equities having regard to the time frame in
			<lb />
			each case.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			13
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			24. In a larger five judge bench ruling in Economic Transport Organization v.
			<lb />
			Charan Spinning Mills (P) Ltd 4 , the question was whether an insurer, who honours
			<lb />
			its contract, and pays the insured the agreed money, in the event of an insurable
			<lb />
			incident such as an accident, can maintain a consumer complaint against the carrier,
			<lb />
			who is responsible for the accident. This court held that such complaints are not
			<lb />
			barred:
			<lb />
			&quot;29. In all three types of subrogation, the insurer can sue the
			<lb />
			wrongdoer in the name of the assured. This means that the insurer
			<lb />
			requests the assured to file the suit/complaint and has the option of
			<lb />
			joining as co-plaintiff. Alternatively, the insurer can obtain a
			<lb />
			special power of attorney from the assured and then to sue the
			<lb />
			wrongdoer in the name of the assured as his attorney.
			<lb />
			******************
			<lb />
			**************
			<lb />
			37. Whether the document executed by the assured in favour of the
			<lb />
			insurer is a subrogation simpliciter, or a subrogation-cum-
			<lb />
			assignment is relevant only in a dispute between the assured and
			<lb />
			the insurer. It may not be relevant for deciding the maintainability
			<lb />
			of a complaint under the Act. If the complaint is filed by the assured
			<lb />
			(who is the consumer), or by the assured represented by the insurer
			<lb />
			as its attorney holder, or by the assured and the insurer jointly as
			<lb />
			complainants, the complaint will be maintainable, if the presence of
			<lb />
			insurer is explained as being a subrogee. Whether the amount
			<lb />
			claimed is the total loss or only the amount for which the claim was
			<lb />
			settled would make no difference for the maintainability of the
			<lb />
			complaint, so long as the consumer is the complainant (either
			<lb />
			personally or represented by its attorney-holder) or is a co-
			<lb />
			complainant along with his subrogee.
			<lb />
			38. On the other hand, if the assured (who is the consumer) is not
			<lb />
			the complainant, and the insurer alone files the complaint in its own
			<lb />
			name, the complaint will not be maintainable, as the insurer is not a
			<lb />
			&quot;consumer&quot;, nor a person who answers the definition of
			<lb />
			&quot;complainant&quot; under the Act. The fact that it seeks to recover from
			<lb />
			the wrongdoer (service provider) only the amount paid to the
			<lb />
			assured and not any amount in excess of what was paid to the
			<lb />
			assured will also not make any difference, if the assured-consignor
			<lb />
			is not the complainant or co-complainant. The complaint will not be
			<lb />
			maintainable unless the requirements of the Act are fulfilled. The
			<lb />
			remedy under the Act being summary in nature, once the consumer
			<lb />
			is the complainant or is a co-complainant, it will not be necessary
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			4 (2010) 4 SCC 114
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			14
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			for the Consumer Forum to probe the exact nature of relationship
			<lb />
			between the consumer (assured) and the insurer, in a complaint
			<lb />
			against the service provider.
			<lb />
			******************
			<lb />
			**************
			<lb />
			40. If in a summary proceedings by a consumer against a service
			<lb />
			provider, the insurer is added as a co-complainant or if the insurer
			<lb />
			represents the consumer as a power-of-attorney, there is no need to
			<lb />
			examine the nature of rights inter se between the consumer and his
			<lb />
			insurer. When the complaint is by the consignor-consumer, with or
			<lb />
			without the insurer as a co-complainant, the service provider
			<lb />
			cannot require the Consumer Forum to consider the nature of
			<lb />
			relationship between the assured and the insurer or the nature and
			<lb />
			true purport of the document produced as a letter of subrogation. A
			<lb />
			wrongdoer cannot side-track the issue before the Consumer Forum.
			<lb />
			Once the &quot;consumer&quot;, that is the assured, is the complainant, the
			<lb />
			complaint will be maintainable subject to fulfilment of the
			<lb />
			requirements of the Act.&quot;
			<lb />
			25. In another decision, Canara Bank v. United India Insurance Co. Ltd. 5 the issue
			<lb />
			which this court had to consider was whether the insurer could repudiate liability in
			<lb />
			respect of a fire which destroyed farm produce kept in a cold storage, when the
			<lb />
			farmers had no privity with the insurer, but with the cold storage, and who availed
			<lb />
			credit on the security of the crop. The court held as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;28. Taking the issue of privity of contract, we are of the considered
			<lb />
			view that as far as the Act is concerned, it is not necessary that there
			<lb />
			should be privity of contract between the Insurance Company and the
			<lb />
			claimants. The definition of &quot;consumer&quot; under Section 2(d) quoted
			<lb />
			hereinabove is in two parts. Sub-clause (i) of Section 2(1)(d) deals with
			<lb />
			a person who buys any goods and includes any user of such goods other
			<lb />
			than the person who buys such goods as long as the use is made with the
			<lb />
			approval of such person. Therefore, the definition of consumer even in
			<lb />
			the first part not only includes the person who has purchased but
			<lb />
			includes any user of the goods so long as such user is made with the
			<lb />
			approval of the person who has purchased the goods. As far as the
			<lb />
			definition of &quot;consumer&quot; in relation to hiring or availing of services is
			<lb />
			concerned, the definition, in our view, is much wider. In this part of the
			<lb />
			section, consumer includes not only the person who has hired or availed
			<lb />
			of the services but also includes any beneficiary of such services.
			<lb />
			Therefore, an insured could be a person who hires or avails of the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place='footnote'>
			5
			<lb />
			(2020) 3 SCC 455
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			15
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			services of the Insurance Company but there could be many other
			<lb />
			persons who could be the beneficiaries of the services. It is not
			<lb />
			necessary that those beneficiaries should be parties to the contract of
			<lb />
			insurance. They are the consumers not because they are parties to the
			<lb />
			contract of insurance but because they are the beneficiaries of the policy
			<lb />
			taken out by the insured.
			<lb />
			29. The definition of &quot;consumer&quot; under the Act is very wide and it
			<lb />
			includes beneficiaries who can take benefit of the insurance availed by
			<lb />
			the insured. As far as the present case is concerned, under the tripartite
			<lb />
			agreement entered between the Bank, the cold store and the farmers, the
			<lb />
			stock of the farmers was hypothecated as security with the Bank and the
			<lb />
			Bank had insisted that the said stock should be insured with a view to
			<lb />
			safeguard its interest..&quot;
			<lb />
			26. If one also considers the broad objective of the Consumer Protection Act,
			<lb />
			which is to provide for better protection of the interests of consumers and for that
			<lb />
			purpose, provide for the establishment of Consumer Councils and other authorities
			<lb />
			for the settlement of consumer disputes and for matters connected therewith, as
			<lb />
			evident from the Statement of Objects and Reasons of the Act. The Statement further
			<lb />
			seeks inter alia to promote and protect the rights of consumers such as-
			<lb />
			&quot;(a) The right to be protected against marketing of goods which are
			<lb />
			hazardous to life and property;
			<lb />
			(b) the right to be informed about the quality, quantity, potency, purity,
			<lb />
			standard and price of goods to protect the consumer against unfair
			<lb />
			trade practices;
			<lb />
			(c) the right to be assured, wherever possible, access to variety of goods
			<lb />
			at competitive prices;
			<lb />
			(d) the right to be heard and to be assured that consumers&apos; interests will
			<lb />
			receive due consideration at appropriate forums;
			<lb />
			(e) the right to seek redressal against unfair trade practice or
			<lb />
			unscrupulous exploitation of consumers; and
			<lb />
			(f) right to consumer education.&quot;
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			16
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			27. In Lucknow Development Authority v. M.K. Gupta 6 this Court held:
			<lb />
			&quot;The importance of the Act lies in promoting welfare of the society by
			<lb />
			enabling the consumer to participate directly in the market economy. It
			<lb />
			attempts to remove the helplessness of a consumer which he faces
			<lb />
			against powerful business, described as, &apos;a network of rackets&apos; or a
			<lb />
			society in which, &apos;producers have secured power&apos; to &apos;rob the rest&apos; and
			<lb />
			the might of public bodies which are degenerating into storehouses of
			<lb />
			inaction where papers do not move from one desk to another as a matter
			<lb />
			of duty and responsibility but for extraneous consideration leaving the
			<lb />
			common man helpless, bewildered and shocked.&quot;
			<lb />
			28. It was further held that
			<lb />
			&quot;The Act thus aims to protect the economic interest of a consumer as
			<lb />
			understood in commercial sense as a purchaser of goods and in the
			<lb />
			larger sense of user of services. … It is a milestone in history of socio-
			<lb />
			economic legislation and is directed towards achieving public benefit.&quot;
			<lb />
			29. This court has further observed in State of Karnataka v. Vishwabharathi
			<lb />
			House Building Coop. Society, 7 that (the) &quot;provisions of the said Act are required to
			<lb />
			be interpreted as broadly as possible. It has jurisdiction to entertain a complaint
			<lb />
			despite the fact that other forums/courts would also have jurisdiction to adjudicate
			<lb />
			upon the lis&quot; 8
			<lb />
			30. It is therefore evident that the Consumer Protection Act, 1986 was conceived
			<lb />
			as a legislation to address complaints of consumers (an expression defined and
			<lb />
			interpreted widely) and provide a forum for their quick redressal, and, furthermore,
			<lb />
			wherever third parties have claimed relief, technicalities have been brushed aside
			<lb />
			consistently, by this court. Thus, even after an original consumer is indemnified for a
			<lb />
			fire accident, the insurer can maintain a complaint against the carrier/service
			<lb />
			provider, and claim damages (of course along with the insured party). Likewise,
			<lb />
			absence of privity of contract is not a bar for maintaining a complaint against a
			<lb />
			service provider, by a third party who suffers an incident, which is otherwise covered
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place='footnote'>
			6 (1994) 1 SCC 243
			<lb />
			7
			<lb />
			(2003) 2 SCC 412
			<lb />
			8
			<lb />
			This court also relied on Fair Air Engineers (P) Ltd. v. N.K. Modi [(1996) 6 SCC 385] and Satpal
			<lb />
			Mohindra v. Surindra Timber Stores [(1999) 5 SCC 696
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			17
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			by an agreement. This court has also ruled, recently 9 that proceedings initiated by
			<lb />
			complainants and resultant actions including of the NCDRC are fully saved by
			<lb />
			provisions of the Real Estate Regulatory Authority Act, 2019.
			<lb />
			31. In view of these considerations, this court is of the opinion that the per se bar
			<lb />
			to the relief of interest on refund, enunciated by the decision in Raje Ram (supra)
			<lb />
			which was applied in Wg. Commander Arifur Rehman (supra) cannot be considered
			<lb />
			good law. The nature and extent of relief, to which a subsequent purchaser can be
			<lb />
			entitled to, would be fact dependent. However, it cannot be said that a subsequent
			<lb />
			purchaser who steps into the shoes of an original allottee of a housing project in
			<lb />
			which the builder has not honoured its commitment to deliver the flat within a
			<lb />
			stipulated time, cannot expect any -even reasonable time, for the performance of the
			<lb />
			builder&apos;s obligation. Such a conclusion would be arbitrary, given that there may be a
			<lb />
			large number-possibly thousands of flat buyers, waiting for their promised flats or
			<lb />
			residences; they surely would be entitled to all reliefs under the Act. In such case, a
			<lb />
			purchaser who no doubt enters the picture later surely belongs to the same class.
			<lb />
			Further, the purchaser agrees to buy the flat with a reasonable expectation that
			<lb />
			delivery of possession would be in accordance within the bounds of the delayed
			<lb />
			timeline that he has knowledge of, at the time of purchase of the flat. Therefore, in
			<lb />
			the event the purchaser claims refund, on an assessment that he too can (like the
			<lb />
			original allottee) no longer wait, and face intolerable burdens, the equities would
			<lb />
			have to be moulded. It would no doubt be fair to assume that the purchaser had
			<lb />
			knowledge of the delay. However, to attribute knowledge that such delay would
			<lb />
			continue indefinitely, based on an a priori assumption, would not be justified. The
			<lb />
			equities, in the opinion of this court, can properly be moulded by directing refund of
			<lb />
			the principal amounts, with interest @ 9% per annum from the date the builder
			<lb />
			acquired knowledge of the transfer, or acknowledged it.
			<lb />
			32. In the present case, there is material on the record suggestive of the
			<lb />
			circumstance that even as on the date of presentation of the present appeal, the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			Imperia Structures Ltd. v. Anil Patni, (2020) 10 SCC 783
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			18
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			occupancy certificate was not forthcoming. In these circumstances, given that the
			<lb />
			purchaser/respondent had stepped into the shoes of the original allottee, and
			<lb />
			intimated Laureate about this fact in April 2016, the interests of justice demand that
			<lb />
			interest at least from that date should be granted, in favour of the respondent. The
			<lb />
			directions of the NCDRC are accordingly modified in the above terms.
			<lb />
			33. The impugned order of the NCDRC is modified in the above terms; the appeal
			<lb />
			is partly allowed. There shall be no order on costs.
			<lb />
			……………………………….J
			<lb />
			[UDAY UMESH LALIT]
			<lb />
			……...........................................J
			<lb />
			[HEMANT GUPTA]
			<lb />
			……...........................................J
			<lb />
			[S. RAVINDRA BHAT]
			<lb />
			New Delhi
			<lb />
			July 22,2021
		</body>


	</text>
</tei>