<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			W.P.(C) No. 8736/2016
			<lb />
			Page 1 of 5
			<lb />
			$~20
			<lb />
			*
			<lb />
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF DELHI AT NEW DELHI
			<lb />
			%
			<lb />
			Judgment delivered on: 29.11.2016
			<lb />
			+
			<lb />
			W.P.(C) 8736/2016 &amp; CM No.35837/2016
			<lb />
			S A INFRASTRUCTURE CONSULTANTS PVT TLD
			<lb />
			...
			<lb />
			Petitioner
			<lb />
			versus
			<lb />
			NATIONAL HIGHWAY AUTHORITY OF INDIA
			<lb />
			... Respondent
			<lb />
			Advocates who appeared in this case:-
			<lb />
			For the Petitioner
			<lb />
			: Mr Joy Basu, Sr Advocate with Mr Alok Agarwal,
			<lb />
			Mr Sudhir Mishra, Ms Ritwika Nanda and Mr Abhinav
			<lb />
			For the Respondent : Mr S. Nanda Kumar, Mr Parivesh Singh, Mr M.S. Saran
			<lb />
			Kumar and Mr Prateek Gupta
			<lb />
		</front>

		<body>
			CORAM:-
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR JUSTICE BADAR DURREZ AHMED
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR JUSTICE JAYANT NATH
			<lb />
			JUDGMENT
			<lb />
			BADAR DURREZ AHMED, J (ORAL)
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			This writ petition has been filed in respect of the Request for
			<lb />
			Proposal (RFP) dated 22.02.2016 as also the RFP dated 09.09.2016
			<lb />
			pertaining to the project -Independent Engineer Services for Six-Laning
			<lb />
			of Vijaywada-Gundugolanu Section of NH-5 from km 1076.48 to km
			<lb />
			1022.48 including 6-lane Hanuman Junction bypass (length 6.72 km) and
			<lb />
			4-lane Vijaywada bypass (length-47.88 km) [Total Length: 103.59 km] in
			<lb />
			the State of Andhra Pradesh under NHDP Phase V to be executed in BOT
			<lb />
			(Toll) mode on DBFOT basis.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.(C) No. 8736/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 2 of 5
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			2.
			<lb />
			Initially, the RFP dated 22.02.2016 had been issued. Several
			<lb />
			parties had participated, including the present petitioner. The petitioner
			<lb />
			was found to be H-1 on 14.02.2016. Thereafter, as per the terms of the
			<lb />
			RFP document, the petitioner was liable to be called for further
			<lb />
			negotiations.
			<lb />
			The negotiation process started on 20.06.2016 and
			<lb />
			concluded on 08.07.2016. The validity period of the proposal was to be
			<lb />
			120 days from the last date of submission of the bids. In the present case,
			<lb />
			this translated to the validity being upto and including 24.07.2016.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			The petitioner is aggrieved by the fact that despite the petitioner
			<lb />
			being H-1 and the negotiations having concluded on 08.07.2016, no letter
			<lb />
			of award was issued to it and the respondents even allowed the date of
			<lb />
			24.07.2016 to pass by. Instead, the respondents took the step of issuing a
			<lb />
			fresh Request for Proposal on 09.09.2016 and that is why the petitioner
			<lb />
			has sought the quashing of the Request for Proposal dated 09.09.2016 as
			<lb />
			also for issuance of the letter of award in respect of the Request for
			<lb />
			Proposal dated 22.02.2016.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			The respondents have taken a stand on two points. The first point
			<lb />
			being that there is an opinion of the Chief General Manager through letter
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.(C) No. 8736/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 3 of 5
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			dated 11.07.2016 which would disqualify the petitioner. However, we
			<lb />
			may note that this ground is no longer available to the respondent in view
			<lb />
			of our judgment in S. A. Infrastructure Consultants Pvt. Ltd v. National
			<lb />
			Highway Authority of India: [WP(C) 7214/2016, decided on
			<lb />
			30.08.2016]. Paragraph 17 of the said decision is relevant and the same
			<lb />
			reads under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;17. After hearing counsel for the parties, we are of the view
			<lb />
			that the course of action taken by the respondents insofar as
			<lb />
			the petitioner is concerned cannot be accepted. There are
			<lb />
			several reasons for this. First of all, there has been no
			<lb />
			determination on the show cause notices which were issued to
			<lb />
			inter alia the petitioner. Thus, there is no conclusive finding
			<lb />
			with regard to the four certificates of work experience
			<lb />
			submitted by Nicholas O&apos; Dwyer Limited were alleged to be
			<lb />
			false or fabricated. Apart from this, there is no finding that
			<lb />
			there was any complicity on the part of the petitioner. The
			<lb />
			respondent should have taken a final decision in the matter
			<lb />
			and if and only if there was a finding against the petitioner
			<lb />
			could the respondent have taken the decision to exclude the
			<lb />
			petitioner from the stage of opening of financial bids. The
			<lb />
			second reason is that we get the impression that the
			<lb />
			respondent was bent upon excluding the petitioner from the
			<lb />
			stage of opening of financial bids and that is why it went on
			<lb />
			seeking opinions after the first two opinions were against the
			<lb />
			course of action which they have taken. We are of the view
			<lb />
			that the first two opinions given by the Vigilance Department
			<lb />
			of NHAI in the first instance and by the legal consulting firm
			<lb />
			of NHAI were correct and sufficient to enable the respondent
			<lb />
			to open the financial bid of the petitioner. The respondent
			<lb />
			ought to have followed that course of action and permitted the
			<lb />
			petitioner to participate in the second stage i.e., opening of the
			<lb />
			financial bids yet, it persisted and sought further opinion from
			<lb />
			a Senior Government Standing Counsel and furthermore from
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.(C) No. 8736/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 4 of 5
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			the CGM (Legal), NHAI. We do not understand as to how
			<lb />
			the CGM (Legal) could have given an opinion that the
			<lb />
			petitioner had used fraudulent means / misrepresented in the
			<lb />
			NHAI projects and that therefore the petitioner should not be
			<lb />
			entertained and be debarred from future projects also till he
			<lb />
			conclusively proves his bona fides with documents. This
			<lb />
			understanding of the law is completely contrary to what it
			<lb />
			actually is. Once show cause notices had been issued to the
			<lb />
			petitioner, unless they were taken to their logical end, there
			<lb />
			could not be any finding against the petitioner. Furthermore,
			<lb />
			we do not know how the CGM (Legal), NHAI could have
			<lb />
			given an opinion that the petitioner be debarred from future
			<lb />
			projects without even considering petitioner&apos;s replies to the
			<lb />
			show cause notices. This would clearly militate against the
			<lb />
			principles of natural justice. Even the opinion given by the
			<lb />
			Senior Central Government Standing Counsel to the effect
			<lb />
			that it is always advisable that during the pendency of enquiry
			<lb />
			the financial bids of the company should not be opened is
			<lb />
			erroneous and contrary to law. Thirdly, we do not see as to
			<lb />
			why the respondents did not take heed of the earlier two
			<lb />
			opinions and sought to rely on the latter two opinions which
			<lb />
			we have already indicated are contrary to settled legal
			<lb />
			principles.&quot;
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			The Second point that has been taken by the learned counsel for the
			<lb />
			respondent (NHAI) is that the letter of award could not be issued because
			<lb />
			the validity period of the proposal submitted by the petitioner had expired
			<lb />
			on 24.07.2016. We do not see as to how this stand can be taken by the
			<lb />
			respondent, particularly because the negotiations ended on 08.07.2016 and
			<lb />
			there was enough time for issuing the letter of award by 24.07.2016. In
			<lb />
			any event, to obviate any controversy, the learned counsel for the
			<lb />
			petitioner, on instructions, states that there is no difficulty in extending the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.(C) No. 8736/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 5 of 5
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			validity period of the proposal. We are also of the view that the validity
			<lb />
			period of the proposal is for the benefit of the bidder / proposer in order to
			<lb />
			prevent the respondent from endlessly delaying the conclusion of the bid
			<lb />
			process. In these circumstances, we feel that the respondent was wrong in
			<lb />
			not issuing the letter of award to the petitioner despite the petitioner
			<lb />
			having been found to be H-1 and the negotiations also having concluded
			<lb />
			on 08.07.2016.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			Consequently, as a first step, the Request for Proposal dated
			<lb />
			09.09.2016 is quashed. Secondly, the respondent is directed to issue the
			<lb />
			letter of award to the petitioner within a period of 60 days. The petitioner
			<lb />
			shall, within a week, send a communication to the respondent extending
			<lb />
			the validity period of the proposal for 60 days from today with effect from
			<lb />
			24.07.2016.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			The writ petition is allowed as above. There shall be no order as to
			<lb />
			costs.
			<lb />
			BADAR DURREZ AHMED, J
			<lb />
			JAYANT NATH, J
			<lb />
			NOVEMBER 29, 2016
			<lb />
			dutt
		</body>


	</text>
</tei>