<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF HIMACHAL PRADESH AT SHIMLA
			<lb />
			ON THE 5 th DAY OF MARCH, 2022
			<lb />
			BEFORE
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MS. JUSTICE JYOTSNA REWAL DUA
			<lb />
			CIVIL MISC. PETITION MAIN (ORIGINAL) No.33 of 2022
			<lb />
			Between:-
			<lb />
			1. SMT. RAMA ALIAS RITA DEVI
			<lb />
			AGE 75 YEARS,
			<lb />
			W/O SH. RANJEET SINGH,
			<lb />
			R/O NAYA BAZAAR,
			<lb />
			OPPOSITE MAIN GATE OF
			<lb />
			NAHAN FOUNDARY, DISTRICT SIRMAUR, HP
			<lb />
			2. BHANU,
			<lb />
			AGE 44 YEARS,
			<lb />
			S/O SH. RANJEET SINGH,
			<lb />
			R/O NAYA BAZAAR,
			<lb />
			OPPOSITE MAIN GATE OF
			<lb />
			NAHAN FOUNDARY, DISTRICT SIRMAUR, HP
			<lb />
			…...PETITIONERS
			<lb />
			(BY SH. KARAN SINGH KANWAR, ADVOCATE)
			<lb />
			AND
			<lb />
			1. ASHWANI KUMAR,
			<lb />
			S/O LATE SH. SARWAN SINGH,
			<lb />
			AGED 66 YEARS,
			<lb />
			R/O NEAR DELHI GATE, NAHAN,
			<lb />
			DISTRICT SIRMAUR, H.P.
			<lb />
			2. SMT. KAMLESH THAKUR,
			<lb />
			W/O LATE SH. ANIL KUMAR,
			<lb />
			AGED 56 YEARS,
			<lb />
			R/O NEAR DELHI GATE, NAHAN,
			<lb />
			DISTRICT SIRMAUR, H.P.
			<lb />
			3. KITTY THAKUR,
			<lb />
			D/O LATE SH. ANIL KUMAR,
			<lb />
			AGED 29 YEARS,
			<lb />
			
		</front>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:14 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
		</front>

		<page>
			2
			<lb />
		</page>

		<front>
			R/O NEAR DELHI GATE, NAHAN,
			<lb />
			DISTRICT SIRMAUR, H.P.
			<lb />
			4. RAVISH KUMAR,
			<lb />
			S/O LATE SH. ANIL KUMAR,
			<lb />
			AGED 26 YEARS,
			<lb />
			R/O NEAR DELHI GATE, NAHAN,
			<lb />
			DISTRICT SIRMAUR, H.P.
			<lb />
			5. ARUSHI BANSAL,
			<lb />
			AGED 24 YEARS,
			<lb />
			D/O LATE SH. ANIL KUMAR,
			<lb />
			R/O CHOTTA CHOWK, NAHAN,
			<lb />
			DISTRICT SIRMAUR, H.P.
			<lb />
			(W/O SH. AMAN BANSAL,
			<lb />
			S/O SH. PARVEEN KUMAR
			<lb />
			……RESPONDENTS/PLAINTIFFS
			<lb />
			6. SMT. ARUNA
			<lb />
			W/O LATE SH. KISHAN SINGH,
			<lb />
			S/O SH. RATTAN SINGH,
			<lb />
			R/O NAYA BAZAAR,
			<lb />
			OPPOSITE MAIN GATE OF NAHAN
			<lb />
			FOUNDARY, DISTRICT SIRMAUR, H.P.
			<lb />
			7. SANJAY THAKUR ALIAS SANJU,
			<lb />
			S/O SH. KISHAN SINGH,
			<lb />
			S/O SH. RATTAN SINGH,
			<lb />
			R/O NAYA BAZAAR,
			<lb />
			OPPOSITE MAIN GATE OF NAHAN
			<lb />
			FOUNDARY, DISTRICT SIRMAUR, H.P.
			<lb />
			8. AMIT THAKUR ALIAS PINTU,
			<lb />
			S/O SH. KISHAN SINGH,
			<lb />
			S/O SH. RATTAN SINGH,
			<lb />
			R/O NAYA BAZAAR,
			<lb />
			OPPOSITE MAIN GATE OF NAHAN
			<lb />
			FOUNDARY, DISTRICT SIRMAUR, H.P.
			<lb />
			9. SMT. KRISHNA THAKUR,
			<lb />
			W/O SH. SHER SINGH,
			<lb />
			S/O SH. RATTAN SINGH,
			<lb />
			R/O NAYA BAZAAR,
			<lb />
			
		</front>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:14 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
		</front>

		<page>
			3
			<lb />
		</page>

		<front>
			OPPOSITE MAIN GATE OF NAHAN
			<lb />
			FOUNDARY, DISTRICT SIRMAUR, H.P.
			<lb />
			…...PROFORMA RESPONDENTS/
			<lb />
			DEFENDANTS 3 TO 6
			<lb />
			(SH. ASHOK K. TYAGI, ADVOCATE,
			<lb />
			FOR R-1 TO R-5)
			<lb />
			Whether approved for reporting? 1 Yes.
			<lb />
			</front>
		<body>
			This petition coming on for admission this day, the
			<lb />
			Court passed the following:
			<lb />
			O R D E R
			<lb />
			Whether notwithstanding the pendency of an
			<lb />
			application under Order 7 Rule 11 of the Code of Civil
			<lb />
			Procedure (in short &apos;CPC&apos;) moved by the defendant about
			<lb />
			two years after the institution of the suit, can he be directed
			<lb />
			to file written statement as last opportunity, is the point
			<lb />
			involved in the present petition.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Facts:-
			<lb />
			2(i).
			<lb />
			A civil suit was filed by respondents No.1 to 5
			<lb />
			for possession and mandatory injunction on the basis of
			<lb />
			title against six defendants. The suit was filed in December,
			<lb />
			2019. The case status document produced by learned
			<lb />
			counsel for respondents No.1 to 5 during hearing of the
			<lb />
			case gives the impression that the defendants were served
			<lb />
			in the suit by April, 2020. This has not been disputed by
			<lb />
			1 Whether reporters of print and electronic media may be allowed to see the order?
			<lb />
			</body>

			<note place="footnote">
				::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:14 :::CIS
			<lb />
			</note>
		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
		</front>

		<page>
			4
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			learned counsel for the petitioners. First date given for filing
			<lb />
			the written statement as per the case status document was
			<lb />
			09.04.2020. The matter was thereafter listed before the
			<lb />
			learned
			<lb />
			Trial
			<lb />
			Court
			<lb />
			on
			<lb />
			19.06.2020,
			<lb />
			22.09.2020,
			<lb />
			10.11.2020, 06.01.2021 and 22.03.2021 for filing of written
			<lb />
			statement. The case was thereafter fixed for proper orders
			<lb />
			on 06.05.2021 and 12.07.2021. Perhaps on account of
			<lb />
			COVID-19 pandemic, the matter could not be taken up and
			<lb />
			was fixed on 21.08.2021 for the purpose of service. It was
			<lb />
			again posted for filing of written statement on 01.11.2021.
			<lb />
			2(ii).
			<lb />
			On 01.11.2021, instead of filing the written
			<lb />
			statement, defendants No.1 and 2 (petitioners herein)
			<lb />
			moved an application under Order 7 Rule 11 read with
			<lb />
			Section 151 CPC for rejection of plaint. The rejection was
			<lb />
			sought on the ground that the suit filed by the plaintiffs
			<lb />
			was undervalued for the purposes of court fees and
			<lb />
			jurisdiction. That the plaintiff had deliberately not paid the
			<lb />
			requisite court fees in terms of Section 7(5)(e) of the
			<lb />
			Himachal Pradesh Court Fees Act, 1968. It was pleaded
			<lb />
			that the learned Trial Court lacked pecuniary jurisdiction to
			<lb />
			entertain and try the suit.
			<lb />
			2(iii).
			<lb />
			Vide order dated 01.11.2021, learned Trial
			<lb />
			Court took cognizance of the Order 7 Rule 11 CPC
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:14 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
		</front>

		<page>
			5
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			application and directed the plaintiffs to file reply to the
			<lb />
			application. Learned Trial Court also noticed that the
			<lb />
			written statement had not been filed. The defendants
			<lb />
			prayed for time to file the written statement. One last
			<lb />
			opportunity was granted by the learned Trial court to file
			<lb />
			written statement, failing which the opportunity for filing
			<lb />
			the written statement was to be closed. The matter was
			<lb />
			ordered to be next listed for 22.02.2022.
			<lb />
			The order dated 01.11.2021, to the extent it
			<lb />
			grants last opportunity to the defendants to file written
			<lb />
			statement, failing which they were not to be granted any
			<lb />
			further opportunity to file the same, has been assailed by
			<lb />
			defendants No.1 and 2 (petitioners) in the instant petition.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			Contentions:-
			<lb />
			3(i).
			<lb />
			Sh. Karan Singh Kanwar, learned counsel for
			<lb />
			the petitioners (defendants No.1 and 2), relying upon (2003)
			<lb />
			1 SCC 557, titled Saleem Bhai and others Versus State
			<lb />
			of Maharashtra &amp; others and (2016) 14 SCC 275, titled
			<lb />
			R.K. Roja Versus U.S. Rayudu and another, argued that
			<lb />
			the learned Trial Court erred in law in directing defendants
			<lb />
			No.1 and 2 to file written statement before the decision of
			<lb />
			their application moved under Order 7 Rule 11 CPC.
			<lb />
			Learned counsel submitted that the question of filing the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:14 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
		</front>

		<page>
			6
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			written statement would come only after the adjudication of
			<lb />
			application moved under Order 7 Rule 11 CPC. By granting
			<lb />
			last opportunity to defendants No.1 and 2, they cannot be
			<lb />
			compelled to file the written statement during pendency of
			<lb />
			their Order 7 Rule 11 CPC application. The approach of the
			<lb />
			learned Trial Court is wholly erroneous and illegal.
			<lb />
			3(ii).
			<lb />
			According to Sh. Ashok K. Tyagi, learned
			<lb />
			counsel for respondents No.1 to 5 (plaintiffs), defendants
			<lb />
			No.1 and 2 had been unnecessarily dragging the litigation.
			<lb />
			They had not opted to file the written statement even after
			<lb />
			grant of umpteenth number of opportunities during the last
			<lb />
			about two years. Under the pretext of filing the application
			<lb />
			under Order 7 Rule 11 CPC, the time limit for filing the
			<lb />
			written statement stipulated under Order 8 Rule 1 CPC
			<lb />
			cannot be extended. (2019) 12 SCC 210, titled SCG
			<lb />
			Contracts
			<lb />
			(India)
			<lb />
			Private
			<lb />
			Limited
			<lb />
			Versus
			<lb />
			K.S.
			<lb />
			Chamankar Infrastructure Private Limited and others,
			<lb />
			was cited in support of the plea.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			I have heard learned counsel for the parties and
			<lb />
			gone through the case file.
			<lb />
			4(i).
			<lb />
			Order 7 Rule 11 CPC pertains to rejection of
			<lb />
			plaint and reads as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;O7 R11. Rejection of plaint
			<lb />
			The plaint shall be rejected in the following cases:-
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:14 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
		</front>

		<page>
			7
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			(a) where it does not disclose a cause of action;
			<lb />
			(b) where the relief claimed is undervalued, and the plaintiff,
			<lb />
			on being required by the court to correct the valuation
			<lb />
			within a time to be fixed by the court, fails to do so;
			<lb />
			(c) where the relief claimed is properly valued, but the plaint
			<lb />
			is written upon paper insufficiently stamped, and the
			<lb />
			plaintiff, on being required by the court to supply the
			<lb />
			requisite stamp-paper within a time to be fixed by the
			<lb />
			Court, fails to do so;
			<lb />
			(d) where the suit appears from the statement in the plaint to
			<lb />
			be barred by any law;
			<lb />
			(e) where it is not filed in duplicate;
			<lb />
			(f) where the plaintiff fails to comply with the provisions of
			<lb />
			rule9:
			<lb />
			Provided that the time fixed by the court for the
			<lb />
			correction of the valuation or supplying of the requisite stamp-
			<lb />
			papers shall not be extended unless the court, for reasons to
			<lb />
			be recorded, is satisfied that the plaintiff was prevented by
			<lb />
			any cause of an exceptional nature from correcting the
			<lb />
			valuation or supplying the requisite stamp papers, as the
			<lb />
			case may be, within the time fixed by the court and that
			<lb />
			refusal to extend such time would cause grave injustice to the
			<lb />
			plaintiff.&quot;
			<lb />
			It is settled principle of law that an application
			<lb />
			under Order 7 Rule 11 CPC can be filed at any stage. Once
			<lb />
			such an application is instituted, the Court is bound to
			<lb />
			dispose of the same before proceeding with the trial.
			<lb />
			4(ii).
			<lb />
			(2003) 1 SCC 557, titled Saleem Bhai and
			<lb />
			others Versus State of Maharashtra and others, was a
			<lb />
			case before the Apex Court, where the appellant had filed
			<lb />
			an application under Order 7 Rule 11 CPC, praying for
			<lb />
			dismissal of the suit on the stated grounds. The
			<lb />
			respondents had also filed an application under Order 8
			<lb />
			Rule 10 CPC with a prayer to the Court for pronouncing the
			<lb />
			judgment in the suit as the appellant had not filed the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:14 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
		</front>

		<page>
			8
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			written statement. The appellant also moved an application
			<lb />
			under Section 151 CPC praying the Court to first decide the
			<lb />
			application under Order 7 Rule 11 CPC. Learned Trial
			<lb />
			Court dismissed the application filed under Order 8 Rule 10
			<lb />
			CPC as well as the application filed under Section 151 CPC.
			<lb />
			The appellant was directed to file his written statement. The
			<lb />
			High Court affirmed the order passed by the learned Trial
			<lb />
			Court that appellant should file his written statement and
			<lb />
			observed that the Trial Court shall frame issues and record
			<lb />
			its finding on preliminary issues before proceeding to try
			<lb />
			the suit on facts. The order passed by the High Court was
			<lb />
			agitated in the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court. The question that
			<lb />
			arose before the Hon&apos;ble Apex Court was as to whether an
			<lb />
			application under Order 7 Rule 11 CPC was to be decided
			<lb />
			on the basis of allegations in the plaint and filing of written
			<lb />
			statement by the contesting defendant was irrelevant and
			<lb />
			unnecessary. The Hon&apos;ble Apex Court held that for the
			<lb />
			purpose of deciding the application under Order 7 Rule 11
			<lb />
			CPC, it is only the averments in the plaint that are
			<lb />
			germane. The pleas taken up by the defendants in the
			<lb />
			written statement will be wholly irrelevant at that stage. The
			<lb />
			Apex Court also held that a direction to file the written
			<lb />
			statement without deciding the application under Order 7
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:14 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
		</front>

		<page>
			9
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Rule 11 CPC is a procedural irregularity touching the
			<lb />
			exercise of jurisdiction by the learned Trial Court. Relevant
			<lb />
			para of the judgment reads as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;9. A perusal of Order 7 Rule 11 CPC makes it clear that the
			<lb />
			relevant facts which need to be looked into for deciding an
			<lb />
			application thereunder are the averments in the plaint. The
			<lb />
			trial court can exercise the power under Order 7 Rule 11 CPC
			<lb />
			at any stage of the suit-before registering the plaint or after
			<lb />
			issuing summons to the defendant at any time before the
			<lb />
			conclusion of the trial. For the purposes of deciding an
			<lb />
			application under clauses (a) and (d) of Rule 11 of Order 7
			<lb />
			CPC, the averments in the plaint are germane; the pleas
			<lb />
			taken by the defendant in the written statement would be
			<lb />
			wholly irrelevant at that stage, therefore, a direction to file the
			<lb />
			written statement without deciding the application under
			<lb />
			Order 7 Rule 11 CPC cannot but be procedural irregularity
			<lb />
			touching the exercise of jurisdiction by the trial court. The
			<lb />
			order, therefore, suffers from non-exercising of the jurisdiction
			<lb />
			vested in the court as well as procedural irregularity. The
			<lb />
			High Court however, did not advert to these aspects.&quot;
			<lb />
			The judgment in Saleem Bhai&apos;s case, supra,
			<lb />
			came up for consideration in (2016) 14 SCC 275, titled
			<lb />
			R.K. Roja Versus U.S. Rayudu and another. Reiterating
			<lb />
			the law laid down in Saleem Bhai&apos;s case, supra, it was held
			<lb />
			that once the application is filed under Order 7 Rule 11
			<lb />
			CPC, the Court has to dispose of the same before
			<lb />
			proceeding with the trial. At this stage, it will be appropriate
			<lb />
			to extract relevant portion of the judgment:-
			<lb />
			&quot;5. Once an application is filed under Order 7 Rule 11 CPC, the
			<lb />
			court has to dispose of the same before proceeding with the
			<lb />
			trial. There is no point or sense in proceeding with the trial of
			<lb />
			the case, in case the plaint (election petition in the present
			<lb />
			case) is only to be rejected at the threshold. Therefore, the
			<lb />
			defendant is entitled to file the application for rejection before
			<lb />
			filing his written statement. In case the application is
			<lb />
			rejected, the defendant is entitled to file his written statement
			<lb />
			thereafter (see Saleem Bhai v. State of Maharashtra, (2003) 1
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:14 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
		</front>

		<page>
			10
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			SCC 557). But once an application for rejection is filed, the
			<lb />
			court has to dispose of the same before proceeding with the
			<lb />
			trial court. To quote the relevant portion from para 20 of the
			<lb />
			Sopan Sukhdeo Sable case [(2004) 3 SCC 137]: (SCC pp. 148-
			<lb />
			49)
			<lb />
			&quot;20.
			<lb />
			… Rule 11 of Order 7 lays down an independent
			<lb />
			remedy made available to the defendant to challenge the
			<lb />
			maintainability of the suit itself, irrespective of his right to
			<lb />
			contest the same on merits. The law ostensibly does not
			<lb />
			contemplate at any stage when the objections can be
			<lb />
			raised, and also does not say in express terms about the
			<lb />
			filing of a written statement. Instead, the word &quot;shall&quot; is
			<lb />
			used, clearly implying thereby that it casts a duty on the
			<lb />
			court to perform its obligations in rejecting the plaint when
			<lb />
			the same is hit by any of the infirmities provided in the
			<lb />
			four clauses of Rule 11, even without intervention of the
			<lb />
			defendant.&quot;
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			In Saleem Bhai case [(2003) 1 SCC 557], this Court has also
			<lb />
			held that: (SCC p. 560, para 9)
			<lb />
			&quot;9. … a direction to file the written statement without
			<lb />
			deciding the application under Order 7 Rule 11 cannot but
			<lb />
			be a procedural irregularity touching the exercise of
			<lb />
			jurisdiction by the trial court.&quot;
			<lb />
			The principles laid down in the above two
			<lb />
			judgments have been reiterated in 2020 (8) SCALE 219,
			<lb />
			titled Shakti Bhog Food Industries Ltd. VS The Central
			<lb />
			Bank of India &amp; Anr.
			<lb />
			4(iii).
			<lb />
			Interwoven with the question involved in the
			<lb />
			case is the time schedule for filing the written statement.
			<lb />
			Order 8 Rule 1 CPC sets down following timeline for filing
			<lb />
			the written statement:-
			<lb />
			&quot;O8 R1. Written statement.-The defendant shall, within thirty
			<lb />
			days from the date of service of summons on him, present a
			<lb />
			written statement of his defence:
			<lb />
			Provided that where the defendant fails to file the written
			<lb />
			statement within the said period of thirty days, he shall be
			<lb />
			allowed to file the same on such other day, as may be
			<lb />
			specified by the Court, for reasons to be recorded in writing,
			<lb />
			but which shall not be later than ninety days from the date of
			<lb />
			service of summons.&quot;
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:14 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
		</front>

		<page>
			11
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Nature of above provision has been held to be
			<lb />
			procedural and not substantive law. Settled legal position is
			<lb />
			that the provisions of Order 8 Rule 1 CPC are directory and
			<lb />
			not mandatory. The time limit prescribed for filing the
			<lb />
			written statement therein has to be respected ordinarily.
			<lb />
			The provision provides for extension of time for filing the
			<lb />
			written statement. However, the extension should not be
			<lb />
			granted in routine, but only in exceptionally hard cases. It
			<lb />
			would be apt to refer here following paras from (2018) 6
			<lb />
			SCC 639, titled ATCOM Technologies Limited Versus
			<lb />
			Y.A. Chunawala and Company and others:-
			<lb />
			&quot;19. It has to be borne in mind that as per the provisions of Order
			<lb />
			VIII Rule 1 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, the
			<lb />
			defendant is obligated to present a written statement of his
			<lb />
			defence within thirty days from the date of service of
			<lb />
			summons. Proviso thereto enables the Court to extend the
			<lb />
			period upto ninety days from the date of service of summons
			<lb />
			for sufficient reasons. Order VIII Rule 1 of the Code of Civil
			<lb />
			Procedure, 1908 reads as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;1. Written statement.-The defendant shall, within thirty
			<lb />
			days from the date of service of summons on him, present
			<lb />
			a written statement of his defence:
			<lb />
			Provided that where the defendant fails to file the written
			<lb />
			statement within the said period of thirty days, he shall be
			<lb />
			allowed to file the same on such other day, as may be
			<lb />
			specified by the Court, for reasons to be recorded in
			<lb />
			writing, but which shall not be later than ninety days from
			<lb />
			the date of service of summons.&quot;
			<lb />
			20. This provision has come up for interpretation before this Court
			<lb />
			in number of cases. No doubt, the words &quot;shall not be later
			<lb />
			than ninety days&quot; do not take away the power of the court to
			<lb />
			accept written statement beyond that time and it is also held
			<lb />
			that the nature of the provision is procedural and it is not a
			<lb />
			part of substantive law. At the same time, this Court has also
			<lb />
			mandated that time can be extended only in exceptionally
			<lb />
			hard cases. We would like to reproduce the following
			<lb />
			discussion from Salem Advocate Bar Assn. v. Union of India
			<lb />
			[(2005) 6 SCC 344]: (SCC p.354, para 21)
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:14 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
		</front>

		<page>
			12
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			&quot;21. ...There is no restriction in Order 8 Rule 10 that after
			<lb />
			expiry of ninety days, further time cannot be granted. The
			<lb />
			court has wide power to &quot;make such order in relation to
			<lb />
			the suit as it thinks fit&quot;. Clearly, therefore, the provision of
			<lb />
			Order 8 Rule 1 providing for the upper limit of 90 days to
			<lb />
			file written statement is directory. Having said so, we wish
			<lb />
			to make it clear that the order extending time to file
			<lb />
			written statement cannot be made in routine. The time can
			<lb />
			be extended only in exceptionally hard cases. While
			<lb />
			extending time, it has to be borne in mind that the
			<lb />
			legislature has fixed the upper time-limit of 90 days. The
			<lb />
			discretion of the court to extend the time shall not be so
			<lb />
			frequently and routinely exercised so as to nullify the
			<lb />
			period fixed by Order 8 Rule 1.&quot;
			<lb />
			21. In such a situation, onus upon the defendant is of a higher
			<lb />
			degree to plead and satisfactorily demonstrate a valid reason
			<lb />
			for not filing the written statement within thirty days. When
			<lb />
			that is a requirement, could it be a ground to condone delay
			<lb />
			of more than 5 years even when it is calculated from the year
			<lb />
			2009, only because of the reason that Writ of Summons were
			<lb />
			not served till 2009?
			<lb />
			22. We fail to persuade ourselves with this kind of reasoning
			<lb />
			given by the High Court in condoning the delay, thereby
			<lb />
			disregarding the provisions of Order 8 Rule 1 of the Code of
			<lb />
			Civil Procedure, 1908 and the spirit behind it. This reason of
			<lb />
			the High Court that delay was condoned &quot;by balancing the
			<lb />
			rights and equities&quot; is far-fetched and, in the process,
			<lb />
			abnormal delay in filing the written statement is condoned
			<lb />
			without addressing the relevant factor viz. whether the
			<lb />
			respondents had furnished proper and satisfactory
			<lb />
			explanation for such a delay. The approach of the High Court
			<lb />
			is clearly erroneous in law and cannot be countenanced. No
			<lb />
			doubt, the provisions of Order 8 Rule 1 of the Code of Civil
			<lb />
			Procedure, 1908 are procedural in nature and, therefore,
			<lb />
			handmaid of justice. However, that would not mean that the
			<lb />
			defendant has right to take as much time as he wants in
			<lb />
			filing the written statement, without giving convincing and
			<lb />
			cogent reasons for delay and the High Court has to condone it
			<lb />
			mechanically.&quot;
			<lb />
			In the case in hand, the defendants were
			<lb />
			admittedly served in the civil suit by April, 2020. The civil
			<lb />
			suit thereafter had been repeatedly fixed for filing of written
			<lb />
			statement by them. As observed earlier, according to the
			<lb />
			case status document supplied by learned counsel for the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:14 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
			</front>
			<page>
				13
			<lb />
			</page>
			<body>
			respondents, the matter was fixed before the learned Trial
			<lb />
			Court for filing of written statement by the defendants on
			<lb />
			09.04.2020,
			<lb />
			19.06.2020,
			<lb />
			22.09.2020,
			<lb />
			10.11.2020,
			<lb />
			06.01.2021 and 22.03.2021. On three subsequent dates,
			<lb />
			i.e. 06.05.2021, 12.07.2021 and 21.08.2021, the matter
			<lb />
			was fixed for proper orders/service. Lastly, the matter was
			<lb />
			fixed on 01.11.2021 for filing of written statement. The
			<lb />
			written statement was not filed by the defendants. Instead
			<lb />
			of filing the written statement, an application was moved
			<lb />
			under Order 7 Rule 11 CPC for rejection of plaint on the
			<lb />
			ground of undervaluation of the suit for the purposes of
			<lb />
			court fees &amp; jurisdiction and that the learned Trial Court
			<lb />
			lacked pecuniary jurisdiction to try the suit. No explanation
			<lb />
			was offered by the defendants for not filing the written
			<lb />
			statement during the last about two years.
			<lb />
			Admittedly, no application has been filed by the
			<lb />
			defendants for extension of time to file the written
			<lb />
			statement beyond the period prescribed under Order 8 Rule
			<lb />
			1 CPC. Instead of filing the written statement on
			<lb />
			01.11.2021, the defendants came up with an application
			<lb />
			under Order 7 Rule 11 CPC. A copy of this application
			<lb />
			appended at Annexure P-3, prima-facie, shows that it was
			<lb />
			signed on 22.03.2021 and attested on 12.07.2021.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:14 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
		</front>

		<page>
			14
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Despite having entered appearance in the civil
			<lb />
			suit about two years ago, the defendants have neither filed
			<lb />
			their written statement nor moved any application seeking
			<lb />
			extension of time to file it. In R.K. Roja&apos;s case, supra, the
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Apex Court had also cautioned that liberty to file an
			<lb />
			application under Order 7 Rule 11 CPC cannot be made as
			<lb />
			a ruse for retrieving the lost opportunity to file the written
			<lb />
			statement. These observations relevant in context of present
			<lb />
			controversy are extracted hereinafter:-
			<lb />
			&quot;However, we may hasten to add that the liberty to file
			<lb />
			an application for rejection under Order 7 Rule 11 CPC cannot
			<lb />
			be made as a ruse for retrieving the lost opportunity to file the
			<lb />
			written statement.&quot;
			<lb />
			The above observations were again noticed and
			<lb />
			explained by the Hon&apos;ble Apex Court in (2019) 12 SCC
			<lb />
			210, titled SCG Contracts (India) Private Limited Versus
			<lb />
			K.S. Chamankar Infrastructure Private Limited and
			<lb />
			others. It was a case involving provisions of Order 8 Rule 1
			<lb />
			CPC as amended by the Commercial Courts Act, 2015. The
			<lb />
			amended provisions of Order 8 Rule 1 CPC read as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;O8 R1. Written statement
			<lb />
			The defendant shall, within thirty days from the date
			<lb />
			of service of summons on him, present a written statement of
			<lb />
			his defence:
			<lb />
			Provided that where the defendant fails to file the
			<lb />
			written statement within the said period of thirty days, he
			<lb />
			shall be allowed to file the written statement on such other
			<lb />
			day, as may be specified by the Court, for reasons to be
			<lb />
			recorded in writing and on payment of such costs as the
			<lb />
			Court deems fit, but which shall not be later than one
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:14 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
		</front>

		<page>
			15
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			hundred twenty days from the date of service of summons
			<lb />
			and on expiry of one hundred twenty days from the date of
			<lb />
			service of summons, the defendant shall forfeit the right to file
			<lb />
			the written statement and the Court shall not allow the
			<lb />
			written statement to be taken on record.&quot;
			<lb />
			Defendant No.1 in the above case had not filed
			<lb />
			written statement within 120 days from the date of service
			<lb />
			of summons in the suit. Instead, he moved an application
			<lb />
			under Order 7 Rule 11 CPC. The application was taken up
			<lb />
			and rejected. After dismissal of Order 7 Rule 11 CPC
			<lb />
			application, the defendant prayed for seven days&apos; time to file
			<lb />
			written statement. The Court allowed the defendant to file
			<lb />
			written statement within the specified time subject to
			<lb />
			payment of costs of Rs.25,000/-to the plaintiff. The order
			<lb />
			was complied with and written statement was filed within
			<lb />
			the time limit mentioned in the order. The plaintiff agitated
			<lb />
			that changes made in the CPC were not adhered to. That
			<lb />
			the written statement could not be taken on record in view
			<lb />
			of the fact that 120 days had elapsed from the date of
			<lb />
			service of summons of the suit. Amended provisions of
			<lb />
			Order 8 Rule 1 CPC were pressed in service by the plaintiff.
			<lb />
			One of the arguments raised by the respondents before the
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Apex Court was that as an application under Order
			<lb />
			7 Rule 11 CPC had been filed and that had to be answered
			<lb />
			before the trial of the suit could commence. That a written
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:14 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
		</front>

		<page>
			16
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			statement could not be filed prior to the adjudication of the
			<lb />
			application under Order 7 Rule 11 CPC. The argument was
			<lb />
			based upon the judgment in R.K. Roja&apos;s case, supra. While
			<lb />
			answering this contention, the Apex Court held that the
			<lb />
			judgment in R.K. Roja&apos;s case cannot be read in the manner
			<lb />
			sought for by the respondents. That Order 7 Rule 11
			<lb />
			proceedings are independent of filing of the written
			<lb />
			statement once a suit has been filed. The written statement
			<lb />
			was ordered to be taken off the record. It would be
			<lb />
			appropriate at this stage to extract the observations of the
			<lb />
			Apex Court in this regard:-
			<lb />
			&quot;11. We are of the view that the view taken by the Delhi High
			<lb />
			Court in these judgments is correct in view of the fact that the
			<lb />
			consequence of forfeiting a right to file the written statement;
			<lb />
			non-extension of any further time; and the fact that the Court
			<lb />
			shall not allow the written statement to be taken on record all
			<lb />
			points to the fact that the earlier law on Order 8 Rule 1 on the
			<lb />
			filing of written statement under Order 8 Rule 1 has now
			<lb />
			been set at naught.
			<lb />
			13.
			<lb />
			We are of the view that since both these judgments dealt with
			<lb />
			the pre-amendment position, they would not be of any direct
			<lb />
			reliance insofar as the facts of the present case are
			<lb />
			concerned.
			<lb />
			14.
			<lb />
			The learned counsel appearing for the respondents also relied
			<lb />
			upon R.K. Roja v. U.S. Rayudu for the proposition that the
			<lb />
			defendant is entitled to file an application for rejection of
			<lb />
			plaint under Order 7 Rule 11 before filing his written
			<lb />
			statement. We are of the view that this judgment cannot be
			<lb />
			read in the manner sought for by the learned counsel
			<lb />
			appearing on behalf of the respondents. Order 7 Rule 11
			<lb />
			proceedings are independent of the filing of a written
			<lb />
			statement once a suit has been filed. In fact, para 6 of that
			<lb />
			judgment records: (SCC p. 277)
			<lb />
			&quot;6. … However, we may hasten to add that the liberty to
			<lb />
			file an application for rejection under Order 7 Rule 11 CPC
			<lb />
			cannot be made as a ruse for retrieving the lost
			<lb />
			opportunity to file the written statement.&quot;
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:14 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
		</front>

		<page>
			17
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Civil Appeal No.1318 of 2022, titled Prakash
			<lb />
			Corporates Versus Dee Vee Projects Limited, decided on
			<lb />
			14.02.2022, was a case under the Commercial Courts Act,
			<lb />
			2015, where the learned Trial Court declined the prayer of
			<lb />
			defendant for granting further time to file the written
			<lb />
			statement after expiry of 120 days from the date of service
			<lb />
			of summons in view of amended provisions of Order 8 Rule
			<lb />
			1 CPC. The order was upheld by the High Court. Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Apex Court though allowed the appeal and permitted the
			<lb />
			written statement to be taken on record on certain grounds
			<lb />
			and also taking note of the orders passed in Suo Moto Writ
			<lb />
			Petition (Civil) No.3 of 2020, but held as under with respect
			<lb />
			to the time limit for filing the written statement and
			<lb />
			consequences of default:-
			<lb />
			&quot;17. If the aforesaid provisions and explained principles are
			<lb />
			literally and plainly applied to the facts of the present case,
			<lb />
			the 120 th day from the date of service of summons came to an
			<lb />
			end with 06.05.2021 and the defendant, who had earlier
			<lb />
			been granted time for filing its written statement on payment
			<lb />
			of costs, forfeited such right with the end of 120 th day, i.e.,
			<lb />
			06.05.2021. However, it is required to be kept in view that
			<lb />
			the provisions aforesaid and their interpretation in SCG
			<lb />
			Contracts (supra) operate in normal and non-extraordinary
			<lb />
			circumstances with the usual functioning of Courts. It is also
			<lb />
			noteworthy that the above referred provisions of CPC are not
			<lb />
			the only provisions of law which lay down mandatory
			<lb />
			timelines for particular proceedings. The relevant principles,
			<lb />
			in their normal and ordinary operation, are that such
			<lb />
			statutory timelines are of mandatory character with little, or
			<lb />
			rather no, discretion with the Adjudicating Authority for
			<lb />
			enlargement. The question in the present case is, as to
			<lb />
			whether the said provisions and principles are required to be
			<lb />
			applied irrespective of the operation and effect of other orders
			<lb />
			passed/issued by the Courts under the force of aberrant,
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:14 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
		</front>

		<page>
			18
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			abnormal and extraordinary circumstances? In our view, the
			<lb />
			answer to this question cannot be in the affirmative for a
			<lb />
			variety of reasons, as indicated infra.&quot;
			<lb />
			4(iv).
			<lb />
			Reverting back to the facts of the present case,
			<lb />
			the defendants even after entering appearance in the matter
			<lb />
			two years ago, have still not filed their written statement.
			<lb />
			No doubt, application under Order 7 Rule 11 CPC can be
			<lb />
			filed at any stage and this application has to be adjudicated
			<lb />
			first before proceeding with the trial. Nonetheless Order 7
			<lb />
			Rule 11 CPC proceedings have been held to be independent
			<lb />
			of filing of written statement. There is no embargo upon the
			<lb />
			defendants to file written statement before adjudication of
			<lb />
			Order 7 Rule 11 CPC application. Pendency of Order 7 Rule
			<lb />
			11 CPC application filed two years later to the date of
			<lb />
			appearance of defendants in the civil suit cannot be taken
			<lb />
			as a ruse for not filing the written statement. Provisions of
			<lb />
			Order 8 Rule 1 CPC cannot be simply ignored or else under
			<lb />
			the guise of moving frivolous Order 7 Rule 11 CPC
			<lb />
			applications, the defendants can always protract the trials,
			<lb />
			thereby defeating not only the object of the provisions, but
			<lb />
			also the cause of justice. Also as per the impugned order, it
			<lb />
			was the defendants, who prayed for more time to file written
			<lb />
			statement. Learned Trial Court accordingly granted them
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:14 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
		</front>

		<page>
			19
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			one last opportunity. There is nothing wrong in the
			<lb />
			approach of the learned Trial Court.
			<lb />
			For all the above reasons, this petition lacks
			<lb />
			merit and is accordingly dismissed. Parties, through their
			<lb />
			learned counsel, are directed to appear before the learned
			<lb />
			Trial Court on 21.03.2022. It shall be open to the
			<lb />
			petitioners to file the written statement in the learned Trial
			<lb />
			Court by 21.03.2022 in terms of the impugned order, failing
			<lb />
			which, learned Trial Court shall proceed further in the
			<lb />
			matter in accordance with law.
			<lb />
			Before parting, it is clarified that this Court has
			<lb />
			not expressed any opinion on merits of application under
			<lb />
			Order 7 Rule 11 CPC moved by defendants No.1 and 2. The
			<lb />
			observations made above are confined only to adjudication
			<lb />
			of present petition.
			<lb />
			Jyotsna Rewal Dua
			<lb />
			March 05, 2022
			<lb />
			Judge
			<lb />
			Mukesh
			<lb />
		</body>
	</text>
</tei>