<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF HIMACHAL PRADESH, SHIMLA
			<lb />
			CWP No. 2616 of 2020
			<lb />
			Date of decision: 28.07.2020
			<lb />
			Maharishi Markandeshwar University and another
			<lb />
			…Petitioners.
			<lb />
			Versus
			<lb />
			State of Himachal Pradesh and others
			<lb />
			...Respondents.
			<lb />
			</front>
		<body>
			Coram
			<lb />
			The Hon&apos;ble Mr. Justice Tarlok Singh Chauhan, Judge.
			<lb />
			The Hon&apos;ble Ms. Justice Jyotsna Rewal Dua, Judge.
			<lb />
			Whether approved for reporting? 1
			<lb />
			For the Petitioners
			<lb />
			:
			<lb />
			Mr. K.D. Shreedhar, Senior Advocate
			<lb />
			with Ms. Shreya Chauhan, Advocate,
			<lb />
			through Video Conferencing.
			<lb />
			For the Respondents
			<lb />
			:
			<lb />
			Mr. Ajay Vaidya, Senior Additional
			<lb />
			Advocate General, through Video
			<lb />
			Conferencing.
			<lb />
			PROCEEDINGS CONVENED THROUGH VIDEO CONFERENCE
			<lb />
			Tarlok Singh Chauhan, Judge (Oral)
			<lb />
			Mr. Ajay Vaidya, learned Senior Additional Advocate
			<lb />
			General has obtained instructions in terms of the order passed by
			<lb />
			us yesterday. In terms thereof, the Committee that was
			<lb />
			1
			<lb />
			Whether reporters of Local Papers may be allowed to see the Judgment ?
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 12:57:27 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
			<front>
				H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
			</front>
			
			<page>
				2
			<lb />
			</page>
		<body>
			constituted, has decided that in case the seats will remain
			<lb />
			vacant/unfilled after Mop up round, then the petitioners-College
			<lb />
			will be allowed to fill-up the said seats on its own level on
			<lb />
			31.07.2020 from the NEET-PG 2020 candidates. Relevant portion
			<lb />
			of the instructions reads as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;After deliberations, the Committee decided that in
			<lb />
			case seats will remain vacant/unfilled after Mop up round,
			<lb />
			then M.M.C. Solan will allow to fill up the said seats at
			<lb />
			College level on 31.07.2020 from NEET-PG-2020
			<lb />
			candidates. However, counseling shall be held under the
			<lb />
			supervision of the representatives of DM E&amp;R, H.P. from
			<lb />
			amongst the candidates already registered upto Mop round.
			<lb />
			No fresh application can be included as per MCCI.&quot;
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Learned Senior Counsel for the petitioners states that
			<lb />
			the petitioners have no difficulty in complying with the aforesaid
			<lb />
			instructions, but would take strong exception and rightly so to that
			<lb />
			portion of the instructions, which provides &quot;No fresh application
			<lb />
			can be included as per MCCI&quot;.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			It is more than settled that admissions in the
			<lb />
			professional colleges pertaining to Medical and Dental Colleges
			<lb />
			in Post Graduate &amp; Super-Specialty Courses are required to be
			<lb />
			made purely on the basis of merit and merit alone because the
			<lb />
			object must be to select the best and most meritorious student
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 12:57:27 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
		</front>
		<page>
			3
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			and cannot, therefore, be restricted or made on the basis of &quot;first
			<lb />
			come first serve&quot;. (Refer: Dr. Pradeep Jain and others Versus
			<lb />
			Union of India and others, (1984) 3 SCC 654).
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Accordingly, we direct the petitioners-College to fill-up
			<lb />
			the remaining vacant/unfilled seats after the mop up round strictly
			<lb />
			on the basis of merit. In order to ensure that the admissions are
			<lb />
			made in a transparent manner and that too strictly in order of
			<lb />
			merit amongst the candidates, who might be desirous to seek
			<lb />
			admissions, such admissions shall be made in presence of an
			<lb />
			Observer(s) to be appointed by the Director, Medical Education &amp;
			<lb />
			Research, Himachal Pradesh.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			It is clarified that admissions shall be made on the
			<lb />
			basis of the advertisement that was issued by the petitioners-
			<lb />
			College in compliance to the orders passed on 27.07.2020. All
			<lb />
			those candidates, who apply upto 10:00 am on 31.07.2020, shall
			<lb />
			be eligible for consideration.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			In view of the aforesaid orders, nothing survives for
			<lb />
			adjudication in this petition and the same is accordingly disposed
			<lb />
			of in the aforesaid terms, leaving the parties to bear their own
			<lb />
			costs. Pending application(s), if any, shall also stand disposed of.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 12:57:27 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
		</front>

		<page>
			4
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Authenticated copy of this order be supplied to the
			<lb />
			parties by the Secretary/Private Secretary.
			<lb />
			(Tarlok Singh Chauhan)
			<lb />
			Judge
			<lb />
			(Jyotsna Rewal Dua)
			<lb />
			Judge
			<lb />
			28 th July, 2020
			<lb />
			(krt/Mukesh)
			<lb />
		</body>
	</text>
</tei>