<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			W.P.(C) 7615/2016
			<lb />
			Page 1 of 10
			<lb />
			$~26
			<lb />
			*
			<lb />
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF DELHI AT NEW DELHI
			<lb />
			Judgment dated: 29 th August, 2016.
			<lb />
			+
			<lb />
			W.P.(C) 7615/2016 &amp; CM No. 31395/2016
			<lb />
			MAHANAGAR TELEPHONE NIGAM
			<lb />
			LIMITED AND ANR.
			<lb />
			..... Petitioners
			<lb />
			Through : Ms. Sangita Rai, Advocate.
			<lb />
			versus
			<lb />
			ANIL KUMAR AND ANR.
			<lb />
			..... Respondents
			<lb />
			Through : Nemo.
			<lb />
		</front>

		<body>
			CORAM:
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE G.S.SISTANI
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE I.S.MEHTA
			<lb />
			G.S.SISTANI, J (ORAL)
			<lb />
			W.P.(C) 7615/2016
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			Challenge in this writ petition is to the order dated 8 th August, 2016
			<lb />
			passed by the Central Administrative Tribunal (hereinafter referred to as &quot;the
			<lb />
			Tribunal&quot;), by which the OA No. 1167/2016 filed by the respondents herein
			<lb />
			was allowed and the order of their transfer stands quashed.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			It is well settled that a government servant has no right to stay in a
			<lb />
			particular post and transfer is an incident of service. We may also, however
			<lb />
			add, that normally Courts do not interfere in the transfer orders, if they are
			<lb />
			made in public interest. The rider is of course that unless, the transfer has
			<lb />
			been made in violation of any statute or on the grounds of malafide. In this
			<lb />
			case, the Tribunal has quashed the order of transfer on the ground of
			<lb />
			malafide.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.(C) 7615/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 2 of 10
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			3.
			<lb />
			The necessary facts to be noticed are that the respondent No. 1 joined
			<lb />
			the MTNL in the year 1978 while the respondent No. 2 joined the MTNL in
			<lb />
			the year 1994. Both these respondents had filed a police complaint on 22 nd
			<lb />
			February, 2016 against the petitioner No. 2. On 2 nd March, 2016, the name of
			<lb />
			respondent No. 1 was struck off from the strength of Vishwas Nagar, where
			<lb />
			he was working as a Phone Mechanic with instructions to report to DE (OD-
			<lb />
			III) LXR for further duties. While the name of respondent No. 2 was struck
			<lb />
			off from the strength of Karkardooma on 17 th March, 2016 with instructions
			<lb />
			to report to DE(OD-I) LXR for further duties. The transfers stated to have
			<lb />
			been made in the interest of service and on administration exigencies.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Learned counsel for the petitioners submits that the learned Tribunal
			<lb />
			has exceeded its jurisdiction and failed to appreciate the fact that the
			<lb />
			petitioners are the Competent Authority to decide when and where an
			<lb />
			employee is to be transferred from the place of his present posting. She also
			<lb />
			submits that the Court cannot sit in judgment as an appeal over the order
			<lb />
			passed by the competent authority in the matters relating to transfers.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			Counsel for petitioners also contends that the competent authority has
			<lb />
			passed the order of transfer of both the respondent employees as per clause
			<lb />
			19 of the certified standing orders framed by the MTNL under Section 3 (1)
			<lb />
			of the Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Act, 1946. The orders have
			<lb />
			also been passed by the competent authority keeping in mind, the smooth
			<lb />
			functioning and working of the department and thus, the transfer orders
			<lb />
			cannot be treated as having been issued on account of malice by the
			<lb />
			petitioner No. 2 or merely because of the fact that the respondents had filed a
			<lb />
			police complaint against him especially when no copy of the complaint has
			<lb />
			been marked to the CMD. Counsel further submits that mere allegations
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.(C) 7615/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 3 of 10
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			made by the respondents cannot be taken as proved and thus the order on
			<lb />
			transfer cannot be vitiated by filing a false and frivolous police complaint.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			We have heard counsel for petitioners and also examined the material
			<lb />
			placed on record as also the impugned order, which has been passed by the
			<lb />
			Tribunal. The learned Tribunal has quashed the orders of transfer on the
			<lb />
			ground that the orders of transfer have been issued out of malice and not in
			<lb />
			public interest. The Tribunal has noticed that the applicants (respondents
			<lb />
			herein) had lodged a police complaint against the petitioner No. 2 herein on
			<lb />
			22 nd February, 2016, in which they alleged that the petitioiner No. 2 was
			<lb />
			involved in exorting money from them and was threatening them with
			<lb />
			transfer and involvement in disciplinary proceedings in case they refuse to
			<lb />
			pay. Two days after filing of the police complaint dated 22 nd February, 2016,
			<lb />
			the applicant No. 1 (respondent No. 1 herein) was transferred. Similarly, the
			<lb />
			respondent No. 2 was also transferred. Before the Tribunal, the petitioners
			<lb />
			had taken a plea that the petitioners herein at the time, when the order of
			<lb />
			transfer was made, were not aware about the police complaint having been
			<lb />
			lodged by the respondents but this submission turned out to be false as a
			<lb />
			charge sheet dated 02.03.2016 was available on the record with a clear
			<lb />
			mention about lodging of the police compliant in article III, whereas, the
			<lb />
			transfer order of applicant No. 2 was first made on 5 th March, 2016. Thus,
			<lb />
			the Tribunal came to the conclusion that it is clear that the petitioners herein
			<lb />
			were well aware of the police complaint lodged by the respondents.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			The Tribunal also noticed that as per the official record of the
			<lb />
			respondents, there was no note sheet which would show any reason as to
			<lb />
			why, the respondents herein had been transferred.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			The learned counsel for the petitioners has laboured hard to contend
			<lb />
			that the transfer orders were made in public interest and relied upon the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.(C) 7615/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 4 of 10
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			judgment in the case of State of U.P. and others v. Gobardhan Lal, (2004)
			<lb />
			11 SCC 402 more particularly, paragraphs Nos. 7, 8 and 9 in support of her
			<lb />
			submissions that courts should normally not interfere in orders of transfer
			<lb />
			and that the grounds of malafides are required to be proved. The relevant
			<lb />
			paragraphs of the judgment read as under :-
			<lb />
			&quot;7. It is too late in the day for any Government
			<lb />
			Servant to contend that once appointed or posted
			<lb />
			in a particular place or position, he should
			<lb />
			continue in such place or position as long as he
			<lb />
			desires. Transfer of an employee is not only an
			<lb />
			incident inherent in the terms of appointment but
			<lb />
			also implicit as an essential condition of service in
			<lb />
			the absence of any specific indication to the
			<lb />
			contra, in the law governing or conditions of
			<lb />
			service. Unless the order of transfer is shown to be
			<lb />
			an outcome of a mala fide exercise of power or
			<lb />
			violative of any statutory provision (an Act or
			<lb />
			Rule) or passed by an authority not competent to
			<lb />
			do so, an order of transfer cannot lightly be
			<lb />
			interfered with as a matter of course or routine for
			<lb />
			any or every type of grievance sought to be made.
			<lb />
			Even administrative guidelines for regulating
			<lb />
			transfers or containing transfer policies at best
			<lb />
			may afford an opportunity to the officer or servant
			<lb />
			concerned to approach their higher authorities for
			<lb />
			redress but cannot have the consequence of
			<lb />
			depriving or denying the competent authority to
			<lb />
			transfer a particular officer/servant to any place in
			<lb />
			public interest and as is found necessitated by
			<lb />
			exigencies of service as long as the official status
			<lb />
			is not affected adversely and there is no infraction
			<lb />
			of any career prospects such as seniority, scale of
			<lb />
			pay and secured emoluments. This Court has often
			<lb />
			reiterated that the order of transfer made even in
			<lb />
			transgression of administrative guidelines cannot
			<lb />
			also be interfered with, as they do not confer any
			<lb />
			legally enforceable rights, unless, as noticed
			<lb />
			supra, shown to be vitiated by mala fides or is
			<lb />
			made in violation of any statutory provision.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.(C) 7615/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 5 of 10
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			8.
			<lb />
			A challenge to an order of transfer should
			<lb />
			normally be eschewed and should not be
			<lb />
			countenanced by the Courts or Tribunals as
			<lb />
			though they are Appellate Authorities over such
			<lb />
			orders, which could assess the niceties of the
			<lb />
			administrative needs and requirements of the
			<lb />
			situation concerned. This is for the reason that
			<lb />
			Courts or Tribunals cannot substitute their own
			<lb />
			decisions in the matter of transfer for that of
			<lb />
			competent authorities of the State and even
			<lb />
			allegations of mala fides when made must be such
			<lb />
			as to inspire confidence in the Court or are based
			<lb />
			on concrete materials and ought not to be
			<lb />
			entertained on the mere making of it or on
			<lb />
			consideration borne out of conjectures or surmises
			<lb />
			and except for strong and convincing reasons, no
			<lb />
			interference could ordinarily be made with an
			<lb />
			order of transfer.
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			The very questions involved, as found
			<lb />
			noticed by the High Court in these cases, being
			<lb />
			disputed questions of facts, there was hardly any
			<lb />
			scope for the High Court to generalise the
			<lb />
			situations based on its own appreciation and
			<lb />
			understanding of the prevailing circumstances as
			<lb />
			disclosed from some write ups in journals or
			<lb />
			newspaper reports. Conditions of service or rights,
			<lb />
			which are personal to the parties concerned, are to
			<lb />
			be governed by rules as also the inbuilt powers of
			<lb />
			supervision and control in the hierarchy of the
			<lb />
			administration of State or any Authority as well as
			<lb />
			the basic concepts and well-recognised powers
			<lb />
			and jurisdiction inherent in the various authorities
			<lb />
			in the hierarchy. All that cannot be obliterated by
			<lb />
			sweeping observations and directions unmindful of
			<lb />
			the anarchy which it may create in ensuring an
			<lb />
			effective supervision and control and running of
			<lb />
			administration merely on certain assumed notions
			<lb />
			of orderliness expected from the authorities
			<lb />
			effecting transfers. Even as the position stands,
			<lb />
			avenues are open for being availed of by anyone
			<lb />
			aggrieved, with the concerned authorities, the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.(C) 7615/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 6 of 10
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Courts and Tribunals, as the case may be, to seek
			<lb />
			relief even in relation to an order of transfer or
			<lb />
			appointment or promotion or any order passed in
			<lb />
			disciplinary proceedings on certain well-settled
			<lb />
			and recognized grounds or reasons, when properly
			<lb />
			approached and sought to be vindicated in the
			<lb />
			manner known to and in accordance with law. No
			<lb />
			such generalised directions as have been given by
			<lb />
			the High Court could ever be given leaving room
			<lb />
			for an inevitable impression that the Courts are
			<lb />
			attempting to take over the reigns of executive
			<lb />
			administration. Attempting to undertake an
			<lb />
			exercise of the nature could even be assailed as an
			<lb />
			onslaught and encroachment on the respective
			<lb />
			fields or areas of jurisdiction earmarked for the
			<lb />
			various other limbs of the State. Giving room for
			<lb />
			such an impression should be avoided with utmost
			<lb />
			care and seriously and zealously courts endeavour
			<lb />
			to safeguard the rights of parties.&quot;
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			There is no quarrel to the proposition which is sought to be made by
			<lb />
			the learned counsel for the petitioners but the issue is whether the
			<lb />
			observation of the Supreme Court in State of U.P. and others (supra) are
			<lb />
			applicable to the facts of the present case or not.
			<lb />
			10. The law in respect of the challenge to transfer orders is well settled.
			<lb />
			The courts should generally not interfere with transfer orders as they are a
			<lb />
			mere incidence of service, but may interfere when transfer is made in
			<lb />
			violation of any statute or is actuated by mala fide. In Abani Kanta Ray v.
			<lb />
			State of Orissa., 1995 Supp (4) SCC 169, the Supreme Court observed as
			<lb />
			under:
			<lb />
			&quot;It is settled law that a transfer which is an incident of service is
			<lb />
			not to be interfered with by the Courts unless it is shown to be
			<lb />
			clearly arbitrary or vitiated by mala fides or infraction of any
			<lb />
			professed norm or principle governing the transfer. (See N.K.
			<lb />
			Singh v. Union of India).&quot;
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.(C) 7615/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 7 of 10
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			11. In Union of India and Ors. v.Janardan Debanath &amp; Anr., (2004) 4
			<lb />
			SCC 245, the Supreme Court held as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;No government servant or employee of a public undertaking has
			<lb />
			any legal right to be posted forever at any one particular place or
			<lb />
			place of his choice since transfer of a particular employee
			<lb />
			appointed to the class or category of transferable posts from one
			<lb />
			place to another is not only an incident, but a condition of
			<lb />
			service, necessary too in public interest and efficiency in the
			<lb />
			public administration. Unless an order of transfer is shown to be
			<lb />
			an outcome of mala fide exercise or stated to be in violation of
			<lb />
			statutory provisions prohibiting any such transfer, the courts or
			<lb />
			the tribunals normally cannot interfere with such orders as a
			<lb />
			matter of routine, as though they were the appellate authorities
			<lb />
			substituting their own decision for that of the
			<lb />
			employer/management, as against such orders passed in the
			<lb />
			interest of administrative exigencies of the service concerned.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis Supplied)
			<lb />
			12. In Somesh Tiwari v. Union of India &amp; Ors., AIR 2009 SC 1399 it
			<lb />
			has been observed as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;19. Indisputably an order of transfer is an administrative order.
			<lb />
			There cannot be any doubt whatsoever that transfer, which is
			<lb />
			ordinarily an incident of service should not be interfered with,
			<lb />
			save in cases where inter alia mala fide on the part of the
			<lb />
			authority is proved. Mala fide is of two kinds -one malice in fact
			<lb />
			and the second malice in law.
			<lb />
			20. The order in question would attract the principle of malice in
			<lb />
			law as it was not based on any factor germane for passing an
			<lb />
			order of transfer and based on an irrelevant ground i.e. on the
			<lb />
			allegations made against the appellant in the anonymous
			<lb />
			complaint. It is one thing to say that the employer is entitled to
			<lb />
			pass an order of transfer in administrative exigencies but it is
			<lb />
			another thing to say that the order of transfer is passed by way of
			<lb />
			or in lieu of punishment. When an order of transfer is passed in
			<lb />
			lieu of punishment, the same is liable to be set aside being wholly
			<lb />
			illegal.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis Supplied)
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.(C) 7615/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 8 of 10
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			13. In this case, as has been observed by the Tribunal that initially, three
			<lb />
			persons had lodged a police complaint against the petitioner No. 2 at the
			<lb />
			Police Station, Anand Vihar on 22 nd February, 2016. The Tribunal also
			<lb />
			noticed that within two days of lodging of the police complaint by three
			<lb />
			persons, all the three persons stood transferred. However, out of the three
			<lb />
			complainants, one Mr. Krishan Kumar has subsequently given a letter
			<lb />
			withdrawing his police complaint and hence, he was spared by the petitioner
			<lb />
			No.2. This observation by the Tribunal which finds mention in the impugned
			<lb />
			order has not been denied or clarified in the present petition. In fact, we find
			<lb />
			that the grounds in the writ petition have not addressed the question of
			<lb />
			malafide, which has been raised by the respondents before the Tribunal.
			<lb />
			Although, the petition is supported by the affidavit of the petitioner No. 2
			<lb />
			which, in our view, should have been filed by another officer, as specific
			<lb />
			allegations were raised against this officer and the grounds of the writ
			<lb />
			petition should have at least, clarified the following points :
			<lb />
			(i)
			<lb />
			as to whether, the three complaints were lodged with the police
			<lb />
			or not;
			<lb />
			(ii) as to whether the three orders of transfer were subsequently
			<lb />
			issued;
			<lb />
			(iii) as to whether Mr. Krishan Kumar, the third complainant
			<lb />
			withdrew his complaint;
			<lb />
			(iv) as to whether after the withdrawal of complaint by Mr. Krishan
			<lb />
			Kumar, his transfer orders were withdrawn or not;
			<lb />
			(v) as to what steps were taken by the higher authorities to examine
			<lb />
			the complaints made by the two respondents.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.(C) 7615/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 9 of 10
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			14. It has been submitted before us that copies of the complaints were not
			<lb />
			marked to the higher authorities, hence should not have been relied upon. In
			<lb />
			our view, the copies of the complaints may or may not have been marked to
			<lb />
			the CMD but once, the matter had reached the Court and specific allegation
			<lb />
			was made against petitioner No.2, it cannot be said that the senior officers
			<lb />
			were not aware of the stand taken by the two respondents in the O.A. There
			<lb />
			is nothing on record to show that the CMD or any other higher officer above
			<lb />
			the petitioner No. 2 took note of the police complaint when two employees
			<lb />
			of MTNL had the courage to specifically make allegations of extortion of
			<lb />
			money by a senior officer. The department was duty bound to look into the
			<lb />
			matter and, if there was any truth in the complaints, they should have ordered
			<lb />
			an independent inquiry and, if there was no truth in the complaint, then the
			<lb />
			note sheet of the file would have given the reasons as to why after the third
			<lb />
			complainant withdrew his complaint and why his orders of transfer were
			<lb />
			withdrawn and the note sheet would have also revealed as to what was the
			<lb />
			exigency or public interest in passing the transfer orders of the respondents
			<lb />
			or what was the basis of passing of the transfer orders of respondents and
			<lb />
			these reasons should have been at least mentioned in the record maintained
			<lb />
			by the petitioners. We are not able to get any satisfactory answer with regard
			<lb />
			to the above queries. The law on transfer of an employee is well settled. The
			<lb />
			courts should not interefere with the orders on transfer unless the same
			<lb />
			suffers from malafide. However, in the facts of the present case and in the
			<lb />
			absence of any clarification from the petitioners to dispel the stand taken by
			<lb />
			the respondents as noticed by the Tribunal and even in the writ petition, we
			<lb />
			are left with no option but to dismiss this writ petition.
			<lb />
			15. We also direct the CMD of the petitioner No. 1 to look into the police
			<lb />
			complaints made by the respondents, examine them and if there is any truth
			<lb />
			in them, take appropriate action in accordance with law.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.(C) 7615/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 10 of 10
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			16. In view of the above, the writ petition being devoid of merits is hereby
			<lb />
			dismissed with costs of Rs. 10,000/-to be deposited by the petitioners with
			<lb />
			the Delhi High Court Legal Services Commmittee.
			<lb />
			CM No. 31395/2016 (Stay)
			<lb />
			17. In view of the order passed in the writ petition, the stay application
			<lb />
			stands dismissed being infrutuous.
			<lb />
			G.S.SISTANI
			<lb />
			(JUDGE)
			<lb />
			I.S. MEHTA
			<lb />
			(JUDGE)
			<lb />
			AUGUST 29, 2016/j
		</body>


	</text>
</tei>