<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			FAO 228/2016
			<lb />
			Page 1 of 11
			<lb />
			$~7
			<lb />
			* IN THE HIGH COURT OF DELHI AT NEW DELHI
			<lb />
			%
			<lb />
			Date of Decision: 19 th April, 2018
			<lb />
			+
			<lb />
			FAO 228/2016 and C.M. Appl. 18806/2016
			<lb />
			SUBHASH CHAUDHARY
			<lb />
			..... Appellant
			<lb />
			Through: Appellant in person.
			<lb />
			versus
			<lb />
			NIRMALA DEVI &amp; ORS
			<lb />
			..... Respondents
			<lb />
			Through: Mr. R.K. Nain, Advocate
			<lb />
		</front>

		<body>
			CORAM:
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE J.R. MIDHA
			<lb />
			JUDGMENT (ORAL)
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			The appellant has challenged the order dated 15 th November, 2016
			<lb />
			passed by the Commissioner, Employees&apos; Compensation whereby
			<lb />
			compensation of Rs.6,77,760/-along with interest @ 12% per annum has
			<lb />
			been awarded to respondents no.1 to 3.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			The appellant is the owner of property bearing No.RZ-B-30, Mahavir
			<lb />
			Vihar, Sector-1, Dwarka, New Delhi and he was constructing the second
			<lb />
			floor of the said property through the contractor (respondent No.4) in
			<lb />
			September, 2014. On 04 th September, 2014 at about 08:45 A.M., two
			<lb />
			labourers namely, Laxmi Pandit and Ramesh were pulling an iron window
			<lb />
			frame using a rope from the second floor of the building when the rope
			<lb />
			suddenly broke down due to the heavy weight of the iron window frame and
			<lb />
			both the labourers fell down and suffered fatal injuries. The police
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			FAO 228/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 2 of 11
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			registered FIR No.560/2014 under Sections 288/337/304 IPC at P.S. Dwarka
			<lb />
			against the contractor.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			The deceased, Laxmi Pandit was survived by his widow and two
			<lb />
			minor daughters who filed an application for compensation before the
			<lb />
			Commissioner, Employees&apos; Compensation. The appellant contested the
			<lb />
			application on the ground that he had awarded the contract for construction
			<lb />
			of the residential house to respondent No.4, who alone is liable to pay
			<lb />
			compensation. The appellant disputed the relationship of employment with
			<lb />
			the deceased. The appellant further pleaded that the deceased was a casual
			<lb />
			worker. It was further pleaded that the construction of the residential house
			<lb />
			was not for his trade and business and, therefore, the appellant was not liable
			<lb />
			to pay compensation to the respondent no.1 to 3.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			The Commissioner, Employees&apos; Compensation held that the deceased
			<lb />
			suffered fatal injuries in the accident during the construction of the
			<lb />
			residential house of the appellant and the accident arose out of and during
			<lb />
			the course of his employment. The Commissioner, Employees&apos;
			<lb />
			Compensation held that respondents No.1 to 3 were entitled to compensation
			<lb />
			of Rs.6,77,760/-along with interest @ 12% per annum. The Commissioner
			<lb />
			held the appellant liable to pay compensation to respondents No.1 to 3. The
			<lb />
			Commissioner observed that appellant being the principal employer is liable
			<lb />
			to indemnify the respondents No.1 to 3 with liberty to recover the same from
			<lb />
			respondent No.4 under Section 12 (2) of the Employee&apos;s Compensation Act
			<lb />
			but did not grant recovery rights to the appellant.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			Vide order dated 17 th January, 2018, this Court initiated the penalty
			<lb />
			proceedings against the appellant and issued a show cause notice to the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			FAO 228/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 3 of 11
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			appellant under Section 4A(3) of the Employees Compensation Act to which
			<lb />
			the appellant has filed the reply.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			The appellant submits that he had awarded the contract for
			<lb />
			construction of the second floor of his residential house to respondent No.4
			<lb />
			who should be held liable to pay the compensation. It is further submitted
			<lb />
			that the penalty should not be imposed on the appellant considering that the
			<lb />
			appellant has already deposited the compensation amount along with interest
			<lb />
			@ 12% per annum. The appellant further submits that he took the deceased
			<lb />
			to the hospital in his car and provided all possible medical help to the
			<lb />
			deceased and, therefore, a lenient view should be taken with respect to
			<lb />
			amount of penalty.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			The law with respect to the liability of the owner of the building to
			<lb />
			pay the compensation to the legal representatives of the worker who dies
			<lb />
			during the construction of a residential house is well settled. Reference is
			<lb />
			made to the recent judgment of this Court in Krishan v. Jasoda Devi, 2017
			<lb />
			SCC OnLine Del 11137. Relevant portion of Krishan v. Jasoda Devi
			<lb />
			(supra) is reproduced hereunder:
			<lb />
			&quot;43. Summary of Principles
			<lb />
			43.1.
			<lb />
			The Employees&quot; Compensation Act, 1923 is a piece of
			<lb />
			social beneficial legislation and its provisions have to be
			<lb />
			interpreted in a manner so as not to deprive the employees of
			<lb />
			the benefit of the legislation.
			<lb />
			43.2.
			<lb />
			The object for enacting the Employees&quot; Compensation
			<lb />
			Act even as early as 1923 was to ameliorate the hardship of
			<lb />
			economically poor employees who were exposed to risks in
			<lb />
			work, or occupational hazards by providing a cheaper and
			<lb />
			quicker machinery for compensating them with pecuniary
			<lb />
			benefits.
			<lb />
			43.3.
			<lb />
			Section 12 safeguards the right to compensation when
			<lb />
			the employer delegates the work to another person. Section
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			FAO 228/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 4 of 11
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			12 is intended to secure to an employee the right to claim
			<lb />
			compensation not only against his immediate employer who, in
			<lb />
			the Act, is referred to as a contractor, but also against the
			<lb />
			person who had employed such contractor to execute the
			<lb />
			work. The Act refers to him as the principal.
			<lb />
			43.4.
			<lb />
			The main object of enacting Section 12 of the Act is to
			<lb />
			secure compensation to the employees who have been engaged
			<lb />
			by the principal employer through the contractor for the work
			<lb />
			which the principal employer is supposed to carry out by his
			<lb />
			own employees. If a person substitutes another for himself to do
			<lb />
			his work, he ought not to escape the liability which would have
			<lb />
			been imposed upon him, if he had done it himself.
			<lb />
			43.5.
			<lb />
			The intention of the Legislature in enacting Section 12
			<lb />
			provision appears to be that the injured employee or the
			<lb />
			dependent of a deceased employee who has been awarded
			<lb />
			compensation by the Commissioner, should not be put to any
			<lb />
			difficulty in realising such amount of compensation on account
			<lb />
			of any recalcitrance of the employer or on account of the
			<lb />
			vicissitudes of his (the employer&quot;s) financial position.
			<lb />
			43.6.
			<lb />
			Section 12 of the Act has, in effect, stretched the
			<lb />
			contours of the word &quot;employer&quot; wider as to include the person
			<lb />
			contracting with another person for carrying out the work of
			<lb />
			the former. In such cases, the provision enjoins that the
			<lb />
			principal shall stand substituted as the employer. This is
			<lb />
			achieved by the words &quot;where compensation is claimed from
			<lb />
			the principal, this Act shall apply as if references to the
			<lb />
			principal were substituted for references to the employer&quot;. The
			<lb />
			principal may have a claim for indemnity from his contractor
			<lb />
			or delegatee but the victim or his dependents are not to be
			<lb />
			involved in such disputes.
			<lb />
			43.7.
			<lb />
			Section 12 will apply notwithstanding the agreement
			<lb />
			or contract entered into between the principal and contractor
			<lb />
			regarding their liability for payment of compensation under the
			<lb />
			Act. The agreement or contract between the principal and the
			<lb />
			contractor shall govern only their inter-se rights and liabilities,
			<lb />
			and cannot affect the right of the employee or the dependants of
			<lb />
			the employee, to get the compensation from the principal or
			<lb />
			from the contractor at their option.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			FAO 228/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 5 of 11
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			43.8.
			<lb />
			Section 12 shall apply even in cases of several tiers of
			<lb />
			employers or petty contractors. It is a matter of common
			<lb />
			knowledge that contractors in turn employ other petty
			<lb />
			contractors working under their direction and an employee may
			<lb />
			be actually employed by one of these aforesaid persons and in
			<lb />
			such a case, there may be no direct privity of contract between
			<lb />
			the principal and the employee in the last analysis. The
			<lb />
			employee has, for all practical purposes to deal with an
			<lb />
			immediate employer but when it comes to lodging a legal claim
			<lb />
			for compensation on account of an accident, he is concerned
			<lb />
			with the principal employer and not the immediate
			<lb />
			employer qua the employee.
			<lb />
			43.9.
			<lb />
			In case of the multiplicity of immediate and indirect or
			<lb />
			remote employers/contractors, Section 12 relieves an employee
			<lb />
			of the difficulty of ascertaining with precision as to who should
			<lb />
			be deemed to be the actual employer liable for compensation
			<lb />
			under the Act. The purport of Section 12 is to create a deemed
			<lb />
			employer-employee relationship between the principal
			<lb />
			employer and the employee of the immediate employer who is
			<lb />
			brought in by the principal employer as his contractor.
			<lb />
			43.10. Section 12 secures compensation to the employee who
			<lb />
			cannot fight out his battle for compensation by a speedy
			<lb />
			process. A person who employs others to advance his own
			<lb />
			interest is expected to provide a surer basis for payment of the
			<lb />
			injured employee than the intermediary, who may often turn out
			<lb />
			to be a man of straw, from whom compensation may not be
			<lb />
			available. This is the purpose for which the claimant is given
			<lb />
			the option under section 12(3) of the Act to claim the
			<lb />
			compensation either from the principal or from the contractor.
			<lb />
			43.11. The contractor may not be a man of means or he may
			<lb />
			be merely a man of straw or it may be that wittingly or
			<lb />
			unwittingly he may possibly be part of an arrangement
			<lb />
			conceived by the principal to avoid confrontation directly with
			<lb />
			the employee engaged in the execution of the work. In either
			<lb />
			case, the interests of the employee need to be protected and that
			<lb />
			is what the provision secures to the employee. The principal
			<lb />
			can seek indemnification from the contractor if he has been
			<lb />
			made answerable for the payment of compensation. The right of
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			FAO 228/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 6 of 11
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			the principal to be indemnified has thus been incorporated
			<lb />
			under Section 12(2), who has entrusted the work to the
			<lb />
			contractor stipulating the right of indemnification under the
			<lb />
			Act.
			<lb />
			43.12. Section 12 of the Act gives protection to the employee
			<lb />
			in case of an accident and secures compensation from the
			<lb />
			persons who can pay, so that such employee will not be
			<lb />
			dependent upon a petty contractor(s) who may themselves not
			<lb />
			be able to pay compensation on account of their financial
			<lb />
			inability.
			<lb />
			43.13. Section 12 is an enabling provision for the benefit of
			<lb />
			the employee(s) and enacted with the clear objective that the
			<lb />
			employee(s) should not be hampered by technicalities or
			<lb />
			practical difficulties of deciphering the correct employers. A
			<lb />
			pragmatic method has thus been devised for fixing the liability
			<lb />
			of the principal employer and thereby affording speedy relief to
			<lb />
			the employee for payment of compensation on account of the
			<lb />
			accident, though the principal has been invested with the right
			<lb />
			of indemnifying himself from the contractor who may have
			<lb />
			employed the employee and may have been responsible for
			<lb />
			immediately taking work from him.
			<lb />
			43.14. The words &quot;trade&quot; or &quot;business&quot; used in Section 12
			<lb />
			of the Act have to be understood in the context in which this Act
			<lb />
			was enacted. The Act was enacted to provide compensation to
			<lb />
			the employees suffering during the course of their employment.
			<lb />
			It was also the purpose of the Act that employees should get
			<lb />
			speedy remedies and it appears that the intention of enacting
			<lb />
			the Section 12 of the Act was only to ensure that compensation
			<lb />
			is paid by the principal expeditiously and if this purpose of the
			<lb />
			Act and the provision are kept in mind, then the words &quot;trade&quot;
			<lb />
			or &quot;business&quot; may not have the same meaning which it would
			<lb />
			have, for instance, when used in interpreting a taxing statute.
			<lb />
			43.15. The words &quot;trade&quot; or &quot;business&quot; are used in several
			<lb />
			statutes like fiscal statutes, taxing statues and rent laws. The
			<lb />
			meaning ascribed to such words shall always be with reference
			<lb />
			to the context and with respect to the content of the statute
			<lb />
			itself, Therefore, the meaning that is ascribed in one statute
			<lb />
			cannot be taken to interpret the very same words in another
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			FAO 228/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 7 of 11
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			statute legislated with altogether a different intention and
			<lb />
			object. The said words in the fiscal statutes or rent laws cannot
			<lb />
			have a similar meaning when employed in any welfare
			<lb />
			legislation like Employee&quot;s Compensation Act.
			<lb />
			43.16. The term &quot;trade&quot; or &quot;business&quot; would not have been
			<lb />
			used in Section 12(1) to mean the same, though in certain
			<lb />
			contexts they may bear the same meaning. The very fact that
			<lb />
			both these terms are employed in the section would indicate
			<lb />
			that they connote different ideas and they do not cover the
			<lb />
			identical field, &quot;trade&quot; as generally understood means activities
			<lb />
			of buying and selling and the business which is related to such
			<lb />
			buying and selling, whereas &quot;business&quot; is a term of much larger
			<lb />
			import.
			<lb />
			43.17. The word &quot;trade&quot; connotes commercial activity
			<lb />
			whereas the word &quot;business&quot; is of much wider import and may
			<lb />
			be used in different contexts in different senses. Used in one
			<lb />
			context, it may imply a particular occupation or employment to
			<lb />
			earn livelihood or gain, whereas used in a different context it
			<lb />
			may mean an activity which engages time, attention, or labour
			<lb />
			as a principal serious concern or interest. Its connotation may
			<lb />
			thus vary with the varying contexts in which it is used. In taxing
			<lb />
			statutes for instance, the word &quot;business&quot; will always denote an
			<lb />
			activity carried out with the object of earning profit, though the
			<lb />
			same may not be true when used in relation to other activities.
			<lb />
			Used in broader sense, a person building his residential house
			<lb />
			or a Government constructing a road, may well be said to do
			<lb />
			&quot;business&quot; in so far as the said activity engages his or its time,
			<lb />
			attention or labour as principal serious concern or interest.
			<lb />
			43.18. The meaning of these two crucial words in Section
			<lb />
			12 has to be understood in the context of its object. The word
			<lb />
			&quot;business&quot; in the Section need not be restricted to what is
			<lb />
			synonymous with &quot;trade&quot;. The use of the conjunction &quot;or&quot;
			<lb />
			should be understood as disjunctive for covering totally
			<lb />
			different areas unconnected with &quot;trade&quot;. The word &quot;business&quot;
			<lb />
			has different shades of meanings. Among them, the most
			<lb />
			suitable in the present context is that which &quot;The Oxford
			<lb />
			Advanced Learners Dictionary of Current English&quot; has given
			<lb />
			as its third meaning: &quot;Task, duty, concern or undertaking to do
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			FAO 228/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 8 of 11
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			a work&quot;. The word &quot;business&quot; in its wider connotation may
			<lb />
			have more extensive meaning than the word &quot;trade&quot;. Lord
			<lb />
			Jessel M.R. in Smith v. Anaerson, 1880 15 Ch D 247, stressed
			<lb />
			the meaning of &quot;business&quot; as &quot;anything which occupies the time
			<lb />
			and attention and labour of a man for the purpose of profit&quot;.
			<lb />
			Some succinct illustrations have also been given in the said
			<lb />
			dictionary to drive the meaning home. They are: &quot;It is a
			<lb />
			teacher&apos;s business to help his pupils; I still make it my business
			<lb />
			to see that money is paid promptly; that is no business of
			<lb />
			yours&quot;. In none of the illustrations, the word &quot;business&quot; is used
			<lb />
			to denote anything connected with trade or commerce. The
			<lb />
			word &quot;business&quot; used in Section 12 of the Act has been
			<lb />
			intended to convey the meaning &quot;the work or task undertaken
			<lb />
			by the person concerned&quot; which is not restricted to trade or
			<lb />
			commercial work alone.
			<lb />
			43.19. The word &quot;ordinarily&quot; is an elastic term. It is seen to
			<lb />
			be used in different statutes. The word has different shades of
			<lb />
			meaning in different contexts. The word &quot;ordinarily&quot; is
			<lb />
			employed in Section 12 of the Act for a different connotation.
			<lb />
			That has to be understood in the background of the preceding
			<lb />
			portion in the Section 12 wherein execution of the work carried
			<lb />
			out through any other person contracted by the principal for
			<lb />
			this purpose is mentioned. What the principal would have done
			<lb />
			if he would not have contracted with another person to carry
			<lb />
			out that work? He himself would have normally done that work
			<lb />
			or caused it to be done under his supervision. The word
			<lb />
			&quot;ordinarily&quot; is used in Section 12 for projecting this idea. So
			<lb />
			the word &quot;ordinarily&quot; in Section 12 means &quot;otherwise,
			<lb />
			normally&quot;. No other meaning can be conferred to the term
			<lb />
			&quot;ordinarily&quot; as it appears in Section 12.
			<lb />
			43.20. Applying the rules of liberal and purposive
			<lb />
			interpretation, superior purpose and felt necessity, the word
			<lb />
			&quot;business&quot; occurring in Section 12 is given an extended
			<lb />
			meaning, so as to include even an activity which engages time,
			<lb />
			attention, or labour. Hence, construction of a residential house
			<lb />
			would be covered in Section 12. This Court agrees with the
			<lb />
			view taken by the different High Courts in the judgments
			<lb />
			discussed herein above.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			FAO 228/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 9 of 11
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			43.21. If the person who employs contractor is allowed to
			<lb />
			evade his liability by raising the defence that only the
			<lb />
			contractor or the intermediary should pay the compensation,
			<lb />
			then Section 12 will become redundant.
			<lb />
			43.22. This interpretation finds support from the amendment
			<lb />
			of Section 2(1)(n) of the Act (vide Workmen&quot;s Compensation
			<lb />
			(Amendment) Act, 2000) by including casual employees and
			<lb />
			employees employed other than for the purposes of employer&apos;s
			<lb />
			trade or business in the definition of &quot;employee&quot;.
			<lb />
			43.23. The definition of &quot;employee&quot; envisaged in Section 2
			<lb />
			(1) (n) of the said Act has undergone drastic change. Prior to
			<lb />
			the amendment, an employee whose employment was of a
			<lb />
			casual nature and who was employed otherwise than for the
			<lb />
			purpose of trade or business of the employer; did not fall in the
			<lb />
			said definition. However, after the amendment of the said
			<lb />
			definition through the Amending Act 46 of 2000, the Parliament
			<lb />
			had removed the said mischief which was then prevailing and
			<lb />
			coming in the way of such casual employee who met with an
			<lb />
			accident during the course of the employment unconnected with
			<lb />
			the employer&apos;s trade or business. With the amendment of the
			<lb />
			said definition, now an employee whose employment is of
			<lb />
			casual nature and who is employed otherwise than for the
			<lb />
			purpose of employer&quot;s trade or business is certainly covered
			<lb />
			within the definition of employee.
			<lb />
			43.24. Applying the rules of literal and purposive
			<lb />
			interpretation, superior purpose and felt necessity, this Court is
			<lb />
			of the view that the casual employees and employees employed
			<lb />
			otherwise than for the purposes of the employer&quot;s trade or
			<lb />
			business are entitled to all the benefits of the Employee&quot;s
			<lb />
			Compensation Act including that of Section 12 of the Act. This
			<lb />
			Court agrees with the view taken by this Court in Govind
			<lb />
			Goenka v. Dayawati (supra).&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis Supplied)
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			This case is squarely covered by the principles laid down by this
			<lb />
			Court in the aforesaid judgment. The appellant being the principal employer
			<lb />
			cum owner is liable under Section 12 of the Employees Compensation Act
			<lb />
			to pay the compensation to the legal representatives of the deceased, Laxmi
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			FAO 228/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 10 of 11
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Pandit who suffered an accident arising out of and during the course of his
			<lb />
			employment with the contractor while constructing the appellant&apos;s house.
			<lb />
			There is no infirmity in the award of compensation of Rs.6,77,760/-along
			<lb />
			with interest @ 12% per annum passed by the Commissioner, Employees
			<lb />
			Compensation. The impugned award of the Commissioner, Employees&apos;
			<lb />
			Compensation is upheld. However, recovery rights are granted to the
			<lb />
			appellant to recover the compensation amount from respondent No.4.
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			With respect to the issue of penalty, a lenient view is taken against the
			<lb />
			appellant, who took the deceased to the hospital immediately after the
			<lb />
			accident and extended all possible help to save the life of the deceased. In
			<lb />
			that view of the matter, penalty of Rs.1,60,000/-is imposed on the appellant
			<lb />
			under Section 4A(3) of the Employees Compensation Act. The appellant is
			<lb />
			directed to deposit the penalty amount with the Registrar General of this
			<lb />
			Court within four weeks.
			<lb />
			10. The appeal is dismissed. Pending application is disposed of.
			<lb />
			11. List for disbursement of the balance compensation amount as well as
			<lb />
			penalty amount on 30 th May, 2018.
			<lb />
			12. Learned counsel for the respondents shall furnish the particulars of the
			<lb />
			savings bank accounts of respondents No.2 and 3 near the place of their
			<lb />
			residence on the next date of hearing. The concerned bank of respondents
			<lb />
			No.2 and 3 is directed not to issue any cheque book or debit card to
			<lb />
			respondents No.2 and 3 and if the same have already been issued, the bank is
			<lb />
			directed to cancel the same and make an endorsement on their passbooks to
			<lb />
			this effect. Respondents No.2 and 3 shall produce the copy of this order to
			<lb />
			the concerned bank, whereupon the bank shall make an endorsement on the
			<lb />
			passbooks of respondents No.2 and 3 that no cheque book and/or debit card
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			FAO 228/2016
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 11 of 11
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			shall be issued to respondents No.2 and 3 without the permission of this
			<lb />
			Court. However, the concerned bank shall permit respondents No.2 and 3 to
			<lb />
			withdraw money from their savings bank account by means of a withdrawal
			<lb />
			form. The respondents No.2 and 3 shall produce the original passbooks of
			<lb />
			their individual savings bank account with the necessary endorsement on the
			<lb />
			next date of hearing.
			<lb />
			13. Copy of this judgement be given dasti to parties under signatures of
			<lb />
			the Court Master.
			<lb />
			APRIL 19, 2018
			<lb />
			J.R.MIDHA, J.
			<lb />
			rsk
		</body>


	</text>
</tei>