<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			958-wp-2159-22
			<lb />
			1
			<lb />
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF JUDICATURE AT BOMBAY
			<lb />
			BENCH AT AURANGABAD
			<lb />
			WRIT PETITION NO.2159 OF 2022
			<lb />
			1. Gopalkrishna S/o. Digambarrao Kulkarni,
			<lb />
			Age: 51 years, Occ.: Business and Agri.,
			<lb />
			R/o Nimbhora, Tq. Kannad, at present
			<lb />
			Mauli Nagar, in front of Datta Mandir and
			<lb />
			Ganpati Mandir, Beed Bypass, Aurangabad.
			<lb />
			2. Ramkrishna S/.. Digambarrao Kulkarni,
			<lb />
			Age: 35 years, Occ.: Business and Agri.,
			<lb />
			R/o. Siemens Company Housing Society,
			<lb />
			Bajaj Nagar, Aurangabad.
			<lb />
			3. Bhagyashree Gopalkrishna Kulkarni,
			<lb />
			Age: 51 years, Occ.: Housewife,
			<lb />
			R/o Nimbhora, Tq. Kannad, at present
			<lb />
			Mauli Nagar, in front of Datta Mandir and
			<lb />
			Ganpati Mandir, Beed Bypass, Aurangabad.
			<lb />
			4. Dhanshree Ramkrishna Kulkarni,
			<lb />
			Age: 27 years, Occ.: Housewife,
			<lb />
			R/o. Siemens Company Housing Society,
			<lb />
			Bajaj Nagar, Aurangabad.
			<lb />
			... Petitioners
			<lb />
			Versus
			<lb />
			1. Rajshekhar S/o. Digambarrao Kulkarni,
			<lb />
			Age: 45 years, Occu: Business and Agri.,
			<lb />
			R/o Nimbhora, Tq. Kannad,
			<lb />
			Dist. Aurangabad at present,
			<lb />
			Plot No.32, Jawahar Colony, Hivarkhede
			<lb />
			Road, Kannad.
			<lb />
			2. Chandrashekhar S/o. Digambarrao Kulkarni,
			<lb />
			Age : 40 years, Occu.: Business and Agri.,
			<lb />
			R/o. Nimbhora, Tq. Kannad,
			<lb />
			Dist. Aurangabad, at present Sneh Nagar,
			<lb />
			behind Old High Court Building, Auranabad
			<lb />
			(Original plaintiff Nos. 1 and 2)
			<lb />
			1 of 7
			<lb />
			::: Uploaded on -25/02/2022
			<lb />
			::: Downloaded on -19/03/2022 09:57:39 :::
			<lb />
			958-wp-2159-22
			<lb />
			2
			<lb />
			3. Lilabai W/o Arunrao Bendre,
			<lb />
			Age: 50 years, Occ.: Housewife,
			<lb />
			R/o Varud Kaji via Chilkalthana,
			<lb />
			Tq. &amp; Dist. Aurangabad.
			<lb />
			4. Ashwini W/o. Arunrao Pade,
			<lb />
			Age: 47 years, Occu.: Housewife,
			<lb />
			R/o. Brahmin Galli Gangapur,
			<lb />
			Tq. Gangapur, Dist. Aurangabad.
			<lb />
			5. Sau. Prabhavati Pramodrao Kulkarni,
			<lb />
			Age: 42 years, Occu: Housewife,
			<lb />
			R/o. Brahmin Galli Soygaon,
			<lb />
			Tq. Soygaon, Dist. Aurangabad.
			<lb />
			6. Laxman S/o Tanhaji Sonawne,
			<lb />
			Age: 40 years, Occu. Agri.,
			<lb />
			R/o. Nimbhora, Tq. Kannad,
			<lb />
			Dist. Aurangabad.
			<lb />
			7. Bajirao S/o. Gavnaji Ghuge,
			<lb />
			Age: 45 years, Occu. Agri.,
			<lb />
			R/o. Nimbhora, Tq. Kannad,
			<lb />
			Dist. Aurangabad.
			<lb />
			8. Hasusabai W/o. Narayan Sonawne,
			<lb />
			Age: 55 years, Occu. Housewife,
			<lb />
			R/o. Nimbhora, Tq. Kannad,
			<lb />
			Dist. Aurangabad.
			<lb />
			8/1. Ashok S/o Narayan Sonawane,
			<lb />
			Age: 53 years, Occu. Agri.,
			<lb />
			R/o. Nimbhora, Tq. Kannad,
			<lb />
			Dist. Aurangabad.
			<lb />
			8/2. Sanjay S/o Narayan Sonawne,
			<lb />
			Age: 45 years, Occu. Agri.,
			<lb />
			R/o. Nimbhora, Tq. Kannad,
			<lb />
			Dist. Aurangabad.
			<lb />
			2 of 7
			<lb />
			::: Uploaded on -25/02/2022
			<lb />
			::: Downloaded on -19/03/2022 09:57:39 :::
			<lb />
			958-wp-2159-22
			<lb />
			3
			<lb />
			8/3. Balu @ Dnyaneshwar S/o Narayan Sonwane,
			<lb />
			Age: 42 years, Occu. Agri.,
			<lb />
			R/o. Nimbhora, Tq. Kannad,
			<lb />
			Dist. Aurangabad.
			<lb />
			8/4. Sau. Sharda W/o. Vasudeo Tonde,
			<lb />
			Age: 51 years, Occu: Housewife,
			<lb />
			R/o. By Vasudeo Jankiram Tonde,
			<lb />
			Teacher, Savitribai Phule Girss School,
			<lb />
			Tq. Kannad, Dist. Aurangabad.
			<lb />
			8/5. Sau. Akka @ Sunanda Bhausahb Khade,
			<lb />
			Age: 38 years, Occu: Housewife,
			<lb />
			R/o. Kandari, Tq. Bhokardan,
			<lb />
			Dist. Jalna.
			<lb />
			… Respondents.
			<lb />
			....
			<lb />
			Mr. P.N. Sonpethkar, Advocate for the Petitioners
			<lb />
			Mr. Vikrant Palsikar, Advocate for Advocate Respondent No.1
			<lb />
			….
			<lb />
		</front>

		<body>
			CORAM : SHRIKANT D. KULKARNI, J.
			<lb />
			DATE : 15 th FEBRUARY, 2022
			<lb />
			ORAL JUDGMENT :-
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			Rule. Rule made returnable forthwith. Heard finally with
			<lb />
			the consent of both the sides.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			The petitioners have challenged the impugned order passed
			<lb />
			below exhibit 1 in R.C.S. No. 144 of 2008 by 2 nd Joint Civil Judge,
			<lb />
			Junior Division at Kannad.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			3 of 7
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Uploaded on -25/02/2022
			<lb />
			::: Downloaded on -19/03/2022 09:57:39 :::
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="headnote">
			958-wp-2159-22
			<lb />
			4
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			4 of 7
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Uploaded on -25/02/2022
			<lb />
			::: Downloaded on -19/03/2022 09:57:39 :::
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			3.
			<lb />
			Mr. Sonpethkar, learned counsel for the petitioners invited
			<lb />
			my attention to the impugned order and submitted that the suit
			<lb />
			was fixed for final argument. The trial Court has framed additional
			<lb />
			issues 6-A and 6-B without giving an opportunity of being heard to
			<lb />
			either side. It has caused serious prejudice to the rights and
			<lb />
			interest of the parties. He submitted that the Court has ample
			<lb />
			power to frame additional issues or strike out any issue even
			<lb />
			before passing the decree. But that exercise needs to be done after
			<lb />
			giving an opportunity of hearing to both the sides. He submitted
			<lb />
			that the suit came to be adjourned on number of occasions for final
			<lb />
			arguments and all of a sudden, this impugned order regarding
			<lb />
			framing of additional issues came to be passed by the trial Court.
			<lb />
			The impugned order below exhibit 1 in R.C.S. No. 144 of 2008
			<lb />
			does not sustain in the eyes of law and it needs to be quashed and
			<lb />
			set aside.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Mr. Palsikar, learned counsel for respondent no.1 /
			<lb />
			contesting party vehemently submitted that the suit is old one. The
			<lb />
			Court has given sufficient opportunity and thereafter passed the
			<lb />
			impugned order and framed two additional issues after taking into
			<lb />
			consideration the amendment made in the plaint. He has also
			<lb />
			invited my attention to the copy of plaint, more particularly para
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			958-wp-2159-22
			<lb />
			5
			<lb />

		</note>
		<page>
			5 of 7
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Uploaded on -25/02/2022
			<lb />
			::: Downloaded on -19/03/2022 09:57:39 :::
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			no. 3-a and 4-a. He submitted that the additional issues came to be
			<lb />
			framed in order to cover the entire controversy between the parties
			<lb />
			and to have a finding on it. No injustice is caused to the
			<lb />
			petitioners. He supported the impugned order passed by the trial
			<lb />
			Court.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			I have considered the submissions of the learned counsel
			<lb />
			for both the sides. I have also gone through the provisions of Order
			<lb />
			XV Rule 1 and Rule 5 of the Civil Procedure Code. There cannot
			<lb />
			be a debate that the trial Court has ample power to frame
			<lb />
			additional issues as well as strike out any issue before passing the
			<lb />
			decree. That exercise needs to be done in order to decide the
			<lb />
			controversy between the parties completely and finally. Order XV
			<lb />
			Rule 1 speaks that framing of issues is not an empty formality. The
			<lb />
			trial Court is required to hear both the parties before framing
			<lb />
			issues or additional issues. That exercise is important.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			On perusing the impugned order, it is very much clear that
			<lb />
			the trial Court has framed two additional issues 6-A and 6-B when
			<lb />
			the suit was fixed for final argument. It further appears from the
			<lb />
			impugned order that opportunity of hearing is not given to both
			<lb />
			the sides before framing additional issues. The impugned order has
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			6 of 7
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Uploaded on -25/02/2022
			<lb />
			::: Downloaded on -19/03/2022 09:57:39 :::
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="headnote">
			958-wp-2159-22
			<lb />
			6
		</note>
		<body>
			<lb />
			certainly caused prejudice to the rights and interest to both the
			<lb />
			sides. It was very much necessary on the part of the learned trial
			<lb />
			Judge to extend an opportunity of being heard to both the sides
			<lb />
			before framing additional issues in view of the provisions of Order
			<lb />
			XV Rule 1 and Rule 5 of the Civil Procedure Code. Framing of
			<lb />
			issues is a very important stage of Civil trial. It is imperative for a
			<lb />
			trial Court Judge to critically examine the pleadings of the parties
			<lb />
			before framing of issues. Order XIV Rule 2 of the Civil Procedure
			<lb />
			Code allows the trial Court Judge to go to the genesis of the lis and
			<lb />
			narrow down or even eliminate the controversy. For that exercise,
			<lb />
			opportunity must be given to both the sides to assist the Court to
			<lb />
			narrow down the controversy.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			Certainly, the impugned order does not sustain in the eyes
			<lb />
			of law. It has caused serious prejudice to both parties to the suit.
			<lb />
			The impugned order needs to be quashed and set aside. It is
			<lb />
			necessary to issue directions to the trial Court to hear all the
			<lb />
			parties and then frame additional issues, if any, in order to cover
			<lb />
			the entire controversy between the parties. With this, I conclude
			<lb />
			and proceed to pass the following order.
			<lb />
			<body>
				
				<note place="headnote">
					958-wp-2159-22
					<lb />
					7
					<lb />
				</note>
				<page>
					7 of 7
					<lb />
				</page>
				<note place="footnote">
					::: Uploaded on -25/02/2022
					<lb />
					::: Downloaded on -19/03/2022 09:57:39 :::
				</note>
			</body>
			O R D E R
			<lb />
			(i)
			<lb />
			The petition is hereby allowed.
			<lb />
			(ii) The impugned order passed below exhibit 1 in R.C.S. No.
			<lb />
			144 of 2008 passed by 2 nd Joint Civil Judge, Junior Division,
			<lb />
			Kannad is hereby quashed and set aside.
			<lb />
			(iii) The learned 2 nd Joint Civil Judge, Junior Division, Kannad is
			<lb />
			hereby directed to call all the parties to the suit before framing
			<lb />
			additional issues and give them an opportunity of being heard.
			<lb />
			After completing that exercise, 2 nd Joint Civil Judge, Junior
			<lb />
			Division, Kannad may frame additional issues, if any, having regard
			<lb />
			to the amendment made in the plaint from time to time.
			<lb />
			(iv) The exercise of hearing of all the parties and framing
			<lb />
			additional issues, if any, shall be completed within two weeks from
			<lb />
			the receipt of the writ of this Court.
			<lb />
			(v) The suit is now ready for argument and it should be
			<lb />
			disposed of as early as possible within one (01) month after
			<lb />
			completion of argument.
			<lb />
			(vi) The rule is made absolute in above terms.
			<lb />
			(vii) The writ petition is accordingly disposed of.
			<lb />
			[ SHRIKANT D. KULKARNI ]
			<lb />
			JUDGE
			<lb />
			S.P. Rane
			<lb />
		</body>


	</text>
</tei>