<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>HIGH COURT OF JUDICATURE FOR RAJASTHAN <lb/>AT JODHPUR <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 85/2020 <lb/>Ramji Lal Kulhari S/o Shri Chet Ram, Aged About 60 Years, R/o <lb/>Behind Radha Swami Satsang, Sharma Colony, Ward No. 24, <lb/>Churu-331001. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through Additional Chief Secretary To <lb/>Govt. Of Rajasthan Medical Health And Family Welfare <lb/>Department, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>The Joint Director, Medical And Health Services, Bikaner <lb/>Zone, Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>Additional Chief Medical And Health Officer (Family <lb/>Welfare), Churu, Distt. Churu. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>Connected With <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 2968/2019 <lb/>Kheenya Ram S/o Shri Uma Ram, Aged About 67 Years, Opp, <lb/>Choudhary Charan Singh Hostel, Tilak Nagar, Sagar Road, <lb/>Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, Colonisation <lb/>Department, Government Of Rajasthan, Secretariat, <lb/>Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>The Commissioner, Colonisation Department, Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>Tehsildar (Colonisation), Kolayat No. 2, Post Bajju, District <lb/>Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 2974/2019 <lb/>Prem Ratan Taneja S/o Shri Ganpat Ram Taneja, Aged About 59 <lb/>Years, R/o Ii E-202, Jnv Colony, District Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, School <lb/>Education Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/></front>
			
			<page> (2 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<front> Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, Secondary Education Department, Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 3841/2019 <lb/>Neelam Devani W/o Shri Nandlal Devani, Aged About 62 Years, <lb/>7-Ga-23, South Extension, Pawanpuri, District Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, School <lb/>Education Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>The Director, Secondary Education Department, Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>District <lb/>Education <lb/>Officer, <lb/>Secondary <lb/>Education <lb/>Department, Bikaner. <lb/>4. <lb/>Principal, Senior Sec. School Kalasar Dist. Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 3844/2019 <lb/>Kailash Sharma S/o Shri Mali Ram Sharma, Aged About 63 <lb/>Years, Nand Niketan, Jail Well, District Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, Finance <lb/>Department, Government Of Rajasthan, Secretariat, <lb/>Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>The Director, Treasuries And Accounts (D.t.a.) Rajasthan, <lb/>Jaipur. <lb/>3. <lb/>Director, Elementary Education Department, Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 3848/2019 <lb/>Nandlal Devani S/o Shri Naumal Devani, Aged About 64 Years, <lb/>7-Ga-23, Pawanpuri, South Extension, District Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, Command <lb/>Area Development And Wu Department, Government Of <lb/>Rajasthan, Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Commissioner, Command Area Development Department, <lb/></front>
			
			<page>(3 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<front> Ignp, Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>Chief Engineer (West), Command Area Development, <lb/>Bikaner. <lb/>4. <lb/>Superintending Engineer, Field Testing And Quality, <lb/>Control Circle, Command Area Development, Ignp, <lb/>Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 3852/2019 <lb/>Chand Ratan Mahatma S/o Shri Ramdas, Aged About 62 Years, <lb/>6-B-18, Pawanpuri, South Extension, District Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, Finance <lb/>Department, Government Of Rajasthan, Secretariat, <lb/>Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, Elementary Education Department, Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 4216/2019 <lb/>Mangla Ram S/o Shri Sukha Ram, Aged About 60 Years, Ward <lb/>No. 3, Near Bilal Masjid, Behind Circuit House, District Churu. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, School <lb/>Education Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, Secondary Education Department, Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>Deputy Director, Secondary Education, Churu Division, <lb/>Churu. <lb/>4. <lb/>District Education Officer, Secondary Education, Churu. <lb/>5. <lb/>Chief Block Education Officer, Churu, District Churu. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 4310/2019 <lb/>Om Prakash Sharma S/o Shri Padma Ram, Aged About 61 Years, <lb/>Chanakya Emporium, Jain Market, District Churu. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, School <lb/></front>
			
			<page>(4 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<front> Education Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, Secondary Education Department, Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>District Education Officer, Secondary Education, Churu. <lb/>4. <lb/> Chief Block Education Officer, Churu, District Churu. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 4312/2019 <lb/>Norang Ram Kaswan S/o Shri Teja Ram, Aged About 61 Years, <lb/>124 Van Vihar Colony, Road No. 3, District Churu. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, School <lb/>Education Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, Secondary Education Department, Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>District Education Officer, Secondary Education, Churu. <lb/>4. <lb/>Chief Block Education Officer, Churu, District Churu. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 4451/2019 <lb/>Ummed Singh Rathore S/o Shri Bhagwant Singh Rathore, Aged <lb/>About 60 Years, R/o Pragy Sadan, Ward No. 2, Gayatri Nagar, <lb/>District Churu. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, School <lb/>Education Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>The Director, Secondary Education Department, Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>The District Education Officer, Secondary Education, <lb/>Churu. <lb/>4. <lb/>Chief Block Education Officer, Churu, District Churu. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 4963/2019 <lb/>Chhatar Singh Dhuwan S/o Shri Peeru Ram, Aged About 61 <lb/>Years, R/o V.p.o. Jhadsar Chhota, Via Sadulpur, Tehsil Taranagar, <lb/>District Churu. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/></front>

			<page>(5 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<front> Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, School <lb/>Education Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, Secondary Education Department, Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>District Education Officer, Secondary Education, Churu. <lb/>4. <lb/>Chief Block Education Officer, Secondary Education, <lb/>Taranagar, District Churu. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 4983/2019 <lb/>Ratan Lal Sharma S/o Shri Bherudan, Aged About 61 Years, <lb/>Gopeshwar Basti, Gangashahar, Main Road, Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, Finance <lb/>Department, Government Of Rajasthan, Secretariat, <lb/>Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, Pension And Pensioners Welfare Department, <lb/>Vitta Bhawan, A Block, Janpath, Jaipur. <lb/>3. <lb/>Additional Director, Pension And Pensioners Welfare <lb/>Department, Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 5457/2019 <lb/>Kishan Kumar Kiradoo S/o Shri Ratan Lal Kiradoo, Aged About <lb/>60 Years, R/o Peerudan Kiradoo Street, Sale Ki Holi Ka Chowk, <lb/>District Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, School <lb/>Education Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, Secondary Education Department, Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>Deputy <lb/>Director <lb/>(Admn.), <lb/>Secondary <lb/>Education <lb/>Department, Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 5549/2019 <lb/>Madhu Sudan Kiradoo S/o Shri Shree Chand Kiradoo, Aged <lb/></front>
			
			<page>(6 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<front> About 60 Years, Near Chhota Gopal Temple, Dammani Chauk, <lb/>District Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, School <lb/>Education Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, Secondary Education Department, Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>Deputy <lb/>Director <lb/>(Admn.), <lb/>Secondary <lb/>Education <lb/>Department, Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 6393/2019 <lb/>Nazeer Mohammed S/o Shri Avej Khan Mehriwale, Aged About <lb/>61 Years, R/o Atunha Mohalla, Ward No. 9, District Churu. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, School <lb/>Education Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, Secondary Education Department, Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>District Education Officer, Secondary Education, Churu. <lb/>4. <lb/>Chief Block Education Officer, Sardar Sahar, District <lb/>Churu. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 6542/2019 <lb/>Shriram Sharma S/o Shri Onkarmal Sharma, Aged About 62 <lb/>Years, Opp. Ashok Cinema, Behind Water Tanki, Ward No. 20, <lb/>District Churu. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, School <lb/>Education Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, Secondary Education Department, Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>District Education Officer, Secondary Education, Churu. <lb/>4. <lb/>Chief Block Education Officer, Churu, District Churu. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/></front>
			
			<page>(7 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<front> S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 6608/2019 <lb/>Jagdish Prasad Sharma S/o Shri Onkarmal Sharma, Aged About <lb/>64 Years, R/o Behind Agrasen Complex, Ward No. 28, District <lb/>Churu. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, School <lb/>Education Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, Secondary Education Department, Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>District Education Officer, Secondary Education, Churu. <lb/>4. <lb/>Chief Block Education Officer, Churu, District Churu. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 6859/2019 <lb/>Jagdish Prasad Jangir S/o Shri Mala Ram Jangir, Aged About 62 <lb/>Years, Vpo Rampura Bas, Tehsil And District Churu. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, School <lb/>Education Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, Secondary Education Department, Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>District Education Officer, Secondary Education, Churu. <lb/>4. <lb/>Chief Block Education Officer, Churu, District Churu. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 6875/2019 <lb/>Kishan Ram Dhayal S/o Shri Ganpat Ram, Aged About 62 Years, <lb/>House No. C-29, Sector No. 4, Sainik Basti, Pankha Circle, <lb/>District Churu. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, School <lb/>Education Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, Secondary Education Department, Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>District Education Officer, Secondary Bikaner. <lb/>4. <lb/>Chief Block Education Officer, Churu, District Churu. <lb/></front>
			
			<page>(8 of 32) <lb/> </page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<front>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 9846/2019 <lb/>Khurashid Ali Kohri S/o Shri Nijamuddin Khan, Aged About 65 <lb/>Years, R/o House No. 26, Raheem Gali, Bhotto Ka Chouraha, <lb/>Gajner Road, Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, Finance <lb/>Department, Government Of Rajasthan, Secretariat, <lb/>Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, Treasury And Accounts Department, Jaipur. <lb/>3. <lb/>Financial Advisor, Command Area Development, Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 9888/2019 <lb/>Mukteshwar Mishra S/o Late Shri Prakash Chandra Mishra, Aged <lb/>About 62 Years, R/o D-513, Murlidhar Vyas Nagar, Opp. <lb/>Bhootnath Mandir, District Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, Finance <lb/>Department, Government Of Rajasthan, Secretariat, <lb/>Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, Elementary Education Department, Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>Director, Treasury And Accounts, Jaipur. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 11431/2019 <lb/>Murli Manohar Chouhan S/o Hanuman Prasad, Aged About 63 <lb/>Years, Maliyon Ka Mohalla, O/s Jassusar Gate, Tehsil And District <lb/>Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, Public Health <lb/>And Engineering Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Additional Chief Engineer, Public Health And Engineering <lb/>Department, Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>Superintending Engineer, Public Health And Engineering <lb/></front>
			
			<page>(9 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<front> Department, Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 14045/2019 <lb/>Banwari Lal Fageria S/o Shri Toru Ram, Aged About 61 Years, <lb/>R/o Ward No. 23, Puniya Colony, Tehsil And District Churu. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, Finance <lb/>Department, Government Of Rajasthan, Secretariat, <lb/>Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, Treasury And Accounts Department, Jaipur. <lb/>3. <lb/>Director, Secondary Education Department, Government <lb/>Of Rajasthan, Bikaner. <lb/>4. <lb/>Principal, Government Adarsh Higher Secondary School, <lb/>Depasar, Churu. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 14147/2019 <lb/>Sultan Singh Jaria S/o Shri Panna Lal Jaria, Aged About 61 <lb/>Years, R/o D-110, Behind Eye Hospital, Ward No. 11, Sainik <lb/>Colony, Sector-1, District Churu. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, Finance <lb/>Department, Government Of Rajasthan, Secretariat, <lb/>Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, Treasury And Accounts Department, Jaipur. <lb/>3. <lb/>Director, Secondary Education Department, Government <lb/>Of Rajasthan, Bikaner. <lb/>4. <lb/>Principal, Government Higher Secondary School, Ghantel, <lb/>Churu. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 14162/2019 <lb/>Pyare Lal S/o Shri Gida Ram, Aged About 61 Years, R/o V.p.o. <lb/>Ganghu, Tehsil And District Churu. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, Finance <lb/></front>
			
			<page>(10 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<front> Department, Government Of Rajasthan, Secretariat, <lb/>Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, Treasury And Accounts Department, Jaipur. <lb/>3. <lb/>Director, Secondary Education Department, Government <lb/>Of Rajasthan, Bikaner. <lb/>4. <lb/>Principal, Government Adarsh Higher Secondary School, <lb/>Sirsala, Churu. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 16059/2019 <lb/>Surendra Singh S/o Late Shri Ishwar Singh, Aged About 60 <lb/>Years, R/o 4-C-38, Sainik Basti, Opp. Circuit House, District <lb/>Churu. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Director, Elementary <lb/>Education Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Joint Director, School Education, Churu Division, District <lb/>Churu. <lb/>3. <lb/>District Education Officer (Headquarter), Elementary <lb/>Education, Churu. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 16461/2019 <lb/>Vijendra Pal Yadav S/o Shri Hanuman Mal Yadav, Aged About 63 <lb/>Years, R/o Hanuman Sadan, Vivek Nagar, Lalgarh, District <lb/>Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, Ayurved And <lb/>Indian Medical Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, Ayurved Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Ajmer. <lb/>3. <lb/>District Ayurved Officer, District Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 16582/2019 <lb/>Manohar Lal Modi S/o Shri Hari Kishan Modi, Aged About 63 <lb/></front>
			
			<page>(11 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<front> Years, R/o Ist.d.-38, Jai Narain Vyas Colony, District Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, Water <lb/>Resources Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Chief <lb/>Engineer, <lb/>Water <lb/>Resourced <lb/>Department, <lb/>Government Of Rajasthan, Jaipur. <lb/>3. <lb/>Additional Chief Engineer And Director, Hydrolozy And <lb/>Water Management Institute, Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 16893/2019 <lb/>Ranu Singh S/o Shri Jassu Ram, Aged About 61 Years, By Caste <lb/>Purohit, R/o A-55, Karni Nagar, Lalgarh, Tehsil And District <lb/>Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Principal Secretary, <lb/>Revenue <lb/>Department, <lb/>Government <lb/>Of <lb/>Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>District Collector, Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>Tehsildar (Revenue), Tehsil Kolayat, District Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 16960/2019 <lb/>Radha Krishan S/o Shri Bharatlal, Aged About 63 Years, R/o <lb/>Ashirvad, Near Agarwal School, Nagar Nigam Road, Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Principal Secretary, <lb/>School Education Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, Secondary Education, District Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 17021/2019 <lb/>Narendra Gupta S/o Hari Prakash Gupta, Aged About 60 Years, <lb/>A-120, Rajmata Sudarshan Nagar, Near Nagnechi Mandir, <lb/>Bikaner. <lb/></front>
			
			<page> (12 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<front> ----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Principal Secretary, <lb/>School Education Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, School Education, District Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 18801/2019 <lb/>Ramdayal S/o Shri Manaram, Aged About 67 Years, By Caste <lb/>Choudhary, R/o Mandi Samiti Residential Colony, Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>Director, Agricultural Marketing Directorate, Rajasthan, <lb/>Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Joint Director, Agricultural Marketing Department, <lb/>Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>Secretary, Krishi Upaj Mandi (Anaj), Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 18924/2019 <lb/>Dhan Singh Bhati S/o Late Shri Jeevraj Singh Bhati, Aged About <lb/>66 Years, R/o Indra Colony, Behind Roadways Bus Stand, <lb/>Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>Director, Agricultural Marketing Directorate, Rajasthan, <lb/>Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Joint Director, Agricultural Marketing Department, <lb/>Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>Secretary, Krishi Upaj Mandi (Anaj), Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 18941/2019 <lb/>Smt. Krishna Choudhary W/o Shri Mohanram Choudhary, Aged <lb/>About 64 Years, R/o 134-A, Sardulganj, District Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>Director, Agricultural Marketing Directorate, Rajasthan, <lb/>Jaipur. <lb/></front>
			
			<page> (13 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<front> 2. <lb/>Joint Director, Agricultural Marketing Department, <lb/>Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>Secretary, Krishi Upaj Mandi (Anaj), Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 18958/2019 <lb/>Yashpal Godara S/o Shri Rooparam Godara, Aged About 67 <lb/>Years, R/o B-3/3, Patel Nagar, Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>Director, Agricultural Marketing Directorate, Rajasthan, <lb/>Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Joint Director, Agricultural Marketing Department, <lb/>Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>Secretary, Krishi Upaj Mandi (Anaj), Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 505/2020 <lb/>Bhagwan Das S/o Maggaram Meena, Aged About 61 Years, <lb/>Meena Was Village And Post Palari (M), District Sirohi, Rajasthan. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>The State Of Rajasthan, Through Its Principal Finance <lb/>Secretary, Secretariat, Jaipur, Rajasthan. <lb/>2. <lb/>The Director, Treasury And Accounts Department, Jaipur. <lb/>3. <lb/>The Director, Department Of Pension And Pensioners <lb/>Welfare, Jaipur. <lb/>4. <lb/>The Joint Director, Secondary Education, Pali <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 580/2020 <lb/>Dr. Prahalad Das Swami S/o Ganesh Lal Swami, Aged About 67 <lb/>Years, 1St D-6, Jai Narain Vyas Colony, District Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>Raj. University Of Veterinary And Animal Science Bkn., <lb/>Through Its Registrar. <lb/>2. <lb/>Dean And Faculty Chairman, College Of Veterinary And <lb/>Animal Science, Bikaner. <lb/></front>
			
			<page> (14 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<front> 3. <lb/>Registrar, Rajasthan University Of Veterinary And Animal <lb/>Science, Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 589/2020 <lb/>Hari Narayan Vyas S/o Late Shri Suraj Karan Vyas, Aged About <lb/>61 Years, R/o Daga Mohalla, Radha Kunj, Near Gopi Nath <lb/>Bhawan, District Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, Finance <lb/>Department, Government Of Rajasthan, Secretariat, <lb/>Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, Treasury And Accounts Department, Jaipur. <lb/>3. <lb/>Additional Director, State Insurance And Provident Fund <lb/>Department, Bikaner Division, Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 617/2020 <lb/>Baldev Krishan Beniwal S/o Shri Hari Singh Choudhary, Aged <lb/>About 64 Years, R/o 33 Gandhi Nagar (West), Near Lalgarh <lb/>Palace, Bikaner, District -Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>Vice Chancellor, Rajasthan University Of Veterinary And <lb/>Animal Sciences, Bikaner. <lb/>2. <lb/>Rajasthan University Of Veterinary And Animal Sciences, <lb/>Bikaner. <lb/>3. <lb/>Dean And Faculty Chairman, College Of Veterinary And <lb/>Animal Science, Rajasthan University Of Veterinary And <lb/>Animal Sciences, Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 622/2020 <lb/>Dalpat Singh Parihar S/o Shivnath Singh, Aged About 62 Years, <lb/>Resident Of Ambika Chowk, Gali No. 3, Badgaon Road, <lb/>Sheoganj, District -Sirohi, Rajasthan. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>The State Of Rajasthan, Through Its Principal Secretary, <lb/></front>
			
			<page>(15 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<front> Secretariat, Jaipur, Rajasthan. <lb/>2. <lb/>The Director, Treasury And Accounts Department, Jaipur. <lb/>3. <lb/>The Director, Department Of Pension And Pensioners <lb/>Welfare, Jaipur. <lb/>4. <lb/>The District Collector, Sirohi. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 637/2020 <lb/>Narendra Kumar Pandey S/o Shri Shivutt Sharma, Aged About <lb/>62 Years, R/o &apos;narhari Bhawan&apos;, Behind I.t.i., Old Shivbari Road, <lb/>Patel Nagar, District Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, Water <lb/>Resources Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>Chief Engineer, Irrigation Department, Government Of <lb/>Rajasthan, Jaipur. <lb/>3. <lb/>Chief Engineer, I.g.n.p., Bikaner. <lb/>4. <lb/>Superintending Engineer, Regulation, I.g.n.p., Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 778/2020 <lb/>Dhanne Singh S/o Shri Rewant Singh, Aged About 61 Years, R/o <lb/>254, Kailash Puri, Bikaner District Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, Secondary Education <lb/>Department, Government Of Rajasthan, Jaipur. <lb/>----Respondent <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 1923/2020 <lb/>Maharatan Gehlot S/o Shri Mahadev Ji Gehlot, Aged About 65 <lb/>Years, Resident Of Radhakrishna Bhawan, 4-A, Parwati Nagar, <lb/>Circuit House Road, Jodhpur. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>The State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, <lb/>Department Of Local Self Government, Government Of <lb/>Rajasthan, Jaipur. <lb/></front>
			
			<page>(16 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<front> 2. <lb/>The Director, Local Self Department, Jaipur. <lb/>3. <lb/>The Joint Director, Pension And Pensioners Welfare <lb/>Department, Jodhpur. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 2728/2020 <lb/>Ramdeen Firoda S/o Late Shri Hapu Ram, Aged About 67 Years, <lb/>R/o Village Barmi Khurd, Tehsil Bhopalgarh, District Jodhpur. At <lb/>Present House No. 38, Khasra No. 55/4, Saharan Nagar, Digari, <lb/>Jodhpur. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through Principal Secretary, <lb/>Department Of Finance, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>The District Collector, Jodhpur. <lb/>3. <lb/>The <lb/>Director, <lb/>Pension <lb/>And <lb/>Pensioners <lb/>Welfare <lb/>Department, Rajasthan, Jaipur. <lb/>4. <lb/>The Treasurer City, Jodhpur. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 6743/2020 <lb/>Purushottam Pareek S/o Shri Kishanlal Pareek, Aged About 62 <lb/>Years, R/o F-6, Majisa Ka Baas, Tehsil And District Bikaner. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, Finance <lb/>Department, Government Of Rajasthan, Secretariat, <lb/>Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>The Director, Treasury And Accounts, Jaipur. <lb/>3. <lb/>Additional Director, Local Fund Audit Department, Bikaner. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 7545/2020 <lb/>Suresh Chandra Mathur S/o Shri Pyarelal Mathur, Aged About 69 <lb/>Years, R/o 148, Ashapurna Colony, Jalore, Rajasthan. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, Department <lb/>Oe Education (Elementary), Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/></front>
			
			<page>(17 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<front> Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>The District Education Officer (Elementary), Jalore. <lb/>3. <lb/>The Joint Director, Pension And Pensioners Welfare <lb/>Department, Jodhpur, High Court Campus, Jodhpur, <lb/>Rajasthan. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 12287/2020 <lb/>1. <lb/>Dwarka Das S/o Sitadas, Aged About 36 Years, Village <lb/>And Post Gusainsar Bara, Tehsil Shri Dungargarh, District <lb/>Bikaner ( No. 4006992W Hav/clk (Sd)) <lb/>2. <lb/>Vijay Kumar Tiwari S/o Narayan Prasad Sharma, Aged <lb/>About 44 Years, C-187, Karni Nagar, Lalgarh, Bikaner <lb/>(No.jc-519716W Sub (Rt)) <lb/>3. <lb/>Sadhu Ram Yadav S/o Laxmi Narayan Yadav, Aged About <lb/>54 Years, Dhani Sunarwali, Vpo Kariri, Tehsil Shahpura, <lb/>District Jaipur (No. Jc-521217A Ex. Sub Clk) <lb/>4. <lb/>Keran Singh S/o Ram Dayal Jat, Aged About 36 Years, <lb/>Kondla, District Dausa (No.4006787P L/nk) <lb/>----Petitioners <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>Union Of India, Through Secretary, Ministry Of Defence, <lb/>South Block, New Delhi-110011 <lb/>2. <lb/>Controller General Of Defence Accounts, Delhi Cantt, <lb/>Delhi. <lb/>3. <lb/>The Pcda (Pension), Draupadi Ghat, Sadar Bazar, Prayag <lb/>(Up) Raj. 211014 <lb/>4. <lb/>Pao (Or), The Dogra Regiment, Faizabad (Up) -224001 <lb/>5. <lb/>Oic Records, The Dogra Regiment, Faizabad (Up) -<lb/>224001 <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 12540/2020 <lb/>Ramchandar Sinwar S/o Shri Budha Ram, Aged About 60 Years, <lb/>R/o V And P Jocheena, Tehsil Jayal, Nagaur, District Nagaur, <lb/>Rajasthan (Date Of Birth 21-06-1960) <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, Department <lb/>Of Public Health Engineering Department, Government Of <lb/></front>
			
			<page>(18 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<front> Rajasthan, Jaipur, Rajasthan. <lb/>2. <lb/>Principal Finance Secretary, Secretariat, Government Of <lb/>Rajasthan, Jaipur. <lb/>3. <lb/>Director, Treasury And Accounts Department, Rajasthan, <lb/>Jaipur. <lb/>4. <lb/>Director, Department Of Pension And Pensioners Welfare, <lb/>Rajasthan, Jaipur. <lb/>5. <lb/>Additional Chief Engineer (Headquarter), Public Health <lb/>Engineering Department, Rajasthan, Jaipur. <lb/>6. <lb/>Additional Chief Engineer, Public Health Engineering <lb/>Department, Area Ajmer, Rajasthan. <lb/>7. <lb/>Superintending Engineer, Public Health Engineering <lb/>Department, Circle Nagaur, District Nagaur, Rajasthan. <lb/>8. <lb/>Assistant <lb/>Engineer, <lb/>Public <lb/>Health <lb/>Engineering <lb/>Department, Sub Division Jayal, District Nagaur, <lb/>Rajasthan. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 12623/2020 <lb/>Man Singh S/o Shri Kalyan Singh, Aged About 61 Years, R/o <lb/>Nokha Jodha, Jochina, District Nagaur, Rajasthan. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, Department <lb/>Of Secondary Education, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Jaipur, Rajasthan. <lb/>2. <lb/>Principal Finance Secretary, Secretariat, Government Of <lb/>Rajasthan, Jaipur. <lb/>3. <lb/>Director, Treasury And Accounts Department, Rajasthan, <lb/>Jaipur. <lb/>4. <lb/>Director, Department Of Pension And Pensioners Welfare, <lb/>Rajasthan, Jaipur. <lb/>5. <lb/>Director, Secondary Education, Bikaner, Rajasthan. <lb/>6. <lb/>District Education Officer, Education Department, Nagaur, <lb/>Rajasthan. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 12666/2020 <lb/>Bhanwar Lal Lomror S/o Shri Ramkrishna Lomror, Aged About 60 <lb/>Years, R/o Mukam Post Jayal, Tehsil Jayal, District Nagaur, <lb/></front>

			<page>(19 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<front> Rajasthan. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, Department <lb/>Of Secondary Education, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Jaipur, Rajasthan. <lb/>2. <lb/>Principal Finance Secretary, Secretariat, Government Of <lb/>Rajasthan, Jaipur. <lb/>3. <lb/>Director, Treasury And Accounts Department, Rajasthan, <lb/>Jaipur. <lb/>4.Director,department Of Pension And Pensioners Welfare, <lb/>Rajasthan, Jaipur. <lb/>5. <lb/>Director, Elementary Education, Bikaner, Rajasthan. <lb/>6. <lb/>District Education Officer, Elementary Education, Nagaur , <lb/>Rajasthan. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 2614/2021 <lb/>Mohammad Yakub Khan S/o Mohammad Ayub Khan, Aged About <lb/>60 Years, R/o Faiz-E-Aam Maszid, Gali No. 01, G Sector, Pratap <lb/>Nagar, Jodhpur, Rajasthan. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>Principal Secretary, Finance Dept., Govt. Of Raj., Ist Floor, <lb/>Main Building, Gate 2, Government Secretariat, Jaipur, <lb/>Rajasthan -302005 <lb/>2. <lb/>Director, <lb/>State <lb/>Insurance <lb/>And <lb/>Provident <lb/>Fund <lb/>Department, Government Of Rajasthan, Jaipur <lb/>3. <lb/>Additional Director, State Insurance And Provident Fund <lb/>Department, Jodhpur Region, Jodhpur. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 8976/2021 <lb/>Ramdeen Suthar S/o Late Shri Nathu Ram Suthar, Aged About <lb/>64 Years, R/o Vpo Ransi Gaon, Tehsil Bilara, District Jodhpur, <lb/>Rajasthan. <lb/>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary, Public Health <lb/></front>
			
			<page>(20 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<front> And Engineering Department, Government Of Rajasthan, <lb/>Secretariat, Jaipur. <lb/>2. <lb/>The Chief Engineer, Public Health And Engineering <lb/>Department, Jodhpur, District Jodhpur, Rajasthan. <lb/>3. <lb/>The Superintendent Engineer, Public Health And <lb/>Engineering Department, Jodhpur, District Jodhpur, <lb/>Rajasthan. <lb/>4. <lb/>That Executive Engineer, Public Health And Engineering <lb/>Department, Block-First Jodhpur, District Jodhpur, <lb/>Rajasthan. <lb/>5. <lb/>The Assistant Engineer, Public Health And Engineering <lb/>Department, Sub Division Pipar City, District Jodhpur, <lb/>Rajasthan. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 15502/2021 <lb/>1. <lb/>Sarfraj Khan S/o Kalu Khan, Aged About 61 Years, House <lb/>No 1115, Near Charbhuja Temple, Kotadi, District <lb/>Bhilwara. <lb/>2. <lb/>Ishlamudeen Kureshi S/o Nizamudeen, Aged About 63 <lb/>Years, 7508/12 Shahid Hamir Nagar, M.i. Road, <lb/>Panchbatti, Jaipur. <lb/>3. <lb/>Indra Singh S/o Banshi Lal, Aged About 62 Years, Plot <lb/>No.16-17, Balaji Vihar-5, Kalla Wala Vatika Road, <lb/>Sanganer, Jaipur. <lb/>----Petitioners <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through The Secretary To The <lb/>Government, <lb/>Medical <lb/>And <lb/>Health <lb/>Department, <lb/>Government Of Rajasthan, Jaipur (Raj.). <lb/>2. <lb/>The Director, Medical Health And Family Welfare Services, <lb/>Government Of Rajasthan, Jaipur. <lb/>3. <lb/>The Director (Non-Gazetted), Medical And Health <lb/>Services, Rajasthan, Jaipur. <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 15904/2021 <lb/>Bhagwan Lakhyani S/o Nenumal Lakhyani, Aged About 65 Years, <lb/>House No.11/495, Mata Pita Ashish, Chopasani Housing Board, <lb/>Jodhpur (Rajasthan) <lb/></front>
			
			<page>(21 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			
			<front>----Petitioner <lb/>Versus <lb/>1. <lb/>State Of Rajasthan, Through Its Secretary To The <lb/>Government, <lb/>Department <lb/>Of <lb/>Home <lb/>(Group-10), <lb/>Government Of Rajasthan, Secretariat, Jaipur <lb/>2. <lb/>Secretary To The Government, Department Of Finance <lb/>(Rules), Government Of Rajasthan, Secretariat, Jaipur <lb/>3. <lb/>Director, Prosecution, Rajasthan, Jaipur <lb/>4. <lb/>Assistant Director (Prosecution), Jodhpur <lb/>5. <lb/>Additional Director, Pension And Pensioners Welfare <lb/>Department, Jodhpur <lb/>----Respondents <lb/>For Petitioner(s) <lb/>: Mr. Jai Kumar Kaushik <lb/>Mr. SS Ladrecha <lb/>Mr. Shreyansh Mardia <lb/>Mr. Sushil Solanki <lb/>Mr. RS Choudhary <lb/>Mr. Kuldeep Mathur <lb/>Mr. Rakesh Kumar Saini <lb/>Mr. Pawan Singh <lb/>Mr. Vikas Balia <lb/>Mr. Kailash Jangid <lb/>Mr. Khet Singh Rajpurohit &amp; <lb/>Mr. Mukesh Rajpurohit, on VC <lb/>For Respondent(s) <lb/>: Mr. Sandeep Shah, AAG <lb/>Ms. Vandana Bhansali <lb/>Mr. Dinesh Kumar Joshi <lb/>Mr. Vishal Jangid for <lb/>Mr. Hemant Choudhary, GC <lb/>Ms. Anjana Jawa <lb/>Mr. Himanshu Shrimali <lb/>Ms. Abhilasha Kumbhat <lb/>Mr. MC Bishnoi <lb/>Mr. LK Purohit <lb/>Mr. Ravi Panwar <lb/>Mr. KK Bissa, on VC <lb/>HON&apos;BLE DR. JUSTICE PUSHPENDRA SINGH BHATI <lb/></front>
			
			<body>Order <lb/></body>
			
			<page>(22 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<body> 10/01/2022 <lb/>In wake of instant surge in COVID-19 cases and spread of its <lb/>highly infectious Omicron variant, the lawyers have been advised <lb/>to refrain from coming to the Courts. <lb/>Since the controversy involved in all these writ petitions is <lb/>common, thus, are decided by a common order; Ramji Lal Kulhari <lb/>being the lead case. <lb/>The petitioners have preferred these writ petitions, in sum <lb/>and substance, for the following reliefs :-<lb/>SBCWP No.85/2020: <lb/>&quot;To issue an appropriate writ and direct the respondents to grant one <lb/>notional increment to the petitioner with effect from 1.7.2019, on rendering 12 <lb/>months service and re-fix his pension taking into account the same and revise all his <lb/>pensionary benefits and make payments of the consequential arrears thereof, along <lb/>with interest as per mandatory provisions for grant of interest on delayed payment <lb/>of retiral benefits, under Rule 89 of RSR. Any adverse order, if passed, on the <lb/>pending notice for demand of justice may also be quashed.&quot; <lb/>The factual matrix of case in brief is that the petitioner was <lb/>initially appointed on the post of Vehicle Driver on 5.8.1996 and <lb/>posted in Prathmic Health Centre at Bhansali (Rajgarh). His date <lb/>of birth being 10.06.1959. The petitioner retired from service on <lb/>30.6.2019 vide order dated 28.6.2019. <lb/>The bone of contention is Rule 14 of the Rajasthan Civil <lb/>Services (Revised Pay) Rules, 2008 (hereinafter referred to as the <lb/>&quot;Rules of 2008&quot;) and Rule 13 of the Rajasthan Civil Services <lb/>(Revised Pay) Rules, 2017 (hereinafter referred to as the &quot;Rules of <lb/>2017&quot;). The petitioner is seeking implementation of retiral benefits <lb/>as on 01.07.2019. <lb/>Counsel for the petitioner has drawn attention of this Court <lb/>to order dated on 30.07.2021 passed by Hon`ble Orissa High <lb/></body>
			
			<page>(23 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<body> Court in Arun Kumar Biswal Vs. State of Odisha and Ors., <lb/>reported in MANU/OR/0388/2021; relevant paras whereof are <lb/>reads as follows :-<lb/>&quot;13. In the above order of the Madras High Court, it was held that <lb/>as the petitioner therein had completed one full year service as on <lb/>30.06.2013, but the increment fell due on 01.07.2013, on which <lb/>date he was not in service, though the date of increment fell due on <lb/>the next date of his retirement, the petitioner would be given one <lb/>notional increment for the period from 01.07.2012 to 30.06.2013, <lb/>as he had completed full one year of service, for the purpose of <lb/>pensionary benefits and not for any other purpose. The said order <lb/>of the Madras High Court was challenged in SLP(C) Diary No(s). <lb/>22283 of 2018 and the apex Court dismissed the said SLP preferred <lb/>by the Union of India and upheld the order of the Madras High <lb/>Court in P. Ayyamperumal (supra). Although a review petition was <lb/>filed by the Union of India bearing R.P.(C) No. 1731 of 2019, the <lb/>same was dismissed vide order dated 08.08.2019. Thereby, the <lb/>order of the Madras High Court has reached its finality by <lb/>dismissal of the SLP as well as the review petition preferred by the <lb/>Union of India. <lb/>14. Similarly, in the case of Yogendra Singh Bhadauria, mentioned <lb/>supra, Madhya Pradesh High Court, by applying the ratio decided <lb/>in P. Ayyamperumal (supra), directed as follows:-<lb/>&quot;(i) The official respondents are directed to release the <lb/>increment due to the appellants w.e.f. 01.07.2014, <lb/>01.07.2010, 01.07.2013, 01.07.2012, 01.07.2015 and <lb/>01.07.2015 respectively. <lb/>(ii) The pension be refixed after adding the grant of <lb/>aforesaid increment and the arrears of pension be paid <lb/>to the petitioners. <lb/>(iii) The petitioners are entitled to interest over the <lb/>aforesaid arrears of pension @ 10% p.a. from the date <lb/>the arrears became due till their payment. <lb/>(iv) Despite the rule position having been explained by <lb/>the Division Bench of Madras High Court on 15.09.2017 <lb/>against which Supreme Court declined to entertain the <lb/></body>
			
			<page> (24 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<body> SLP of the employer on 23.07.2018, the official <lb/>respondents ought to have offered the benefit of one <lb/>increment to the petitioners without compelling the <lb/>petitioners to approach the court in the evening of 10 WA <lb/>645-2020 their life. Not having done so, the official <lb/>respondents have failed to adhere to the policy of the <lb/>Government of being a welfare State and therefore, <lb/>respondents are liable to pay cost of this litigation to the <lb/>petitioners which are quantified at Rs. 5000/-to each of <lb/>the petitioners. <lb/>(v) The aforesaid direction be complied with within a <lb/>period of 60 days from the date of receipt copy of this <lb/>order.&quot; <lb/>15. In Gopal Singh (supra), the Delhi High Court in paragraph-10 <lb/>of the order dated 23.01.2020 directed as follows: <lb/>&quot;10. Accordingly, the impugned order dated 3rd May, <lb/>2019 is set aside. A direction is issued to the Respondents <lb/>to grant notional increment to the petitioner with effect <lb/>from 1st July, 2019. The petitioner&apos;s pension will <lb/>consequentially be refixed. The appropriate orders will be <lb/>issued and arrears of pension will be paid to the <lb/>petitioner within a period of 6 weeks, failing which the <lb/>respondents would be liable to simple interest at 6% per <lb/>annum on the arrears of period of delay.&quot; <lb/>16. The cumulative effect of the ratio decided in all the <lb/>aforementioned judgments is that if a person continues in service <lb/>and completes one year, he shall be entitled to get the notional <lb/>increment to be fixed, as on the next date he is no more in <lb/>employment, for the purpose of grant of pensionary benefits. <lb/>17. The stand taken in the present case by the opposite parties is <lb/>akin to the objection raised in P. Ayyamperumal (supra) by Union <lb/>of India contending that the petitioner being no more in <lb/>employment on the date the increment fallen due, even though he <lb/>had completed 12 months of service and on attaining the age of <lb/>superannuation he was retired. Having considered such contention, <lb/>the Madras High Court passed an order to fix the notional <lb/>increment for pensionary benefits and extend the same to the <lb/>petitioner therein. In such view of the matter, this Court is of the <lb/>view that the representations filed by the petitioner have been <lb/></body>
			
			<page>(25 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<body> rejected on 14.07.2020 in Annexure-3 without complying with the <lb/>provisions of law, as have been settled by the different High Courts <lb/>as well as the apex Court and, thereby, the same cannot sustain in <lb/>the eye of law. <lb/>18. In view of the facts and law, as discussed above, this Court is of <lb/>the considered view that the petitioner, having rendered service <lb/>from 01.01.2019 to 31.12.2019 for a period of 12 months and his <lb/>increment having due on 01.01.2020 and he having stood at par <lb/>with P. Ayyamperumal (supra), is entitled to get the notional <lb/>increment for the year i.e. from 01.01.2019 to 31.12.2019 for the <lb/>purpose of pensionary benefits only. Accordingly, it is directed that <lb/>the benefits admissible to the petitioner be re-fixed taking into <lb/>account the notional increment admissible to the petitioner by <lb/>01.01.2020 and the same should be paid as early as possible by <lb/>revising the pension as due, preferably within a period of 3 (three) <lb/>months from the date of communication of this judgment. <lb/>Consequentially, the order dated 14.07.2020 in Annexure-3, <lb/>whereby the representations of the petitioner have been rejected, is <lb/>liable to be quashed and is hereby quashed. <lb/>19. In the result, the writ petition is allowed. There shall be no <lb/>order as to costs. <lb/>As the restrictions due to resurgence of COVID-19 situation are <lb/>continuing, learned counsel for the parties may utilize a printout of <lb/>the judgment available in the High Court&apos;s website, at par with <lb/>certified copy, subject to attestation by the concerned advocate, in <lb/>the manner prescribed vide Court&apos;s Notice No. 4587, dated 25th <lb/>March, 2020 as modified by Court&apos;s Notice No. 4798 dated 15th <lb/>April, 2021.&quot; <lb/>Counsel for the respondents, however, submits that the <lb/>controversy of benefit being applicable to the persons who have <lb/>retired on 30 th June of a particular year and not with effect from <lb/>1 st July has already been decided by Hon`ble Division Bench of <lb/>this Court in the matter of Safi Mohammad Vs. State of <lb/>Rajasthan &amp; Anr. (D.B. Civil Writ Petition No.6024/2021), <lb/></body>
			
			<page>(26 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<body> >decided on 01.12.2021. The order dated 01.12.2021 reads as <lb/>follows :-<lb/>&quot;This petition is filed by several retired employees of the State of <lb/>Rajasthan. They all have retired in different years, however, the <lb/>common factor being that their date of retirement was 30th June of <lb/>the respective year. They have challenged Rule 14 of the Rajasthan <lb/>Civil Services (Revised Pay) Rules, 2008 (hereinafter to be referred <lb/>as the &quot;Rules of 2008&quot;) and Rule 13 of the Rajasthan Civil <lb/>Services (Revised Pay) Rules, 2017 (hereinafter to be referred to as <lb/>the &quot;Rules of 2017&quot;). They have also prayed for direction to grant <lb/>notional annual increment for having worked for one full year <lb/>before the date of retirement and to draw the pension accordingly. <lb/>Briefly stated the case of the petitioners is that prior to the <lb/>promulgation of the Rules of 2008 in the State service, annual <lb/>increment of an employee was released on the date of completion of <lb/>a year in service. With introduction of the Rules of 2008, the <lb/>different dates of the increments falling due for different employees <lb/>was consolidated on 1st July of the year concerned, as provided in <lb/>Rule 14 which reads as under:-<lb/>&quot;14. Date of next increment in the running pay <lb/>band-There will be uniform date of annual increment, <lb/>viz. 1st July of every year. Employees completing 6 <lb/>months and above in the running pay band as on 1st <lb/>of July will be eligible ot be granted the increment. <lb/>The first increment after fixation of pay on 01.09.2006 <lb/>or thereafter as per option in the running pay band <lb/>will be granted to the employees, who have completed <lb/>6 months and above as on 01.07.2007. <lb/>Provided that in the case of persons who had <lb/>been drawing maximum of the existing pay scale for <lb/>more than a year as on the 1st day of September, <lb/>2006, the next increment in the running pay band shall <lb/>be allowed on the 1st day of September, 2006. <lb/>Thereafter, the provision of Rule 14 would apply. <lb/>Note-In cases where two existing scales, one being a <lb/>promotional scale for the other, are merged, and the <lb/>junior Government servant, now drawing his pay at <lb/></body>
			
			<page>(27 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<body> equal or lower stage in the lower scale of pay, <lb/>happens to draw more pay in the running pay band <lb/>than the pay of the Senior Government servant in the <lb/>existing higher scale, the pay in the running pay band <lb/>of the senior Government servant shall be stepped up <lb/>to that of his junior from the same date and he shall <lb/>draw next increment in accordance with Rule 14.&quot; <lb/>This pattern continued even under the Rules of <lb/>2017 as provided in Rule 13 which reads as under:-<lb/>&quot;13. Date of next increment in revised pay structure-<lb/>(1) There will be a uniform date of annual <lb/>increment viz. 1st July of every year after fixation of <lb/>pay under these rules. Employees completing 6 <lb/>months and above in any Level as on 1st of July will <lb/>be eligible to be granted the increment. <lb/>(2) Every new recruit on completion of <lb/>probation period successfully shall be allowed first <lb/>annual increment on 1st July, which immediately <lb/>follows the date of completion of probation period.&quot; <lb/>Since all the petitioners retired on 30th June of the <lb/>respective years, they were not granted the increment falling due <lb/>on the following 1st July. Their grievance is that they having <lb/>rendered Government service for one full year, the benefit of the <lb/>last increment has not been given to them. They argue that the rule <lb/>should be interpreted in such a way that they get this last <lb/>increment. In the alternative, their contention is that the rule <lb/>should be held ultra-vires and should be struck down. Learned <lb/>counsel for the petitioners have referred to certain decisions of <lb/>Madras High Court and Delhi High Court taking such a view. We <lb/>would make a reference to these judgments at a later stage. <lb/>On the other hand, learned Additional Advocate General <lb/>appearing for the Government opposed the petition contending that <lb/>the rule making authority has specified 1st July of the year for <lb/>release of annual increment for all Government employees. The <lb/>rule is reasonable and non-discriminatory. As the rule stands, the <lb/>only interpretation possible is that a person who retires w.e.f. 30th <lb/>June of a year, is not entitled to claim the increment falling due on <lb/>1 st July of that year. <lb/></body>
			
			<page>(28 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<body> Learned counsel relied on a decision of Division Bench of <lb/>Himachal Pradesh High Court in the case of Hari Prakash Vs. <lb/>State of Himanchal Pradesh and others reported in 2020 SCC <lb/>OnLine HP 2362, in which this interpretation has been accepted. <lb/>We have reproduced Rules 14 and 13 of the respective rules <lb/>which pertain to the date of next increment in a pay band. As noted, <lb/>prior to the promulgation of the Rules of 2008, the increments were <lb/>released in favour of a Government employee on different dates <lb/>depending on the date of joining the service. However, the Central <lb/>Government as well as the State Government rationalized this date <lb/>of release of annual increment for all Government employees on <lb/>1st July of a particular year. In Rule 14 of Rules of 2008, therefore, <lb/>it is provided that there will be uniform date of annual increment, <lb/>namely, 1st July of every year. Such annual increment would be <lb/>released to every employee completing 6 months and above in the <lb/>running pay band as on 1st July. To obviate the difficulties of the <lb/>existing employees, this rule provides that the first increment after <lb/>fixation of pay on 01.09.2006 (i.e. the date from which the Rules of <lb/>2008 were made effective) or thereafter as per the option in the <lb/>running pay band will be granted to the employees who had <lb/>completed 6 months and above as on 01.07.2007. Similar <lb/>provisions have been made in Rule 13 of the Rules of 2017. <lb/>We do not find any force in the submission of the learned <lb/>counsel for the petitioners that every employee who retires on 30th <lb/>June of a particular year, must receive the increment which as per <lb/>these rules falls due on 1st July. The grant of annual increment is <lb/>part of pay structure which the Government prescribes for its <lb/>employees and is governed by statutory rules. Annual increment is <lb/>granted by way of incentive in order to reward long service <lb/>rendered by the Government employee. It is different from the <lb/>dearness allowance which the Government declares from time to <lb/>time and is meant to offset for the diminished value of purchasing <lb/>price of the rupee with increase in inflation. Such increment can be <lb/>claimed only in terms of the statutory rules. <lb/>We are conscious that the Madras High Court and Delhi <lb/>High Court have taken a different view. Heavy reliance was placed <lb/>by the learned counsel for the petitioner on a Division Bench <lb/>judgment of Madras High Court in the case of P. Ayyamperumal <lb/>Vs. The Registar and others (W.P. No. 15732 of 2017 decided on <lb/></body>
			
			<page>(29 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<body> 15.09.2017). This judgment proceeds on the earlier judgment of the <lb/>Court in the case of State of Tamil Nadu Vs. M. <lb/>Balasubramaniam (CDJ 2012 MHC 6525) which was rendered by <lb/>the Single Judge and approved by the Division Bench. Likewise, the <lb/>Division Bench of Delhi High Court in the case of Gopal Singh Vs. <lb/>Union of India and others (W.P.(C) 10509/2019 decided on <lb/>23.01.2020), has also relied upon and accepted the decision in case <lb/>of M. Balasubramaniam(supra) of Madras High Court. Yet another <lb/>decision in the case of Arun Chhibber Vs. Union of Indian and <lb/>others (W.P.(C) 5539/2019 decided on 13.01.2020), the Division <lb/>Bench of Delhi High Court reiterated this proposition on the basis <lb/>of decision in the case of M. Balasubramaniam (supra). <lb/>We have perused the decision of the Madras High Court in <lb/>the case of M. Balasubramaniam (supra) which is the base <lb/>judgment, which the subsequent Division Benches of Madras High <lb/>Court and Delhi High Court have followed. This was a case in <lb/>which the petitioner, who was in State service, had retired w.e.f. <lb/>31st March, 2003. He had claimed the benefit of pension on the <lb/>basis of increment which fell due on 01.04.2003, on the basis of the <lb/>judgment of Supreme Court in the case of S. Banerjee Vs. Union <lb/>of India and others (AIR 1990 SC 285). Upon his superannuation, <lb/>he was re-employed and continued in service up to 31st March, <lb/>2003. It was on that basis that the petitioner had claimed the <lb/>benefit of an additional annual increment falling due on <lb/>01.04.2003. This was opposed by the Government on the ground <lb/>that on 01.04.2003, he was not in Government service. In such <lb/>background, the High Court had allowed the petition and directed <lb/>that the representation of the petitioner for grant of annual <lb/>increment for the period from 01.04.2002 to 31.03.2003 shall be <lb/>considered in light of the judgment of the Supreme Court in the <lb/>case of S. Banerjee (supra). <lb/>If we peruse the judgment of the Supreme Court in the case <lb/>of S. Banerjee (supra), the facts were that the petitioner was <lb/>allowed to retire voluntarily from service with effect from the <lb/>forenoon of 1st January, 1986. He was not given the benefit of <lb/>revision of salary which was brought into effect from 01.01.1986. <lb/>The Government had argued before the Supreme Court that in view <lb/>of the proviso of Rule 5(2) of the Central Civil Service (Pension) <lb/>Rules, 1972, the petitioner will not be entitled to any salary for the <lb/></body>
			
			<page>(30 of 32) <lb/></page>

			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<body> day on which he actually retired and therefore, his claim for <lb/>granting the benefit of revision of pay scales would not be justified. <lb/>The Supreme Court repelled this contention on the ground that the <lb/>employee retired with effect from the forenoon of 01.01.1986 and <lb/>not with effect from 31st December, 1985 and therefore the revision <lb/>of pay scales would be applicable to him. <lb/>In our view, there is a fine distinction in the judgment of the <lb/>Supreme Court in the case of S. Banerjee (supra) and the facts of <lb/>the present case. In the present case, all the petitioners admittedly <lb/>retired on 30th June and not with effect from 1st July. The decision <lb/>of the Supreme Court therefore will not aid the petitioners in the <lb/>present case. We are in respectful disagreement with the view of <lb/>Madras High Court in the case of N. Balasubramaniam (supra) in <lb/>which in our opinion, the decision of the Supreme Court in case of <lb/>S. Banarjee (supra) has been applied though the facts were <lb/>different. Since all subsequent judgments noted above merely refer <lb/>to and rely upon the judgment in the case of M. Balasubramaniam <lb/>(supra), we cannot concur with such views. <lb/>We notice that a Division Bench of Himachal Pradesh High <lb/>Court in the case of Hari Prakash (supra) has taken a similar view. <lb/>The earlier decisions of Madras High Court and Delhi High Court <lb/>have been noticed. <lb/>We are conscious that the SLP against the decision of the <lb/>Madras High Court in the case of P. Ayyamperumal (supra) came <lb/>to be dismissed by the Supreme Court observing that &quot;on the facts&quot; <lb/>the Court is not inclined to interfere with the judgment. However, <lb/>this expression cannot be seen as approval of the judgment on <lb/>merits. We are therefore entitled to take an independent view, which <lb/>we have taken. <lb/>In case of Prabhu Dayal Sesma vs. State of Rajasthan, it <lb/>wqs held that while calculating the age of a person, the day of his <lb/>birth must be counted as a whole and he attains the specified age <lb/>on the day preceding the anniversary of his birthday. A Division <lb/>Bench of the Delhi High Court in case of Union of India vs. A. <lb/>Chaudhari reported in 2009 SCC Online Del. 4338 considered a <lb/>case where an employee retired on superannuation on 31.3.1995. <lb/>Fifth Pay Commission recommendations were made effective from <lb/>1.4.1995 in which death-cum-retiral gratuity benefits were <lb/>increased. The employee claimed such higher benefits. The court <lb/></body>
			
			<page>(31 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<body> relying on a Division Bench judgement of Karnataka High Court <lb/>held that the employee cannot contend that he had retired with <lb/>effect from 01.04.1995 and therefore higher benefits cannot be <lb/>granted. Similar view was taken by the Division Bench of the <lb/>Gujarat High Court in case of C.R.Samajpati vs. Uniono fIndia <lb/>reported in 2009 SCC OnLine Guj. 10857. <lb/>Before closing, we find nothing arbitrary or discriminatory <lb/>about the rules in question. The annual increment is released with <lb/>effect from a particular date. As a consequence, it is natural that <lb/>someone would fall on the wrong side of such a date. That by itself <lb/>would not render the rule arbitrary. The direction for releasing an <lb/>additional increment in favour of retirees is also not free from <lb/>practical complications. None of the judgments cited by the learned <lb/>counsel for the petitioners refer to the date as on which such <lb/>increment would be released. For proper pay fixation and <lb/>calculation of the re-fixed pay after releasing the annual increment, <lb/>it is absolutely essential that the date as on which such increment is <lb/>released, be specified. If it is to be released as on 30th June of the <lb/>year of retirement, we do not see how this can result into any <lb/>benefit to the petitioners since their pension would be drawn on the <lb/>basis of last 10 months of salary and releasing the notional <lb/>increment on the last date of service would not augment the salary <lb/>in any manner. On the other hand, if the expectation of the <lb/>petitioners is that such annual increment may be released as on 1st <lb/>July of the last year of their working, this would lead to two <lb/>increments being released on the same date which is wholly <lb/>impermissible. <lb/>In the result, the petition is dismissed.&quot; <lb/>This Court after hearing counsel for the parties at length and <lb/>examining facts of the case finds that the Hon`ble Division Bench <lb/>of this Court in a clear order has rested the controversy to an end <lb/>by holding that there is nothing arbitrary or discriminatory about <lb/>the Rules in question. The annual increment/retiral benefits are <lb/>released with effect from a particular date. As a consequence, it is <lb/>natural that someone would fall on the wrong side of such a date. <lb/>Such event by itself would not render the rule arbitrary. <lb/></body>
			
			<page>(32 of 32) <lb/></page>
			
			<note place='headnote'>[CW-85/2020] <lb/></note>
			
			<body>The finding given by Division Bench comprehensively covers <lb/>the lis in all these writ petitions. <lb/>This Court is bound by the <lb/>Division Bench judgment of Safi Mohammad (supra) of this Court <lb/>and, thus, there is no question of taking any different view. <lb/>The writ petitions are dismissed in light of Safi Mohammad <lb/>(supra). <lb/>(DR.PUSHPENDRA SINGH BHATI),J. <lb/>58-Sanjay/-</body>



	</text>
</tei>
