<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			HIGH COURT OF JUDICATURE FOR RAJASTHAN
			<lb />
			JODHPUR
			<lb />
			S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 14964/2019
			<lb />
			Kiran Kumari w/o shri Manishpal Singh, aged 34 years, resident
			<lb />
			of Ragha Chhoti, Tehsil Rajgarh, District Churu.
			<lb />
			----Petitioner
			<lb />
			Versus
			<lb />
			1. State Of Rajasthan through the Secretary, Department of
			<lb />
			Medical &amp; Health, Secretariat, Jaipur.
			<lb />
			2. Additional Director (Administration), Medical &amp; health
			<lb />
			Services, Tilak Marg, jaipur.
			<lb />
			3. Chief Medical &amp; Health Officer, Ratangarh, District Churu.
			<lb />
			4. Block Chief Medical &amp; Health Officer, Rajgarh, District Churu.
			<lb />
			5. Principal Secretary, Department of Rural Development and
			<lb />
			Panchayati Raj., Rajasthan, Jaipur.
			<lb />
			----Respondent
			<lb />
			For Petitioner(s)
			<lb />
			: Mr. Manish Patel, Mr. R.C. Joshi
			<lb />
			Mr. Vikas Bijarnia, Mr. Sushil Solanki
			<lb />
			Mr. Shreekant Verma, Mr. Yashpal
			<lb />
			Khileri, Mr. Rishabh Tayal, Mr. Tanwar
			<lb />
			Singh, Mr. Manoj Bohra, Mr. N.R.
			<lb />
			Budania, Mr. Jaidev Singh, Mr.
			<lb />
			Mahaveer Vishnoi, Mr. Ripudaman
			<lb />
			Singh, Mr. L.K. Ramdhari, Mr. Ramdev
			<lb />
			Potaliya, Mr. Bhoop Singh Choudhary,
			<lb />
			Mr. Akhilesh Rajpurohit, Mr. Ashok
			<lb />
			Kumar Choudhary, Mr. Inderjeet
			<lb />
			Yadav, Mr. Sitaram Beniwal, Mr. Om
			<lb />
			Rajpurohit, Mr. Hapu Ram, Mr. S.K.
			<lb />
			Dadhich, Mr. Jitendra Singh Bhaleria,
			<lb />
			Mr. S.K. Punia, Mr. Suresh Kumar
			<lb />
			Maru, Mr. Firoz Khan, Mr. Pawan
			<lb />
			Singh, Mr. Hukam Singh, Mr. Moti
			<lb />
			Singh, Mr. V.R. Choudhary, Mr. Yurvaj
			<lb />
			Sonel
			<lb />
			For Respondent(s)
			<lb />
			: Mr. Karan Singh Rajpurohit, AAG with
			<lb />
			Mr. Shreyansh Mehta, Mr. Surender
			<lb />
			Singh Rathore, Mr. Rajat Arora
			<lb />
			Mr. Ankur Mathur
			<lb />
		</front>

		<page>
			(2 of 16)
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place='headnote'>
			[CW-14964/2019]
			<lb />
		</note>

		<front>
			JUSTICE DINESH MEHTA
			<lb />
		</front>

		<body>
			Judgment
			<lb />
			REPORTABLE :
			<lb />
			15/01/2020
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			This group of writ petitions (enumerated in the Schedule
			<lb />
			appended with the present order, which be treated an integral part
			<lb />
			of this order) lay challenge to separate transfer order(s) issued on
			<lb />
			one
			<lb />
			day
			<lb />
			i.e.
			<lb />
			29.09.2019
			<lb />
			by
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Additional
			<lb />
			Director
			<lb />
			(Administration), Medical &amp; Health Services, Rajasthan Jaipur.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			The essence of petitioners&apos; contention is that the respondent
			<lb />
			State, more particularly the Department of Medical &amp; Health
			<lb />
			Service, has no authority to transfer the petitioners, whose
			<lb />
			services are governed by the Rajasthan Panchayati Raj
			<lb />
			(Transferred Activities) Rules, 2011 (hereinafter after referred to
			<lb />
			as &quot;the Rules of 2011&quot;). For the sake of convenience and clarity,
			<lb />
			the relevant facts from Kiran Kumari&apos;s case (SB Civil Writ Petition
			<lb />
			No.14964/2019) are taken into consideration.
			<lb />
			2.1 It may be noted that the State Government issued a
			<lb />
			circular/order dated 02.10.2010, whereby Sub-Centres, Primary
			<lb />
			Health Centres (PHC) and Community Health Centres (CHC)
			<lb />
			situated in various rural areas of Medical &amp; Health Department,
			<lb />
			including their staff were transferred to the Panachati Raj
			<lb />
			Institutions.
			<lb />
			2.2 According to such decision of the State, services of all such
			<lb />
			employees (including the petitioners) were ordered to be governed
			<lb />
			by the Rules of 2011. Consequently, their parent department
			<lb />
			remains Medical &amp; Health Department, but their other incidence of
			<lb />
			service, including transfer are governed by the Rules of 2011.
			<lb />
			2.3 Petitioner was afforded appointment on the post of Auxiliary
			<lb />
			Nurse Midwifery (ANM) on 29.01.2016.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			(3 of 16)
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place='headnote'>
			[CW-14964/2019]
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			2.4 The present bunch of writ petitions includes those persons
			<lb />
			who have been transferred from one District to another and one
			<lb />
			Panchayat Samiti to another Panchayat Samit, so also one Gram
			<lb />
			Panchayat to other.
			<lb />
			2.5 By way of the order dated 29.09.2019, respondent No.2 has
			<lb />
			transferred the petitioner -Kiran Kumari from Community Health
			<lb />
			Center Rajgarh, Churu to Sub-Center, Bhawta, Kuchaman City,
			<lb />
			Nagaur -from one district to another.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			Mr. Vikas Bijarnia, learned counsel leading the arguments in
			<lb />
			this group of matters, at the outset submitted that after transfer
			<lb />
			of petitioner&apos;s services to the Panchayati Raj Department,
			<lb />
			petitioners&apos; transfer can be made only in accordance with Rule 8 of
			<lb />
			the Rules of 2011, which reads thus :-
			<lb />
			&quot;8. Transfer.-Transfer of such transferred
			<lb />
			employees shall be made under the transfer policy
			<lb />
			and directions issued by the State Government from
			<lb />
			time to time, by :-
			<lb />
			(i) the Administration and Establishment
			<lb />
			Committee of the Panchayat Samiti concerned
			<lb />
			within the same Panchayat Samit.
			<lb />
			(ii) the District Establishment Committee of the
			<lb />
			Zila Parishad concerned from one Panchayat
			<lb />
			Samiti to another Panchayat Samiti within the
			<lb />
			same District.
			<lb />
			(iii) the department Concerned from one district
			<lb />
			to another district with the consent of the
			<lb />
			Panchayati Raj Department.&quot;
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Having read the provisions of Rule 8 of the Rules of 2011,
			<lb />
			learned counsel contended that transfer of an employee, from one
			<lb />
			Gram Panchayat to another, can be effected by the Administration
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			(4 of 16)
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place='headnote'>
			[CW-14964/2019]
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			and Establishment Committee of Panchayat Samiti concerned; in
			<lb />
			case of transfer from one Panchayat Samiti to another, it can be
			<lb />
			done by District Establishment Committee of the Zila Parishad
			<lb />
			concerned and in case of inter district transfer, the same can be
			<lb />
			done by the department concerned i.e. Medical &amp; Health
			<lb />
			Department, of course with the consent of Panchayati Raj
			<lb />
			Department.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			Learned counsel contended that as per the mandate of Rule
			<lb />
			8 of the Rules of 2011, transfer of an ANM or any employee for
			<lb />
			that matter, governed by the Rules of 2011, in the contingencies
			<lb />
			mentioned in (i) and (ii) of Rule 8 can be effected by the
			<lb />
			Panchayati Raj Department and in the third contingency i.e. in
			<lb />
			case of inter-district transfer, the same can be done by Medical &amp;
			<lb />
			Health Department, subject of course to consent of the Panchayati
			<lb />
			Raj Department.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			Inviting Court&apos;s attention towards transfer order, Mr. Bijarnia
			<lb />
			pointed out that the same has been done by the Medical &amp; Health
			<lb />
			Department and thus, petitioner&apos;s transfer from District Churu to
			<lb />
			Nagaur, which otherwise is governed by Rule 8 (iii) of the Rules of
			<lb />
			2011, is illegal and deserves to be quashed as no consent of
			<lb />
			Panchayati Raj Department has been obtained.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			In a bid to lend support to his argument aforesaid, learned
			<lb />
			counsel placed reliance on a series of judgments, more
			<lb />
			particularly, judgment dated 14.11.2017 rendered in SB Civil Writ
			<lb />
			Petition No.11862/2017 (Samleta Vs. State of Raj. &amp; Ors.);
			<lb />
			Division Bench judgment dated 11.10.2018 in DB Special Appeal
			<lb />
			Writ No.736/2018 (State of Raj. &amp; Ors. Vs. Samleta) -affirming
			<lb />
			the Single Bench decision; judgment dated 28.05.2019 rendered
			<lb />
			in SB Civil Writ Petition No.6917/2019 (Harish Chandra Katara Vs.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			(5 of 16)
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place='headnote'>
			[CW-14964/2019]
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			State of Raj. &amp; Ors.); judgment dated 12.11.2018 rendered in SB
			<lb />
			Civil Writ Petition No.16963/2018 (Smt. Bimla Devi Vs. State of
			<lb />
			Raj. &amp; Ors.).
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			Navigating the Court through the judgments aforesaid,
			<lb />
			learned counsel submitted that it has been consistent view of this
			<lb />
			Court, that transfer of ANMs or any such employee governed by
			<lb />
			the Rules of 2011, cannot be made by the parent department,
			<lb />
			without the prior consent of the Panchayati Raj Department in
			<lb />
			case of inter district transfer and in case of transfer within district,
			<lb />
			it can be done only by the District Establishment Committee or
			<lb />
			Administration and Establishment Committee, as the case may be.
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			Mr. K.S. Rajpurohit, learned Additional Advocate General
			<lb />
			assisted by Mr. Shreyansh Mehta defending the impugned transfer
			<lb />
			order(s) issued by the State Government placed before the Court
			<lb />
			an order dated 16.06.2018 issued by the State Government,
			<lb />
			whereby an in-principle decision has been taken that in case of
			<lb />
			transfer, the consent of Panchayati Raj Department will not be
			<lb />
			necessary. It was also argued that while taking such decision, a
			<lb />
			general consent has been taken from the Panchayati Raj
			<lb />
			Department in relation to all the transfers governed by Rule 8 of
			<lb />
			the Rules of 2011, hence, no separate consent of the Panchayati
			<lb />
			Raj Department is necessary in case of inter-district transfers.
			<lb />
			10. It was further argued that in light of the said decision of the
			<lb />
			State Government, it is no more necessary that transfer should be
			<lb />
			effected by Administration &amp; Establishment Committee or District
			<lb />
			Establishment Committee of the Panchayati Raj Department in
			<lb />
			case of transfers within the district.
			<lb />
			11. Learned Additional Advocate General pointed out that the
			<lb />
			order dated 16.06.2018 passed by the Chief Secretary, though in
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			(6 of 16)
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place='headnote'>
			[CW-14964/2019]
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			his administrative capacity has the equal effect, if not more to
			<lb />
			Rule 8 in view of the power given to the State Government in the
			<lb />
			body of Rule 8 of the Rules of 2011, permitting the State
			<lb />
			Government to issue directions and guidelines.
			<lb />
			12. He zealously read opening words of Rule 8, particularly the
			<lb />
			expression &quot;… … … under the transfer policy and directions issued
			<lb />
			by the State Government from time to time, …&quot;, and argued that
			<lb />
			the order dated 16.06.2018 fills the gap between the rules and in
			<lb />
			light of what has been provided in the order dated 16.06.2018, all
			<lb />
			the transfers made by the State, subject matter of instant writ
			<lb />
			petitions are valid and in accordance with law.
			<lb />
			13. Having argued so, learned counsel for the respondents
			<lb />
			submitted that the transfers in question have been made in public
			<lb />
			interest and looking to the administrative exigencies, as it is the
			<lb />
			Medical and Health Department, who is otherwise held responsible
			<lb />
			or accountable for deficiency or lack of medical facilities and it is
			<lb />
			the parent medical department, which can ascertain and adjudge
			<lb />
			requirement or suitability of a particular employee. Resting his
			<lb />
			arguments, he urged that since the transfers impugned were done
			<lb />
			in public interest, interference with such orders be avoided,
			<lb />
			keeping the public interest and public health as a paramount.
			<lb />
			14. Heard.
			<lb />
			15. A bare reading of Rule 8 of the Rules of 2011 leaves no room
			<lb />
			for ambiguity that transfer of the employees, whose services have
			<lb />
			been transferred to Panchayati Raj institution can be made by an
			<lb />
			authority who is authorized to transfer such employee, as has
			<lb />
			been clearly defined rather prescribed in the Rule 8 itself, viz. (i)
			<lb />
			in case of transfer within Panchayat Samiti -Administration and
			<lb />
			Establishment Committee of Panchayat Samiti, (ii) in case of
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			(7 of 16)
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place='headnote'>
			[CW-14964/2019]
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			transfer from one Panchayat Samiti to another Panchayat Samiti
			<lb />
			within the same District -District Establishment Committee of the
			<lb />
			Zila Parishad and (iii) in case of transfer from one District to
			<lb />
			another or inter district transfer -department concerned with
			<lb />
			consent of Panchayati Raj Department.
			<lb />
			16. This Court is unable to accept the argument advanced by
			<lb />
			learned counsel for the respondents that by virtue of order dated
			<lb />
			16.06.2018, the State Government has given an in-principle
			<lb />
			consent for transfer and has permitted transfers by the Medical &amp;
			<lb />
			Health Department in case of intra Panchayat Samiti and inter
			<lb />
			Panchayat Samiti also.
			<lb />
			17. Rules of 2011 have been framed under Article 309 of the
			<lb />
			Constitution and they have statutory force. Any order or circular,
			<lb />
			may it be passed by the Chief Secretary, cannot alter, obliterate or
			<lb />
			override the provisions contained in the Rules. This Court hardly
			<lb />
			finds any substance in the arguments of learned Additional
			<lb />
			Advocate General that since the State legislature or rule making
			<lb />
			authority cannot amend the Rules every of and on, as and when
			<lb />
			required, executive order passed by the State Government can do
			<lb />
			the same and such administrative order can be issued in public
			<lb />
			interest and to meet the exigencies.
			<lb />
			18. All the judgments cited by learned counsel for the petitioners
			<lb />
			right from the judgment dated 14.11.2017 in case of Samleta
			<lb />
			(supra) till the judgment dated 28.05.2019 in case of Harish
			<lb />
			Chandra Katara (supra), have consistently held that Rule 8 of the
			<lb />
			Rules of 2011 is sacrosanct and the State Government cannot
			<lb />
			transfer its staff/employee dehors the provisions contained in Rule
			<lb />
			8 of the Rules of 2011. Relevant portions of the judgments
			<lb />
			aforesaid are being reproduced hereunder :-
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			(8 of 16)
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place='headnote'>
			[CW-14964/2019]
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			(i) (Samleta Vs. State of Rajasthan &amp; Ors.) :
			<lb />
			&quot;3. concededly no such consent was taken. I note
			<lb />
			that vide order dated 20.09.2017 it was directed that
			<lb />
			joining of duties by the petitioner pursuant to impugned
			<lb />
			transfer order dated 15.09.2017 at the place where she
			<lb />
			has been transferred shall be subject to the decision of the
			<lb />
			writ petition.
			<lb />
			4. The respondents have not been able to show to
			<lb />
			the Court as to why consent of the PanchayatiDepartment
			<lb />
			is not warranted.&quot;
			<lb />
			(ii) (State of Raj. &amp; Ors. Vs. Samleta) :
			<lb />
			&quot;Sub-rule (ii) of Rule 8 of the Rajasthan Panchayati
			<lb />
			Raj (Transfer Activities) Rules, 2011 clearly postulates that
			<lb />
			when a person is transferred from one District to another,
			<lb />
			there is a prerequisite condition of obtaining prior consent
			<lb />
			of Panchayati Raj Department. In the present case, the
			<lb />
			respondent is an employee of the Panchayati Raj
			<lb />
			Institution and she has been transferred from one district
			<lb />
			to another. Admittedly, no consent as per Rule 8 of the
			<lb />
			Rules of 2011 was obtained from the Panchayati Raj
			<lb />
			Department and therefore, her transfer is bad and in
			<lb />
			violation of the provisions of Rule 8 of the Rules of 2011.
			<lb />
			Even in the cases of transfer of surplus employees,
			<lb />
			consent has to be obtained from the Panchayati Raj
			<lb />
			Department.
			<lb />
			In view of the above observations, we are not
			<lb />
			inclined to interfere in the order passed by the learned
			<lb />
			Single Judge.
			<lb />
			The appeal is, therefore, dismissed.&quot;
			<lb />
			(iii) (Smt. Bimla Devi Vs. State of Raj. &amp; Ors.) :
			<lb />
			&quot;Sh. S.K. Gupta Additional Advocate General
			<lb />
			appearing for the respondents submits that in each &amp;
			<lb />
			every matter consent as required under Rule 8 of the
			<lb />
			Rules, 2011 is not necessary and submits that a circular
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			(9 of 16)
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place='headnote'>
			[CW-14964/2019]
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			dated 16.06.2018 was issued in this regard by the
			<lb />
			Panchayati Raj Department.
			<lb />
			After hearing counsel for the parties, the contention
			<lb />
			advanced by the counsel for the petitioners holds
			<lb />
			substance for the reasons; firstly according to Rule 8 of
			<lb />
			the Rules, 2011 the consent is necessary to be obtained as
			<lb />
			required from the Panchayati Raj. Department; secondly a
			<lb />
			bare perusal of the order/circular dated 16.6.2018 clearly
			<lb />
			shows that it holds that for transfer of an employee the
			<lb />
			consent of the Panchayati Raj Department is not necessary
			<lb />
			which is violative of Rule 8 of the Rules, 2011.
			<lb />
			In that view of the matter, the writ petitions filed by
			<lb />
			the petitioners deserve acceptance and the transfer orders
			<lb />
			impugned herein deserve to be set aside.
			<lb />
			Accordingly, the writ petitions are allowed and the
			<lb />
			respective transfer orders impugned in the present
			<lb />
			petitions are set aside. However, the respondent-State is
			<lb />
			at liberty to pass order of transfer afresh, if exigency of
			<lb />
			service so require, only after strict compliance of Rule 8 of
			<lb />
			the Rules, 2011. Copy of the order be separately placed in
			<lb />
			each file.&quot;
			<lb />
			(iv) (Harish Chandra Katara Vs. State of Raj. &amp;
			<lb />
			Ors.) :
			<lb />
			&quot;Learned counsel appearing for the respondent
			<lb />
			department placed reliance on the order dated 16.06.2018
			<lb />
			(Annex.9 in SBCWP No.7212/2019), purportedly directing
			<lb />
			under Rule 8 and ordering that the required consent of the
			<lb />
			Panchayati Raj Department would not be required and
			<lb />
			therefore, the plea raised by the petitioners in this regard
			<lb />
			has no substance.
			<lb />
			Learned counsel for the petitioners in SBCWP
			<lb />
			No.7212/2019 submits that the circular dated 16.06.2018
			<lb />
			relied on by the respondents being contrary to the express
			<lb />
			provisions of Rule 8, the transfer orders without requisite
			<lb />
			consent under Rule 8 has been set aside in Smt. Bimla
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			(10 of 16)
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place='headnote'>
			[CW-14964/2019]
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			Devi v. State of Rajasthan &amp; Ors. ; SB Civil Writ Petition
			<lb />
			No.16963/2018, decided on 12.11.2018 at Jaipur Bench.
			<lb />
			… … …
			<lb />
			… … …
			<lb />
			In view of the express provision of Rule 8 as well as
			<lb />
			the judgment in the case of Bimla Devi (supra), wherein
			<lb />
			the circular sought to be relied on by the respondents has
			<lb />
			been taken into consideration, the action of the
			<lb />
			respondents in effecting transfers of the petitioners in
			<lb />
			SBCWP Nos.4214/2019 and 7212/2019 cannot be
			<lb />
			sustained.
			<lb />
			The order dated 08.03.2019 (Annex.2 in
			<lb />
			SBCWP No.4214/2019) and order dated 08.03.2019
			<lb />
			(Annex.8 in SBCWP No.7212/2019), qua the petitioners
			<lb />
			are quashed and set aside.&quot;
			<lb />
			19. State&apos;s endeavour to justify, rather defend impugned
			<lb />
			order(s) by submitting that these transfers have been made in
			<lb />
			public interest and that too by the Medical &amp; Health Department,
			<lb />
			which is the best suited to ascertain the suitability of an employee
			<lb />
			considering the ground realities, also does not cut any ice.
			<lb />
			20. It is settled preposition of law that if a statute or rule
			<lb />
			provides something to be done in a particular manner, such act is
			<lb />
			required to be done only as mandated by such rule. In the
			<lb />
			present case, Rule 8 is not only the fountain head of power to
			<lb />
			transfer but also a dividing line or road-map setting out clearly the
			<lb />
			authority and manner in which the transfers are to be effected.
			<lb />
			21. This Court has no hesitation in holding that transfer of
			<lb />
			petitioners governed by the Rules of 2011 can be done only by the
			<lb />
			authorities/committees mentioned in clause (i), (ii) and (iii) of
			<lb />
			Rule 8 of the Rules of 2011. No authority or officer, howsoever
			<lb />
			high he may be placed in the bureaucratic hierarchy, can transfer
			<lb />
			an employee governed by the Rules of 2011, in violation of Rule 8.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			(11 of 16)
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place='headnote'>
			[CW-14964/2019]
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			22. Argument of respondents that by virtue of order dated
			<lb />
			16.06.2018 passed by the Chief Secretary, the Medical &amp; Health
			<lb />
			Department has been authorized to transfer the employees of
			<lb />
			Panchayati Raj Department is untenable. In considered opinion of
			<lb />
			this Court, any executive order cannot over-take or take place of
			<lb />
			substantive Rules.
			<lb />
			23. In unqualified opinion of this Court, the Rules of 2011 framed
			<lb />
			by the State Government under Article 309 of the Constitution are
			<lb />
			paramount. Much relied expression in Rule 8 &quot;… … … under the
			<lb />
			transfer policy and directions issued by the State Government … …
			<lb />
			…&quot; are only to supplement the Rule. State&apos;s attempt to give a
			<lb />
			complete go by to the Rules in the garb of such expression is
			<lb />
			unsustainable.
			<lb />
			24. The State Government can frame policy or issue directions
			<lb />
			only on those aspects, in relation to which, the Rules are silent.
			<lb />
			Any executive order of the State Government, which is contrary to
			<lb />
			the express provision of the Rules cannot get sanction of the
			<lb />
			Court. Such orders will have to concede, on all aspects wherever
			<lb />
			they come in conflict with the statutory Rules.
			<lb />
			25. The order of the State Government dated 16.06.2018, if read
			<lb />
			carefully reveals that all the stipulations contained in order dated
			<lb />
			16.06.2018 are contrary to express provisions contained in Rule 8.
			<lb />
			(i) Para (v) requires the consent of parent Department i.e. Medical
			<lb />
			&amp; Health Department in cases of transfer under Rule 8(i) and 8(ii);
			<lb />
			the same clearly falls foul to Rule 8 (i) and 8 (ii);
			<lb />
			(ii) (c) seeks to ratify such transfers affected, that too cannot be
			<lb />
			done -an act which is void ab-initio cannot be ratified and that
			<lb />
			too by the authority which has usurped the powers;
			<lb />
			(iii) and direction given in (l) in relation to inter-district transfers.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			(12 of 16)
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place='headnote'>
			[CW-14964/2019]
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			26. The order dated 16.06.2018 at best be read or construed to
			<lb />
			be a prior rather tacit approval of the Panchayati Raj Department.
			<lb />
			But in the opinion of this Court, even that is impermissible and
			<lb />
			unsustainable because Rule 8(iii) postulates consent of Panchayati
			<lb />
			Raj Department; whereas part (l) of the order goes on to say that
			<lb />
			in case of inter-district transfers, parent Department will not be
			<lb />
			required to take consent of Panchayati Raj Department.
			<lb />
			27. In considered opinion of this Court, stipulation given in part
			<lb />
			(l) of the order does violence with what is contained in para (iii)
			<lb />
			of Rule 8 and it is in direct conflict with Rule 8(iii) of the Rules of
			<lb />
			2011.
			<lb />
			28. The order dated 16.06.2018 issued by the Chief Secretary of
			<lb />
			the State does not go along with Rule 8 of the Rules of 2011 and
			<lb />
			thus, the same cannot be allowed to endure. Though there is no
			<lb />
			specific challenge to said order, but since it has been relied upon
			<lb />
			by the State as a shield to protect the order of transfers, the
			<lb />
			Government order dated 16.06.2018 is hereby quashed.
			<lb />
			29. As a natural corollary, the impugned transfer orders (dated
			<lb />
			29.09.2019) issued by the Additional Director (Administration),
			<lb />
			Medical &amp; Health Department, Rajasthan Jaipur are also quashed;
			<lb />
			writ petitions are allowed.
			<lb />
			30. It is informed that the petitioners involved in the present
			<lb />
			bunch of writ petitions are protected by way of interim order(s)
			<lb />
			passed by this Court, the interim order(s) passed in these writ
			<lb />
			petitions, consequent to petitions being allowed, are made
			<lb />
			absolute.
			<lb />
			31. At the request of learned Additional Advocate General, the
			<lb />
			orders of transfer dated 29.09.2019 shall be treated to have been
			<lb />
			cancelled only qua these petitioners or who are protected by
			<lb />
		</body>

		<page>
			(13 of 16)
			<lb />
		</page>

		<note place='headnote'>
			[CW-14964/2019]
			<lb />
		</note>

		<body>
			interim orders already passed.
			<lb />
			Whosoever has/have joined
			<lb />
			pursuant to the transfer order dated 29.09.2019, at the new place
			<lb />
			of positing, shall not be entitled for relief and they shall not be
			<lb />
			disturbed.
			<lb />
			32. Needless to observe that if State in administrative exigencies
			<lb />
			wishes to transfer these petitioners, the same be done, needless
			<lb />
			to say, strictly in accordance with Rule 8 of the Rules of 2011.
			<lb />
			33. Registry is directed to keep photostat copy of this order in
			<lb />
			each file, mentioned in the Schedule.
			<lb />
			34. All interlocutory applications, including stay petitions stand
			<lb />
			disposed of.
			<lb />
			(DINESH MEHTA),J
			<lb />
			17-ArunV/-
			<lb />
			</body>


	</text>
</tei>