<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) 4483/2017
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 1 of 3
			<lb />
		</page>

		<front>
			$~21
			<lb />
			*IN THE HIGH COURT OF DELHI AT NEW DELHI
			<lb />
			%
			<lb />
			Judgment delivered on: 26.05.2017
			<lb />
			+
			<lb />
			W.P.(C) 4483/2017
			<lb />
			SANGHE TENPA LAMA
			<lb />
			..... Petitioner
			<lb />
			versus
			<lb />
			UNION OF INDIA &amp; ORS
			<lb />
			..... Respondents
			<lb />
			Advocates who appeared in this case:
			<lb />
			For the Petitioner
			<lb />
			:
			<lb />
			Mr. Sidhant Krishan Singh, Adv.
			<lb />
			For the Respondents
			<lb />
			:
			<lb />
			Mr. Rajesh Gogna, CGSC with Ms. Vipra
			<lb />
			Bhardwaj, Adv. for R-2
			<lb />
		</front>

		<body>
			CORAM:-
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR JUSTICE SANJEEV SACHDEVA
			<lb />
			JUDGMENT
			<lb />
			26.05.2017
			<lb />
			SANJEEV SACHDEVA, J. (ORAL)
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			The petitioner by the present petition seeks a direction to
			<lb />
			respondent to accept surrender of the identity certificate issued to the
			<lb />
			petitioner and for issuance of an Indian passport.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Learned counsel for the respondent submits that on the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) 4483/2017
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 2 of 3
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			petitioner&apos;s approaching the concerned passport office for surrender of
			<lb />
			the identity card and makes an application for issuance of the
			<lb />
			passport, the application would be processed in accordance with law
			<lb />
			and a passport would be issued provided the petitioner satisfies the
			<lb />
			requirement of the Passport Act, 1967 read with Passport Manuals
			<lb />
			2016 and the Rules framed thereunder.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			Learned counsel for the respondent submits that if the petitioner
			<lb />
			makes an application for surrender of identify card along with fresh
			<lb />
			application for issuance passport disclosing the number of identity
			<lb />
			certificates, the respondent shall consider the same in accordance with
			<lb />
			law.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			In view of the above, the writ petition is disposed of directing
			<lb />
			the petitioner to surrender the identity certificate with the regional
			<lb />
			passport office within 10 days. The petitioner thereafter shall be also
			<lb />
			be at liberty to make an application for surrender of identity certificate
			<lb />
			along with an application for issuance of fresh passport disclosing the
			<lb />
			number of identity certificates. On such an application being filed, the
			<lb />
			respondent shall consider the same in accordance with law.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			It is clarified that the petitioner may possess as many identity
			<lb />
			certificates as per rule and issuance of fresh passport could not be a
			<lb />
			ground to refuse the passport to the petitioner. The respondent shall
			<lb />
			issue a passport as expeditiously as possible preferably within a period
			<lb />
			of four weeks, subject to petitioner&apos;s satisfying the terms and
			<lb />
			conditions as well as the requirement of Passport Act, 1967 read with
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			WP(C) 4483/2017
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			Page 3 of 3
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Passport Manuals 2016 and the Rules framed thereunder.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			Order dasti under signatures of the Court Master.
			<lb />
			SANJEEV SACHDEVA, J
			<lb />
			MAY 26, 2017
			<lb />
			&apos;rs&apos;
		</body>


	</text>
</tei>