<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<head>
			CORAM:
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE J.R. MIDHA
			<lb />
			J U D G M E N T
			<lb />
		</head>

		<p>
			1.
			<lb />
			The appellant has challenged the order dated 6 th May, 2016
			<lb />
			passed by the Commissioner, Employees&quot; Compensation whereby
			<lb />
			compensation of Rs.10,69,008/-along with interest @ 12% per annum
			<lb />
			has been awarded to respondent no.1.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			The appellant is the owner of property bearing No.BU-48,
			<lb />
			Pitampura, Delhi on which a four storey building was being
			<lb />
			constructed in March 2012. On 6 th March, 2012, the roof (lintel) of
			<lb />
			the third floor was being laid. Respondent no.1 and his father were
			<lb />
			working as labourers on the construction site, along with 12-13 other
			<lb />
			labourers. According to respondent no.1, the contractor Gulab Singh
			<lb />
			(respondent no.2) instructed respondent no.1 to climb the wall of the
			<lb />
			third floor and club the grease of the lift with a cord from the bamboo
			<lb />
			whereupon respondent no.1 and another labourer told the contractor
			<lb />
			that the wall was weak and wet and would fall down. On the
			<lb />
			insistence of the contractor Gulab Singh, respondent no.1 climbed the
			<lb />
			wall whereupon wall broke and respondent no.1 fell down and
			<lb />
			suffered grievous injuries namely compression fracture of L1
			<lb />
			vertebrae and olecranon fracture of the left elbow along with tendon
			<lb />
			deformity in both lower legs. Respondent no.1 was admitted to Hindu
			<lb />
			Rao Hospital. The injuries suffered by respondent no.1 resulted in
			<lb />
			80% permanent disability relating to both lower limbs due to post-
			<lb />
			traumatic paraplegia as per the disability certificate dated 12 th April,
			<lb />
			2013. Police Station, Maurya Enclave registered FIR No.75 dated 6 th
			<lb />
			March, 2012 under Sections 288/337 against the contractor, Gulab
			<lb />
			Singh (respondent no.2) in which charge sheet has been filed.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			On 22 nd August, 2012, respondent no.1 filed an application for
			<lb />
			compensation before the Commissioner, Employees&quot; Compensation
			<lb />
			against the appellant as well as respondent no.2. Respondent No.1
			<lb />
			claimed that the accident arose out of and during the course of his
			<lb />
			employment. Respondent No.1 claimed compensation according to his
			<lb />
			age of 21 years, wages of Rs.10,500/-per month @ Rs.350/-per day
			<lb />
			and 100% permanent disability.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			The appellant contested the compensation application on the
			<lb />
			ground that the appellant had given the contract for construction of the
			<lb />
			stilt parking and a four storey building to respondent No.2 vide
			<lb />
			agreement for construction dated 10 th August, 2011 and, therefore, the
			<lb />
			appellant was not liable to pay any compensation to respondent No.1.
			<lb />
			The appellant filed an application for being deleted from the array of
			<lb />
			the parties which was dismissed by the Commissioner vide order dated
			<lb />
			2 nd May, 2013.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			Respondent no.2 contested the application for compensation on
			<lb />
			the ground that he had given the sub-contract for construction to
			<lb />
			Mohd. Rahil who had employed respondent no.1. Respondent no.2,
			<lb />
			however, admitted having taken respondent no.1 to the hospital where
			<lb />
			he spent Rs.85,000/-on the treatment of respondent no.1. Respondent
			<lb />
			No.2 filed an application for impleading Mohd. Rahil as a respondent
			<lb />
			which was dismissed by the Commissioner vide order dated 2 nd May,
			<lb />
			2013.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			On 21 st December, 2012, the appellant filed an application
			<lb />
			seeking direction to the Medical Superintendent of Aruna Asaf Ali
			<lb />
			Hospital, Delhi to examine respondent No.1 and assess his disability
			<lb />
			and issue a disability certificate in pursuance to which on 21 st
			<lb />
			February, 2013, the Commissioner directed the Medical
			<lb />
			Superintendent of Aruna Asaf Ali Hospital to examine respondent
			<lb />
			No.1 and issue the certificate.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			On 12 th April, 2013, the Medical Superintendent of Aruna Asaf
			<lb />
			Ali Government Hospital issued a certificate assessing the permanent
			<lb />
			disability of respondent No.1 as 80% in respect of both lower limbs
			<lb />
			due to post-traumatic paraplegia. The relevant portion of the said
			<lb />
			certificate is reproduced hereunder:-
			<lb />
			-GOVERNMENT OF NCT OF DELHI
			<lb />
			OFFICE OF MEDICAL SUPERINTENDENT
			<lb />
			ARUNA ASIF ALI GOVERNMENT HOSPITAL
			<lb />
			5, RAJPUR ROAD, DELHI-54
			<lb />
			No.1262
			<lb />
			Dated:12.04.2013
			<lb />
			CERTIFICATE FOR THE PERSONS WITH DISABILITIES
			<lb />
			This is to certify that Sh/Smt./Km. Aurangjeb Son/wife/Daughter of
			<lb />
			Sh. Harun Age 22 years old male/female, registration no.23964 is
			<lb />
			a case of Post Traumatic Paraplegia. He/She is physically
			<lb />
			disabled/visual disabled/speech disabled and has 80% (Eighty
			<lb />
			percent)
			<lb />
			permanent
			<lb />
			(Physical
			<lb />
			impairment/visual
			<lb />
			impairment/speech &amp; hearing impairment) in relation to his/her
			<lb />
			Both lower limbs
			<lb />
			Note:
			<lb />
			1. This condition is progressive/non-progressive/ likely to
			<lb />
			improve/ not likely to improve.
			<lb />
			2. Re-assessment is not recommended/is recommended after
			<lb />
			a period of _________Months/years.
			<lb />
			(Strike out which is not applicable)
			<lb />
			Signed/-
			<lb />
			Specialist
			<lb />
			Dr. B. Kanhar
			<lb />
			M.S. (Ortho)
			<lb />
			Sr. Ortho Specialist &amp; HOD
			<lb />
			(Ortho)
			<lb />
			Reg. No. 10361-DMC
			<lb />
			Aruna Asif Ali Govt. Hospital
			<lb />
			5, Rajpur Road, Delhi-110054
			<lb />
			Signed/-
			<lb />
			Specialist
			<lb />
			Dr. V.S. Rawat
			<lb />
			Specialist Medicine
			<lb />
			DMC Reg. No.2653
			<lb />
			Member Disability
			<lb />
			Board
			<lb />
			Signed/-
			<lb />
			Specialist
			<lb />
			Dr. Rajender
			<lb />
			Singh‖
			<lb /></p>

			<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			The Commissioner, Employees&quot; Compensation held that
			<lb />
			respondent no.1 suffered grievous injuries in the accident while
			<lb />
			working on the construction of building for the appellant and the
			<lb />
			accident arose out of and during the course of his employment with
			<lb />
			respondent no.2. The Commissioner took the upper-wage limit of
			<lb />
			Rs.8,000/-per month, respondent no.1&quot;s age of 21 years at the time of
			<lb />
			the accident and the factor of 222.71. The permanent disability of
			<lb />
			respondent no.1 was assessed by the Medical Board as 80% relating to
			<lb />
			both limbs due to post-traumatic paraplegia. However, considering
			<lb />
			that respondent no.1 was unable to do any physical work, the
			<lb />
			Commissioner took the loss of earning capacity as 100%. The
			<lb />
			Commissioner, Employees&quot; Compensation held that respondent no.1
			<lb />
			was entitled to compensation of Rs.10,69,008/-along with interest @
			<lb />
			12% per annum. The Commissioner held the appellant liable to pay
			<lb />
			compensation to respondent No.1. The Commissioner gave liberty to
			<lb />
			the appellant to recover the amount from respondent no.2 or any other
			<lb />
			person liable according to the appellant by invoking Sections 12 and
			<lb />
			13 of the Employee&quot;s Compensation Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			Vide order dated 09 th January, 2017, this Court requisitioned
			<lb />
			the record of FIR No.75/2012 dated 06 th March, 2012 under Section
			<lb />
			288/338 IPC, P.S. Maurya Enclave, Delhi in pursuance to which the
			<lb />
			relevant record of the FIR No.75/2012 was produced before this
			<lb />
			Court on 16 th May, 2017. The record of the FIR No.75/2012 contains
			<lb />
			the statement made by the appellant before the police on 03 rd
			<lb />
			September, 2012 under Section 161 Cr.P.C. The appellant stated
			<lb />
			before the police on 03 rd September, 2012 that there was no written
			<lb />
			agreement between him and Gulab Singh. Translation of the statement
			<lb />
			of the appellant before the police under Section 161 Cr.P.C is
			<lb />
			hereunder:
			<lb />
			-Case FIR No.75/2012 dated 06.03.12 u/s 288/338 IPC P.S.
			<lb />
			Maurya Encalve, Delhi
			<lb />
			Statement of Brijesh Kumar Verma s/o R.T.Verma r/o BU-48
			<lb />
			Pitam Pura, Delhi
			<lb />
			U/S 161 CRPC
			<lb />
			I am the current resident of abovementioned address
			<lb />
			and I am doing my private work and I had given the
			<lb />
			construction work of my house no. BU-48 Pitam
			<lb />
			Pura, Delhi to contractor Gulab Singh s/o Ram
			<lb />
			Singh r/o T-133 Mangol Puri, Delhi at the rate of
			<lb />
			Rs.115 per square feet. Gulab Singh started
			<lb />
			construction work of my house in October, 2011 and
			<lb />
			at that time there was no written agreement between
			<lb />
			us.
			<lb />
			You have taken my statement which is correct.
			<lb />
			Singed
			<lb />
			H.C. Satbir 60/NW
			<lb />
			P.S. M. enclave
			<lb />
			3.9.12‖
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			10. Learned counsel for the appellant urged at the time of the
			<lb />
			hearing that respondent no.1 was employed by respondent no.2 who
			<lb />
			alone was liable to pay the compensation to the petitioner. Reference
			<lb />
			was made to the construction agreement dated 10 th August, 2011
			<lb />
			between appellant and respondent no.2 under which respondent no.2
			<lb />
			was responsible for the accident during construction. It was further
			<lb />
			submitted that respondent no.2 had appointed a sub-contractor, Rahil
			<lb />
			who in turn had employed respondent no.1. It was further submitted
			<lb />
			that the appellant cannot be held liable to pay the compensation under
			<lb />
			Section 12 of the Employees&quot; Compensation Act because the
			<lb />
			construction of the residential house was not part of his trade or
			<lb />
			business. The appellant disputed the income of respondent no.1 taken
			<lb />
			by the Commissioner, Employees&quot; Compensation. The appellant
			<lb />
			further disputed the permanent disability of 80% assessed by the
			<lb />
			Medical Board and the loss of earning capacity of 100% assessed by
			<lb />
			the Commissioner. Reliance was placed on Bharat Earth Movers Ltd.
			<lb />
			v. Bhagyamma, 1975 A.C.J. 113, Dr. B. Radhakrishna v.
			<lb />
			Gouramma, 2000 (85) FLR 388, Lakshminarayana Shetty v.
			<lb />
			Shantha, 2002 III LLJ 523, Ajay Singh Lal v. Somwati, 116 (2005)
			<lb />
			DLT 421, Om Parkash Batish v. Ranjit, II (2008) ACC 462 (SC),
			<lb />
			Management, Sirishad Construction (P) v. C.P. Ravinder, 2000 LAB
			<lb />
			I.C. 1817 and Kolhan Samvedak Sangh v. State of Jharkhand, 2017
			<lb />
			(154) FLR 298.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			11. Learned counsel for respondent no.1 urged at the time of the
			<lb />
			hearing that respondent no.1 was an &quot;employee&quot; within the meaning of
			<lb />
			Section 2(1)(dd) of the Employees&quot; Compensation Act. It was
			<lb />
			submitted that the definition of &quot;workman‖ in Section 2(1) (n) of the
			<lb />
			Workmen&quot;s Compensation Act was amended in the year 2000. It was
			<lb />
			submitted that Section 2(1) (n) of the Workmen&quot;s Compensation Act,
			<lb />
			1923 was amended by Workmen&quot;s Compensation (Amendment) Act,
			<lb />
			2000 with effect from 8 th December, 2000 whereby the words &quot;other
			<lb />
			than a person whose employment is of a casual nature and who is
			<lb />
			employed otherwise than for the purposes of the employer&apos;s trade or
			<lb />
			business&quot; in the definition of ‗workman&apos; in Section 2(1) (n) were
			<lb />
			omitted. The effect of the omission of words &quot;other than a person
			<lb />
			whose employment is of a casual nature and who is employed
			<lb />
			otherwise than for the purposes of the employer&apos;s trade or business&quot;
			<lb />
			in the definition of workman in Section 2(1)(n) by the amendment in
			<lb />
			2000 is that a person whose employment is of a casual nature and is
			<lb />
			employed other than for the purposes of the employer&quot;s trade or
			<lb />
			business, would be covered within the meaning of -employee‖ as
			<lb />
			defined in Section 2(1)(dd) of the Employees Compensation Act and
			<lb />
			entitled to compensation against the principal under section 12 of the
			<lb />
			Employees Compensation Act. Reliance was placed on Govind
			<lb />
			Goenka v. Dayawati, 2013 ACJ 1897 in which this Court held that
			<lb />
			after the amendment, the workman whose employment is of casual
			<lb />
			nature and who is employed otherwise than for the purpose of
			<lb />
			employer&apos;s trade or business, would also be covered within the
			<lb />
			definition of &quot;workman‖. Reliance was also placed on Public Works
			<lb />
			Department v. Commissioner, Workmen Compensation, 1981
			<lb />
			Lab.I.C. 493 in which Division Bench of Jammu and Kashmir High
			<lb />
			Court held that the word &quot;business&quot; in Section 12 has to be given an
			<lb />
			extended meaning, so as to include even an activity which engages
			<lb />
			time, attention or labour as a principal serious concern or interest of an
			<lb />
			individual without an element of profit in it. The Response of
			<lb />
			respondent no.1 to the judgments relied upon by the appellant is as
			<lb />
			under:-
			<lb />
			11.1. In Bharat Earth Movers Ltd. v. Bhagyamma (supra) relied
			<lb />
			upon by the appellant, the Karnataka High Court exonerated the
			<lb />
			principal holding that the construction of the building was not
			<lb />
			ordinarily a part of trade or business of the appellant who was engaged
			<lb />
			in the business of manufacture of earth moving machinery. This
			<lb />
			judgment does not help the appellant as it relates to an accident in
			<lb />
			1969 i.e. prior to the Workmen&quot;s Compensation (Amendment) Act,
			<lb />
			2000.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			11.2. In Dr. B. Radhakrishna v. Gouramma (supra) relied upon by
			<lb />
			the appellant, the Karnataka High Court held that a person
			<lb />
			constructing a residential building cannot be held liable unless it is
			<lb />
			shown that he had given a contract and he was the principal employer.
			<lb />
			This judgment does not help the appellant as it relates to an accident in
			<lb />
			1990 i.e. prior to the Workmen&quot;s Compensation (Amendment) Act,
			<lb />
			2000.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			11.3. Lakshminarayana Shetty v. Shantha (supra) also relates to
			<lb />
			case prior to Workmen&quot;s Compensation (Amendment) Act, 2000 by
			<lb />
			which the words &quot;other than a person whose employment was of
			<lb />
			casual nature&quot; were omitted.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			11.4. In Ajay Singh Lal v. Somwati (supra), the owner of a
			<lb />
			residential house was exonerated from the liability under Section 12 of
			<lb />
			the Act on the ground that the construction work was ordinarily not
			<lb />
			part of the ‗trade or business&apos; of the owner. This judgement also
			<lb />
			relates to an accident prior to Workmen&quot;s Compensation
			<lb />
			(Amendment) Act, 2000.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			11.5. All the aforesaid four judgments relied upon by the appellant
			<lb />
			relates to the accidents prior to the Workmen&quot;s Compensation
			<lb />
			(Amendment) Act, 2000 whereas the present case relates to an
			<lb />
			accident after the 2000 amendment, which came into force on 8 th
			<lb />
			December, 2000. Workmen&quot;s Compensation (Amendment) Act, 2000
			<lb />
			deleted the words ‗trade or business&apos; from the definition of the word
			<lb />
			‗workman&apos;. In Govind Goenka v. Dayawati (supra), this court held
			<lb />
			that the effect of omission of -trade or business‖ from the definition
			<lb />
			of -workman‖ meant that the owner shall be liable even in respect of
			<lb />
			the work other than his trade or business.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			11.6. Bharat Earth Movers Ltd. v. Bhagyamma (supra), Dr. B.
			<lb />
			Radhakrishna v. Gouramma (supra), Ajay Singh Lal v. Somwati
			<lb />
			(supra) and Lakshminarayana Shetty v. Shantha (supra) did not
			<lb />
			consider the interpretation of the word -business‖ in Section 12. The
			<lb />
			word ‗business&apos; in Section 12 has been interpreted in Payyannur
			<lb />
			Educational Society v. Narayani (supra), Public Works Department
			<lb />
			v. Commissioner, Workmen Compensation (supra), Bala Mallamma
			<lb />
			v. Registrar, Osmania University (supra), Govind Goenka v.
			<lb />
			Dayawati (supra), Raj Pal Saini v. Kamla (supra) to include an
			<lb />
			activity which engages time, attention and labour.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			11.7. In Om Parkash Batish v. Ranjit (supra), the Supreme Court
			<lb />
			dealt with the question as to whether a casual employee would be a
			<lb />
			-workman‖ within the meaning of Section 2(n) of the Workmen&quot;s
			<lb />
			Compensation Act, 1923 in respect of an accident dated 30 th June,
			<lb />
			1996. The Supreme Court held that the person, whose employment
			<lb />
			was of casual nature, was specifically excluded in the definition of
			<lb />
			workman under Section 2(n) of the Workmen&quot;s Compensation Act,
			<lb />
			1923. The Supreme Court further held that the words &quot;other than a
			<lb />
			person whose employment was of casual nature‖ were omitted by an
			<lb />
			amendment in 2000 but the amendment would not apply to an
			<lb />
			accident occurred prior to the date on which amendment came into
			<lb />
			force. The Supreme Court clearly recorded in para 22 of the judgment
			<lb />
			that they were considering the statutory provision prior to the
			<lb />
			amendment of 2000 by which the words &quot;other than a person whose
			<lb />
			employment was of casual nature&quot; were omitted.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			11.8. In Management, Sirishad Construction (P) v. C.P. Ravinder
			<lb />
			(supra), the employee suffered hearing loss of 20% as per the medical
			<lb />
			certificate issued by a doctor. The Commissioner, Employees&quot;
			<lb />
			Compensation held the loss of earning capacity to be 70%. The
			<lb />
			Andhra Pradesh High Court set aside the order and remanded back the
			<lb />
			matter to the Commissioner. This judgement does not help the
			<lb />
			appellant as the claimant in that case was not examined by the Medical
			<lb />
			Board of a Government Hospital whereas in the present case, the
			<lb />
			Commissioner, Employees&quot; Compensation directed the Medical
			<lb />
			Superintendent of Aruna Asif Ali Hospital, Delhi on 21 st February,
			<lb />
			2013 to examine respondent No.1 and certify his disability in
			<lb />
			pursuance to which the Medical Board examined the injured-claimant
			<lb />
			and issued the disability certificate dated 12 th April, 2013.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			11.9. In Kolhan Samvedak Sangh v. State of Jharkhand (supra), this
			<lb />
			Court held the contractor liable to pay the cess and dismissed the writ
			<lb />
			petition of the contractor for seeking refund of 1% cess deducted by
			<lb />
			the Rural Works Department. This judgment is not relevant with
			<lb />
			respect to the liability of an owner of a residential house to pay the
			<lb />
			compensation under Section 12 in respect of the death/injury to the
			<lb />
			employee employed through the contractor.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			12. Vide order dated 9 th January, 2017, Mr. Sanjoy Ghose, learned
			<lb />
			Additional Standing Counsel for Govt. of NCT of Delhi was directed
			<lb />
			place on record the safety requirements for construction workers and
			<lb />
			the legal position with respect to the responsibilities for failure to
			<lb />
			comply with the legal norms and standards. Learned Additional
			<lb />
			Standing Counsel was also directed to give suggestions with respect to
			<lb />
			the responsibility of the owners of the building who carry out
			<lb />
			construction without any safety measures for building workers.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			13. Mr. Sanjoy Ghose submitted a note with respect to the various
			<lb />
			statutes applicable to the construction workers and suggestions for
			<lb />
			ensuring the safety of the construction workers. It was submitted that
			<lb />
			the definition of &quot;workman‖ in Section 2 (1) (n) of the Workmen&quot;s
			<lb />
			Compensation Act was amended in the year 2000 to include the
			<lb />
			workers whose appointment were of casual nature and who were
			<lb />
			employed otherwise for the purpose of employers -trade or business‖.
			<lb />
			It was submitted that the rules of purposive construction, liberal
			<lb />
			interpretation and cessante ratione legis, cessat et ipsa lex would
			<lb />
			apply to interpret the amendment of Section 2 (1) (n). Reliance was
			<lb />
			placed on Workmen of American Express v. Management of
			<lb />
			American Express, AIR 1986 SC 458, Union of India v.
			<lb />
			Prabhakaran Vijaya Kumar, (2008) 9 SCC 527, Kunal Singh v.
			<lb />
			Union of India, (2003) 4 SCC 524, B.D. Shetty v. CEAT Ltd., (2002)
			<lb />
			1 SCC 193, Transport Corporation of India v. ESI Corporation,
			<lb />
			(2000) 1 SCC 332, Regional P.F. Commissioner v. Hooghly Mills
			<lb />
			Co. Ltd., (2012) 1 SCR 363 and H.H. Shri Swamiji Shri Admar Mutt
			<lb />
			Etc. v. The Commissioner, Hindu Religious &amp; Charitable
			<lb />
			Endowments Department, (1980) 1 SCR 368. Mr. Sanjoy Ghose also
			<lb />
			submitted a note on the meaning of -trade or business‖ in Section 12
			<lb />
			and the legal effect of the omission of words &quot;trade or business‖ from
			<lb />
			the definition of &quot;employee&quot; in Section 2(1)(dd) of the Employees&quot;
			<lb />
			Compensation Act on Section 12 of the Employees&quot; Compensation
			<lb />
			Act. It was submitted that the word &quot;business‖ in Section 12 has been
			<lb />
			interpreted by the Division Bench of Andhra Pradesh High Court in
			<lb />
			Balla Mallamma v. Registrar, Osmania University, Hyderabad, 2001
			<lb />
			(2) T.A.C. 182 (AP) 11 and Govind Goenka v. Dayawati (supra), in
			<lb />
			which this Court held that the word -business‖ has to be given
			<lb />
			extended meaning to include an activity that engages time, attention or
			<lb />
			labour.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			14. During the course of the hearing dated 31 st July, 2017, this
			<lb />
			Court considered the applicability of Building and Other Construction
			<lb />
			Workers (Regulation of Employment and Conditions of Service) Act,
			<lb />
			1996 which applies to residential buildings in which more than 10
			<lb />
			workers are employed on any day during preceding 12 months and the
			<lb />
			total cost of the construction is more than Rs.10 lakh. The appellant
			<lb />
			admitted that he spent more than Rs.10 lakh in the construction of the
			<lb />
			building but disputed the applicability of the Act on the ground that
			<lb />
			the building workers employed by the contractor never exceeded 10.
			<lb />
			The relevant portion of the order dated 31 st July, 2017 is reproduced
			<lb />
			hereunder:
			<lb />
			-1.
			<lb />
			Arguments heard with respect to the applicability of
			<lb />
			Building and Other Construction Workers&apos; (Regulation of
			<lb />
			Employment and Conditions of Service) Act,1996 to residential
			<lb />
			buildings in which more than 10 workers are employed on any
			<lb />
			day during 12 months and the cost of the building is more than
			<lb />
			Rs.10,00,000/-and scope of Section 45(2) which imposes the
			<lb />
			responsibility of payment of the compensation under the
			<lb />
			Employee&apos;s Compensation Act on the owner as defined in
			<lb />
			Section 2(i), if the contractor fails to make the payment of
			<lb />
			compensation in respect of the building workers.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			Mr. Harvinder Singh, leaned counsel for the appellant
			<lb />
			admits that the appellant spent more than Rs.10,00,000/-in
			<lb />
			construction of the building but the building workers employed
			<lb />
			by the contractor never exceeded 10.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			At this stage, this Court considered necessary to examine
			<lb />
			the appellant on oath. The appellant has been partly examined
			<lb />
			to ascertain the cost of construction and the number of workers
			<lb />
			employed in the construction of the building.‖
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			15. On 31 st July, 2017, this Court examined the appellant under
			<lb />
			Section 165 of the Indian Evidence Act when the appellant deposed
			<lb />
			on oath that only 4-5 persons worked on the site during construction
			<lb />
			The statement of the appellant recorded by this Court on 31 st July,
			<lb />
			2017 is reproduced hereunder:
			<lb />
			-Statement of Brijesh Kumar Verma, S/o late Sh. Tirath Verma,
			<lb />
			R/o. BU-48, Pitampura, Delhi.
			<lb />
			On SA
			<lb />
			I awarded the contract for construction of
			<lb />
			residential house at property No.BU-48,
			<lb />
			Pitampura, New Delhi in September, 2011 to
			<lb />
			respondent No.2. The construction of the building
			<lb />
			was completed in January, 2013. I incurred cost of
			<lb />
			Rs.40,00,000/-
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			Rs.45,00,000/-
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			construction of this building. I paid approximately
			<lb />
			Rs.5,50,000/-to the contractor Gulab Singh. I
			<lb />
			visited the property approximately about 25-30
			<lb />
			times during the course of the construction.
			<lb />
			Whenever I visited the property, only 4-5 persons
			<lb />
			(1-2 mistari and 2-3 workers) were doing the
			<lb />
			construction work.‖
			<lb />
			16. Respondent no.1, in his cross-examination dated 10 th December,
			<lb />
			2014, had stated that more than 30 workers were working on the site
			<lb />
			and 12-13 labourers were present on the date of accident. Relevant
			<lb />
			portion of the cross-examination of respondent no.1 is reproduced
			<lb />
			hereunder:
			<lb />
			-It is correct that I was daily wage labourer. My father is
			<lb />
			also a daily wage labourer. It is correct that I was part of
			<lb />
			labours who were in supposed to put linter in BU-48,
			<lb />
			Pitam pura, delhi and I was called my Md. Rahil as well
			<lb />
			as Sh. Gulab Singh. 30 more workers were working with
			<lb />
			Mohd. Rahil……
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			………On that day i.e. 06.03.2012, I was working on the
			<lb />
			3rd floor of the premises. It is incorrect that I was
			<lb />
			specifically called for putting up of linter in the said
			<lb />
			premises and I did not do any other work……12-13 other
			<lb />
			labourers were present on the date of accident‖
			<lb />
			17. On 11 th August, 2017, this Court heard the arguments on the
			<lb />
			applicability of BOCW Act to the present case. It was submitted on
			<lb />
			behalf of the appellant that the appellant was the owner of the building
			<lb />
			but he was not an employer as defined in Section 2(1) (i) of BOCW
			<lb />
			Act. It was further submitted that respondent no.2 (contractor) was
			<lb />
			the employer for the purpose of Section 2(1) (i) of BOCW Act. It was
			<lb />
			further submitted that the owner of the building can be held liable only
			<lb />
			when the owner himself carries on the construction activity on his
			<lb />
			premises but when the construction is carried out through the
			<lb />
			contractor, the contractor will be deemed to be the owner. It was
			<lb />
			further submitted that the appellant was not liable to pay compensation
			<lb />
			under Section 45 of the BOCW Act. It was further submitted that the
			<lb />
			liability, if at all, will arise if the contractor fails to make the payment.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			18. The submissions of respondent no.1 with respect to the BOCW
			<lb />
			Act are that the Act applies to every establishment where 10 or more
			<lb />
			building workers were employed in the building or other construction
			<lb />
			work; -building or other construction work‖ has been defined in
			<lb />
			Section 2(1)(d) of the BOCW Act; the term &quot;employer‖ has been
			<lb />
			defined in Section 2(1)(i) of the BOCW Act which defines employer
			<lb />
			to mean owner and includes the contractor in relation to an
			<lb />
			establishment; -establishment‖ has been defined in Section 2(1)(j)
			<lb />
			which only excludes the construction work of the residential house by
			<lb />
			the owner himself where the cost of construction is less than Rs.10
			<lb />
			lakh; and Section 45 imposes the liability of payment of compensation
			<lb />
			on the employer as defined in Section 2(1)(i) . It was submitted that
			<lb />
			the appellant was the employer and clearly liable to pay the
			<lb />
			compensation under Section 45 of the BOCW Act as the cost of
			<lb />
			construction was more than Rs.10 lakh and more than 10 employees
			<lb />
			were employed in the construction work.
			<lb />
			19. Mr. Sanjoy Ghose, learned Additional Standing Counsel for
			<lb />
			GNCTD urged at the time of the hearing that BOCW Act applies to
			<lb />
			private construction of residential building where the cost of such
			<lb />
			construction is more than Rs.10 lakh and more than 10 building
			<lb />
			workers had been employed on any day in the preceding 12 months.
			<lb />
			The -employer‖ defined in Section 2(1) (i) of BOCW Act specifically
			<lb />
			includes the owner. Section 58 of the BOCW Act clearly provides
			<lb />
			that the provisions of Employee&quot;s Compensation Act shall apply to the
			<lb />
			building workers. Section 45 of the BOCW Act makes the contractor
			<lb />
			and employer liable to pay the compensation to the building worker.
			<lb />
			The appellant, being the owner of the building, is an -employer‖
			<lb />
			within the meaning of Section 2(1) (i) and is liable to pay the
			<lb />
			compensation under Section 45 of the BOCW Act.
			<lb />
			20. Liability of the principal under Section 12 of the Employee&apos;s
			<lb />
			Compensation Act
			<lb />
			Section 12 of the Employee&quot;s Compensation Act imposes the liability
			<lb />
			of payment of compensation on the principal with right to recover the
			<lb />
			same from the contractor in respect of work being carried out by the
			<lb />
			contractor. Section 12 of the Employee&quot;s Compensation Act is
			<lb />
			reproduced hereunder:
			<lb />
			-Section 12 -Contracting -
			<lb />
			(1) Where any person (hereinafter in this section referred to as the
			<lb />
			principal) in the course of or for the purposes of his trade or
			<lb />
			business contracts with any other person (hereinafter in this
			<lb />
			section referred to as the contractor) for the execution by or under
			<lb />
			the contractor of the whole or any part of any work which is
			<lb />
			ordinarily part of the trade or business of the principal, the
			<lb />
			principal shall be liable to pay to any employee employed in the
			<lb />
			execution of the work any compensation which he would have been
			<lb />
			liable to pay if that employee had been immediately employed by
			<lb />
			him; and where compensation is claimed from the principal, this
			<lb />
			Act shall apply as if references to the principal were substituted for
			<lb />
			references to the employer except that the amount of compensation
			<lb />
			shall be calculated with reference to the wages of the employee
			<lb />
			under the employer by whom he is immediately employed.
			<lb />
			(2) Where the principal is liable to pay compensation under this
			<lb />
			section, he shall be entitled to be indemnified by the contractor, or
			<lb />
			any other person from whom the employee could have recovered
			<lb />
			compensation and where a contractor who is himself a principal is
			<lb />
			liable to pay compensation or to indemnify a principal under this
			<lb />
			section he shall be entitled to be indemnified by any person
			<lb />
			standing to him in the relation of a contractor from whom
			<lb />
			the employee could have recovered compensation and all questions
			<lb />
			as to the right to and the amount of any such indemnity shall, in
			<lb />
			default of agreement, be settled by the Commissioner.
			<lb />
			(3) Nothing in this section shall be construed as preventing an
			<lb />
			employee from recovering compensation from the contractor
			<lb />
			instead of the principal.
			<lb />
			FAO 345/2016
			<lb />
			Page 18 of 72
			<lb />
			(4) This section shall not apply in any case where the accident
			<lb />
			occurred elsewhere that on, in or about the premises on which the
			<lb />
			principal has undertaken or usually undertakes, as the case may
			<lb />
			be, to execute the work or which are otherwise under his control or
			<lb />
			management.‖
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			21. Object of Section 12 of the Employee&apos;s Compensation Act
			<lb />
			The object for enacting the Employees&quot; Compensation Act even as
			<lb />
			early as 1923 was to ameliorate the hardship of economically poor
			<lb />
			employees who were exposed to risks in work, or occupational
			<lb />
			hazards by providing a cheaper and quicker machinery for
			<lb />
			compensating them with pecuniary benefits. Section 12 safeguards
			<lb />
			the right to compensation when the employer delegates the work to
			<lb />
			another person. Section 12 is intended to secure to an employee the
			<lb />
			right to claim compensation not only against his immediate employer
			<lb />
			who, in the Act, is referred to as a contractor, but also against the
			<lb />
			person who had employed such contractor to execute the work. The
			<lb />
			Act refers to him as the principal. The main object of enacting Section
			<lb />
			12 of the Act is to secure compensation to the employees who have
			<lb />
			been engaged by the principal employer through a contractor for the
			<lb />
			work which the principal employer is supposed to carry out. If a
			<lb />
			person substitutes another for himself to do his work, he ought not to
			<lb />
			escape the liability which would have been imposed upon him, if he
			<lb />
			had done it himself. The intention of the Legislature in enacting
			<lb />
			Section 12 provision appears to be that the injured employee or the
			<lb />
			dependent of a deceased employee who has been awarded
			<lb />
			compensation by the Commissioner, should not be put to any
			<lb />
			difficulty in realising such amount of compensation on account of any
			<lb />
			FAO 345/2016
			<lb />
			Page 19 of 72
			<lb />
			recalcitrance of the employer or on account of the vicissitudes of his
			<lb />
			(the employer&quot;s) financial position. The Employees&quot; Compensation
			<lb />
			Act, 1923 is a piece of social beneficial legislation and its provisions
			<lb />
			have to be interpreted in a manner so as not to deprive the employees
			<lb />
			of the benefit of the legislation. Reference be made to Bhutabhai
			<lb />
			Angadbhai v. Gujarat Electricity Board, 1987 (1) L.L.N. 156; M.R.
			<lb />
			Mishrikoti v. Muktumsab Hasansab Asoti, (1972) 2 Mys LJ 449;
			<lb />
			Koli Mansukh Rana v. Patel Natha Ramji, 1992 ACJ 772;
			<lb />
			Payyannur Educational Society v. Narayani, (1996) 72 FLR 709;
			<lb />
			Public Works Department v. Commissioner, Workmen
			<lb />
			Compensation, (supra); Koodalingam v. Superintending Engineer,
			<lb />
			Project Circle, Public Works Department, Kozhikode, 1994 (2)
			<lb />
			L.L.N. 779; Sardar Sewa Singh v. Hindustan Lever Ltd., 1980 (1)
			<lb />
			L.L.N. 566 and Executive Engineer/Deputy General Manager, Sub
			<lb />
			Urban Division, DHBVNL, Bhiwani v. Priyanka, 2017 (153) FLR
			<lb />
			302 in which the Courts have examined the scope of Section 12.
			<lb />
			22. Section 12 of the Act has, in effect, stretched the contours of the
			<lb />
			word &quot;employer‖ wider as to include the person contracting with
			<lb />
			another person for carrying out the work of the former. In such cases,
			<lb />
			the provision enjoins that the principal shall stand substituted as the
			<lb />
			employer. This is achieved by the words &quot;where compensation is
			<lb />
			claimed from the principal, this Act shall apply as if references to the
			<lb />
			principal were substituted for references to the employer&quot;. The
			<lb />
			principal may have a claim for indemnity from his contractor or
			<lb />
			delegatee but the victim or his dependents are not to be involved in
			<lb />
			such disputes.
			<lb />
			FAO 345/2016
			<lb />
			Page 20 of 72
			<lb />
			23. Section 12 will apply notwithstanding the agreement or contract
			<lb />
			entered into between the principal and contractor regarding their
			<lb />
			liability for payment of compensation under the Act. The agreement or
			<lb />
			contract between the principal and the contractor shall govern only
			<lb />
			their inter-se rights and liabilities, and cannot affect the right of the
			<lb />
			employee or the dependants of the employee, to get the compensation
			<lb />
			from the principal or from the contractor at their option.
			<lb />
			24. Section 12 secures compensation to the employee who cannot
			<lb />
			fight out his battle for compensation by a speedy process. A person
			<lb />
			who employs others to advance his own interest is expected to provide
			<lb />
			a surer basis for payment of the injured employee than the
			<lb />
			intermediary, who may often turn out to be a man of straw, from
			<lb />
			whom compensation may not be available. This is the purpose for
			<lb />
			which the claimant is given the option under section 12 (3) of the Act
			<lb />
			to claim the compensation either from the principal or from the
			<lb />
			contractor.
			<lb />
			25. The contractor may not be a man of means or he may be merely
			<lb />
			a man of straw or it may be that wittingly or unwittingly he may
			<lb />
			possibly be part of an arrangement conceived by the principal to avoid
			<lb />
			confrontation directly with the employee engaged in the execution of
			<lb />
			the work. In either case, the interests of the employee need to be
			<lb />
			protected and that is what this provision secures to the employee. The
			<lb />
			principal can seek indemnification from the contractor if he has been
			<lb />
			made answerable for the payment of compensation. The right of the
			<lb />
			principal to be indemnified has thus been incorporated under Section
			<lb />
			12 (2), who has entrusted the work to the contractor stipulating the
			<lb />
			right of indemnification under the Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			26. Section 12 of the Act gives protection to the employee in case
			<lb />
			of an accident and secures compensation from the persons who can
			<lb />
			pay, so that such employee will not be dependent upon a petty
			<lb />
			contractor(s) who may themselves not be able to pay compensation on
			<lb />
			account of their financial inability.
			<lb />
			27. Section 12 is an enabling provision for the benefit of the
			<lb />
			employee(s) and enacted with the clear objective that the employee(s)
			<lb />
			should not be hampered by technicalities or practical difficulties of
			<lb />
			deciphering the correct employers. A pragmatic method has thus been
			<lb />
			devised for fixing the liability of the principal employer and thereby
			<lb />
			affording speedy relief to the employee for payment of compensation
			<lb />
			on account of the accident, though the principal has been invested with
			<lb />
			the right of indemnifying himself from the contractor who may have
			<lb />
			employed the employee and may have been responsible for taking
			<lb />
			work from him.
			<lb />
			28. Interpretation of the words &quot;trade or business‖ in Section 12
			<lb />
			The words -trade or business‖ used in Section 12 of the Act have to
			<lb />
			be understood in the context in which this Act was enacted. The Act
			<lb />
			was enacted to provide compensation to the employees suffering
			<lb />
			during the course of their employment. It was also the purpose of the
			<lb />
			Act that the employees should get speedy remedies and it appears that
			<lb />
			the intention of enacting Section 12 of the Act was only to ensure that
			<lb />
			compensation is paid by the principal expeditiously and if this purpose
			<lb />
			of the Act and the provision is kept in mind, then the words -trade‖ or
			<lb />
			-business‖ may not have the same meaning which they would have,
			<lb />
			for instance, when used in interpreting a taxing statute. The word
			<lb />
			&quot;trade&quot; connotes commercial activity whereas the word &quot;business&quot; is
			<lb />
			of much wider import and may be used in different contexts in
			<lb />
			different senses. Used in one context, it may imply a particular
			<lb />
			occupation or employment to earn livelihood or gain, whereas used in
			<lb />
			a different context it may mean an activity which engages time,
			<lb />
			attention, or labour as a principal serious concern or interest. Its
			<lb />
			connotation may thus vary with the varying contexts in which it is
			<lb />
			used. In taxing statutes for instance, the word &quot;business&quot; will always
			<lb />
			denote an activity carried out with the object of earning profit, though
			<lb />
			the same may not be true when used in relation to other activities. The
			<lb />
			meaning of these two crucial words in Section 12 has to be understood
			<lb />
			in the context of its object. The word &quot;business&quot; in the Section 12 need
			<lb />
			not be restricted to what is synonymous with -trade‖. The use of the
			<lb />
			conjunction ‗or&apos; should be understood as disjunctive for covering
			<lb />
			totally different areas unconnected with -trade‖. The word &quot;business&quot;
			<lb />
			has different shades of meanings. Among them, the most suitable in
			<lb />
			the present context is the meaning task, duty, concern or undertaking
			<lb />
			to do a work. The word &quot;business&quot; in its wider connotation may have
			<lb />
			more extensive meaning than the word -trade‖ and it means
			<lb />
			&quot;anything which occupies the time and attention and labour of a
			<lb />
			man for the purpose of profit&quot;. The word -business‖ used in Section
			<lb />
			12 of the Act has been intended to convey the meaning -the work or
			<lb />
			task undertaken by the person concerned‖ which is not restricted to
			<lb />
			trade or commercial work alone. Used in broader sense, a person
			<lb />
			building his residential house may well be said to do &quot;business&quot; in so
			<lb />
			far as the said activity engages his or its time, attention or labour as
			<lb />
			principal serious concern or interest. Used in broader sense, a person
			<lb />
			building his residential house, may well be said to do &quot;business&quot; in so
			<lb />
			far as the said activity engages his time, attention or labour as
			<lb />
			principal serious concern or interest. Reference be made to the
			<lb />
			following judgments in which the Courts interpreted the words -trade
			<lb />
			or business‖ in Section 12:-
			<lb />
			28.1. In Payyannur Educational Society v. Narayani, (supra), two
			<lb />
			workmen engaged in land excavating operation were buried alive in a
			<lb />
			landslide whereupon claim for compensation was made against an
			<lb />
			educational society. The society contested the claim on the ground
			<lb />
			that the society sold the soil to the contractor, who had engaged the
			<lb />
			workman and was liable to pay the compensation. It was further
			<lb />
			pleaded that ordinary business of the society was to impart education
			<lb />
			and digging work was not part of its -trade‖ or -business‖. The
			<lb />
			Division Bench of Kerala High Court headed by K.T.Thomas, J. as he
			<lb />
			then was, held that the word -business‖ used in Section 12 of the Act
			<lb />
			has been intended to convey the meaning as the work or task
			<lb />
			undertaken by the person concerned which are not restricted to trade
			<lb />
			or commercial work alone. The relevant portion of the judgment is
			<lb />
			reproduced hereunder:-
			<lb />
			-9. It is trite law that the safe guidance for interpreting any
			<lb />
			provision in a statute or for understanding the scope and
			<lb />
			meaning of a particular word in provision, is to ascertain the
			<lb />
			intention of the legislature. However wide in the abstract,
			<lb />
			general words and phrases are more or less elastic and admit of
			<lb />
			restriction or extension to suit the legislative intention. &quot;The
			<lb />
			object of the legislation would afford answer to the problems
			<lb />
			arising from ambiguities which it contains&quot;, (vide Maxwell on
			<lb />
			the &quot;Interpretation of Statutes&quot; 12 th edition at page 86).
			<lb />
			10.
			<lb />
			We bear in mind that one of the objects for enacting the
			<lb />
			Act even as early as 1923 was to ameliorate the hardships of
			<lb />
			economically poor workmen who were exposed to risks in work,
			<lb />
			or occupational hazards by providing a cheaper and quicker
			<lb />
			machinery for compensating them with pecuniary benefits. With
			<lb />
			the progress of times the concept impelled the courts, by and
			<lb />
			large, to make stretched constructions without violating the
			<lb />
			fundamental principles in order to advance the above object.
			<lb />
			Looking at it from the above angle, the object of the legislature
			<lb />
			in providing Section 12 in the Act is to safeguard the right to
			<lb />
			compensation when the employer delegates the work to another
			<lb />
			person.
			<lb />
			11. We will now proceed to consider in what manner the
			<lb />
			words &quot;business&quot; and &quot;ordinarily&quot; in Section 12 of the Act
			<lb />
			should be understood.
			<lb />
			12.
			<lb />
			Section 3 of the Act imposes a liability on the employer
			<lb />
			to pay compensation in cases where personal injury is caused to
			<lb />
			a workman by accident arising out of and in the course of the
			<lb />
			employment. Section 12 of the Act has, in effect, stretched the
			<lb />
			contours of the word &quot;employer&quot; wider as to include the person
			<lb />
			contracting with another person for carrying out the work of the
			<lb />
			former. In such cases, the provision enjoins that the principal
			<lb />
			shall stand substituted as the employer. This is achieved by the
			<lb />
			words &apos;where compensation is claimed from the principal, this
			<lb />
			Act shall apply as if references to the principal were substituted
			<lb />
			for references to the employer&quot;. The principal may have any
			<lb />
			claim for contribution from his contractor or delegatee, but that
			<lb />
			can be dealt with as between them separately. The victim or his
			<lb />
			dependents are not to be involved in such disputes. This much
			<lb />
			can easily be discerned from the section.
			<lb />
			13. The meaning of the two crucial words in Section 12 has
			<lb />
			to be understood in the above context. We do not think that the
			<lb />
			word &quot;business&quot; in the section need be restricted to what is
			<lb />
			synonymous with trade. The use of the conjunction &quot;or&quot; should
			<lb />
			be understood as disjunctive for covering totally different areas
			<lb />
			unconnected with &quot;trade&apos;. A reference to the Dictionary would
			<lb />
			reveal that the word &quot;business&quot; has different shades of
			<lb />
			meanings. Among them the most suitable in the present context
			<lb />
			is that which &quot;The Oxford Advanced Learners Dictionary of
			<lb />
			Current English&quot; has given as its third meaning: &quot;Task, duty,
			<lb />
			concern or undertaking to do a work&quot;. Some succinct
			<lb />
			illustrations have also been given in the said dictionary to drive
			<lb />
			the meaning home. They are: &quot;It is a teacher&apos;s business to help
			<lb />
			his pupils; I still make it my business to see that money is paid
			<lb />
			promptly; that is no business of yours&quot;. In none of the
			<lb />
			illustrations the word &quot;business&quot; is used to denote anything
			<lb />
			connected with trade or commerce. We think that, the word
			<lb />
			business used in Section 12 of the Act has been intended to
			<lb />
			convey the meaning as the work or task undertaken by the
			<lb />
			person concerned which are not restricted to trade or
			<lb />
			commercial work alone. Hence the interpretation given to the
			<lb />
			words &quot;trade or business&quot; appearing in Article 19 of the
			<lb />
			Constitution, or in the Rent Control Law is not apposite in the
			<lb />
			context of Section 12 of the Act. We may observe with great
			<lb />
			respect that the Division Bench of this Court in Travancore
			<lb />
			Devaswom Board v. Prushothaman (1989 2 LLJ 114), has not
			<lb />
			adopted any principle in conflict with the above view.
			<lb />
			14.
			<lb />
			In Bata Shoe Company v. Union of India AIR 1954
			<lb />
			Bombay 129 Gajendragadhkar, J. (as he then was) observed
			<lb />
			that the word &quot;business&quot; in its wider connotation may have
			<lb />
			more extensive meaning than the word &quot;trade&quot;. His Lordship
			<lb />
			then quoted Jessel M.R. in Smith v. Anaerson 1880 15 Ch D 247
			<lb />
			who stressed the meaning of business as &quot;anything which
			<lb />
			occupies the time and attention and labour of a man for the
			<lb />
			purpose of profit&quot;. This wide meaning was followed in Public
			<lb />
			Works Dept. v. Commissioner 1981 Lab I.C. 498 by a Division
			<lb />
			Bench consisting of Dr. A.S. Anand, J. (as His Lordship then
			<lb />
			was) and I.K. Kotwal, J. in Workmen&apos;s Compensation cases. We
			<lb />
			are, therefore, emboldened by the above decisions in adopting
			<lb />
			the wide connotation for the word &quot;business&quot; in the present
			<lb />
			case.
			<lb />
			15.
			<lb />
			Our next endeavour is to ascertain what the legislature
			<lb />
			meant by the word &quot;ordinarily&quot; in Section 12 of the Act. The
			<lb />
			word &quot;ordinarily&quot; is an elastic term. It is seen used in different
			<lb />
			statutes. The word has different shades of meaning in different
			<lb />
			contexts (vide Kailash Chandra v. Union of India (1961-II-LLJ-
			<lb />
			369) (SC). If it is used for referring to jurisdictional aspects it
			<lb />
			may mean &quot;in large majority of cases but not invariably&quot;. When
			<lb />
			the word is used for referring to residential qualification it may
			<lb />
			sometimes include even temporary residence. But the word
			<lb />
			&quot;ordinarily&quot; is employed in Section 12 of the Act for a different
			<lb />
			connotation. That has to be understood in the background of the
			<lb />
			preceding portion in the section wherein execution of the work
			<lb />
			carried out through any other person contracted by the
			<lb />
			principal for this purpose is mentioned. What the principal
			<lb />
			would have done if he has not contracted with another person to
			<lb />
			carry out that work? He himself would have normally done that
			<lb />
			work or caused it to be done under his supervision. The word
			<lb />
			&quot;Ordinarily&quot; is used in Section 12 of the Act for projecting that
			<lb />
			idea. So the word &quot;ordinarily&quot; in Section 12 of the Act means
			<lb />
			&quot;otherwise, normally&quot;. We cannot confer any other meaning to
			<lb />
			the term &quot;ordinarily&quot; as it appears in the section. We did not
			<lb />
			find anything contrary to the above legal position in the
			<lb />
			decision of the Division Bench of this Court in Vijayaraghavan
			<lb />
			v. Velu (1973 I LLJ 490).
			<lb />
			16. Learned counsel for the appellant lastly contended that as
			<lb />
			the soil was sold to the second respondent, appellant had lost
			<lb />
			any ownership thereof and hence he cannot be made liable.
			<lb />
			What was sold by the appellant was only the soil and not the
			<lb />
			land. As long as the soil was not separated and transported, it
			<lb />
			remained as part of the land. The work involved in transforming
			<lb />
			land into soil must necessarily have been done when the
			<lb />
			ownership and title of the land remained with the appellant. So
			<lb />
			the appellant cannot disclaim liability in that line either.
			<lb />
			17. When the legal position is understood thus, we are of the
			<lb />
			view that appellant is the employer vis-a-vis the victims, as
			<lb />
			per Section 12 of the Act. Appellant is therefore liable to pay the
			<lb />
			compensation due under the Act to the claimants. Accordingly,
			<lb />
			we dismiss the appeals.‖
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			28.2. In Public Works Department v. Commissioner, Workmen
			<lb />
			Compensation (supra), the Division Bench of Jammu and Kashmir
			<lb />
			High Court held that the word &quot;business&quot; occurring in Section 12 has
			<lb />
			to be given an extended meaning, so as to include even an activity
			<lb />
			which engages time, attention or labour as a principal serious concern
			<lb />
			or interest of the Government or an individual without an element of
			<lb />
			profit in it. The relevant portion of the judgment is reproduced
			<lb />
			hereunder:
			<lb />
			-4. Unlike the word &quot;trade&quot; which merely; connotes
			<lb />
			commercial activity, the word &quot;business&quot; is of much wider
			<lb />
			import and may be used in different contexts in different senses.
			<lb />
			Used in one context, it may imply a particular occupation or
			<lb />
			employment to earn livelihood or gain, whereas used in a
			<lb />
			different context it may mean an activity which engages time,
			<lb />
			attention, or labour as a principal serious concern or interest.
			<lb />
			Its connotation may thus vary with the varying contexts in which
			<lb />
			it is used. In taxing statutes for instance, the word &quot;business&quot;
			<lb />
			will always denote an activity carried out with the object of
			<lb />
			earning profit, though the same may not be true when used in
			<lb />
			relation to other activities. Used in broader sense, a person
			<lb />
			building his residential house or a Government constructing a
			<lb />
			road, may well be said to do business in so far as the said
			<lb />
			activity engages his or its time, attention or labour as principal
			<lb />
			serious concern or interest. In saying so, I derive support from
			<lb />
			the following observations made by their Lordships of the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court in M/s. Hindustan Steel Ltd. v. State of Orissa,
			<lb />
			AIR 1970 S C 253:
			<lb />
			&quot;The expression &quot;business&quot; though extensively
			<lb />
			used is a word of indefinite import, in taxing
			<lb />
			statutes it is used in the sense of an occupation, or
			<lb />
			profession which occupies the time, attention and
			<lb />
			labour of a person, normally with the object of
			<lb />
			making profit. To regard an activity as business
			<lb />
			there must be a course of dealings, either actually
			<lb />
			continued or contemplated to be continued with a
			<lb />
			profit motive, and not for sport or pleasure.&quot;
			<lb />
			Its amplitude has been more exhaustively dealt with by
			<lb />
			Gajendragadkar J. in Bata Shoe Co. Ltd. v. Union of India, AIR
			<lb />
			1954 Bom 129 wherein it has been observed :
			<lb />
			&quot;In its wider denotation, the word &quot;business&quot;
			<lb />
			may have a more extensive meaning than the word
			<lb />
			&quot;trade&quot;. But in the context, we think it would be
			<lb />
			safe to adopt the definition of the word &quot;business&quot;
			<lb />
			laid down by Jessel M. R. in &apos;Smith v. Anderson&apos;,
			<lb />
			(1880) 15 Ch D 247 at p. 258 (B), where the
			<lb />
			learned Judge has observed that &apos;anything which
			<lb />
			occupies the time and attention and labour of a
			<lb />
			man, for the purpose of profit, is business&quot;. It is
			<lb />
			true that the word &quot;business&quot; in its most general
			<lb />
			and unrestricted sense may conceivably cover all
			<lb />
			human activities. It may even include the business
			<lb />
			of governing a country. But we are disposed to
			<lb />
			hold that the context in which the word has been
			<lb />
			used in S. 18 (b), Presidency Small Cause Courts
			<lb />
			Act, S. 20, Civil P. C. and CL 12 of the Letters
			<lb />
			Patent, requires that this word should not be
			<lb />
			construed in such a wide and unrestricted sense.&quot;
			<lb />
			5. The next question which then falls for determination is; what
			<lb />
			meaning should be assigned to the word &quot;business&quot; occurring in
			<lb />
			Section 12?
			<lb />
			6. It is well settled that where a word used in a statute is
			<lb />
			capable of two meanings, only that meaning should be assigned
			<lb />
			to it which carries out its object. This rule &apos;of interpretation of
			<lb />
			statutes has been often times affirmed by their Lordships of the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court. In M/s. New India Sugar Mills Ltd. v. Commr.
			<lb />
			of Sales Tax, Bihar, AIR 1963 S C 1207 it was held:
			<lb />
			&quot;....It is a recognised rule of interpretation of
			<lb />
			statutes that the expressions used therein should
			<lb />
			ordinarily be understood in a sense in which they
			<lb />
			best harmonise with the object of the statute, and
			<lb />
			which effectuate the object of the Legislature. If an
			<lb />
			expression is susceptible of a narrow or technical
			<lb />
			meaning, as well as a popular meaning the Court
			<lb />
			would be justified in assuming that the Legislature
			<lb />
			used the expression in the sense which would carry
			<lb />
			out its object and reject that which renders the
			<lb />
			exercise of its powers invalid.&quot;
			<lb />
			Again, in South Asia Industries Pvt. Ltd. v. S. Sarup Singh AIR
			<lb />
			1966 SC 346, it was observed:
			<lb />
			&quot;.... A court would be fully justified in holding
			<lb />
			that in such a case it was intended that an order
			<lb />
			for recovery of possession can be made against the
			<lb />
			assignee alone for that would enable the object of
			<lb />
			the statute which was to enable the landlord to
			<lb />
			recover possession, to be achieved. An
			<lb />
			interpretation which defeats the objects of a statute
			<lb />
			is, therefore, of course, not permissible.&quot;
			<lb />
			7. The only object behind the provisions of Section appears to
			<lb />
			be to secure speedy payment of compensation resulting from
			<lb />
			injuries to a workman. The legislature intended to make doubly
			<lb />
			sure payment of such compensation to the workman, or to his
			<lb />
			dependants in the event of his death, as it could not exclude the
			<lb />
			possibility of the contractor being in some cases a man of straw,
			<lb />
			whose straitened circumstances might jeopardise the changes of
			<lb />
			recovery of such compensation. If, therefore, a restricted
			<lb />
			meaning is given to the word &quot;business&quot; so as to imply an
			<lb />
			activity with the object of earning profit only, the object behind
			<lb />
			Section 12 is likely to be defeated. Not only to speak of the
			<lb />
			Government performing its various functions of a welfare State,
			<lb />
			even many other persons may have to be kept out of the purview
			<lb />
			of Section 12 by assigning such a limited meaning to the word
			<lb />
			&quot;business&quot; occurring in it. Such an interpretation would absolve
			<lb />
			from liability to pay compensation even a person who would
			<lb />
			appoint a contractor for building his residential house, as
			<lb />
			building one&apos;s residential house cannot be said to have the
			<lb />
			object of earning profit or gain behind it. It cannot, as such, be
			<lb />
			said to partake of &quot;business or trade&quot; in commercial sense.
			<lb />
			Merely because the word &quot;business&quot; is clubbed with the word
			<lb />
			&quot;trade&quot; in Section 12, it should not be inferred that it has been
			<lb />
			used in simple commercial sense. Both these words have to be
			<lb />
			read disjunctively and rot conjunctively. Similarly, the doctrine
			<lb />
			of immunity attached to sovereign acts of State cannot be
			<lb />
			extended to acts like constructing roads or bridges, as such acts
			<lb />
			are not of such a nature as cannot be done by a private person.
			<lb />
			Viewed thus, the word &quot;business&quot; occurring in Section 12 has to
			<lb />
			be given an extended meaning, so as to include even an activity
			<lb />
			which engages time, attention, or labour as a principal serious
			<lb />
			concern or interest of the Government or an individual without
			<lb />
			an element of profit in it. It is one of the meanings given to the
			<lb />
			word &quot;business&quot; in dictionary. (See Webster&apos;s New International
			<lb />
			Dictionary, Vol. I, Ed. 1926). Construction of roads being one
			<lb />
			of the principal concerns of the Public Works Department of the
			<lb />
			Government inviting its serious attention, it is &quot;business&quot; within
			<lb />
			the meaning of Section 12 and the appellant was thus the
			<lb />
			principal employer vis-a-vis the deceased labourers.‖
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			28.3. In Bala Mallamma v. Registrar, Osmania University (supra),
			<lb />
			a claim for compensation was made for the death of a workman who
			<lb />
			fell down from a height of 40 feet while whitewashing the walls of
			<lb />
			Osmania University Science College. The claim was contested by the
			<lb />
			University on the ground that the University was constituted for
			<lb />
			imparting education and the whitewashing of the walls of the
			<lb />
			University was not a part of the -trade‖ or -business‖ of the
			<lb />
			University. The Division Bench of Andhra Pradesh High Court,
			<lb />
			following Public Works Department v. Commissioner, Workmen
			<lb />
			Compensation (supra), held that whitewashing/colour washing was a
			<lb />
			regular feature of the activity of the University and it could be treated
			<lb />
			ordinarily as part of the -business‖ of the University because the
			<lb />
			words &apos;trade&apos; or &apos;business&apos;, as used in the Act, have to be understood in
			<lb />
			the context in which the Act was enacted, failing which the very
			<lb />
			raison d&apos;être of Section 12 of the Act would be defeated. The relevant
			<lb />
			portion of the judgment is reproduced hereunder:
			<lb />
			-14. The learned Counsel for the applicant has drawn our
			<lb />
			attention to the judgment of the Supreme Court reported in
			<lb />
			Mohan Lal v. R. Kondaiah, . Para No.3 of the said judgment is
			<lb />
			important for the purpose of the present case, which is
			<lb />
			reproduced below:
			<lb />
			&quot;The expression business has not been defined
			<lb />
			in the Andhra Pradesh Buildings (Lease, Rent and
			<lb />
			Eviction) Control Act, 1960. It is a common
			<lb />
			expression which is sometimes used by itself and
			<lb />
			sometimes in a collection of words as in &quot;business,
			<lb />
			trade or profession&quot;. It is a word of large and wide
			<lb />
			import, capable of a variety of meanings. It is
			<lb />
			needless to refer to the meanings given to that term
			<lb />
			in the various Dictionaries except to say that every
			<lb />
			one of them notices a large number of meanings of
			<lb />
			the word. In a broad sense it is taken to mean
			<lb />
			&apos;everything that occupies the time, attention and
			<lb />
			labour of men for the purpose of livelihood or
			<lb />
			profit&apos;. In a narrow sense it is confined to
			<lb />
			commercial activity. It is obvious that the meaning
			<lb />
			of the word must be gleaned from the context in
			<lb />
			which it is used. Reference to the provisions of the
			<lb />
			Constitution or other statutes where the expression
			<lb />
			is used cannot be of any assistance in determining
			<lb />
			its meaning in Section 10(3) (a) (iii) of the Andhra
			<lb />
			Pradesh Buildings (Lease, Rent and Eviction)
			<lb />
			Control Act, 1960. It is not a sound principle of
			<lb />
			construction to interpret expressions used in one
			<lb />
			Act with reference to their use in another Act;
			<lb />
			more so if the two Acts in which the same word is
			<lb />
			used are not cognate Acts. Neither the meaning,
			<lb />
			nor the definition of the term in one statute affords
			<lb />
			a guide to the construction of the same term in
			<lb />
			another statute and the sense in which the term has
			<lb />
			been understood in the several statutes does not
			<lb />
			necessarily throw any light on the manner in which
			<lb />
			the term should be understood generally. On the
			<lb />
			other hand, it is a sound, and, indeed, a well-
			<lb />
			known principle of construction that meaning of
			<lb />
			words and expressions used in an Act must take
			<lb />
			their colour from the context in which they
			<lb />
			appear&quot;.
			<lb />
			15. This judgment reiterates a principle of interpretation and
			<lb />
			the principle is that the meaning of the word must be gleaned
			<lb />
			from the context in which it is used. Meaning assigned to a word
			<lb />
			in a particular Act may mean one thing and the meaning of the
			<lb />
			same term may give a different meaning when used in a
			<lb />
			different Act. Therefore, the word &apos;trade&apos; or &apos;business&apos; as used in
			<lb />
			this Act have to be understood in the context in which this Act
			<lb />
			has been enacted. Basically the Act has been enacted to provide
			<lb />
			compensation to the workers suffering during the course of
			<lb />
			employment. It is also the purpose of the Act that they should
			<lb />
			get speedy remedies and it appears that the intention of enacting
			<lb />
			the Section 12 of the Act was only to ensure that compensation
			<lb />
			is paid by the principal expeditiously and if this purpose of the
			<lb />
			Act and the provision are kept in mind, then the word &apos;trade&apos; or
			<lb />
			&apos;business&apos; may not have the same meaning which it would have,
			<lb />
			for instance, when used in interpreting a taxing statute. If the
			<lb />
			plea of the University is accepted that they are engaged in
			<lb />
			imparting education, conducting examinations and conferring
			<lb />
			degrees only and cannot be termed to be doing any business or
			<lb />
			trade and hence they are not liable to pay compensation, then
			<lb />
			any person engaged for similar activity by any Government
			<lb />
			Department, any University, any hospital, if faced with an
			<lb />
			accident, would not be able to get compensation in terms
			<lb />
			of Section 12 of the Act although such a person would be a
			<lb />
			workman under the Act. Similarly if an individual who wants to
			<lb />
			construct a residential house of his own engages a person for
			<lb />
			construction of the house and if such a person faces an accident
			<lb />
			during the course of the building of the house, he would be
			<lb />
			remediless under the Act. Even otherwise the normal activity of
			<lb />
			the University is imparting education, conducting of
			<lb />
			examinations and conferring degrees, this they cannot do
			<lb />
			without having proper buildings.‖
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			28.4. In Govind Goenka v. Dayawati (supra), the appellant engaged
			<lb />
			a contractor for repairs and alterations in his shop. A portion of the
			<lb />
			wall fell on a labourer who suffered fatal injuries whereupon a claim
			<lb />
			for compensation was made against the owner who contested it on the
			<lb />
			ground that the deceased labourer was employed by the contractor.
			<lb />
			This Court, following the judgement of Division Bench of Andhra
			<lb />
			Pradesh High Court in Balla Mallamma v. Registrar, Osmania
			<lb />
			University (supra), held that the word -business‖ in Section 12 has to
			<lb />
			be given an extended meaning. The relevant portion of the judgment is
			<lb />
			reproduced hereunder:
			<lb />
			-6. As would be seen from the definition of &quot;employer&quot;
			<lb />
			envisaged under Section 2(e) of the Act, the same is of wide
			<lb />
			amplitude and would certainly encompass the present
			<lb />
			appellant who at the relevant time had employed the services
			<lb />
			of the contractor to carry out the job of repairs and alterations
			<lb />
			in his shop. The contractor who had taken the services of the
			<lb />
			deceased workman as a labourer no doubt will also be
			<lb />
			covered within the definition of employer but qua the appellant
			<lb />
			he would remain his agent and the appellant would be the
			<lb />
			principal employer. There is thus no difficulty to arrive at a
			<lb />
			conclusion that the appellant for all intents and purposes was
			<lb />
			the principal employer who had engaged the services of an
			<lb />
			Agent contractor to carry out the said job of the repair work.
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			9. So far as the interpretation of section 12 of the Act is
			<lb />
			concerned, again reference has been made to the principal
			<lb />
			making a contract for the purposes of trade or business, the
			<lb />
			judgment of the Division Bench of Andhra Pradesh High
			<lb />
			Court in the case of Balla Mallamma v. Registrar, Osmania
			<lb />
			University, Hyderabad and Anr, 2001(2)T.A.C.182(AP) is a
			<lb />
			complete answer………
			<lb />
			10. As would be seen from the above judgment of the Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Division Bench where the Osmania University, Hyderabad
			<lb />
			had engaged services of a contractor for white washing and
			<lb />
			painting the walls of the University and a worker employed by
			<lb />
			the contractor while white washing the walls had fallen and
			<lb />
			died and the objection raised was that whitewashing the walls
			<lb />
			of the University would not be an activity which could be
			<lb />
			construed as an activity for the purposes of trade and business
			<lb />
			of the University. Giving an extended meaning to the word
			<lb />
			&quot;business&quot; employed in the said section 12, the Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Division Bench took a view that the restricted meaning given
			<lb />
			to the said expression would defeat the very raison d&apos;être
			<lb />
			of section 12 of the Act.
			<lb />
			12. The said interpretation given by the Division Bench also
			<lb />
			finds support from the amendment brought by the Parliament
			<lb />
			in the definition of Section 2(1)(n) of the Act omitting the
			<lb />
			words &quot;Casual workman&quot; and a workman who is employed
			<lb />
			other than for the purposes of employer&apos;s trade or business.
			<lb />
			Reverting back to the facts of the present case, here also the
			<lb />
			deceased workman was employed by the contractor and
			<lb />
			although for carrying out repair job it might not be the
			<lb />
			principal activity of the appellant but yet the appellant cannot
			<lb />
			escape its liability keeping in view the object of the said
			<lb />
			beneficial piece of legislation.
			<lb />
			13. For the expeditious grant of compensation in the event of
			<lb />
			such accidents taking place in favour of the victim&apos;s dependent
			<lb />
			members, this act was enacted and a hyper technical
			<lb />
			interpretation of the statute would not only defeat the purpose
			<lb />
			of the said Act but would be adding insult to injury………‖
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			28.5. In Raj Pal Saini v. Kamla, (2016) 151 FLR 302, a mistry
			<lb />
			suffered an electric shock during the construction of second floor of a
			<lb />
			building. The owner of the building contested the claim on the ground
			<lb />
			that he had engaged the contractor who in turn had engaged the
			<lb />
			employee. Following Govind Goenka v. Dayawati (supra), this Court
			<lb />
			held the owner liable to pay compensation under Section 12 of the
			<lb />
			Act. The relevant portion of the judgment is reproduced hereunder:
			<lb />
			-6. On careful consideration of the rival contentions of the
			<lb />
			parties, this Court is of the view that the appellant, being the
			<lb />
			principal employer, is liable to pay the compensation to the
			<lb />
			respondent who was admittedly engaged in the construction
			<lb />
			work at the petitioner&apos;s house and was electrocuted on 16 th
			<lb />
			December, 2009. This case squarely covered by Govind
			<lb />
			Goenka v. Dayawati (supra) in which this Court held that the
			<lb />
			principal employer cannot escape its liability on the ground
			<lb />
			that the deceased employee was employed by the
			<lb />
			contractor.‖
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			28.6. Applying the rules of liberal and purposive interpretation,
			<lb />
			superior purpose and felt necessity, the word &quot;business&quot; occurring in
			<lb />
			Section 12 is given an extended meaning, so as to include even an
			<lb />
			activity which engages time, attention, or labour. Hence, construction
			<lb />
			of a residential house would be covered in Section 12. If the person
			<lb />
			who employs contractor is allowed to evade his liability by raising the
			<lb />
			defence that only the contractor or the intermediary should pay the
			<lb />
			compensation, then Section 12 will become redundant. This Court
			<lb />
			agrees with the view taken by the different High Courts in the
			<lb />
			judgments discussed herein above.
			<lb />
			29. Section 12 would apply notwithstanding the agreement or
			<lb />
			contract entered into between the principal and contractor regarding
			<lb />
			their liability for payment of compensation under the Act
			<lb />
			In Koodalingam v. Superintending Engineer, Project Circle, Public
			<lb />
			Works Department, Kozhikode (supra), the Division Bench of Kerala
			<lb />
			High Court held that Section 12 would apply notwithstanding the
			<lb />
			agreement or contract entered into between the principal and
			<lb />
			contractor regarding their liability for payment of compensation under
			<lb />
			the Act. The agreement of contract between the principal and the
			<lb />
			contractor governs only their inter-se rights and liabilities, and cannot
			<lb />
			affect the right of the workmen or their dependants to get the
			<lb />
			compensation form the principal or from the contractor at their option.
			<lb />
			Relevant portion of the judgment is as under:
			<lb />
			-11..........The avowed object with which Section 12 was
			<lb />
			enacted as part of the Act as seen from the Report of the Select
			<lb />
			Committee is to enable the workmen or the dependents of the
			<lb />
			workmen to proceed against the contractor or against the
			<lb />
			principal or both and to make the contractor liable to
			<lb />
			indemnify the principal in all cases in the absence of any
			<lb />
			agreement to the contrary. The Report of the Select Committee
			<lb />
			would also show that while finalising the provision the
			<lb />
			Committee has eliminated the provision which in the Bill as
			<lb />
			introduced exempted the Government and local authorities
			<lb />
			from liability imposed by this clause. The Committee has
			<lb />
			observed that these authorities are liable just in the same
			<lb />
			manner as private individuals. If these were the avowed
			<lb />
			objects with which Section 12 of the Act was incorporated in
			<lb />
			an enactment which itself is a beneficial legislation intended to
			<lb />
			confer benefits on the workmen, we are of the view that the
			<lb />
			provisions in Section 12(1) would apply notwithstanding the
			<lb />
			agreement or contract entered into between the principal and
			<lb />
			contractor regarding their liability for payment of
			<lb />
			compensation under the Act. So long as the Section has not
			<lb />
			been made specifically subject to any contract to the contrary,
			<lb />
			the Section would have application in all cases where the
			<lb />
			conditions specified in the Section are satisfied. The fact that
			<lb />
			no non obstante provision is used in the Section may not be a
			<lb />
			sufficient reason to exclude the application of the Section to
			<lb />
			cases where the conditions are satisfied. At best, agreements
			<lb />
			or contracts entered into between the principal and contractor
			<lb />
			can govern only their inter se rights and liabilities and cannot
			<lb />
			affect the right of the workmen or their dependents to get
			<lb />
			compensation either from the principal or from the contractor
			<lb />
			at their option. Right to get indemnified from the contractor
			<lb />
			specifically conferred on the principal under Section 12(2) of
			<lb />
			the Act sufficiently safeguards the interest of the principal who
			<lb />
			has entrusted the work to the contractor stipulating the
			<lb />
			liability under the Act.‖
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			30. Section 12 imposes the liability on the principal where several
			<lb />
			tiers of contractors or petty contractors are employed
			<lb />
			In Sardar Sewa Singh v. Hindustan Lever Ltd. (supra), the Allahabad
			<lb />
			High Court held Section 12 of the Workmen&quot;s Compensation Act to
			<lb />
			be an enabling provision for the benefit of the workmen enacted with a
			<lb />
			clear objective that the workmen should not be hampered by
			<lb />
			technicalities or practical difficulties of deciphering the correct
			<lb />
			employers. A pragmatic method has been advised for fixing the
			<lb />
			liability on the principal employer for affording speedy relief to the
			<lb />
			workmen for payment of compensation on account of the accident.
			<lb />
			Section 12 imposes the liability on the principal where several tiers of
			<lb />
			contractors or petty contractors are employed. The relevant discussion
			<lb />
			of Section 12 is as under:
			<lb />
			-3………Chapter II of the Act captioned -workmen&apos;s
			<lb />
			compensation‖ deals with the question of compensation
			<lb />
			claimed by a workman. Ordinarily such claims are disposed of
			<lb />
			under the provisions of Ss. 3 to 5. The scheme of the Act is that
			<lb />
			the -employer‖ as defined in S. 2(c) should be liable in the
			<lb />
			manner mentioned in S. 3. In view, however, of the vastly
			<lb />
			increasing ramifications of industrial establishments and the
			<lb />
			multiplicity of immediate and indirect or remote employers
			<lb />
			which such process inevitably involves the Legislature has
			<lb />
			inserted a provision in the Act which may relieve a workman of
			<lb />
			the difficulty of ascertaining with precision as to who should
			<lb />
			be deemed to be the actual employer liable for compensation
			<lb />
			under the Act. Section 12, therefore, provides for a case where
			<lb />
			we have several tiers of employers or petty employers. It is a
			<lb />
			matter of common knowledge that in big industrial
			<lb />
			establishments important branches of undertakings are
			<lb />
			entrusted to contractors, who may in their turn have to employ
			<lb />
			other petty contractor working under their direction and a
			<lb />
			workman may be actually employed by one of these aforesaid
			<lb />
			persons and in such an elaborate hereby there may be no
			<lb />
			direct privity of contract between the principal and the
			<lb />
			workman in the last analysis. The workman has for all
			<lb />
			practical purposes to deal with an immediate employer but
			<lb />
			when it comes to lodging a legal claim for compensation on
			<lb />
			account of an accident he is concerned with the principal
			<lb />
			employer and not the immediate employer qua the workman.
			<lb />
			This is an enabling provision for the benefit of the workman
			<lb />
			and enacted with the clear objective that the workman should
			<lb />
			not be hampered by technicalities or practical difficulties of
			<lb />
			deciphering the correct employers. A pragmatic method has
			<lb />
			thus been devised for fixing the liability of the principal
			<lb />
			employer and thereby affording speedy relief to the workman
			<lb />
			for payment of compensation on account of the accident,
			<lb />
			though the principal has been invested with the right of
			<lb />
			indemnifying himself from the contractor who may have
			<lb />
			employed the workman and may have been responsible for
			<lb />
			immediately taking work from him.‖
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			31. Effect of amendment of Workmen&apos;s Compensation Act by
			<lb />
			Workmen&apos;s Compensation (Amendment) Act, 2000
			<lb />
			31.1. Definition of -Workman/Employee‖ -The definition of
			<lb />
			‗workman&apos;, as it originally existed in the Workmen&quot;s Compensation
			<lb />
			Act, 1923, excluded the workmen whose employment was of a casual
			<lb />
			nature and who were employed otherwise than for the purpose of
			<lb />
			employer&quot;s -trade‖ or -business‖. Section 2(1) (n) of the Workmen&quot;s
			<lb />
			Compensation Act, 1923 was amended by Workmen&quot;s Compensation
			<lb />
			(Amendment) Act, 2000 with effect from 8 th December, 2000 whereby
			<lb />
			the words &quot;other than a person whose employment is of a casual
			<lb />
			nature and who is employed otherwise than for the purposes of the
			<lb />
			employer&apos;s trade or business&quot; in the definition of ‗workman&apos; in
			<lb />
			Section 2(1) (n) were omitted.
			<lb />
			31.2. Section 2(1) (n) of the Workmen&quot;s Compensation Act, prior to
			<lb />
			the Workmen&quot;s Compensation (Amendment) Act, 2000 read as under:
			<lb />
			-Section 2(1) (n) -
			<lb />
			-workman‖ means any person (other than a person
			<lb />
			whose employment is of a casual nature and who is employed
			<lb />
			otherwise than for the purposes of the employer&apos;s trade or
			<lb />
			business) who is -
			<lb />
			(i) .........
			<lb />
			(ii) employed ****] 2 in any such capacity as is
			<lb />
			specified in Schedule II, whether the contract of
			<lb />
			employment was made before or after the passing
			<lb />
			of this Act and whether such contract is
			<lb />
			expressed or implied, oral or in writing; but does
			<lb />
			not include any person working in the capacity of
			<lb />
			a member of the Armed Forces of the Union; and
			<lb />
			any reference to a workman who has been
			<lb />
			injured shall, where the workman is dead,
			<lb />
			include a reference to his dependants or any of
			<lb />
			them.‖
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			31.3. Section 2(1)(n) of the Workmen&quot;s Compensation Act, after the
			<lb />
			Workmen&quot;s Compensation (Amendment) Act, 2000 reads as under:
			<lb />
			-Section 2(1) (n) -
			<lb />
			-workman‖ means any person who is -
			<lb />
			(i) .........
			<lb />
			(ia).........
			<lb />
			(ii) employed in any such capacity as is specified
			<lb />
			in Schedule II, whether the contract of
			<lb />
			employment was made before or after the passing
			<lb />
			of this Act and whether such contract is
			<lb />
			expressed or implied, oral or in writing; but does
			<lb />
			not include any person working in the capacity of
			<lb />
			a member of the Armed Forces of the Union;
			<lb />
			and any reference to a workman who has been
			<lb />
			injured shall, where the workman is dead,
			<lb />
			include a reference to his dependants or any of
			<lb />
			them.‖
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			31.4. Workmen&quot; Compensation Act was again amended in 2009 by
			<lb />
			Workmen&quot;s Compensation (Amendment) Act, 2009 with effect from
			<lb />
			18 th January, 2010 whereby the words -workman‖ and -workmen‖,
			<lb />
			were substituted with the words -employee‖ and -employees‖. The
			<lb />
			Workmen&quot;s Compensation (Amendment) Act, 2009 omitted Section
			<lb />
			2(1)(n) that defined -workman‖ and replaced it by Section 2(1)(dd)
			<lb />
			which defined -employee‖, though the substance of the definition
			<lb />
			remained the same. The aforesaid amendment also changed the name
			<lb />
			of the Workmen&quot;s Compensation Act to Employee&quot;s Compensation
			<lb />
			Act. Section 2(1)(dd) of the Employee&quot;s Compensation Act reads as
			<lb />
			under:
			<lb />
			-Section 2(1) (dd) -
			<lb />
			-employee‖ means a person, who is -
			<lb />
			(i)
			<lb />
			.........
			<lb />
			(ii) .........
			<lb />
			(iii) employed in any such capacity as is
			<lb />
			specified in Schedule II, whether the contract of
			<lb />
			employment was made before or after the passing
			<lb />
			of this Act and whether such contract is expressed
			<lb />
			or implied, oral or in writing; but does not include
			<lb />
			any person working in the capacity of a member of
			<lb />
			the Armed Forces of the Union; and any reference
			<lb />
			to any employee who has been injured shall, where
			<lb />
			the employee is dead, include a reference to his
			<lb />
			dependants or any of them;‖
			<lb />
			31.5. The definition of -employee‖ in Section 2(1)(dd) of the
			<lb />
			Employee&quot;s Compensation Act has to be read with Schedule II and the
			<lb />
			relevant Entry No.(viii) of Schedule II reads as under:
			<lb />
			-SCHEDULE II
			<lb />
			[Section 2(1) (dd)]
			<lb />
			LIST OF PERSONS WHO SUBJECT TO THE
			<lb />
			PROVISIONS OF SECTION 2(1) (dd), ARE INCLUDED
			<lb />
			IN THE DEFINITION OF EMPLOYEES
			<lb />
			The following persons are employees within the
			<lb />
			meaning of Section 2(1) (dd) and subject to the
			<lb />
			provisions of that section that is to say any person
			<lb />
			who is -
			<lb />
			-(viii) employed in the construction, maintenance,
			<lb />
			repair or demolition of -
			<lb />
			(a) any building which is designed to be or is or
			<lb />
			has been more than one storey in height above the
			<lb />
			ground or twelve feet or more from the ground
			<lb />
			level to the apex of the roof; or......‖
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			31.6. In Govind Goenka v. Dayawati (supra), this Court examined
			<lb />
			the effect of Workmen&quot;s Compensation (Amendment) Act, 2000 and
			<lb />
			held that, after the amendment, the workman whose employment is of
			<lb />
			casual nature and who is employed otherwise than for the purpose of
			<lb />
			employer&apos;s trade or business, would also be covered within the
			<lb />
			definition of &quot;workman‖. Relevant portion of the said judgment is
			<lb />
			reproduced hereunder:
			<lb />
			-8. So far as the definition of workman envisaged in Section
			<lb />
			2(n) of the said Act is concerned, there has been a drastic
			<lb />
			change in the definition of the &quot;workman&quot; as it stood prior to
			<lb />
			the amendment and after the amendment. Prior to the
			<lb />
			amendment, certainly the workman whose employment was
			<lb />
			of a casual nature and who was employed otherwise than for
			<lb />
			the purpose of trade or business of the employer would not
			<lb />
			fall in the said definition. However, after the amendment of
			<lb />
			the said definition through the Amending Act 46 of 2000, the
			<lb />
			Parliament had removed the said mischief which was then
			<lb />
			prevailing and coming in the way of such casual workmen
			<lb />
			who met with an accident during the course of the
			<lb />
			employment unconnected with the employer&apos;s trade or
			<lb />
			business. With the amendment of the said definition, now
			<lb />
			certainly the workman whose employment is of casual nature
			<lb />
			and who is employed otherwise than for the purpose of
			<lb />
			employer&apos;s trade or business would also be covered within
			<lb />
			the definition of workman.‖
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			32. Rules of Interpretation of Social welfare legislations
			<lb />
			32.1. The principles of statutory construction are well settled that
			<lb />
			the words occurring in statutes of liberal import such as social welfare
			<lb />
			legislation and &apos;Human Rights&apos; legislation are not to be put in
			<lb />
			procrustean beds or shrunk to Lilliputian dimensions. In construing
			<lb />
			these legislations, the imposture of literal construction must be
			<lb />
			avoided and the prodigality of its misapplication must be recognized
			<lb />
			and reduced. Where legislation is designed to give relief against
			<lb />
			certain kinds of mischief, the Court is not to make inroads by making
			<lb />
			etymological excursions but to advance the intent.
			<lb />
			32.2. It is a recognized rule of interpretation of statutes that the
			<lb />
			expressions used therein should ordinarily be understood in a sense in
			<lb />
			which they best harmonize with the object of the statute, and which
			<lb />
			effectuate the object of the Legislature. If an expression is susceptible
			<lb />
			of a narrow or technical meaning as well as a popular meaning, the
			<lb />
			Court would be justified in assuming that the Legislature used the
			<lb />
			expression in the sense which would carry out its object and reject that
			<lb />
			which renders the exercise of its powers invalid.
			<lb />
			32.3. It is trite law that the safe guidance for interpreting any
			<lb />
			provision in a statute or for understanding the scope and meaning of a
			<lb />
			particular word in provision, is to ascertain the intention of the
			<lb />
			legislature. However wide in the abstract, general words and phrases
			<lb />
			are more or less elastic and admit of restriction or extension to suit the
			<lb />
			legislative intention. The object of the legislation would afford answer
			<lb />
			to the problems arising from ambiguities which it contains.
			<lb />
			32.4. Purpose of Employee&apos;s Compensation Act, 1923
			<lb />
			In N.P. Lalan v. V.A. John, (1972) II LLJ 273 Ker, V.R. Krishna Iyer,
			<lb />
			J. as he then was, explained the purpose of Employee&apos;s Compensation
			<lb />
			Act in the following words:-
			<lb />
			-4.The Act with which I am concerned relates to workers, and
			<lb />
			the entire purpose of the statute is to see that the weaker section
			<lb />
			of the community, namely, the working class, is not caught in
			<lb />
			the meshes of litigation which involves a protracted course of
			<lb />
			appeal. That is why the statute creates a special Tribunal and
			<lb />
			provides only for a restricted appeal ………
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			Part IV of the Indian Constitution serves as a perspective while
			<lb />
			construing the Workmen&apos;s Compensation Act. May be that pre-
			<lb />
			Constitution statutes were interpreted in a particular way by
			<lb />
			Courts on certain assumptions of the State&apos;s functions at that
			<lb />
			time. Today it is absolutely plain that the Directive Principles of
			<lb />
			State Policy, though not enforceable by a Court, are
			<lb />
			nevertheless fundamental in the governance of the country, and
			<lb />
			must inform the judicial mind when interpreting statutes
			<lb />
			calculated to promote the welfare of the working class. In fact,
			<lb />
			Article 42 enjoins upon the State to make provision for securing
			<lb />
			just and humane conditions of work and Article 43 compels the
			<lb />
			State to endeavour to secure, by suitable legislation, to all
			<lb />
			workers conditions of work ensuring a decent standard of life.
			<lb />
			Indeed, the spirit of Part IV of the Constitution must colour the
			<lb />
			semantic exercises of the judiciary when applying the provisions
			<lb />
			of the Workmen&apos;s Compensation Act. If that be the approach to
			<lb />
			be made, I am clear in my mind that the argument that the
			<lb />
			proviso to Section 30 has been interpreted liberally in the pre-
			<lb />
			Constitution days is of no significance. The same words, with
			<lb />
			socio-economic developments in society, acquire a new
			<lb />
			emphasis in tune with the changed conditions. It is clear
			<lb />
			therefore, that the dynamics of legal interpretation based on
			<lb />
			social changes which have taken place in the nation&apos;s life and
			<lb />
			goals demand ………‖
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			32.5. Rules of -Purposive Interpretation‖, -Superior Purpose‖
			<lb />
			and -Felt Necessity‖
			<lb />
			In Lanco Anpara Power Ltd v. State Of Uttar Pradesh, (2016) 10
			<lb />
			SCC 329, the appellants challenged the applicability of Building and
			<lb />
			Other Construction Workers&apos; (Regulation of Employment and
			<lb />
			Conditions of Service) Act, 1996 (hereinafter referred to as &quot;the
			<lb />
			BOCW Act&quot;) and the Buildings and Other Construction Workers&apos;
			<lb />
			Welfare Cess Act, 1996 (hereinafter referred to as &quot;the Welfare Cess
			<lb />
			Act&quot;) on the ground that they were registered under the Factories Act,
			<lb />
			1948 and therefore, they were not covered by the definition of
			<lb />
			-building or other construction work‖ as contained in Section 2(1)(d)
			<lb />
			of the BOCW Act and, therefore, the said Act was not applicable to
			<lb />
			them by virtue of Section 1(4) of BOCW Act. The Supreme Court
			<lb />
			held that the &quot;superior purpose&quot; of BOCW Act and the Welfare Cess
			<lb />
			Act has to be kept in mind as both these enactments namely BOCW
			<lb />
			Act and Welfare Cess Act are social welfare legislations. It was
			<lb />
			further observed that the concept of &quot;felt necessity&quot; and &quot;purposive
			<lb />
			interpretation&quot; would apply since the purpose of BOCW Act is to take
			<lb />
			care of a particular necessity i.e. welfare of unorganized labour class
			<lb />
			involved in construction activity as stated in the Statement of Objects
			<lb />
			and Reasons of the BOCW Act. The relevant portion of this
			<lb />
			judgement is reproduced herein under:-
			<lb />
			-25. We have bestowed our due and serious consideration to
			<lb />
			the submissions made of both sides, which these submissions
			<lb />
			deserve. The central issue is the meaning that is to be assigned
			<lb />
			to the language of Section 2(1)(d) of the Act, particularly that
			<lb />
			part which is exclusionary in nature i.e. which excludes such
			<lb />
			building and construction work to which the provisions of the
			<lb />
			Factories Act apply. Before coming to the grip of this central
			<lb />
			issue, we deem it appropriate to refer to the objectives with
			<lb />
			which the Factories Act and the BOCW Act were enacted, as
			<lb />
			that would be the guiding path to answer the core issue
			<lb />
			delineated above.
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			39. ……… As pointed out above, if the construction of this
			<lb />
			provision as suggested by the appellants is accepted, the
			<lb />
			construction workers who are engaged in the construction of
			<lb />
			buildings/projects will neither get the benefit of the Factories
			<lb />
			Act nor of the BOCW Act/Welfare Cess Act. That could not have
			<lb />
			been the intention of the legislature. The BOCW Act and the
			<lb />
			Welfare Cess Act are pieces of social security legislation to
			<lb />
			provide for certain benefits to the construction workers.
			<lb />
			40. Purposive interpretation in a social amelioration legislation
			<lb />
			is an imperative, irrespective of anything else. This is so
			<lb />
			eloquently brought out in the following passage in Atma Ram
			<lb />
			Mittal v. Ishwar Singh Punia [Atma Ram Mittal v. Ishwar Singh
			<lb />
			Punia, (1988) 4 SCC 284] : (SCC p. 289, para 9)
			<lb />
			-9. Judicial time and energy is more often
			<lb />
			than not consumed in finding what is the intention
			<lb />
			of Parliament or in other words, the will of the
			<lb />
			people. Blackstone tells us that the fairest and
			<lb />
			most rational method to interpret the will of the
			<lb />
			legislator is by exploring his intentions at the time
			<lb />
			when the law was made, by signs most natural and
			<lb />
			probable. And these signs are either the words, the
			<lb />
			context, the subject-matter, the effects and
			<lb />
			consequence, or the spirit and reason of the law.
			<lb />
			See Commentaries
			<lb />
			on
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Laws
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			England (facsimile of 1 st Edn. Of 1765, University
			<lb />
			of Chicago Press, 1979, Vol. 1, p. 59). Mukherjea,
			<lb />
			J. as the learned Chief Justice then was,
			<lb />
			in Poppatlal Shah v. State of Madras[Poppatlal
			<lb />
			Shah v. State of Madras, AIR 1953 SC 274 : 1953
			<lb />
			Cri LJ 1105 : 1953 SCR 677 : (1953) 4 STC 188]
			<lb />
			said that each word, phrase or sentence was to be
			<lb />
			construed in the light of purpose of the Act itself.
			<lb />
			But words must be construed with imagination of
			<lb />
			purpose behind them said Judge Learned Hand, a
			<lb />
			long time ago. It appears, therefore, that though
			<lb />
			we are concerned with seeking of intention, we are
			<lb />
			rather looking to the meaning of the words that the
			<lb />
			legislature has used and the true meaning of what
			<lb />
			words [Ed.: Lord Reid in the afore cited case had
			<lb />
			observed: (AC p. 613: All ER p. 814) -We often
			<lb />
			say that we are looking for the intention of
			<lb />
			Parliament, but this is not quite accurate. We are
			<lb />
			seeking the meaning of the words which
			<lb />
			Parliament used. We are seeking not what
			<lb />
			Parliament meant but the true meaning of what
			<lb />
			they said.‖] as was said by Lord Reid in Black-
			<lb />
			Clawson
			<lb />
			International
			<lb />
			Ltd. v. Papierwerke
			<lb />
			Waldhof-Aschaffenburg
			<lb />
			A.G. [Black-Clawson
			<lb />
			International
			<lb />
			Ltd. v. Papierwerke
			<lb />
			Waldhof-
			<lb />
			Aschaffenburg A.G., 1975 AC 591 : (1975) 2 WLR
			<lb />
			513 : (1975) 1 All ER 810 (HL)] We are clearly of
			<lb />
			the opinion that having regard to the language we
			<lb />
			must find the reason and the spirit of the law.‖
			<lb />
			(Emphasis in original)
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			41. How labour legislations are to be interpreted has been
			<lb />
			stated and restated by this Court time and again. In M.P.
			<lb />
			Mineral Industry Assn. v. Regl. Labour Commr. (Central) [M.P.
			<lb />
			Mineral Industry Assn. v. Regl. Labour Commr. (Central), AIR
			<lb />
			1960 SC 1068] , this Court while dealing with the provisions of
			<lb />
			the Minimum Wages Act, 1948, observed that this Act is
			<lb />
			intended to achieve the object of doing social justice to
			<lb />
			workmen employed in the scheduled employments by
			<lb />
			prescribing minimum rates of wages for them, and so in
			<lb />
			construing the said provisions the court should adopt what is
			<lb />
			sometimes described as a beneficent rule of construction.
			<lb />
			In Surendra Kumar Verma v. Central Govt. Industrial Tribunal-
			<lb />
			cum-Labour Court [Surendra Kumar Verma v. Central Govt.
			<lb />
			Industrial Tribunal-cum-Labour Court, (1980) 4 SCC 443 :
			<lb />
			1981 SCC (L&amp;S) 16] , this Court reminded that semantic
			<lb />
			luxuries are misplaced in the interpretation of -bread and
			<lb />
			butter‖ statutes. Welfare statutes must, of necessity, receive a
			<lb />
			broad interpretation. Where legislation is designed to give relief
			<lb />
			against certain kinds of mischief, the Court is not to make
			<lb />
			inroads by making etymological excursions.
			<lb />
			42. We would also like to reproduce a passage
			<lb />
			from Workmen v. American Express International Banking
			<lb />
			Corpn. [Workmen v. American Express International Banking
			<lb />
			Corpn, (1985) 4 SCC 71: 1985 SCC (L&amp;S) 940], which
			<lb />
			provides complete answer to the argument of the appellants
			<lb />
			based on literal construction: (SCC p. 76, para 4)
			<lb />
			&quot;4. The principles of statutory construction
			<lb />
			are well settled. Words occurring in statutes of
			<lb />
			liberal import such as social welfare legislation
			<lb />
			and human rights&apos; legislation are not to be put in
			<lb />
			Procrustean beds or shrunk to Lilliputian
			<lb />
			dimensions. In construing these legislations the
			<lb />
			imposture of literal construction must be avoided
			<lb />
			and the prodigality of its misapplication must be
			<lb />
			recognised and reduced. Judges ought to be more
			<lb />
			concerned with the -colour‖, the -content‖ and
			<lb />
			the -context‖ of such statutes (we have borrowed
			<lb />
			the words from Lord Wilberforce&apos;s opinion
			<lb />
			in Prenn v. Simmonds [Prenn v. Simmonds, (1971)
			<lb />
			3 All ER 237: (1971) 1 WLR 1381 (HL)]). In the
			<lb />
			same opinion Lord Wilberforce pointed out that
			<lb />
			law is not to be left behind in some island of literal
			<lb />
			interpretation but is to enquire beyond the
			<lb />
			language, unisolated from the matrix of facts in
			<lb />
			which they are set; the law is not to be interpreted
			<lb />
			purely on internal linguistic considerations.‖
			<lb />
			43. In equal measure is the message contained Carew and
			<lb />
			Co. Ltd. v. Union of India [Carew and Co. Ltd. v. Union of
			<lb />
			India, (1975) 2 SCC 791]: (SCC p. 802, para 21)
			<lb />
			-21. The law is not -a brooding
			<lb />
			omnipotence in the sky‖ but a pragmatic
			<lb />
			instrument of social order. It is an operational art
			<lb />
			controlling economic life, and interpretative effort
			<lb />
			must be imbued with the statutory purpose. No
			<lb />
			doubt, grammar is a good guide to meaning but a
			<lb />
			bad master to dictate.‖
			<lb />
			44. The sentiments were echoed in Bombay Anand Bhavan
			<lb />
			Restaurant v. ESI
			<lb />
			Corpn. [Bombay
			<lb />
			Anand
			<lb />
			Bhavan
			<lb />
			Restaurant v. ESI Corpn., (2009) 9 SCC 61: (2009) 2 SCC
			<lb />
			(L&amp;S) 573] in the following words: (SCC p. 66, para 20)
			<lb />
			-20. The Employees&apos; State Insurance Act is
			<lb />
			a beneficial legislation. The main purpose of the
			<lb />
			enactment as the Preamble suggests, is to provide
			<lb />
			for certain benefits to employees of a factory in
			<lb />
			case of sickness, maternity and employment injury
			<lb />
			and to make provision for certain other matters in
			<lb />
			relation thereto. The Employees&apos; State Insurance
			<lb />
			Act is a social security legislation and the canons
			<lb />
			of interpreting a social legislation are different
			<lb />
			from the canons of interpretation of taxation law.
			<lb />
			The courts must not countenance any subterfuge
			<lb />
			which would defeat the provisions of social
			<lb />
			legislation and the courts must even, if necessary,
			<lb />
			strain the language of the Act in order to achieve
			<lb />
			the purpose which the legislature had in placing
			<lb />
			this legislation on the statute book. The Act,
			<lb />
			therefore, must receive a liberal construction so as
			<lb />
			to promote its objects.‖
			<lb />
			45. In taking the aforesaid view, we also agree with the learned
			<lb />
			counsel for the respondents that -superior purpose‖ contained
			<lb />
			in the BOCW Act and the Welfare Cess Act has to be kept in
			<lb />
			mind when two enactments -the Factories Act on the one hand
			<lb />
			and the BOCW Act/Welfare Cess Act on the other hand, are
			<lb />
			involved, both of which are welfare legislations. [See Allahabad
			<lb />
			Bank v. Canara Bank[Allahabad Bank v. Canara Bank, (2000)
			<lb />
			4 SCC 406] , which has been followed in Pegasus Assets
			<lb />
			Reconstruction (P) Ltd. v. Haryana Concast Ltd. [Pegasus
			<lb />
			Assets Reconstruction (P) Ltd. v. Haryana Concast Ltd., (2016)
			<lb />
			4 SCC 47 : (2016) 2 SCC (Civ) 524 : (2016) 1 Scale 1] in the
			<lb />
			context of the Securitisation and Reconstruction of Financial
			<lb />
			Assets and Enforcement of Security Interest Act, 2002 and the
			<lb />
			Companies Act, 1956.] Here the concept of -felt necessity‖
			<lb />
			would get triggered and as per the Statement of Objects and
			<lb />
			Reasons contained in the BOCW Act, since the purpose of this
			<lb />
			Act is to take care of a particular necessity i.e. welfare of
			<lb />
			unorganised labour class involved in construction activity, that
			<lb />
			needs to be achieved and not to be discarded. Here the doctrine
			<lb />
			of purposive interpretation also gets attracted which is
			<lb />
			explained in recent judgments of this Court in Richa
			<lb />
			Mishra v. State of Chhattisgarh [Richa Mishra v. State of
			<lb />
			Chhattisgarh, (2016) 4 SCC 179.
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			32.6. Rule of liberal interpretation of social welfare legislations
			<lb />
			In Prakash Cotton Mills (P) Ltd. v. State of Bombay, (1957) 2 LLJ
			<lb />
			490, Chagla J. unerringly observed that no labour legislation, no
			<lb />
			social legislation, no economic legislation, can be considered by a
			<lb />
			Court without applying the principles of social justice in interpreting
			<lb />
			the provisions of these laws. Social justice is an objective which is
			<lb />
			embodied and enshrined in our Constitution. It would indeed be
			<lb />
			startling for anyone to suggest that the Court should shut its eyes to
			<lb />
			social justice and consider and interpret a law as if our Country had
			<lb />
			not pledged itself to bringing about social justice.
			<lb />
			32.7. The rule of interpretation is that welfare, social and beneficial
			<lb />
			statutes are not to be construed strictly. In Regional P.F.
			<lb />
			Commissioner v. Hooghly Mills Co. Ltd., [2012] 1 SCR 363, the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court observed that a liberal rule of interpretation should be
			<lb />
			applied to social welfare legislations. The Court observed as follows:
			<lb />
			-23. If we look at the modern legislative trend we will
			<lb />
			discern that there is a large volume of legislation enacted with
			<lb />
			the purpose of introducing social reform by improving the
			<lb />
			conditions of certain class of persons who might not have been
			<lb />
			fairly treated in the past. These statutes are normally called
			<lb />
			remedial statutes or social welfare legislation, whereas penal
			<lb />
			statutes are sometime enacted providing for penalties for
			<lb />
			disobedience of laws making those who disobey, liable to
			<lb />
			imprisonment, fine, forfeiture or other penalty.
			<lb />
			24. The normal canon of interpretation is that a remedial
			<lb />
			statute receives liberal construction whereas a penal statute
			<lb />
			calls for strict construction. In the cases of remedial statutes, if
			<lb />
			there is any doubt, the same is resolved in favour of the class of
			<lb />
			persons for whose benefit the statute is enacted, but in cases of
			<lb />
			penal statutes if there is any doubt the same is normally
			<lb />
			resolved in favour of the alleged offender.‖
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			32.8. Cessante ratione legis, cessat et ipsa lex
			<lb />
			One of the most ancient maxims known to our law and constantly
			<lb />
			followed by our Courts is cessante ratione legis, cessat et ipsa lex i.e.
			<lb />
			when the reason for a law ceases, the law itself ceases. This principle
			<lb />
			of law can be applied to the present proposition. A restrictive
			<lb />
			interpretation to the words -trade or business‖ would disallow large
			<lb />
			claims of employees who otherwise would be covered by the Statute
			<lb />
			and the purpose behind the enactment would be lost. This principle of
			<lb />
			law has been applied in H.H. Shri Swamiji Shri Admar Mutt Etc, v.
			<lb />
			The Commissioner, Hindu Religious &amp; Charitable Endowments
			<lb />
			Department and Ors., [1980] 1 SCR 368 as well as the Foreign
			<lb />
			Courts. In Fox v Snow, 6 N.J. 12 (1950), the Supreme Court of New
			<lb />
			Jersey observed:
			<lb />
			-Cessante ratione legis, cessat et ipsa lex (the reason for
			<lb />
			a law ceasing, the law itself ceases) is one of the most ancient
			<lb />
			maxims known to our law and it is constantly followed by our
			<lb />
			courts. Of this maxim it was said in Beardsley v. City of
			<lb />
			Hartford, 50 Conn. 529, 47 Am. Rep. 677, 682 (1883), &quot;This
			<lb />
			means that no law can survive the reason on which it is
			<lb />
			founded. It needs no statute to change it; it abrogates itself.&quot;
			<lb />
			The same thought was enunciated by Lord Coke in Milborn&apos;s
			<lb />
			Case, 7 Coke 7a (K.B. 1609): &quot;Ratio legis est anima legis, et
			<lb />
			mutata legis ratione, mutatur ex lex&quot; (the reason for a law is the
			<lb />
			soul of the law, and if the reason for a law has changed, the law
			<lb />
			is changed). &quot;It is revolting,&quot; says Mr. Justice Holmes, &quot;to have
			<lb />
			no better reason for a rule of law than that so it was laid down
			<lb />
			in the time of Henry IV. It is still more revolting if the grounds
			<lb />
			upon which it was laid down have vanished long since, and the
			<lb />
			rule simply persists from blind imitation of the past,&quot; and &quot;To
			<lb />
			rest upon a formula is a slumber that, prolonged, means death.‖
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			33. Interplay of Section 12 and Section 2(1) (dd) of the Employees
			<lb />
			Compensation Act. (Earlier Section 2(1)(n) of Workmen&apos;s
			<lb />
			Compensation Act)
			<lb />
			The effect of the omission of words &quot;other than a person whose
			<lb />
			employment is of a casual nature and who is employed otherwise than
			<lb />
			for the purposes of the employer&apos;s trade or business&quot; in the definition
			<lb />
			of workman in Section 2(1)(n) by the amendment in 2000 is that a
			<lb />
			person whose employment is of a casual nature and is employed other
			<lb />
			than for the purposes of the employer&quot;s trade or business comes within
			<lb />
			the meaning of -employee‖ as defined in Section 2(1)(dd) of the
			<lb />
			Employees Compensation Act. Although the words ‗trade&apos; or
			<lb />
			‗business&apos; remain in Section 12 of the Employees Compensation Act,
			<lb />
			applying the rules of ‗purposive interpretation&apos;, ‗superior purpose&apos;,
			<lb />
			and ‗felt necessity&apos; this Court is of the view that the words ‗trade&apos; or
			<lb />
			‗business&apos; in the definition of -employee‖ in Section 2(1) (dd) were
			<lb />
			omitted to grant all the benefits of the Act to casual employees and
			<lb />
			employees employed other than for the purposes of employer&apos;s trade
			<lb />
			or business as held in Govind Goenka (supra).
			<lb />
			34. Judicial precedents must be applied with reference to the facts
			<lb />
			of the case
			<lb />
			34.1. The judgments relied upon by the appellant, namely, Bharat
			<lb />
			Earth Movers Ltd. v. Bhagyamma (supra), Dr. B. Radhakrishna v.
			<lb />
			Gouramma (supra), Lakshminarayana Shetty v. Shantha (supra),
			<lb />
			Ajay Singh Lal v. Somwati (supra), Om Parkash Batish v. Ranjit
			<lb />
			(supra), Management, Sirishad Construction (P) v. C.P. Ravinder
			<lb />
			(supra) and Kolhan Samvedak Sangh v. State of Jharkhand (supra),
			<lb />
			do not help the appellant for the reasons given by the respondent no.1
			<lb />
			in para 12 which are hereby accepted and are not being repeated
			<lb />
			herein for the sake of brevity. The other judgments cited by the
			<lb />
			appellant do not support the appellant.
			<lb />
			34.2. It is well settled that judicial precedent cannot be followed as a
			<lb />
			statute and has to be applied with reference to the facts of the case
			<lb />
			involved in it. The ratio of any decision has to be understood in the
			<lb />
			background of the facts of that case. What is of the essence in a
			<lb />
			decision is its ratio and not every observation found therein nor what
			<lb />
			logically follows from the various observations made in it. It has to be
			<lb />
			remembered that a decision is only an authority for what it actually
			<lb />
			decides. It is well settled that a little difference in facts or additional
			<lb />
			facts may make a lot of difference in the precedential value of a
			<lb />
			decision. The ratio of one case cannot be mechanically applied to
			<lb />
			another case without regard to the factual situation and circumstances
			<lb />
			of the two cases.
			<lb />
			34.3. In Padma Sundara Rao v. State of Tamil Nadu (2002) 3 SCC
			<lb />
			533 the Supreme Court held that the ratio of a judgment has to be read
			<lb />
			in the context of the facts of the case and even a single fact can make a
			<lb />
			difference. In para 9 of the said judgment, the Supreme Court held as
			<lb />
			under:
			<lb />
			-9. Courts should not place reliance on decisions without
			<lb />
			discussing as to how the factual situation fits in with the fact
			<lb />
			situation of the decision on which reliance is placed. There is
			<lb />
			always peril in treating the words of a speech or judgment as
			<lb />
			though they are words in a legislative enactment, and it is to be
			<lb />
			remembered that judicial utterances are made in the setting of
			<lb />
			the facts of a particular case, said Lord Morris in British
			<lb />
			Railways Board v. Herrington. Circumstantial flexibility, one
			<lb />
			additional or different fact may make a world of difference
			<lb />
			between conclusions in two cases.‖
			<lb />
			34.4. In Bharat Petroleum Corporation Ltd v. N.R. Vairamani,
			<lb />
			(2004) 8 SCC 579, the Supreme Court held that a decision cannot be
			<lb />
			relied on without considering the factual situation. The Supreme Court
			<lb />
			observed as under:-
			<lb />
			-9. Courts should not place reliance on decisions without
			<lb />
			discussing as to how the factual situation fits in with the fact
			<lb />
			situation of the decision on which reliance is placed.
			<lb />
			Observations of courts are neither to be read as Euclid&apos;s
			<lb />
			theorems nor as provisions of a statute and that too taken out of
			<lb />
			their context. These observations must be read in the context in
			<lb />
			which they appear to have been stated. Judgments of courts are
			<lb />
			not to be construed as statutes. To interpret words, phrases and
			<lb />
			provisions of a statute, it may become necessary for judges to
			<lb />
			embark into lengthy discussions but the discussion is meant to
			<lb />
			explain and not to define. Judges interpret statutes, they do not
			<lb />
			interpret judgments. They interpret words of statutes; their
			<lb />
			words are not to be interpreted as statutes. In London Graving
			<lb />
			Dock Co. Ltd. v. Horton [1951 AC 737: (1951) 2 All ER 1
			<lb />
			(HL)] (AC at p. 761) Lord Mac Dermott observed: (All ER p. 14
			<lb />
			C-D)
			<lb />
			-The matter cannot, of course, be settled merely by
			<lb />
			treating the ipsissima verba of Willes, J., as though
			<lb />
			they were part of an Act of Parliament and
			<lb />
			applying the rules of interpretation appropriate
			<lb />
			thereto. This is not to detract from the great weight
			<lb />
			to be given to the language actually used by that
			<lb />
			most distinguished judge…‖
			<lb />
			10. In Home Office v. Dorset Yacht Co. [(1970) 2 All ER 294:
			<lb />
			1970 AC 1004: (1970) 2 WLR 1140 (HL)] (All ER p. 297g-h)
			<lb />
			Lord Reid said,
			<lb />
			-Lord Atkin&apos;s speech … is not to be treated as if it
			<lb />
			were a statutory definition. It will require
			<lb />
			qualification in new circumstances‖.
			<lb />
			Megarry, J. in Shepherd Homes Ltd. v. Sandham (No.
			<lb />
			2) [(1971) 1 WLR 1062: (1971) 2 All ER 1267] observed:
			<lb />
			-One must not, of course, construe even a
			<lb />
			reserved judgment of Russell, L.J. as if it were an
			<lb />
			Act of Parliament.‖
			<lb />
			And, in Herrington v.British Railways Board [(1972) 2 WLR
			<lb />
			537: (1972) 1 All ER 749 (HL)] Lord Morris said: (All ER p.
			<lb />
			761c)
			<lb />
			-There is always peril in treating the words of a
			<lb />
			speech or a judgment as though they were words in
			<lb />
			a legislative enactment, and it is to be remembered
			<lb />
			that judicial utterances made in the setting of the
			<lb />
			facts of a particular case.‖
			<lb />
			11. Circumstantial flexibility, one additional or different fact
			<lb />
			may make a world of difference between conclusions in two
			<lb />
			cases. Disposal of cases by blindly placing reliance on a
			<lb />
			decision is not proper.
			<lb />
			12. The following words of Lord Denning in the matter of
			<lb />
			applying precedents have become locus classicus:
			<lb />
			-Each case depends on its own facts and a close
			<lb />
			similarity between one case and another is not
			<lb />
			enough because even a single significant detail
			<lb />
			may alter the entire aspect, in deciding such cases,
			<lb />
			one should avoid the temptation to decide cases
			<lb />
			(as said by Cardozo) by matching the colour of one
			<lb />
			case against the colour of another. To decide
			<lb />
			therefore, on which side of the line a case falls, the
			<lb />
			broad resemblance to another case is not at all
			<lb />
			decisive.
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			xxx
			<lb />
			Precedent should be followed only so far as it
			<lb />
			marks the path of justice, but you must cut the dead
			<lb />
			wood and trim off the side branches else you will
			<lb />
			find yourself lost in thickets and branches. My plea
			<lb />
			is to keep the path to justice clear of obstructions
			<lb />
			which could impede it.‖‖
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			Liability of the owner of a residential building under the Building
			<lb />
			and Other Construction Workers Act, 1996
			<lb />
			35. BOCW Act is a social welfare legislation to benefit the
			<lb />
			construction workers. The preamble of BOCW Act is reproduced
			<lb />
			hereunder:
			<lb />
			-An Act to regulate the employment and conditions
			<lb />
			of service of building and other construction workers and
			<lb />
			to provide for their safety, health and welfare measures
			<lb />
			and for other matters connected therewith or incidental
			<lb />
			thereto.‖
			<lb />
			36. BOCW Act applies to every establishment which employs or
			<lb />
			had employed 10 or more building workers in any building or other
			<lb />
			construction work on any day in preceding 12 months. Section 1(4) of
			<lb />
			the Act is reproduced hereunder:
			<lb />
			&quot;Section 1 -Short title, extent, commencement and
			<lb />
			application
			<lb />
			...............
			<lb />
			(4) It applies to every establishment which employs, or
			<lb />
			had employed on any day of the preceding twelve
			<lb />
			months, ten or more building workers in any building or
			<lb />
			other construction work.
			<lb />
			Explanation.-For the purposes of this sub-section, the
			<lb />
			building workers employed in different relays in a day
			<lb />
			either by the employer or the contractor shall be taken
			<lb />
			into account in computing the number of building
			<lb />
			workers employed in the establishment.‖
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			37. Section 2(1) (d) of the BOCW Act defines ‗building or other
			<lb />
			construction work&apos;. Section 2(1)(d) is reproduced hereunder:
			<lb />
			-Section 2 -Definitions
			<lb />
			(1) In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-
			<lb />
			...
			<lb />
			(d) -building or other construction work‖ means the
			<lb />
			construction, alteration, repairs, maintenance or
			<lb />
			demolition, of or, in relation to, buildings, streets, roads,
			<lb />
			railways, tramways, airfields, irrigation, drainage,
			<lb />
			embankment and navigation works, flood control works
			<lb />
			(including storm water drainage works), generation,
			<lb />
			transmission and distribution of power, water works
			<lb />
			(including channels for distribution of water), oil and gas
			<lb />
			installations, electric lines, wireless, radio, television,
			<lb />
			telephone, telegraph and overseas communications,
			<lb />
			dams, canals, reservoirs, watercourses, tunnels, bridges,
			<lb />
			viaducts, aquaducts, pipelines, towers, cooling towers,
			<lb />
			transmission towers and such other work as may be
			<lb />
			specified in this behalf by the appropriate Government,
			<lb />
			by notification but does not include any building or other
			<lb />
			construction work to which the provisions of the
			<lb />
			Factories Act, 1948 (63 of 1948), or the Mines Act, 1952
			<lb />
			(35 of 1952), apply;‖
			<lb />
			38. Section 2(1) (j) of the BOCW Act defines -establishment‖. It
			<lb />
			is a wide definition which includes the establishment of an individual
			<lb />
			who employs building workers as well as establishment belonging to a
			<lb />
			contractor. However, an individual who employs workers in any
			<lb />
			building or construction work in relation to his own residence, where
			<lb />
			the cost of construction is less than Rs.10 lakh, is not included.
			<lb />
			Section 2(1)(j) is reproduced hereunder:
			<lb />
			-Section 2 -Definitions
			<lb />
			(1) In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-
			<lb />
			...
			<lb />
			(j) -establishment‖ means any establishment belonging
			<lb />
			to, or under the control of, Government, any body
			<lb />
			corporate or firm, an individual or association or other
			<lb />
			body of individuals which or who employs building
			<lb />
			workers in any building or other construction work; and
			<lb />
			includes an establishment belonging to a contractor, but
			<lb />
			does not include an individual who employs such workers
			<lb />
			in any building or construction work in relation to his
			<lb />
			own residence the total cost of such construction not
			<lb />
			being more than rupees ten lakhs‖
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			39. Section 2(1) (i) of the BOCW Act defines the -employer‖
			<lb />
			which includes the owner. Section 2(1)(i) is reproduced hereunder:
			<lb />
			-Section 2 -Definitions
			<lb />
			(1) In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-
			<lb />
			...
			<lb />
			(i) -employer‖, in relation to an establishment, means
			<lb />
			the owner thereof, and includes,-
			<lb />
			(i) in relation to a building or other construction work
			<lb />
			carried on by or under the authority of any department of
			<lb />
			the Government, directly without any contractor, the
			<lb />
			authority specified in this behalf, or where no authority is
			<lb />
			specified, the head of the department;
			<lb />
			(ii) in relation to a building or other construction work
			<lb />
			carried on by or on behalf of a local authority or other
			<lb />
			establishment, directly without any contractor, the chief
			<lb />
			executive officer of that authority or establishment;
			<lb />
			(iii) in relation to a building or other construction work
			<lb />
			carried on by or though a contractor, or by the
			<lb />
			employment of building workers supplied by a
			<lb />
			contractor, the contractor;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			40. Section 2(1) (g) of the BOCW Act defines the -contractor‖.
			<lb />
			Section 2(1)(g) is reproduced hereunder:
			<lb />
			-Section 2 -Definitions
			<lb />
			(1) In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-
			<lb />
			...
			<lb />
			(g) -contractor‖ means a person who undertakes to
			<lb />
			produce a given result for any establishment, other than
			<lb />
			a mere supply of goods or articles of manufacture, by the
			<lb />
			employment of building workers or who supplies building
			<lb />
			workers for any work of the establishment; and includes
			<lb />
			a sub-contractor;
			<lb />
			41. Section 2(1) (e) of the BOCW Act defines ‗building worker&apos;.
			<lb />
			Section 2(i)(e) is reproduced hereunder:
			<lb />
			-(e) -building worker‖ means a person who is employed
			<lb />
			to do any skilled, semi-skilled or unskilled, manual,
			<lb />
			supervisory, technical or clerical work for hire or
			<lb />
			reward, whether the terms of employment be expressed
			<lb />
			or implied, in connection with any building or other
			<lb />
			construction work but does not include any such
			<lb />
			person-
			<lb />
			(i) who is employed mainly in a managerial or
			<lb />
			administrative capacity; or
			<lb />
			(ii) who, being employed in a supervisory
			<lb />
			capacity, draws wages exceeding one thousand
			<lb />
			six hundred rupees per mensem or exercises,
			<lb />
			either by the nature of the duties attached to the
			<lb />
			office or by reason of the powers vested in him,
			<lb />
			functions mainly of a managerial nature;‖
			<lb />
			42. Section 45 of the BOCW Act imposes the liability of payment
			<lb />
			of compensation on the employer in the event of the failure of the
			<lb />
			contractor to make the payment of compensation to the building
			<lb />
			worker pay compensation in accordance with the provision of the
			<lb />
			Employee&quot;s Compensation Act. Section 45 of the BOCW Act is
			<lb />
			reproduced hereunder:
			<lb />
			-Section 45 -Responsibility for payment of wages and
			<lb />
			compensation
			<lb />
			(1) An employer shall be responsible for payment of
			<lb />
			wages to each building worker employed by him and
			<lb />
			such wages shall be paid on or before such date as may
			<lb />
			be prescribed.
			<lb />
			(2) In case the contractor fails to make payment of
			<lb />
			compensation in respect of a building worker employed
			<lb />
			by him, where he is liable to make such payment when
			<lb />
			due, or makes short payment thereof, then, in the case of
			<lb />
			death or disablement of the building worker, the
			<lb />
			employer shall be liable to make payment of that
			<lb />
			compensation in full or the unpaid balance due in
			<lb />
			accordance with the provisions of the Workmen&apos;s
			<lb />
			Compensation Act, 1923 (8 of 1923), and recover the
			<lb />
			amount so paid from the contractor either by deduction
			<lb />
			from any amount payable to the contractor under any
			<lb />
			contract or as a debt payable by the contractor.‖
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			43. Section 58 of the BOCW Act extends the provisions of the
			<lb />
			Employee&quot;s Compensation Act to the building workers. Section 58 of
			<lb />
			the BOCW Act is reproduced hereunder:
			<lb />
			-Section 58 -Application of Act 8 of 1923 to building
			<lb />
			workers
			<lb />
			The provisions of the Workmen&apos;s Compensation Act,
			<lb />
			1923, shall so far as may be, apply to building workers
			<lb />
			as if the employment to which this Act applies had been
			<lb />
			included in the Second Schedule to that Act‖
			<lb />
			44. This Court is of the view that the BOCW Act applies to the
			<lb />
			construction of a residential building in which more than 10 building
			<lb />
			workers have been employed in the preceding 12 months and the cost
			<lb />
			of such construction is more than Rs.10 lakh. The owner of the
			<lb />
			aforesaid residential building would be an employer within the
			<lb />
			meaning of Section 2 (1) (i) and Section 45 of BOCW Act makes him
			<lb />
			liable to pay the compensation under the Employee&quot;s Compensation
			<lb />
			Act.
			<lb />
			Findings
			<lb />
			45. The appellant is the owner of property bearing No. BU-48,
			<lb />
			Pitam Pura, Delhi on which he raised a four storeyed building through
			<lb />
			the contractor (respondent no.2). On 06 th March, 2012, respondent
			<lb />
			No.1 was working as a labourer on the construction site of the
			<lb />
			aforesaid building when he fell down and suffered grievous injuries.
			<lb />
			The aforesaid accident arose out of and during the course of the
			<lb />
			employment of respondent No.1 with respondent No.2. Respondent
			<lb />
			no.1 is held to be an employee as defined in Section 2 (1) (dd) of the
			<lb />
			Employee&quot;s Compensation Act read with Clause (viii) (a) of Schedule
			<lb />
			II of the Employee&quot;s Compensation Act.
			<lb />
			46. The definition of ‗workman&apos;, as it originally existed in the
			<lb />
			Workmen&quot;s Compensation Act, 1923, excluded the workmen whose
			<lb />
			employment was of a casual nature and who were employed otherwise
			<lb />
			than for the purpose of employers -trade or business‖. Section 2 (1)
			<lb />
			(n) of the Workmen&quot;s Compensation Act, 1923 was amended by
			<lb />
			Workmen&quot;s Compensation (Amendment) Act, 2000 with effect from
			<lb />
			8 th December, 2000 whereby the words &quot;other than a person whose
			<lb />
			employment is of a casual nature and who is employed otherwise than
			<lb />
			for the purposes of the employer&apos;s trade or business&quot; in the definition
			<lb />
			of ‗workman&apos; in Section 2(1) (n) were omitted. The effect of the
			<lb />
			omission of words &quot;other than a person whose employment is of a
			<lb />
			casual nature and who is employed otherwise than for the purposes of
			<lb />
			the employer&apos;s trade or business&quot; in the definition of workman in
			<lb />
			Section 2(1)(n) by the amendment in 2000 is that a person whose
			<lb />
			employment is of a casual nature and who is employed other than for
			<lb />
			the purposes of the employer&quot;s trade or business is covered within the
			<lb />
			meaning of -employee‖ as defined in Section 2 (1) (dd) of the
			<lb />
			Employees Compensation Act. Applying the rules of ‗purposive
			<lb />
			interpretation&apos;, ‗superior purpose&apos;, and ‗felt necessity&apos;, this Court is of
			<lb />
			the view that the words ‗trade or business&apos; in the definition of
			<lb />
			-employee‖ in Section 2 (1) (dd) were omitted to grant all the benefits
			<lb />
			of the Act to casual employees and employees employed other than
			<lb />
			for the purposes of employer&apos;s trade or business. In Govind Goenka v.
			<lb />
			Dayawati (supra), this Court examined the effect of Workmen&quot;s
			<lb />
			Compensation (Amendment) Act, 2000 and held that, after the
			<lb />
			amendment, the workman whose employment is of casual nature and
			<lb />
			who is employed otherwise than for the purpose of employer&apos;s trade or
			<lb />
			business, would also be covered within the definition of &quot;workman‖.
			<lb />
			This Court agrees with the above interpretation.
			<lb />
			47. In Payyannur Educational Society v. Narayani (supra), Public
			<lb />
			Works Department v. Commissioner, Workmen Compensation
			<lb />
			(supra), Bala Mallamma v. Registrar, Osmania University (supra),
			<lb />
			Govind Goenka v. Dayawati (supra), the Courts have interpreted the
			<lb />
			word &quot;business&apos; in Section 12 of the Employee&quot;s Compensation Act to
			<lb />
			include an activity which engages time, attention and labour. This
			<lb />
			Court agrees with the interpretation of the word ‗business&apos; in the
			<lb />
			aforesaid judgments. Applying the principles laid down in the
			<lb />
			aforesaid judgments, construction of a residential house by the
			<lb />
			appellant through the contractor (respondent no.2) would fall within
			<lb />
			the meaning of ‗business&apos; and, therefore, the appellant is liable to pay
			<lb />
			the compensation to respondent no.1 under Section 12 of the
			<lb />
			Employee&quot;s Compensation Act.
			<lb />
			48. All the ingredients of Section 12 are satisfied in the present case
			<lb />
			and the appellant, being the principal, is liable to pay the
			<lb />
			compensation to respondent no.1 with right to recover the same from
			<lb />
			the contractor (respondent no.2). This case is squarely covered by the
			<lb />
			principles laid down in the judgments discussed above.
			<lb />
			49. There is no merit in the appellant&quot;s contention that the appellant
			<lb />
			cannot be held liable in view of written agreement with the contractor
			<lb />
			under which the contractor is liable. As held in Koodalingam v.
			<lb />
			Superintending Engineer, Project Circle, Public Works Department,
			<lb />
			Kozhikode (supra), Section 12 would apply notwithstanding the
			<lb />
			agreement or contract entered into between the principal and
			<lb />
			contractor regarding their liability for payment of compensation under
			<lb />
			the Act. The agreement or contract between the principal and the
			<lb />
			contractor shall govern only their inter-se rights and liabilities, and
			<lb />
			cannot affect the right of the employee or the dependants of the
			<lb />
			employee, to get the compensation from the principal or from the
			<lb />
			contractor at their option. The appellant&quot;s contention is, therefore,
			<lb />
			rejected.
			<lb />
			50. There is no merit in the defense of respondent no.2 that he had
			<lb />
			appointed Mohd. Rahil as sub-contractor who in turn had employed
			<lb />
			respondent no.1. Respondent no.2 filed an application under Order 1
			<lb />
			Rule 10 of the Code of Civil Procedure for impleading Mohd. Rahil as
			<lb />
			a respondent which was rejected by the Commissioner vide order
			<lb />
			dated 02 nd May, 2013. On the appreciation of evidence before the
			<lb />
			Commissioner, this Court holds respondent no.1 to be the employee of
			<lb />
			respondent no.2 and the defence of respondent no.2 before the
			<lb />
			Commissioner for shifting the liability to Mohd. Rahil is rejected. So
			<lb />
			far as the appellant is concerned, Section 12 imposes the liability on
			<lb />
			the principal where several tiers of contractors or petty contractors are
			<lb />
			employed as held in Sardar Sewa Singh v. Hindustan Lever Ltd.
			<lb />
			(supra).
			<lb />
			51. Notwithstanding clear liability of the appellant to pay the
			<lb />
			compensation to respondents No.1 under Section 12 of the
			<lb />
			Employee&quot;s Compensation Act, the appellant is also liable to pay the
			<lb />
			compensation under Section 45 read with Section 1(4), Section 2(1)
			<lb />
			(d), (e), (g), (i), (j) and 58 of the BOCW Act. BOCW Act applies to
			<lb />
			construction of a residential buildings in which more than 10 workers
			<lb />
			had been employed and cost of the residential building was more than
			<lb />
			Rs.10,00,000/-. Section 45 of BOC Act makes the employer liable to
			<lb />
			pay the compensation and the term ‗employer&apos; in Section 2(1) (i) of
			<lb />
			the BOCW Act includes the owner. In the present case, BOCW Act is
			<lb />
			applicable as the cost of the appellant&quot;s building was more than
			<lb />
			Rs.10,00,000/-and more than 10 building workers were employed
			<lb />
			during the construction work. The appellant&quot;s building falls within the
			<lb />
			definition of ‗building and other construction work&apos; as defined in
			<lb />
			Section 2(1)(d); respondent no.1 is a ‗building worker&apos; within the
			<lb />
			meaning of Section 2(1)(e) of the BOCW Act; the appellant&quot;s building
			<lb />
			is an ‗establishment&apos; within the meaning of Section 2(1)(j) of the
			<lb />
			BOCW Act as the cost of the construction was more than Rs.10 lakhs;
			<lb />
			Respondent no.2 is a ‗contractor&apos; within the definition of Section
			<lb />
			2(1)(g) of the BOCW Act and the appellant, being the owner, is an
			<lb />
			‗employer&apos; within the definition of Section 2(1) (i) of the BOCW Act
			<lb />
			which includes the owner. The appellant is liable to pay the
			<lb />
			compensation to respondent no.1 under Section 45 of the Employee&quot;s
			<lb />
			Compensation Act as the contractor has failed to make the payment of
			<lb />
			the compensation when it fell due. The objection of the appellant that
			<lb />
			the appellant is not the employer and he is not liable to pay the
			<lb />
			compensation under Section 45 is rejected.
			<lb />
			52. Respondent no.1 suffered post-traumatic paraplegia which
			<lb />
			resulted in 80% permanent disability relating to both lower limbs as
			<lb />
			per the disability certificate dated 12 th April, 2013.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			Commissioner, Employees&quot; Compensation has taken the loss of
			<lb />
			earning capacity as 100%. Respondent no.1 appeared before this
			<lb />
			Court on 9 th March, 2017 and this Court is satisfied that the
			<lb />
			Commissioner, Employees&quot; Compensation has rightly taken the loss
			<lb />
			of earning capacity as 100% as respondent no.1 is unable to do any
			<lb />
			work. Computation of compensation of Rs.10,69,008/-by the
			<lb />
			Commissioner is upheld.
			<lb />
			Conduct of the appellant
			<lb />
			53. During the course of hearing dated 31 st July, 2017, the appellant
			<lb />
			raised a false claim before this Court that less than 10 workers were
			<lb />
			employed during the construction whereupon this Court examined the
			<lb />
			appellant under Section 165 of Indian Evidence Act when the
			<lb />
			appellant made a false statement on oath with respect to the number of
			<lb />
			the workers. It is matter of record that more than 30 workers were
			<lb />
			employed on the site as stated by respondent No.1 during his cross-
			<lb />
			examination on 10 th December, 2014. Even the appellant, in his
			<lb />
			written submissions filed before the Commissioner, Employees&quot;
			<lb />
			Compensation on 27 th January, 2016, admitted that respondent no.1
			<lb />
			and 10-15 labourers were working on the site on the date of the
			<lb />
			accident. The relevant portion of the written submissions of the
			<lb />
			appellant, duly signed by the appellant and respondent no.2 as well as
			<lb />
			their counsel are reproduced herein below:-
			<lb />
			-3. ………………The above said applicant was brought to
			<lb />
			the site of work by Mr. Mohd. Rahil alongwith 10-15
			<lb />
			labourers on daily wages, who used to lay linter work in
			<lb />
			the building on the day of incident i.e. 6.3.2012…………
			<lb />
			Gulab Singh
			<lb />
			Brijesh Kumar Verma
			<lb />
			Signed/-
			<lb />
			Signed/-
			<lb />
			Respondents
			<lb />
			Signed/-
			<lb />
			Counsel
			<lb />
			Delhi
			<lb />
			Through
			<lb />
			Dated: 27.1.2016‖
			<lb />
			54. Raising a false claim before the Court is an offence under
			<lb />
			Section 209 of Indian Penal Code which is reproduced here under:-
			<lb />
			-Section 209 -Dishonestly making false claim in Court
			<lb />
			-Whoever fraudulently or dishonestly, or with intent
			<lb />
			to injure or annoy any person, makes in a Court of
			<lb />
			Justice any claim which he knows to be false, shall be
			<lb />
			punished with imprisonment of either description for a
			<lb />
			term which may extend to two years, and shall also be
			<lb />
			liable to fine.‖
			<lb />
			55. In H.S. Bedi v. National Highway Authority of India, 2016
			<lb />
			(155) DRJ 259, this Court examined the scope of Section 209 of the
			<lb />
			Indian Penal Code and held as under:
			<lb />
			-15.1 Section 209 of the Indian Penal Code makes
			<lb />
			dishonestly making a false claim in a Court as an offence
			<lb />
			punishable with imprisonment upto two years and fine.
			<lb />
			15.2 The essential ingredients of an offence under
			<lb />
			Section 209 are: (i) The accused made a claim; (ii) The
			<lb />
			claim was made in a Court of Justice; (iii) The claim was
			<lb />
			false, either wholly or in part; (iv) That the accused knew
			<lb />
			that the claim was false; and (v) The claim was made
			<lb />
			fraudulently, dishonestly, or with intent to injure or to
			<lb />
			annoy any person.
			<lb />
			15.3 A litigant makes a ‗claim&apos; before a Court of Justice
			<lb />
			for the purpose of Section 209 when he seeks certain relief
			<lb />
			or remedies from the Court and a ‗claim&apos; for relief
			<lb />
			necessarily impasses the ground for obtaining that relief.
			<lb />
			The offence is complete the moment a false claim is filed
			<lb />
			in Court.
			<lb />
			15.4 The word -claim‖ in Section 209 of the IPC cannot
			<lb />
			be read as being confined to the prayer clause. It means
			<lb />
			the -claim‖ to the existence or non-existence of a fact or
			<lb />
			a set of facts on which a party to a case seeks an outcome
			<lb />
			from the Court based on the substantive law and its
			<lb />
			application to facts as established. To clarify, the word
			<lb />
			-claim‖ would mean both not only a claim in the
			<lb />
			affirmative to the existence of fact(s) as, to illustrate, may
			<lb />
			be made in a plaint, writ petition, or an application; but
			<lb />
			equally also by denying an averred fact while responding
			<lb />
			(to the plaint/petition, etc.) in a written statement, counter
			<lb />
			affidavit, a reply, etc.
			<lb />
			Doing so is making a -claim‖ to
			<lb />
			the non-existence of the averred fact. A false -denial‖,
			<lb />
			except when the person responding is not aware, would
			<lb />
			constitute making a -claim‖ in Court under Section 209
			<lb />
			IPC.
			<lb />
			15.5 The word ‗claim&apos; for the purposes of Section 209 of
			<lb />
			the Penal Code would also include the defence adopted by
			<lb />
			a defendant in the suit. The reason for criminalising false
			<lb />
			claims and defences is that the plaintiff as well as the
			<lb />
			defendant can abuse the process of law by deliberate
			<lb />
			falsehoods, thereby perverting the course of justice and
			<lb />
			undermining the authority of the law.
			<lb />
			15.6 Whether the litigant&apos;s ‗claim&apos; is false, is not
			<lb />
			considered merely from whatever he pleads (or omits to
			<lb />
			plead): that would be to elevate form over substance. To
			<lb />
			make out the offence, the Court does not merely
			<lb />
			inspect how a litigant&apos;s pleadings have been drafted or
			<lb />
			the case has been presented. The real issue to be
			<lb />
			considered is whether, all said and done, the litigant&apos;s
			<lb />
			action has a proper foundation which entitles him to seek
			<lb />
			judicial relief.
			<lb />
			15.7 Section 209 was enacted to preserve the sanctity of
			<lb />
			the Court of Justice and to safeguard the due
			<lb />
			administration of law by deterring the deliberate
			<lb />
			making of false claims. Section 209 was intended to
			<lb />
			deter the abuse of Court process by all litigants who
			<lb />
			make false claims fraudulently, dishonestly, or with
			<lb />
			intent to injure or annoy.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			15.8 False claims delay justice and compromise the
			<lb />
			sanctity of a Court of justice as an incorruptible
			<lb />
			administrator of truth and a bastion of rectitude.
			<lb />
			15.9 Filing of false claims in Courts aims at striking a
			<lb />
			blow at the rule of law and no Court can ignore such
			<lb />
			conduct which has the tendency to shake public
			<lb />
			confidence in the judicial institutions because the very
			<lb />
			structure of an ordered life is put at stake. It would be a
			<lb />
			great public disaster if the fountain of justice is allowed to
			<lb />
			be poisoned by anyone resorting to filing of false claims.
			<lb />
			15.10 The Courts of law are meant for imparting justice
			<lb />
			between the parties. One who comes to the Court, must
			<lb />
			come with clean hands. More often than not, process of
			<lb />
			the Court is being abused. Property-grabbers, tax-
			<lb />
			evaders, bank-loan-dodgers and other unscrupulous
			<lb />
			persons from all walks of life find the Court-process a
			<lb />
			convenient lever to retain the illegal gains indefinitely. A
			<lb />
			person, who&apos;s case is based on falsehood, has no right to
			<lb />
			approach the Court. He can be summarily thrown out at
			<lb />
			any stage of the litigation.
			<lb />
			15.11 The disastrous result of leniency or indulgence in
			<lb />
			invoking Section 209 is that it sends out wrong signals. It
			<lb />
			creates almost a licence for litigants and their lawyers to
			<lb />
			indulge in such serious malpractices because of the
			<lb />
			confidence that no action will result.
			<lb />
			15.12 Unless lawlessness which is all pervasive in the
			<lb />
			society is not put an end with an iron hand, the very
			<lb />
			existence of a civilized society is at peril if the people of
			<lb />
			this nature are not shown their place. Further if the
			<lb />
			litigants making false claims are allowed to go scot free,
			<lb />
			every law breaker would violate the law with immunity.
			<lb />
			Hence, deterrent action is required to uphold the majesty
			<lb />
			of law. The Court would be failing in its duties, if false
			<lb />
			claims are not dealt with in a manner proper and effective
			<lb />
			for maintenance of majesty of Courts as otherwise the
			<lb />
			Courts would lose its efficacy to the litigant public.‖
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			Conclusion
			<lb />
			56. The impugned order holding the appellant liable to pay the
			<lb />
			compensation of Rs.10,69,008/-along with interest @12% per annum
			<lb />
			to respondent no.1 is upheld. However, the appellant is granted
			<lb />
			recovery rights to recover the compensation amount from respondent
			<lb />
			no.2 (contractor) after making the payment of the entire compensation
			<lb />
			amount to respondent no.1.
			<lb />
			57. In the present case, the compensation was not paid to
			<lb />
			respondent no.1 when it fell due. Section 4A(3) of the Employees&quot;
			<lb />
			Compensation Act provides for penalty upto 50% of the compensation
			<lb />
			amount if the compensation due under the Act is not paid within one
			<lb />
			month it fell due. However, the Commissioner, Employees&quot;
			<lb />
			Compensation has not imposed penalty under Section 4A (3) of the
			<lb />
			Employees&quot; Compensation Act. The Commissioner, Employees&quot;
			<lb />
			Compensation is directed to initiate the penalty proceedings under
			<lb />
			Section 4A (3) of the Employees&quot; Compensation Act in accordance
			<lb />
			with law.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			58. This Court is of the prima facie view that the appellant has
			<lb />
			raised a false claim before this Court and therefore, a show cause
			<lb />
			notice is hereby issued to the appellant to show cause as to why a
			<lb />
			complaint be not made against him under Section 340 Cr.P.C. for
			<lb />
			raising a false claim under Section 209 IPC. Reply to the show cause
			<lb />
			notice be filed by the appellant within four weeks.
			<lb />
			59. The appeal is disposed of in the above terms. Pending
			<lb />
			application is also disposed of.
			<lb />
			Disbursement of Compensation Amount
			<lb />
			60. The appellant has deposited Rs.10,69,008/-with the
			<lb />
			Commissioner, Employees&quot; Compensation on 14 th July, 2016. The
			<lb />
			appellant is directed to deposit interest amount with the Registrar
			<lb />
			General of this Court within four weeks.
			<lb />
			61. Vide order dated 9 th March, 2017, this Court directed the
			<lb />
			Commissioner, Employees&quot; Compensation to instruct State Bank of
			<lb />
			India, Tis Hazari Courts Branch to transfer the aforesaid amount of
			<lb />
			Rs.75,000/-to the savings bank account No.36035499387 of
			<lb />
			respondent No.1 with State Bank of India, Tis Hazari Courts Branch
			<lb />
			and the monthly interest on the FDR of the balance amount be
			<lb />
			transferred to the savings bank account of respondent No.1 near the
			<lb />
			place of the residence of respondent No.1.
			<lb />
			62. The Commissioner, Employees&quot; Compensation is directed to
			<lb />
			disburse the remaining amount to respondent No.1 by directing the
			<lb />
			State Bank of India, Tis Hazari Courts Branch in the following
			<lb />
			manner:-
			<lb />
			(i) Rs.8,00,000/-be kept in 50 FDRs of Rs.16,000/-each in the
			<lb />
			name of respondent no.1, Aurangjeb for the period 1 month
			<lb />
			to 50 months respectively with cumulative interest.
			<lb />
			(ii) The balance amount, after keeping Rs.8 lakh in FDRs, be
			<lb />
			released to respondent No.1 by transferring the same to his
			<lb />
			individual savings bank account near the place of his
			<lb />
			residence.
			<lb />
			(iii) The maturity amounts of the FDRs made in the name of
			<lb />
			respondent no.1, Aurangjeb along with the interest shall be
			<lb />
			transferred to his individual savings bank account near the
			<lb />
			place of his residence.
			<lb />
			(iv) All the original FDRs shall be retained by the State Bank of
			<lb />
			India, Tis Hazari Courts Branch. However, the statement
			<lb />
			containing FDR number, FDR amount, date of maturity and
			<lb />
			the maturity amount be furnished to respondent No.1.
			<lb />
			(v) No loan or advance or pre-mature discharge shall be
			<lb />
			permitted without the permission of this Court.
			<lb />
			(vi) The concerned bank of respondent No.1 is directed not to
			<lb />
			issue any cheque book or debit card to respondent no.1 and
			<lb />
			if the same have already been issued, concerned bank is
			<lb />
			directed to cancel the same. Respondent no.1 shall produce
			<lb />
			the copy of this judgement before the concerned bank
			<lb />
			whereupon the concerned bank shall make an endorsement
			<lb />
			on the passbook of respondent no.1 that no debit card or
			<lb />
			cheque book shall be issued to respondent no.1 without the
			<lb />
			permission of this Court.
			<lb />
			(vii) The concerned bank shall permit respondent no.1 to make
			<lb />
			cash withdrawals on the basis of the withdrawal forms.
			<lb />
			(viii) Respondent no.1 shall produce his passbook to the Manager,
			<lb />
			State Bank of India, Tis Hazari Courts Branch who shall
			<lb />
			ensure and verify that an endorsement on the passbook of
			<lb />
			respondent no.1 has been made to the effect that no cheque
			<lb />
			book or debit card has been issued and if the same have
			<lb />
			already been issued, concerned bank has cancelled the same.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			63. List on 29 th January, 2018.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			64. The record of the Commissioner, Employees&quot; Compensation be
			<lb />
			returned back forthwith for being listed before the Commissioner,
			<lb />
			Employees&quot; Compensation for initiating penalty proceedings on 15 th
			<lb />
			January, 2018.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			65. Copy of this judgement be given dasti to the counsel for the
			<lb />
			parties.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			66. Copy of this judgement be given dasti to Sanjoy Ghose,
			<lb />
			Additional Standing counsel for GNCTD for compliance by
			<lb />
			Commissioner, Employees&quot; Compensation and Mr. Sajiv Kakra,
			<lb />
			Advocate for compliance by State Bank of India, Tis Hazari Courts
			<lb />
			Branch.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>	
			DECEMBER 20, 2017
			<lb />
			J.R. MIDHA
			<lb />
			(JUDGE)
			<lb />
			ak/dk
		</p>


	</text>
</tei>