<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">

<head>COMMON JUDGMENT<lb/>
 R.SUDHAKAR,J.<lb/>
</head>

<p>The appellant/consortium, having met its waterloo before<lb/>
 the learned Single Judge, has filed these appeals challenging<lb/>
 the order dated 7.4.2015 passed in W.P.Nos.26762 and 27529<lb/>
 of 2014.<lb/>
</p>

<p>A THUMBNAIL SKETCH OF THE FACTS<lb/>
</p>

<p>2.1. The first respondent vide tender notification dated<lb/>
 6.5.2013 floated a tender for setting up of two units of 660<lb/>
 MW Ennore SEZ Supercritical Thermal Power Project at Ash<lb/>
 Dyke of NCTPS. In all, four bidders, including the appellant<lb/>
 and third respondent (BHEL), participated. The two other<lb/>
 bidders who participated in the tender were disqualified as<lb/>
 they failed to meet the Bid Qualification Requirements. The<lb/>
 appellant is a Consortium of Trishe Energy Infrastructure<lb/>
 Services Private Limited, a company registered under the<lb/>
 provisions of the Indian Companies Act, and Central Southern<lb/>
 China Electric Power Design Institute (CSEPDI), a power<lb/>
 engineering, survey and design, and general engineering<lb/>
 contracting company.<lb/>
</p>

<p>2.2. The bids of appellant and the third respondent were<lb/>
 taken up for consideration by respondents 1 and 2. Prior to<lb/>
 the opening of the price bids, the appellant and the third<lb/>
 respondent submitted Supplementary Price Bids on 5.2.2014.<lb/>
 The price bids were opened on 5.2.2014 by the second<lb/>
 respondent in the presence of the representatives of the<lb/>
 appellant and the third respondent.<lb/>
</p>

<p>2.3. Thereafter, as the tender process was hanging fire,<lb/>
 the appellant sent its representations dated 16.6.2014,<lb/>
 17.6.2014, 1.7.2014 and 8.7.2014 to the first respondent,<lb/>
 highlighting various aspects of the bid and the relevance of<lb/>
 Clause 29.0(viii) of the Instructions to Bidders which deals with<lb/>
 rejection of bids of the tender whose past performance/vendor<lb/>
 rating is not satisfactory, more particularly, the poor track<lb/>
 record and past performance of the third respondent, and also<lb/>
 pointing out the wrong and improper calculations made<lb/>
 contrary to financial statements submitted by the appellant.<lb/>
</p>

<p>2.4. As the first respondent did not pay heed to the<lb/>
 request made by the appellant, it filed W.P.No.19247 of 2014<lb/>
 seeking issuance of a writ of Mandamus to direct respondents<lb/>
 1 and 2 to consider the appellant&apos;s representations dated<lb/>
 16.6.2014, 17.6.2014, 1.7.2014 and 8.7.2014, and take<lb/>
 necessary action on the same in accordance with the tender<lb/>
 terms and the provisions of the Tamil Nadu Transparency in<lb/>
 Tenders Act, 1998 (for brevity, &quot;the TTIT Act&quot;).<lb/>
 <lb/>
</p>

<p>2.5. When the said writ petition was taken up for hearing,<lb/>
 the learned Advocate General appearing for the first<lb/>
 respondent undertook that post-bid representations submitted<lb/>
 by the appellant will be duly considered while finalizing the<lb/>
 tenders and appropriate orders will be passed in accordance<lb/>
 with the tender specifications, TTIT Act and the Tamil Nadu<lb/>
 Transparency in Tenders Rules, 2000 (for brevity, &quot;the TTIT<lb/>
 Rules&quot;) Rules framed thereunder. Recording the said<lb/>
 undertaking, the learned Single Judge, by order dated<lb/>
 31.7.2014 made in M.P.No.1 of 2014 in W.P.No.19247 of 2014,<lb/>
 directed respondents 1 and 2 to consider and pass orders on<lb/>
 the representations of the appellant herein after affording<lb/>
 them an opportunity of personal hearing and till such orders<lb/>
 are passed, it held that the tender should not be finalized.<lb/>
</p>

<p>2.6. Calling into question the order dated 31.7.2014<lb/>
 made in M.P.No.1 of 2014 in W.P.No.19247 of 2014,<lb/>
 respondents 1 and 2 filed W.A.No.1065 of 2014. A Division<lb/>
 Bench of this Court, by judgment dated 19.8.2014, disposed of<lb/>
 the writ appeal and writ petition by modifying the order of the<lb/>
<lb/>
 learned Single Judge only to the extent of holding that the<lb/>
 rules did not contemplate personal hearing to the person who<lb/>
 is objecting. The appellant was permitted to submit additional<lb/>
 particulars/documents raising all its objections and the first<lb/>
 respondent was directed to pass an order and communicate<lb/>
 the same to the appellant and the third respondent. It is the<lb/>
 specific plea of the appellant that the Division Bench did not<lb/>
 modify the order of the learned Single Judge holding that till<lb/>
 the first respondent passed an order on the representation,<lb/>
 finalization of the bid/tender could not be done.<lb/>
</p>

<p>2.7. Pursuant to the direction issued by the Division<lb/>
 Bench, the appellant sent its representation on 25.8.2014<lb/>
 along with necessary documents. However, the first respon-<lb/>
dent vide its communication dated 27.9.2014 (alleged to be<lb/>
 received by the appellant on 29.9.2014), rejected the repre-<lb/>
sentation made by the appellant. Challenging the same, the<lb/>
 appellant filed W.P.No.26762 of 2014 seeking a writ of<lb/>
 Certiorarified Mandamus calling for the records of the first<lb/>
 respondent culminating in the impugned communication<lb/>
 bearing<lb/>
 Lr.No.CE/P/SE/M/P/EE-10/E/P/F.2x660MW<lb/>
 Ennore<lb/>
 SEZ/D.58/2014 dated 27.9.2014, quash the same and forbear<lb/>
 the first and second respondents from in any manner taking<lb/>
 any steps to proceed with the tender with the third respondent<lb/>
 in respect of SPEC.No.CE/C/P&amp;E/EE/ E/OT No.3/2013-14<lb/>
 issued by the first and second respondents for the 2 x 660 MW<lb/>
 Ennore SEZ Supercritical Thermal Power Project at Ash Dyke of<lb/>
 NCTPS in accordance with the provisions of Clause 29(viii) of<lb/>
 the Tender Document read with the provisions of the Tamil<lb/>
 Nadu Transparency in Tenders Act, 1998 and the Tamil Nadu<lb/>
 Transparency in Tenders Rules, 2000.<lb/>
</p>

<p>2.8. At the time of hearing of W.P.No.26762 of 2014, the<lb/>
 learned Advocate General produced a copy of the letter dated<lb/>
 27.9.2014 awarding the contract to the third respondent<lb/>
 (BHEL). Based on the acceptance letter of the third respon-<lb/>
dent dated 27.9.2014, which makes reference to price negotia-<lb/>
tion meetings held by the first respondent with the third re-<lb/>
spondent on 5.6.2014, 13.6.2014 and 27.6.2014, and the ex-<lb/>
change of correspondence dated 26.6.2014, 30.6.2014 and<lb/>
 <lb/>
</p>

<p>2.7.2014, the appellant sent a letter dated 1.10.2014 to the<lb/>
 first respondent highlighting the arbitrariness, anomalies and<lb/>
 inconsistencies in its reasoning and the mala fide intent in the<lb/>
 matter of evaluating the bid submitted by the appellant. How-<lb/>
ever, the Chief Engineer (Projects), TANGEDCO, by letter dated<lb/>
 10.10.2014, informed the appellant that the subject tender has<lb/>
 been finalised and awarded to the third respondent. Assailing<lb/>
 the letter dated 27.9.2014 awarding the contract to the third<lb/>
 respondent and the subsequent communication dated<lb/>
 10.10.2014, the appellant filed W.P.No.27529 of 2014 seeking<lb/>
 a writ of Certiorarified Mandamus calling for the records of the<lb/>
 fourth<lb/>
 respondent&apos;s<lb/>
 impugned<lb/>
 proceedings<lb/>
 bearing<lb/>
 Lr.No.CE/P/SE/M/P/EE-10/E/P/F.2x660MW Ennore SEZ/STPP/<lb/>
 D.60, dated 27.9.2014 awarding to the 3rd respondent the<lb/>
 tender bearing SPEC.No.CE/C/P&amp;E/EE/E/OT No.3/2013-14<lb/>
 issued in respect of the 2x660 MW Ennore SEZ Supercritical<lb/>
 Thermal Power Project at Ash Dyke of NCTPS invited by the 1st<lb/>
 and 2nd respondents culminating in its Lr.No.CE/P/SE/M/P/EE-<lb/>
10/E/F.Ennore SEZ/D.64/14 dated 10.10.2014, quash the<lb/>
 same and direct the 1st, 2nd and 4th respondents to<lb/>
 determine the award of the tender strictly in terms of the<lb/>
 Tender/Bid document bearing SPEC.No.CE/C/P&amp;E/EE/E/OT<lb/>
 No.3/2013-14 taking into account the petitioner&apos;s bid and the<lb/>
 comparative merits of the petitioner and the 3rd respondent.<lb/>
</p>

<p>2.9. It is the case of the appellant that after culmination<lb/>
 of hearing before the learned Single Judge, certain files were<lb/>
 handed over to the learned Single Judge, without furnishing<lb/>
 them a copy of it, and the learned Single Judge, by order<lb/>
 dated 7.4.2015, dismissed the writ petitions primarily based on<lb/>
 the current/note files containing a purported Consultant Report<lb/>
 dated 30.5.2014, holding that the conduct of process of<lb/>
 evaluation of the tenders, does not appear to be arbitrary,<lb/>
 capricious or unfair; and that the price bids of the appellant as<lb/>
 well as the third respondent had been evaluated as per the<lb/>
 parameters indicated in the tender notification, by an<lb/>
 independent consultant, who himself was selected through a<lb/>
 tender floated earlier. The reasoning of the learned Single<lb/>
 Judge truly hinges on the Consultant&apos;s report to the effect that<lb/>
 the third respondent is identified as L1 and hence, appellant<lb/>
 has no role after L1 has been identified.<lb/>
</p>

<p>2.10. Assailing the said common order passed by the<lb/>
 learned Single Judge, the present appeals are filed.<lb/>
 CONTENTIONS MADE ON BEHALF OF THE APPELLANT<lb/>
</p>

<p>3. Mr.Sriram Panchu, learned Senior Counsel appearing<lb/>
 on behalf of the appellant and Mr.N.L.Rajah, learned Counsel<lb/>
 for the appellant, pleaded for setting aside the order of the<lb/>
 learned Single Judge and to direct the first respondent to<lb/>
 evaluate the two bids on the basis of the bids submitted, the<lb/>
 representations and letter clarifying the issue, based on<lb/>
 comparative merits. Their contentions on varied issues are<lb/>
 recorded in the succeeding paragraphs issue-wise.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(A) VIOLATION OF THE STATUTORY PROVISIONS:<lb/>
</p>

<p>4.1. The proceedings dated 27.9.2014 awarding the<lb/>
 tender to the third respondent, and the proceedings dated<lb/>
| <lb/>
</p>

<p>10.10.2014 intimating the appellant that tender has been<lb/>
 awarded to the third respondent are cryptic and bereft of<lb/>
 reasons. That apart, there is no comparative analysis of the<lb/>
 tenders submitted and, therefore, the same runs counter to<lb/>
 the provisions of Section 10 of the TTIT Act, 1998, Rule 30 of<lb/>
 the TTIT Rules, 2000 and Section 4(1)(d) of the RTI Act, 2005.<lb/>
</p>

<p>4.2. In the said impugned communications, the end<lb/>
 result has only been communicated without reasons and the<lb/>
 same is contrary to Section 10(6) of the TTIT Act, 1998 which<lb/>
 mandates that &quot;If the Tender Accepting Authority proposes to<lb/>
 accept the tender as per the provisions of this section, he shall<lb/>
 pass orders accepting the tender together with reasons for<lb/>
 such acceptance&quot;,<lb/>
 and the same also runs counter to the<lb/>
 procedure contemplated under Section 4(1)(d) of the Right to<lb/>
 Information Act (for brevity, &quot;the RTI Act&quot;) which states that<lb/>
 every public authority shall provide reasons for its<lb/>
 administrative or quasi judicial decisions to affected persons. It<lb/>
 is pleaded that the lack of reasoning in the impugned<lb/>
 proceedings is evidence of the fact that the pith and substance<lb/>
 <lb/>
 of TTIT Act and TTIT Rules have been violated and there is<lb/>
 something more to it than meets the eye.<lb/>
</p>

<p>4.3. The object behind Section 10(7) of the TTIT Act is to<lb/>
 inform the public as to why one tenderer was chosen over the<lb/>
 others, however till date no iota of evidence is produced to<lb/>
 show that the Tender Accepting Authority has intimated the<lb/>
 information regarding the name and address of the tenderer<lb/>
 whose tender has been accepted along with the reasons for<lb/>
 rejection of other tenders to the Tender Bulletin Officer. Even<lb/>
 though the learned Advocate General pleaded before the<lb/>
 learned Single Judge that the tender evaluation report has<lb/>
 been sent to the Tender Bulletin Officer as contemplated under<lb/>
 Rule 30(3) of the TTIT Rules, no material has been placed<lb/>
 before the Court in support of the said stand.<lb/>
</p>

<p>4.4. Referring to paragraph (35) of the order of the<lb/>
 learned Single Judge, which reads as under:<lb/></p><p>
 &quot;First of all, what is contemplated under Section<lb/>
 10(6) is only an obligation to record reasons for<lb/>
 accepting the tender of one. Once these reasons<lb/>
 are communicated to the losers, Section 10(6)<lb/>
 would stand satisfied. Secondly, victors neither<lb/>
 need reasons nor would be interested in<lb/>
 knowing the reasons. For them, victory is<lb/>
 sufficient. Thirdly, Section 10(6) speaks only of<lb/>
 an obligation to record reasons for acceptance of<lb/>
 tender and does not speak of any obligation to<lb/>
 communicate the reasons . &quot;,<lb/></p><p>
 it is contended that the said observations are self-<lb/>
contradictory, as in the first reasoning the learned Single Judge<lb/>
 has observed that once reasons are communicated to the<lb/>
 losers, Section 10(6) of the TTIT Act would stand satisfied and<lb/>
 subsequently, it is observed that there is only an obligation on<lb/>
 the authorities to record reasons for acceptance of the tender<lb/>
 but there is no such obligation to communicate the reasons.<lb/>
</p>

<p>4.5. Dissecting the communication dated 27.9.2014, it is<lb/>
 pleaded that the said communication does not contain: (a) the<lb/>
 comparative analysis; (b) particulars as to who are L1 and L2;<lb/>
 (c) that the third respondent (BHEL) is the lowest bidder; and<lb/>
 (d) that the offer of BHEL is accepted or the offer of the<lb/>
 appellant is rejected. Therefore, it is not an order with reasons<lb/>
 <lb/>
 in compliance of the provisions of the TTIT Act and RTI Act.<lb/>
</p>

<p>4.6. A statute should not be construed as a theorem of<lb/>
 Euclid, but must be construed as to the purpose which lies<lb/>
 behind the statute. The rules of purposive construction have<lb/>
 to be resorted to which would require the construction of the<lb/>
 Act in such a manner so as to see that the object of the Act is<lb/>
 fulfilled. In other words, if the process in which they have to<lb/>
 express the result is regulated by a statute, it has to be done<lb/>
 that way and when the authority has not complied with the<lb/>
 same, the Court is empowered to interfere and direct the<lb/>
 authorities to follow the procedure prescribed by law.<lb/>
</p>

<p>4.7. To fortify the said plea of violation of the statutory<lb/>
 provisions, attention of this Court was specifically invited to<lb/>
 Sections 10(6) and 10(7) of the TTIT Act to plead that the<lb/>
 same contemplate that reasons should be stated. In support<lb/>
 of this plea, reliance is placed on the decision of the Delhi High<lb/>
 Court in Indian Oil Corporation ltd. v. SPS Engineering Ltd.,<lb/>
 2006 (88) DRJ 93 (DB), wherein it is held as under:<lb/>
 <lb/>
 &quot;</p>

<item>27. In this connection, it may be mentioned that<lb/>
 earlier there were only two rules of natural<lb/>
 justice viz:<lb/>
</item>

<item>(i) Giving opportunity of hearing (audi<lb/>
 alteram partem)<lb/>
</item>

<item>(ii) the rule against bias.<lb/>
</item>

<item>28. However, in recent times a third rule of<lb/>
 natural justice has been developed by courts<lb/>
 all over the world, namely, the requirement to<lb/>
 give reasons in the order affecting rights or<lb/>
 liabilities.<lb/>
</item>

<item>29. The above decision has been followed in a series<lb/>
 of decisions of the Supreme Court subsequently, the<lb/>
 latest one being State of Orissa v. Dhaniram Lohar<lb/>
 (2004) 5 SCC 58: (AIR 2004 SC 1794) wherein the<lb/>
 Supreme Court observed (vide paras 7 and 8):<lb/>
</item>

<item>&apos;Reason<lb/>
 is<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 heartbeat<lb/>
 of<lb/>
 every<lb/>
 conclusion, and without the same it<lb/>
 becomes lifeless.<lb/>
</item>

<item>Even in respect of administrative orders<lb/>
 Lord<lb/>
 Denning<lb/>
 M.R.<lb/>
 In<lb/>
 Breen<lb/>
 v.<lb/>
 Amalgamated Engg. Union, (1971) 1 All ER<lb/>
 1148 : (1971) 2 QB 175 : (1971) 2 WLR<lb/>
 742 (CA) observed: &quot;The giving of reasons<lb/>
 is one of the fundamental of good<lb/>
 administration.&quot; In Alexander Machinery<lb/>
 (Dudley) Ltd. v. Crabtree, 1974 ICR 120<lb/>
 (NIRC) it was observed: &quot;Failure to give<lb/>
 reasons amounts to denial of justice.&quot;<lb/>
 &quot;Reasons are live-links between the<lb/>
 mind of the decision-taker to the<lb/>
 controversy<lb/>
 in<lb/>
 question<lb/>
 and<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 decision or conclusion arrived at.&quot;<lb/>
 Reasons substitute subjectivity by<lb/>
 objectivity. The emphasis on recording<lb/>
 reasons is that if the decision reveals<lb/>
 the &quot;inscrutable face of the sphinx&quot;, it<lb/>
 can, by its silence, render it virtually<lb/>
 impossible for the courts to perform<lb/>
 their appellate function or exercise the<lb/>
 power of judicial review in adjudging<lb/>
 the validity of the decision. Right to<lb/>
 reason is an indispensable part of a<lb/>
 sound judicial system; reasons at least<lb/>
 sufficient to indicate an application of<lb/>
 mind to the matter before Court.<lb/>
 Another rationale is that the affected<lb/>
 party can know why the decision has<lb/>
 gone against him. One of the salutary<lb/>
 requirements of natural justice is<lb/>
 spelling out reasons for the order<lb/>
 made; in other words, a speaking-out.<lb/>
 The inscrutable face of the sphinx&apos; is<lb/>
 ordinarily incongruous with a judicial or<lb/>
 quasi-judicial performance.&apos;<lb/>
 ....<lb/>
</item>

<item>32. It is well settled that the impugned order cannot<lb/>
 be supplemented by additional material either in the<lb/>
 form of an affidavit or otherwise vide Mohinder<lb/>
 Singh v. Chief Election Commissioner, AIR 1978 SC<lb/>
 851; State Govt, Houseless Harijan Employees<lb/>
 Association v. State of Karnataka, (2001) 1 SCC 610<lb/>
 (Para 49): (AIR 2001 SC 437, Para 48); Pavanendra<lb/>
 Naraian Verma v.SGPGI of Medical Science, (2002) 1<lb/>
 SCC 520: (AIR 2002 SC 23) (Para 34): Union of<lb/>
 India v. GTC Industries (2003) 5 SCC 106 (Para 13):<lb/>
 (AIR 2003 SC 1383), etc. In our opinion, reasons<lb/>
 must be contained in the order under challenge, and<lb/>
 mere existence of reasons in the show-cause notice,<lb/>
 or any material referred to in the show-cause notice,<lb/>
 is not sufficient. In our opinion, the authority<lb/>
 concerned must, at least in brief, deal in the<lb/>
 impugned order with the explanation given in<lb/>
 the reply to the show-cause notice. This in our<lb/>
 opinion is even more necessary where a<lb/>
 personal hearing is not being given. The<lb/>
 authority<lb/>
 concerned<lb/>
 must<lb/>
 discuss<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 explanation given in the reply, and give its<lb/>
 reasons for holding that the explanation is not<lb/>
 satisfactory. In the present case all that has<lb/>
 not been done.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>(emphasis supplied)<lb/></p><p>
 (B) ARBITRARINESS:<lb/>
</p>

<p>5.1. It is pleaded that the department cannot adopt two<lb/>
 yardsticks in the process of awarding tender and when the<lb/>
 process of granting tender is based on indecisiveness and<lb/>
 vagueness, the Court can correct the error in decision making<lb/>
 process. To buttress the said argument, reliance was placed on<lb/>
 a decision rendered by one of us (R.Sudhakar,J.) in SAP<lb/>
 Industries v. Tamil Nadu Electricity Board, 2010 SCC Online<lb/>
 Mad 4138, more particularly, paragraph 17(xviii) and (xix),<lb/>
 which reads as under:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;17. .... (xviii) Assuming for a moment that the<lb/>
 price quoted by the SSI Unit of other State is the<lb/>
 price which is to be taken for consideration,<lb/>
 necessarily the petitioners should be given the<lb/>
 benefit of Rule 29(f) read with the Government&apos;s<lb/>
 clarification issued by the Principal Secretary to<lb/>
 Government,<lb/>
 Micro,<lb/>
 Small<lb/>
 and<lb/>
 Medium<lb/>
 Enterprises(F) Department in Lr. No. 561/2009-3<lb/>
 dated 5.5.2009 For denying the benefit to the<lb/>
 petitioners, the Department on one hand relies upon<lb/>
 the price quoted by the new entrant, and in the<lb/>
 same breath the Department relies upon the price<lb/>
 quoted by the SSI Unit of other State, but refuses to<lb/>
 extend the benefit that has to flow from Rule 29(f)<lb/>
 and the Government clarification in letter dated<lb/>
 5.5.2009 This is a contradiction in terms. Therefore,<lb/>
 the two letters impugned in the writ petition cannot<lb/>
 form the basis of finalizing the tender. The<lb/>
 Department has to therefore, necessarily<lb/>
 follow the provision of Section 10 of the Tamil<lb/>
 Nadu Transparency in Tenders Act, 1998 and<lb/>
 Rule 29 of the Tamil Nadu Transparency in<lb/>
 Tenders Rule, 2000 and first evaluate the<lb/>
 lowest price on comparison of the tenderers<lb/>
 and thereafter give the price preference in<lb/>
 terms of Rule 29(f) of the Rule and the<lb/>
 Government&apos;s clarification issued by the Principal<lb/>
 Secretary to Government, Micro, Small and Medium<lb/>
 Enterprises(F) Department in Lr. No. 561/2009-3<lb/>
 dated 5.5.2009 if the price of SSI Unit of other State<lb/>
 is taken as the lowest evaluated price which is the<lb/>
 case on hand.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(xix) The second respondent cannot adopt two<lb/>
 yardsticks in the process of awarding the<lb/>
 tender. Since the entire process of granting the<lb/>
 tender is based on indecisiveness and<lb/>
 vagueness, this Court has to step in to correct<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 error<lb/>
 in<lb/>
 decision making<lb/>
 process.<lb/>
 Irrelevant factors, like negotiated price, are<lb/>
 stated in the impugned letters and that leads<lb/>
 to confusion. The Department is adopting two<lb/>
 variables to deny the benefit to the petitioners<lb/>
 which cannot be justified. Hence, this Court has<lb/>
 <lb/>
 no hesitation to hold that both the letters impugned<lb/>
 in the writ petition No.4423 of 2010 are liable to set<lb/>
 aside and are set aside.&quot;<lb/>
 (emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</item>

<p>5.2. Reliance was placed on a decision of the Punjab and<lb/>
 Haryana High Court in S.C.T.Limited and another v. Punjab<lb/>
 State Electricity Board and others, AIR 2006 P&amp;H 44, to<lb/>
 contend that the courts can interfere with the award of<lb/>
 contract if it is arbitrary or discriminatory or mala fide or it has<lb/>
 no nexus with the object it seeks to achieve. The relevant<lb/>
 portion of the said decision reads as under:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;17. In Tata Cellular v. Union of India, (1994) 6 SCC<lb/>
 651, the Apex Court restated the law in the realm of<lb/>
 public contracts and policies that impact upon<lb/>
 commercial or economic matters, after reviewing its<lb/>
 previous decisions on the scope of judicial review.<lb/>
 One of the principles, out-lining the powers and<lb/>
 duties of the State of its instrumentalities, was<lb/>
 stated thus:<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;The Government must have freedom of<lb/>
contract. In other words, a fair play in the<lb/>
 joints is a necessary concomitant for an<lb/>
 administrative body functioning in an<lb/>
 administrative<lb/>
 sphere<lb/>
 or<lb/>
 quasi-<lb/>
administrative sphere. However, the<lb/>
 decision must not only be tested by the<lb/>
 application of Wednesbury principle of<lb/>
 reasonbleness (including its other facts<lb/>
 pointed out above) but must be free<lb/>
 from arbitrariness not affected by bias<lb/>
 or actuated by mala fides.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>18. As to what precisely is &quot;Wednesbury<lb/>
 unreasonableness&quot; or irrationality was discussed in<lb/>
 great detail in the same judgment and it would be<lb/>
 apposite to extract a quotation from R. v. Tower<lb/>
 Hamlets London Borough Council, (1988) 1 All<lb/>
 England Reports 961:<lb/>
 &quot;The Court is entitled to investigate the<lb/>
 action of the local authority with a view<lb/>
 to seeing whether or not they have<lb/>
 taken into account matters which they<lb/>
 ought not to have taken into account,<lb/>
 or conversely, have refused to take into<lb/>
 account or neglected to take into<lb/>
 account matter which they ought to<lb/>
 take into account. Once that question is<lb/>
 answered in favour of the local authority, it<lb/>
 may still be possible to say that, although<lb/>
 the local authority had kept within the four<lb/>
 corners of the matters which they ought to<lb/>
 consider, they have nevertheless come to a<lb/>
 conclusion<lb/>
 so<lb/>
 unreasonable<lb/>
 that<lb/>
 no<lb/>
 reasonable authority could ever have come<lb/>
 to it. In such a case, again, I think the Court<lb/>
 can interfere…….&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>19. In cases involving award of tenders, the Apex<lb/>
 Court as well as the High Courts have been<lb/>
 consistently following the principles culled out in<lb/>
 Tata Cellular&apos;s case (supra). These principles can,<lb/>
 briefly, be summarised as follows:<lb/>
 (a) The Courts can interfere when the policy or<lb/>
 the award of contract is arbitrary or<lb/>
 discriminatory of mala fide or it has no nexus<lb/>
 with the object it seeks to achieve (see:<lb/>
 Monarch<lb/>
 Infrastructure<lb/>
 (P)<lb/>
 Ltd.<lb/>
 v.<lb/>
 Commissioner,<lb/>
 Lilhasnagar<lb/>
 Municipal<lb/>
 Corporation, (2000) 5 SCC 287 and Directorate<lb/>
 of Education v.Edu Comp Datamatics Ltd., 2004<lb/>
 (2) RCR (Civil) 486 (SC) : (2004) 4 SCC 19).<lb/>
 (b) The power of judicial review has to be used<lb/>
 to interdict State agencies&apos; policies or actions<lb/>
 in the realm of award of contracts with great<lb/>
 care and circumspection and not merely<lb/>
 because according to the Courts, the policy or<lb/>
 measure is incorrect, (see M.P. Oil Extraction<lb/>
 v. State of M.P., (1997) 7 SCC 592 and Air<lb/>
 India Ltd. v. Cochin International Airport Ltd.,<lb/>
 2000 (2) RCR (Civil) 670 (SC) : (2000) 2 SCC<lb/>
 617). In Cochin International Airport Ltd.&apos;s<lb/>
 case (supra), it was also emphasised that<lb/>
 <lb/>
 judicial intervention would be warranted only<lb/>
 when the overwhelming public interest so<lb/>
 requires.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>(emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</p>

<p>5.3. It is pleaded that as per the specific direction of the<lb/>
 Division Bench dated 19.8.2014 in W.A.No.1065 of 2014,<lb/>
 which is as under:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;13. On a perusal of the statutory provisions, we find<lb/>
 that the rule nowhere contemplates affording of<lb/>
 personal hearing to the person who is objecting.<lb/>
 Hence, the 1 st respondent cannot demand personal<lb/>
 hearing, as a matter of right. However, it is made<lb/>
 clear that if any clarification is required regarding<lb/>
 the documents submitted by the 1 st respondent to<lb/>
 the appellants to consider its objections, the same<lb/>
 shall be called for from the 1 st respondent and if<lb/>
 such clarification is sought, the same shall be<lb/>
 communicated to the 2 nd respondent also and after<lb/>
 considering the clarification to be given by the<lb/>
 1 st respondent, the 1 st appellant shall pass an<lb/>
 order as directed by the learned Single Judge.<lb/>
 It is also made clear that if an opportunity of<lb/>
 personal hearing is afforded to the 1 st respond, if it is<lb/>
 required to be afforded, after considering the<lb/>
 clarification given by the 1 st respondent, the same<lb/>
 shall be extended to the 2 nd respondent also.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p><lb/>
 the appellant was always ready and willing to give further<lb/>
 particulars other than what was submitted, but the TANGEDCO<lb/>
 did not call for particulars despite the specific direction of the<lb/>
 Division Bench to seek clarifications from the appellant if so<lb/>
 advised, as was done with BHEL and the same would<lb/>
 tantamount to discriminatory treatment, violating the doctrine<lb/>
 of level playing field. In this regard, reliance was placed on a<lb/>
 decision of the Supreme Court in Reliance Energy Limited and<lb/>
 another v. Maharashtra State Road Development Corporation<lb/>
 Limited and others, 2007 (4) RAJ 139 (SC), wherein it was<lb/>
 observed as under:<lb/>
 &quot;</p>

<item>36. We find merit in this civil appeal. Standards<lb/>
 applied by courts in judicial review must be justified<lb/>
 by constitutional principles which govern the proper<lb/>
 exercise of public power in a democracy. Article 14<lb/>
 of the Constitution embodies the principle of &quot;non-<lb/>
discrimination&quot;. However, it is not a free-standing<lb/>
 provision. It has to be read in conjunction with rights<lb/>
 conferred by other articles like Article 21 of the<lb/>
 Constitution. The said Article 21 refers to &quot;right to<lb/>
 life&quot;.<lb/>
 It includes &quot;opportunity&quot;. In our view, as held in the<lb/>
 latest judgment of the Constitution Bench of nine<lb/>
 Judges in I.R. Coelho v. State of T.N. [(2007) 2 SCC<lb/>
 1], Articles 21/14 are the heart of the chapter on<lb/>
 fundamental rights. They cover various aspects of<lb/>
 life. &quot;Level playing field&quot; is an important<lb/>
 concept while construing Article 19(1)(g) of<lb/>
 the Constitution. It is this doctrine which is<lb/>
 invoked by REL/HDEC in the present case. When<lb/>
 Article 19(1)(g) confers fundamental right to carry<lb/>
 on business to a company, it is entitled to invoke the<lb/>
 said doctrine of &quot;level playing field&quot;. We may clarify<lb/>
 that this doctrine is, however, subject to public<lb/>
 interest. In the world of globalisation, competition<lb/>
 is an important factor to be kept in mind. The<lb/>
 doctrine of &quot;level playing field&quot; is an important<lb/>
 doctrine which is embodied in Article 19(1)(g) of the<lb/>
 Constitution. This is because the said doctrine<lb/>
 provides space within which equally placed<lb/>
 competitors are allowed to bid so as to subserve the<lb/>
 larger public interest. &quot;Globalisation&quot;, in essence, is<lb/>
 liberalisation of trade. Today India has dismantled<lb/>
 licence raj. The economic reforms introduced after<lb/>
 1992 have brought in the concept of &quot;globalisation&quot;.<lb/>
 Decisions or acts which result in unequal and<lb/>
 discriminatory treatment, would violate the doctrine<lb/>
 of &quot;level playing field&quot; embodied in Article 19(1)(g).<lb/>
 Time has come, therefore, to say that Article 14<lb/>
 which refers to the principle of &quot;equality&quot; should not<lb/>
 be read as a stand alone item but it should be read<lb/>
 in conjunction with Article 21 which embodies<lb/>
 several aspects of life. There is one more aspect<lb/>
 which needs to be mentioned in the matter of<lb/>
 implementation of the aforestated doctrine of &quot;level<lb/>
 playing field&quot;. According to Lord Goldsmith,<lb/>
 commitment to the &quot;rule of law&quot; is the heart of<lb/>
 parliamentary democracy. One of the important<lb/>
 elements of the &quot;rule of law&quot; is legal certainty.<lb/>
 Article 14 applies to government policies and if the<lb/>
 policy or act of the Government, even in contractual<lb/>
 matters, fails to satisfy the test of &quot;reasonableness&quot;,<lb/>
 then such an act or decision would be<lb/>
 unconstitutional.<lb/>
 ....<lb/>
</item>

<item>38. When tenders are invited, the terms and<lb/>
 conditions must indicate with legal certainty,<lb/>
 norms and benchmarks. This &quot;legal certainty&quot;<lb/>
 is an important aspect of the rule of law. If<lb/>
 there is vagueness or subjectivity in the said<lb/>
 norms<lb/>
 it<lb/>
 may<lb/>
 result<lb/>
 in<lb/>
 unequal<lb/>
 and<lb/>
 discriminatory treatment. It may violate<lb/>
 doctrine of &quot;level playing field&quot;.<lb/>
</item>

<item>39. In Reliance Airport Developers (P) Ltd. v.<lb/>
 Airports Authority of India, [(2006) 10 SCC 1] the<lb/>
 Division Bench of this Court has held that in matters<lb/>
 of judicial review the basic test is to see whether<lb/>
 there is any infirmity in the decision-making process<lb/>
 and not in the decision itself. This means that the<lb/>
 decision-maker must understand correctly the law<lb/>
 that regulates his decision-making power and he<lb/>
 must give effect to it otherwise it may result in<lb/>
 illegality. The principle of &quot;judicial review&quot;<lb/>
 cannot be denied even in contractual matters<lb/>
 or matters in which the Government exercises<lb/>
 its contractual powers, but judicial review is<lb/>
 intended to prevent arbitrariness and it must<lb/>
 be exercised in larger public interest.<lb/>
 Expression of different views and opinions in<lb/>
 exercise of contractual powers may be there,<lb/>
 however, such difference of opinion must be<lb/>
 based on specified norms. Those norms may be<lb/>
 legal norms or accounting norms. As long as the<lb/>
 norms are clear and properly understood by the<lb/>
 decision-maker<lb/>
 and the<lb/>
 bidders<lb/>
 and other<lb/>
 stakeholders, uncertainty and thereby breach of the<lb/>
 rule of law will not arise. The grounds upon which<lb/>
 administrative action is subjected to control by<lb/>
 judicial review are classifiable broadly under<lb/>
 three heads, namely, illegality, irrationality<lb/>
 and procedural impropriety. In the said judgment<lb/>
 it has been held that all errors of law are<lb/>
 jurisdictional errors. One of the important principles<lb/>
 laid down in the aforesaid judgment is that<lb/>
 whenever a norm/benchmark is prescribed in the<lb/>
 tender process in order to provide certainty that<lb/>
 norm/standard should be clear. As stated above<lb/>
 &quot;certainty&quot; is an important aspect of the rule of law.<lb/>
 In Reliance Airport Developers[(2006) 10 SCC 1] the<lb/>
 scoring system formed part of the evaluation<lb/>
 process. The object of that system was to provide<lb/>
 identification of factors, allocation of marks of each<lb/>
 of the said factors and giving of marks at different<lb/>
 stages. Objectivity was thus provided.&quot;<lb/>
 (emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</item>

<p>5.4. The learned Single Judge while passing orders in the<lb/>
 earlier writ petition in W.P.No.19247 of 2014, and subsequently<lb/>
 the Division Bench while disposing of W.P.No.19247 of 2014<lb/>
 and W.A.No.1065 of 2014 gave opportunity to the appellant to<lb/>
 send representation and additional particulars/documents.<lb/>
 Accordingly, representation was sent highlighting the issues<lb/>
 that require to be considered and in spite of it, the order<lb/>
 passed by the TANGEDCO is bereft of reasons. Highlighting<lb/>
 the plea that reasons have to be reflected in the impugned<lb/>
 order, reliance is placed on a decision of this Court in Hasbi<lb/>
 Traders v. The Chief Engineer (Distribution), TNEB, (Judgment<lb/>
 dated 18.11.2008 made in W.A.No.2059 of 2004), wherein it is<lb/>
 held as under:<lb/>
 &quot;</p>

<item>4. The Tamil Nadu Electricity Board is a public<lb/>
 authority and even in contractual matters, it<lb/>
 cannot have an unfettered discretion and in<lb/>
 contracts having commercial element even<lb/>
 though some extra discretion is to be conceded<lb/>
 in such authority, it is bound to follow the<lb/>
 norms recognised by courts while dealing with<lb/>
 public property. This requirement is necessary<lb/>
 to avoid unreasonable and arbitrary decisions<lb/>
 being taken by public authorities whose<lb/>
 actions are amenable to judicial review. Clause<lb/>
 5(b) of the tender specification empowers the Tamil<lb/>
 Nadu Electricity Board to reject any or all the<lb/>
 tenders without assigning any reasons there of<lb/>
 whatsoever. Even though such discretion is given to<lb/>
 the authorities, whether it could be exercised in an<lb/>
 arbitrary manner is a question to be further<lb/>
 considered. In R.D.Shetty v. International Airport<lb/>
 Authority of India, (1979) 3 SCC 489 as well as in<lb/>
 Ajay Hasia v. Khalid Mujib Sehravardi, (1981) 1 SCC<lb/>
 722, the Supreme Court has held that an<lb/>
 instrumentality of the State should act within<lb/>
 the ambit of Rule of Law and would not be<lb/>
 allowed to conduct itself arbitrarily and in its<lb/>
 dealings with the public would be liable to<lb/>
 judicial review.<lb/>
</item>

<item>5. In fact the very same question as to whether this<lb/>
 Court would be justified in interfering with such<lb/>
 orders of rejection of tender without any reason<lb/>
 came up for consideration before the Supreme Court<lb/>
 in M/s Star Enterprises and others v. City and<lb/>
 Industrial Development Corporation of Maharashtra<lb/>
 Ltd.and others, (1990) 3 SCC 280 and in paragraph-<lb/>
9, the Supreme Court has held as follows:-<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;The question which still remains to be<lb/>
 answered is as to whether when the highest<lb/>
 offer in response to an invitation is rejected,<lb/>
 would not the public authority be required to<lb/>
 provide reasons for such action? Mr.Dwivedi<lb/>
 has not asked us to look for a reasoned<lb/>
 decision but has submitted that it is in the<lb/>
 interest of the public authority itself, the<lb/>
 State and everyone in the society at large<lb/>
 that reasons for State action are placed on<lb/>
 record and are even communicated to the<lb/>
 persons from whom the offers came so that<lb/>
 the dealings remain above board; the<lb/>
 interest of the public authority is adequately<lb/>
 protected and a citizen knows where he<lb/>
 stands with reference to his offer.&quot;<lb/>
 In the very same judgment, as to the power of<lb/>
 judicial review of administrative action, the Supreme<lb/>
 Court has held as follows:-<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;In recent times, judicial review of<lb/>
 administrative<lb/>
 action<lb/>
 has<lb/>
 become<lb/>
 expansive and is becoming wider day<lb/>
 by day. The traditional limitations have<lb/>
 been vanishing and the sphere of<lb/>
 judicial scrutiny is being expanded.<lb/>
</item>

<item>
 State activity too is becoming fast<lb/>
 pervasive. As the State has descended<lb/>
 into the commercial field and giant<lb/>
 public sector undertakings have grown<lb/>
 up, the stake of the public exchequer is<lb/>
 also large justifying larger social audit,<lb/>
 judicial control and review by opening<lb/>
 of the public gaze; these necessitate<lb/>
 recording of reasons for executive<lb/>
 actions including cases of rejection of<lb/>
 highest offers. That very often involves<lb/>
 large stakes and availability of reasons<lb/>
 for actions on the record assures<lb/>
 credibility to the action; disciplines<lb/>
 public conduct and improves the<lb/>
 culture of accountability. Looking for<lb/>
 reasons in support of such action<lb/>
 provides<lb/>
 an<lb/>
 opportunity<lb/>
 for<lb/>
 an<lb/>
 objective review in appropriate cases<lb/>
 both by the administrative superior and<lb/>
 by the judicial process.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>6. Mr.P.Srinivas, learned counsel appearing for the<lb/>
 Tamil Nadu Electricity Board, however, would submit<lb/>
 that though the order dated 21.2.2004 had not<lb/>
 assigned any reason for not accepting the tender,<lb/>
 pursuant to the notice issued by the very same<lb/>
 appellant dated 28.2.2004, a reply was sent to him<lb/>
 on 5.3.2004 stating that the tenders have not been<lb/>
 approved by the tender committee as the market<lb/>
 rate was higher than the rate offered by the<lb/>
 tenderers.<lb/>
 Hence<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 appellant<lb/>
 had<lb/>
 been<lb/>
 communicated with the reasons which would satisfy<lb/>
 the act of the authority as to its fairness. We are not<lb/>
 inclined to accept the said submission as the order<lb/>
 impugned before this Court should be judged with<lb/>
 reference to the contents of the order. The Tamil<lb/>
 Nadu Electricity Board is not entitled to withdraw its<lb/>
 case later on after the orders were passed. That<lb/>
 apart, by a subsequent order dated 5.3.2004,<lb/>
 though the respondent-Board had taken the stand<lb/>
 that the tender of the appellant was not accepted as<lb/>
 the same was not approved by the tender committee<lb/>
 as the market rate was higher than the rate offered<lb/>
 by the tenderers, in the counter affidavit it takes<lb/>
 entirely a new stand for not accepting the tender of<lb/>
 the appellant. In paragraph-4 of the counter<lb/>
 affidavit, it is stated that contrary to clause 6(e) of<lb/>
 the tender specification in quoting separate amount<lb/>
 for four lots, namely, lot nos.5, 9, 13 &amp; 14, the<lb/>
 appellant had quoted a lumpsum of Rs.22,10,000/-<lb/>
for all the four lots, which is in violation of the<lb/>
 tender specification. From the above two different<lb/>
 stand taken by the respondent-Board, it appears to<lb/>
 us that even the respondents were not confident of<lb/>
 the reasons for which the tender of the appellant<lb/>
 was not accepted and the same was communicated<lb/>
 by the letter dated 21.2.2004. Further the counter<lb/>
 affidavit cannot supplement the reasons as held by<lb/>
 the Supreme Court in Mohinder Singh Gill v. Chief<lb/>
 Election Commissioner, AIR 1978 SC 851. In<lb/>
 paragraph-8 of the said judgment, the Supreme<lb/>
 Court has observed that &quot;the validity of an order<lb/>
 must be judged by the reasons so mentioned<lb/>
 and the order cannot be supplemented by<lb/>
 fresh reasons in the shape of affidavit or<lb/>
 otherwise.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>Hence the reliance placed by Mr.P.Srinivas, learned<lb/>
 counsel for the respondent-Board that the reasons<lb/>
 for the rejection were communicated to the<lb/>
 appellant subsequently cannot cure the defect in<lb/>
 respect of the violation of Article 14 of the<lb/>
 Constitution of India.&quot;<lb/>
 (emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</item>

<p>5.5. In any event, it is pleaded that while awarding<lb/>
 tenders, the comparative merits of bidders, i.e., past<lb/>
 performance and vendor rating, have to be assessed and<lb/>
 guidelines should be framed. In support of such plea, reliance<lb/>
 is placed on the decision of the Supreme Court in Manohar Lal<lb/>
 Sharma v. The Principal Secretary and Others, 2014 (9) SCALE<lb/>
 693, wherein it is held as under:<lb/>
</p><item>
 &quot;132 Significantly, the guidelines framed and applied<lb/>
 by the Screening Committee for the period from<lb/>
 14.07.1993 (1st meeting) to 19.8.2003 (21st<lb/>
 meeting) are conspicuously silent about inter se<lb/>
 priority between the applicants for the same block.<lb/>
 In the 18th meeting, the Screening Committee<lb/>
 considered the issue of determining inter se merit of<lb/>
 applicants for the same block as well as certain other<lb/>
 issues for bringing in transparency. The Screening<lb/>
 Committee felt that guidelines for determining inter<lb/>
 se priority among claims for block between public<lb/>
 sector and private sector for captive use and<lb/>
 between public sector for non-captive use and<lb/>
 private sector for captive use need to be evolved.<lb/>
 However, no guidelines for determining inter se<lb/>
 priority of applicants for the same block was<lb/>
 evolved. The guidelines also do not contain any<lb/>
 objective criterion for determining the merits<lb/>
 of applicants and lack in healthy competition<lb/>
 and equitable treatment. In the first counter<lb/>
 affidavit filed by the Central Government, it is<lb/>
 admitted that from the 1st meeting (held on<lb/>
 14.07.1993) to the 21st Meeting (held on<lb/>
 19.08.2003), the guidelines did not deal with the<lb/>
 subject of determining inter se priority between<lb/>
 applicants.<lb/>
 .....<lb/>
</item>

<item>151. The entire exercise of allocation through<lb/>
 Screening Committee route thus appears to suffer<lb/>
 from the vice of arbitrariness and not following any<lb/>
 objective criteria in determining as to who is to be<lb/>
 selected or who is not to be selected. There is no<lb/>
 evaluation of merit and no inter se comparison of<lb/>
 the applicants. No chart of evaluation was prepared.<lb/>
 The determination of the Screening Committee is<lb/>
 apparently subjective as the minutes of the<lb/>
 Screening Committee meetings do not show that<lb/>
 selection was made after proper assessment. The<lb/>
 project preparedness, track record etc., of the<lb/>
 applicant company were not objectively kept in<lb/>
 view. Until the amendment was brought in Section<lb/>
 3(3) of the CMN Act w.e.f. 09.06.1993, the Central<lb/>
 Government alone was permitted to mine coal<lb/>
 through its companies with the limited exception of<lb/>
 private companies engaged in the production of iron<lb/>
 and steel. By virtue of the bar contained in Section<lb/>
 3(3) of the CMN Act, between 1976 and 1993, no<lb/>
 private company (other than the company engaged<lb/>
 in the production of iron and steel) could have<lb/>
 carried out coal mining operations in India. Section<lb/>
 3(3) of the CMN Act, which was amended on<lb/>
 09.06.1993 permitted private sector entry in coal<lb/>
 mining operations for captive use. The power for<lb/>
 grant of captive coal block is governed by Section<lb/>
 3(3)(a) of the CMN Act, according to which, only two<lb/>
 kind of entities, namely, (a) Central Government or<lb/>
 undertakings/corporations owned by the Central<lb/>
 Government; or (b) companies having end-use<lb/>
 plants in iron and steel, power, washing of coal or<lb/>
 cement can carry out coal mining operations. The<lb/>
 expression &quot;engaged in&quot; in Section 3(3)(a)(iii)<lb/>
 means that the company that was applying for the<lb/>
 coal block must have set up an iron and steel plant,<lb/>
 power plant or cement plant and be engaged in the<lb/>
 production of steel, power or cement. The<lb/>
 prospective engagement by a private company in<lb/>
 the production of steel, power or cement would not<lb/>
 entitle such private company to carry out coal<lb/>
 mining operation. Most of the companies, which<lb/>
 have been allocated coal blocks, were not engaged<lb/>
 in the production of steel, power or cement at the<lb/>
 time of allocation nor in the applications made by<lb/>
 them any disclosure was made whether or not the<lb/>
 power, steel or cement plant was operational. They<lb/>
 only stated that they proposed to set up such plants.<lb/>
 Thus, the requirement of end-use project was not<lb/>
 met at the time of allocation.<lb/>
 ....<lb/>
</item>

<item>154. To sum up, the entire allocation of coal block as<lb/>
 per recommendations made by the Screening<lb/>
 Committee from 14.07.1993 in 36 meetings and the<lb/>
 allocation through the Government dispensation<lb/>
 route suffers from the vice of arbitrariness and legal<lb/>
 flaws. The Screening Committee has never been<lb/>
 consistent, it has not been transparent, there is no<lb/>
 proper application of mind, it has acted on no<lb/>
 material in many cases, relevant factors have<lb/>
 seldom been its guiding factors, there was no<lb/>
 transparency and guidelines have seldom guided it.<lb/>
 On many occasions, guidelines have been honoured<lb/>
 more in their breach. There was no objective<lb/>
 criteria, nay, no criteria for evaluation of<lb/>
 comparative merits. The approach had been ad-hoc<lb/>
 and casual. There was no fair and transparent<lb/>
 procedure, all resulting in unfair distribution of the<lb/>
 national wealth. Common good and public interest<lb/>
 have, thus, suffered heavily. Hence, the allocation of<lb/>
 coal blocks based on the recommendations made in<lb/>
 all the 36 meetings of the Screening Committee is<lb/>
 illegal.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>(emphasis supplied)<lb/></p><p>
 Placing strong reliance on the above said decision, it is pleaded<lb/>
 that the procedure adopted must be fair and transparent;<lb/>
 there should be guidelines; there should be objective criteria<lb/>
 for evaluation of comparative merits; and application of mind.<lb/>
</p>

<p>5.6. On the issue as to how vendor rating should be<lb/>
 assessed, reliance is placed on the decision of the Delhi High<lb/>
 Court in Telephone Cables Ltd. v. Bharat Sanchar Nigam<lb/>
 Limited and Others, (2004) 112 DLT 112 (DB), wherein it<lb/>
 is held as under:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;4. Thus, this petition is to be decided on the simple<lb/>
 issue as to whether it was permissible for the BSNL,<lb/>
 under the Tender Conditions, to alter the Delivery<lb/>
 Rating of the tenderers after the date of opening of<lb/>
 the tender, i.e 22.5.2001 and, if so, to what extent?<lb/>
</item>

<item>In order to arrive at an answer, it would be<lb/>
 necessary to refer to certain clauses of the Special<lb/>
 Conditions of Contract pertaining to the tender in<lb/>
 question. We need to note Clauses 13(i), 13(ii),<lb/>
 Clauses 19, 19.3.8 and Clause 22(d). The aforesaid<lb/>
 clauses are set out hereinbelow:<lb/>
 &quot;13(i). The purchaser intends to limit the<lb/>
 number of bidders selected for ordering against<lb/>
 this tender to 2/3rd of the participating and<lb/>
 eligible bidders in each group (eligible as per<lb/>
 Clause 2 of Section II of the Bid Documents).<lb/>
 The bidders for placement of order will be<lb/>
 selected from the list of technically and<lb/>
 commercially responsive bidders arranged in<lb/>
 decreasing order of the Vendor Rating starting<lb/>
 from the highest. Any fraction below 0.5 in the<lb/>
 number of vendors, as computed above shall be<lb/>
 ignored and the same equal and above 0.5 will<lb/>
 be rounded off to the next higher integer.<lb/>
 13(ii). The bidder with the highest Vendor<lb/>
 Rating (V-I bidder) will be considered for about<lb/>
 30% of his tendered quantity. The balance<lb/>
 quantity will be distributed amongst the<lb/>
 remaining selected bidders in each group in<lb/>
 direct ratio of their Vendor Rating.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;19. All the vendors will be rated as per the<lb/>
 following Vendor Rating formula.<lb/>
 VENDOR RATING (VR)=0.6 PR + 0.3 DR + 0.1<lb/>
 QR<lb/>
 Vendor PR=Price Rating.<lb/>
 DR=Delivery Rating<lb/>
 QR=Quality Rating.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;19.3.8 If the delay is caused due to<lb/>
 Departmental<lb/>
 reasons<lb/>
 as<lb/>
 certified<lb/>
 by<lb/>
 Competent<lb/>
 Authority<lb/>
 or<lb/>
 Force<lb/>
 Majeure<lb/>
 Conditions, it will not be taken into account in<lb/>
 computing delays in supply.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;22. Clarifications on VRS:<lb/>
</item>

<item>xxx<lb/>
 xxx<lb/>
</item>

<item>(d) Any modification obtained by supplier on his<lb/>
 request made after the date of NIT which are in<lb/>
 the nature of affecting the existing DR will not<lb/>
 be taken into account.<lb/>
</item>

<p>xxx&quot;<lb/>
 In the light of the said decision, it is submitted that the<lb/>
 provisions of TTIT Act as well as the guidelines issued by the<lb/>
 Central Vigilance Commission should be followed in letter and<lb/>
 spirit, more so in cases of this nature, where the value of work<lb/>
 involved is high and technical. In the case on hand, Clause<lb/>
 29.0 (viii) -Rejection of Bids states that the tender shall be<lb/>
 rejected<lb/>
 if<lb/>
 it<lb/>
 is<lb/>
 from<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 tenderer<lb/>
 whose<lb/>
 past<lb/>
 performance/vendor rating is not satisfactory, but there is no<lb/>
 formulae or guidelines formulated in this regard. This has lead<lb/>
 to arbitrariness in the tendering process, particularly<lb/>
 evaluation.<lb/>
</p>

<p>5.7. It is submitted that the partners of the appellant<lb/>
 consortium are world renowned companies and they have done<lb/>
 many projects worldwide. In support of the said plea, End-<lb/>
User Certificates were also produced.<lb/>
</p>

<p>5.8. Inviting our attention to paragraph (51) of the order<lb/>
 passed by the learned Single Judge, wherein it is recorded as<lb/>
 under:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;51. I have carefully considered the above<lb/>
 submissions. It is true that in the previous writ<lb/>
 petition, the first respondent took a stand that<lb/>
 the process of evaluation was still on. But it is<lb/>
 seen from the current files that the Consultant<lb/>
 appointed<lb/>
 by<lb/>
 TANGEDCO<lb/>
 had<lb/>
 already<lb/>
 submitted a report on 30.5.2014. As per this<lb/>
 report titled &quot;Price Evaluation Report&quot;, the<lb/>
 third respondent was identified as L1. ......... &quot;<lb/>
</item><p>
 it is contended that the Consultant&apos;s Report is erroneously<lb/>
 treated by the learned Single Judge as evaluation of L1 in<lb/>
 terms of Section 10(1) and 10(2) of the TTIT Act. According<lb/>
 to the provisions of the TTIT Act, the Consultant is not<lb/>
 empowered to complete the evaluation and he can at the best<lb/>
 make recommendation. However, in the case on hand, since<lb/>
 opportunity was given to the third respondent to reduce<lb/>
 interest after the Consultant&apos;s Report, it is quite obvious that<lb/>
 the Consultant is treated as tender accepting authority,<lb/>
 whereas the first respondent took a stand before the Court in<lb/>
 the preceding paragraphs that the process of evaluation was<lb/>
 still on, which shows that the tender evaluation process is<lb/>
 vitiated by non observance of the TTIT Act and TTIT Rules.<lb/>
 Besides, the whole exercise is illegal and arbitrary and suffers<lb/>
 from procedural impropriety.<lb/>
</p>

<p>5.9. With regard to the report of the Consultant, who has<lb/>
 loaded on the appellant an upfront fee of Rs.801.18 Crores and<lb/>
 only Rs.8.925 Crores for the third respondent, it is pleaded<lb/>
 that out of the said sum of Rs.801.18 Crores, there is no<lb/>
 dispute about the management fee and guarantee fee, which<lb/>
 amounts to Rs.489.136 Crores.<lb/>
 The Commitment fee of<lb/>
 Rs.156.184 Crores, besides the Interest During Construction<lb/>
 (IDC) on Financial Charges to the tune of Rs.127.613 Crores,<lb/>
 as included by the Consultant is perverse and unreasonable.<lb/>
 This has been deliberately misstated to load the cost on the<lb/>
 appellant&apos;s bid and tilt the balance in favour of the third<lb/>
 respondent. In support of the said pleading, they have filed a<lb/>
 brief memo on financials, which we extract as such:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;B. The Consultant has loaded on the Appellant<lb/>
 an upfront fee (including interest) of Rs.801.18<lb/>
 Crores (See page 1298, Vol.III). The said figure<lb/>
 of Rs.801.18 Crores consists of the following<lb/>
 components:<lb/>
</item>

<item>a.<lb/>
 Guarantee Fee<lb/>
 :<lb/>
 Rs.371.743 Crores<lb/>
 b.<lb/>
 Management Fee<lb/>
 :<lb/>
 Rs.117.393 Crores<lb/>
 c.<lb/>
 Commitment Fee<lb/>
 :<lb/>
 Rs.156.184 Crores<lb/>
 (the above three components are termed as Financial<lb/>
 Charges)<lb/>
</item>

<item>d.<lb/>
 Interest for 36 months on<lb/>
 financial charges<lb/>
 :<lb/>
 Rs.127.613 Crores<lb/>
 e.<lb/>
 Moratorium interest (from :<lb/>
 Rs.28.247 Crores<lb/>
 financial charges<lb/>
 Rs.801.180 Crores<lb/>
 (Consultant had evaluated the bid of the<lb/>
 Appellant at 9207.264 Crores.)<lb/>
</item>

<item>If Commitment Fee and Interest on Management<lb/>
 Fee and Guarantee Fee are excluded and<lb/>
 accordingly the Moratorium Interest reduced to<lb/>
 17.875 Crores, the Consultant could have only<lb/>
 loaded Rs.489.136 Crores.<lb/>
</item>

<item>C. The Repayment Schedule submitted by the<lb/>
 Appellant for repayment (Principal and Interest)<lb/>
 by TANGEDCO on the loan is at page 616, Vol I<lb/>
 (See Clause 14.10, page 48, Vol I). The relevant<lb/>
 figures are:<lb/>
 Net Loan Amount<lb/>
 :<lb/>
 Rs.10012.9286/-<lb/>
which comprises of<lb/>
 a.<lb/>
 Loan amount (85% of Total<lb/>
 EPC Cost of 9709.3822<lb/>
 Crores)<lb/>
</item>

<item>:<lb/>
 Rs.8252.9748/-<lb/>
</item>

<item>b.<lb/>
 Interest<lb/>
 During<lb/>
 Construction for 36 months<lb/>
 on the loan amount<lb/>
 :<lb/>
 Rs.896.2032/-<lb/>
</item>

<item>c.<lb/>
 Guarantee Fee<lb/>
 :<lb/>
 Rs.392.0163/-<lb/>
d.<lb/>
 Management Fee<lb/>
 :<lb/>
 Rs.123.7946/-<lb/>
e.<lb/>
 Moratorium period interest<lb/>
 for 36 th to 42 nd month<lb/>
 :<lb/>
 Rs.347.9396/-<lb/>
Total<lb/>
 :<lb/>
 Rs.10012.9286/-<lb/>
The Net Loan Amount does not include<lb/>
 Commitment Fee or Interest on Management<lb/>
 and Guarantee Fee during the construction<lb/>
 period of 36 months.<lb/>
</item>

<item>
 A sum of Rs.5025.3628 Crores is the total<lb/>
 Interest payable on the above loan amount<lb/>
 calculated at 7.2% (mentioned at page 616,<lb/>
 Vol.I).<lb/>
</item>

<item>The total of the Principal (Rs.10012.928 Crores)<lb/>
 and<lb/>
 Interest<lb/>
 (Rs.5025.3628<lb/>
 Crores)<lb/>
 is<lb/>
 Rs.15038.2914 Crores.<lb/>
</item>

<item>On this basis, the EQI (Equated Quarterly<lb/>
 Installments) payable every quarter for 12 years<lb/>
 is Rs.313.2977 Crores.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(This figure would come down as the Repayment<lb/>
 Schedule was submitted by the Appellant for<lb/>
 9709.3822 Crores while the Consultant had<lb/>
 evaluated the bid of the Appellant at 9207.264<lb/>
 Crores (after disallowing Rs.508 Crores)).<lb/>
</item>

<item>D. If the Appellant&apos;s offer of reduction in interest<lb/>
 rate from 7.2% p.a. to 6.2% p.a. had been<lb/>
 accepted, TANGEDCO would have saved over<lb/>
 Rs.1300 Crores on Total Cost of Ownership<lb/>
 (TCO)<lb/>
 basis<lb/>
 (See<lb/>
 Representation<lb/>
 dated<lb/>
 16.6.2014 at page 628).<lb/>
 Actual savings would have been Rs.1562.512<lb/>
 Crores as per the comparative chart submitted<lb/>
 by the Appellant at page 1220, Vol.III.<lb/>
 This has not been disputed by any of the<lb/>
 Respondents.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>5.10. With regard to the observation of the learned Single<lb/>
 Judge that the appellant in effect wants the Court to work out<lb/>
 the financial aspects of the tender, it is pleaded that the<lb/>
 appellant never sought for working out the financial aspects<lb/>
 and what has been prayed for is to see whether the relevant<lb/>
 factors have been properly considered and applied and eschew<lb/>
 irrelevant factors.<lb/>
</p>

<p>5.11. Qua the binding effect of the report of the<lb/>
 Comptroller and Auditor General which was produced by the<lb/>
 Appellant questioning the virtues of BHEL, reliance was placed<lb/>
 on the decision of the Supreme Court in Arun Kumar Agrawal<lb/>
 v. Union of India and others, (2013) 7 SCC 1, wherein it was<lb/>
 held as under:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;67. The question that is germane for consideration<lb/>
 in this case is whether this Court can grant reliefs by<lb/>
 merely placing reliance on the CAG&apos;s Report. The<lb/>
 CAG&apos;s Report is always subject to parliamentary<lb/>
 debates and it is possible that PAC can accept the<lb/>
 ministry&apos;s objection to the CAG Report or reject the<lb/>
 report of the CAG. The CAG, indisputably is an<lb/>
 independent constitutional functionary, however, it is<lb/>
 for Parliament to decide whether after receiving the<lb/>
 report i.e. PAC to make its comments on the CAG&apos;s<lb/>
 Report.<lb/>
</item>

<item>68. We may, however, point out that since the<lb/>
 report is from a constitutional functionary, it<lb/>
 commands respect and cannot be brushed<lb/>
 aside as such, but it is equally important to<lb/>
 examine the comments what respective<lb/>
 Ministries have to offer on the CAG&apos;s Report.<lb/>
 The Ministry can always point out, if there is<lb/>
 any mistake in the CAG&apos;s report or the CAG has<lb/>
 inappropriately appreciated the various issues.<lb/>
 For instance, we cannot as such accept the CAG<lb/>
 report in the instance case.&quot;<lb/>
 (emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</item>

<p>It is pleaded that since the report is from a Constitutional<lb/>
 Functionary, it cannot be brushed aside as such.<lb/>
</p>

<p>5.12. In effect, it is pleaded that non-consideration of all<lb/>
 the above vital factors fortifies their plea of arbitrariness in the<lb/>
 tender process.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(C) RATE OF INTEREST AND PUBLIC INTEREST<lb/>
 (NON CONSIDERATION)<lb/>
</p>

<p>6.1. It is the specific plea of the appellant that even<lb/>
 though they originally offered interest at 7.2% per annum and<lb/>
 subsequently, on 5.6.2014, offered to reduce the same to<lb/>
 6.2% per annum, the respondents 1 and 2, without assigning<lb/>
 any reasons, accepted the tender of the third respondent, who<lb/>
 agreed for interest reduction from 12.25% to 12.15% later<lb/>
 on, i.e., 27.6.2014. It is pleaded that on this score alone, the<lb/>
 first respondent would have been benefited with a savings of<lb/>
 over Rs.1300 Crores had he accepted the offer made by the<lb/>
 appellant. This reduction of interest is in larger public interest.<lb/>
</p>

<p>6.2. In support of the plea that the decision taken by the<lb/>
 respondents must be free from arbitrariness and favouritism<lb/>
 and must be in public interest, reliance is placed on a decision<lb/>
 of a Division Bench of the Bombay High Court in B.Himmatlal<lb/>
 Agrawal and another v. Western Coalfields Limited and Others,<lb/>
 2006 SCC Online Bom 887, wherein it is held as under:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;27. It is no doubt true that right to choose a<lb/>
 bidder as per conditions and procedure<lb/>
 stipulated in the tender document is of the<lb/>
 Authority/Tender Committee and the Court<lb/>
 does not sit in appeal on the decision taken by<lb/>
 the Authority in this regard. Nevertheless such<lb/>
 decision must be free from arbitrariness and<lb/>
 favouritism, must be in the public interest and<lb/>
 must be taken by the Tender Committee after<lb/>
 proper application of mind. The decision taken by<lb/>
 the Tender Committee, in view of mandatory<lb/>
 condition 3.5(b), therefore, must demonstrate that<lb/>
 the Tender Committee has applied its mind to the<lb/>
 contingencies mentioned in the said condition and on<lb/>
 the basis thereof, has considered performance of<lb/>
 work executed by the bidder on the earlier occasion<lb/>
 and it must show that it is only thereafter the Tender<lb/>
 Committee<lb/>
 has<lb/>
 concluded<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 issue<lb/>
 of<lb/>
 disqualification. If the decision of the Tender<lb/>
 Committee is silent on these aspects, such decision,<lb/>
 in our view, undoubtedly would be arbitrary, unjust<lb/>
 and no amount of explanation given in the affidavit<lb/>
 filed on behalf of the Authority can legitimise such<lb/>
 decision, which does not show proper application of<lb/>
 mind by the Tender Committee as required in view<lb/>
 of essential conditions of tender. It is the decision,<lb/>
 which must show that same is taken by the Tender<lb/>
 Committee after proper application of mind and such<lb/>
 inference cannot be drawn on the basis of<lb/>
 explanation or justification given by the Authority in<lb/>
 the affidavits filed in the Court.&quot;<lb/>
 (emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</item>

<p>6.2. It is contended that even for awarding the contract<lb/>
 in favour of the third respondent-BHEL, the respondents must<lb/>
 be satisfied that it is in public interest. In support of the said<lb/>
 plea, reliance was placed on the decision in Bharat Biotech<lb/>
 International Ltd. v. Directorate of Medical Education and<lb/>
 Research and others, 2010 SCC OnLine Bom 1845, wherein, a<lb/>
 Division Bench of the Bombay High Court held as under:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;17. There is merit in the submission that the<lb/>
 entire tendering process has suffered from a clear<lb/>
 case of arbitrariness. Tenders were specifically<lb/>
 invited with reference to the Government Resolution<lb/>
 dated 27 March, 2000. A public body when it invites<lb/>
 tenders is duty bound to comply with the terms of<lb/>
 the tender and by the norms of fairness that Article<lb/>
 14 of the Constitution embodies. When the Tender<lb/>
 Approval Committee holds that a bidder is<lb/>
 disqualified, it is totally arbitrary then to proceed to<lb/>
 award contract to that very bidder on the ground<lb/>
 that other bidders have not matched the commercial<lb/>
 bid of a disqualified bidder. Once a bid is disqualified,<lb/>
 the bid in its entirety has to be kept aside and no<lb/>
 part of that bid can be utilized for evaluating the<lb/>
 merits of the other bidders. Once a bid is<lb/>
 disqualified, it is impossible to conceive how a<lb/>
 contract can be awarded to that very party on the<lb/>
 basis that the commercial bid quoted by it is the<lb/>
 lowest and the other bidders have not matched the<lb/>
 bid. The question of comparing commercial bids<lb/>
 arises between bidders similarly circumstanced, that<lb/>
 is to say, between bidders who meet the<lb/>
 requirement of technical eligibility. Bidders who meet<lb/>
 eligibility requirements are not equal to bidders who<lb/>
 are disqualified and do not stand on the same basis<lb/>
 as bidders who are eligible. To equate them is to<lb/>
 treat unequals equally: something that is forbidden<lb/>
 by Article 14 of the Constitution. As a matter of fact,<lb/>
 the committee, as we have already noted, has not<lb/>
 even come to the conclusion that the decision to<lb/>
 disqualify the second respondent was erroneous or<lb/>
 that the second respondent was not a defaulter.<lb/>
</item>

<item>18. In W.B. State Electricity Board v. Patel<lb/>
 Engineering Co. Ltd., (2001) 2 SCC 451 the<lb/>
 Supreme Court applied the principles, and observed<lb/>
 as follows:<lb/>
</item>

<item>&apos;The contract is, therefore, awarded<lb/>
 normally to the lowest tenderer which<lb/>
 is in public interest. The principle of<lb/>
 awarding contract to the lowest<lb/>
 tenderer applies when all things are<lb/>
 equal. It is equally in public interest to<lb/>
 adhere to the rules and conditions<lb/>
 subject to which bids are invited.<lb/>
 Merely because a bid is the lowest the<lb/>
 requirements of compliance with the<lb/>
 rules<lb/>
 and<lb/>
 conditions<lb/>
 cannot<lb/>
 be<lb/>
 ignored.&apos;&quot;<lb/>
 (emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</item>

<p>6.3. With regard to the power of the Court to interfere in<lb/>
 tender or contractual matter, reliance was placed on a decision<lb/>
 of the Supreme Court in Jagdish Mandal v. State of Orissa,<lb/>
 (2007) 14 SCC 517, wherein it is held as under:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;24. Therefore, a court before interfering in tender<lb/>
 or contractual matters, in exercise of power of<lb/>
 judicial review, should pose to itself the following<lb/>
 questions:<lb/>
</item>

<item>(i) Whether the process adopted or decision<lb/>
 made by the authority is mala fide or intended<lb/>
 to favour someone; or whether the process<lb/>
 adopted or decision made is so arbitrary and<lb/>
 irrational that the court can say: &quot;the decision<lb/>
 is such that no responsible authority acting<lb/>
 reasonably and in accordance with relevant<lb/>
 law could have reached&quot;? and<lb/>
</item>

<item>(ii) Whether the public interest is affected?<lb/>
</item>

<item>If the answers to the above questions are in<lb/>
 the negative, then there should be no<lb/>
 interference under Article 226.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>(emphasis supplied)<lb/></p><p>
 In the case on hand, it is contended that when lack of public<lb/>
 interest has been paraded, the learned Single Judge has<lb/>
 rejected the same.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(D) FILE NOTINGS:<lb/>
</p>

<p>7. With regard to the value of file notings and jottings, on<lb/>
 which heavy reliance was placed by the learned Single Judge,<lb/>
 it is pleaded that such file notings and jottings are not a final<lb/>
 decision and they are merely expressions of opinion of the<lb/>
 individual and what the Court should consider is the validity of<lb/>
 the ultimate order passed, that is under challenge. In the case<lb/>
 on hand, the Consultant&apos;s Report is the opinion of an individual<lb/>
 and nothing transcribes into an actionable order.<lb/>
 To<lb/>
 substantiate the said plea, reliance is placed on the decision of<lb/>
 the Supreme Court in Shanti Sports Club v. Union of India,<lb/>
 (2009) 15 SCC 705, wherein it is held as under:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;41. The issue deserves to be considered from<lb/>
 another angle. All executive actions of the<lb/>
 Government of India and the Government of a State<lb/>
 are required to be taken in the name of the<lb/>
 President or the Governor of the State concerned, as<lb/>
 the case may be [Articles 77(1) and 166(1)]. Orders<lb/>
 and other instruments made and executed in the<lb/>
 name of the President or the Governor of a State, as<lb/>
 the case may be, are required to be authenticated in<lb/>
 such manner as may be specified in rules to be<lb/>
 made by the President or the Governor, as the case<lb/>
 may be [Articles 77(2) and 166(2)]. Article 77(3)<lb/>
 lays down that:<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;77. (3) The President shall make rules for<lb/>
 the more convenient transaction of the<lb/>
 business of the Government of India, and<lb/>
 for the allocation among Ministers of the<lb/>
 said business.&quot;<lb/>
 Likewise, Article 166(3) lays down that:<lb/>
 166. (3) The Governor shall make rules for<lb/>
 the more convenient transaction of the<lb/>
 business of the Government of the State,<lb/>
 and for the allocation among Ministers of the<lb/>
 said business insofar as it is not business<lb/>
 with respect to which the Governor is by or<lb/>
 under this Constitution required to act in his<lb/>
 discretion.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>42. This means that unless an order is expressed in<lb/>
 the name of the President or the Governor and is<lb/>
 authenticated in the manner prescribed by the rules,<lb/>
 the same cannot be treated as an order on behalf of<lb/>
 the Government.<lb/>
</item>

<item>43. A noting recorded in the file is merely a noting<lb/>
 simpliciter and nothing more. It merely represents<lb/>
 expression of opinion by the particular individual. By<lb/>
 no stretch of imagination, such noting can be<lb/>
 treated as a decision of the Government. Even if the<lb/>
 competent authority records its opinion in the file on<lb/>
 the merits of the matter under consideration, the<lb/>
 same cannot be termed as a decision of the<lb/>
 Government unless it is sanctified and acted upon by<lb/>
 issuing an order in accordance with Articles 77(1)<lb/>
 and (2) or Articles 166(1) and (2). The noting in the<lb/>
 file or even a decision gets culminated into an order<lb/>
 affecting right of the parties only when it is<lb/>
 expressed in the name of the President or the<lb/>
 Governor, as the case may be, and authenticated in<lb/>
 the manner provided in Article 77(2) or Article<lb/>
 166(2). A noting or even a decision recorded in the<lb/>
 file can always be reviewed/reversed/overruled or<lb/>
 overturned and the court cannot take cognizance of<lb/>
 the earlier noting or decision for exercise of the<lb/>
 power of judicial review.<lb/>
</item>

<item>44. In State of Punjab v. Sodhi Sukhdev Singh [AIR<lb/>
 1961 SC 493] this Court considered the question<lb/>
 whether a provisional decision taken by the Council<lb/>
 of Ministers to reinstate an employee could be made<lb/>
 the basis for filing an action for issue of a mandamus<lb/>
 for reinstatement and held: (AIR p. 512, para 42)<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;42. … We are unable to understand this<lb/>
 argument. Even if the Council of Ministers<lb/>
 had provisionally decided to reinstate the<lb/>
 respondent that would not prevent the<lb/>
 Council from reconsidering the matter and<lb/>
 coming to a contrary conclusion later on,<lb/>
 until a final decision is reached by them and<lb/>
 is communicated to the Rajpramukh in the<lb/>
 form of advice and acted upon by him by<lb/>
 issuing an order in that behalf to the<lb/>
 respondent.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>45. A somewhat similar question was considered by<lb/>
 the Constitution Bench in Bachhittar Singh v. State<lb/>
 of Punjab [AIR 1963 SC 395 : 1962 Supp (3) SCR<lb/>
 713] in the backdrop of the argument that once the<lb/>
 Revenue Minister of PEPSU had recorded a note in the<lb/>
 file that the punishment imposed on the respondent<lb/>
 be reduced from dismissal to that of reversion, the<lb/>
 same could not be changed/reviewed/overruled by<lb/>
 the Chief Minister. This Court proceeded on the<lb/>
 assumption that the note recorded by the Revenue<lb/>
 Minister of PEPSU in the file was an order, referred to<lb/>
 the provisions of Article 166 of the Constitution and<lb/>
 held: (AIR p. 398, paras 9-11)<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;9. … Merely writing something on the<lb/>
 file does not amount to an order.<lb/>
 Before something amounts to an order<lb/>
 of the State Government two things are<lb/>
 necessary. The order has to be expressed<lb/>
 in the name of the Governor as required by<lb/>
 clause (1) of Article 166 and then it has to<lb/>
 be communicated. As already indicated, no<lb/>
 formal order modifying the decision of the<lb/>
 Revenue Secretary was ever made. Until<lb/>
 such an order is drawn up the State<lb/>
 Government cannot, in our opinion, be<lb/>
 regarded as bound by what was stated in<lb/>
 the file. As along as the matter rested with<lb/>
 him the Revenue Minister could well score<lb/>
 out his remarks or minutes on the file and<lb/>
 write fresh ones.<lb/>
</item>

<item>10. The business of State is a complicated<lb/>
 one and has necessarily to be conducted<lb/>
 through the agency of a large number of<lb/>
 officials and authorities. The Constitution,<lb/>
 therefore, requires and so did the Rules of<lb/>
 Business framed by the Rajpramukh of PEPSU<lb/>
 provide, that the action must be taken by<lb/>
 the authority concerned in the name of the<lb/>
 Rajpramukh. It is not till this formality is<lb/>
 observed that the action can be regarded as<lb/>
 that of the State or here, by the<lb/>
 Rajpramukh. We may further observe that,<lb/>
 constitutionally speaking, the Minister is no<lb/>
 more than an adviser and that the Head of<lb/>
 the State, the Governor or Rajpramukh (till<lb/>
 the abolition of that office by the<lb/>
 amendment of the Constitution in 1956), is<lb/>
 to act with the aid and advice of his Council<lb/>
 of Ministers. Therefore, until such advice is<lb/>
 accepted by the Governor whatever the<lb/>
 Minister or the Council of Ministers may say<lb/>
 in regard to a particular matter does not<lb/>
 become the action of the State until the<lb/>
 advice of the Council of Ministers is accepted<lb/>
 or deemed to be accepted by the Head of<lb/>
 the State. Indeed, it is possible that after<lb/>
 expressing one opinion about a particular<lb/>
 matter at a particular stage a Minister or the<lb/>
 Council of Ministers may express quite a<lb/>
 different opinion, one which may be<lb/>
 completely opposed to the earlier opinion.<lb/>
 Which of them can be regarded as the<lb/>
 &apos;order&apos; of the State Government? Therefore,<lb/>
 to make the opinion amount to a decision of<lb/>
 the Government it must be communicated<lb/>
 to the person concerned. In this connection<lb/>
 we may quote the following from the<lb/>
 judgment of this Court in State of Punjab v.<lb/>
 Sodhi Sukhdev Singh [AIR 1961 SC 493] :<lb/>
 (AIR p. 512, para 42)<lb/>
</item>

<item>&apos;42. … Mr Gopal Singh attempted to<lb/>
 argue that before the final order was<lb/>
 passed the Council of Ministers had<lb/>
 decided to accept the respondent&apos;s<lb/>
 representation and to reinstate him,<lb/>
 and that, according to him, the<lb/>
 respondent seeks to prove by calling<lb/>
 the two original orders. We are unable<lb/>
 to understand this argument. Even if<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 Council<lb/>
 of<lb/>
 Ministers<lb/>
 had<lb/>
 provisionally decided to reinstate the<lb/>
 respondent that would not prevent the<lb/>
 Council from reconsidering the matter<lb/>
 and coming to a contrary conclusion<lb/>
 later on, until a final decision is<lb/>
 reached by them and is communicated<lb/>
 to the Rajpramukh in the form of<lb/>
 advice and acted upon by him by<lb/>
 issuing an order in that behalf to the<lb/>
 respondent.&apos;<lb/>
 Thus it is of the essence that the order has<lb/>
 to be communicated to the person who<lb/>
 would be affected by that order before the<lb/>
 State and that person can be bound by that<lb/>
 order. For, until the order is communicated<lb/>
 to the person affected by it, it would be<lb/>
 open to the Council of Ministers to consider<lb/>
 the matter over and over again and,<lb/>
 therefore, till its communication the order<lb/>
 cannot be regarded as anything more than<lb/>
 provisional in character.<lb/>
</item>

<item>11. We are, therefore, of the opinion that<lb/>
 the remarks or the order of the Revenue<lb/>
 Minister, PEPSU are of no avail to the<lb/>
 appellant.&quot;<lb/>
 (emphasis added)<lb/>
</item>

<item>(E) ALTERNATIVE REMEDY:<lb/>
</item>

<p>8. With regard to the plea of the respondents that the<lb/>
 appellant has not availed the alternative remedy available<lb/>
 under Section 11 of the TTIT Act and has directly knocked the<lb/>
 doors of this Court, it is submitted that the appeal against the<lb/>
 order passed by respondents 1 and 2 lies to the Government<lb/>
 and since the Secretary to Government, Energy Department<lb/>
 will be the signatory to the said decision, the appeal will go<lb/>
 only from Caesar to Caesar. It was also pleaded that even<lb/>
 assuming, there is an appellate forum, it is not functioning as<lb/>
 on date and, therefore, there is no question of alternative<lb/>
 remedy. In this regard, reliance is placed on a decision of a<lb/>
 learned Single Judge of this Court in Consolidated Construction<lb/>
 Consortium Ltd. v. Tidel Park Coimbatore Ltd. And others,<lb/>
 2009-5-LW-858, wherein it is held as under:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;20. Therefore, even from the object of the Act, the<lb/>
 TTIT Act was enacted to prevent executive<lb/>
 interference and also to prevent recurrence of<lb/>
 irregularities by the procuring entity. It presupposes<lb/>
 that the Appeal that is contemplated under Section<lb/>
 11 of the TTIT Act can be filed by the tenderer<lb/>
 aggrieved by the order passed by the tender<lb/>
 accepting authority favouring one tenderer. It<lb/>
 impliedly means that any internecine dispute<lb/>
 between various tenderers can be referred to the<lb/>
 Government by way of an appeal and the<lb/>
 Government can decide the matter as it being the<lb/>
 controlling authority of all the schedule mentioned<lb/>
 organizations. The appellate authority has not been<lb/>
 clothed with any power of recording evidence nor<lb/>
 any power of civil court has been entrusted to the<lb/>
 Government when deciding an appeal.<lb/>
 21. In the present case, the dispute is between the<lb/>
 plaintiff and the first defendant company and it being<lb/>
 Government company, the Government cannot<lb/>
 decide such a dispute. Justice must not only be<lb/>
 done, but must be seen to be done. If allowed it can<lb/>
 be an appeal from caesar to caesar and law never<lb/>
 permits such a power for a Government, functioning<lb/>
 under a written Constitution. If the intention of the<lb/>
 TTIT Act is only to provide an appellate forum for<lb/>
 resolving disputes between various tenderers, who<lb/>
 had stake their claims, then the present dispute may<lb/>
 not come within its ambit.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>(emphasis supplied)<lb/></p><p>
 However, it is fairly conceded that since the learned Single<lb/>
 Judge went into the merits of the issue and the respondents<lb/>
 have not filed any appeal, this issue is not seriously canvassed<lb/>
 by them.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(F) ALLEGATION OF GAINING INSIDE INFORMATION:<lb/>
</p>

<p>9. With regard to the observation of the learned Single<lb/>
 Judge that the appellant gained inside information and only<lb/>
 thereafter made representations, it is contended that both the<lb/>
 appellant and the third respondent were visiting the<lb/>
 TANGEDCO office regularly and were discussing the formula as<lb/>
 to how evaluation should be done and that does not mean that<lb/>
 the appellant had gained inside information. In this regard, he<lb/>
 placed reliance on a decision of a learned Single Judge of this<lb/>
 Court in M.Ramalingam v. N.Thangavelu, 1997-2-LW-35,<lb/>
 wherein it is held as under:<lb/></p><p>
 &quot;14. In &apos;Estoppel by Representation&apos; -by Spencer<lb/>
 Bower and Turner-3rd Edition (First Indian Reprint<lb/>
 1994), in Chapter XII, at page 285, regarding<lb/>
 &apos;Encouragement or Acquiescence&apos;, the learned<lb/>
 authors have, after elaborating the case-law,<lb/>
 considered as to what is meant by &apos;acquiescence&apos;, as<lb/>
 understood in law. The relevant portion reads thus:<lb/>
 -<lb/></p><item>
&quot;Regarded in the light of &quot;acquiescence&quot;, the<lb/>
 essential elements of the form of estoppel<lb/>
 under consideration have been precisely and<lb/>
 lucidly stated by the Court of Appeal, in a<lb/>
 memorable judgment, as follows:-<lb/>
&quot;If a person having a right, and seeing<lb/>
 another person about to commit, or in<lb/>
 the course of committing, an act<lb/>
 infringing upon that right, stands by in<lb/>
 such a manner as really to induce the<lb/>
 person committing the act, and who<lb/>
 might otherwise have abstained from<lb/>
 it, to believe that he assents to its<lb/>
 being committed, he cannot afterwards<lb/>
 be heard to complain of the Act. This,<lb/>
 as Lord Cottenham said in the case<lb/>
 already cited, is the proper sense of the<lb/>
 term &apos;acquiescence&apos; and in that sense it<lb/>
 may be defined as acquiescence under<lb/>
 such circumstances as that assent may<lb/>
 be reasonably inferred from it, and is<lb/>
 no more than an instance of the law of<lb/>
 estoppel by words or conduct&quot;.<lb/>
</item>

<item>A good, though rather diffuse, statement of the rule,<lb/>
 in terms of &quot;encouragement&quot;, rather than of<lb/>
 &quot;acquiescence&quot;, is to be found in one of the<lb/>
 judgments pronounced by Lord Eldon, L.C:<lb/>
 &quot;this Court will not permit a man knowingly,<lb/>
 though but passively, to encourage another to<lb/>
 lay out money under an erroneous impression<lb/>
 of title; and the circumstance of looking on is in<lb/>
 many cases as strong as using terms of<lb/>
 encouragement;<lb/>
 a<lb/>
 lessor<lb/>
 knowing<lb/>
 and<lb/>
 permitting those acts which the lessee would<lb/>
 not have done, and the other must conceive he<lb/>
 would not have done, but upon an expectation<lb/>
 that the lessor would not throw an objection in<lb/>
 the way of his enjoyment. Still, it must be put<lb/>
 upon the party to prove that case by strong and<lb/>
 cogent evidence; leaving no reasonable doubt<lb/>
 that<lb/>
 he<lb/>
 acted<lb/>
 upon<lb/>
 that<lb/>
 sort<lb/>
 of<lb/>
 encouragement… In order to give a person a<lb/>
 larger interest in the property than he derives<lb/>
 under the instrument making his title, it must<lb/>
 be shown that with the knowledge of the person<lb/>
 under whom he claims, he conceived he had<lb/>
 that larger interest, and was putting himself to<lb/>
 a<lb/>
 considerable<lb/>
 expense,<lb/>
 un-reasonable<lb/>
 compared with the smaller interest; and which<lb/>
 the other party observed, and must have<lb/>
 supposed incurred under the idea that he<lb/>
 intended to give that larger interest, or to<lb/>
 refrain from disturbing the other in the<lb/>
 enjoyment&quot;.<lb/>
 Without using either the term &quot;acquiescence&quot; or the<lb/>
 term &quot;encouragement&quot;. Loard Cran Worth L.C stated<lb/>
 the necessary conditions of the kind of estoppel now<lb/>
 under consideration in the following terms.<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;If a stranger begins to build on my land,<lb/>
 supposing it to be his own, and I, perceiving his<lb/>
 mistake, abstain from setting him right, and,<lb/>
 leave him to persevere in his error, a court of<lb/>
 equity will not allow me afterwards to assert my<lb/>
 title to the land on which he had expended<lb/>
 money on the supposition that the land was his<lb/>
 own. It considers that, when I saw the mistake<lb/>
 into which he had fallen, it was my duty to be<lb/>
 active and to stage my adverse title; and that it<lb/>
 would be dishonest in me to remain wholly<lb/>
 impassive on such an occasion, in order<lb/>
 afterwards to profit by the mistake which I<lb/>
 might have prevented. But it will be observed<lb/>
 that, to raise such an equity, two things are<lb/>
 required, first, that the person expending his<lb/>
 money supposes himself to be building on his<lb/>
 own land; and, secondly, that the real owner at<lb/>
 the time of the expenditure knows that the land<lb/>
 belongs to him and not to the person expending<lb/>
 the money in the belief that he is the owner. For<lb/>
 if a stranger builds on my land, knowing it to be<lb/>
 mine, there is no principle of equity which<lb/>
 would prevent my claiming the land with the<lb/>
 benefit of all the expenditure made on it. There<lb/>
 would be nothing in my conduct, active or<lb/>
 passive, making it inequitable in me to assert<lb/>
 my legal rights. It follows are a corollary from<lb/>
 these rules, or, perhaps, it would be more<lb/>
 accurate to say that it forms part of them, that<lb/>
 if my tenant builds on land which he holds<lb/>
 under me, he does not thereby, in the absence<lb/>
 of special circumstances, acquire any right to<lb/>
 prevent me taking possession of the lands and<lb/>
 buildings when the tenancy has determined. He<lb/>
 knew the extent of his interest, and it was his<lb/>
 folly to expend money upon a title which he<lb/>
 knew he would or might soon come to an end.&quot;<lb/>
 Finally, in a passage which is always referred to in<lb/>
 this connection, and which, like the first of those<lb/>
 already cited, is not limited to encroachments on<lb/>
 land, but is framed with the utmost generality. Sir<lb/>
 Edward Fry deduced from the previous authorities in<lb/>
 his judgment in Willmott v. Barber, the following<lb/>
 condensed statement of the requisites of a good<lb/>
 case of acquiescence or encouragement. In the first<lb/>
 place, the plaintiff -in the case before him, the<lb/>
 person said to have been &quot;encouraged&quot; happened to<lb/>
 be the plaintiff -must have made a mistake as to<lb/>
 his legal rights. Secondly, the plaintiff must have<lb/>
 expended some money, or must have done some<lb/>
 act… on the faith of his mistaken belief. Thirdly, the<lb/>
 defendant, the possessor of the legal right, must<lb/>
 know of the existence of his own right which is<lb/>
 inconsistent with the right claimed by the plaintiff. If<lb/>
 he does not know of it, he is in the same position as<lb/>
 the plaintiff. Fourthly, the defendant, the possessor<lb/>
 of the legal right, must know of the plaintiff&apos;s<lb/>
 mistaken belief of his rights. If he does not, there is<lb/>
 nothing to call upon him to assert his own rights.<lb/>
 Lastly, the defendant, the possessor of the legal<lb/>
 right, must have encouraged the plaintiff in his<lb/>
 expenditure of money or in the other acts which he<lb/>
 has done, either directly or by abstaining from<lb/>
 asserting his legal rights.&quot;<lb/>
</item>
<p>
 CONTENTIONS MADE ON BEHALF OF TANGEDCO<lb/>
</p>
<p>10. Per contra, Mr.A.L.Somayaji, learned Advocate<lb/>
 General appearing on behalf of TANGEDCO, pleaded for<lb/>
 dismissal of the writ appeals and his submissions are recorded<lb/>
 under various heads in paragraphs hereunder.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(A) SCOPE OF JUDICIAL REVIEW:<lb/>
</p>

<p>11.1. At the outset, the learned Advocate General, while<lb/>
 emphasizing the scope of judicial review in contractual<lb/>
 matters, relied on the following decisions of the Supreme Court<lb/>
 and other High Courts:<lb/>
</p>

<p>(a) Maa Binda Express Carrier and another v. North-East<lb/>
 Frontier Railway and others, (2014) 3 SCC 760, wherein the<lb/>
 Supreme Court held as under:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;8. The scope of judicial review in matters relating to<lb/>
 award of contract by the State and its<lb/>
 instrumentalities is settled by a long line of decisions<lb/>
 of this Court. While these decisions clearly recognize<lb/>
 that power exercised by the Government and its<lb/>
 instrumentalities in regard to allotment of contract is<lb/>
 subject to judicial review at the instance of an<lb/>
 aggrieved party, submission of a tender in response<lb/>
 to a notice inviting such tenders is no more than<lb/>
 making an offer which the State or its agencies are<lb/>
 under no obligation to accept. The bidders<lb/>
 participating in the tender process cannot, therefore,<lb/>
 insist that their tenders should be accepted simply<lb/>
 because a given tender is the highest or lowest<lb/>
 depending upon whether the contract is for sale of<lb/>
 public property or for execution of works on behalf<lb/>
 of the Government. All that participating bidders are<lb/>
 entitled to is a fair, equal and non-discriminatory<lb/>
 treatment in the matter of evaluation of their<lb/>
 tenders. It is also fairly well-settled that award of a<lb/>
 contract is essentially a commercial transaction<lb/>
 which must be determined on the basis of<lb/>
 consideration that are relevant to such commercial<lb/>
 decision. This implies that terms subject to which<lb/>
 tenders are invited are not open to the judicial<lb/>
 scrutiny unless it is found that the same have been<lb/>
 tailor made to benefit any particular tenderer or<lb/>
 class of tenderers. So also the authority inviting<lb/>
 tenders can enter into negotiations or grant<lb/>
 relaxation for bona fide and cogent reasons provided<lb/>
 such relaxation is permissible under the terms<lb/>
 governing the tender process.<lb/>
</item>

<item>9. Suffice it to say that in the matter of award of<lb/>
 contracts the Government and its agencies have to<lb/>
 act reasonably and fairly at all points of time. To<lb/>
 that extent the tenderer has an enforceable right in<lb/>
 the Court who is competent to examine whether the<lb/>
 aggrieved party has been treated unfairly or<lb/>
 discriminated against to the detriment of public<lb/>
 interest. (See: Meerut Development Authority v.<lb/>
 Association of Management Studies and Anr. etc.<lb/>
 (2009) 6 SCC 171 and Air India Ltd. v. Cochin<lb/>
 International Airport Ltd. (2000) 1 SCR 505).<lb/>
</item>

<item>10. The scope of judicial review in contractual<lb/>
 matters was further examined by this Court in Tata<lb/>
 Cellular v. Union of India, (1994) 6 SCC 651,<lb/>
 Raunaq International Ltd.&apos;s case (supra) and in<lb/>
 Jagdish Mandal v. State of Orissa and Ors. (2007)<lb/>
 14 SCC 517 besides several other decisions to which<lb/>
 we need not refer. In Michigan Rubber (India) Ltd. v.<lb/>
 State of Karnataka and Ors., (2012) 8 SCC 216, the<lb/>
 legal position on the subject was summed up after a<lb/>
 comprehensive review and principles of law<lb/>
 applicable to the process for judicial review identified<lb/>
 in the following words:<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;19. From the above decisions, the following<lb/>
 principles emerge:<lb/>
</item>

<item>(a) the basic requirement of Article 14 is<lb/>
 fairness in action by the State, and non-<lb/>
arbitrariness in essence and substance is the<lb/>
 heartbeat of fair play. These actions are<lb/>
 amenable to the judicial review only to the<lb/>
 extent that the State must act validly for a<lb/>
 discernible reason and not whimsically for<lb/>
 any ulterior purpose. If the State acts within<lb/>
 the bounds of reasonableness, it would be<lb/>
 legitimate to take into consideration the<lb/>
 national priorities;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(b) fixation of a value of the tender is<lb/>
 entirely within the purview of the executive<lb/>
 and courts hardly have any role to play in<lb/>
 this process except for striking down such<lb/>
 action of the executive as is proved to be<lb/>
 arbitrary<lb/>
 or<lb/>
 unreasonable.<lb/>
 If<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 Government acts in conformity with certain<lb/>
 healthy standards and norms such as<lb/>
 awarding of contracts by inviting tenders, in<lb/>
 those circumstances, the interference by<lb/>
 Courts is very limited;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(c) In the matter of formulating conditions<lb/>
 of a tender document and awarding a<lb/>
 contract, greater latitude is required to be<lb/>
 conceded to the State authorities unless the<lb/>
 action of tendering authority is found to be<lb/>
 malicious and a misuse of its statutory<lb/>
 powers, interference by Courts is not<lb/>
 warranted;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(d) Certain preconditions or qualifications for<lb/>
 tenders have to be laid down to ensure that<lb/>
 the contractor has the capacity and the<lb/>
 resources to successfully execute the work;<lb/>
 and<lb/>
</item>

<item>(e) If the State or its instrumentalities act<lb/>
 reasonably, fairly and in public interest in<lb/>
 awarding contract, here again, interference<lb/>
 by Court is very restrictive since no person<lb/>
 can claim fundamental right to carry on<lb/>
 business with the Government.<lb/>
</item>

<item>20. Therefore, a Court before interfering in<lb/>
 tender or contractual matters, in exercise of<lb/>
 power of judicial review, should pose to<lb/>
 itself the following questions:<lb/>
</item>

<item>(i) Whether the process adopted or decision<lb/>
 made by the authority is mala fide or<lb/>
 intended to favour someone; or whether the<lb/>
 process adopted or decision made is so<lb/>
 arbitrary and irrational that the court can<lb/>
 say: &quot;the decision is such that no<lb/>
 responsible authority acting reasonably and<lb/>
 in accordance with relevant law could have<lb/>
 reached&quot;; and (ii) Whether the public<lb/>
 interest is affected. If the answers to the<lb/>
 above questions are in negative, then there<lb/>
 should be no interference under Article<lb/>
 226.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>(emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</p>

<p>(b) Ratnagiri Gas and Power Private Limited v. RDS Projects<lb/>
 Limited and others, (2013) 1 SCC 524, wherein the Supreme<lb/>
 Court held as under:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;38. We need hardly point out that in cases where<lb/>
 the decision making process is multi-layered,<lb/>
 officers associated with the process are free and<lb/>
 indeed expected to take views on various issues<lb/>
 according to their individual perceptions. They may<lb/>
 in doing so at time strike discordant notes, but that<lb/>
 is but natural and indeed welcome for it is only by<lb/>
 independent deliberation, that all possible facets of<lb/>
 an issue are unfolded and addressed and a decision<lb/>
 that is most appropriate under the circumstances<lb/>
 shaped. If every step in the decision making<lb/>
 process is viewed with suspicion the integrity<lb/>
 of the entire process shall be jeopardized.<lb/>
 Officers taking views in the decision making<lb/>
 process will feel handicapped in expressing<lb/>
 their opinions freely and frankly for fear of<lb/>
 being seen to be doing so for mala fides<lb/>
 reasons which would in turn affect public<lb/>
 interest. Nothing in the instant case was done<lb/>
 without a reasonable or probable cause which is the<lb/>
 very essence of the doctrine of malice in law vitiating<lb/>
 administrative actions. We have, therefore, no<lb/>
 hesitation in holding that the findings recorded by<lb/>
 the High Court to the effect that the process of<lb/>
 annulment of the tender process or the rejection of<lb/>
 the tender submitted by RDS was vitiated by mala<lb/>
 fides is unsustainable and is hereby set aside.... &quot;<lb/>
</item><p>
 (emphasis supplied)<lb/></p><p>
 and submitted that in the case on hand also the decision-<lb/>
making process is multi-layered.<lb/>
</p>
<p>(c) Tejas Constructions and Infrastructure Private Limited v.<lb/>
 Municipal Council, Sendhwa and another, (2012) 6 SCC 464,<lb/>
 wherein the Supreme Court held as under:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;19. It is also noteworthy that in the matter of<lb/>
 evaluation of the bids and determination of the<lb/>
 eligibility of the bidders Municipal Council had the<lb/>
 advantage of the aid &amp; advice of an empanelled<lb/>
 consultant, a technical hand, who could well<lb/>
 appreciate the significance of the tender condition<lb/>
 regarding the bidder executing the single integrated<lb/>
 water supply scheme and fulfilling that condition of<lb/>
 tender by reference to the work undertaken by<lb/>
 them. We, therefore, see no reason to interfere with<lb/>
 the view taken by the High Court of the allotment of<lb/>
 work made in favour of respondent No.2.<lb/>
</item>

<item>20. We may while parting point out that out of a<lb/>
 total of Rs.19.5 crores representing the estimated<lb/>
 value of the contract, respondent No.2 is certified to<lb/>
 have already executed work worth Rs.11.50 crores<lb/>
 and received a sum of Rs.8.79 crores towards the<lb/>
 said work. More importantly the work in question<lb/>
 relates to a drinking water supply scheme for the<lb/>
 residents of a scarcity stricken municipality. The<lb/>
 project is sponsored with the Central Government<lb/>
 assistance under its urban infrastructure scheme for<lb/>
 small and middle towns. The completion target of<lb/>
 the scheme is September 2012. Any interference<lb/>
 with the award of the contract at this stage is bound<lb/>
 to delay the execution of the work and put the<lb/>
 inhabitants of the municipal area to further<lb/>
 hardship.<lb/>
 …<lb/>
</item>

<item>33. Interference with the on-going work is,<lb/>
 therefore, not conducive to public interest which can<lb/>
 be served only if the scheme is completed as<lb/>
 expeditiously as possible giving relief to the thirsting<lb/>
 residents of Sendhwa. This is particularly so when<lb/>
 the allotment of work in favour of respondent No.2<lb/>
 does not involve any extra cost in comparison to the<lb/>
 cost that may be incurred if the contract was allotted<lb/>
 to the appellant-company.&quot;<lb/>
 (emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</item>

<p>(d) Siemons Public Communication Pvt. Ltd. v. Union of India,<lb/>
 AIR 2009 SC 1204, wherein the Supreme Court held as under:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;33. As was noted in the case of Asia Foundation &amp;<lb/>
 Construction Ltd. (supra) though the principle of<lb/>
 judicial review cannot be denied so far as exercise of<lb/>
 contractual powers of government bodies are<lb/>
 concerned, but it is intended to prevent arbitrariness<lb/>
 or favouritism and it is exercised in the larger public<lb/>
 interest or if it is brought to the notice of the Court<lb/>
 that in the matter of award of a contract power has<lb/>
 been exercised for any collateral purpose.<lb/>
</item>

<item>34. On examining the facts and circumstances of the<lb/>
 present case, we are of the view that none of the<lb/>
 criteria has been satisfied justifying Court&apos;s<lb/>
 interference in the grant of contract in favour of the<lb/>
 appellants. When the power of judicial review is<lb/>
 invoked in the matters relating to tenders or award<lb/>
 of contracts, certain special features have to be<lb/>
 considered. A contract is a commercial transaction<lb/>
 and evaluating tenders and awarding contracts are<lb/>
 essentially commercial functions. In such cases<lb/>
 principles of equity and natural justice stay at a<lb/>
 distance. If the decision relating to award of<lb/>
 contracts is bonafide and is in public interest, Courts<lb/>
 will not exercise the power of judicial review and<lb/>
 interfere even if it is accepted for the sake of<lb/>
 argument that there is a procedural lacuna.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>(emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</p>

<p>(e) Reliance Airport Developers (P) Ltd. v. Airports Authority of<lb/>
 India and others, (2006) 10 SCC 1, wherein the Supreme<lb/>
 Court held as under:<lb/>
 &quot;</p>

<item>84. In the ultimate, the question would be whether<lb/>
 in the process of selection the Government had<lb/>
 adopted transparent and fair process.<lb/>
 ....<lb/>
</item>

<item>89. The extent of judicial review in a case of this<lb/>
 nature where the texture cannot be matched with<lb/>
 one relating to award of contract, the observations<lb/>
 of this Court in Raunaq International Ltd. v. I.V.R.<lb/>
 Construction Ltd. and Ors. (1999 (1) SCC 492) are<lb/>
 relevant. It was observed as follows:<lb/>
</item>

<item>&apos;13. Hence before entertaining a writ<lb/>
 petition and passing any interim orders in<lb/>
 such petitions, the court must carefully<lb/>
 weigh conflicting public interests. Only when<lb/>
 it comes to a conclusion that there is an<lb/>
 overwhelming public interest in entertaining<lb/>
 the petition, the court should intervene.&apos;<lb/>
</item>

<item>...<lb/>
</item>

<item>91. In the Queens Bench decision in R. v.<lb/>
 Department of Constitutional Affairs (2006 All ER<lb/>
 (D) 101) it was inter-alia held as follows:<lb/>
 &apos;It is not every wandering from the precise<lb/>
 paths of best practice that lends fuel to a<lb/>
 claim for judicial review.&apos;&quot;<lb/>
 (emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</item>

<p>(f) Johnson and Johnson Ltd. v. State of J &amp; K and others, AIR<lb/>
 2010 Jammu and Kashmir 113, wherein a Division Bench of<lb/>
 the Jammu and Kashmir High Court held as under:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;6. In the writ petition, it was contended that<lb/>
 Suturing materials, manufactured and sold by the<lb/>
 writ petitioner-respondent, have no complaint as<lb/>
 regards their quality but, surprisingly, the tender<lb/>
 submitted by writ petitioner-respondent has not<lb/>
 been accepted and, instead, tender submitted by<lb/>
 appellant has been accepted, although, the price<lb/>
 offered by respondent-writ petitioner was almost<lb/>
 40% lower than the price offered by appellant.<lb/>
</item>

<item>...<lb/>
</item>

<item>21. The materials discussed above, would indicate<lb/>
 that it is not a case of absence of any material. All<lb/>
 those materials suggested that the quality of<lb/>
 materials to be supplied by appellant is without any<lb/>
 defect and the said reputation has been maintained<lb/>
 by appellant for a considerable period of time. On<lb/>
 the other hand, there is a view that materials of<lb/>
 other suppliers, including those of writ petitioner<lb/>
 -respondent, used by them do not have such<lb/>
 unblemished record. In other words, the materials<lb/>
 on record depicted that whereas materials to be<lb/>
 supplied by appellant are doubt free, but materials<lb/>
 to be supplied by petitioner-respondent and other<lb/>
 tenderers are with some ting of doubt. The Tender<lb/>
 Committee, at that stage, could do many a things.<lb/>
 One of them could be sending the samples of<lb/>
 materials to be supplied by different tenderers to a<lb/>
 laboratory, as has been directed by the judgment<lb/>
 and order under appeal, but only after specifying<lb/>
 standard. They could take assistance of Indian<lb/>
 Standard Institution. They could also approach many<lb/>
 other bodies in India and abroad. But before a<lb/>
 Judicial Review Court, the question is not what they<lb/>
 could do, but what they did. It is possible that they<lb/>
 could devise a mean for the purpose of making it<lb/>
 absolutely doubt free that the quality of materials to<lb/>
 be supplied by appellant is better than the quality of<lb/>
 the materials to be supplied by respondent writ<lb/>
 petitioner. It is also possible that by taking recourse<lb/>
 to such device they could bring on record factors<lb/>
 which would show that they have done a stupendous<lb/>
 work. However, they have not done so. The decision<lb/>
 taken by them is based on the aforementioned<lb/>
 materials. A Judicial Review Court could pronounce<lb/>
 that what they have done could not be done, for,<lb/>
 there was no material to support what they have<lb/>
 done. For that purpose, it was necessary for the<lb/>
 Judicial Review Court to say that none of the<lb/>
 opinions contained in the recommendation as well as<lb/>
 those<lb/>
 six<lb/>
 letters hold good. The<lb/>
 original<lb/>
 recommendation may be ignored, some of those<lb/>
 letters may also be ignored but can all of them be<lb/>
 ignored? If all of them cannot be ignored, then the<lb/>
 conclusion would be that there was some material,<lb/>
 on the basis of which the decision as was taken<lb/>
 could be taken. If the logical conclusion is that the<lb/>
 decision on the materials, as were placed before the<lb/>
 Purchase Committee, is one of the plausible<lb/>
 decisions, but may not be the perfect or best<lb/>
 decision, a Judicial Review Court may not touch the<lb/>
 decision.&quot;<lb/>
 (emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</item>

<p>11.2. Relying on the above said decisions, it is submitted<lb/>
 by the learned Advocate General that the contract is a<lb/>
 commercial transaction and it is not open to judicial scrutiny<lb/>
 and any interference would only delay the execution of the<lb/>
 work.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(B) COMPLIANCE OF STATUTORY REQUIREMENTS<lb/>
</p>

<p>12.1. Referring to the provisions of the TTIT Act, he<lb/>
 submitted that the Tender Accepting Authority is bound to<lb/>
 accept the lowest tender in terms of Section 10(2) of the TTIT<lb/>
 Act. Only with the lowest bidder, negotiation can be held in<lb/>
 terms of Section 10(3) of the TTIT Act. Before accepting the<lb/>
 bid in terms of Section 10(6) of the TTIT Act, Section 12 of the<lb/>
 TTIT Act empowers the Tender Accepting Authority to negotiate<lb/>
 with the lowest tenderer and reject the tender with reasons.<lb/>
</p>

<p>12.2. Expatiating the above said plea, it is submitted<lb/>
 that the Techno-Commercial Bid was opened on 26.7.2013.<lb/>
 The Board Level Tender Committee (for brevity, &quot;the BLTC&quot;), in<lb/>
 its 129 th Meeting held on 18.11.2013, accepted the Bid<lb/>
 Qualification Requirements (BQR) of the appellant and the<lb/>
 third respondent and rejected the other two bids. In the 140 th<lb/>
 meeting convened on 27.1.2014, the BLTC approved opening<lb/>
 of price bids of the appellant and the third respondent. The<lb/>
 44 th Board Meeting held on 30.1.2014 granted approval for<lb/>
 opening of the price bids of BHEL and the appellant as per the<lb/>
 recommendation of the BLTC. In the said meeting, it was also<lb/>
 resolved to negotiate with the evaluated L1 bidder after<lb/>
 evaluation of their price-cum-financial offer. This is stated to<lb/>
 be in due compliance of Section 10(1) of the TTIT Act.<lb/>
 Thereafter, price bids were opened on 5.2.2014. It is stated<lb/>
 that Supplementary Price Bids submitted by the appellant and<lb/>
 the third respondent on 5.2.2014 were also considered.<lb/>
 Thereafter, the Consultant gave his recommendation on<lb/>
 30.5.2014. On 2.6.2014, BLTC granted approval for conducting<lb/>
 negotiation with the third respondent. After some intervening<lb/>
 proceedings, in the 51 st Board Meeting dated 26.9.2014, the<lb/>
 Board resolved to accept the tender of the third respondent<lb/>
 and this is stated to be in compliance of Section 10(6) of the<lb/>
 TTIT Act. It is submitted by the learned Advocate General that<lb/>
 under Section 10(2) of the TTIT Act, the lowest tenderer is<lb/>
 identified and it is only formal acceptance, based on which<lb/>
 negotiation is done with the lowest tenderer as contemplated<lb/>
 under Sections 10(3) and 12 of the TTIT Act. In the order<lb/>
 under Section 10(6) of the TTIT Act, the reasons for such<lb/>
 acceptance are stated.<lb/>
 Thereafter, by proceedings dated<lb/>
 27.9.2014, the reasons for not accepting the appellant&apos;s<lb/>
 representations were set out in detail and communicated to<lb/>
 the appellant.<lb/>
</p>

<p>12.3. In the case on hand, there is no violation of<lb/>
 statutory provisions as alleged by the appellant and, therefore,<lb/>
 the order passed by the learned Single Judge does not warrant<lb/>
 interference.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(C) VIOLATION OF INSTRUCTIONS TO BIDDERS BY<lb/>
 THE APPELLANT<lb/>
</p>

<p>13.1. Highlighting Clause 7.3 of the Instructions to<lb/>
 Bidders which states that the owner is not bound to give any<lb/>
 reason for the rejection of the bid, it is contended that the<lb/>
 appellant having accepted the tender conditions is not bound<lb/>
 to seek reasons for rejection of the bid.<lb/>
</p>

<p>13.2. Inviting attention to Clause 25.4 of the Instructions<lb/>
 to Bidders which states that while the bids are under<lb/>
 consideration, bidders and/or their representatives or other<lb/>
 interested parties are advised to refrain from contacting by any<lb/>
 means, the purchaser and/or his employees/representatives on<lb/>
 matters related to the bids under consideration, it is pleaded<lb/>
 that despite such specific clause in the Instructions to Bidders,<lb/>
 the appellant had sent representations on 30.5.2014,<lb/>
 5.6.2014, 16.6.2014, 17.6.2014, 1.7.2014 and 8.7.2014 to<lb/>
 exert pressure on TANGEDCO.<lb/>
</p>

<p>13.3. That apart, Clause 25.5 of the Instructions to<lb/>
 Bidders states that any effort by a bidder to influence the<lb/>
 owner in the owner&apos;s bid evaluation, bid comparison or<lb/>
 contract award decision may result in the rejection of the<lb/>
 bidder&apos;s bid. However, the appellant sent representation on<lb/>
 16.6.2014 giving comparative statement of evaluation of the<lb/>
 bids of BHEL and the appellant; alleging poor track record of<lb/>
 the third respondent, and also stating about the wrong<lb/>
 evaluation done by the TANGEDCO. This is in clear violation of<lb/>
 Clause 25.5 of the Instructions to Bidders. In effect, it is<lb/>
 pleaded that the representations sent by the appellant are in<lb/>
 gross violation of Clause 25 of the Instructions to bidders.<lb/>
</p>

<p>13.4. It is submitted that Rule 27 of the TTIT Rules<lb/>
 mandates that the process of tender evaluation to be<lb/>
 confidential until the award of the contract is notified. The<lb/>
 appellant could not have knowledge of what has been<lb/>
 considered and there is no scope for them to know about it.<lb/>
 Moreover, as per Rule 27(iii) of the TTIT Rules, the tenderers<lb/>
 shall not make any attempt to establish unsolicited and<lb/>
 unauthorised contact with the Tender Accepting Authority,<lb/>
 Tender Inviting Authority or Tender Scrutiny Committee and,<lb/>
 therefore, the representations made by the appellant are<lb/>
 meant to exert pressure on the Tender Accepting Authority. It<lb/>
 is pleaded that this aspect should be considered in the light of<lb/>
 the fact that there are only two qualified bidders.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(D) PUBLICATION IN TENDER BULLETIN:<lb/>
</p>

<p>14.1. It is contended that as per Rule 30(3) of the TTIT<lb/>
 Rules, there is no requirement that the tender evaluation<lb/>
 report should be sent to the Tender Bulletin Officer. All that is<lb/>
 contemplated to be sent to the Tender Bulletin Officer is a<lb/>
 statement of evaluation of tenders with a comparative<lb/>
 statement of tenders received and decision therein for<lb/>
 publication in the Tender Bulletin.<lb/>
 The learned Advocate<lb/>
 General submitted that publication has been effected in the<lb/>
 Tender Bulletin on 9.10.2014 complying with Section 10(7) of<lb/>
 the TTIT Act and Rule 30(3) of the TTIT Rules. The copy of the<lb/>
 tender bulletin was filed for the first time before this Court.<lb/>
</p>

<p>14.2. Be that as it may, taking support from the<lb/>
 judgment of the learned Single Judge, more particularly,<lb/>
 paragraph 37, it is pleaded that even if the procedure<lb/>
 contemplated under Section 10(7) of the TTIT Act read with<lb/>
 Rule 30(3) of the TTIT Rules is not complied with, it will not<lb/>
 vitiate the tender process, as post finalization of tender only<lb/>
 the said provisions come into play.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(E) SECTION 4(1)(D) OF THE RIGHT TO INFORMATION<lb/>
 ACT:<lb/>
</p>

<p>15.1. The obligation under Section 4(1)(d) of the Right to<lb/>
 Information Act is only to furnish information and not reasons.<lb/>
 What is &quot;information&quot; is mentioned in Section 2(f) of the RTI<lb/>
 Act. This information will not include the reasons for the<lb/>
 decision. Even for getting information under Section 4(1)(d) of<lb/>
 the RTI Act, he has to make a request under Section 6 of the<lb/>
 RTI Act.<lb/>
 It is submitted that, in any event, this provision will<lb/>
 apply only for administrative or quasi-judicial decisions and not<lb/>
 to contractual matters. Moreover, seeking reasons for a<lb/>
 decision is not information within the meaning of Section<lb/>
 4(1)(d) of the RTI Act. In any event, Section 4(1) of the RTI<lb/>
 Act is only a guideline. In support of the said submission,<lb/>
 reliance was placed on a decision of the Bombay High Court in<lb/>
 Dr.Celsa Pinto v. Goa State Information Commission and<lb/>
 Another, AIR 2008 Bombay 120, wherein it is held as under:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;8. As regards the requisition Nos. 2 &amp; 3 by which<lb/>
 the petitioner was called upon to give information as<lb/>
 to why the post of Curator was not filled up by<lb/>
 promotion and why the Librarian from the<lb/>
 Engineering College was not considered for<lb/>
 promotion, the petitioner had initially answered by<lb/>
 stating that the information was N.A.(Not Available).<lb/>
 Thereafter, she had clarified by stating that it means<lb/>
 I don&apos;t know. The Commission has initially observed<lb/>
 in para. No. 13 that it does not see anything wrong<lb/>
 in the petitioner&apos;s reply that she does not know the<lb/>
 information because P.I.O. cannot manufacture the<lb/>
 information. However, in para. No. 14, the<lb/>
 Commission has observed that the petitioner has not<lb/>
 supplied a correct information because she corrected<lb/>
 information on points No. 2 &amp; 3. It can be recalled<lb/>
 that the petitioner corrected the information by<lb/>
 explaining that Not Available meant she does not<lb/>
 know. It is not possible to accept the reasoning of<lb/>
 the Commission. There is no substance in the<lb/>
 observation that merely because the petitioner<lb/>
 initially said Not Available and later on corrected her<lb/>
 statement and said she does not know and the<lb/>
 petitioner provided incomplete and incorrect<lb/>
 information. In the first place, the Commission ought<lb/>
 to have noticed that the Act confers on the citizen<lb/>
 the right to information. Information has been<lb/>
 defined by Section 2(f) as follows.<lb/>
</item>

<item>&apos;Section 2(f) -Information means any<lb/>
 material in any form, including records,<lb/>
 documents,memos<lb/>
 e-mails,<lb/>
 opinions,<lb/>
 advices, press releases, circulars, orders,<lb/>
 logbooks,<lb/>
 contracts,<lb/>
 reports,<lb/>
 papers,<lb/>
 samples, models, data material held in any<lb/>
 electronic form and information relating to<lb/>
 any private body which can be accessed by<lb/>
 a public authority under any other law for<lb/>
 the time being in force;&apos;<lb/>
</item>

<item>The definition cannot include within its fold answers<lb/>
 to the question why which would be the same thing<lb/>
 as asking the reason for a justification for a<lb/>
 particular thing. The Public Information Authorities<lb/>
 cannot expect to communicate to the citizen the<lb/>
 reason why a certain thing was done or not done in<lb/>
 the sense of a justification because the citizen<lb/>
 makes a requisition about information. Justifications<lb/>
 are matter within the domain of adjudicating<lb/>
 authorities and cannot properly be classified as<lb/>
 information.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>(emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</p>

<p>15.2. That apart, he also placed reliance on a decision of<lb/>
 a Division Bench of this Court in M.Vasudevan v. The Chief<lb/>
 Executive Officer, CMDA, Chennai and others, AIR 2006<lb/>
 Madras 45, wherein it is held as under:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;4. Mr.R.Krishnamurthy, learned senior counsel<lb/>
 appearing for the appellant submitted that no<lb/>
 reasons have been given in the order rejecting the<lb/>
 petitioner&apos;s tender. He relied on section 12 of the<lb/>
 Tamil Nadu Transparency in Tenders Act, 1998 and<lb/>
 has contended that reasons must be given for<lb/>
 rejecting the tender.<lb/>
</item>

<item>5. We do not accept this contention. An order<lb/>
 rejecting tender is not a quasi judicial order nor is it<lb/>
 even an administrative order which affects rights<lb/>
 and liabilities. Hence neither reasons have to be<lb/>
 given in the said order nor opportunity of hearing<lb/>
 has to be given before passing the said order.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>15.3. It is submitted that the provisions of the TTIT Act<lb/>
 cannot be interpreted in the light of the RTI Act, as TTIT Act is<lb/>
 a special enactment dealing with tenders. In this regard,<lb/>
 reliance was placed on Sections 19 and 20 of the Act, more<lb/>
 particularly Section 20 of the Act, which states that the<lb/>
 provisions of the Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything<lb/>
 inconsistent therewith contained in any other law for the time<lb/>
 being in force, which also includes the subsequent enactments.<lb/>
</p>

<p>15.4. That apart, Rule 7(1) of the TTIT Rules states that<lb/>
 the tender bulletin shall contain only information of the notice<lb/>
 inviting tenders and the orders accepting a tender and does<lb/>
 not in itself create a legal right or liability. Therefore, even a<lb/>
 successful bidder cannot claim any right.<lb/>
</p>

<p>15.5. The Division Bench in the earlier round of litigation<lb/>
 (dated 19.8.2014 in W.A.No.1065 of 2014) has directed the<lb/>
 TANGEDCO to communicate the reasons and the same have<lb/>
 been duly communicated in compliance of the said order, even<lb/>
 though reasons need not be given in terms of the decision of<lb/>
 the decision of the Division Bench of this Court in<lb/>
 M.Vasudevan case, referred supra.<lb/>
</p>

<p>15.6. In any event, the impugned communication dated<lb/>
 27.9.2014 of the first respondent deals with as to how each<lb/>
 item of evaluation is done. They refer to some materials and if<lb/>
 those materials are sufficient for consideration by the<lb/>
 TANGEDCO, then it cannot be said that all other aspects have<lb/>
 not been considered. He submitted that adequacy of material<lb/>
 will not affect the decision and in this regard, he placed<lb/>
 reliance on the decision of the Supreme Court in Michigan<lb/>
 Rubber (India) Limited v. State of Karnataka, (2012) 8 SCC<lb/>
 216, wherein after referring to Jagdish Mandal case and Tejas<lb/>
 Constructions and Infrastructure Private Limited v. Municipal<lb/>
 Council, Sendhwa and another, (2012) 6 SCC 464, it was held<lb/>
 as under:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;23. From the above decisions, the following<lb/>
 principles emerge:<lb/>
</item>

<item>(a) the basic requirement of Article 14 is fairness in<lb/>
 action by the State, and non-arbitrariness in essence<lb/>
 and substance is the heartbeat of fair play. These<lb/>
 actions are amenable to the judicial review only to<lb/>
 the extent that the State must act validly for a<lb/>
 discernible reason and not whimsically for any<lb/>
 ulterior purpose. If the State acts within the bounds<lb/>
 of reasonableness, it would be legitimate to take into<lb/>
 consideration the national priorities;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(b) fixation of a value of the tender is entirely within<lb/>
 the purview of the executive and courts hardly have<lb/>
 any role to play in this process except for striking<lb/>
 down such action of the executive as is proved to be<lb/>
 arbitrary or unreasonable. If the Government acts in<lb/>
 conformity with certain healthy standards and norms<lb/>
 such as awarding of contracts by inviting tenders, in<lb/>
 those circumstances, the interference by Courts is<lb/>
 very limited;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(c) In the matter of formulating conditions of a<lb/>
 tender document and awarding a contract, greater<lb/>
 latitude is required to be conceded to the State<lb/>
 authorities unless the action of tendering authority is<lb/>
 found to be malicious and a misuse of its statutory<lb/>
 powers, interference by Courts is not warranted;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(d) Certain preconditions or qualifications for tenders<lb/>
 have to be laid down to ensure that the contractor<lb/>
 has the capacity and the resources to successfully<lb/>
 execute the work; and<lb/></item><item>
 (e) If the State or its instrumentalities act<lb/>
 reasonably, fairly and in public interest in awarding<lb/>
 contract, here again, interference by Court is very<lb/>
 restrictive since no person can claim fundamental<lb/>
 right to carry on business with the Government.&quot;<lb/>
 (emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</item>

<p>15.7. Repudiating the contention of the appellant that the<lb/>
 impugned order does not contain comparative evaluation; the<lb/>
 Tender Bulletin did not contain comparative evaluation nor<lb/>
 placed any material with reference to comparative evaluation,<lb/>
 it is submitted that the said plea is hypertechnical and on that<lb/>
 ground the tender process cannot be interfered with. There<lb/>
 are materials before the authority to show that decision has<lb/>
 been taken after proper application of mind and the same does<lb/>
 not vitiate the tender process.<lb/>
</p>

<p>15.8. There cannot be any two different opinions on the<lb/>
 question that this project is of great public interest because, it<lb/>
 is for a power starved State. That apart, just because two<lb/>
 views are possible commercially, it cannot be a ground for<lb/>
 judicial review.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(F) RATE OF INTEREST:<lb/>
</p>

<p>16.1. Rule 14(5) of the TTIT Rules states that &quot;The<lb/>
 tender documents shall clearly indicate whether any variations<lb/>
 in the commercial terms prescribed in the documents will be<lb/>
 permitted and if so to what extent such variations would be<lb/>
 considered.&quot; In the case on hand, Clause 25.4 of the<lb/>
 Instructions to Bidders does not permit to change the<lb/>
 substance of the bids, after the bids have been opened.<lb/>
 However, the appellant claims that they have offered lower<lb/>
 rate of interest. The original interest rate offered is not in<lb/>
 accordance with tender terms. As per Clause 14.0(d)(5), the<lb/>
 rate of interest the bidder should quote should be fixed,<lb/>
 whereas the appellant has not specified the fixed rate of<lb/>
 interest. However, in the term sheet submitted on behalf of<lb/>
 the appellant, it is stated that &quot;Both rates are estimated based<lb/>
 on current market conditions. The final pricing is subject to<lb/>
 the lender&apos;s final discretion, and may be adjusted in the<lb/>
 future.&quot; This quote of variant rate of interest is against the<lb/>
 Tender conditions and, therefore, it cannot be considered.<lb/>
 However, it is not disputed that before opening of the bid,<lb/>
 namely on 5.2.2014, the appellant has produced a letter from<lb/>
 its bankers dated 13.1.2014, agreeing for fixed rate of interest<lb/>
 (hedged) till the entire tenor of loan.<lb/>
</p>

<p>16.2. On the question of reduction of interest, it is<lb/>
 submitted that as per Rule 23 of the TTIT Rules, changes and<lb/>
 alternations are not permitted after opening of the tender. In<lb/>
 this case, there is a material change because this interest<lb/>
 forms part of substance of the bid, in terms of Clause 12.0,<lb/>
 which states that the price bid shall include all taxes and duties<lb/>
 and interest and finance charges, commitment fees, etc.<lb/>
 during IDC period. Therefore, according to the learned<lb/>
 Advocate General, any change in the rate of interest would be<lb/>
 material change affecting the substance of the bid. That part,<lb/>
 Clause 25.4 of the Instructions to Bidders does not permit the<lb/>
 bidders to change the substance of the bids, after the bids are<lb/>
 opened.<lb/>
</p>

<p>16.3. In the case on hand, the price bid was opened on<lb/>
 5.2.2014 and supplementary bid was submitted by the<lb/>
 appellant and third respondent on the said date. The offer of<lb/>
 the appellant for reducing the rate of interest from 7.2% to<lb/>
 6.2% was given on 5.6.2014. The Consultant&apos;s report is dated<lb/>
 30.5.2014. As per the terms of Rule 23 of the TTIT Rules, one<lb/>
 cannot alter the price bid after it is opened and the substance<lb/>
 of the bid cannot be altered in terms of Clause 25.4 of the<lb/>
 Instructions to Bidders.<lb/>
</p>

<p>16.4. In response to the plea of the appellant that Clause<lb/>
 25.3 of Instructions to Bidders enables the respondents to<lb/>
 relax or waive any of the conditions of the specification in the<lb/>
 best interests of the TANGEDCO, the learned Advocate General<lb/>
 submitted that the appellant cannot claim such relaxation as a<lb/>
 matter of right. The TANGEDCO reduced the rate of interest<lb/>
 for third respondent on 27.6.2014 in exercise of the power<lb/>
 under Section 10(3) of the TTIT Act, which permits<lb/>
 negotiation. Even if Clause 25.3 of the Instructions to Bidders<lb/>
 permits relaxation of the conditions in the best interests of the<lb/>
 TANGEDCO, in view of Rule 23 of the TTIT Rules, no alterations<lb/>
 can be permitted after tender opening.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(G) COMMITMENT FEE:<lb/>
</p>

<p>17.1. Anent Commitment Fee, in the term sheet it is<lb/>
 stated that &quot;The accrued commitment fee (1% per annum) is<lb/>
 payable on the last day of each successive interest period<lb/>
 which ends during the availability period, on the last day of the<lb/>
 availability period and, if cancelled in full, on the cancelled<lb/>
 amount of the relevant Lender&apos;s Commitment at the time the<lb/>
 cancellation is effective.&quot; According to the learned Advocate<lb/>
 General, the Commitment Fee is part of Financing Charges<lb/>
 specified in Clause 14.0 (d)(6) and the appellant cannot<lb/>
 contend that the same should be excluded for the purpose of<lb/>
 bid evaluation. He submitted that payment of commitment fee<lb/>
 is contingent, but the TANGEDCO decided to include it and<lb/>
 such terms have been accepted by the appellant and now the<lb/>
 appellant cannot resile from such commitment. It is within the<lb/>
 exclusive prerogative of the employer to include commitment<lb/>
 fee in the price. When the terms of tender are clear that<lb/>
 commitment fee cannot be excluded, the appellant cannot<lb/>
 quote in contra terms.<lb/>
</p>

<p>17.2. As per Clause 14.0 (d)(1) of the Instructions to<lb/>
 bidders, the loan amount should include &quot;at least 75% of the<lb/>
 Total EPC Cost + 100% of Interest during construction and<lb/>
 Financing Cost&quot;. Therefore, interest on the entire loan amount<lb/>
 from the date of signing has to be reckoned separately based<lb/>
 on the drawal.<lb/>
 The failure on the part of the appellant to<lb/>
 include commitment fee in the repayment schedule found at<lb/>
 Page 616 of Volume I, while including the same in the break-<lb/>
up of financial charges found at Page 615 of Volume I is<lb/>
 nothing but an error of calculation and cannot be interpreted to<lb/>
 his advantage. In support of the said plea, the Repayment<lb/>
 Schedule found at page 616 of Volume I is extracted as such:<lb/>
</p>

<p>(H) INTEREST ON MANAGEMENT FEE AND GUARANTEE<lb/>
 FEE CANNOT BE EXCLUDED:<lb/>
</p>

<p>18.1. The lender in his letter dated 21.10.2013 had<lb/>
 clearly confirmed that all fees, including management fees,<lb/>
 commitment fees and legal fees, insurance premium, etc., will<lb/>
 form part of debt-financing. The appellant is not disputing the<lb/>
 liability for payment of interest on financial charges, but wants<lb/>
 such interest to be reckoned only for the moratorium period<lb/>
 which begins after the completion of the project.<lb/>
 It is<lb/>
 submitted that all the above charges fall due during the period<lb/>
 of construction and, therefore, the plea of the appellant not to<lb/>
 include interest on these amounts during the construction<lb/>
 period is totally flawed. Therefore, there is no perversity or<lb/>
 arbitrariness in the decision taken as per the terms of the<lb/>
 tender; as per the banking practice and as per the term sheet<lb/>
 given by the lender.<lb/>
</p>

<p>18.2. The learned Advocate General submitted that<lb/>
 overwhelming public interest should be the consideration even<lb/>
 in cases where a legal point has been made out. In support of<lb/>
 this plea, he relied on the decision of the Supreme Court in<lb/>
 Master Marine Services (P) Ltd. v. Metcalfe &amp; Hodgkinson (P)<lb/>
 Ltd. and another, (2005) 6 SCC 139, wherein it is held as<lb/>
 under:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;15. The law relating to award of contract by State<lb/>
 and public sector corporations was reviewed in Air<lb/>
 India Ltd. v. Cochin International Airport Ltd. 2000<lb/>
 (2) SCC 617 and it was held that the award of a<lb/>
 contract, whether by a private party or by a State, is<lb/>
 essentially a commercial transaction. It can choose<lb/>
 its own method to arrive at a decision and it is free<lb/>
 to grant any relaxation for bona fide reasons, if the<lb/>
 tender conditions permit such a relaxation. It was<lb/>
 further held that the State, its corporations,<lb/>
 instrumentalities and agencies have the public duty<lb/>
 to be fair to all concerned. Even when some defect<lb/>
 is found in the decision making process, the Court<lb/>
 must exercise its discretionary powers under Article<lb/>
 226 with great caution and should exercise it only in<lb/>
 furtherance of public interest and not merely on the<lb/>
 making out of a legal point. The Court should always<lb/>
 keep the larger public interest in mind in order to<lb/>
 decide whether its intervention is called for or not.<lb/>
 Only when it comes to a conclusion that<lb/>
 overwhelming public interest requires interference,<lb/>
 the Court should interfere.&quot;<lb/></item><p>
 (emphasis supplied)<lb/></p><p>
 The only public interest the appellant is arguing is that there is<lb/>
 a difference in the interest rates and if that is reckoned, the<lb/>
 appellant would be the lowest bidder. In fact, the interest rate<lb/>
 quoted by the appellant is variant and vague and not fixed as<lb/>
 contemplated under the Instructions to bidders.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(I) APPOINTMENT OF CONSULTANT:<lb/>
</p>

<p>19. In the case on hand, Consultant was appointed<lb/>
 pursuant to the Board Resolution dated 28.1.2012. He<lb/>
 participated in all pre-bid and post-bid meetings and the<lb/>
 minutes are signed by all the parties and the consultant and,<lb/>
 therefore, the appellant was very much aware of the<lb/>
 appointment of the consultant and the role played by him and<lb/>
 cannot plead ignorance.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(J) VENDOR RATING &amp; PAST PERFORMANCE:<lb/>
</p>

<p>20.1. Vendor rating is not defined in the terms of<lb/>
 conditions. But there is a reference to such term in Clause<lb/>
 29(viii). There is no statute which defines vendor rating or<lb/>
 prescribes the method for vendor rating. Therefore, assessing<lb/>
 the vendor rating and past performance is within the subjective<lb/>
 satisfaction of the employer or the purchaser.<lb/>
</p>

<p>20.2. The appellant relied on the following circumstances<lb/>
 to show that the vendor rating and past performance of BHEL<lb/>
 is not satisfactory:<lb/>
</p>

<item>(i)The letter from the Hon&apos;ble Chief Minister dated<lb/>
</item>

<item>26.11.2013 addressed to the Hon&apos;ble Prime Minister of<lb/>
 India;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(ii)The Counter Affidavit filed by Tamil Nadu Electricity<lb/>
 Board in W.P.(MD) No.3730 of 2012 before the Madurai<lb/>
 Bench of the Madras High Court;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(iii)The report of Comptroller and Auditor General of India,<lb/>
 New Delhi dated 17.2.2014;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(iv)Order of the Central Electricity Regulatory Commission,<lb/>
 New Delhi, dated 19.6.2014; and<lb/>
</item>

<item>(v)various newspaper reports and the contents of the<lb/>
 TANGEDCO website.<lb/>
</item>

<p>20.3. In response to the above, the learned Advocate<lb/>
 General submitted that the letter of the Hon&apos;ble Chief Minister<lb/>
 has referred to the fact that many Central Generating Stations<lb/>
 have been shut down at the same time and there is no specific<lb/>
 reference to BHEL.<lb/>
</p>

<p>20.4. With regard to North Chennai Thermal Power<lb/>
 Station Stage-II, Unit-I, it is submitted that the said power<lb/>
 station is in operation now. The reason for the delay is an<lb/>
 accident to generator stator. The Tamil Nadu Electricity Board<lb/>
 filed a counter affidavit in W.P.(MD) No.3730 of 2012 before<lb/>
 the Madurai Bench of the Madras High Court stating that<lb/>
 penalty towards delay in completion of the project is<lb/>
 attributable to BHEL and the same will be recovered from<lb/>
 them. It is submitted that it cannot be the sole criterion for<lb/>
 deciding the past performance of the vendor.<lb/>
</p>

<p>20.5. With regard to the report of the Comptroller and<lb/>
 Auditor General, it is stated that it is not for this Court to look<lb/>
 into it and draw any inference. In support of the said plea,<lb/>
 reliance was placed on a decision of the Delhi High Court in<lb/>
 Sarvesh Bisaria v. Union of India (Order dated 3.12.2014<lb/>
 made in W.P.(C) No.8502 of 2014), wherein it is held as<lb/>
 under:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;20. The role of CAG Reports thus, is to enable the<lb/>
 legislature to oversee that functioning of the<lb/>
 Government and it is for the legislature to take<lb/>
 action on the basis of CAG Reports or to direct the<lb/>
 Government to take action on the basis thereof and<lb/>
 till the legislature has not so directed, this Court<lb/>
 cannot direct any action to be taken on the basis of<lb/>
 the CAG Reports. The Supreme Court, in Centre for<lb/>
 Environment &amp; Food Security Vs. Union of India<lb/>
 (2011) 5 SCC 668, concerned with directions sought<lb/>
 for proper implementation of the Mahatma Gandhi<lb/>
 National Rural Employment Guarantee Act, 2005,<lb/>
 ordered investigation by CBI in reference to the CAG<lb/>
 Report, only after satisfying itself that the CAG<lb/>
 Report had been accepted by the Government and<lb/>
 the Government itself had directed follow up action<lb/>
 in terms thereof. The petitioner herein however<lb/>
 wants us to issue a mandamus, for the CAG Reports,<lb/>
 even before they are placed before the Parliament /<lb/>
 Legislature and before the Parliament / Legislature<lb/>
 has accepted or rejected the same, to become the<lb/>
 basis of investigation by CVC and / or Lokpal /<lb/>
 Lokayukta. The same is clearly not permitted under<lb/>
 the Constitutional scheme.&quot;<lb/>
 (emphasis supplied)<lb/></item><p>
 It is submitted that only when the report is placed before the<lb/>
 Assembly and accepted, action can be taken based on such<lb/>
 report.<lb/>
</p>

<p>20.6. He also placed reliance on a decision of this Court<lb/>
 in C.Selvaraj v. State of Tamil Nadu, (Order dated 21.8.2014<lb/>
 made in W.P.No.34038 of 2014), wherein it was held as under:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;16. Learned Advocate General has also referred to<lb/>
 the unreported judgment of the Division Bench of<lb/>
 Delhi High Court decided on 03.12.2014 in W.P. (C)<lb/>
 No.8502 of 2014 (Sarvesh Bisaria vs. Union of India<lb/>
 and others), which in turn has referred to certain<lb/>
 earlier judicial pronouncements in respect of the<lb/>
 major controversy raised in the present petition. The<lb/>
 Division Bench of the Delhi High Court in CWP<lb/>
 No.1716/2000 (B.L.Wadhera vs. Union of India)<lb/>
 decided on 16.05.2001 raised the issue of follow-up<lb/>
 action on the reports of the CAG pointing out<lb/>
 irregularities or illegalities. A preliminary objection<lb/>
 was raised regarding the subject matter as the same<lb/>
 was within the specific domain of the Parliament.<lb/>
 The Court opined that the validity of any proceedings<lb/>
 in the Parliament cannot be called into question in<lb/>
 the Court and held that once it was found that the<lb/>
 Legislature had the power and privilege, it must be<lb/>
 left to the House itself to determine whether there in<lb/>
 fact has been any breach of privilege, while taking<lb/>
 support from the judgment of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme<lb/>
 Court in Pandit M.S.M.Sharma vs. Dr.Shreekrishna<lb/>
 Sinha (AIR 1960 SC 1186).<lb/>
</item>

<item>17. It is enunciated that once the CAG Report is laid<lb/>
 before the Assembly, it is dealt with by the Rules<lb/>
 and Procedures of the Assembly. The role of CAG<lb/>
 report is to enable the Legislature to oversee that<lb/>
 functioning of the Government and it is for the<lb/>
 Legislature to take action on the basis of CAG<lb/>
 Reports or to direct the Government to take action<lb/>
 on the basis thereof.<lb/>
</item>

<item>18. On the conspectus of the legal position<lb/>
 enunciated aforesaid and the averments made in the<lb/>
 petition, it is quite obvious from the cryptic petition<lb/>
 that there only allegations of misappropriation and<lb/>
 mis-utilisation of thousands of crores! It, thus,<lb/>
 appear that the past history of disputes between the<lb/>
 petitioner and its employer, the second respondent,<lb/>
 11 has coloured the thinking of the petitioner to<lb/>
 make allegations largely on the press reporting or<lb/>
 averment in other petitions, other than the aspect of<lb/>
 minority view, of the third respondent/Commission,<lb/>
 which is stated to be the subject matter of challenge<lb/>
 in appeal proceedings.<lb/>
</item>

<item>19. The substratum of the submissions of the<lb/>
 learned counsel for the petitioner really arose over<lb/>
 the aspects emanating from the report of the CAG,<lb/>
 the procedure for which has been explained<lb/>
 aforesaid. We are faced with the position where in<lb/>
 terms of the procedure, the COPU is stated to be still<lb/>
 examining the matter, and no finality has been<lb/>
 achieved as yet. Only on submission of the COPU<lb/>
 report, the same being placed before the Legislative<lb/>
 Assembly, would the occasion arise for final view to<lb/>
 emerge in terms of Rule 217(1) and even the<lb/>
 reports of COPU are to be treated as confidential<lb/>
 until presented to the Assembly. Thus, what is the<lb/>
 confidential material disclosed to us was to satisfy<lb/>
 our conscience and cannot be relied upon or that<lb/>
 material required to be produced and filed before the<lb/>
 Court.&quot;<lb/>
</item>
 <item>

	 (emphasis supplied)<lb/>
 </item>

<p>
 The report of CAG on BHEL will be examined and considered by<lb/>
 the Public Undertakings Committee and it is not for this Court<lb/>
 to pass any order based on such reports.<lb/>
</p>

<p>20.7. Moreover, the reference made by the appellant to<lb/>
 the order of the Central Electricity Regulatory Commission,<lb/>
 New Delhi, dated 19.6.2014; and various newspaper reports<lb/>
 and the contents of the TANGEDCO website is of no<lb/>
 consequence, as the project referred to in the order of the<lb/>
 CERC is in operation as on date, and with regard to newspaper<lb/>
 reports, it is stated that TANGEDCO cannot act on media<lb/>
 reports and has to act only based on acceptable documents<lb/>
 furnished by the bidders.<lb/>
</p>

<p>20.8. With regard to the past performance of the<lb/>
 appellant, it is submitted by the learned Advocate General that<lb/>
 most of the projects undertaken by them are sub-critical<lb/>
 projects. That apart, the work involved in BTG (Boiler Turbine<lb/>
 Generator) is only 40% of the total work involved in<lb/>
 supercritical project.<lb/>
 The scheduled completion period in<lb/>
 respect of one of the projects undertaken by the members of<lb/>
 the appellant consortium was delayed for years, and in yet<lb/>
 another project the name of the appellant consortium is not<lb/>
 found.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(K) ALTERNATIVE REMEDY:<lb/>
</p>

<p>21. The writ petition is not maintainable because of the<lb/>
 alternative remedy of appeal available under Section 11 of the<lb/>
 TTIT Act. All the issues now raised by the appellant have to be<lb/>
 gone into by the Appellate Authority both factually and legally.<lb/>
 There is a statute and there is a statutory appeal. With regard<lb/>
 to the plea of the appellant that the appeal would be from<lb/>
 Caesar to Caesar, the learned Advocate General submitted that<lb/>
 in terms of Rules 9 and 12 of the Tamil Nadu Government<lb/>
 Business Rules the appeal has to be decided by the Hon&apos;ble<lb/>
 Minister and the signing authority is the Secretary to the<lb/>
 Government of the department concerned and, therefore, the<lb/>
 appeal if filed would be decided on its own individual merits.<lb/>
 The writ petitions are liable to be rejected on the plea of<lb/>
 alternative remedy.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(L) FINANCIAL STATUS OF THE APPELLANT:<lb/>
</p>

<p>22. With regard to the financial status of the appellant,<lb/>
 the Chief Engineer/Projects, TANGEDCO has filed an affidavit<lb/>
 dated 25.8.2015 stating that proceedings have been initiated<lb/>
 under Securitization and Reconstruction of Financial Assets and<lb/>
 Security Interest Act, 2002 against Trishe Renewable Energy<lb/>
 Services Limited, to which proceedings the appellant stood as<lb/>
 guarantor and, therefore, it is submitted that all is not well<lb/>
 with the financial status of the appellant and it is pleaded that<lb/>
 this subsequent event should also be considered by the Court<lb/>
 to assess the conduct of the appellant.<lb/>
 CONTENTIONS RAISED ON BEHALF OF THE THIRD<lb/>
 RESPONDENT<lb/>
</p>

<p>23.1. Mr.Krishna Srinivas, learned counsel appearing for<lb/>
 the third respondent contended that the appellant lacks the<lb/>
 basic credibility to make any allegation against the third<lb/>
 respondent. The Consortium Agreement itself was born on<lb/>
 11.5.2013, after the Notice Inviting Tender was issued on<lb/>
 6.5.2013. Trishe, the local company, was incorporated on<lb/>
 31.10.2011 and there is no material produced to justify their<lb/>
 competence in the field of energy. The entire focus is only on<lb/>
 CSEPDI, which is a design institute. He pleaded that a reading<lb/>
 of Brief Introduction and Achievement shows that CSEPDI<lb/>
 undertook only design projects and they are not EPC Projects.<lb/>
 In effect, it is argued that design is the core area of the leader<lb/>
 of the consortium and moreover, they have no experience in<lb/>
 India insofar as supercritical Thermal Power Projects.<lb/>
</p>

<p>23.2. He pleaded that BHEL has been granted<lb/>
 &quot;Maharatna&quot; status by the Department of Heavy Industries,<lb/>
 Ministry of Heavy Industries and Public Enterprises,<lb/>
 Government of India, which has been so far awarded to only<lb/>
 seven Central Public Sector Enterprises in the country.<lb/>
 He<lb/>
 also brought to the notice of this Court the various awards<lb/>
 given to BHEL by the Ministry of Power for Outstanding<lb/>
 Performance.<lb/>
</p>

<p>23.3. It is pleaded that the present tender is an<lb/>
 International Competitive Bidding, whereas the consortium has<lb/>
 got private contracts to the maximum by negotiation.<lb/>
</p>

<p>23.4. With regard to the letter of the Hon&apos;ble Chief<lb/>
 Minister dated 25.11.2013 addressed to the Hon&apos;ble Prime<lb/>
 Minister of India, it is pleaded that BHEL has not been singled<lb/>
 out, so vendor rating need not fall and this does not vitiate the<lb/>
 fact that the third respondent has done a lot in the power<lb/>
 sector.<lb/>
</p>

<p>23.5. With regard to the reports of the CAG; the order of<lb/>
 the CERC and other newspaper reports, he reiterated the<lb/>
 submissions made by the learned Advocate General.<lb/>
</p>

<p>23.6. The third respondent produced a status report of<lb/>
 the project, stating that the work is under progress and they<lb/>
 have expended substantial amount.<lb/>
 REPLY OF THE APPELLANT<lb/>
</p>

<p>24.1. Refuting the above said contentions made on behalf<lb/>
 of the respondents, Mr.Sriram Panchu, learned Senior Counsel<lb/>
 appearing for the appellant argued that:<lb/>
</p>

<p>(i)The Consultant&apos;s report is dated 30.5.2014 and the<lb/>
 Consultant in any way declared that BHEL is L1. That apart,<lb/>
 the day on which the Consultant&apos;s report was submitted,<lb/>
 namely 30.5.2014, is a Friday and there is no chance for the<lb/>
 Board to take a decision by 2.6.2014, namely within two<lb/>
 days (Saturday and Sunday), after scrutinizing voluminous<lb/>
 records submitted by the appellant, BHEL and the<lb/>
 Consultant.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(ii)The Board Level Technical Committee is also not the<lb/>
 Tender Accepting Authority. They cannot declare BHEL as<lb/>
 L1. Only the Board can do it and it cannot delegate the<lb/>
 legal duty cast on it to the BLTC. At best, BLTC can be an<lb/>
 evaluation or scrutiny committee, but not Tender Accepting<lb/>
 Authority. When the appellant submitted representations,<lb/>
 BHEL was not L1 and, therefore, the representations should<lb/>
 have been considered, more so, in compliance of the<lb/>
 direction of the Division Bench of this Court in the judgment<lb/>
 dated 19.8.2014 made in W.A.No.1065 of 2014.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(iii)In the representation dated 13.6.2014, it has been<lb/>
 clearly stated that &quot;there shall be No Commitment Fee, if<lb/>
 the loan amount is fully utilized as per the Schedule spelt<lb/>
 out in the Financial Contract.&quot; Despite such stand taken by<lb/>
 the appellant, the TANGEDCO has included it.<lb/>
 (iv)<lb/>
 It is pleaded that the Consultant has loaded on the<lb/>
 appellant an upfront fee (including interest) of Rs.801.18<lb/>
 Crores. According to the appellant, if Commitment Fee and<lb/>
 the Interest on Management Fee and Guarantee Fee are<lb/>
 excluded and accordingly, the Moratorium Interest is<lb/>
 reduced to Rs.17.875 Crores, the Consultant could have<lb/>
 only loaded Rs.489.136 Crores. However, the Consultant<lb/>
 has erroneously evaluated the bid of the appellant at<lb/>
 Rs.9207.264 Crores.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(v)Moreover, if the appellant&apos;s offer dated 5.6.2014 for<lb/>
 reduction of interest rate from 7.2% per annum to 6.2% per<lb/>
 annum had been accepted, TANGEDCO would have saved<lb/>
 over Rs.1300 Crores on the Total Cost of Ownership basis.<lb/>
 The appellant offered reduction of interest rate from 7.2%<lb/>
 to 6.2% much before the third respondent offered interest<lb/>
 reduction from 12.25% to 12.15% only on 27.6.2014,<lb/>
 however the same was not considered by TANGEDCO.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(vi)With regard to the fixed rate of interest, it was pointed<lb/>
 out that in the email dated 10.1.2014 sent by the Chief<lb/>
 Engineer, enclosing a tabular column, it is specifically<lb/>
 clarified at Sl.No.9 with regard to &quot;Interest Rate&quot; that &quot;the<lb/>
 fixed rate of interest has already been indicated in the<lb/>
 Financial Term Sheet and the exact value has been<lb/>
 submitted along with the price bid&quot;. This, even according to<lb/>
 TANGEDCO, was the bidder&apos;s response vide letters dated<lb/>
 18.12.2013 and 7.1.2014. If any clarification was required,<lb/>
 the same ought to have been sought for, as in the case of<lb/>
 the third respondent, before taking a decision on who is L1.<lb/>
 Failure to consider renders the decision making process bad<lb/>
 on account of procedural impropriety, one of tenets of<lb/>
 Wednesbury&apos;s Principle.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(vii)As per Section 10(1) of the TTIT Act, the Tender<lb/>
 Accepting Authority shall cause an objective evaluation of<lb/>
 the tenders taking into consideration the prevailing market<lb/>
 rate for procurement. The appellant is procuring money.<lb/>
 Therefore, the Tender Accepting Authority should take into<lb/>
 account the prevailing market rate, saving interest to the<lb/>
 tune of Rs.1300 Crores. This is an issue that should have<lb/>
 been considered in public interest.<lb/>
</p>

<p>24.2. Mr.N.L.Rajah, learned counsel for the appellant<lb/>
 argued that:<lb/>
</p>

<p>(i)As per Clause 14.0 of the Instructions to Bidders, more<lb/>
 specifically Clause 14.0(b), the Financing Term Sheet shall<lb/>
 be based on preliminary appraisal of the project jointly by<lb/>
 the bidder and the lender satisfying themselves on the<lb/>
 project financial viability. Laying emphasis on the term<lb/>
 &quot;preliminary&quot; it is pleaded that it is only a preliminary stage<lb/>
 and the TANGEDCO ought to have called for clarifications, if<lb/>
 so advised. If in the repayment schedule the appellant has<lb/>
 stated anything wrong, the lender will rectify it, there is<lb/>
 nothing for the TANGEDCO to ring alarm bells.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(ii)The poor performance in executing the project by BHEL,<lb/>
 referred to in the order of CERC, is not only on account of<lb/>
 shutdown, but also on technical reasons and, therefore, the<lb/>
 past performance of BHEL should also be considered.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(iii)The CAG report says Rs.3200 Crores is to be collected<lb/>
 from BHEL by TANGEDCO, but there is no reply from<lb/>
 TANGEDCO. Even if the CAG report requires approval from<lb/>
 the Public Undertakings Committee, there must be an<lb/>
 answer by the TANGEDCO to the Court as to the veracity of<lb/>
 the said disclosure in the CAG report.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(iv)It cannot be said that the appellant is a private player<lb/>
 and just because the appellant is a private enterprise, it<lb/>
 cannot be disregarded. The appellant produced End-user<lb/>
 Certificates. However, the learned Single Judge has held<lb/>
 that the appellant has no experience in India, when the<lb/>
 tender is an International Competitive Bidding. The learned<lb/>
 Single Judge has erroneously restricted the scope of the<lb/>
 work to the projects done only in India.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(v)It is stated that on 2.6.2014, BHEL was identified as L1.<lb/>
 However, on 18.7.2014 TANGEDCO submitted before the<lb/>
 Court in the first round of litigation that performance<lb/>
 evaluation is yet to be done and they will look into the<lb/>
 representation of the appellant. Therefore, BHEL could not<lb/>
 have been identified as L1 by then and the entire<lb/>
 proceedings reeks of malafide.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(vi)Sections 10(2) and 10(6) of the TTIT Act should be read<lb/>
 together. If at all Section 10(3) of the Act is to be invoked<lb/>
 by the Authority, it can only be after 26.9.2014, on which<lb/>
 day the Board resolved to accept the tender of the third<lb/>
 respondent in compliance of Section 10(6) of the TTIT Act.<lb/>
 Therefore, for negotiation under Section 10(3) of the TTIT<lb/>
 Act, the appellant should have also been called for.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(vii)The non-obstante clause in Section 10(3) of the TTIT<lb/>
 Act should be read harmoniously and should not obliterate<lb/>
 the effect of Section 10(2) of the TTIT Act. Section 10(2) of<lb/>
 the TTIT Act states that after evaluation and comparison of<lb/>
 tenders, the Tender Accepting Authority shall accept the<lb/>
 lowest tender. Only after evaluation, the Tender Accepting<lb/>
 Authority can come to a conclusion as to who is the lowest<lb/>
 tenderer. Only after that stage, negotiation under Section<lb/>
 10(3) of the TTIT Act should have been called for and not as<lb/>
 stated by the learned Advocate General immediately after<lb/>
 Section 10(2) of the TTIT Act.<lb/>
 CONSIDERATION<lb/>
</p>

<p>25. We have heard the rival contentions at length,<lb/>
 perused the order passed by the learned Single Judge; the<lb/>
 documents filed in these appeals; the records produced before<lb/>
 this Court as was produced before the learned Single Judge,<lb/>
 and given our anxious consideration to the issue involved in<lb/>
 these appeals. We heard the appellant and the respondents<lb/>
 for several days, i.e., 3.6.2015, 9.6.2015, 10.6.2015,<lb/>
 16.6.2015, 19.6.2015, 25.6.2015, 1.7.2015, 15.7.2015,<lb/>
 16.7.2015, 20.7.2015, 21.7.2015, 22.7.2015, 23.7.2015,<lb/>
 27.7.2015, 29.7.2015, 31.7.2015, 7.8.2015, 20.8.2015,<lb/>
 21.8.2015, 24.8.2015 and 25.8.2015, in the course of our<lb/>
 regular hearing, some in part and the rest specifically at their<lb/>
 request.<lb/>
 ALTERNATIVE REMEDY<lb/>
</p>

<p>26.1. With regard to the plea of the learned Advocate<lb/>
 General that the appellant instead of filing an appeal as<lb/>
 contemplated under Section 11 of the TTIT Act has directly<lb/>
 invoked the writ jurisdiction and, therefore, the writ<lb/>
 proceedings are not maintainable, it is to be noted that the<lb/>
 learned Single Judge in the order under challenge has clearly<lb/>
 observed that:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;38. Incidentally, one more contention was raised in<lb/>
 this regard, with respect to the failure of the first<lb/>
 respondent to notify the appellate authority under<lb/>
 Section 11 of the Tamil Nadu Transparency in<lb/>
 Tenders Act, 1998. But, in this case, there is actually<lb/>
 no scope for considering the said contention. As<lb/>
 admitted by the petitioner themselves, the<lb/>
 supplementary bid was submitted by them on<lb/>
 05.02.2014. Thereafter, the petitioner sent several<lb/>
 representations not only to the first respondent, but<lb/>
 also to the Government on 16.6.2014, 17.6.2014,<lb/>
 01.7.2014 and 08.7.2014. These representations<lb/>
 were addressed to all important officers of the<lb/>
 Government, including the Chief Secretary, the<lb/>
 Secretary to Government, Environment and Forests,<lb/>
 etc. The petitioner even came up with a writ petition<lb/>
 in W.P.No.19247 of 2014 seeking a Mandamus to<lb/>
 direct the first respondent to dispose of his<lb/>
 representations. Therefore, this is a case where<lb/>
 the petitioner ignited the fire of litigation much<lb/>
 before the finalisation of the tenders. In such<lb/>
 circumstances, I do not think that the<lb/>
 notification of an Appellate Authority would<lb/>
 have really made a difference. In any case, I<lb/>
 do not propose to hold the non availing of an<lb/>
 alternative remedy of appeal under Section 11<lb/>
 against the petitioner . This is the second round<lb/>
 of litigation in respect of the same contract,<lb/>
 with the first one preceding the finalisation.<lb/>
 Therefore, this incidental plea relating to non<lb/>
 notification of the Appellate Authority cannot be<lb/>
 accepted by me.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</item>

<p>26.2. In respect of challenge to tender, Courts have been<lb/>
 entertaining the writ petition on certain parameters and<lb/>
 availability of an alternative remedy is not an absolute<lb/>
 embargo. The said view of this Court is fortified by the<lb/>
 following decisions:<lb/>
</p>

<p>(a) In Harbanslal Sahnia v. Indian Oil Corporation Ltd., (2003)<lb/>
 2 SCC 107, the Supreme Court held as under:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;In an appropriate case in spite of availability<lb/>
 of the alternative remedy, the High Court may<lb/>
 still exercise its writ jurisdiction in at least<lb/>
 three contingencies: (i) where the writ petition<lb/>
 seeks enforcement of any of the Fundamental<lb/>
 Rights; (ii) where there is failure of principles<lb/>
 of natural justice or, (iii) where the orders or<lb/>
 proceedings are wholly without jurisdiction or<lb/>
 the vires of an Act and is challenged [ See<lb/>
 Whirlpool Corporation v. Registrar of Trade<lb/>
 Marks, Mumbai and Ors ., (1998) 8 SCC 11. The<lb/>
 present case attracts applicability of first two<lb/>
 contingencies. Moreover, as noted, the petitioners&apos;<lb/>
 dealership, which is their bread and butter came to<lb/>
 be terminated for an irrelevant and non-existent<lb/>
 cause. In such circumstances, we feel that the<lb/>
 appellants should have been allowed relief by the<lb/>
 High Court itself instead of driving them to the need<lb/>
 of initiating arbitration proceedings.&quot;<lb/>
</item>
<item>

	(emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</item>

<p>(b) In ABL International Ltd. v. Export Credit Guarantee<lb/>
 Corporation of India Ltd., (2004) 3 SCC 553, the Supreme<lb/>
 Court held as under:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;8. As could be seen from the arguments addressed in this<lb/>
 appeal and as also from the divergent views of the two<lb/>
 courts below one of the questions that falls for our<lb/>
 consideration is whether a writ petition under Article 226<lb/>
 of the Constitution of India is maintainable to enforce a<lb/>
 contractual obligation of the State or its instrumentality, by<lb/>
 an aggrieved party.<lb/>
 ***<lb/>
</item>

<item>23. It is clear from the above observations of this<lb/>
 Court, once State or an instrumentality of State is a<lb/>
 party to the contract, it has an obligation in law to<lb/>
 act fairly, justly and reasonably which is the<lb/>
 requirement of Article 14 of the Constitution of<lb/>
 India. Therefore, if by the impugned repudiation of<lb/>
 the claim of the appellants the first respondent as<lb/>
 an instrumentality of the State has acted in<lb/>
 contravention of the above said requirement of<lb/>
 article 14 then we have no hesitation that a writ<lb/>
 court can issue suitable directions to set right the<lb/>
 arbitrary actions of the first respondent.<lb/>
 ***<lb/>
</item>

<item>28. However, while entertaining an objection as to<lb/>
 the maintainability of a writ petition under Article<lb/>
 226 of the Constitution of India, the court should<lb/>
 bear in mind the fact that the power to issue<lb/>
 prerogative writs under Article 226 of the<lb/>
 Constitution is plenary in nature and is not limited<lb/>
 by any other provisions of the Constitution. The High<lb/>
 Court having regard to the facts of the case, has a<lb/>
 discretion to entertain or not to entertain a writ<lb/>
 petition. The Court has imposed upon itself certain<lb/>
 restrictions in the exercise of this power [See :<lb/>
 Whirlpool Corporation v. Registrar of Trade Marks, Mumbai<lb/>
 and Ors.] And this plenary right of the High Court to<lb/>
 issue a prerogative writ will not normally be<lb/>
 exercised by the Court to the exclusion of other<lb/>
 available remedies unless such action of the State or<lb/>
 its instrumentality is arbitrary and unreasonable so<lb/>
 as to violate the constitutional mandate of Article 14<lb/>
 or for other valid and legitimate reasons, for which<lb/>
 the court thinks it necessary to exercise the said<lb/>
 jurisdiction.<lb/>
</item>

<item>***<lb/>
</item>

<item>53. From the above, it is clear that when an<lb/>
 instrumentality of the State acts contrary to public<lb/>
 interest, unfairly, unjustly and unreasonably, in its<lb/>
 contractual, constitutional or statutory obligations,<lb/>
 it really acts contrary to the constitutional<lb/></item><item>
 guarantee found in Article 14 of the Constitution.&quot;<lb/>
 (c) In Coal India Ltd. v. Alok Fuels (P) Ltd., (2010) 10 SCC<lb/>
 157, the Supreme Court observed as under:<lb/>
 &quot;</item>

<item>15. It is settled by a series of decisions of this Court starting<lb/>
 from Kumari Shrilekha Vidyarthi v. State of U.P. [(1991) 1<lb/>
 SCC 537] that even in the domain of contractual mat-<lb/>
ters, the High Court can entertain a writ petition on the<lb/>
 ground of violation of Article 14 of the Constitution<lb/>
 when the impugned act of the State or its instrumental-<lb/>
ity is arbitrary, unfair or unreasonable or in breach of<lb/>
 obligations under public law. In Sterling Computers Ltd. v.<lb/>
 M/s M &amp; N Publications Limited and Others [(1993) 1 SCC<lb/>
 445] in para 28, however, this Court held:<lb/>
 &apos;Public authorities are essentially different from those<lb/>
 of private persons. Even while taking decision in<lb/>
 respect of commercial transactions a public authority<lb/>
 must be guided by relevant considerations and not by<lb/>
 irrelevant ones.&apos;&quot;<lb/></item><item>
 (emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</item>

<p>(d) In Union of India v. Tantia Construction Private Limited,<lb/>
 (2011) 5 SCC 697, the Supreme Court has categorically held<lb/>
 that:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;… even on the question of maintainability of the writ<lb/>
 petition on account of the Arbitration Clause included in<lb/>
 the agreement between the parties, it is now well-<lb/>
established that an alternative remedy is not an<lb/>
 absolute bar to the invocation of the writ<lb/>
 jurisdiction of the High Court or the Supreme Court<lb/>
 and that without exhausting such alternative<lb/>
 remedy, a writ petition would not be maintainable.<lb/>
 The various decisions cited by Mr. Chakraborty would<lb/>
 clearly indicate that the constitutional powers vested<lb/>
 in the High Court or the Supreme Court cannot be<lb/>
 fettered by any alternative remedy available to the<lb/>
 authorities. Injustice, whenever and wherever it<lb/>
 takes place, has to be struck down as an anathema<lb/>
 to the rule of law and the provisions of the<lb/>
 Constitution. We endorse the view of the High Court<lb/>
 that notwithstanding the provisions relating to the<lb/>
 Arbitration Clause contained in the agreement, the High<lb/>
 Court was fully within its competence to entertain and<lb/>
 dispose of the Writ Petition filed on behalf of the<lb/>
 Respondent Company.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>(e) In Maa Binda Express Carrier and another v. North-East<lb/>
 Frontier Railway and others, (2014) 3 SCC 760, the Supreme<lb/>
 Court held as under:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;9. Suffice it to say that in the matter of award<lb/>
 of contracts the Government and its agencies<lb/>
 have to act reasonably and fairly at all points<lb/>
 of time. To that extent the tenderer has an<lb/>
 enforceable right in the Court who is<lb/>
 competent to examine whether the aggrieved<lb/>
 party<lb/>
 has<lb/>
 been<lb/>
 treated<lb/>
 unfairly<lb/>
 or<lb/>
 discriminated against to the detriment of<lb/>
 public interest. (See: Meerut Development<lb/>
 Authority v. Association of Management Studies and<lb/>
 Anr. etc. (2009) 6 SCC 171 and Air India Ltd. v.<lb/>
 Cochin International Airport Ltd. (2000) 1 SCR 505).<lb/>
 10. The scope of judicial review in contractual<lb/>
 matters was further examined by this Court in Tata<lb/>
 Cellular v. Union of India, (1994) 6 SCC 651,<lb/>
 Raunaq International Ltd.&apos;s case (supra) and in<lb/>
 Jagdish Mandal v. State of Orissa and Ors. (2007)<lb/>
 14 SCC 517 besides several other decisions to which<lb/>
 we need not refer. In Michigan Rubber (India) Ltd. v.<lb/>
 State of Karnataka and Ors., (2012) 8 SCC 216, the<lb/>
 legal position on the subject was summed up after a<lb/>
 comprehensive review and principles of law<lb/>
 applicable to the process for judicial review identified<lb/>
 in the following words:<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;19. From the above decisions, the following<lb/>
 principles emerge:<lb/>
</item>

<item>(a) the basic requirement of Article 14 is<lb/>
 fairness in action by the State, and non-<lb/>
arbitrariness in essence and substance is the<lb/>
 heartbeat of fair play. These actions are<lb/>
 amenable to the judicial review only to the<lb/>
 extent that the State must act validly for a<lb/>
 discernible reason and not whimsically for<lb/>
 any ulterior purpose. If the State acts within<lb/>
 the bounds of reasonableness, it would be<lb/>
 legitimate to take into consideration the<lb/>
 national priorities;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(b) fixation of a value of the tender is<lb/>
 entirely within the purview of the executive<lb/>
 and courts hardly have any role to play in<lb/>
 this process except for striking down such<lb/>
 action of the executive as is proved to be<lb/>
 arbitrary<lb/>
 or<lb/>
 unreasonable.<lb/>
</item>

<item>If<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 Government acts in conformity with certain<lb/>
 healthy standards and norms such as<lb/>
 awarding of contracts by inviting tenders, in<lb/>
 those circumstances, the interference by<lb/>
 Courts is very limited;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(c) In the matter of formulating conditions<lb/>
 of a tender document and awarding a<lb/>
 contract, greater latitude is required to be<lb/>
 conceded to the State authorities unless the<lb/>
 action of tendering authority is found to be<lb/>
 malicious and a misuse of its statutory<lb/>
 powers, interference by Courts is not<lb/>
 warranted;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(d) Certain preconditions or qualifications for<lb/>
 tenders have to be laid down to ensure that<lb/>
 the contractor has the capacity and the<lb/>
 resources to successfully execute the work;<lb/>
 and<lb/>
</item>

<item>(e) If the State or its instrumentalities act<lb/>
 reasonably, fairly and in public interest in<lb/>
 awarding contract, here again, interference<lb/>
 by Court is very restrictive since no person<lb/>
 can claim fundamental right to carry on<lb/>
 business with the Government.<lb/>
</item>

<item>20. Therefore, a Court before interfering in<lb/>
 tender or contractual matters, in exercise of<lb/>
 power of judicial review, should pose to<lb/>
 itself the following questions:<lb/>
</item>

<item>(i) Whether the process adopted or decision<lb/>
 made by the authority is mala fide or<lb/>
 intended to favour someone; or whether the<lb/>
 process adopted or decision made is so<lb/>
 arbitrary and irrational that the court can<lb/>
 say: &quot;the decision is such that no<lb/>
 responsible authority acting reasonably and<lb/>
 in accordance with relevant law could have<lb/>
 reached&quot;; and (ii) Whether the public<lb/>
 interest is affected. If the answers to the<lb/>
 above questions are in negative, then there<lb/>
 should be no interference under Article<lb/>
 226.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</item>

<p>26.3. In any event, the TANGEDCO has not filed any<lb/>
 appeal challenging the said portion of the order of the learned<lb/>
 Single Judge. This is the fourth litigation on this tender and<lb/>
 mostly the allegation is on the first respondent on the ground<lb/>
 of arbitrariness, unjust and unfair treatment, besides being<lb/>
 against public interest. Therefore, the plea of alternative<lb/>
 remedy has no bearing at this point of time. Accordingly, this<lb/>
 Court does not propose to entertain the said plea of availability<lb/>
 of alternative remedy at this stage and would proceed to<lb/>
 consider the appeals as under.<lb/>
 SCOPE OF CONSIDERATION<lb/>
</p>

<p>27. We are of the considered opinion that these appeals<lb/>
 will have to be tested on the touchstone of the tests laid down<lb/>
 by the Supreme Court in Jagdish Mandal v. State of Orissa,<lb/>
 (2007) 14 SCC 517, wherein it is held as under:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;24. Therefore, a court before interfering in<lb/>
 tender or contractual matters, in exercise of<lb/>
 power of judicial review, should pose to itself the<lb/>
 following questions:<lb/>
</item>

<item>(i) Whether the process adopted or<lb/>
 decision made by the authority is mala fide<lb/>
 or intended to favour someone; or whether<lb/>
 the process adopted or decision made is so<lb/>
 arbitrary and irrational that the court can<lb/>
 say: &apos;the decision is such that no<lb/>
 responsible authority acting reasonably<lb/>
 and in accordance with relevant law could<lb/>
 have reached&apos;? and<lb/></item><item>
 (ii) Whether the public interest is affected?<lb/>
 If the answers to the above questions are<lb/>
 in the negative, then there should be no<lb/>
 interference under Article 226.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>(emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</p>

<p>(I) FIRST TEST -TENDERING PROCESS:<lb/>
</p>

<p>28. On the basis of the law enunciated in the decision<lb/>
 referred supra, let us at first analyze the process adopted and<lb/>
 decision made in the tender by TANGEDCO.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(A) IS THE PROCEDURE FLAWED?<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.1. On 6.5.2013, TANGEDCO invited tenders for 2 x<lb/>
 660 MW Ennore SEZ Supercritical Thermal Power Project at<lb/>
 Ash Dyke of NCTPS, Chennai -600 057. During July, 2013, the<lb/>
 bids submitted by the appellant and the third respondent were<lb/>
 taken up for consideration. By letter dated 3.2.2014, the<lb/>
 second respondent requested the appellant to submit its<lb/>
 supplementary price schedule. In due compliance of the same,<lb/>
 the appellant submitted its Supplementary Price Bid on<lb/>
 5.2.2014.<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.2. The second respondent opened the price bid<lb/>
 submitted by the appellant and the third respondent in the<lb/>
 presence of their respective representatives on 5.2.2014 itself.<lb/>
 It is borne out by records and the files produced, as was<lb/>
 produced before the learned Single Judge, that the appellant&apos;s<lb/>
 quoted price of Rs.9709.3822 was evaluated at Rs.9207.258<lb/>
 Crores by the Consultant after disallowing a sum of Rs.508<lb/>
 Crores and thereafter certain amounts are added, which tilted<lb/>
 the balance in favour of the third respondent (BHEL). The<lb/>
 report of the Consultant, we wish to state was not revealed<lb/>
 before the learned Single Judge, in the first round of litigation,<lb/>
 while the Court passed the two interim orders, as above, and<lb/>
 the Division Bench on 19.8.2014. It is not stated so in the<lb/>
 counter affidavit or in the appeal memorandum. So to say it<lb/>
 was not in public domain.<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.3. Even prior to filing of the first writ petition<lb/>
 (W.P.No.19247 of 2014) on 17.7.2014, the appellant offered<lb/>
 reduction of interest from 7.2% to 6.2% on 5.6.2014 itself.<lb/>
 Thereafter, the appellant sent representations to the first<lb/>
 respondent on 16.6.2014, 17.6.2014, 1.7.2014 and 8.7.2014<lb/>
 impressing upon them the various aspects of the Bid, namely,<lb/>
 lowering of interest, commitment fee, interest on management<lb/>
 fee and guarantee fee, etc., and the relevance of Clause<lb/>
 29(viii) of the Instructions to Bidders in the matter of bid<lb/>
 consideration, particularly in the context of various materials<lb/>
 on the vendor rating and the poor track record of the third<lb/>
 respondent, and also inviting their attention to the wrong and<lb/>
 improper calculations made contrary to financial statements<lb/>
 submitted by the appellant. It is apposite to refer to Clause<lb/>
 29.0 (viii) of the Instructions to Bidders, which reads as under:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;29.0. Rejection of Bids:<lb/>
 The tender shall be rejected if it is:<lb/>
</item>

<item>(i) to (vii) ***<lb/>
</item>

<item>(viii)<lb/>
 From<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 tenderer<lb/>
 whose<lb/>
 past<lb/>
 performance/vendor rating is not satisfactory.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>29.4. As the representations sent by the appellant did not<lb/>
 evoke any response, the appellant filed W.P.No.19247 of 2014<lb/>
 seeking issuance of a writ of Mandamus to direct respondents<lb/>
 1 and 2 to consider the appellant&apos;s representations dated<lb/>
 16.6.2014, 17.6.2014, 1.7.2014 and 8.7.2014 and take<lb/>
 necessary action on the same in strict compliance with law,<lb/>
 particularly in accordance with Sections 10(1) and 10(2) of the<lb/>
 TTIT Act read with Clause 29 of the Tender Documents issued<lb/>
 by TANGEDCO.<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.5. In the interim order dated 18.7.2014 passed in<lb/>
 M.P.No.1 of 2014 in W.P.No.19247 of 2014, it is specifically<lb/>
 recorded as under:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;3. .... The learned Advocate General would further<lb/>
 submit that in respect of tenders floated, Techno-<lb/>
Commercial bid was opened on 27.06.2014 and the<lb/>
 price bid was opened on 8.6.2014 and the<lb/>
 performance evaluation is yet to be done and<lb/>
 while doing so, all the representations of the<lb/>
 petitioners dated 16.6.2014, 17.6.2014, 1.7.2014<lb/>
 and 8.7.2014 would definitely be considered and<lb/>
 seeks time to get written instructions in this regard.<lb/>
 The said submission of the learned Advocate<lb/>
 General, assisted by Mr.P.Gunaraj, learned counsel<lb/>
 appearing for respondents 1 and 2, on instructions,<lb/>
 is placed on record.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>(emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</item>

<p>The date of opening of price bid along with the Supplementary<lb/>
 Price Bid submitted by both tenderers was 5.2.2014 and not<lb/>
 8.6.2014. This is an error in recording of date.<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.6. Consequent to the above order, the first respondent<lb/>
 addressed a communication dated 20.7.2014 to the Advocate<lb/>
 General, wherein it is averred as under:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;I inform that the post bid representations of the<lb/>
 bidder M/s.CSEPDI-TRISHE CONSORTIUM relating to<lb/>
 the award of contract for establishment of Ennore<lb/>
 SEZ Thermal Power Project cited in the reference,<lb/>
 will be duly considered by the Board of Directors of<lb/>
 TANGEDCO as the tender accepting authority while<lb/>
 finalizing the tender and appropriate order passed<lb/>
 strictly in accordance with the Tender Specifications<lb/>
 and Tamil Nadu Transparency in Tenders Act, 1998<lb/>
 and the Tamil Nadu Transparency in Tender Rules,<lb/>
 2000.&quot;<lb/>
 (emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</item>

<p>29.7. When the said communication dated 20.7.2014 was<lb/>
 produced before the learned Single Judge in the first round of<lb/>
 litigation, an interim order dated 31.7.2014 was passed in<lb/>
 M.P.No.1 of 2014 in W.P.No.19247 of 2014, and it is as follows:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;25. It is well settled position of law that as per the<lb/>
 series of decisions rendered by the Hon&apos;ble Supreme<lb/>
 Court of India in the matter of award of contracts,<lb/>
 the Government and its agency, have to act<lb/>
 reasonably and fairly at all points of time and to that<lb/>
 extent the tender has an enforceable right in the<lb/>
 court which is competent to examine whether the<lb/>
 aggrieved party has been treated unfairly or<lb/>
 discriminated against to the detriment of public<lb/>
 interest.<lb/>
 Therefore, it cannot be said that writ<lb/>
 petition is not maintainable.<lb/>
</item>

<item>26. This Court can take judicial notice of the fact<lb/>
 that this State is reeling under power shortage and<lb/>
 the commissioning of the above said projects is vital<lb/>
 and very much important to the welfare of the State<lb/>
 and therefore, excepts the respondents 1 and 2 to<lb/>
 act fairly and reasonably by considering the<lb/>
 representation of the petitioner dated 16.6.2014,<lb/>
 17.6.2014, 1.7.2014 and 8.7.2014. The letter dated<lb/>
 20.7.2014 addressed to the learned Advocate<lb/>
 General by the Principal Secretary/Chairman-cum-<lb/>
 Managing Director of TANGEDCO also states that the<lb/>
 above said post bid representations submitted by the<lb/>
 petitioner will be duly considered by its Board of<lb/>
 Directors while finalizing the tenders and appropriate<lb/>
 orders will be passed strictly in accordance with the<lb/>
 tender specifications and Tamil Nadu Transparency in<lb/>
 Tenders Act, 1998 and the rules framed thereunder<lb/>
 and being a State Agency, it is under obligation to do<lb/>
 so and till the respondents 1 and 2 considers and<lb/>
 pass orders on the above said representations, after<lb/>
 affording opportunity of personal hearing to the<lb/>
 authorized representatives of the petitioner and<lb/>
 communicate<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 same<lb/>
 to<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 petitioner,<lb/>
 finalization of the bid/tender cannot be done.&quot;<lb/>
 (emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</item>

<p>29.8. Aggrieved by the said interim order dated<lb/>
 31.7.2014 passed in M.P.No.1 of 2014 in W.P.No.19247 of<lb/>
 2014, TANGEDCO filed W.A.No.1065 of 2014 before the<lb/>
 Division Bench. The Division Bench tagged the writ petition<lb/>
 along with the writ appeal and disposed of the same by<lb/>
 common judgment dated 19.8.2014, holding as under:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;12. We have considered the rival submissions made<lb/>
 by the learned counsel on either side and we have<lb/>
 also gone through the order passed by the learned<lb/>
 Single Judge as well as the provisions under the<lb/>
 Tamil Nadu Transparency in Tenders Act, 1998 read<lb/>
 with Rule 27 of the Tamil Nadu Transparency in<lb/>
 Tender Rules, 2000.<lb/>
</item>

<item>13. On a perusal of the statutory provisions, we find<lb/>
 that the rule nowhere contemplates affording of<lb/>
 personal hearing to the person who is objecting.<lb/>
 Hence, the 1 st respondent cannot demand personal<lb/>
 hearing, as a matter of right. However, it is made<lb/>
 clear that if any clarification is required regarding<lb/>
 the documents submitted by the 1 st respondent to<lb/>
 the appellants to consider its objections, the same<lb/>
 shall be called for from the 1 st respondent and if<lb/>
 such clarification is sought, the same shall be<lb/>
 communicated to the 2 nd respondent also and after<lb/>
 considering the clarification to be given by the<lb/>
 1 st respondent, the 1 st appellant shall pass an<lb/>
 order as directed by the learned Single Judge.<lb/>
 It is also made clear that if an opportunity of<lb/>
 personal hearing is afforded to the 1 st respond, if it is<lb/>
 required to be afforded, after considering the<lb/>
 clarification given by the 1 st respondent, the same<lb/>
 shall be extended to the 2 nd respondent also.<lb/>
</item>

<item>14. At this juncture, the learned counsel for the 1 st<lb/>
 respondent submitted that the 1 st respondent is<lb/>
 having some additional materials to prove the<lb/>
 disqualification of the 2 nd respondent and he has<lb/>
 prayed for a reasonable time to submit the said<lb/>
 documents in support of its contention.<lb/>
</item>

<item>15. In view of the above submission made by the<lb/>
 learned counsel for the 1 st respondent, the 1 st<lb/>
 respondent is granted one week time from the<lb/>
 date of receipt of a copy of this order to submit<lb/>
 the additional particulars/documents before<lb/>
 the 1 st appellant along with a copy of this order<lb/>
 and the 1 st appellant shall pass an order as<lb/>
 stated above. The order to be passed by the 1 st<lb/>
 appellant shall be communicated to the 1 st<lb/>
 respondent as well as the 2 nd respondent. The<lb/>
 order of the learned Single Judge is modified<lb/>
 accordingly.&quot;<lb/>
 (emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</item>

<p>29.9. Further to the above said order passed by the<lb/>
 Division Bench, the appellant submitted a representation dated<lb/>
 25.8.2014 enclosing relevant documents. However, the first<lb/>
 respondent vide communication dated 27.9.2014 rejected the<lb/>
 representations submitted by the appellant. This proceedings is<lb/>
 challenged in W.P.No.26762 of 2014.<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.10. Without prejudice to the right of the appellant to<lb/>
 challenge the first respondent&apos;s communication dated<lb/>
 27.9.2014, the appellant sent a representation dated<lb/>
 1.10.2014<lb/>
 to<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 first<lb/>
 respondent<lb/>
 highlighting<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 arbitrariness, anomalies and inconsistencies in its approach<lb/>
 and the malafide writ large in the matter of evaluating the<lb/>
 merits of the third respondent&apos;s bid, despite materials placed<lb/>
 by the appellant for rejection of the third respondent&apos;s bid. It<lb/>
 also pleaded for considering the financial terms clarified before<lb/>
 proceeding to finalize the bid.<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.11. When things stood thus, at the time of hearing of<lb/>
 W.P.No.26762 of 2014, namely on 8.10.2014, the learned<lb/>
 Advocate General produced a copy of the fourth respondent&apos;s<lb/>
 proceedings dated 27.9.2014 addressed to the third<lb/>
 respondent awarding the tender in favour of the third<lb/>
 respondent and the letter of the third respondent dated<lb/>
 27.9.2014 accepting the award of tender.<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.12. Thereafter, the fourth respondent, by proceedings<lb/>
 dated 10.10.2014, informed the appellant that tender has been<lb/>
 finalized and orders have been placed on the evaluated L1<lb/>
 bidder, namely the third respondent.<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.13. Aggrieved by the proceedings dated 27.9.2014 of<lb/>
 the fourth respondent awarding the tender in favour of the<lb/>
 third respondent and the consequential proceedings dated<lb/>
 10.10.2014 informing the appellant that the tender has been<lb/>
 finalized in favour of BHEL, the appellant filed W.P.No.27529 of<lb/>
 2014.<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.14. In this factual matrix, let us analyze the process<lb/>
 adopted in finalizing the tender. At the outset, a reading of the<lb/>
 judgment of the Division Bench of this Court, dated<lb/>
 19.08.2014, makes it clear that but for a clarification that<lb/>
 personal hearing cannot be demanded by the appellant herein,<lb/>
 no part of the order of the learned Single Judge in the first<lb/>
 round of litigation has been modified, which in effect, is a<lb/>
 direction to consider the post-bid representation submitted by<lb/>
 the appellant. The appellant was granted one week time<lb/>
 further to submit additional particulars/documents and the first<lb/>
 respondent was directed to pass orders as directed by the<lb/>
 learned Single Judge, by the Division Bench. Even at this<lb/>
 stage, TANGEDCO never averred or stated before the Division<lb/>
 Bench or before the learned Single Judge that the tender has<lb/>
 been finalized and the third respondent is L1. The date of the<lb/>
 learned Single Judge&apos;s order is 31.07.2014 and the order of<lb/>
 the Division Bench is dated 19.08.2014. The Division Bench did<lb/>
 not modify that portion of the order of the learned Single<lb/>
 Judge directing TANGEDCO not to finalize the bid/tender till<lb/>
 TANGEDCO passes orders on the representation of the<lb/>
 appellant and communicates the same to the appellant.<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.15. This stand clearly reveals that the evaluation<lb/>
 process was going on and nothing was finalized and, therefore,<lb/>
 the claim of the appellant would be considered. This is fortified<lb/>
 by the letter of the Chairman and Managing Director,<lb/>
 TANGEDCO, dated 20.7.2014, wherein it is stated that &quot;post<lb/>
 bid representations of the bidder M/s.CSEPDI-TRISHE<lb/>
 CONSORTIUM relating to the award of contract for<lb/>
 establishment of Ennore SEZ Thermal Power Project cited in<lb/>
 the reference, will be duly considered by the Board of Directors<lb/>
 of TANGEDCO as the tender accepting authority while<lb/>
 finalizing the tender and appropriate order passed strictly in<lb/>
 accordance with the Tender Specifications and Tamil Nadu<lb/>
 Transparency in Tenders Act, 1998 and the Tamil Nadu<lb/>
 Transparency in Tender Rules, 2000.&quot; This undertaking clearly<lb/>
 establishes the case that there was no evaluation of L1. This<lb/>
 contradiction clearly shows that to get over the impasse, the<lb/>
 BLTC decision dated 2.6.2014 is quoted as a decision taken to<lb/>
 identify L1, consequent to which negotiation was done with L1,<lb/>
 i.e., the third respondent (BHEL).<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.16. On the face of it, there appears to be a<lb/>
 misstatement of fact before the Court. If the letter of the<lb/>
 Chairman and Managing Director, TANGEDCO dated 20.7.2014,<lb/>
 recorded by the Court is taken into account, then the<lb/>
 evaluation of L1 said to be done on 2.6.2014 is clearly a<lb/>
 misrepresentation of fact. It was agreed by the Chairman and<lb/>
 Managing Director, TANGEDCO that before finalizing the tender,<lb/>
 all the issues raised in the representations will be considered.<lb/>
 It is on record that the decision on issues raised on financial<lb/>
 aspects, vendor rating, etc., was taken only on 27.9.2014.<lb/>
 The comparative analysis of the tenderers was done in the<lb/>
 month of September, 2014, but the first respondent however<lb/>
 has proceeded to negotiate with the third respondent (BHEL)<lb/>
 on and from 2.6.2014. This is also evident from the various<lb/>
 references cited by the third respondent (BHEL) in their letter<lb/>
 of acceptance dated 27.9.2014.<lb/>
 Simultaneously, the first<lb/>
 respondent has been proceeding with the award of the tender<lb/>
 with the third respondent, despite an undertaking to the Court<lb/>
 in the above terms. We find that this itself is a breach on which<lb/>
 the Court can interfere with, as the tendering process is mired<lb/>
 in illegality and arbitrariness, coupled with bias in favour of the<lb/>
 third respondent. We have no hesitation to hold so.<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.17. The learned Advocate General submitted that on<lb/>
 2.6.2014 itself, a decision was taken by BLTC that the third<lb/>
 respondent was L1 and it was decided to negotiate with them.<lb/>
 It is the plea of TANGEDCO that the Consultant submitted its<lb/>
 report on 30.5.2014.<lb/>
 This could be done only after an<lb/>
 evaluation under Section 10(1) of the Act is completed.<lb/>
 However, in the earlier round of litigation during July and<lb/>
 August, 2014, it was submitted before the Court that<lb/>
 performance evaluation is yet to be done. Such statement of<lb/>
 the learned Advocate General is clearly recorded in the order<lb/>
 dated 18.7.2014 passed in M.P.No.1 of 2014 in W.P.No.19247<lb/>
 of 2014, extracted supra. If such performance evaluation is<lb/>
 yet to be done as on 18.7.2014, it is hard to accept the<lb/>
 submission of the learned Advocate General that on 2.6.2014<lb/>
 itself a decision was taken by BLTC that the third respondent<lb/>
 (BHEL) was L1 and negotiations should be held only with them.<lb/>
 In any event, BLTC cannot step into the shoes of the Tender<lb/>
 Accepting Authority as mandated by Section 10 of the TTIT<lb/>
 Act. Neither the provisions of Section 10 nor any other<lb/>
 provision of TTIT Act provide that the role of the Tender<lb/>
 Accepting Authority could be delegated and such delegatee can<lb/>
 perform the act. When the provisions of the Act prescribe a<lb/>
 thing to be done in a particular manner, it has to be done in<lb/>
 that manner and not otherwise.<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.18. It is not the case of the TANGEDCO at any point of<lb/>
 time, before this Court in the first round of litigation that they<lb/>
 have already accepted BHEL as L1 based on the Consultant&apos;s<lb/>
 report. It is the finding of the learned Single Judge that L1<lb/>
 was identified on 30.5.2014 (i.e.,) the date of the Consultant&apos;s<lb/>
 report, that too, on perusal of the files. That is also not the<lb/>
 recommendation of the Tender Scrutiny Committee or the<lb/>
 decision of the Tender Accepting Authority.<lb/>
 We fail to<lb/>
 understand as to how the Court can set the clock back so as to<lb/>
 enure a benefit to BHEL, which the Tender Accepting Authority<lb/>
 did not decide at that point of time.<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.19. At this juncture, the aspect which gains<lb/>
 prominence is the submission of the learned Advocate General<lb/>
 that BLTC may be treated as Tender Scrutiny Committee. As<lb/>
 per Rule 24 of the TTIT Rules, the Tender Scrutiny Committee<lb/>
 may be constituted to scrutinize the tender documents,<lb/>
 supervise opening of tenders, to carry out the preliminary<lb/>
 examination and detailed evaluation of the tenders received<lb/>
 and to prepare an evaluation report for the consideration of<lb/>
 the Tender Accepting Authority. The BLTC is not the Tender<lb/>
 Accepting Authority.<lb/>
 Section 10 of the TTIT Act, which<lb/>
 prescribes the procedure for evaluation and acceptance of<lb/>
 tender clearly stipulates that evaluation and acceptance should<lb/>
 be done only by the Tender Accepting Authority. Moreover,<lb/>
 there is no reference to the proceedings of the BLTC dated<lb/>
 2.6.2014 in any of the proceedings, either it be the first round<lb/>
 of litigation or before the learned Single Judge in the present<lb/>
 round of litigation, which order is impugned.<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.20.<lb/>
 Despite such direction given by the Division<lb/>
 Bench of this Court on 19.8.2014, it is admitted by TANGEDCO<lb/>
 that they did not go back to the Consultant on the clarifications<lb/>
 provided by the appellant. Moreover, till the date of passing of<lb/>
 the judgment, i.e. 19.8.2014, it is never the case of<lb/>
 TANGEDCO that tender has been finalized in favour of the third<lb/>
 respondent. The first respondent apparently kept the issue<lb/>
 fluid and fixed the dates based on the turn of event. If this is<lb/>
 not an arbitrary and malafide action in the Transparent<lb/>
 Tendering process, we fail to know what else.<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.21. The impugned proceedings dated 27.9.2014 of the<lb/>
 fourth respondent addressed to BHEL, accepting their offer, is<lb/>
 extracted hereunder:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;We are pleased to inform that the Board of<lb/>
 TANGEDCO has accepted your offer as the<lb/>
 successful tenderer and decided to award the<lb/>
 work &apos;Design, engineering, inspection and testing at<lb/>
 manufacturer/sub vendor&apos;s works, supply, storage,<lb/>
 erection, testing and commissioning of complete coal<lb/>
 fired Supercritical Thermal Power Plant including all<lb/>
 Mechanical, Electrical, Civil/Structural/Architectural,<lb/>
 Control &amp; Instrumentation&apos; for the establishment of<lb/>
 2x660 MW Ennore SEZ Supercritical Thermal Power<lb/>
 Project in the ash dyke of North Chennai Thermal<lb/>
 Power Station, Vayalur Village, Tiruvallur District, in<lb/>
 Tamil Nadu, for a total contract price of Rs.7788<lb/>
 Crores (Rupees Seven Thousands Seven Hundreds<lb/>
 and Eighty Eight Crores only), which is inclusive of<lb/>
 CIF component price of Rs.1510 Crores, taxes &amp;<lb/>
 duties under single EPC cum debt financing basis<lb/>
 availing loan from Power Finance Corporation (PFC)<lb/>
 for an amount not less than 75% EPC cost plus<lb/>
 100% IDC with fixed rate of interest @ 12.15%.<lb/>
 The details terms and conditions will be issued<lb/>
 shortly.<lb/>
 Kindly acknowledge the receipt of the<lb/>
 acceptance of award of tender.&quot;<lb/></item><item>
 (emphasis supplied)<lb/></item><item>
 In the written submissions submitted on behalf of TANGEDCO,<lb/>
 it is stated that the 51 st Board Meeting convened on 26.9.2014<lb/>
 decided to pass an order in compliance of Sections 10(2) and<lb/>
 10(6) of the Act, whereby the third respondent (BHEL) was<lb/>
 accepted as L1. Hence, the plea of the first respondent that on<lb/>
 2.6.2014, they could negotiate with the third respondent<lb/>
 (BHEL) on the premise that the third respondent (BHEL) is L1<lb/>
 appears to be a fallacy. It is nothing but an unfair approach in<lb/>
 the tendering process. Procedural impropriety is writ large.<lb/>
 This itself establishes the case that the tender process adopted<lb/>
 and the decision taken by TANGEDCO are malafide or intended<lb/>
 to favour the third respondent (BHEL), besides being arbitrary<lb/>
 and unjust. The TANGEDCO has clearly breached the<lb/>
 undertaking given to the Court and proceeded to negotiate<lb/>
 with the third respondent identifying it as L1.<lb/>
</item>

<p>29.22. The shallowness in the case of the TANGEDCO has<lb/>
 been buttressed by placing reliance on the Consultant&apos;s report<lb/>
 in the order of the learned Single Judge, which was on the<lb/>
 basis of the files circulated in the Court. But on going through<lb/>
 the files, we find that the decision to accept BHEL as L1 was<lb/>
 made on 26.9.2014, in the 51 st Board Meeting of the<lb/>
 TANGEDCO. Therefore, by any stretch of imagination, there<lb/>
 cannot be two evaluations and two tender acceptances one by<lb/>
 the Consultant and the other by the Tender Accepting<lb/>
 Authority. The scheme of Section 10 of the TTIT Act does not<lb/>
 provide that evaluation and comparison of tender as done by<lb/>
 the Consultant should be accepted by the Tender Accepting<lb/>
 Authority. Section 10(1) of the TTIT Act postulates that it is<lb/>
 the Tender Accepting Authority which shall cause objective<lb/>
 evaluation of the tenders based on the schedule of rates<lb/>
 mentioned in the tender document; prevailing market rate for<lb/>
 procurement; and comparison of tenders in accordance with<lb/>
 the procedure and criteria specified in the tender document.<lb/>
 Thereafter, in terms of Section 10(2) of the TTIT Act, after<lb/>
 evaluation and comparison of tenders as specified in Section<lb/>
 10(1) of the TTIT Act, the Tender Accepting Authority shall<lb/>
 accept the lowest tender that too on the basis of objective and<lb/>
 quantifiable factors specified in the tender document. There is<lb/>
 also a further emphasis that relative weights of the<lb/>
 participating tenderers should be made. All this makes it clear<lb/>
 that the Tender Accepting Authority has a role to cause<lb/>
 objective evaluation of the tenders and it cannot merely fall<lb/>
 back on the opinion of the Consultant and they have in this<lb/>
 case just did it that way. It is nothing but abdication of their<lb/>
 role and a stark procedural irregularity. It hits the root of<lb/>
 tendering procedure. At best, the Consultant&apos;s report could be<lb/>
 a guiding factor. The decision making has to be by the Tender<lb/>
 Accepting Authority and not by any other authority, much less<lb/>
 the Consultant.<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.23. Before adverting to the procedure for evaluation<lb/>
 and acceptance of tenders, it is apposite to refer to Sections<lb/>
 10(1), 10(2), 10(3), 10(6) and 10(7) of the TTIT Act, which<lb/>
 read as under:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;10. Evaluation and Acceptance of tender.-<lb/>
</item>

<item>(1) The Tender Accepting Authority shall cause an<lb/>
 objective evaluation of the tenders taking into<lb/>
 consideration the schedule of rates as mentioned in the<lb/>
 tender document and the prevailing market rate for<lb/>
 procurement and comparison of the tenders in accordance<lb/>
 with the procedure and criteria specified in the tender<lb/>
 document.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(2) After evaluation and comparison of tenders as specified<lb/>
 in sub-section (1), the Tender Accepting Authority shall<lb/>
 accept the lowest tender ascertained on the basis of<lb/>
 objective and quantifiable factors specified in the tender<lb/>
 document and giving relative weights among them.<lb/>
</item>


<item>(3) Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (2),<lb/>
 if the Tender Accepting Authority decides that the price of<lb/>
 the lowest tender is higher with reference to the prevailing<lb/>
 market rate or the schedule of rates, he may negotiate for<lb/>
 a reduction of price with that tenderer.<lb/>
</item>

<item>….<lb/>
</item>

<item>(6) If the Tender Accepting Authority proposes to accept<lb/>
 the tender as per the provisions of this section, he shall<lb/>
 pass orders accepting the tender together with reasons for<lb/>
 such acceptance.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(7) The Tender Accepting Authority shall intimate the<lb/>
 information regarding the name and address of the<lb/>
 tenderer whose tender has been accepted along with the<lb/>
 reasons for rejection of other tenders to the appropriate<lb/>
 Tender Bulletin Officers.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>29.24. The procedure for evaluation and acceptance of<lb/>
 tender is specified in Section 10 of the TTIT Act. We are at this<lb/>
 stage concerned with Section 10(6) of the Act, which reads as<lb/>
 under:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;If the Tender Accepting Authority proposes to<lb/>
 accept the tender as per the provisions of this<lb/>
 section, the said authority shall pass orders<lb/>
 accepting the tender together with reasons for<lb/>
 such acceptance.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>In the said proceedings dated 27.9.2014, extracted above, as<lb/>
 pleaded by the appellant, we find no reasons as contemplated<lb/>
 under Section 10(6) of the Act. The learned Single Judge<lb/>
 supports the reasoning of the TANGEDCO that BHEL will not be<lb/>
 interest in knowing the reasons for his acceptance, but that is<lb/>
 not the issue here. The provisions of Section 10(6) of the TTIT<lb/>
 Act state that when the Tender Accepting Authority proposes to<lb/>
 accept the tender as per the provisions of the Act, it is<lb/>
 incumbent on them to pass an order accepting the tender<lb/>
 together with reasons for such acceptance. This should be<lb/>
 considered in the light of the objects of the TTIT Act, which<lb/>
 provides for transparency in tenders. When such reasoned<lb/>
 orders are passed, it gives sufficient material to the other<lb/>
 party to know as to what is the ground on which the tender<lb/>
 has been accepted in favour of the lowest tenderer. Section<lb/>
 10(7) of the TTIT Act provides that the Tender Accepting<lb/>
 Authority should intimate the information regarding the name<lb/>
 and address of the tenderer whose tender has been accepted<lb/>
 along with reasons for rejection of other tenders to the Tender<lb/>
 Bulletin Officers. Therefore, the two provisions need not be<lb/>
 confused with each other. If the question posed is whether the<lb/>
 TANGEDCO has complied with the provisions of Section 10(6)<lb/>
 of the TTIT Act and if the answer is &quot;NO&quot;, then the provisions<lb/>
 of the TTIT Act having not been complied with, the order can<lb/>
 be tested by way of judicial review, as it is not only a clear<lb/>
 breach of the said provision, but also a case of procedural<lb/>
 impropriety, unfair approach and arbitrariness.<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.25. In this context, it would be apposite to refer to an<lb/>
 observation of the Supreme Court in Star Enterprises and<lb/>
 others v. City and Industrial Development Corporation of<lb/>
 Maharashtra Ltd., (1990) 3 SCC 280, wherein it was held as<lb/>
 under:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;In recent times, judicial review of administrative<lb/>
 action has become expansive and is becoming wider<lb/>
 day by day. The traditional limitations have been<lb/>
 vanishing and the sphere of judicial scrutiny is being<lb/>
 expanded. State activity too is becoming fast<lb/>
 pervasive. As the State has descended into the<lb/>
 commercial<lb/>
 field<lb/>
 and<lb/>
 giant<lb/>
 public<lb/>
 sector<lb/>
 undertakings have grown up, the stake of the public<lb/>
 exchequer is also large justifying larger social audit,<lb/>
 judicial control and review by opening of the public<lb/>
 gaze; these necessitate recording of reasons for<lb/>
 executive actions including cases of rejection of<lb/>
 highest offers. That very often involves long stakes<lb/>
 and availability of reasons for action on the record<lb/>
 assures credibility to the action; disciplines public<lb/>
 conduct and improves the culture of accountability.<lb/>
 Looking for reasons in support of such action<lb/>
 provides an opportunity for an objective review in<lb/>
 appropriate cases both by the administrative<lb/>
 superior and by the judicial process. The submission<lb/>
 of Mr. Dwivedi, therefore, commends itself to our<lb/>
 acceptance, namely, that when highest offers of the<lb/>
 type in question are rejected reasons sufficient to<lb/>
 indicate the stand of the appropriate authority<lb/>
 should be made available and ordinarily the same<lb/>
 should be communicated to the concerned parties<lb/>
 unless there be any specific justification not to do<lb/>
 so.&quot;<lb/></item><item>
 (emphasis supplied)<lb/></item><p>
 This was a case where the Supreme Court took a view that<lb/>
 reasons for rejection should be made available to the<lb/>
 concerned parties. The paramount indication in this judgment<lb/>
 is that the State or its instrumentality, in commercial dealings,<lb/>
 should act with credibility; improve culture of accountability;<lb/>
 support actions with reasons for an objective review, and<lb/>
 fairness. That appears to be the substance of Section 10(6) of<lb/>
 the TTIT Act.<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.26. Absence of reasons clearly establishes a case of<lb/>
 procedural impropriety, which is susceptible to judicial review,<lb/>
 in the words of Lord Diplock in Council of Civil Service Unions<lb/>
 v. Minister for the Civil Service [1985] AC 374 at 411, (the<lb/>
 &apos;GCHQ case&apos;):<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;I have described the third head as &quot;procedural<lb/>
 impropriety&quot; rather than failure to observe basic<lb/>
 rules of natural justice or failure to act with<lb/>
 procedural fairness towards the person who will<lb/>
 be affected by the decision. This is because<lb/>
 susceptibility to judicial review under this head<lb/>
 covers also failure by an administrative tribunal<lb/>
 to observe procedural rules that are expressly<lb/>
 laid down in the legislative instrument by which<lb/>
 its jurisdiction is conferred, even where such<lb/>
 failure does not involve any denial of natural<lb/>
 justice.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<item>It is quoted in the words of Professor Helen Fenwick-<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;The development of appropriate administrative<lb/>
 procedures is fundamental to any proper system<lb/>
 of administrative law in the interests of<lb/>
 orderliness, openness, timeousness and justice.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>29.27. As to the necessity for giving reasons under<lb/>
 Section 10(6) of the TTIT Act, it will be worthy to refer to the<lb/>
 decision in Jeyeanthan case [2000] 1 WLR 354, at 359B-359D,<lb/>
 in the words of Lord Woolf,-<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;Because of what can be the very undesirable<lb/>
 consequences of a procedural requirement<lb/>
 which is made so fundamental that any<lb/>
 departure<lb/>
 from<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 requirement<lb/>
 makes<lb/>
 everything that happens thereafter irreversibly<lb/>
 a nullity it is to be hoped that provisions<lb/>
 intended to have this effect will be few and far<lb/>
 between. In the majority of cases, whether the<lb/>
 requirement is categorised as directory or<lb/>
 mandatory, the tribunal before whom the defect<lb/>
 is properly raised has the task of determining<lb/>
 what are to be the consequences of failing to<lb/>
 comply with the requirement in the context of<lb/>
 all the facts and circumstances of the case in<lb/>
 which the issue arises. In such a situation the<lb/>
 tribunal&apos;s task will be to seek to do what is just<lb/>
 in all the circumstances.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>29.28. Reasoning for decision could be tested on the<lb/>
 ground that breach was deliberate, which, we wish to hold in<lb/>
 the present case, reasons have not been recorded deliberately<lb/>
 and thereby, prejudice is apparent on the face of record. The<lb/>
 manner in which evaluation was done and coupled with the<lb/>
 lack of reasons in the proceedings in terms of TTIT Act, will<lb/>
 invalidate the decision of the first respondent in determining<lb/>
 the third respondent as L1. We feel, judicial review should be<lb/>
 rightly exercised in this case to test the decision making<lb/>
 process and we are inclined to do so.<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.29. Insofar as rejection of bid of the appellant is<lb/>
 concerned, drawing strength from the decision of the Supreme<lb/>
 Court in Star Enterprises cases, referred supra, we find that<lb/>
 the TANGEDCO is trying to take shelter by the detailed reply<lb/>
 given on 27.9.2014 stating that reasons for rejection are<lb/>
 contained therein. We are not able to accept such a contention.<lb/>
 The reply of the TANGEDCO is to the representations of the<lb/>
 appellant, which partly contain issues relating to the appellant<lb/>
 and partly relating to the third respondent. There is nothing to<lb/>
 show that it has a detailed evaluation and analysis of the offer<lb/>
 made by the appellant and the reasons as to why their offer<lb/>
 has not been accepted. The recording of reasons for rejection<lb/>
 of the other tenders, namely, unsuccessful tenderers, is<lb/>
 contained in Section 10(7) of the Act. Though it is stated that<lb/>
 the such reasons should be sent to the Tender Bulletin Officer<lb/>
 and the same has been published, we find that the said<lb/>
 publication also calls for further introspection, of which we will<lb/>
 deal with later. At present, we find that the reasons for<lb/>
 rejection of appellant&apos;s representations cannot be termed as<lb/>
 reasons for rejection of the bid of the appellant. Bid is<lb/>
 separate from the substance of the representations. The two<lb/>
 need not be confused, one for the other. The requirement of<lb/>
 recording of reasons is in-built in the provision of Section 10 of<lb/>
 the TTIT Act. The reasons in support of rejection of<lb/>
 representations are based on the direction given by the Court.<lb/>
 The first respondent&apos;s plea is that reasons in the order<lb/>
 rejecting the representation are good enough. We do not<lb/>
 accept that proposition. The requirement of the Act is<lb/>
 compliance of Section 10, i.e. to record reasons which the first<lb/>
 respondent failed to do.<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.30. In our considered opinion, the argument of the<lb/>
 learned Advocate General placing reliance on M.Vasudevan<lb/>
 case that reasons as contemplated under Section 4(1)(d) of<lb/>
 the RTI Act need not be given in contractual matters cannot be<lb/>
 sustained. Moreover, in M.Vasudevan case, referred supra, the<lb/>
 decision of the Supreme Court in Star Enterprises, was not<lb/>
 considered.<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.31. That apart, in Hasbi Traders case, referred supra,<lb/>
 which relates to the erstwhile TNEB, the Division Bench of this<lb/>
 Court held that TNEB is a public authority and even in<lb/>
 contractual matters it cannot have an unfettered discretion.<lb/>
 The argument that tender documents provide for rejecting the<lb/>
 tender without assigning reasons was negatived in the said<lb/>
 decision. This decision has been accepted by the TNEB.<lb/>
</p>

<p>29.32. In such view of the matter, we are of the<lb/>
 considered opinion that reasons as contemplated in Section 10<lb/>
 of the TTIT Act are required to be spelt out and should have<lb/>
 been communicated to the appellant. Non furnishing of the<lb/>
 same runs counter to the decisions of the Supreme Court and<lb/>
 this Court and is also contrary to the provisions of the TTIT<lb/>
 Act.<lb/>
 We, therefore, have no hesitation to hold that the<lb/>
 decision making process is flawed and breach of statutory<lb/>
 provisions.<lb/>
 (B) TENDER BULLETIN:<lb/>
</p>

<p>30.1. It is the contention of the learned Advocate General<lb/>
 that as per Rule 30(3) of the TTIT Rules there is no<lb/>
 requirement that the tender evaluation report should be sent<lb/>
 to the Tender Bulletin Officer and all that is contemplated to be<lb/>
 sent to the Tender Bulletin Officer is a statement of evaluation<lb/>
 of tenders with a comparative statement of tenders received<lb/>
 and decision therein for publication in the Tender Bulletin.<lb/>
</p>

<p>30.2. At the outset, it is to be noted that such publication<lb/>
 in the Tender Bulletin was never produced before the learned<lb/>
 Single Judge. However, the same was produced for the first<lb/>
 time before us stating that the publication has been effected in<lb/>
 the Tender Bulletin on 9.10.2014 in due compliance of Section<lb/>
 10(7) of the TTIT Act and Rule 30(3) of the TTIT Rules. For<lb/>
 better clarity, we extract the relevant portion of the English<lb/>
 translated version of the publication in the Tender Bulletin<lb/>
 hereunder:<lb/>
 &quot;Malar 15, Page 70 &amp; 71 in State Tender Bulletin:09.10.2014<lb/>
 6-TAMILNADU GENERATION AND DISTRIBUTION CORPORATION LIMITED<lb/>
</p>

<item>1.<lb/>
 Name of the Tender<lb/>
 Inviting<lb/>
 Officer,<lb/>
 Designation&amp; Address<lb/>
 : Chief Engineer/Civil/Projects &amp; Environment,<lb/>
 3 rd Floor, NPKRR Maaligai,<lb/>
 144, Anna Salai,<lb/>
 Chennai-600 002<lb/>
</item>

<item>2.<lb/>
 a)<lb/>
 Name<lb/>
 of<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 Project/Details of Purchase<lb/>
 &amp; Works<lb/>
 : Establishment of coal based 2x660 MW<lb/>
 Ennore SEZ Supercritical Thermal Power<lb/>
 Project in the ash dyke of existing<lb/>
 NCTPS under Single EPC cum Debt<lb/>
 Finance basis.<lb/>
 Vayalurvillage, Thiruvallur District,<lb/>
 Tamil Nadu.<lb/>
</item>

<item>Sl.<lb/>
 No.<lb/>
 Details<lb/>
 Tender Value<lb/>
 Decision on Tender<lb/>
</item>

<item>1.<lb/>
 M/s.Bharat Heavy<lb/>
 Electricals Limited,<lb/>
 BHEL House,<lb/>
 Sirifort,<lb/>
 New Delhi-110 049<lb/>
</item>

<item>7840.087 Crores<lb/>
 &amp;<lb/>
 Lender:<lb/>
 Power<lb/>
 Finance Corporation<lb/>
 Limited<lb/>
 Rate of Interest:<lb/>
 12.25%<lb/>
</item>

<item>2.<lb/>
 Consortium<lb/>
 of<lb/>
 Central<lb/>
 Southern<lb/>
 China Electric Power<lb/>
 Design<lb/>
 -<lb/>
M/s.Trishe,<lb/>
 668,<lb/>
 Minz Road, Ughan,<lb/>
 China-430 071<lb/>
</item>

<item>9716.5974 Crores<lb/>
 &amp;<lb/>
 Lender: Industrial &amp;<lb/>
 Commerce Bank of<lb/>
 China<lb/>
 Rate of Interest:<lb/>
</item>

<item>7.2% (USD @ Rs<lb/>
 59.26 at SBI Bill<lb/>
 selling rate)<lb/>
 Out of four bids received<lb/>
 for this work and among<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 qualified<lb/>
 two<lb/>
 bidders, negotiation was<lb/>
 called for &amp; held with the<lb/>
 Lowest<lb/>
 bidder<lb/>
 viz<lb/>
 M/s.BHEL.<lb/>
 After negotiation, tender<lb/>
 value -Rs 7788 Crores,<lb/>
 Rate of Interest at<lb/>
 12.15% was accepted by<lb/>
 the<lb/>
 Chief<lb/>
 Engineer/<lb/>
 Projects and order for<lb/>
 acceptance of the tender<lb/>
 issued vide this office<lb/>
 Lr.No.CE/P/SE/M/EE-<lb/>
10/E/<lb/>
 File.2x660MW<lb/>
 Ennore<lb/>
 SEZ<lb/>
 STPP/D.No.60/dt.27.09.2<lb/>
 014<lb/>
 Finally, M/s BHEL/New Delhi offered bid for Rs 7788 Crores<lb/>
 was accepted by the Chief Engineer/Projects/Chennai and<lb/>
 order for acceptance of the tender was issued vide this<lb/>
 office Lr.No.CE/P/SE/ M/EE-10/E/ File.2x660MW Ennore SEZ<lb/>
 STPP/ D.No.60/ dt.27.09.2014.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>30.3. For better understanding regarding what should be<lb/>
 published in the Tender Bulletin, it would be apposite to refer<lb/>
 to the relevant provisions. Section 6(1) of the TTIT Act reads<lb/>
 as under:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;On receipt of intimation relating to details of<lb/>
 notice of invitation of Tender, from the Tender<lb/>
 Inviting Authority, information relating to<lb/>
 acceptance of tender together with a<lb/>
 comparative analysis and reasons for<lb/>
 acceptance of tenders from the Tender<lb/>
 Accepting Authority, the State or as the case<lb/>
 may be, the District Tender Bulletin Officer shall,<lb/>
 publish the same in the State or District<lb/>
 Tender Bulletin, as the case may be within such<lb/>
 time as may be prescribed.&quot;<lb/>
 Section 10(7) of the Act reads thus:<lb/>
</item>

<item>&quot;The Tender Accepting Authority shall intimate<lb/>
 the information regarding the name and address<lb/>
 of the tenderer whose tender has been accepted<lb/>
 along with the reasons for rejection of other<lb/>
 tenders to the appropriate Tender Bulletin<lb/>
 Officers.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>Rule 30(3) of the TTIT Rules reads as under:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;As soon as the tenderer qualified to perform the<lb/>
 contract is identified, in accordance with section<lb/>
 10(6) of the Act, the Tender Accepting Authority<lb/>
 shall pass orders accepting the tender and<lb/>
 communicate the order of acceptance to the<lb/>
 successful tenderer. The Tender Accepting<lb/>
 Authority will also send to the Tender<lb/>
 Bulletin Officer a statement of evaluation of<lb/>
 the tenders with a comparative statement<lb/>
 of tenders received and decision thereon<lb/>
 for publication in the Tender Bulletin.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>30.4. The above said provisions should be read conjointly<lb/>
 in order to further the object of the Act. The main object<lb/>
 behind such publication is to communicate to the public at<lb/>
 large the information received from the Tender Accepting<lb/>
 Authority, which in turn is the object of the TTIT Act, namely to<lb/>
 ensure greater transparency and greater accountability.<lb/>
</p>

<p>30.5. In the Tender Bulletin, extracted above, the reasons<lb/>
 for acceptance of tender are absent. There is no statement of<lb/>
 evaluation of tenders and there is no comparative statement of<lb/>
 tenders received and decision thereon. This is certainly a clear<lb/>
 violation of the requirements of the TTIT Act and the Rules. All<lb/>
 that we can observe is that it is vague as vagueness can be. It<lb/>
 also shows the arbitrariness in approach, besides being casual<lb/>
 and perfunctory. It is stated that the EPC-cum-Debt Financing<lb/>
 Project is an International Competitive Bid and a very big<lb/>
 project. We find, the approach is very casual and therefore<lb/>
 amenable to judicial review.<lb/>
</p>

<p>30.6. Even though the learned Advocate General taking<lb/>
 support from the judgment of the learned Single Judge, more<lb/>
 particularly, paragraph 37, pleaded that even if the procedure<lb/>
 contemplated under Section 10(7) of the TTIT Act read with<lb/>
 Rule 30(3) of the TTIT Rules is not complied with, it will not<lb/>
 vitiate the tender process, as post finalization of tender only<lb/>
 the said provisions come into play, this Court is not inclined to<lb/>
 accept such a plea, as it is well settled proposition of law that<lb/>
 where a power is given to do a certain thing in a certain way,<lb/>
 the thing must be done in that way or not at all and that other<lb/>
 methods of performance are necessarily forbidden (See Taylor<lb/>
 v. Taylor, (1876) 1 Ch.D 426). When even after compliance of<lb/>
 Section 10(7) and Rule 30(3), some more formalities need to<lb/>
 be complied with by the parties and the contract has not been<lb/>
 entered into between the parties, it cannot be claimed that<lb/>
 such non compliance of post-decisional tasks cannot be<lb/>
 assailed.<lb/>
</p>

<p>30.7. In such view of the matter, we hold that publication<lb/>
 effected in Tender Bulletin is not in terms of Section 6(1) read<lb/>
 with Section 10 of the TTIT Act and Rule 30(3) of the TTIT<lb/>
 Rules.<lb/>
</p>

<p>30.8. With regard to the plea of the Advocate General by<lb/>
 referring to Rule 7 of the TTIT Rules that the information<lb/>
 contained in the Tender Bulletin regarding accepting a tender<lb/>
 will not create a legal right or liability, it would be apt to refer<lb/>
 to Rule 7 of the TTIT Rules, which reads as under:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;7. Tender bulletin to contain information only.-(1) The<lb/>
 tender bulletin shall contain only information of the notice<lb/>
 inviting tenders and the orders accepting a tender and<lb/>
 does not in itself create a legal right or liability.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(2) A notice inviting tender will not be invalidated merely<lb/>
 on the grounds that the notice although published in<lb/>
 newspapers has not been published in one or the other of<lb/>
 the District Tender Bulletins or State Tender Bulletins or<lb/>
 when published in the State Tender Bulletin could not be<lb/>
 published in a District Tender Bulletin or vice versa.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>30.8. In our considered opinion, there is no need for this Court<lb/>
 to go into the said provision. On a plain reading of the said<lb/>
 provision, it is evident that it is relatable to the presently successful<lb/>
 bidder, namely, BHEL. That rule provides that the successful bidder<lb/>
 does not have any right. We are not on that issue at present.<lb/>
</p>

<item>(C) (i) WHETHER INTEREST OFFERED BY APPELLANT<lb/>
 IS VAGUE; AND<lb/>
 (ii) WHETHER THE REDUCTION OF INTEREST<lb/>
 FROM 7.2% TO 6.2% SHOULD BE ACCEPTED.<lb/>
</item>

<p>31.1. We will first deal with the issue as to the vagueness<lb/>
 of the rate of interest offered by the appellant.<lb/>
</p>

<p>31.2. With regard to interest rate, it is stated in the Term<lb/>
 Sheet as under:<lb/></p><item>
 &quot;The Borrower will pay interest on the full Loan<lb/>
 amount at a floating rate of 6 month LIBOR (The<lb/>
 relevant Inter-bank Offered rate Bid Rate displayed<lb/>
 on Reuters at or about 10.00am New York time on<lb/>
 the commencement date for each interest period)<lb/>
 plus 3.5-4.5% margin per annum, or at a fixed rate<lb/>
 of 7.2~7.5% per annum. Both rates are estimated<lb/>
 based on current market conditions.<lb/>
 The final<lb/>
 pricing is subject to the Lender&apos;s final discretion, and<lb/>
 may be adjusted in future.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>31.3. While it is the plea of the appellant that fixed rate<lb/>
 of 7.2~7.5% per annum or LIBOR floating rate has been<lb/>
 quoted by them, it is the case of the learned Advocate General<lb/>
 that Clause 12.1 of the Instructions to Bidders stated that<lb/>
 interest is to be quoted at fixed rate and it is not subject to<lb/>
 change, and since the interest quoted is variable, it is not<lb/>
 possible to evaluate the bid.<lb/>
</p>

<p>31.4. It is seen from the records, that subsequently,<lb/>
 based on a query from the first respondent, the appellant had<lb/>
 confirmed that it would be fixed rate of interest at 7.2%. The<lb/>
 same was also confirmed in the Repayment Schedule and the<lb/>
 same rate of interest was taken into consideration by the<lb/>
 Consultant in his report dated 30.5.2014. He did not find fault<lb/>
 with the rate of interest. It is to be noted that the Term Sheet<lb/>
 was submitted during July, 2013 and tender was evaluated in<lb/>
 the year 2014.<lb/>
 The contention of vagueness in rate of<lb/>
 interest does not appeal to us. When the Consultant&apos;s report<lb/>
 dated 30.5.2014 is accepted by TANGEDCO for the purpose of<lb/>
 evaluation, it has to be accepted for all purposes, though we<lb/>
 have reservation on the Consultant&apos;s report dated 30.5.2014.<lb/>
 There is, therefore, no vagueness in the rate of interest quoted<lb/>
 at 7.2%.<lb/>
</p>

<p>31.5. The second issue relates to the reduction of rate of<lb/>
 interest. It is not in dispute that various meetings were held<lb/>
 between the appellant and the TANGEDCO.<lb/>
 The learned<lb/>
 Advocate General states that the Consultant was appointed<lb/>
 based on the 21 st Board Meeting on 28.1.2012 and the<lb/>
 Consultant participated in all pre-bid and post-bid meetings<lb/>
 and minutes were signed by all parties, including BHEL and the<lb/>
 appellant. He stated that the appellant was aware of the<lb/>
 Consultant&apos;s appointment and his role. This only fortifies the<lb/>
 fact that there have been series of consultation between both<lb/>
 the bidders. The finding of the learned Single Judge that the<lb/>
 appellant acted on inside information is demolished by the<lb/>
 stand of the learned Advocate General as above.<lb/>
 The<lb/>
 insinuation has no basis.<lb/>
</p>

<p>31.6. Coming to the issue of reduction of rate of interest,<lb/>
 taking into consideration the prevailing market rate, the<lb/>
 appellant offered to reduce the rate of interest from 7.2% to<lb/>
 6.2% on 5.6.2014, even prior to any form of litigation. When<lb/>
 such an offer was given by the appellant the tender was not<lb/>
 accepted in terms of Section 10(6) of the Act. To recapitulate,<lb/>
 what has happened earlier is that the writ petition in<lb/>
 W.P.No.19247 of 2014 was filed on 17.7.2014, subsequent to<lb/>
 the offer made on 5.6.2014. The first interim order was<lb/>
 passed on 18.7.2014. The second interim order was passed on<lb/>
 31.7.2014. The Division Bench passed an order on 19.8.2014.<lb/>
 At that point of time, there was never a statement by the<lb/>
 TANGEDCO that L1 was identified and discussion was going on.<lb/>
 We have also clearly stated the statement of the Chairman-<lb/>
cum-Managing Director of TANGEDCO that the representations<lb/>
 of the appellant will be duly considered by the Board of<lb/>
 Directors while finalizing the tender and appropriate orders will<lb/>
 be passed strictly in accordance with the tender specifications<lb/>
 and by following the provisions of TTIT Act and TTIT Rules.<lb/>
</p>

<p>31.7. Therefore, the issue relating to reduction of rate of<lb/>
 interest should have been considered. This reasoning of ours<lb/>
 is also based on the fact that we have clearly held that the<lb/>
 third respondent could not be ascertained as L1 on 2.6.2014 as<lb/>
 per the statement of TANGEDCO or on 30.5.2014 as per the<lb/>
 finding of the learned Single Judge.<lb/>
 Once there is no<lb/>
 identification of L1, TANGEDCO is bound to consider the<lb/>
 reduction in rate of interest of both the appellant in their offer<lb/>
 dated 5.6.2014 and that of the third respondent dated<lb/>
 27.6.2014, reducing the rate of interest from 12.25% to<lb/>
 12.15%.<lb/>
 31.8. Even otherwise, by virtue of the power under<lb/>
 Clause 25.3 of the Instructions to bidders, which states that<lb/>
 &quot;The Purchaser reserves the right to relax or waive any of the<lb/>
 conditions of this Specification in the best interests of the<lb/>
 TANGEDCO&quot;, the TANGEDCO could have considered such<lb/>
 reduced rate of interest offered by the appellant and the third<lb/>
 respondent.<lb/>
</p>

<p>31.9. Moreover, when the present tender is for<lb/>
 Engineering, Procurement, Construction and Debt Financing<lb/>
 and Section 10(1) of the TTIT Act specifies that &quot;The Tender<lb/>
 Accepting Authority shall cause an objective evaluation of the<lb/>
 tenders taking into consideration the schedule of rates as<lb/>
 mentioned in the tender document and the prevailing market<lb/>
 rate for procurement and comparison of the tenders in<lb/>
 accordance with the procedure and criteria specified in the<lb/>
 tender document&quot;, certainly in a debt financing contract, where<lb/>
 loan is to be procured for the first respondent, the prevailing<lb/>
 market rate of interest, which was offered at 6.2% as against<lb/>
 7.2% by the appellant ought to have been considered by the<lb/>
 TANGEDCO, while considering the offer of the third respondent<lb/>
 for reduction of interest rate from 12.25% to 12.15%. The fact<lb/>
 that this reduction would result in reduction of cost at about<lb/>
 Rs.1300 Crores, is a very vital and relevant factor. What<lb/>
 prevents the first respondent to accept such an offer is<lb/>
 unfathomable, but certainly unpalatable.<lb/>
</p>

<p>31.10. Even in the letter of acceptance of the third<lb/>
 respondent dated 27.9.2014, it is stated that negotiations<lb/>
 were held on 27.6.2014 qua reduction of interest. On that<lb/>
 day, the offer of the appellant to reduce interest rate from<lb/>
 7.2% to 6.2% was very much available, having been<lb/>
 submitted on 5.6.2014. To avoid such an offer, the clock was<lb/>
 set back and the date was reset to 2.6.2014 by the first<lb/>
 respondent and 30.5.2014 by the learned Single Judge. These<lb/>
 dates identifying BHEL as L1 are contrary to the provisions of<lb/>
 TTIT Act.<lb/>
</p>

<p>31.11. In any event, invoking Clause 25.3, the<lb/>
 TANGEDCO ought to have considered the reduced rate of the<lb/>
 appellant in the best interests of TANGEDCO, as it would have<lb/>
 resulted in a benefit of about Rs.1300 Crores. This valuable<lb/>
 financial benefit cannot be frittered away by the first<lb/>
 respondent on hyper-technical plea.<lb/>
</p>

<p>31.12. It is an admitted fact that the present tender is an<lb/>
 International Competitive Bidding. The degree of care which is<lb/>
 required to be taken and transparency in such bidding is<lb/>
 greater and the same has been emphasized by the Supreme<lb/>
 Court in W.B. State Electricity Board v. Patel Engineering Co.,<lb/>
 (2001) 2 SCC 451, wherein it was observed as under:<lb/>
 &quot;</p>

<item>24. The controversy in this case has arisen at the<lb/>
 threshold, it cannot be disputed that this is an<lb/>
 international competitive bidding which postulates<lb/>
 keen competition and high efficiency. The bidders<lb/>
 have or should have assistance of technical experts.<lb/>
 The degree of care required in such a bidding is<lb/>
 greater than in ordinary local bids for small works. It<lb/>
 is essential to maintain the sanctity and integrity of<lb/>
 process of tender/bid and also award of a contract.<lb/>
 The appellant, Respondents 1 to 4 and Respondents<lb/>
 10 and 11 are all bound by the ITB which should be<lb/>
 complied with scrupulously. In a work of this nature<lb/>
 and<lb/>
 magnitude<lb/>
 where<lb/>
 bidders<lb/>
 who<lb/>
 fulfill<lb/>
 prequalification alone are invited to bid, adherence<lb/>
 to the instructions cannot be given a go-by branding<lb/>
 it as a pedantic approach, otherwise it will<lb/>
 encourage and provide scope for discrimination,<lb/>
 arbitrariness and favouritism which are totally<lb/>
 opposed to the rule of law and our constitutional<lb/>
 values.<lb/>
 The<lb/>
 very<lb/>
 purpose<lb/>
 of<lb/>
 issuing<lb/>
 rules/instructions is to ensure their enforcement lest<lb/>
 the rule of law should be a casualty. Relaxation or<lb/>
 waiver of a rule or condition, unless so<lb/>
 provided under the ITB, by the State or its<lb/>
 agencies (the appellant) in favour of one<lb/>
 bidder would create justifiable doubts in the<lb/>
 minds of other bidders, would impair the rule<lb/>
 of transparency and fairness and provide room<lb/>
 for manipulation to suit the whims of the State<lb/>
 agencies in picking and choosing a bidder for<lb/>
 awarding contracts as in the case of<lb/>
 distributing bounty or charity. In our view such<lb/>
 approach should always be avoided. Where power to<lb/>
 relax or waive a rule or a condition exists under the<lb/>
 rules, it has to be done strictly in compliance with<lb/>
 the rules. We have, therefore, no hesitation in<lb/>
 concluding that adherence to the ITB or rules is the<lb/>
 best principle to be followed, which is also in the<lb/>
 best public interest.&quot;<lb/>
 (emphasis supplied)<lb/>
</item>

<p>31.13. In the case on hand, de hors the factual misgiving<lb/>
 relatable to the first respondent on the date when the<lb/>
 appellant offered to reduce the rate of interest i.e., on<lb/>
 5.6.2014, the third respondent was not called for negotiation.<lb/>
 The third respondent was called for negotiation on 27.6.2014.<lb/>
 Clause 25.3<lb/>
 of Instructions to Bidders enables the<lb/>
 respondents to relax or waive any of the conditions of the<lb/>
 specification in the best interests of the TANGEDCO. When<lb/>
 Rs.1300 Crores is the amount involved on account of the<lb/>
 difference in the interest rate offered by the appellant and third<lb/>
 respondent, certainly, in the best interest of the TANGEDCO,<lb/>
 relaxation or waiver of the condition for consideration of the<lb/>
 bid of the appellant is manifest. However, such indulgence was<lb/>
 granted only to the third respondent, even though even as per<lb/>
 the submission of the TANGEDCO, as on 27.6.2014, finalization<lb/>
 of tender has not taken place. The same would certainly<lb/>
 create justifiable doubts in the minds of other bidders and<lb/>
 would impair the rule of transparency and fairness and provide<lb/>
 room for manipulation to suit the whims of the State agencies<lb/>
 in picking and choosing a bidder for awarding contracts. We<lb/>
 also keep in mind that the decision in W.B. State Electricity<lb/>
 Board case, referred supra, will have a bearing as to how L1<lb/>
 should be determined, because the larger public interest in a<lb/>
 project of this magnitude warrants not only timely<lb/>
 implementation of the project, but also a cost effective<lb/>
 measure. Substantial saving in the order of Rs.1300 Crores<lb/>
 only on account of reduction in interest is by no means a small<lb/>
 amount which could be ignored by the State instrumentality,<lb/>
 especially when this amount will be a boon to the State for<lb/>
 development of other infrastructure or for any other welfare<lb/>
 measure. When the third respondent is clearly not L1 till<lb/>
 27.9.2014, there is no impediment in considering the reduction<lb/>
 of interest, which is part of the representation/record/<lb/>
 document/letter submitted for consideration and which had the<lb/>
 stamp of approval of the Court.<lb/>
</p>

<p>31.14. Moreover, the observation of the learned Single<lb/>
 Judge that the appellant is a private limited company, whereas<lb/>
 the third respondent is a Government of India Enterprise and<lb/>
 therefore the third respondent&apos;s case should be viewed with a<lb/>
 lesser amount of suspicion than a decision in favour of the<lb/>
 private players is, in our considered opinion, uncalled for, as<lb/>
 the present tender is International Competitive Bidding,<lb/>
 wherein tenders have been invited globally. Even though BHEL<lb/>
 is a Government of India Enterprise, it should be placed on the<lb/>
 same pedestal as any private player or else there is no<lb/>
 necessity to invite tenders globally and conduct such a lengthy<lb/>
 tender process.<lb/>
</p>

<p>31.15. We are of the firm view that the TANGEDCO, in its<lb/>
 best interest, ought to have considered the offer made by the<lb/>
 appellant for reduction of interest keeping in mind the vast<lb/>
 difference of Rs.1300 Crores. The project cost will certainly<lb/>
 come down. The cost factor will reduce to a great extent and<lb/>
 consequently, the cost per unit of power produced for the<lb/>
 benefit of the public at large will also be reduced. The first<lb/>
 respondent will have to consider the most competitive bid and<lb/>
 not play on technicalities.<lb/>
</p>


<item>&quot;The accrued commitment fee (1% per annum)<lb/>
 is payable on the last day of each successive<lb/>
 interest period which ends during the availability<lb/>
 period, on the last day of the Availability Period<lb/>
 and, if cancelled in full, on the cancelled amount<lb/>
 of the relevant Lender&apos;s Commitment at the time<lb/>
 the cancellation is effective.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>It clearly states that Commitment Fee is only on the cancelled<lb/>
 portion of the loan. That apart, even as per the Drawdown<lb/>
 Schedule, the fee is to be paid only if the loan amount is not<lb/>
 drawn by the 18 th , 30 th and 42 nd month.<lb/>
 Moreover, the<lb/>
 appellant in the letters dated 13.6.2014, 16.6.2014 and<lb/>
 17.6.2014, clarified that Commitment Fee is only on the<lb/>
 unused credit line and that there shall be no Commitment Fee<lb/>
 if the loan amount is fully utilized as per the Drawdown<lb/>
 Schedule. All these representations sent by the appellant were<lb/>
 not considered by TANGEDCO, despite there being a specific<lb/>
 direction by the Division Bench of this Court to consider the<lb/>
 same. It is a clear case of arbitrariness in approach and<lb/>
 intended to oust the appellant. This act of the TANGEDCO is<lb/>
 nothing but a case of malafide in evaluation process to suit one<lb/>
 and reject the other.<lb/>
</p>

<p>32.3. The proceedings of the first respondent is also hit<lb/>
 by the Wednesbury&apos;s principles. The decision taken by the<lb/>
 TANGEDCO is not only unreasonable but also irrational. They<lb/>
 have taken into account matters which they ought not to have<lb/>
 taken or conversely refused to take into account matters which<lb/>
 they ought to have. In this connection, the observation of<lb/>
 Mukharji,J. State of U.P. v. Renusagar Power Co. reported<lb/>
 in (1988) 4 SCC 59, is apposite:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;The exercise of power whether legislative<lb/>
 or administrative will be set aside if there is<lb/>
 manifest error in the exercise of such power or<lb/>
 the exercise of the power is manifestly arbitrary.<lb/>
 Similarly, if the power has been exercised on<lb/>
 non-consideration or non-application of mind to<lb/>
 relevant factors the exercise of power will be<lb/>
 regarded as manifestly erroneous. If a power<lb/>
 (whether<lb/>
 legislative<lb/>
 or<lb/>
 administrative)<lb/>
 is<lb/>
 exercised on the basis of the facts which do not<lb/>
 exist and which are patently erroneous, such<lb/>
 exercise of power will stand vitiated.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>The failure on the part of the TANGEDCO to take into<lb/>
 consideration relevant materials and clarifications in the form<lb/>
 of representations in support of the plea of no Commitment<lb/>
 Fee, if loan is taken and no Interest during Construction, is an<lb/>
 attempt to misread the documents, which an ordinary man in<lb/>
 normal commercial parlance would clearly understand. This<lb/>
 would establish the case that relevant materials have been<lb/>
 deliberately misread to load the cost on the appellant&apos;s bid.<lb/>
 This action of the TANGEDCO, if tested on Wednesbury&apos;s<lb/>
 principles, will fail.<lb/>
</p>

<p>32.4. While exercising the power of judicial review, in<lb/>
 Associated<lb/>
 Provincial<lb/>
 Picture<lb/>
 Houses<lb/>
 Ltd.<lb/>
 v.<lb/>
 Wednesbury Corporation [1948] 1 KB 223, [1947] 2 All<lb/>
 ER 680, Lord Green MR, drew attention to the fact that the<lb/>
 word &apos;unreasonable&apos; had often been used in a sense which<lb/>
 comprehended different grounds of review. He summarised the<lb/>
 principles as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;The court is entitled to investigate the<lb/>
 action of the local authority with a view to seeing<lb/>
 whether or not they have taken into account<lb/>
 matters which they ought not to have taken into<lb/>
 account, or, conversely, have refused to take into<lb/>
 account or neglected to take into account<lb/>
 matters which they ought to take into account.<lb/>
 Once that question is answered in favour of the<lb/>
 local authority, it may still be possible to say<lb/>
 that, although the local authority had kept within<lb/>
 the four corners of the matters which they ought<lb/>
 to consider, they have nevertheless come to a<lb/>
 conclusion so unreasonable that no reasonable<lb/>
 authority could ever have come to it. In such a<lb/>
 case, again, I think the court can interfere. The<lb/>
 power of the court to interfere in each case is<lb/>
 not as an appellate authority to override a<lb/>
 decision of the local authority, but as a judicial<lb/>
 authority which is concerned, and concerned<lb/>
 only, to see whether the local authority has<lb/>
 contravened the law by acting in excess of the<lb/>
 power which Parliament has confided in them.&quot;<lb/></item><p>
 This principle was further amplified by Lord Diplock with a new<lb/>
 name &apos;irrationality&apos; in the case of Council of Civil Service<lb/>
 Unions v. Minister for the Civil Service [1985] AC 374 at<lb/>
 410-<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;By &quot;irrationality&quot; I mean what can now be<lb/>
 succinctly<lb/>
 referred<lb/>
 to<lb/>
 as<lb/>
 &quot;Wednesbury<lb/>
 unreasonableness&quot;<lb/>
 (Associated<lb/>
 Provincial<lb/>
 Picture Houses Ltd. v. Wednesbury Corporation<lb/>
 [1948] 1 KB 223). It applies to a decision which<lb/>
 is so outrageous in its defiance of logic or of<lb/>
 accepted moral standards that no sensible<lb/>
 person who had applied his mind to the<lb/>
 question to be decided could have arrived at it.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>Tested on these principles of law, the decision making process<lb/>
 followed by TANGEDCO has to fail.<lb/>
</p>


<p>(E) INTEREST ON MANAGEMENT FEE &amp; GUARANTEE FEE<lb/>
</p>

<p>33.1. It is the case of the appellant that the Term Sheet<lb/>
 only mentions that a Management Fee is to be paid, but does<lb/>
 not mention any interest on Management Fee or Guarantee Fee<lb/>
 for the 36 month construction period.<lb/>
</p>

<p>33.2. If the TANGEDCO had any doubt on this issue, a<lb/>
 clarification could have been taken from the appellant.<lb/>
 Appellant has also sent clarifications on this issue on<lb/>
 13.6.2014, 16.6.2014 and 17.6.2014.<lb/>
 That apart, in the<lb/>
 representation sent by the appellant pursuant to the direction<lb/>
 of the Division Bench of this Court in the earlier round of<lb/>
 litigation, the appellant had clarified this issue. The same is<lb/>
 also evident from the Supplementary Price Bid. This makes it<lb/>
 clear that there was no doubt or vagueness on this issue. The<lb/>
 learned Advocate General&apos;s argument that the department<lb/>
 would only read in that manner is untenable. We find that the<lb/>
 department has gone merely by the Consultant&apos;s report, who<lb/>
 had no opportunity to consider the representations. This is a<lb/>
 clear breach of the order of the Division Bench and the<lb/>
 undertaking given therein.<lb/>
</p>

<p>33.3. Even as per the Consultant&apos;s Report the difference<lb/>
 between the bid of the appellant and the third respondent is<lb/>
 around Rs.71 Crores.<lb/>
 That being the case, if either the<lb/>
 Commitment Fee of Rs.156.184 Crores or the interest on<lb/>
 Management Fee and Guarantee Fee for the 36 month<lb/>
 construction period is not loaded on the appellant, it will have<lb/>
 a bearing on deciding which one of the two is the lowest bid.<lb/>
 Assuming the Consultant&apos;s report is of any value, such report<lb/>
 without considering the relevant material is of no use. The<lb/>
 approach to add these figures without taking note of the<lb/>
 representations and additional particulars/documents is,<lb/>
 therefore, arbitrary and tainted in bias. This is in violation of<lb/>
 the Division Bench judgment as well as the orders of the<lb/>
 learned Single Judge in the first round of litigation.<lb/>
</p>

<p>33.4. In the course of arguments made on behalf of<lb/>
 TANGEDCO, an attempt was made to say that the entire case<lb/>
 of the appellant is technical in nature dealing with financial<lb/>
 jugglery and the interpretation which they want to make will<lb/>
 only cause confusion and TANGEDCO should not be asked to<lb/>
 go into these financial aspects to come to a conclusion and,<lb/>
 therefore, they relied on the report of the Consultant. The<lb/>
 learned Single Judge did not want to go into the financial<lb/>
 aspect of the matter stating that it is not within the domain of<lb/>
 judicial review. It is true that the scope of judicial review<lb/>
 should not be concerned with a particular method of<lb/>
 interpretation that is possible insofar as financial implication is<lb/>
 concerned. But the fact remains that if the authority has<lb/>
 simply overlooked a vital factor, which stares on the face of the<lb/>
 record, it would be arbitrary approach to the matter.<lb/>
</p>

<p>33.5. There are two ways to look at a problem -One, to<lb/>
 look at the financial issue as a complicated complex factor and<lb/>
 refrain and the other is to simplify the issue and consider.<lb/>
 According the learned Single Judge, it is a very complicated<lb/>
 way of looking at the matter and, therefore, he would not<lb/>
 embark upon that. But, we would like to approach this issue<lb/>
 by understanding the issue in a simple manner. The financial<lb/>
 implication in respect of two tenderers has been specified by<lb/>
 the Consultant. The issue is what factors mean and how it<lb/>
 impacts the bid. We find that the Repayment Schedule<lb/>
 submitted by the appellant with regard to interest on<lb/>
 management fee and guarantee fee during IDC period is an<lb/>
 accepted document by the Consultant. If nothing more is to<lb/>
 be paid beyond that and that is clarified in the course of<lb/>
 representation in clear terms, we fail to understand as to how<lb/>
 this amount could be included in the cost when there is no<lb/>
 implication. The Consultant, as we have held, did not have the<lb/>
 benefit of considering the representation and other documents<lb/>
 on the financial implications in this issue. His opinion is<lb/>
 therefore not based on relevant document/representation.<lb/>
 This we have held is not in conformity with the order of the<lb/>
 learned Single Judge in the first round of litigation, which was<lb/>
 confirmed by the Division Bench. Withholding such a factor and<lb/>
 to obtain an evaluation from the Consultant loading the bid of<lb/>
 the appellant is clearly a case of bias. It is an unreasonable<lb/>
 approach and an unfair gesture which crumbles the spirit of<lb/>
 transparent tender.<lb/>
</p>

<p>33.6. We, therefore, have no hesitation to hold that the<lb/>
 first respondent had erroneously added interest on<lb/>
 Management Fee and Guarantee Fee when there is none and<lb/>
 there is no ambiguity or vagueness. Once the appellant has<lb/>
 indicated in the representation, in clear terms, as to how it<lb/>
 should be treated, in the light of the order of the Division<lb/>
 Bench, which TANGEDCO accepted to consider the bid of the<lb/>
 appellant, the first respondent ought not to have loaded this<lb/>
 amount on the basis of the Consultant&apos;s Report. In all fairness,<lb/>
 the Tender Accepting Authority of the first respondent should<lb/>
 have excluded this amount, if both the bidders are to be<lb/>
 treated on the touchstone of fairness and on the doctrine of<lb/>
 level-playing field. This becomes necessary because the entire<lb/>
 tender is tested on the larger public interest, that is to say, the<lb/>
 implementation of the project in a time bound manner where<lb/>
 cost is another important factor to be considered in the<lb/>
 decision making. In a Welfare State, public authority cannot<lb/>
 decide arbitrarily to throw away such an offer which they<lb/>
 agreed to consider in the course of judicial proceedings, which<lb/>
 we have referred to above. These factors, namely, adding<lb/>
 interest on Management Fee and Guarantee Fee, have to be<lb/>
 eschewed<lb/>
 for the purpose of considering the bid of the<lb/>
 appellant, otherwise, it will suffer from the vice of<lb/>
 unreasonableness and irrationality.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(F) CONSULTANT&apos;S REPORT<lb/>
</p>

<p>34. We have perused the Consultant&apos;s Report dated<lb/>
 30.5.2014, furnished by the TANGEDCO, which the learned<lb/>
 Single Judge has relied upon with emphasis. In fact, it is a<lb/>
 Price Evaluation Report for the said project. Consultant has<lb/>
 loaded on the appellant an upfront fee (including interest) of<lb/>
 Rs.801.180 Crores. If Commitment Fee and the Interest on<lb/>
 Management Fee and Guarantee Fee are excluded and<lb/>
 accordingly, the Moratorium Interest is reduced to Rs.17.875<lb/>
 Crores, the Consultant could have only loaded Rs.489.136<lb/>
 Crores. If the Consultant had any doubt as to the amount to<lb/>
 be added on any of the heads, he should have sought for<lb/>
 clarification from the appellant, as was done for BHEL.<lb/>
 However, without resorting to such exercise, the Consultant<lb/>
 evaluated the bid of the appellant at Rs.9207.264 Crores, and<lb/>
 added the above amount. The Consultant&apos;s report cannot<lb/>
 supplement the role of the Tender Accepting Authority in terms<lb/>
 of Section 10 of the TTIT Act. In any event, the Consultant<lb/>
 should have been consulted post 30.5.2014 as per the<lb/>
 directions of the Court. That would have clarified the issue.<lb/>
 This has given the third respondent an unfair advantage on<lb/>
 norms. The decision of the Supreme Court in Reliance Energy<lb/>
 Limited, cited supra, answers the issue precisely.<lb/>
 Reliance Energy Limited Case:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;The principle of &quot;judicial review&quot; cannot be denied<lb/>
 even in contractual matters or matters in which the<lb/>
 Government exercises its contractual powers, but<lb/>
 judicial review is intended to prevent arbitrariness<lb/>
 and it must be exercised in larger public interest.<lb/>
 Expression of different views and opinions in<lb/>
 exercise of contractual powers may be there,<lb/>
 however, such difference of opinion must be based<lb/>
 on specified norms. Those norms may be legal<lb/>
 norms or accounting norms.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>(emphasis supplied)<lb/>
 The above said decision may be more appropriate in the<lb/>
 present case insofar as Commitment Fee, Interest During<lb/>
 Construction is concerned because in the repayment schedule,<lb/>
 what is payable has been clearly explained. This has been<lb/>
 submitted to comply with the norms for repayment taking into<lb/>
 consideration the entire project cost and the loan component.<lb/>
 Any attempt to misread the same under the guise of<lb/>
 vagueness is nothing but a self-serving attempt by the first<lb/>
 respondent to load the cost against the appellant and to tilt the<lb/>
 balance in favour of the third respondent.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(G) RIVAL CONTENTIONS ON PAST PERFORMANCE &amp;<lb/>
 VENDOR RATING:<lb/>
</p>

<p>35.1. The ability of the two tenderers to take up the<lb/>
 project of this magnitude was not found fault with by the<lb/>
 Consultant. The volume of work undertaken by the BHEL<lb/>
 cannot be disputed. We cannot comment about the efficiency<lb/>
 of BHEL insofar as power generation in the subcritical arena is<lb/>
 concerned. The issue that we are now grappling with is<lb/>
 whether in this supercritical EPC-cum-debt financing project<lb/>
 the TANGEDCO has floated, as between the two tenderers,<lb/>
 whether there is incapacity in either of them and whether the<lb/>
 efficiency level of the two bidders can be tested.<lb/>

</p>

<p>35.2. We find that the Consultant, on whose report the<lb/>
 learned Single Judge has relied upon in extenso, has not found<lb/>
 the appellant or the BHEL incompetent. The Consultant has not<lb/>
 found either of the parties to be technically unsound. There<lb/>
 rests the matter. The extensive argument by either side is of<lb/>
 no avail on the ability to take up such a project.<lb/>
</p>

<p>35.3. The argument on the side of the respondents that<lb/>
 the appellant is a nascent company and the following points<lb/>
 raised by the respondents on the misgivings of the appellant in<lb/>
 executing the projects, viz., (i) that most of the projects<lb/>
 undertaken by them are sub-critical projects; (ii) that the work<lb/>
 involved in BTG (Boiler Turbine Generator) is only 40% of the<lb/>
 total work involved in supercritical project; (iii) that the<lb/>
 scheduled completion period in respect of one of the projects<lb/>
 undertaken by the members of the appellant consortium was<lb/>
 delayed for years, and (iv) that in yet another project the<lb/>
 name of the appellant consortium is not found, are not the<lb/>
 factors that weighed before the Consultant or the Tender<lb/>
 Accepting Authority. Therefore, if the Consultant&apos;s report is<lb/>
 taken as a benchmark for evaluation of tenders, which has<lb/>
 been accepted by the Tender Scrutiny Committee and the<lb/>
 Board of TANGEDCO blindly, we hold that the analysis of the<lb/>
 two tenderers on technical ability or capacity would be<lb/>
 stretching the issues little far. But, we would like to add that<lb/>
 both the tenderers may be technically sound, but when it<lb/>
 comes to implementation some serious issues are raised<lb/>
 insofar as BHEL is concerned. Few instances are as follows:<lb/>
</p>

<p>(i) The letter from the Hon&apos;ble Chief Minister dated 26.11.2013<lb/>
 addressed to the Hon&apos;ble Prime Minister of India; (ii) The<lb/>
 Counter Affidavit filed by Tamil Nadu Electricity Board in<lb/>
 W.P.(MD) No.3730 of 2012 before the Madurai Bench of the<lb/>
 Madras High Court; (iii) The report of Comptroller and Auditor<lb/>
 General of India, New Delhi dated 17.2.2014; (iv) Order of the<lb/>
 Central Electricity Regulatory Commission, New Delhi, dated<lb/>
 19.6.2014; and (v) various newspaper reports and the<lb/>
 contents of the TANGEDCO website.<lb/>
</p>

<p>35.4. It is for the Tender Scrutiny Committee or the<lb/>
 Tender Accepting Authority to weigh these issues and decide as<lb/>
 speakers who take us nowhere. It is just that one single factor<lb/>
 that we accept inaction or inefficiency as part of life and delay<lb/>
 with a remedial measure where one tends to overlook<lb/>
 important projects set to time limit, with a thought of penalty<lb/>
 on account of delay. This destroys the entire project. Public<lb/>
 interest suffers. Can Courts be mute spectators? We think, not.<lb/>
</p>

<p>35.6. In fact, one should not lose sight of the fact that in<lb/>
 large number of cases, arbitration clause is invoked for<lb/>
 additional cost alleging delay on one or other party. Therefore,<lb/>
 we have no hesitation to observe that time factor should be<lb/>
 strictly adhered to and that is a relevant consideration. The<lb/>
 first respondent should rate the rival bidders on efficiency -<lb/>
ability to take up the project is one thing, but, efficiency in<lb/>
 completing the project is yet another factor. Both are relevant.<lb/>
</p>

<p>36.1. In the present case, the decision making process is<lb/>
 arbitrary, irrational, illegal and procedurally improper. The first<lb/>
 respondent has also abdicated its function by failure to take<lb/>
 into consideration relevant factors and flawed its decision on<lb/>
 irrelevant and non-existent factors, merely based on<lb/>
 Consultant report:<lb/>
</p>

<p>(A) It is the specific direction of the Division Bench on<lb/>
 19.8.2014 in W.A.No.1065 of 2014 to consider the<lb/>
 representations of the appellant, which rests on the issues of<lb/>
 (i) reduction of rate of interest; and (ii) past performance of<lb/>
 BHEL. However, the same were not considered, more so when<lb/>
 the award of tender in favour of BHEL was granted only on<lb/>
 27.9.2014.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(B) Even as per the records of TANGEDCO, BHEL was<lb/>
 awarded tender only on 27.9.2014 and when prior to that<lb/>
 negotiations were held with BHEL for reduction of interest rate,<lb/>
 such an option should have also been given to the appellant as<lb/>
 well.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(C) The reduction of rate of interest is a substantial<lb/>
 saving to TANGEDCO in the EPC-cum-Debt Financing contract<lb/>
 for setting up Supercritical Thermal Power Plant. The cost<lb/>
 would be a decisive factor. Therefore, the offers made by both<lb/>
 the parties should have been considered.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(D) Commitment Fee has been included on the basis of<lb/>
 the Consultant Report. It is merely advisory in nature. In any<lb/>
 event, on this issue, clarification was given by the appellant on<lb/>
 13.6.2014 and that was not considered.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(E) No prudent man will understand the term<lb/>
 &quot;Commitment Fee&quot; in the manner in which TANGEDCO wants.<lb/>
 Interest is taken on the loan amount. If loan is availed as per<lb/>
 the terms, then Commitment fees will be charged. That is how<lb/>
 the document has been clarified. We fail to understand how<lb/>
 TANGEDCO can merely quibble with words to give an illogical<lb/>
 reasoning that commitment fee is payable even if loan is not<lb/>
 availed. Any person in normal commercial transaction can<lb/>
 perceive that if no loan is taken the commitment fee is not<lb/>
 charged. If loan is availed, interest is payable.<lb/>
</p>

<p>(F) Interest on Management Fee and Guarantee Fee is<lb/>
 not included by the appellant.<lb/>
 They have said so in no<lb/>
 uncertain terms.<lb/>
 However, the Consultant has included it<lb/>
 without reference to the representation. If we accept the plea<lb/>
 of the TANGEDCO that this is how they would like to<lb/>
 understand, then it would amount to arbitrary and irrational<lb/>
 appraisal and evaluation. This will render the decision making<lb/>
 process vulnerable to judicial review. We have no hesitation to<lb/>
 hold that the decision of TANGEDCO declaring BHEL as L1 is<lb/>
 flawed for all the reasons that we have discussed earlier.<lb/>
</p>

<p>36.2. We, therefore, hold that the process adopted and<lb/>
 the decision made by TANGEDCO is arbitrary, unfair, irrational,<lb/>
 biased and mala fide. It is not in accordance with the<lb/>
 provisions of the TTIT Act and TTIT Rules. Accordingly, based<lb/>
 on Jagdish Mandal case, referred supra, M/s.TANGEDCO&apos;s<lb/>
 decision to declare the third respondent -BHEL as L1 fails and<lb/>
 has to be interfered with.<lb/>
</p>

<p>II TEST -PUBLIC INTEREST<lb/>
</p>

<p>37.1. The second test to be considered is the public<lb/>
 interest involved in this case.<lb/>
</p>

<p>37.2. The Supreme Court in Raunaq International Ltd. v.<lb/>
 IVR Construction Ltd. and others, (1999) 1 SCC 492 has<lb/>
 clearly laid down as to what are the elements of public interest<lb/>
 in commercial transactions like the award of contract. The<lb/>
 relevant portion of the said decision is extracted hereunder:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;10. What are these elements of public<lb/>
 interest? (1) Public money would be expended<lb/>
 for the purposes of the contract. (2) The goods<lb/>
 or services which are being commissioned<lb/>
 could be for a public purpose, such as,<lb/>
 construction of roads, public buildings, power<lb/>
 plants or other public utilities. (3) The public<lb/>
 would be directly interested in the timely<lb/>
 fulfilment of the contract so that the services<lb/>
 become available to the public expeditiously.<lb/>
 (4) The public would also be interested in the<lb/>
 quality of the work undertaken or goods<lb/>
 supplied by the tenderer…..&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>37.3. In the case on hand, we have already held that the<lb/>
 procedure followed by the TANGEDCO reeks of arbitrariness,<lb/>
 unfair and unjust treatment to appellant, besides malafide and<lb/>
 being unreasonable and irrational. As to how an authority<lb/>
 awarding contract should have conducted itself, has been<lb/>
 specifically stated by the Supreme Court in LIC v. Consumer<lb/>
 Education &amp; Research Centre, (1995) 5 SCC 482, as under:<lb/>
</p>

<item>&quot;27. In the sphere of contractual relations the State,<lb/>
 its instrumentality, public authorities or those whose<lb/>
 acts bear insignia of public element, action to public<lb/>
 duty or obligation are enjoined to act in a manner<lb/>
 i.e. fair, just and equitable, after taking objectively<lb/>
 all the relevant options into consideration and in a<lb/>
 manner that is reasonable, relevant and germane to<lb/>
 effectuate the purpose for public good and in general<lb/>
 public interest and it must not take any irrelevant or<lb/>
 irrational factors into consideration or appear<lb/>
 arbitrary in its decision. Duty to act fairly is part of<lb/>
 fair procedure envisaged under Articles 14 and 21.<lb/>
 Every activity of the public authority or those under<lb/>
 public duty or obligation must be informed by reason<lb/>
 and guided by the public interest.&quot;<lb/>
</item>

<p>37.4. When a writ petition is filed challenging the award<lb/>
 of a contract by a public authority or the State, the Court must<lb/>
 be satisfied that there is some element of public interest<lb/>
 involved in entertaining such a petition. The Court should<lb/>
 always keep the larger public interest in mind in order to<lb/>
 decide whether its intervention is called for or not. Only when<lb/>
 it comes to a conclusion that overwhelming public interest<lb/>
 requires interference, the Court should intervene. On a<lb/>
 challenge to the award of a contract or rejection of a tender, by<lb/>
 a public authority or the State, the court must be satisfied that<lb/>
 there is some element of public interest involved in<lb/>
 entertaining such a petition.<lb/>
</p>

<p>37.5. In the case on hand, even as per the Consultant&apos;s<lb/>
 Report the difference between the bid of the appellant and the<lb/>
 third respondent is around Rs.71 Crores. The difference on<lb/>
 account of the reduction of the rate of interest from 7.2% to<lb/>
 6.2% as offered by the appellant would reduce the cost of the<lb/>
 project by about Rs.1300 Crores. If either the Commitment<lb/>
 Fee of Rs.156.184 Crores or the interest on Management Fee<lb/>
 and Guarantee Fee for the 36 month construction period is not<lb/>
 loaded, certainly the cost of project will come down even<lb/>
 further. The said factors cannot be brushed aside by the<lb/>
 TANGEDCO, as the above constitute overwhelming public<lb/>
 interest, i.e., reduction of cost of the EPC-cum-Debt Financing<lb/>
 project. The TANGEDCO in the larger public interest that it<lb/>
 serves ought to have considered the bid submitted by the<lb/>
 appellant and that of the third respondent in order to ensure a<lb/>
 level-playing field between the tenderers and fruitfully gain the<lb/>
 benefit of lowest cost in the 2x660 MW Supercritical Thermal<lb/>
 Power Project based on all relevant parameters contained in<lb/>
 the two bids.<lb/>
</p>

<p>37.6. In such view of the matter, we answer this issue<lb/>
 also against TANGEDCO.<lb/></p><p>
 CONCLUSION<lb/>
</p>

<p>38. However, we are cognizant of the fact that the price<lb/>
 offered may not always be the sole criterion for awarding a<lb/>
 contract, and it is one among the relevant and important<lb/>
 criteria. The quality of work executed, the past record of the<lb/>
 tenderers, the quality of the goods or services which are<lb/>
 offered, assessing such quality on the basis of the past<lb/>
 performance of the bidders, their market reputation, the cost<lb/>
 factor and so on, play an important role in deciding, to whom<lb/>
 the contract should be awarded. The decision making process<lb/>
 should be transparent and open in finding the best bid<lb/>
 considering all the relevant parameters and keeping in mind<lb/>
 the public interest paramount. When all these relevant factors<lb/>
 have not been considered in the right perspective but more in<lb/>
 breach, as observed above, certainly Courts in exercise of<lb/>
 power of judicial review can interfere and we are inclined to<lb/>
 interfere with the proceedings impugned in the writ petitions.<lb/>
</p>

<p>39. Resultantly, we allow these appeals and set aside the<lb/>
 common order passed by the learned Single Judge.<lb/>
 Consequently, the proceedings of the TANGEDCO impugned in<lb/>
 the writ petitions are set aside. The TANGEDCO is directed to<lb/>
 evaluate the appellant&apos;s price bid along with the bid of the third<lb/>
 respondent, in the light of our findings as above and also<lb/>
 taking into consideration all required parameters and the<lb/>
 clarifications submitted by the appellant in its various<lb/>
 representations, as directed by the Single Judge in the order<lb/>
 dated 31.7.2014 and that of the Division Bench in its order<lb/>
 dated 19.8.2014, afresh, at the earliest.<lb/>
</p>

<p>40. It is made clear that this Court has not expressed any<lb/>
 opinion on whether or not the subject contract should be<lb/>
 awarded to the appellant or the 3 rd respondent, as it is for the<lb/>
 TANGEDCO to decide which one of these two bidders, would<lb/>
 subserve the larger public interest in executing the project by<lb/>
 taking into consideration all relevant parameters including the<lb/>
 representations/documents, etc. submitted. We, however,<lb/>
 make it clear that, while undertaking this exercise, the<lb/>
 TANGEDCO shall record detailed reasons for their decision and<lb/>
 communicate the same to the appellant and the third<lb/>
 respondent so as to comply with the requirement of the<lb/>
 provisions of the TTIT Act and TTIT Rules and the decisions of<lb/>
 the Supreme Court, referred supra. No costs. Consequently,<lb/>
 M.P.No.1 of 2015 in W.A.No.712 of 2015 and M.P.Nos.1 and 2<lb/>
 of 2015 in W.A.No.713 of 2015 are closed.<lb/>
</p>


	<item>
	(R.S.J.) (K.B.K.V.J.)<lb/>
	7.9.2015<lb/>
</item>

<item>Index<lb/>
 :<lb/>
 Yes<lb/>
 Internet :<lb/>
 Yes<lb/>
 sasi/gb/rsb<lb/>
 R.SUDHAKAR,J.<lb/>
 and<lb/>
 K.B.K.VASUKI,J.<lb/>
</item>

<item>(sasi)<lb/>
 Judgment in<lb/>
 W.A.Nos.712 and 713 of 2015<lb/>
</item>

<item>7.9.2015</item>


</text>
</tei>
