<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>CS.No.641 of 2012 <lb/>IN THE HIGH COURT OF JUDICATURE AT MADRAS <lb/>Dated: 20.02.2020 <lb/></front>

			<body>CORAM <lb/>THE HON&apos;BLE MR.JUSTICE M.SUNDAR <lb/>C.S.No.641 of 2012 <lb/>and A.No.4348 of 2016 <lb/>1. Mrs.E.Sathyavathamma (deceased) <lb/>2. E.S.Reddy <lb/>3. E.Anil Kumar Reddy <lb/>4. Mrs.Uma V.Chandru <lb/>5. Mrs.Asha Kiron Jitendra <lb/>6. Mrs.Usha Saxena <lb/>[Plaintiffs 2 to 6 are brought on record <lb/>as Legal Heirs of the deceased sole plaintiff <lb/>as per order dated 29.06.2015 in A.No.3667 to 3669 of 2015] <lb/>... <lb/>Plaintiffs <lb/>-Vs -<lb/>Niranjan Reddy <lb/>... <lb/>Defendant <lb/>Plaint filed under Order VII Rule 1 of Civil Procedure Code and r/w <lb/>Order IV of the High Court Original Side Rules, praying (a) to partition the <lb/>suit property by metes and bounds granting 2/3 rd undivided right of share and <lb/>interest in the suit property to the defendant morefully described in the <lb/>Schedure hereunder and after passing a Preliminary decree after <lb/>Appointment of an Advocate Commissioner who can measure and divide the <lb/>1/21 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/>CS.No.641 of 2012 <lb/>property by metes and bounds and file a report before this Hon&apos;ble Court <lb/>within the time as stipulated by this Hon&apos;ble Court for passing Final Decree <lb/>and failure to divide the property by metes and bounds, the property can be <lb/>bought by either by the Plaintiff or Defendant and in case of such failure, the <lb/>property should be sold through Public Auction and the Proceeds can be <lb/>shared between the Plaintiff and Defendant according to their respective <lb/>shares (b) for a Permanent Injunction restraining the defendant, his agents or <lb/>servants or from any one in dealing with the suit property by the defendant in <lb/>respect of the share of the Plaintiff in the Suit property and not to interfere <lb/>with the possession of the Plaintiff in respect of her share (c) to grant costs of <lb/>the suit and (d) to pass further or other suitable orders as this Hon&apos;ble Court <lb/>may deem fit and proper. <lb/>For Plaintiffs <lb/>: Mr.Srikrishna Bhagavat <lb/>for Mr.P.Subba Reddy <lb/>For Defendant <lb/>: Set exparte <lb/>*** <lb/>JUDGMENT <lb/>This is a judgment in the main suit i.e., C.S.No.641 of 2012, which is a <lb/>typical partition suit. To be noted A.No.4348 of 2016, is a final decree <lb/>application made under Order XXXIV Rule 5(3) of &apos;The Code of Civil <lb/>Procedure, 1908&apos; [&apos;CPC&apos; for brevity]. <lb/>2/21 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/>CS.No.641 of 2012 <lb/>2. There is only one item of suit property situate at Door No.1, Plot <lb/>No.548, 4 th Trust Link Street, Mandavelipakkam being a residential/house <lb/>property wherein superstructure stands on land admeasuring 4800 sq.ft <lb/>thereabouts [2 grounds or thereabouts] (hereinafter land and superstructure <lb/>together shall be referred to as &apos;suit property&apos;). <lb/>3. In the instant suit, originally, there was a lone plaintiff and a sole <lb/>defendant. To be noted, pending suit plaintiff E.Sathyavathamma died and <lb/>her legal heirs were brought on record vide order dated 29.06.2015 in <lb/>A.Nos.3667 to 3669 of 2015 as plaintiffs 2 to 6. <lb/>4. Case file reveals that defendant has already been set exparte by <lb/>Hon&apos;ble Predecessor Judge on 24.02.2014. <lb/>5. Being a typical partition suit, a preliminary judgment/decree came to <lb/>be passed by Hon&apos;ble Predecessor Judge on 28.04.2016, which reads as <lb/>follows: <lb/>3/21 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			CS.No.641 of 2012 <lb/>4/21 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/>CS.No.641 of 2012 <lb/>5/21 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/>CS.No.641 of 2012 <lb/>6/21 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/>CS.No.641 of 2012 <lb/>7/21 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/>CS.No.641 of 2012 <lb/>8/21 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/>CS.No.641 of 2012 <lb/>9/21 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/>CS.No.641 of 2012 <lb/>10/21 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/>CS.No.641 of 2012 <lb/>11/21 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/>CS.No.641 of 2012 <lb/>12/21 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/>CS.No.641 of 2012 <lb/>13/21 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/>CS.No.641 of 2012 <lb/>14/21 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/>CS.No.641 of 2012 <lb/>15/21 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/>CS.No.641 of 2012 <lb/>16/21 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/>CS.No.641 of 2012 <lb/>

			<body>6. The preliminary judgment/decree captures facts comprehensively <lb/>and therefore, it is not necessary to dilate on the same again. <lb/>7. Post preliminary decree, third plaintiff E.Anil Kumar Reddy <lb/>deposed as PW-1 on 13.02.2020 and the Engineer&apos;s report together with <lb/>photographs, a compact disk (CD) containing photographs of suit property <lb/>appended with a plan dated 20.06.2019 and the Advocate Commissioner&apos;s <lb/>report were marked as Exs.C1 and C2 respectively. <lb/>8. A perusal of evidence of PW-1, which obviously remains <lb/>unchallenged as the sole defendant has been set exparte reveals that it is <lb/>cogent, coherent and it compliments the pleadings. A perusal of Exs.C1 and <lb/>C2 reveal that the suit property is such that the superstructure is dilapidated. <lb/>This Court is informed by Mr.Srikrishna Bhagavat, learned counsel <lb/>appearing on behalf of the counsel on record for plaintiffs that the suit <lb/>property is dilapidated. <lb/>9. A further perusal of Ex.C2-Commissioner&apos;s report reveals that the <lb/>suit property is not capable of division into metes and bounds qua shares of <lb/>17/21 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/>CS.No.641 of 2012 <lb/>parties to the lis. Therefore, it has become imperative that a final decree <lb/>directing sale of suit property in public auction with a further direction to <lb/>share the proceeds proportionately (as in preliminary judgment/decree) <lb/>between plaintiffs and the defendant has to be passed. <lb/>10. To be noted, preliminary judgment/decree [scanned and <lb/>reproduced supra] came to be passed after plaint documents were marked as <lb/>Exs.P1 to P8. To be noted, a list of witnesses and exhibits is set out in the <lb/>last page of preliminary judgment/decree [scanned and reproduced supra]. <lb/>11. For appreciating the suit property, this Court deems it appropriate <lb/>to scan and reproduce one of the photographs i.e., photo No.1 forming part <lb/>of Ex.C1. That photo is: <lb/>18/21 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CS.No.641 of 2012 <lb/></note>

			<body>12. The aforesaid photograph, which is part of Ex.C1, makes it clear <lb/>that the suit property is an independent house. Land area as mentioned <lb/>above is two grounds or thereabouts and considering the number of shares, <lb/>there is no difficulty in accepting Commissioner&apos;s report-Ex.C2 that it is not <lb/>capable of division into metes and bounds. <lb/>13. Before passing a final decree, this Court deems it appropriate to <lb/>appoint Mr.D.Sampath Kumar, Advocate at 320 New Law Chambers, 2 nd <lb/>Floor, High Court, Chennai-104 Mobile: 63801 03849, 63811 27941 as <lb/>Advocate Commissioner for bringing suit property to sale by public auction. <lb/>Plaintiffs shall pay initial remuneration of Rs.50,000/-(Rupees Fifty <lb/>Thousand only) to the Advocate Commissioner besides meeting/defraying <lb/>his out of pocket expenses. It is made clear that all the plaintiffs as well as <lb/>the sole defendant [notwithstanding defendant having been set exparte in <lb/>instant suit] can participate in the public auction, make their bid and they <lb/>would be entitled to purchase the suit property subject of course to they <lb/>being able to match the highest price when the hammer goes down. <lb/>19/21 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/>CS.No.641 of 2012 <lb/>14. As the suit property has been held to be incapable of division into <lb/>metes and bounds, suit is decreed directing sale of suit property through <lb/>public auction by aforementioned Advocate Commissioner with a further <lb/>direction to distribute the sale proceeds to the parties to the suit proportionate <lb/>to their shares as concluded in the preliminary decree. <lb/>15. With regard to other limbs of the suit prayer viz., sub paragraphs b) <lb/>and c) the same are decreed as prayed for and the appointment of Advocate <lb/>Commissioner for public auction and sale has been made inter alia under the <lb/>residuary limb of prayer. <lb/>16. Suit is decreed with costs on aforesaid terms. Consequently, <lb/>connected application is closed. <lb/>20.02.2020 <lb/>Index: Yes/No <lb/>Speaking/Non-speaking Order <lb/>kmi <lb/>To <lb/>The Sub Assistant Registrar, <lb/>Original Side, <lb/>High Court, Madras. <lb/>20/21 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/>CS.No.641 of 2012 <lb/>M.SUNDAR, J <lb/>kmi <lb/>C.S.No.641 of 2012 <lb/>20.02.2020 <lb/>21/21 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in </body>


	</text>
</tei>
