<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
			1
			<lb />
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF HIMACHAL PRADESH AT SHIMLA
			<lb />
			ON THE 10 th DAY OF DECEMBER, 2021
			<lb />
			BEFORE
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MS. JUSTICE JYOTSNA REWAL DUA
			<lb />
			(I)
			<lb />
			REGULAR SECOND APPEAL No.517 OF 2010
			<lb />
			Between :-
			<lb />
			RAM RATTAN, S/O SHRI BANTA RAM,
			<lb />
			R/O VILL. SANOLI ROAD,
			<lb />
			SANTOKHGARH, TEHSIL &amp; DISTRICT
			<lb />
			UNA, H.P.
			<lb />
			…APPELLANT/PLAINTIFF
			<lb />
			(BY MR. B.S. CHAUHAN, SENIOR ADVOCATE WITH MR.
			<lb />
			MUNISH DATWALIA, ADVOCATE)
			<lb />
			AND
			<lb />
			1. SHRI SAT PAL SAINI, S/O SHRI
			<lb />
			MOTI RAM ALIAS UPINDER LAL,
			<lb />
			R/O SIDHUWAL LODGE, THE
			<lb />
			RIDGE, SHIMLA, H.P.
			<lb />
			2. SHRI ASHOK KUMAR, S/O SHRI
			<lb />
			MOTI RAM ALIAS UPINDER LAL,
			<lb />
			R/O MOHALL GHUMARAWALA,
			<lb />
			SANTOKHGARH,
			<lb />
			TEHSIL
			<lb />
			&amp;
			<lb />
			DISTRICT UNA, H.P.
			<lb />
			…RESPONDENTS/DEFENDANTS No. 1 &amp; 2
			<lb />
			( MR. Y.P. SOOD, ADVOCATE, FOR RESPONDENT No. 1)
			<lb />
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</front>

		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
			2
			<lb />
			(MS.
			<lb />
			DEVYANI
			<lb />
			SHARMA,
			<lb />
			ADVOCATE,
			<lb />
			FOR
			<lb />
			RESPONDENT No. 2)
			<lb />
			(II)
			<lb />
			REGULAR SECOND APPEAL No.499 OF 2010
			<lb />
			Between :
			<lb />
			1. SHRI SAT PAL SAINI, S/O SHRI
			<lb />
			MOTI RAM ALIAS UPINDER LAL,
			<lb />
			R/O SIDHUWAL LODGE, THE
			<lb />
			RIDGE, SHIMLA, H.P.
			<lb />
			…APPELLANT/DEFENDANT No.1
			<lb />
			(BY MR. Y.P. SOOD, ADVOCATE)
			<lb />
			AND
			<lb />
			1. ASHOK KUMAR, SON OF MOTI
			<lb />
			RAM ALIAS UPINDER LAL,
			<lb />
			RESIDENT OF MOHALLA
			<lb />
			GHUMARAWALA,
			<lb />
			SANTOSHGARH, TEHSIL AND
			<lb />
			DISTRICT UNA, H.P.
			<lb />
			RESPONDENT/DEFENDANT No.2
			<lb />
			2. RAM RATTAN, SON OF BANTA
			<lb />
			RAM, RESIDENT OF SANOLI
			<lb />
			ROAD, SANTOSHGARH, THESIL
			<lb />
			AND DISTRICT UNA, H.P.
			<lb />
			..PROFORMA RESPONDENT/PLAINTIFF
			<lb />
			(MR. B.S. CHAUHAN, SENIOR ADVOCATE WITH MR.
			<lb />
			MUNISH DATWALIA, ADVOCATE FOR PROFORMA
			<lb />
			RESPONDENT).
			<lb />
			(MS.
			<lb />
			DEVYANI
			<lb />
			SHARMA,
			<lb />
			ADVOCATE,
			<lb />
			FOR
			<lb />
			RESPONDENT/DEFENDANT No. 2)
			<lb />
		</front>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			3
			<lb />
		</page>

		<front>
			RESERVED ON : 26.11.2021
			<lb />
			DELIVERED ON : 10.12.2021
			<lb />
			WHETHER APPROVED FOR REPORTING : YES
			<lb />
			____________________________________________________
			<lb />
			This petition coming on for pronouncement this day,
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Ms. Justice Jyotsna Rewal Dua, delivered the
			<lb />
			following :
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			<lb />
			J U D G M E N T
			<lb />
			These two appeals arise out of common judgments and
			<lb />
			decrees passed by the learned Courts below, hence are taken up
			<lb />
			together for decision. RSA No. 517 of 2010 is plaintiff&apos;s appeal
			<lb />
			whereas RSA No. 499 of 2010 is defendant No.1&apos;s appeal.
			<lb />
			Defendants No. 1 &amp; 2 are sons of late Smt. Gurbax
			<lb />
			Kaur. Smt. Gurbax Kaur, defendant No. 2 and daughters of Smt.
			<lb />
			Gurbax Kaur had executed a General Power of Attorney (in short
			<lb />
			GPA) in favour of defendant No. 1 on 09.03.1981. Plaintiff&apos;s case
			<lb />
			was that defendant No. 1 acting as GPA of his mother, on
			<lb />
			11.09.2001 executed an agreement to sell the suit land to the
			<lb />
			plaintiff for a sale consideration of Rs. 75,000/-. Earnest money of
			<lb />
			Rs. 10,000/-was received by Smt. Gurbax Kaur and Rs. 30,000/-
			<lb />
			was received by defendant No.1 towards sale consideration.
			<lb />
			Instead of executing the sale deed in plaintiff&apos;s favour, Smt.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			4
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Gurbax Kaur sold the suit land in favour of defendant No. 2 vide a
			<lb />
			registered sale deed on 28.12.2001. In his written statement,
			<lb />
			defendant No. 1 supported plaintiff&apos;s case in entirety but did not
			<lb />
			step into the witness box. Defendant No. 2 vehemently contested
			<lb />
			plaintiff&apos;s case and called the suit to be collusive between plaintiff
			<lb />
			and defendant No. 1. Learned trial Court decreed the suit on
			<lb />
			16.03.2009. Learned First Appellate Court on 16.08.2010
			<lb />
			reversed the decree and dismissed the suit. Plaintiff was,
			<lb />
			however, held entitled to recover Rs. 30,000/-from defendant No.
			<lb />
			1. Aggrieved against dismissal of his suit, plaintiff has preferred
			<lb />
			RSA No. 517 of 2010. Defendant No. 1 has filed RSA No. 499 of
			<lb />
			2010 against the common judgment and decree, whereby he has
			<lb />
			been held liable to pay Rs. 30,000/-alongwith interest @ 6% per
			<lb />
			annum from the date of institution of suit till its realization to the
			<lb />
			plaintiff.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Brief facts may now be noticed :-
			<lb />
			2(i)
			<lb />
			A civil suit was instituted by the appellant for (i)
			<lb />
			possession through specific performance of an agreement to sell,
			<lb />
			dated 11.09.2001 of land comprised in Khewat No. 595, Khatauni
			<lb />
			No. 646, Khasra Nos. 1540, 1541 and 1542, measuring 114.86
			<lb />
			square meters, situated at village Santoshgarh, Tehsil and District
			<lb />
			Una, H.P.; (ii) declaration that sale deed dated 28.12.2001
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			5
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			executed in favour of defendant No. 2 with respect to the suit land
			<lb />
			is illegal, null and void.
			<lb />
			The factual foundation pleaded in the plaint was that
			<lb />
			defendant No. 1 (respondent No. 1) was the GPA of his mother
			<lb />
			Smt. Gurbax Kaur, his brother Ashok Kumar (defendant No. 2)
			<lb />
			and his sisters (non parties to the suit). Smt. Gurbax Kaur was
			<lb />
			owner in possession of the suit land. In July, 2001, the
			<lb />
			defendants alongwith their mother approached the plaintiff to sell
			<lb />
			the suit land. A consensus was arrived on 09.07.2001 regarding
			<lb />
			purchase of suit land by the plaintiff for a total sale consideration
			<lb />
			of Rs. 75,000/-. A sum of Rs. 10,000/-was paid by the plaintiff as
			<lb />
			earnest money on 09.07.2001. A sum of Rs. 5,000/-was paid on
			<lb />
			07.08.2001. Rs. 5,000/-was also advanced on 21.08.2001
			<lb />
			towards sale consideration. At the time of payment of further
			<lb />
			amount of Rs. 20,000/-an agreement to sell the suit land was
			<lb />
			executed in plaintiff&apos;s favour on 11.09.2001 by defendant No. 1 as
			<lb />
			the general power of attorney on behalf of his mother. The
			<lb />
			plaintiff pleaded that the defendants and their mother received
			<lb />
			total amount of Rs. 40,000/-towards total sale consideration of
			<lb />
			Rs. 75,000/-. The plaintiff was ready and willing to pay the
			<lb />
			balance sale consideration amount of Rs. 35,000/-, however, the
			<lb />
			mother of the defendants died in February, 2002. The sale deed
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			6
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			was not executed in plaintiff&apos;s favour. After issuing legal notice to
			<lb />
			the defendants on 29.08.2002, the plaintiff inspected the revenue
			<lb />
			record and became aware of the fact that sale deed of suit land
			<lb />
			had already been executed by late Smt. Smt. Gurbax Kaur in
			<lb />
			favour of her son i.e. defendant No. 2 on 28.12.2001.
			<lb />
			In the backdrop of above facts, plaintiff instituted the
			<lb />
			suit for specific performance of agreement dated 11.09.2001 and
			<lb />
			for declaration that the sale deed dated 28.12.2001 and
			<lb />
			consequent revenue entries in favour of defendant No. 2 were
			<lb />
			void and illegal.
			<lb />
			2(ii)
			<lb />
			In his written statement, defendant No. 2 claimed the
			<lb />
			suit filed by the plaintiff to be collusive, fraudulent and at the
			<lb />
			instigation of defendant No. 1. Defendant No. 2 admitted
			<lb />
			execution of sale deed of suit land and the &apos;abadi&apos; standing over
			<lb />
			it, in his favour by his mother Smt. Gurbax Kaur on 28.12.2001.
			<lb />
			Defendant No. 2 pleaded himself to be owner in possession of
			<lb />
			the suit land and that he had raised construction over it. He
			<lb />
			denied his mother entering into any agreement to sell the suit
			<lb />
			land in favour of plaintiff or having received any money in lieu
			<lb />
			thereof. He also denied his mother having approached the
			<lb />
			plaintiff for sale of suit land. He also pleaded that his mother
			<lb />
			never authorized defendant No. 1 to sell the suit land in favour of
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			7
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			plaintiff. That he (defendant No. 2) was bonafide purchaser of the
			<lb />
			suit land for valuable consideration. Defendant No. 2 submitted
			<lb />
			that his brother i.e. defendant No. 1 was appointed as GPA by
			<lb />
			him (defendant No.2) and their mother to look after and manage
			<lb />
			their joint property in Ranchi (Bihar) and Hoshiarpur (Punjab).
			<lb />
			Defendant No. 1 became dishonest and alienated entire joint
			<lb />
			property in Bihar and some of the properties in Punjab on the
			<lb />
			basis of GPA without the consent of defendant No. 2 and his
			<lb />
			mother. On coming to know these facts, they cancelled the GPA
			<lb />
			in favour of defendant No.1.
			<lb />
			2(iii)
			<lb />
			Defendant No. 1 in his written statement admitted
			<lb />
			entire case of the plaintiff and denied the averments of the written
			<lb />
			statement filed by defendant No.1. He submitted that the sale
			<lb />
			deed of the suit land in favour of defendant No. 2 was got
			<lb />
			executed taking undue advantage of absence of defendant No.1.
			<lb />
			That it was fabricated and fictitious sale deed. That defendant No.
			<lb />
			2 was liable to execute the sale deed in favour of plaintiff since
			<lb />
			the suit land was now in the name of defendant No. 2.
			<lb />
			2(iv)
			<lb />
			Plaintiff and defendant No. 2 led evidence in support of
			<lb />
			their respective contentions. Defendant No. 1 did not adduce any
			<lb />
			evidence. Learned trial Court decreed the suit vide judgment and
			<lb />
			decree dated 16.03.2009. The decree was reversed by the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			8
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			learned First Appellate Court on 16.08.2010. Plaintiff&apos;s suit was
			<lb />
			dismissed. He, however, was held entitled to recover Rs. 30,000/-
			<lb />
			from defendant No. 1.
			<lb />
			It is in the aforesaid background that the plaintiff and
			<lb />
			defendant No. 1 have preferred their respective appeals.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			RSA No. 517 of 2010
			<lb />
			This appeal was admitted on 03.12.2010 on the
			<lb />
			following substantial questions of law :-
			<lb />
			&quot;1. Whether learned District Judge erred in appreciating the
			<lb />
			provisions of law applicable, pleadings of the parties and
			<lb />
			evidence adduced by them in its right perspective thereby
			<lb />
			vitiating the impugned judgment and decree ?
			<lb />
			2. Whether learned District Judge erred in appreciating the
			<lb />
			oral and documentary evidence with special reference to
			<lb />
			documents, Exhibit PW-2/A, exhibit PW-5/A, exhibit P-4 and
			<lb />
			exhibit P-5 and so also the statement of PW-2 thereby
			<lb />
			vitiating the impugned judgment and decree ?&quot;
			<lb />
			RSA No. 499 of 2010
			<lb />
			This appeal was admitted on 24.11.2010 on the
			<lb />
			following substantial questions of law :-
			<lb />
			&quot;1. Whether a decree for recovery of Rs. 30,000/-could be
			<lb />
			passed against the appellant in the absence of any claim set
			<lb />
			up by the plaintiff in the suit and the decree as passed is is
			<lb />
			beyond pleadings and the findings recorded by the learned
			<lb />
			First Appellate Court contrary to the pleadings are vitiated ?
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			2. Whether the appellant who was having legal and valid
			<lb />
			General Power of Attorney of his mother could be held
			<lb />
			personally liable for the acts done by him while acting as
			<lb />
			General Power of Attorney of his mother and the findings
			<lb />
			thus recorded by the learned Appellate Court are vitiated ?
			<lb />
			3. Whether the suit could be held to be filed in collusion with
			<lb />
			the appellant simply on the ground that the appellant had
			<lb />
			admitted the execution of agreement to sell Ex. PW-2/A
			<lb />
			executed by him as General Power of Attorney and the
			<lb />
			findings thus recorded are vitiated ?
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			The substantial questions of law formulated in both the
			<lb />
			appeals are all based on facts and can be answered after
			<lb />
			considering the pleadings and the evidence.
			<lb />
			I have heard Shri B.S. Chauhan, learned senior
			<lb />
			Counsel for the appellant, Shri Y.P. Sood, learned counsel for
			<lb />
			respondent No. 1 and Ms. Devyani Sharma, learned counsel for
			<lb />
			respondent No. 2. With their assistance, I have seen the record of
			<lb />
			case files.
			<lb />
			There are two aspects of the case :-
			<lb />
			One revolves around the agreement to sell dated
			<lb />
			11.09.2001 allegedly executed by defendant No. 1 as GPA of his
			<lb />
			mother Smt. Gurbax Kaur in favour of the plaintiff regarding sale
			<lb />
			of the suit property. Plaintiff seeks enforcement of this agreement.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			10
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			The other revolves around the sale deed dated
			<lb />
			28.12.2001 allegedly executed by Smt. Gurbax Kaur in favour of
			<lb />
			defendant No. 2 of the suit property. Plaintiff has questioned this
			<lb />
			sale deed.
			<lb />
			The above two aspects are being separately considered
			<lb />
			hereinbelow :-
			<lb />
			4(a)
			<lb />
			Regarding agreement to sell dated 11.09.2001
			<lb />
			Following is relevant in this regard.
			<lb />
			4(a)(i)
			<lb />
			The case set up by the plaintiff is that agreement to sell
			<lb />
			dated 11.09.2001 (Ex. PW-2/A) was preceded by three receipts.
			<lb />
			First receipt is dated 09.07.2001 (Ex. PW-5/A).
			<lb />
			According to this receipt, an amount of Rs. 10,000/-was received
			<lb />
			by Smt. Gurbax Kaur from the plaintiff as earnest money towards
			<lb />
			sale consideration with respect to the sale of suit land by her to
			<lb />
			plaintiff against total agreed sale consideration of Rs. 75,000/-.
			<lb />
			To the naked eye, the receipt (Ex. PW-5/A) does not
			<lb />
			appear to be genuine. The last lines appear to have been
			<lb />
			squeezed in the receipt in order to deliberately adjust them above
			<lb />
			the existing thumb impression stated to be that of Smt. Gurbax
			<lb />
			Kaur.
			<lb />
			As per this receipt, Smt. Gurbax Kaur the vender
			<lb />
			received Rs. 10,000/-from the plaintiff on 09.07.2001. In his
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			11
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			affidavit, submitted by way of examination-in-chief, the plaintiff
			<lb />
			(PW-4) stated that the receipt was handed over to him by Smt.
			<lb />
			Gurbax Kaur on 09.07.2001 after receiving Rs. 10,000/-.
			<lb />
			However, in his cross examination, he stated that this receipt
			<lb />
			was not prepared before him. He did not know who wrote the
			<lb />
			receipt and where. He could not even name the persons in whose
			<lb />
			presence the receipt was written. He stated that he was handed
			<lb />
			over the receipt by Bhagat Ram. However, he again stated that
			<lb />
			Bhagat Ram and Smt. Gurbax Kaur were there while handing
			<lb />
			over the receipt to him. PW-5 Madan Lal though identified his
			<lb />
			father&apos;s (Bhagat Ram) signature at the bottom of the receipt,
			<lb />
			however, PW-5 is not a witness to the contents or to the events
			<lb />
			described in the document.
			<lb />
			Under the orders of learned trial Court, the Finger Print
			<lb />
			Bureau Phillaur was sent receipt dated 09.07.2001, cancellation
			<lb />
			deed dated 19.01.2002 and sale deed dated 28.12.2001. The
			<lb />
			Bureau reported that &quot;impression Q on the receipt Ex. PW-5/A
			<lb />
			dated 09.07.2001 is sufficiently ink smudged and do not permit of
			<lb />
			comparison on its dependable ridge characteristic details. Hence
			<lb />
			no opinion can, therefore, be given on it.&quot;
			<lb />
			4(a)(ii)
			<lb />
			The receipts dated 07.08.2001 (Ex. P-4) and dated
			<lb />
			21.08.2001 (Ex. P-5) bear the signatures of defendant No. 1 as
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			12
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			recipient of the earnest money. Surprisingly, Ex. PW-5/A which
			<lb />
			allegedly bears the thumb impression of Smt. Gurbax Kaur was
			<lb />
			stated to be witnessed by Bhagat Ram, whereas for executing
			<lb />
			these two receipts, i.e. Ex. P-4 and P-5, the witness was not
			<lb />
			considered necessary. The obvious reason for the same, which
			<lb />
			immediately flashes, is that Ex. PW-5/A needed to be secured by
			<lb />
			the plaintiff and defendant No. 1 in order to show that it was
			<lb />
			executed by Smt. Gurbax Kaur, whereas the other two receipts
			<lb />
			are executed by defendant No. 1 who has admitted the entire
			<lb />
			case of the plaintiff and is in league with him.
			<lb />
			4(a) (iii) Case of the plaintiff is that on 11.09.2021, defendant
			<lb />
			No. 1 as GPA of Smt. Gurbax Kaur received Rs. 20,000/-from
			<lb />
			him for his (defendant No.1&apos;s) mother in lieu of intended sale of
			<lb />
			the suit land and executed an agreement to sell. This agreement
			<lb />
			to sell is Ex. PW-2/A. A close look at this agreement shows its
			<lb />
			execution in somewhat unusual manner. The witnesses have not
			<lb />
			signed at the end of the document. One of the witnesses Mangat
			<lb />
			Ram signed on the left hand side margin at the first page of the
			<lb />
			agreement and the other witness Dharam Chand signed on the
			<lb />
			left hand margin of the second page of the agreement. The
			<lb />
			vendee/plaintiff has not signed at the bottom of the agreement,
			<lb />
			but on the left hand margin of the first page of the agreement.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			13
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			The agreement (Ex. PW-2/A) makes no reference to
			<lb />
			the house standing over the suit land. The plaintiff in his affidavit
			<lb />
			furnished by way of examination-in-chief stated that house was
			<lb />
			also intended to be sold under the agreement. While deposing in
			<lb />
			his cross-examination as PW-4, he stated that agreement records
			<lb />
			sale of house whereas it is not so recorded in the agreement.
			<lb />
			The agreement (Ex. PW-2/A) is scribed by document
			<lb />
			writer Anil Jaswal, who appeared in the witness box as PW-2. In
			<lb />
			his affidavit furnished by way of examination-in-chief, he stated
			<lb />
			having scribed the agreement on the asking of defendant No. 1
			<lb />
			and that after scribing the same, he read out the document to
			<lb />
			defendant No. 1 and the witnesses. He has not mentioned that
			<lb />
			plaintiff was present at the time of execution of the agreement.
			<lb />
			Anil Jaswal was directed to produce his register of entry of
			<lb />
			documents. During his cross-examination, he stated to have lost
			<lb />
			this register and did not produce it.
			<lb />
			Mangat Ram, who allegedly witnessed the execution of
			<lb />
			the agreement, dated 11.09.2001 did not step into the witness
			<lb />
			box. Dharam Chand, the other witness to the agreement, also did
			<lb />
			not step into the witness box. The Notary Public also did not step
			<lb />
			into the witness box. The defendant No.1, who executed the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			14
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			agreement as GPA of his mother in favour of the plaintiff, also did
			<lb />
			not step into witness box.
			<lb />
			The plaintiff in his affidavit, furnished by way of
			<lb />
			examination-in-chief, stated that defendant No. 1 as GPA of his
			<lb />
			mother had executed the agreement to sell in his favour on
			<lb />
			11.09.2001 through scribe Anil Jaswal in presence of witnesses.
			<lb />
			He further goes on to state that the agreement was scribed in
			<lb />
			presence of witnesses. It was read out to them and thereafter
			<lb />
			they appended their signatures on the same. That he had paid an
			<lb />
			amount of Rs. 20,000/-to defendant No. 1 on 11.09.2001,
			<lb />
			whereas in cross examination, he deposed that after getting the
			<lb />
			document scribed from the document writer, he had left the
			<lb />
			premises. That he never appeared before any authority for the
			<lb />
			attestation of the document. He further states in his cross
			<lb />
			examination that the document was taken for notarization after 2-
			<lb />
			3 days of its execution. He failed to recall the day and the events
			<lb />
			relating to this agreement.
			<lb />
			Defendant No. 2 stated that defendant No.1 had
			<lb />
			colluded with the plaintiff to deprive him the suit property. Plaintiff
			<lb />
			in connivance with defendant No. 1 had created fictitious receipts
			<lb />
			and agreement to sell. He also stated that entire property of his
			<lb />
			mother and three sisters at Hoshiarpur and Ranchi had been sold
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			15
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			by defendant No. 1. Further, that Smt. Gurbax Kaur was left with
			<lb />
			suit property alone.
			<lb />
			4(b)
			<lb />
			Sale Deed dated 28.12.2001 executed in favour of
			<lb />
			defendant No. 2.
			<lb />
			4(b)(i)
			<lb />
			Ex. DW-3/A is the sale deed executed on 28.12.2001 in
			<lb />
			favour of defendant No. 1. In terms of this sale deed, the seller
			<lb />
			Smt. Gurbax Kaur had sold the suit land in favour of defendant
			<lb />
			No. 2. The sale deed was registered on 19.01.2002 at Sr. No.
			<lb />
			1923. DW-5 is the registration Clerk who has proved the
			<lb />
			registration of Ex. DW-3/A vide endorsement Ex. DW-5/B. DW-6
			<lb />
			is the scribe of the sale deed (Ex. DW-3/A). He has stated that
			<lb />
			the document was scribed by him on the asking of Smt. Gurbax
			<lb />
			Kaur and was read out to her and the witnesses as well as to
			<lb />
			defendant No. 1. After understanding it, they had appended their
			<lb />
			thumb impressions/signatures over it. He has also given the
			<lb />
			details of the serial number and the date when the document was
			<lb />
			entered in the register maintained by him for the said purpose.
			<lb />
			DW-9 is an Advocate, who had attested the sale deed.
			<lb />
			He testified that he and Jarnail Singh had witnessed execution of
			<lb />
			sale deed Ex. DW-3/A. He deposed that scribe had read out the
			<lb />
			document to the seller Smt. Gurbax Kaur who after admitting it to
			<lb />
			be correct appended her thumb impression on it. That witnesses
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			16
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			also signed the document. That the document was taken to the
			<lb />
			Sub Registrar for registration. That the Sub Registrar had read
			<lb />
			out the document to all before registering it. Defendant No. 2 has
			<lb />
			proved execution of sale deed in accordance with law.
			<lb />
			Ex. DW-7/A is the document whereby defendant No.
			<lb />
			2 cancelled the GPA earlier executed by him in favour of
			<lb />
			defendant No. 1. This document was registered on 19.01.2002.
			<lb />
			The document has been proved in accordance with law.
			<lb />
			Ex. DW-5/A is a document whereby Smt. Gurbax
			<lb />
			Kaur and her daughters cancelled the GPA earlier executed by
			<lb />
			them in favour of defendant No. 1. Ex. DW-5/A was executed on
			<lb />
			19.01.2002. The document was registered and has been proved
			<lb />
			in accordance with law. This document records an averment that
			<lb />
			defendant No. 1 had not withstood the confidence reposed in him
			<lb />
			by his mother Smt. Gurbax Kaur and sisters.
			<lb />
			4(b)(ii)
			<lb />
			Ex. DW-4/A is the copy of plaint filed by defendant
			<lb />
			No. 1 against defendant No. 2. This Civil Suit No. 218 of 2002
			<lb />
			was instituted by defendant No. 1 on 30.09.2002 against
			<lb />
			defendant No. 2. In this civil suit, challenge was made by
			<lb />
			defendant No. 1 to the sale deed executed by Smt. Gurbax Kaur
			<lb />
			in favour of defendant No. 2 on 28.12.2001. Contention of
			<lb />
			defendant No. 1 was that the sale deed was void and suit
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			17
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			property, therefore, be declared as joint property of defendants
			<lb />
			No. 1 and 2. Mutation No. 89, attested in favour of defendant No.
			<lb />
			2 on the basis of the sale deed be also declared void. Noticeable
			<lb />
			fact is that in the entire plaint, there is no mention of any
			<lb />
			agreement to sell dated 11.09.2001 executed by defendant No. 1
			<lb />
			as GPA of his mother for selling the suit land in favour of plaintiff.
			<lb />
			The suit filed by defendant No. 1 was dismissed in default on
			<lb />
			24.09.2004. The order has attained finality.
			<lb />
			4(b)(iii) Ex. D-2 is copy of an order passed by Settlement
			<lb />
			Collector Kangra on 22.12.2003 dismissing the appeal preferred
			<lb />
			by defendant No. 1 against mutation No. 89, attested on
			<lb />
			02.01.2002 in favour of defendant No. 2 with respect to the suit
			<lb />
			land. The order notices the fact that sale deed with respect to the
			<lb />
			suit land was executed in favour of defendant No. 2 on
			<lb />
			28.12.2001. In terms of this sale deed, the vender (Smt. Gurbax
			<lb />
			Kaur) had sold the suit land for a sale consideration amount of
			<lb />
			Rs. 53,500/-to defendant No. 2. This sale deed was registered at
			<lb />
			Sr. No. 1923 on 28.12.2001. On the basis of this sale deed,
			<lb />
			mutation No. 89 was attested in favour of defendant No. 2. The
			<lb />
			seller was alive at the time of attestation of mutation. The order
			<lb />
			dated 22.12.2003 has become final.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			18
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			5.
			<lb />
			Having discussed above the entire relevant evidence,
			<lb />
			there is no escape from concluding that in the facts and
			<lb />
			circumstances of the case, the agreement to sell dated
			<lb />
			11.09.2001 is the result of fraud and collusion between plaintiff
			<lb />
			and defendant No.1. Suit filed by the plaintiff for specific
			<lb />
			performance of this agreement cannot be decreed. The reasons
			<lb />
			for this are :-
			<lb />
			5(a)
			<lb />
			Plaintiff&apos;s main thrust is on the stand taken by
			<lb />
			defendant No. 1 in his written statement. Defendant no. 1 in his
			<lb />
			written statement has admitted that he had executed the
			<lb />
			agreement to sell dated 11.09.2001 as a GPA holder of his
			<lb />
			mother Smt. Gurbax Kaur in favour of the plaintiff. He has also
			<lb />
			admitted in his written statement that his mother intended to sell
			<lb />
			the suit property to the plaintiff for a sale consideration of Rs.
			<lb />
			75,000/-. That she herself received Rs. 10,000/-on 09.07.2001,
			<lb />
			whereas as her GPA, he received Rs. 5,000/-on 07.08.2001, Rs.
			<lb />
			5,000/-on 21.08.2001 and Rs. 20,000/-on 11.09.2001.
			<lb />
			Defendant No. 2 has not admitted plaintiff&apos;s case.
			<lb />
			Defendant no. 2 is the person in whose favour sale deed Ex. PW-
			<lb />
			3/A has been executed by Smt. Gurbax Kaur on 28.12.2001.
			<lb />
			Defendant No. 1 may have admitted plaintiff&apos;s case in his written
			<lb />
			statement, but he did not step into the witness box. Defendant
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			19
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			No. 2 did not get any opportunity to cross examine defendant No.
			<lb />
			1. Plaintiff&apos;s case was primarily based upon defendant No. 1&apos;s
			<lb />
			admission. Plaintiff did not produce defendant No. 1 in the
			<lb />
			witness box. Defendant No. 1&apos;s written statement cannot be taken
			<lb />
			to be true and accepted as such as against the version of
			<lb />
			defendant No. 2. The credibility of stand taken by defendant No. 1
			<lb />
			has gone un-tested. Defendant No. 1 has not cross examined
			<lb />
			defendant No. 2, rather plaintiff has cross examined defendant
			<lb />
			No. 2. The other evidence on record in this regard becomes
			<lb />
			material in view of defendant No. 1 having not deposed.
			<lb />
			5(b)
			<lb />
			Defendant No. 1 was aware that sale deed with
			<lb />
			respect to the suit land and the &apos;abadi&apos; standing over it, had been
			<lb />
			executed by Smt. Gurbax Kaur in favour of defendant No. 2 on
			<lb />
			28.12.2001. Mutation No. 89 on the basis of the sale deed was
			<lb />
			attested in favour of defendant No. 2 on 02.01.2002. Defendant
			<lb />
			No. 1 had challenged the order of attestation of mutation. His
			<lb />
			appeal was dismissed by the Settlement Collector on 22.12.2003.
			<lb />
			While dismissing the appeal, the Collector recorded a finding that
			<lb />
			the vender Smt. Gurbax Kaur was alive on 02.01.2002 at the
			<lb />
			time of attestation of mutation. Defendant No. 1 did not challenge
			<lb />
			the order dated 22.12.2003 any further.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			20
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			In his written statement filed on 28.02.2003, defendant
			<lb />
			No. 1 has not even cared to mention about his challenge to the
			<lb />
			mutation attested in favour of defendant No. 2.
			<lb />
			5(c)
			<lb />
			Defendant No. 1 had filed a civil suit challenging the
			<lb />
			sale deed executed in favour of defendant No. 2. This civil suit
			<lb />
			(Ex. DW-4/A) was filed on 30.09.2002. In this plaint, defendant
			<lb />
			No.1 does not mention anything about his executing any
			<lb />
			agreement to sell on 11.09.2001 in favour of present plaintiff. His
			<lb />
			written statement filed in the present civil suit on 28.02.2003
			<lb />
			admitting entire case of the plaintiff with respect to execution of
			<lb />
			agreement dated 11.09.2001 become suspicious.The evidence in
			<lb />
			respect of agreement to sell dated 11.09.2001 and the receipts
			<lb />
			relied upon by the appellant/plaintiff have already been discussed
			<lb />
			earlier. The present suit filed by the appellant has to be held as
			<lb />
			collusive with defendant No. 1.
			<lb />
			5(d)
			<lb />
			Defendant No.1-the executant, of the agreement dated
			<lb />
			11.09.2001, for specific performance of which the present suit
			<lb />
			has been filed, did not step into the witness box. Alleged witness
			<lb />
			to the agreement i.e. Mangat Ram also did not step into the
			<lb />
			witness box. Dharam Chand, the second witness to the
			<lb />
			agreement was also not produced in the witness box. The person
			<lb />
			who notarized the agreement was also not produced. Scribe of
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			21
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			the agreement though appeared in the witness box, but his
			<lb />
			deposition runs contrary on material particulars to the deposition
			<lb />
			of the plaintiff. Scribe&apos;s statement does not even inspire
			<lb />
			confidence. He deposed having executed the agreement only at
			<lb />
			the instance of defendant No. 1. He does not even refer to the
			<lb />
			presence of the plaintiff at the time of scribing the agreement.
			<lb />
			Despite having been asked to produce the register wherein the
			<lb />
			document i.e. agreement to sell dated 11.09.2001 was allegedly
			<lb />
			entered, the scribe did not produce the register.
			<lb />
			5(e)
			<lb />
			Learned senior Counsel for the appellant/plaintiff
			<lb />
			argued that the sale deed executed in favour of defendant No. 2
			<lb />
			by his mother was illegal and void on the ground that no
			<lb />
			money was transacted between the vender and vendee. It was
			<lb />
			highlighted that sale must be for a valid consideration. Section 54
			<lb />
			of the Transfer of Property Act was pressed into service which
			<lb />
			reads as under :-
			<lb />
			&quot;54. &quot;Sale&quot; defined.-&apos;&apos;Sale&quot; is a transfer of ownership in
			<lb />
			exchange for a price paid or promised or part-paid and part-
			<lb />
			promised.
			<lb />
			Sale how made.-Such transfer, in the case of tangible
			<lb />
			immoveable property of the value of one hundred rupees and
			<lb />
			upwards, or in the case of a reversion or other intangible
			<lb />
			thing, can be made only by a registered instrument.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			22
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			In the case of tangible immoveable property of a value less
			<lb />
			than one hundred rupees, such transfer may be made either by
			<lb />
			a registered instrument or by delivery of the property. Delivery
			<lb />
			of tangible immoveable property takes place when the seller
			<lb />
			places the buyer, or such person as he directs, in possession of
			<lb />
			the property.
			<lb />
			Contract for sale.-A contract for the sale of immoveable
			<lb />
			property is a contract that a sale of such property shall take
			<lb />
			place on terms settled between the parties. It does not, of itself,
			<lb />
			create any interest in or charge on such property.&quot;
			<lb />
			In support of the above submissions, reliance was
			<lb />
			placed upon a decision of Hon&apos;ble Apex Court dated 22.11.2021
			<lb />
			in Civil Appeal Nos. 6989-6992 of 2021, titled Kewal Krishan
			<lb />
			Vs. Rajesh Kumar and others etc. wherein it was held that a
			<lb />
			sale of an immovable property has to be for a price. The price
			<lb />
			may be payable in future. It may be partly paid and the remaining
			<lb />
			part can be made payable in future. The payment of price is an
			<lb />
			essential part of a sale covered by section 54 of the TP Act. If a
			<lb />
			sale deed in respect of an immovable property is executed
			<lb />
			without payment of price and if it does not provide for the
			<lb />
			payment of price at a future date, it is not a sale at all in the eyes
			<lb />
			of law. It is of no legal effect. Therefore, such a sale will be void. It
			<lb />
			will not effect the transfer of the immovable property.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			23
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			In AIR 1922 Madras 311, titled Madam Pilai Vs.
			<lb />
			Badrakali Ammal and another, it was held that &quot;price has a well
			<lb />
			defined meaning. It means money, but not necessarily money
			<lb />
			handed over in current coin at the time but includes money which
			<lb />
			might be already due, or might be payable in the future.&quot;
			<lb />
			In the instant case, sale deed (Ex. DW-3/A) was
			<lb />
			executed by Smt. Gurbax Kaur in favour of defendant No. 2 for
			<lb />
			Rs. 53,500/-which were lent to her/spent on her by him. Sale
			<lb />
			deed records the fact that defendant no. 2 has been taking care
			<lb />
			of his mother, providing her with food, clothing, shelter etc. The
			<lb />
			sale deed also records that vender-Gurbax Kaur has already
			<lb />
			been paid Rs. 53,500/-by defendant No. 2 and in lieu of the
			<lb />
			same, she had executed the sale deed. Sale deed (Ex. DW-3/A)
			<lb />
			is not without consideration. In the facts of the case, sale deed
			<lb />
			(Ex. DW-3/A) cannot be said to be a sham transaction. It was a
			<lb />
			registered sale deed, duly proved in evidence in accordance with
			<lb />
			law. On the basis of this sale deed, mutation No. 89 was attested
			<lb />
			in favour of defendant No. 2. The vender was herself alive at the
			<lb />
			time of attestation of mutation. The sale deed has been
			<lb />
			questioned by the plaintiff. It has already been held that
			<lb />
			agreement to sell the suit land executed by defendant No. 2 as
			<lb />
			GPA of Smt. Gurbax Kaur in favour of plaintiff is collusive and
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			24
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			cannot be enforced by the plaintiff. Proceeding from there,
			<lb />
			plaintiff becomes a third party. It is settled law that passing of
			<lb />
			consideration under a sale deed cannot be questioned by a third
			<lb />
			party. {Re: (2016) 12 SCC 288 Muddasani Venkata Narsaiah
			<lb />
			Vs. Muddasani Sarojana}. Insofar as defendant No. 1 is
			<lb />
			concerned, he already took his chance in challenging the sale
			<lb />
			deed (Ex.DW-3/A) in the civil suit and lost it.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			In view of above discussion, both substantial questions
			<lb />
			of law formulated in the Regular Second Appeal No. 517 of 2010
			<lb />
			are answered against the appellant/plaintiff. Learned first
			<lb />
			appellate Court did not commit any error in appreciating the
			<lb />
			pleadings, the evidence and law in dismissing the suit filed by the
			<lb />
			plaintiff. The oral as well as documentary evidence including Ex.
			<lb />
			PW-2/A, Ex. PW-5/A, Ex. P-4, Ex.P-6 and statement of PW-2
			<lb />
			were all properly considered and appreciated by the learned first
			<lb />
			appellate Court. Consequently, I find no merit in Regular Second
			<lb />
			Appeal No. 517 of 2010.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			For all the above reasons, the substantial questions of
			<lb />
			law framed in RSA No. 499 of 2010 are decided against the
			<lb />
			appellant therein (defendant No.1). Defendant No. 1 has admitted
			<lb />
			receipt of an amount of Rs. 30,000/-from the plaintiff for sale of
			<lb />
			suit land in plaintiff&apos;s favour. Therefore, learned first appellate
			<lb />
			</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		
		<page>
			25
			<lb />
		</page>
			<body>
			Court was justified in holding the plaintiff entitled to the recovery
			<lb />
			of this amount alongwith interest from defendant No. 1.
			<lb />
			Consequently, I find no merit in Regular Second Appeal No. 499
			<lb />
			of 2010.
			<lb />
			Regular Second Appeal No. 517 of 2010 and Regular
			<lb />
			Second Appeal No. 499 of 2010 are dismissed. Pending
			<lb />
			applications, if any, in both the appeals are also disposed off.
			<lb />
			10 th DECEMBER, 2021 (K)
			<lb />
			( Jyotsna Rewal Dua )
			<lb />
			Judge
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:20 :::CIS </note>


	</text>
</tei>