<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			H
			<lb />
			i g h
			<lb />
			C
			<lb />
			o u r t o f H
			<lb />
			. P .
			<lb />
			REPORTABLE
			<lb />
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF HIMACHAL PRADESH AT SHIMLA
			<lb />
			ON THE 22 nd DAY OF FEBRUARY,2022
			<lb />
			BEFORE
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE MOHAMMAD RAFIQ,
			<lb />
			CHIEF JUSTICE
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE AJAY MOHAN GOEL
			<lb />
			&amp;
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MS. JUSTICE JYOTSNA REWAL DUA
			<lb />
			CIVIL WRIT PETITION No.2711 of 2017
			<lb />
			ALONGWITH
			<lb />
			CIVIL WRIT PETITION (ORIGINAL APPLICATION)
			<lb />
			No.2208 of 2020
			<lb />
			1. CWP No.2711 of 2017
			<lb />
			Between:
			<lb />
			BALDEV
			<lb />
			S/O SHRI LEHNU RAM,
			<lb />
			R/O VILLAGE &amp; POST OFFICE DHARGLA,
			<lb />
			TEHSIL SALOONI, DISTRICT CHAMBA (H.P.)
			<lb />
			RETIRED AS MALI IN THE OFFICE OF
			<lb />
			DIVISIONAL FOREST OFFICER, CHURAH,
			<lb />
			TEHSIL CHURAH, DISTRICT CHAMBA (H.P.)
			<lb />
			…...PETITIONER
			<lb />
			(BY MR. ADARSH K. VASHISTA, ADVOCATE)
			<lb />
			AND
			<lb />
			1. STATE OF HIMACHAL PRADESH
			<lb />
			THROUGH ITS PRINCIPAL SECRETARY (FORESTS)
			<lb />
			TO THE GOVERNMENT OF HIMACHAL PRADESH,
			<lb />
			SHIMLA171002 (H.P.)
			<lb />
			2. THE PRINCIPAL CHIEF CONSERVATOR
			<lb />
			OF FORESTS, TALLAND, SHIMLA171001 (H.P.)
			<lb />
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</front>


		<page>
			2
			<lb />
		</page>

		<front>
			3. THE DIVISIONAL FOREST OFFICER,
			<lb />
			CHURAH FOREST DIVISION, SALOONI,
			<lb />
			DISTRICT CHAMBA (H.P.)
			<lb />
			…...RESPONDENTS
			<lb />
			(BY MR. ASHOK SHARMA, ADVOCATE GENERAL
			<lb />
			WITH MR. NAND LAL THAKUR, ADDITIONAL
			<lb />
			ADVOCATE GENERAL)
			<lb />
			2. CWPOA No.2208 of 2020
			<lb />
			Between:
			<lb />
			NARDEV SINGH
			<lb />
			S/O SHRI GEETA RAM,
			<lb />
			R/O VILLAGE SAKOL, PO BAGTHAN,
			<lb />
			TEHSIL PACHHAD, DISTRICT SIRMOUR,
			<lb />
			HIMACHAL PRADESH,
			<lb />
			PRESENTLY SERVING AS PEON ON
			<lb />
			REGULAR BASIS, RAJGARH FOREST DIVISION
			<lb />
			…...PETITIONER
			<lb />
			(BY MR. A.K. GUPTA, MR. ABHYENDRA GUPTA
			<lb />
			AND MR. MANIK SETHI, ADVOCATES)
			<lb />
			AND
			<lb />
			1. STATE OF HIMACHAL PRADESH
			<lb />
			THROUGH ITS PRINCIPAL SECRETARY (FORESTS)
			<lb />
			TO THE GOVERNMENT OF HIMACHAL PRADESH
			<lb />
			2. PRINCIPAL CHIEF CONSERVATOR
			<lb />
			OF FOREST, SHIMLA, H.P.
			<lb />
			3. THE DIVISIONAL FOREST OFFICER,
			<lb />
			RAJGARH, DISTRICT SIRMOUR,
			<lb />
			HIMACHAL PRADESH
			<lb />
			4. SECRETARY (PERSONNEL) TO THE
			<lb />
			GOVERNMENT OF HIMACHAL PRADESH
			<lb />
			…...RESPONDENTS
			<lb />
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</front>
 

		<page>
			3
			<lb />
		</page>

		<front>
			(BY MR. ASHOK SHARMA, ADVOCATE GENERAL
			<lb />
			WITH MR. NAND LAL THAKUR, ADDITIONAL
			<lb />
			ADVOCATE GENERAL)
			<lb />
			RESERVED ON
			<lb />
			:
			<lb />
			31.12.2021
			<lb />
			PRONOUNCED ON
			<lb />
			:
			<lb />
			22.02.2022
			<lb />
			These petitions coming on for orders this day, Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Mr. Justice Mohammad Rafiq, passed the following:
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			O R D E R
			<lb />
			A Division Bench of this Court observed
			<lb />
			&apos;apparent conflict&apos; in the decisions rendered by different
			<lb />
			Benches of this Court regarding interpretation of Rule 56 of
			<lb />
			Fundamental Rules (in short &apos;F.R.&apos;) visàvis notification
			<lb />
			dated 10.05.2001 amending this Fundamental Rule in the
			<lb />
			State of Himachal Pradesh as well as circular dated
			<lb />
			22.02.2010 clarifying the amendment and its applicability.
			<lb />
			For authoritative pronouncement on the subject, the matter
			<lb />
			has been referred to the Larger Bench vide following order
			<lb />
			dated 28.12.2019:
			<lb />
			&quot;Apparently there appears to be a conflict in the decisions
			<lb />
			rendered by different Benches of this Court with regard to the
			<lb />
			interpretation of FR 56.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			In LPA No. 196 of 2010, titled Bar Chand vs. State of H.P. &amp;
			<lb />
			others, decided on 21.10.2010, it was observed that all those who
			<lb />
			had been appointed even if on daily waged service prior to
			<lb />
			10.05.2001, would be entitled to continue upto the age of 60 years.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			However, the aforesaid judgment has later on been
			<lb />
			distinguished, as one rendered per incuriam, since the position
			<lb />
			under the Rules was not considered in that case and this was so
			<lb />
			stated clearly by a Division Bench (Coram: The Hon&apos;ble Mr. Justice
			<lb />
			Kurian Joseph, Chief Justice {as his Lordship then was} and The
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Mr. Justice Sanjay Karol, Judge, {as his Lordship then
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			4
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			was}) in LPA No. 298 of 2011, titled State of H.P. &amp; others vs. Chuni
			<lb />
			Lal Beldar, decided on 22.11.2011, relevant paras whereof reads as
			<lb />
			under:
			<lb />
			&quot;The State has come up in appeal against the
			<lb />
			judgment dated 24th February, 2011. The issue pertains to
			<lb />
			continuance of Class IV employee upto the age of 60 years.
			<lb />
			There is no dispute on the question of law that all those
			<lb />
			who have been appointed in regular service as Class IV
			<lb />
			employee prior to 10.5.2011, they are entitled to continue
			<lb />
			upto the age of 60 years. In LPA No. 196 of 2010 titled as
			<lb />
			Bar Chand vs. State of H.P. and others decided on 21st
			<lb />
			October, 2010, this Court had observed that all those, who
			<lb />
			have been appointed even if on daily waged service prior to
			<lb />
			10.5.2001 would be entitled to continue upto the age of 60
			<lb />
			years. That judgment has been later distinguished as one
			<lb />
			rendered per incurium since the position under the Rules
			<lb />
			was not considered in that case. What was considered in
			<lb />
			that case was the Notification issued by the Government. As
			<lb />
			per the amendment in FR 56, only those who have been
			<lb />
			regularly appointed/regularized in service prior to
			<lb />
			10.5.2001, they alone will be entitled to continue upto 60
			<lb />
			years.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Learned Single Judge in the judgment under appeal
			<lb />
			has followed LPA No. 196 of 2010, which is no more a good
			<lb />
			law in view of the position under law that being a judgment
			<lb />
			rendered per incurium it has no precedential value and it is
			<lb />
			no more binding. As far as the facts of the case of the
			<lb />
			petitioner are concerned, it is an admitted fact that he had
			<lb />
			entered regular service only in the year 2007, though he
			<lb />
			was on daily waged service prior to 2001. Only in case the
			<lb />
			writ petitioner entered regular service before 10.5.2001, he
			<lb />
			would be entitled to continue upto the age of 60 years.&quot;
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Similar issue came up before one of us (Justice Tarlok Singh
			<lb />
			Chauhan, J.) in CWP No. 7140 of 2012, titled Gian Singh vs. State of
			<lb />
			H.P. and others, decided on 24.09.2014, wherein after placing
			<lb />
			reliance upon a decision rendered by a Coordinate Bench of this
			<lb />
			Court (Coram: The Hon&apos;ble Mr. Justice Sanjay Karol, Judge, as his
			<lb />
			Lordship then was) in CWP No. 1837 of 2012, titled Tara Chand vs.
			<lb />
			State of H.P. &amp; others, decided on 21.08.2014, the age of retirement
			<lb />
			was held to be 60 years.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			The Judgment rendered in Gian Singh&apos;s case (supra) has
			<lb />
			been affirmed by learned Division Bench of this Court in LPA No.
			<lb />
			194 of 2015, titled State of H.P. &amp; others vs. Gian Singh, decided on
			<lb />
			03.12.2015 and it has been held that daily wagers appointed prior
			<lb />
			to the amendments carried out in the FR 56, have right to continue
			<lb />
			till the age of 60 years and they would not retire at the age of 58
			<lb />
			years.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			This judgment apparently is in direct conflict with the
			<lb />
			judgment rendered by another Division Bench of this Court in Chuni
			<lb />
			Lal Beldar&apos;s case (supra).
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			The issue in question is likely to come up repeatedly before
			<lb />
			this Court, therefore, it would be desirable that an authoritative
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			5
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			pronouncement qua the issue in question be made by a Larger
			<lb />
			Bench of the Court.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			Accordingly, the Registry is directed to place the matter
			<lb />
			before Hon&apos;ble the Chief Justice for constitution of the Larger Bench
			<lb />
			to resolve the issue.&quot;
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			The matter revolves around F.R. 56 and its
			<lb />
			amendments carried out by the respondentState.
			<lb />
			2(i).
			<lb />
			F.R. 56 pertains to &apos;retirement&apos;. F.R. 56(a), (b)
			<lb />
			and (e) as they existed in the year 1997, read as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;F.R. 56. (a) Except as otherwise provided in this rule,
			<lb />
			every Government servant shall retire from service on
			<lb />
			the afternoon of the last day of the month in which he
			<lb />
			attains the age of fiftyeight years.
			<lb />
			(b)
			<lb />
			A workman who is governed by these rules shall
			<lb />
			retire from service on the afternoon of the last day of
			<lb />
			the month in which he attains the age of sixty years.
			<lb />
			Note. In this Clause, a workman means a highly
			<lb />
			skilled, skilled, semiskilled, or unskilled artisan
			<lb />
			employed on a monthly rate of pay in an industrial or
			<lb />
			workcharged establishment.
			<lb />
			(e)
			<lb />
			A Government servant in Class IV service or post
			<lb />
			shall retire from service on the afternoon of the last day
			<lb />
			of the month in which he attains the age of sixty years:
			<lb />
			Provided that a Class IV employee of the
			<lb />
			Secretariat Security Force who initially enters service on
			<lb />
			or after the 15 th day of September, 1969, shall retire
			<lb />
			from service on the afternoon of the last day of the
			<lb />
			month in which he attains the age of fiftyeight years.
			<lb />
			Provided further that a Group &apos;D&apos; employee
			<lb />
			recruited as Pioneer in the General Reserve Engineer
			<lb />
			Force (GREF) on or after the 25 th day of September,
			<lb />
			1993, shall retire from service on the afternoon of the
			<lb />
			last day of the month in which he attains the age of 50
			<lb />
			years:
			<lb />
			Provided also that a Group &apos;D&apos; employee
			<lb />
			recruited or redesignated as Pioneer in the General
			<lb />
			Reserve Engineer Force (GREF) prior to the 25 th day of
			<lb />
			September, 1993 and having attained the age of 50
			<lb />
			years shall retire from service on the afternoon of the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			6
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			last day of the month in which he is declared by the
			<lb />
			appropriate authority as medically unfit and/or
			<lb />
			physically incapacitated to satisfactorily discharge the
			<lb />
			duties assigned to him.&quot;
			<lb />
			F.R. 56(e) was deleted by the Central
			<lb />
			Government vide notification dated 13.05.1998, whereby
			<lb />
			certain other amendments were also carried out in various
			<lb />
			clauses of F.R. 56.
			<lb />
			2(ii).
			<lb />
			State of Himachal Pradesh however carried out
			<lb />
			its own amendment in F.R. 56 vide notification dated
			<lb />
			30.07.1998. F.R. 56(a), (c), (d) and (e) were amended as
			<lb />
			under:
			<lb />
			&quot;(a)
			<lb />
			Except as otherwise provided in this rule, every
			<lb />
			Government servant shall retire from service on the
			<lb />
			afternoon of the last day of the month in which he
			<lb />
			attains the age of fiftyeight years.
			<lb />
			(c)
			<lb />
			A workman referred to in Clause (b) may be
			<lb />
			granted extension of service, under very special
			<lb />
			circumstances to be recorded in writing, after he attains
			<lb />
			the age of sixty years with the sanction of the
			<lb />
			appropriate authority.
			<lb />
			(d)
			<lb />
			A Government servant to whom Clause (a)
			<lb />
			applies, other than a workman referred to Clause (b),
			<lb />
			may be granted extension of service after he attains the
			<lb />
			age of fiftyeight years with the sanction of the
			<lb />
			appropriate authority if such extension is in the public
			<lb />
			interest and the grounds therefor are recorded in
			<lb />
			writing:
			<lb />
			Provided that no extension under this clause
			<lb />
			shall be granted beyond the age of sixty years except in
			<lb />
			very special circumstances:
			<lb />
			Provided further that the appropriate authority
			<lb />
			shall have the right to terminate the extension of service
			<lb />
			before the expiry of such extension by giving a notice in
			<lb />
			writing of not less than three months in the case of a
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="headnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			7
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			permanent or a quasipermanent Government servant,
			<lb />
			or, one month in the case of a temporary Government
			<lb />
			servant, or, pay and allowances in lieu of such notice.
			<lb />
			(e)
			<lb />
			A Government servant in Class IV service or post
			<lb />
			shall retire from service on the afternoon of the last day
			<lb />
			of the month in which he attains the age of sixty years:
			<lb />
			Provided that a Class IV employee of the
			<lb />
			Secretariat Security Force who initially enters service on
			<lb />
			or after the 15 th day of September, 1969, shall retire
			<lb />
			from service on the afternoon of the last day of the
			<lb />
			month in which he attains the age of fiftyeight years.&quot;
			<lb />
			2(iii).
			<lb />
			In exercise of powers conferred by proviso to
			<lb />
			Article 309 of the Constitution of India, F.R. 56(b) and (e)
			<lb />
			were further amended by the State of Himachal Pradesh on
			<lb />
			10.05.2001 as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;In exercise of the powers conferred by proviso to Article 309 of the
			<lb />
			Constitution of India, the Governor, Himachal Pradesh is pleased to
			<lb />
			make following rules further to amend the Fundamental rules, in
			<lb />
			their application to the State of Himachal Pradesh, namely:
			<lb />
			1. Short title and
			<lb />
			commencement:
			<lb />
			1. (1) These Rules may be called
			<lb />
			Fundamental (in their application to the State
			<lb />
			of Himachal Pradesh) Amendment Rules,
			<lb />
			2001.
			<lb />
			(2) These shall come into force from the date
			<lb />
			of publication in the Rajpatra Himachal
			<lb />
			Pradesh.
			<lb />
			Amendment
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			rule56
			<lb />
			2. In Rule56 of the Fundamental Rules
			<lb />
			(a) After clause (b) the following proviso shall
			<lb />
			be inserted, namely:
			<lb />
			&quot;Provided that a workman appointed on or
			<lb />
			after the date of publication of this
			<lb />
			notification in the Rajpatra Himachal
			<lb />
			Pradesh shall retire from service on the
			<lb />
			afternoon of the last day of the month in
			<lb />
			which he attains the age of 58 years.&quot;
			<lb />
			(b) After proviso to clause (e) the following
			<lb />
			second proviso shall be inserted, namely:
			<lb />
			&quot;Provided further that a ClassIV Government
			<lb />
			servant appointed on or after the date of
			<lb />
			publication of this notification in Rajpatra
			<lb />
			Himachal Pradesh shall retire from service
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			8
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			on the afternoon of the last day of the month
			<lb />
			in which he attains the age of 58 years.&quot;
			<lb />
			By order
			<lb />
			Sd/
			<lb />
			F.C.cumSecretary (Finance) to the
			<lb />
			Government of Himachal Pradesh&quot;
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			notification
			<lb />
			came
			<lb />
			into
			<lb />
			force
			<lb />
			from
			<lb />
			11.05.2001, when it was published in the Gazette. As per
			<lb />
			the above amendment, a workman appointed after
			<lb />
			10.05.2001 shall retire from service in the afternoon of the
			<lb />
			last day of the month in which he attains the age of 58
			<lb />
			years. Also as per the amendment, a ClassIV government
			<lb />
			servant appointed on or after 10.05.2001 shall retire from
			<lb />
			service in the afternoon of the last day of the month in
			<lb />
			which he attains the age of 58 years.
			<lb />
			2(iv).
			<lb />
			The effect of 2001 amendment was that all those
			<lb />
			workmen and ClassIV employees, who were appointed on
			<lb />
			and after 10.05.2001, were to retire on attaining the age of
			<lb />
			58 years. Prior to this amendment, their age of
			<lb />
			superannuation in terms of notification dated 30.07.1998
			<lb />
			was 60 years. A question arose as to what would be the age
			<lb />
			of superannuation of those, who were appointed/engaged
			<lb />
			on daily wage basis prior to 10.05.2001. A clarification was
			<lb />
			issued in this regard by the Department of Personnel on
			<lb />
			22.02.2010 as under:
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			9
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			&quot;No.PER (AP)CB(2)1/2006Vol.VIII
			<lb />
			Government of Himachal Pradesh,
			<lb />
			Department of Personnel (APIII)
			<lb />
			Dated Shimla171002
			<lb />
			22 nd February, 2010.
			<lb />
			From
			<lb />
			The Secretary (Personnel) to the
			<lb />
			Government of Himachal Pradesh.
			<lb />
			To
			<lb />
			1. All the F.C./Principal Secretaries/Secretaries to the
			<lb />
			Government of Himachal Pradesh, Shimla171002.
			<lb />
			2. All Divisional Commissioners in Himachal Pradesh.
			<lb />
			3. All Heads of Departments in Himachal Pradesh.
			<lb />
			4. All Deputy Commissioners in Himachal Pradesh.
			<lb />
			Subject: Age limit for disengagement of a daily wager.
			<lb />
			Sir,
			<lb />
			I am directed to say that consequent upon
			<lb />
			amendment in Rule56 of the Fundamental Rules vide
			<lb />
			Government
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			Himachal
			<lb />
			Pradesh,
			<lb />
			Finance
			<lb />
			(Regulations) Department Notification No.Fin(C) A(3)
			<lb />
			3/98 dated 10 th May, 2001, the issue of fixing the age
			<lb />
			of disengagement of a daily wager in all the
			<lb />
			departments had also been engaging the attention of
			<lb />
			the Government for sometime past. After careful
			<lb />
			consideration, the Government has now decided that
			<lb />
			the people who are engaged on daily wages they will
			<lb />
			also be governed by the same set of age restriction of
			<lb />
			disengagement as is applicable to regular Government
			<lb />
			employees. As such, the ClassIV daily wager engaged
			<lb />
			prior to 2001 i.e. when said notification of limiting the
			<lb />
			age of ClassIV Employees was reduced from 60 to 58
			<lb />
			years will cease to be in the employment at the age of
			<lb />
			60 years and no daily wager deployed after the
			<lb />
			reduction of the age limit in 2001 will be retained after
			<lb />
			attaining the age of 58 years. Similarly, all ClassIII
			<lb />
			and above employees if working on daily wage will
			<lb />
			cease to be employed at the age of 58 years. There
			<lb />
			should be no ambiguity in this matter and all
			<lb />
			departments are to follow this age restriction.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			The policy regarding regularization of daily
			<lb />
			waged persons remain as circulated vide this office
			<lb />
			letter No.PER (AP)CB(2)1/2006Vol.VII (Loose2),
			<lb />
			dated 28.8.2009.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			10
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			3.
			<lb />
			The above instructions may kindly be brought to
			<lb />
			the notice of all concerned for strict compliance.
			<lb />
			Yours faithfully,
			<lb />
			Sd/
			<lb />
			Deputy Secretary (Personnel) to the
			<lb />
			Government of Himachal Pradesh&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			The Government clarified that a ClassIV daily
			<lb />
			wager engaged prior to 2001 amendment will continue to
			<lb />
			serve till the age of 60 years, whereas a daily wager engaged
			<lb />
			after 2001, will cease to be in service on attaining the age of
			<lb />
			58 years.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			Certain decisions of this Court involving 2001
			<lb />
			amendment and circular dated 22.02.2010 as indicated in
			<lb />
			the reference order dated 28.12.2019 are being noticed
			<lb />
			hereinafter:
			<lb />
			3(i).
			<lb />
			Bar Chand Versus State of H.P. &amp; Ors.
			<lb />
			(LPA No.196 of 2010, decided on 21.10.2010)
			<lb />
			The issue before the Division Bench was
			<lb />
			whether the appellant engaged as a Daily Waged Beldar on
			<lb />
			05.09.1994, i.e. prior to coming into force of 2001
			<lb />
			amendment, was entitled to continue in service till the age
			<lb />
			of 60 years or not. The Court considered the circular dated
			<lb />
			22.02.2010 and held that those daily waged ClassIV
			<lb />
			employees, who were engaged as such prior to 2001
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			11
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			amendment, can continue in service till they attain the age
			<lb />
			of 60 years. It was further held that the restriction of
			<lb />
			continuing in service upto the reduced age of 58 years will
			<lb />
			apply only to those who were engaged after 2001
			<lb />
			amendment. Relevant para of the judgment reads as
			<lb />
			under:
			<lb />
			&quot;3.
			<lb />
			The learned Single Judge took the view that
			<lb />
			since the petitioner has been regularized in service after
			<lb />
			2001, he is entitled to continue only up to 58 years.
			<lb />
			But, as clearly stated in the circular, no distinction
			<lb />
			whatsoever is made as to regular service. In fact the
			<lb />
			expression used is daily wager engaged prior to 2001.
			<lb />
			Admittedly, the petitioner was engaged as Beldar in
			<lb />
			1994. The restriction up to the age of 58 years would
			<lb />
			apply only in the case of those engaged on daily wages
			<lb />
			after 2001 when the retirement age was reduced to 58
			<lb />
			years. In view of the above circumstances, we set aside
			<lb />
			the judgment of the learned Single Judge, allow the writ
			<lb />
			petition with the direction that the petitioner shall be
			<lb />
			permitted to continue up to the age of 60 years. He
			<lb />
			shall be engaged forthwith with continuity of service at
			<lb />
			any rate within a period of one week from the date of
			<lb />
			production of copy of this judgment. It is made clear
			<lb />
			that the period during which the petitioner was kept out
			<lb />
			of service shall be treated as duty for all purposes
			<lb />
			except the actual wages. In other words, there shall be
			<lb />
			continuity of service for all purposes except the actual
			<lb />
			wages since the petitioner has not actually worked
			<lb />
			during the period.&quot;
			<lb />
			3(ii).
			<lb />
			State of H.P. &amp; others Versus Chuni Lal
			<lb />
			(LPA No.298 of 2011, decided on 22.11.2011)
			<lb />
			The Division Bench in this case was considering
			<lb />
			the age upto which ClassIV employees could serve. The
			<lb />
			Bench held that:
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			12
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			(a). All those who were appointed in regular service
			<lb />
			as ClassIV employees prior to 10.05.2001 can
			<lb />
			continue to serve till they attain the age of 60
			<lb />
			years.
			<lb />
			(b). Bar Chand Versus State of H.P. &amp; others (LPA
			<lb />
			No.196 of 2010), decided on 21.10.2010, holding
			<lb />
			that daily wagers appointed prior to 10.05.2001
			<lb />
			can continue till the age of 60 years, is per
			<lb />
			incurium as rule position was not considered in
			<lb />
			Bar Chand&apos;s case, supra. As per 10.05.2001
			<lb />
			amendment,
			<lb />
			only
			<lb />
			regularly
			<lb />
			appointed/
			<lb />
			regularized in service prior to 10.05.2001 can
			<lb />
			continue in service upto the age of 60 years.
			<lb />
			(c). Writ petitioner therein engaged on daily wage
			<lb />
			basis prior to 10.05.2001 was made regular in
			<lb />
			the year 2007. Since he was regularized after
			<lb />
			10.05.2001,
			<lb />
			therefore,
			<lb />
			his
			<lb />
			age
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			superannuation will be 58 years and not 60
			<lb />
			years. The appeal filed by the State was
			<lb />
			accordingly allowed.
			<lb />
			The judgment reads as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;The State has come up in appeal against the
			<lb />
			judgment dated 24 th February, 2011. The issue pertains
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			13
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			to continuance of Class IV employee upto the age of 60
			<lb />
			years. There is no dispute on the question of law that
			<lb />
			all those who have been appointed in regular service as
			<lb />
			Class IV employee prior to 10.5.2011, they are entitled
			<lb />
			to continue upto the age of 60 years. In LPA No.196 of
			<lb />
			2010 titled as Bar Chand vs. State of H.P. and others
			<lb />
			decided on 21 st October, 2010, this Court had observed
			<lb />
			that all those, who have been appointed even if on daily
			<lb />
			waged service prior to 10.5.2001 would be entitled to
			<lb />
			continue upto the age of 60 years. That judgment has
			<lb />
			been later distinguished as one rendered per incurium
			<lb />
			since the position under the Rules was not considered
			<lb />
			in that case. What was considered in that case was the
			<lb />
			Notification issued by the Government. As per the
			<lb />
			amendment in FR 56, only those who have been
			<lb />
			regularly appointed/regularized in service prior to
			<lb />
			10.5.2001, they alone will be entitled to continue upto
			<lb />
			60 years.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Learned Single Judge in the judgment under
			<lb />
			appeal has followed LPA No. 196 of 2010, which is no
			<lb />
			more a good law in view of the position under law that
			<lb />
			being a judgment rendered per incurium it has no
			<lb />
			precedential value and it is no more binding. As far as
			<lb />
			the facts of the case of the petitioner are concerned, it is
			<lb />
			an admitted fact that he had entered regular service
			<lb />
			only in the year 2007, though he was on daily waged
			<lb />
			service prior to 2001. Only in case the writ petitioner
			<lb />
			entered regular service before 10.5.2001, he would be
			<lb />
			entitled to continue upto the age of 60 years.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			In that view of the matter, the appeal is allowed,
			<lb />
			the judgment under appeal is set aside and the writ
			<lb />
			petition is dismissed.&quot;
			<lb />
			3(iii).
			<lb />
			Tara Chand Versus State of H.P. &amp; others
			<lb />
			(CWP No.1837 of 2012, decided on21.08.2014):
			<lb />
			The writ petitioner therein was engaged as a
			<lb />
			ClassIV daily wager in the year 1991 and regularized w.e.f.
			<lb />
			01.09.2006. On 26.09.2011, the respondents granted him
			<lb />
			work charge status retrospectively w.e.f. 01.01.2001.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			14
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			Learned Single Judge noticed the 2001 amendment to F.R.
			<lb />
			56, the clarification dated 22.02.2010, the judgment passed
			<lb />
			in Bar Chand&apos;s case supra and observed that the petitioner
			<lb />
			was regularized prior to 10.05.2001, therefore, was entitled
			<lb />
			to continue in service till he attained the age of 60 years.
			<lb />
			Since the petitioner had crossed the age of superannuation,
			<lb />
			i.e. 60 years, at the time of decision of his writ petition, the
			<lb />
			respondents were directed to give him all monetary benefits
			<lb />
			for the period in question. Relevant paras from the
			<lb />
			judgment are as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;2.
			<lb />
			Petitioner was engaged as a daily wage worker
			<lb />
			in the year 1991. His services were regularized w.e.f.
			<lb />
			01.09.2006, by the Divisional Forest Officer, Wildlife
			<lb />
			Division Kullu, District Kullu, H.P., vide office order
			<lb />
			dated 11.09.2006. Respondents did not consider the
			<lb />
			petitioner&apos;s case for regularization in the light of
			<lb />
			decision rendered by the apex Court in Mool Raj
			<lb />
			Upadhyaya Versus State of H.P., 1994, Supp. (2) SCC
			<lb />
			316 as also this Court in Gauri Dutt and others Versus
			<lb />
			State of H.P., Latest HLJ 2008 (HP) 366 as such vide
			<lb />
			judgment dated 03.05.2011 rendered in CWP No. 2360
			<lb />
			of 2011, titled as Tara Chand Versus State of H.P. and
			<lb />
			others, State was directed to consider the petitioner&apos;s
			<lb />
			case, in accordance with law. Pursuant thereto, vide
			<lb />
			order dated 26.09.2011 (Annexure P1) now petitioner&apos;s
			<lb />
			case stands considered and respondents have granted
			<lb />
			him work charge status with effect from 01.01.2001.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			In the light of such development, petitioner is
			<lb />
			legally entitled to continue to serve the State up to the
			<lb />
			age of 60 years. Policy so communicated vide order
			<lb />
			dated 22.02.2010 (Annexure P7), which reads as
			<lb />
			under is evidently clear and squarely applicable………
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			The question of applicability of Fundamental
			<lb />
			Rules, 2001, so amended on 10.05.2001 (Annexure P3)
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			15
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			would not arise. It applies only to those employees who
			<lb />
			stand appointed on or after the date of amendment of
			<lb />
			Rules, which was so done in the year 2001. In the
			<lb />
			instant case, work charge status stands accorded to
			<lb />
			the petitioner with effect from 01.01.2001, date prior to
			<lb />
			the amendment of Rules. In fact, the issue is no longer
			<lb />
			res integra and squarely covered by the decision
			<lb />
			rendered by this Court in LPA No.196 of 2010, titled as
			<lb />
			Bar Chand Versus State of H.P. &amp; Others…...
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			As such, present petition as prayed is allowed.
			<lb />
			Petition was filed in the year 2012. Petitioner who has
			<lb />
			now crossed the age of superannuation i.e. 60 years
			<lb />
			hence shall be deemed to be in service. Consequently
			<lb />
			respondents are directed to take all consequential
			<lb />
			actions, including disbursement of monetary benefits, in
			<lb />
			accordance with law, within a period of three months
			<lb />
			from the date of production of copy of this order, failing
			<lb />
			which, thereafter, petitioner shall be entitled to interest
			<lb />
			thereupon @ 9% per annum. Needless to add, petitioner
			<lb />
			shall be entitled to all consequential benefits of pension
			<lb />
			etc., if otherwise permissible, in accordance with law.&quot;
			<lb />
			Though the above judgment did not notice the
			<lb />
			judgment in Chuni Lal&apos;s case, supra, however, the fact
			<lb />
			remains that the petitioner in Tara Chand&apos;s case was
			<lb />
			regularized prior to 10.05.2001. Therefore, even going by
			<lb />
			the ratio in Chuni Lal&apos;s case, supra, the petitioner in Tara
			<lb />
			Chand&apos;s case having been engaged and regularized as
			<lb />
			ClassIV employee prior to 2001 amendment would have
			<lb />
			continued to serve till the age of 60 years.
			<lb />
			3(iv).
			<lb />
			Gian Singh Versus State of H.P. and others
			<lb />
			(CWP No.7140 of 2012, decided on 24.9.2014):
			<lb />
			The petitioner therein was appointed as a Daily
			<lb />
			Wager on 01.09.1992. Learned Single Judge held him
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			16
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			entitled to be regularized w.e.f. 01.01.2000, i.e. on
			<lb />
			completion of eight years of continuous service. On that
			<lb />
			basis, the petitioner was not only engaged prior to
			<lb />
			10.05.2001, but he was also deemed to have been
			<lb />
			regularized prior to 10.05.2001, therefore, following the
			<lb />
			judgment rendered in Tara Chand&apos;s case supra, he was
			<lb />
			held entitled to continue in service till the age of 60 years.
			<lb />
			The petitioner therein had also crossed the age of 60 years
			<lb />
			at the time of decision of his writ petition, therefore, the
			<lb />
			respondents were directed to disburse monetary benefits to
			<lb />
			him for the period in question. This judgment was affirmed
			<lb />
			in LPA No.194 of 2015, decided on 03.12.2015.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			We have heard learned counsel for the parties at
			<lb />
			length. According to the learned counsel for the writ
			<lb />
			petitioners, the law laid down in Bar Chand&apos;s case is the
			<lb />
			correct interpretation of applicable rules/notifications and
			<lb />
			circulars, whereas, according to the learned Advocate
			<lb />
			General, it is the judgment rendered in Chuni Lal&apos;s case,
			<lb />
			which
			<lb />
			properly
			<lb />
			interprets
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			applicable
			<lb />
			rules/
			<lb />
			amendments/circulars.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			17
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			We hereinafter notice the sum and substance of
			<lb />
			the above decisions mentioned in the reference order dated
			<lb />
			28.12.2019:
			<lb />
			4(a).
			<lb />
			Bar Chand&apos;s case:
			<lb />
			The Division Bench held that the circular dated
			<lb />
			22.02.2010 did not differentiate between daily waged and
			<lb />
			regular ClassIV service. Those daily wagers, who were
			<lb />
			engaged prior to 10.05.2001, were held entitled to serve till
			<lb />
			the age of 60 years and those daily wagers, who were
			<lb />
			engaged after 10.05.2001, were held entitled to work till the
			<lb />
			age of 58 years. The writ petitioner (therein) engaged prior
			<lb />
			to 10.05.2001 and regularized after 10.05.2001 was held
			<lb />
			entitled to serve till the age of 60 years.
			<lb />
			4(b).
			<lb />
			Chuni Lal&apos;s case:
			<lb />
			The judgment in Bar Chand&apos;s case, supra, was
			<lb />
			held per incurium since it did not consider the rule
			<lb />
			position. It was held that in accordance with the
			<lb />
			amendment carried out by the respondentsState on
			<lb />
			10.05.2001 in F.R. 56, only those ClassIV employees, who
			<lb />
			were regularly appointed/regularized in service prior to
			<lb />
			10.05.2001, could continue to serve till the age of 60 years.
			<lb />
			While allowing State&apos;s appeal, it was held that the writ
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			18
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			petitioner though was engaged on daily wage basis prior to
			<lb />
			10.05.2001, but was regularized after this date, could only
			<lb />
			continue to serve upto the age of 58 years.
			<lb />
			4(c).
			<lb />
			Tara Chand/Gian Singh&apos;s case:
			<lb />
			The judgment in Tara Chand&apos;s case followed the
			<lb />
			decision in Bar Chand&apos;s case and did not take into
			<lb />
			consideration the judgment rendered in Chuni Lal&apos;s case.
			<lb />
			However, even if the judgment in Chuni Lal&apos;s case had been
			<lb />
			considered in Tara Chand&apos;s case, then also the outcome
			<lb />
			would not have been different since in Tara Chand&apos;s case,
			<lb />
			the petitioner was engaged and regularized prior to
			<lb />
			10.05.2001. Similar was the position in Gian Singh&apos;s case,
			<lb />
			wherein the petitioner was held entitled to be regularized
			<lb />
			w.e.f. 01.01.2000, i.e. prior to 10.05.2001. The judgment
			<lb />
			passed by ld. Single judge in Gian Singh&apos;s case was upheld
			<lb />
			by the Ld. Division Bench in LPA no. 194/2015. While
			<lb />
			affirming the judgment, ld. Division Bench held that the
			<lb />
			writ petitioner was entitled to be regularised prior to
			<lb />
			10.5.2001 therefore fetters of age restriction placed under
			<lb />
			2001 amendment were not applicable to him.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			Notifications/Clarification with respect to
			<lb />
			F.R. 56(e) and their effect:
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			19
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			5(i).
			<lb />
			Vide notification dated 30.07.1998, State of
			<lb />
			Himachal Pradesh amended F.R. 56(e) as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;(e)
			<lb />
			A Government servant in Class IV service or post
			<lb />
			shall retire from service on the afternoon of the last day
			<lb />
			of the month in which he attains the age of sixty years:
			<lb />
			Provided that a Class IV employee of the
			<lb />
			Secretariat security force who initially enters service on
			<lb />
			or after 15 th day of September, 1969 shall retire from
			<lb />
			service on the afternoon of the last day of the month in
			<lb />
			which he attains the age of fiftyeight years.&quot;
			<lb />
			As per F.R. 56(e) as amended by the State on
			<lb />
			30.07.1998, a government servant in ClassIV &apos;service or
			<lb />
			post&apos; was to retire from service on attaining the age of 60
			<lb />
			years. The word used in F.R. 56(e) was &apos;service or post&apos;.
			<lb />
			5(ii).
			<lb />
			On 10.05.2001, further amendment was carried
			<lb />
			out in F.R. 56(e) by adding second proviso as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;Provided further that a ClassIV Government servant
			<lb />
			appointed on or after the date of publication of this
			<lb />
			notification in Rajpatra Himachal Pradesh shall retire
			<lb />
			from service on the afternoon of the last day of the
			<lb />
			month in which he attains the age of 58 years.&quot;
			<lb />
			The 2001 amendment came into force from the
			<lb />
			date of publication in the Gazette, i.e. on 11.05.2001. The
			<lb />
			amendment was to the effect that all those ClassIV
			<lb />
			government servants appointed on or after 10.05.2001
			<lb />
			could continue to serve only upto 58 years of age. The
			<lb />
			amendment used the word &apos;appointed&apos; and not &apos;engaged&apos;.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			20
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			The amendment though leads to a definite conclusion that
			<lb />
			those who were appointed/engaged on daily wage basis in
			<lb />
			ClassIV services and regularized prior to 10.05.2001 could
			<lb />
			continue to serve upto the age of 60 years, however, the
			<lb />
			position was not clear in the amendment qua those
			<lb />
			employees, who were engaged on daily wage basis in Class
			<lb />
			IV services prior to 10.05.2001 and were continuing as
			<lb />
			such on 10.05.2001 and regularized after 10.05.2001.
			<lb />
			5(iii).
			<lb />
			In order to clarify the situation, the Government
			<lb />
			issued a circular on 22.02.2010 (extracted earlier). In terms of
			<lb />
			this circular, the amendment notification dated 10.05.2001
			<lb />
			was made applicable to the ClassIV daily wagers as well.
			<lb />
			Those daily wagers, who were engaged prior to 10.05.2001,
			<lb />
			were to continue till the age of 60 years. However, such of
			<lb />
			the daily wagers, who were engaged after 10.05.2001, could
			<lb />
			serve till the age of 58 years.
			<lb />
			5(iv).
			<lb />
			A
			<lb />
			vacuum
			<lb />
			still
			<lb />
			remained
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			notification/clarification about the superannuation age of
			<lb />
			daily wager engaged prior to 10.05.2001, but regularized
			<lb />
			after 10.05.2001. To meet this situation, another
			<lb />
			notification was issued on 21.02.2018, amending F.R. 56(e)
			<lb />
			yet again. This notification has not been noticed in the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			21
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			reference order dated 28.12.2019. Relevant portion of the
			<lb />
			notification reads as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;Short title
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			commencement:
			<lb />
			(1) These rules may be called
			<lb />
			Fundamental (in their application to the
			<lb />
			State of Himachal Pradesh) First
			<lb />
			Amendment, Rules, 2018.
			<lb />
			(2) These rules shall come into force from
			<lb />
			the date of publication in the Rajpatra (e
			<lb />
			Gazette), Himachal Pradesh.
			<lb />
			Amendment of
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			rule56.
			<lb />
			In rule56 of the Fundamental Rules,
			<lb />
			after the second proviso to clause (e), the
			<lb />
			following third proviso shall be inserted,
			<lb />
			namely:
			<lb />
			&quot;Provided further that a ClassIV
			<lb />
			Government servant appointed on part
			<lb />
			time/daily wages basis prior to 1005
			<lb />
			2001 and regularized on or after 1005
			<lb />
			2001 shall retire from service on the
			<lb />
			afternoon of the last day of the month in
			<lb />
			which he attains the age of 60 years.&quot;
			<lb />
			The above amendment inserting third proviso in
			<lb />
			F.R. 56(e) came into force from the date of publication in
			<lb />
			the Gazette, i.e. on 22.02.2018. The gist of the amendment
			<lb />
			was that with effect from 21.02.2018, ClassIV government
			<lb />
			servants appointed on parttime/daily wage basis prior to
			<lb />
			10.05.2001 and regularized on or after 10.05.2001, were to
			<lb />
			retire on attaining the age of 60 years. It was the date of
			<lb />
			first appointment/engagement, which was made the basis
			<lb />
			for their continuation in service till the age of 60 years and
			<lb />
			not the date of regularization. A corrigendum has also been
			<lb />
			issued by the State on 10.06.2019 to the effect that for the
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			22
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			word &apos;appointed&apos; used in the notification dated 21.02.2018,
			<lb />
			the word &apos;engaged&apos; shall be substituted.
			<lb />
			F.R. 56(e) as it stood on 22.02.2018 (with
			<lb />
			corrigendum) now reads as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;(e)
			<lb />
			A Government servant in Class IV service or post
			<lb />
			shall retire from service on the afternoon of the last day
			<lb />
			of the month in which he attains the age of sixty years:
			<lb />
			Provided that a Class IV employee of the
			<lb />
			Secretariat Security Force who initially enters service on
			<lb />
			or after the 15 th day of September, 1969, shall retire
			<lb />
			from service on the afternoon of the last day of the
			<lb />
			month in which he attains the age of fiftyeight years.
			<lb />
			Provided further that a ClassIV Government
			<lb />
			servant appointed on or after 10.05.2001 shall retire
			<lb />
			from service on the afternoon of the last day of the
			<lb />
			month in which he attains the age of 58 years.(2001
			<lb />
			amendment)
			<lb />
			Provided further that with effect from 21.02.2018
			<lb />
			a ClassIV Government servant engaged on part
			<lb />
			time/daily wages basis prior to 10052001 and
			<lb />
			regularized on or after 10052001 shall retire from
			<lb />
			service on the afternoon of the last day of the month in
			<lb />
			which he attains the age of 60 years.(2018 amendment)&quot;
			<lb />
			Answering the Reference:
			<lb />
			6(i). Conflict in the Judgments; There appears to be a
			<lb />
			very thin difference in the line of approach taken in the
			<lb />
			judgments referred to in the reference order dated
			<lb />
			28.12.2019. The view taken in Bar Chand&apos;s case was held
			<lb />
			to be per incurium in the judgment delivered in Chuni Lal&apos;s
			<lb />
			case. A different approach was adopted by the Division
			<lb />
			Bench in Chuni Lal&apos;s case, which held that both
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			23
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			engagement and regularization of a ClassIV employee had
			<lb />
			to be prior to 10.05.2001 to enable him to continue to serve
			<lb />
			till the age of 60 years, whereas, in Bar Chand&apos;s case,
			<lb />
			relying on the circular dated 22.02.2010, supra, it was held
			<lb />
			that if engagement on daily wage basis was prior to
			<lb />
			10.05.2001, then, such an employee could continue to
			<lb />
			serve till he attained the age of 60 years, irrespective of date
			<lb />
			of his regularization. The judgment in Chuni Lal&apos;s case was,
			<lb />
			however, not brought to the notice of the learned Single
			<lb />
			Judge in Tara Chand&apos;s case. In Tara Chand&apos;s case, learned
			<lb />
			Single Judge followed the judgment in Bar Chand&apos;s case.
			<lb />
			Similarly, in Gian Singh&apos;s case, learned Single Judge
			<lb />
			followed the judgment delivered in Tara Chand&apos;s case. The
			<lb />
			judgment in Chuni Lal&apos;s case was not noticed by the
			<lb />
			learned Single Judges either in Tara Chand&apos;s case or in
			<lb />
			Gian Singh&apos;s case.
			<lb />
			6(ii).
			<lb />
			Age of Continuance in Service:
			<lb />
			6(ii)(a).
			<lb />
			In terms of 2001 amendment of F.R. 56(e), such
			<lb />
			of the ClassIV employees, who were engaged on daily wage
			<lb />
			basis prior to 10.05.2001 and regularized also prior to
			<lb />
			10.05.2001, are entitled to continue to serve till the age of
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			24
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			60 years. This position is acknowledged in the judgments
			<lb />
			rendered in Bar Chand as well as Chuni Lal&apos;s cases, supra.
			<lb />
			6(ii)(b).
			<lb />
			Such of the ClassIV employees, who were
			<lb />
			engaged on daily wage basis prior to 10.05.2001 and
			<lb />
			regularized after 10.05.2001 were not given the benefit of
			<lb />
			continuation till the age of 60 years in Chuni Lal&apos;s case. The
			<lb />
			judgment in Chuni Lal&apos;s case was based upon the
			<lb />
			interpretation of F.R. 56(e), as amended by the
			<lb />
			respondentsState vide notification dated 10.05.2001.
			<lb />
			6(ii)(c).
			<lb />
			In terms of the State notification dated
			<lb />
			21.02.2018 carrying out further amendment in F.R. 56(e),
			<lb />
			with effect from 21.02.2018, all daily wagers appointed
			<lb />
			prior to 10.05.2001 and regularized on or after 10.05.2001
			<lb />
			are to continue to serve till the age of 60 years. This
			<lb />
			amendment is post the decisions rendered in Bar Chand
			<lb />
			and Chuni Lal&apos;s cases, supra and has not been noticed in
			<lb />
			the reference order dated 28.12.2019. While affirming the
			<lb />
			judgment of ld. Single Judge in Gian Singh&apos;s case, ld.
			<lb />
			Division Bench though did not notice Chuni Lal&apos;s judgment
			<lb />
			but held that writ petitioner&apos;s date of regularisation was
			<lb />
			prior to 10.5.2001 therefore reduced age of 58 years
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			25
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			introduced in 2001 amendment would not be applicable to
			<lb />
			him.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			There is now no confusion regarding employees
			<lb />
			falling in para 6(ii)(a) above. These employees can continue
			<lb />
			to serve till they attain the age of 60 years. However, an
			<lb />
			anomalous situation has developed amongst the employees
			<lb />
			falling in para 6(ii)(b) &amp; 6(ii)(c). The employees falling in
			<lb />
			above para 6(ii)(b) and 6(ii)(c) for all practical purposes
			<lb />
			belong to the same category and are similarly situated.
			<lb />
			Both sets of employees were engaged on daily wage basis
			<lb />
			prior to 10.05.2001 and regularized after 10.05.2001. Such
			<lb />
			of the employees engaged on daily wage basis prior to
			<lb />
			10.05.2001 and regularized after 10.05.2001, if were in
			<lb />
			service on 21.02.2018, will continue to serve till they attain
			<lb />
			the age of 60 years. On the other hand, such of the
			<lb />
			employees, who were engaged on daily wage basis prior to
			<lb />
			10.05.2001 and regularized after 10.05.2001, but have
			<lb />
			retired before the issuance of notification dated 21.02.2018,
			<lb />
			will not get the benefit of notification dated 21.02.2018.
			<lb />
			This to our mind is wholly discriminatory. Similarly
			<lb />
			situated employees are being treated differently. The
			<lb />
			employees, who were engaged on daily wage basis prior to
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			26
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			10.05.2001 and regularized after 10.05.2001, constitute
			<lb />
			one homogenous class. Differential treatment to the
			<lb />
			employees falling in same homogenous class is
			<lb />
			impermissible. In fact, amendment carried out in F.R. 56(e)
			<lb />
			on 21.02.2018 suggests that the date of regularization will
			<lb />
			have no impact upon the superannuation age. Date of
			<lb />
			engagement is the determinative factor. If a daily wager is
			<lb />
			engaged prior to 10.05.2021, then he is entitled to serve till
			<lb />
			60 years of age irrespective of date of his regularization.
			<lb />
			This was held so in Bar Chand&apos;s case, decided on
			<lb />
			21.10.2010. However, at the time of decision in Bar
			<lb />
			Chand&apos;s case, the amendment dated 21.02.2018 had not
			<lb />
			been carried out in F.R. 56(e). Therefore, though later
			<lb />
			judgment in Chuni Lal&apos;s case dated 22.11.2011, holding the
			<lb />
			decision in Bar Chand&apos;s case as per incuriam cannot be
			<lb />
			faulted as it was based upon strict interpretation of F.R.
			<lb />
			56(e) as amended by the State at that time. However, in
			<lb />
			view of subsequent amendment of F.R. 56(e) on 21.02.2018
			<lb />
			in the interregnum, situation has undergone further
			<lb />
			change. Reference made to the larger Bench is not only to
			<lb />
			decide about the inconsistency in the decisions referred
			<lb />
			therein, but also to put at rest related issues coming or
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			27
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			likely to arise before different benches. Therefore, we hold
			<lb />
			that:
			<lb />
			(i).
			<lb />
			There is an apparent inconsistency or conflict
			<lb />
			between the decisions referred to in the reference order
			<lb />
			dated 28.12.2019, which lies in a very narrow compass, as
			<lb />
			noticed in para 6(i) above. In Chuni Lal&apos;s case, the decision
			<lb />
			rendered in Bar Chand&apos;s case was held to be per incuriam.
			<lb />
			The decision in Chuni Lal&apos;s case was based upon
			<lb />
			interpretation of F.R. 56(e) as it existed in the State at that
			<lb />
			time. But the judgment delivered in Tara Chand&apos;s case did
			<lb />
			not notice the decision in Chuni Lal&apos;s case. The judgment in
			<lb />
			Gian Singh&apos;s case in respect of continuation in service was
			<lb />
			based upon the verdict in Tara Chand&apos;s case. In both these
			<lb />
			judgments, learned Single Judges did not notice the
			<lb />
			judgment delivered in Chuni Lal&apos;s case. In Letters patent
			<lb />
			appeal, the Division Bench while affirming the judgment
			<lb />
			passed by the ld. Single Judge in Gian Singh&apos;s case though
			<lb />
			did not notice the judgment rendered in Chuni Lal&apos;s case
			<lb />
			however the amendment dated 10.5.2001 reducing the
			<lb />
			superannuation age from 60 to 58 years was held to be not
			<lb />
			applicable to the writ petitioner, who was held entitled for
			<lb />
			regularisation prior to 10.5.2001.
			<lb />
		</body>

		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>


		<page>
			28
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			(ii).
			<lb />
			Inconsistency between Bar Chand and Chuni
			<lb />
			Lal now stands, not just resolved, but rather dissolved, in
			<lb />
			view of notification dated 21.02.2018 amending F.R. 56(e),
			<lb />
			issued by the State, which has now reinforced and
			<lb />
			reiterated what was held in Bar Chand&apos;s case, i.e. date of
			<lb />
			regularization of a class IV daily wager whether prior or
			<lb />
			after 10.05.2001, will make no difference to the age of his
			<lb />
			continuing in service. It is the date of engagement, which is
			<lb />
			the decisive factor. If date of engagement/appointment is
			<lb />
			prior to 10.05.2001, the ClassIV employee will continue to
			<lb />
			serve till 60 years of age. In case, it is later than
			<lb />
			10.05.2001, then restriction in age upto 58 years will apply.
			<lb />
			(iii).
			<lb />
			There cannot be any discrimination amongst
			<lb />
			similarly situated ClassIV employees belonging to one
			<lb />
			homogenous class. Therefore the retirement date, of such of
			<lb />
			those employees, who had been engaged on daily wage
			<lb />
			basis prior to 10.05.2001, but regularized after 10.05.2001
			<lb />
			and have actually been retired prior to the issuance of
			<lb />
			notification dated 21.02.2018 at the age of 58 years, shall
			<lb />
			be deemed to be the date when they otherwise attained the
			<lb />
			age of 60 years. Since these employees have not actually
			<lb />
			worked beyond the age of 58 years, therefore, they will not
			<lb />
			
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>

		<page>
			29
			<lb />
		</page>

		<body>
			be entitled to the actual monetary benefits of wages/salary
			<lb />
			etc. for the period of service from the date of their actual
			<lb />
			retirement till deemed dates of their retirement. However,
			<lb />
			they will be entitled to notional fixation of their pay for the
			<lb />
			period in question for working out their payable pension
			<lb />
			and payment of consequential arrears of pension
			<lb />
			accordingly.
			<lb />
			Reference is accordingly answered. The writ
			<lb />
			petitions be now placed appropriately before the respective
			<lb />
			Benches.
			<lb />
			(Mohammad Rafiq)
			<lb />
			Chief Justice
			<lb />
			(Ajay Mohan Goel)
			<lb />
			Judge
			<lb />
			(Jyotsna Rewal Dua)
			<lb />
			February 22, 2022
			<lb />
			Judge
			<lb />
			( Mukesh/rajni )
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			::: Downloaded on -20/03/2022 13:01:08 :::CIS
		</note>


	</text>
</tei>