<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			CORAM : SWATANTER KUMAR, C.J.,
			<lb />
			P.V. HARDAS &amp; N.D. DESHPANDE, JJ
			<lb />
			JUDGMENT RESERVED ON
			<lb />
			: 26TH AUGUST 2008
			<lb />
			JUDGMENT PRONOUNCED ON : 25TH SEPTEMBER 2008
			<lb />
			JUDGMENT (Per Swatanter Kumar, C.J.)
			<lb />
			RELEVANT FACTS:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			Mohd. Riyazur Rehman Siddiqui met with an accident on 30 th
			<lb />
			September 1986 on Bidar-Udgir road while he was driving a motor-cycle
			<lb />
			No. MZV-6233. According to him, while he was driving the vehicle at a
			<lb />
			very moderate speed, the driver of jeep bearing No. MZV-6437 who was
			<lb />
			driving the vehicle rashly and negligently gave a dash to the motor-cycle and
			<lb />
			resultantly he sustained injuries. A case under Sections 279, 337 and 338 of
			<lb />
			the Indian Penal Code was registered with the Police Station, Udgir. The
			<lb />
			Appellant resultantly of the accident sustained permanent disability to the
			<lb />
			extent of 48%. He filed a Petition under Section 166 of the Motor Vehicles
			<lb />
			Act, 1988 being Case No. 26 of 1987 before the Motor Accident Claims
			<lb />
			Tribunal, Latur, which was contested and decided finally by the Tribunal
			<lb />
			vide its judgment and award dated 5 th May 1989 awarding compensation of
			<lb />
			Rs.51,000/-only with interest at the rate of 10% per annum from the date of
			<lb />
			the claim petition. This judgment of the Tribunal was impugned by the
			<lb />
			Claimant by filing First Appeal No.638 of 1989 before this Court praying for
			<lb />
			enhancement of the compensation awarded. The owner-driver of the jeep
			<lb />
			died on 16 th July, 1987 during the pendency of the Claim Petition before the
			<lb />
			Tribunal. The Insurance Company had denied its liability and the present
			<lb />
			Appeal was only preferred against the Respondent No.1-owner of the
			<lb />
			vehicle. The Deputy Director of Health Services-original Respondent No.1,
			<lb />
			being owner of the jeep also preferred Appeal being First Appeal No. 637 of
			<lb />
			1989 impugning the judgment of the Tribunal. First Appeal No.637 of 1989
			<lb />
			was dismissed by a learned Single Judge of this Court vide common
			<lb />
			judgment dated 12 th February 2004. The Appeal filed by the Claimant (First
			<lb />
			Appeal No.638 of 1989) was partly allowed and the compensation was
			<lb />
			enhanced to Rs.56,000/-with interest at the rate of 9% per annum.
			<lb />
			Dissatisfied from the judgment of the learned Single Judge, the Claimant
			<lb />
			filed Letters Patent Appeal No. 35 of 2005 praying for further enhancement.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			Civil Application No. 1407 of 2006 has been filed in Letters
			<lb />
			Patent Appeal (Stamp) No. 20447 of 2006 for condonation of delay of 212
			<lb />
			days caused in filing Letters Patent Appeal against judgment of the learned
			<lb />
			Single Judge in First Appeal No. 129 of 1998.
			<lb />
			There was no serious objection on behalf of the learned Counsel
			<lb />
			appearing for the Respondents for condonation of delay in filing the
			<lb />
			present Appeal. We have perused the Application. Since sufficient
			<lb />
			cause for condonation of delay is shown, the Civil Application is
			<lb />
			allowed. The delay of 212 days in filing the present appeal is
			<lb />
			condoned. The Civil Application is accordingly disposed of. Registry
			<lb />
			to register and number the Letters Patent Appeal accordingly.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			First Appeal No. 129 of 1998 was filed challenging judgment
			<lb />
			and award of the Motor Accident Claims Tribunal, Jalna. The Claimants
			<lb />
			therein are the dependents of deceased Kalyan Takale, aged 28 years, who
			<lb />
			died on 16 th April 1995 due to injuries sustained in an accident arising out of
			<lb />
			use of motor vehicle which occurred on 15 th April 1995. The accident
			<lb />
			occurred when motor-cycle No.MH-21 driven by the deceased was dashed
			<lb />
			by Taxi No. MH-20-A-7090 driven by Respondent No.1 in a rash or
			<lb />
			negligent manner. The taxi was owned by Respondent No.2 and was
			<lb />
			insured with Respondent No.3. The Motor Accident Claims Tribunal, Jalna
			<lb />
			by Judgment and Award dated 4 th April 1997 directed Respondent Nos.1 to
			<lb />
			3 to pay amount of Rs.1,50,000/-(inclusive of no fault liability) to
			<lb />
			Claimants with interest at the rate of 12% per annum. The Judgment/Award
			<lb />
			of the Tribunal was challenged in First Appeal No. 129 of 1998 in which the
			<lb />
			learned Single Judge by Judgment and Award dated 25 th January 2005
			<lb />
			modified the Award by substituting figure of Rs.2,00,000/-(Two lakhs) in
			<lb />
			place of Rs.1,00,000/-(One lakh). This Judgment/Award of the learned
			<lb />
			Single Judge is challenged by filing Letters Patent Appeal (Stamp) No.
			<lb />
			20447 of 2005 by Claimants seeking further enhancement in the amount of
			<lb />
			compensation.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			ORDER OF REFERENCE:
			<lb />
		</head>

		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			When the matter came up for hearing before a Division Bench
			<lb />
			of this Court on 22 nd February 2008, the learned Counsel appearing for the
			<lb />
			respective parties relied upon different judgments of this Court as well as of
			<lb />
			the Supreme Court to argue for and against the very maintainability of the
			<lb />
			Letters Patent Appeal in view of the provisions of Sections 100A of the
			<lb />
			Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, Section 173 of the Motor Vehicles Act, 1988
			<lb />
			(hereinafter referred to as the &quot;M.V. Act&quot;) Clause 15 of the Letters Patent.
			<lb />
			The Division Bench of this Court noticed the view expressed by another
			<lb />
			Division Bench of this Court in the case of Asha d/o Bhalchandra Joshi vs
			<lb />
			National Insurance Co. Ltd., 2008 (1) Mh.L.J. 724, and the view of the
			<lb />
			other Benches and noticing the difference of opinion expressed in different
			<lb />
			judgments, directed the matter to be referred to a larger Bench for settling
			<lb />
			the legal issue involved in the present case with regard to the maintainability
			<lb />
			of the Letters Patent Appeal.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			It will be useful to refer to the Order of Reference dated 22 nd
			<lb />
			February 2008 which reads as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;1.
			<lb />
			The learned counsel, appearing for the
			<lb />
			appellant, stated that Full Bench Judgment of this High
			<lb />
			Court in the case of &quot;Laxminarayan vs. Shivlal Gujar,
			<lb />
			2003 (1) MPLJ (FB) 10 = AIR 2003 MP 49 (FB)&quot; was
			<lb />
			considered by a Division Bench of this Court in the case of
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;Asha d/o Bhalchandra Joshi vs. National Insurance
			<lb />
			Company Ltd., 2008 (1) Mh. L.J. 724&quot; and in paragraph
			<lb />
			No. 28 of the said judgment, while declining to adjudicate
			<lb />
			upon the effect of Section 100-A of the Code of Civil
			<lb />
			Procedure on maintainability of the letters patent appeal,
			<lb />
			arising from the award of the Tribunal, it was held that the
			<lb />
			appeal is maintainable.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			2.
			<lb />
			On the other hand, learned counsel, appearing
			<lb />
			for the respondent, contended that besides the fact that the
			<lb />
			Full Bench&apos;s conclusions or dictums could not have been
			<lb />
			varied or dilated by the Division Bench and also the fact that
			<lb />
			the Supreme Court in the case of &quot;Kamal Kumar Dutta &amp;
			<lb />
			another vs. Ruby General Hospital Ltd., &amp; others, 2008
			<lb />
			AIR SCW 4594&quot;, has held that such an appeal is not
			<lb />
			maintainable, the Supreme Court had overruled the view of
			<lb />
			the Bombay High Court taken in AIR 2004 Bombay 38.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			3.
			<lb />
			In view of above mentioned circumstances, we
			<lb />
			feel it appropriate and the principles of judicial propriety
			<lb />
			demand that this matter is placed before the Full Bench.
			<lb />
			Accordingly, this matter be placed before the Full Bench.
			<lb />
			The Registry shall communicate the date fixed for hearing
			<lb />
			of the matter before the Full Bench to the parties.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			QUESTIONS OF LAW FORMULATED:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			In order to appropriately deal with the different questions
			<lb />
			which require consideration of the Court, it will be desirable to
			<lb />
			formulate the questions which are likely to arise repeatedly before the
			<lb />
			Court and even otherwise are questions of law of some significance as
			<lb />
			under :-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			(a)
			<lb />
			Whether, upon amendment to Section 100A of
			<lb />
			the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 ( with effect
			<lb />
			from 1 st July, 2002 ), the Letters Patent Appeal
			<lb />
			against the judgment rendered by the learned
			<lb />
			Single Judge of
			<lb />
			High
			<lb />
			Court would be
			<lb />
			maintainable ?
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			(b)
			<lb />
			Whether an appeal arising out of special statute
			<lb />
			like Motor Vehicles Act, 1988 ( even if
			<lb />
			assuming that it is a special statute ) would be
			<lb />
			maintainable under Clause 15 of the Letter
			<lb />
			Patent against the judgment passed by the
			<lb />
			learned Single Judge of this Court in exercise of
			<lb />
			its appellate jurisdiction ?
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			RELEVANT PROVISIONS OF LAW AND THEIR IMPACT ON THE
			<lb />
			LEGAL ISSUES FORMULATED.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			The language of Section 4 of the Code of Civil Procedure is
			<lb />
			specific but still of wide connotation and impact. It contemplates that
			<lb />
			in absence of any specific provision to the contrary nothing in the Code
			<lb />
			shall be deemed to limit or otherwise affect any special or local law,
			<lb />
			special judicial jurisdiction or power conferred or any special form of
			<lb />
			procedure prescribed under any other law. This Section, upon its
			<lb />
			plain construction, indicates the purpose for incorporating such a
			<lb />
			provision. The Code of Civil procedure being a Code to control and
			<lb />
			regulate the proceedings before the Courts under various remedies and
			<lb />
			enforcing law makes a clear exception in regard to operation and
			<lb />
			effect of a specific provision contained in any other law unless some
			<lb />
			provision of Code specifically excludes an application of that other
			<lb />
			provision. General Rule is that wherever a special provision renders
			<lb />
			the general provision incapable to apply to a remedy, then the
			<lb />
			provisions of the Code will not limit or affect such special provision.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			An appeal to be filed under a decree or order passed by
			<lb />
			the Court of competent jurisdiction in exercise of its original or
			<lb />
			appellate jurisdiction is again controlled by the specific provision of
			<lb />
			the Code. Under Section 96 of the Code, an appeal shall lie from
			<lb />
			every decree passed by any Court exercising original jurisdiction to the
			<lb />
			Court authorized to hear appeals from the decision of such Court.
			<lb />
			An appeal from the appellate decree is permissible under the provision
			<lb />
			of Section 100 of the Code of Civil Procedure, where it is stated that
			<lb />
			an appeal shall lie to the High Court from every decree passed in
			<lb />
			appeal by any Court subordinate to the High Court, if the High Court
			<lb />
			is satisfied that the case involves substantial questions of law.
			<lb />
			In
			<lb />
			terms of Section 101 of the Code, no appeal is provided from an
			<lb />
			appellate decree which is passed by the High Court itself. Under
			<lb />
			Section 102 of the Code which was also amended by the Code of Civil
			<lb />
			Procedure Amendment Act, 2002 with effect from 1 st July, 2002, no
			<lb />
			second appeal would be maintainable from any decree when the
			<lb />
			subject matter of the original suit is for recovery of money not
			<lb />
			exceeding Rs.25,000/-. By this very amendment Act, Section 100A
			<lb />
			was amended which opens with non obstante clause and which takes
			<lb />
			within its sweep even the provisions of Letters patent of any High
			<lb />
			Court. Not only that it even renders any instrument having the force
			<lb />
			of law or any other law for the time being in force ineffective. Thus,
			<lb />
			the provision of Section 100A is an exception to the appeals provided
			<lb />
			under other statutes and it in no uncertain terms mandates that where
			<lb />
			any appeal from the original or appellate decree or order is heard and
			<lb />
			decided by the learned Single Judge of the High Court, no further
			<lb />
			appeal shall lie from such judgment and decree.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			Section 104 in no uncertain terms provides that an appeal
			<lb />
			shall lie from the orders stated in that Section and save as otherwise
			<lb />
			provided in the body of this Code or by any law for the time being in
			<lb />
			force and from no other orders. This process of first and second
			<lb />
			appeals specified under the Code is further regulated and controlled by
			<lb />
			the provisions of Orders XLI, XLII and XLIII, respectively, of the Code
			<lb />
			of Civil Procedure. They provide as to how and in what manner
			<lb />
			appeal from an appellate decree or order is maintainable and would be
			<lb />
			decided and also the procedure to be adopted by the Court while
			<lb />
			deciding such appeals including the power of the Court under those
			<lb />
			provisions.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			10.
			<lb />
			It will be appropriate to examine the legislative
			<lb />
			amendment to the Code of Civil Procedure. The Code of Civil
			<lb />
			Procedure, 1882 was replaced by Code of 1908. However, Section
			<lb />
			100A was introduced for the first time by amending Act 104 of 1976.
			<lb />
			The intent was to bar third appeal before a Division Bench of the High
			<lb />
			Court from a judgment of the Single Judge deciding a matter in a
			<lb />
			Second Appeal. By the amending Act of 1999, the earlier Section
			<lb />
			100A was substituted. Section 100A as introduced by amending Act
			<lb />
			46 of 1999, though attained the assent of the President on 30 th
			<lb />
			December 1999, it was not enforced because of various factors. Clause
			<lb />
			(b) of Section 100A was subsequently deleted finally and as already
			<lb />
			noticed, by the amending Act of 2002, present Section 100A was
			<lb />
			introduced. Present Section 100A reads as under :-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;Section 100A. Notwithstanding anything contained in
			<lb />
			any Letters Patent for any High Court or in any other
			<lb />
			instrument having the force of law or in any other law
			<lb />
			for the time being in force, where any appeal from an
			<lb />
			original or appellate decree or order is heard and
			<lb />
			decided by a single judge of a High Court, no further
			<lb />
			appeal shall lie from the judgment and decree of such
			<lb />
			single judge.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			11.
			<lb />
			The design behind frequent amendments of these
			<lb />
			provisions is obvious. Legislative attempt has been to reduce the
			<lb />
			number of Appeals which a litigant could prefer against an original or
			<lb />
			appellate decree. Where the Single Judge hears an appeal from an
			<lb />
			appellate decree or order, the question of there being a further appeal
			<lb />
			would not arise as it is not so contemplated. Where the regular First
			<lb />
			Appeal is heard by a Division Bench, the question of there being an
			<lb />
			intra Court appeal does not arise. It is only in cases where the value is
			<lb />
			not substantial that the Rules of the High Court may provide for the
			<lb />
			regular First Appeal to be heard by a learned Single Judge and in such
			<lb />
			a case to give further right of appeal may not be convenient as it may
			<lb />
			amount to over-loading the judicial work.
			<lb />
			Since the Appeal is
			<lb />
			creation of the statute, no prejudice would be caused to the litigant by
			<lb />
			not providing intra Court appeal even where the value involved is
			<lb />
			large. Newly incorporated Section 100A in clear and specific terms
			<lb />
			prohibits further appeal against the judgment and decree or an order
			<lb />
			of a learned Single Judge to a Division Bench.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			12.
			<lb />
			It is thus obvious that the provisions of Section 100A
			<lb />
			curtailed the right of intra-Court appeal available to a litigant where
			<lb />
			the Single Judge of the High Court was deciding a matter in exercise
			<lb />
			of its appellate jurisdiction. The object and reasons for introduction of
			<lb />
			Section 100A is another aspect which can be examined by the Court.
			<lb />
			The Malimath Committee had examined the issue of further appeal
			<lb />
			and recommended suitable amendments to then existing Section 100A
			<lb />
			so as to bar further Appeal.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			13.
			<lb />
			In the case of Salem Advocate Bar Association, Tamil Naidu
			<lb />
			vs Union of India, AIR 2003 SC 189, the Supreme Court while
			<lb />
			examining the constitutional validity of the amending Act held that the
			<lb />
			provisions of Section 100A were not unreasonable and did not place
			<lb />
			any unjustifiable restriction by removing the right to file intra-court
			<lb />
			appeal and held as under :-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;15. Section 100-A deals with two types of cases
			<lb />
			which are decided by a single Judge. One is where the
			<lb />
			single Judge hears an appeal from an appellate decree
			<lb />
			or order. The question of there being any further
			<lb />
			appeal in such a case cannot and should not be
			<lb />
			contemplated. Where, however, an appeal is filed
			<lb />
			before the High Court against the decree of a trial
			<lb />
			Court, a question may arise whether any further appeal
			<lb />
			should be permitted or not. Even at present depending
			<lb />
			upon the value of the case, the appeal from the original
			<lb />
			decree is either heard by a single Judge or by a Division
			<lb />
			Bench of the High Court. Where the regular first
			<lb />
			appeal so filed is heard by a Division Bench, the
			<lb />
			question of there being an intra-Court appeal does not
			<lb />
			arise. It is only in cases where the value is not
			<lb />
			substantial that the rules of the High Court may
			<lb />
			provide for the regular first appeal to be heard by a
			<lb />
			single Judge. In such a case to give a further right of
			<lb />
			appeal where the amount involved is nominal to a
			<lb />
			Division Bench will really be increasing the workload
			<lb />
			unnecessarily. We do not find that any prejudice
			<lb />
			would be caused to the litigants by not providing for
			<lb />
			intra-Court appeal, even where the value involved is
			<lb />
			large. In such a case, the High Court by Rules, can
			<lb />
			provide that the Division Bench will hear the regular
			<lb />
			first appeal. No fault can, thus, be found with the
			<lb />
			amended provision Section 100-A.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			14.
			<lb />
			Of course, the application of Section 100A is stated to be
			<lb />
			prospective and would not affect the right and remedies of an
			<lb />
			Appellant who had filed the Appeal prior to 1 st July 2002. In other
			<lb />
			words, accrued right of appeal vested in a suitor was not affected.
			<lb />
			This view was also taken by a Full Bench of the Punjab &amp; Haryana
			<lb />
			High Court in the case of Parashottam Dass vs State of Haryana, AIR
			<lb />
			2003 P&amp;H 301. The Full Bench of this Court in the case of Rahul
			<lb />
			Sharad vs Ratnakar, 2004 (3) Mh. L.J. 706, took the same view which
			<lb />
			is approved by the Apex Court in Bento De Souza Egipsy vs Yvette
			<lb />
			Alvares Colaco, (2004) 13 SCC 438. The Supreme Court in a more
			<lb />
			recent case of Kamla Devi vs Kushal Kanwar and another, (2006) 13
			<lb />
			SCC 295 referring to Bento De Souza (supra) and Sanjay Z Rane vs
			<lb />
			Saibai S Dubaxi, (2004) 13 SCC 439 wherein it is opined that Section
			<lb />
			100A of the Code has no retrospective effect observed that the Letters
			<lb />
			Patent Appeal filed prior to coming into force of the 2002 Act would
			<lb />
			be maintainable.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			15.
			<lb />
			The right of Appeal is a substantive right. The vested right
			<lb />
			of appeal can be taken away only by a subsequent enactment if so
			<lb />
			provided expressly or by necessary intendment and not otherwise.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			16.
			<lb />
			The Supreme Court in the case of Garikapati Veeraya vs N
			<lb />
			Subbiah Choudhry, AIR 1957 SC 540, spelt out the five propositions as
			<lb />
			precepts to right of appeal. The formulated propositions read as
			<lb />
			under :-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			(i) That the legal pursuit of a remedy, suit, appeal and
			<lb />
			second appeal are really but steps in a series of
			<lb />
			proceedings all connected by an intrinsic unity and
			<lb />
			are to be regarded as one legal proceeding.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii) The right of appeal is not a mere matter of
			<lb />
			procedure but is a substantive right.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) The institution of the suit carries with it the
			<lb />
			implication that all rights of appeal then in force
			<lb />
			are preserved to the parties thereto till the rest of
			<lb />
			the career of the suit.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iv) The right of appeal is a vested right and such a
			<lb />
			right to enter the superior Court accrues to the
			<lb />
			litigant and exists as on and from the date the lis
			<lb />
			commences and although it may be actually
			<lb />
			exercised when the adverse judgment is
			<lb />
			pronounced such right is to be governed by the law
			<lb />
			prevailing at the date of the institution of the suit
			<lb />
			or proceeding and not by the law that prevails at
			<lb />
			the date of its decision or at the date of the filing
			<lb />
			of the appeal.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(v) This vested right of appeal can be taken away only
			<lb />
			by a subsequent enactment, if it so provides
			<lb />
			expressly or by necessary intendment and not
			<lb />
			otherwise.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			17.
			<lb />
			Once the Legislature has decided to take away the right of
			<lb />
			Second Appeal the intra-Court appeals are impermissible specifically in
			<lb />
			face of the fact that constitutional validity of Section 100A has been
			<lb />
			upheld. The scope of Section 100A is so wide that it would take into
			<lb />
			its sweep not only other laws but even the Letters Patent of a High
			<lb />
			Court. The intention of the Legislature in taking away of right of
			<lb />
			appeal by abolishing an intra-Court appeal to a Bench of two Judges of
			<lb />
			the very High Court against a decision rendered by a Single Judge, is
			<lb />
			in no way prejudicial to the protected right of appeal of a litigant. The
			<lb />
			Scheme of Section 100A thus indicates that intra-Court appeal from an
			<lb />
			appellate jurisdiction of a Single Judge of the High Court is not
			<lb />
			permissible.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			18.
			<lb />
			The Motor Vehicle Act, 1988 is considered and was
			<lb />
			enacted as social welfare legislation to provide adequate compensation
			<lb />
			to the people who sustained bodily injuries or to dependents of
			<lb />
			persons who are killed in vehicular accident expeditiously. This Act
			<lb />
			has been considered even as a self-contained Code as it provides
			<lb />
			methodology to be adopted for institution of claim petition, powers of
			<lb />
			the Tribunal and passing of an award and how such an award would
			<lb />
			be executed. The Tribunal is established for adjudicating such claims
			<lb />
			by a State Notification issued under the provisions of Section 165 of
			<lb />
			the Act. On receipt of an application for compensation claimed under
			<lb />
			Section 166 of the Act, the Claims Tribunal is expected to issue
			<lb />
			notice/afford an opportunity of being heard to parties, hold inquiry
			<lb />
			into the claim and then to make an award determining the amount of
			<lb />
			compensation payable to the claimants. The Tribunal determines all
			<lb />
			questions of law and fact while arriving at a conclusion. The
			<lb />
			jurisdiction of the Tribunal does not limit to determine compensation
			<lb />
			but even as to the party/parties liable to pay compensation and its
			<lb />
			extent.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			19.
			<lb />
			While holding an inquiry as contemplated under Section
			<lb />
			168 of the Act, the Claims Tribunal has to follow summary procedure
			<lb />
			as the Tribunal thinks fit, subject to the rules made in this behalf.
			<lb />
			However, it has all the powers of a civil court for the purpose of taking
			<lb />
			evidence on oath and of enforcing the attendance of witnesses and of
			<lb />
			compelling the discovery and production of documents and material
			<lb />
			objects and for such other purposes as may be prescribed. Further the
			<lb />
			Claims Tribunal shall be deemed to be a civil court for all purposes of
			<lb />
			Section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure,
			<lb />
			1973. Section 175 mandates that where any Claims Tribunal has been
			<lb />
			constituted for any area, no civil court shall have jurisdiction to
			<lb />
			entertain any question relating to any claim for compensation which
			<lb />
			may be adjudicated upon by the Claims Tribunal.
			<lb />
			The State
			<lb />
			Government is competent to frame rules for the purposes of carrying
			<lb />
			into effect the provisions of Sections 165 to 174 of the Act and it can
			<lb />
			frame rules which may provide for the matters indicated in that
			<lb />
			section and in particular, the procedure to be followed by a Claims
			<lb />
			Tribunal in holding an inquiry under the said Chapter XXVI and in
			<lb />
			terms of Section 176(c) of the Act, the powers vested in a civil court
			<lb />
			which may be exercised by a Claims Tribunal.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			20.
			<lb />
			In exercise of its power vested in it under Section 176, the
			<lb />
			State of Maharashtra has framed rules known as &quot;Maharashtra Motor
			<lb />
			Vehicles Rules, 1989&quot; and Rules 275 and 276 thereof deal with the
			<lb />
			powers of a civil court which may be exercised by Claims Tribunal and
			<lb />
			the procedure to be followed by a Claims Tribunal in holding inquiries
			<lb />
			respectively. The Tribunal is fully empowered to exercise powers
			<lb />
			vested in a civil court in relation to the procedural matters and is
			<lb />
			vested with wide powers including Sections 151, 152 and 153 of the
			<lb />
			Code.
			<lb />
			Some of the other provisions of the Code of Criminal
			<lb />
			Procedure are also applicable to the proceedings before the Tribunal.
			<lb />
			Some of the provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure i.e. Orders V, VI,
			<lb />
			VII, IX, XI, XII, XIII, XIV, XVI, XVII, XVIII, XIX, XX, XXI, XXII, XXIII,
			<lb />
			XXIV, XXVI, XXVII, XXVIII, XXIX, XXX, XXXII, XXXVII AND XXXIX are
			<lb />
			also applicable to the proceedings before the Tribunal.
			<lb />
			These
			<lb />
			provisions clearly indicate that the Tribunal has all trapping of a civil
			<lb />
			court may be in stricto senso it is not a court within the meaning of the
			<lb />
			provisions of Code of Civil Procedure. The provisions of the Code of
			<lb />
			Civil Procedure by and large are applicable in all matters to the
			<lb />
			proceedings before the Tribunal.
			<lb />
			The Tribunal in exercise of its
			<lb />
			power is obliged to determine all issues in controversy of fact and law
			<lb />
			in accordance with the provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure. As
			<lb />
			already noticed, even the provisions relating to amendment of
			<lb />
			pleadings additional evidence, service of summons and proceedings by
			<lb />
			an indigent person, all are applicable to the Tribunal.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			21.
			<lb />
			As early as in 1950s, the Supreme Court in the case of The
			<lb />
			Bharat Bank Limited, Delhi v. The Employees of the Bharat Bank
			<lb />
			Limited, Delhi, and the Bharat Bank Employee&apos;s Union, Delhi, reported
			<lb />
			in AIR 1950 SC 184, enunciated the principle that an industrial
			<lb />
			tribunal performs all duties and functions of a court. The provisions of
			<lb />
			that Act also shows that the Tribunal is discharging functions very
			<lb />
			near to those of a court, although it is not a court in the technical
			<lb />
			sense of the word.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			22.
			<lb />
			In the case of Jaswant Sugar Mills Ltd. Meerut v. Lakshmi
			<lb />
			Chand &amp; Ors., reported in AIR 1963 SC 677, the Court while
			<lb />
			considering the essential characteristics of judicial adjudication by
			<lb />
			process of determination culminating in the judicial decision observed
			<lb />
			that a judicial decision always postulates the existence of a duty laid
			<lb />
			upon the authority to act judicially, and to make a decision or an act
			<lb />
			judicial, following criteria was spelt out,
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;1)
			<lb />
			It is in substance a determination upon
			<lb />
			investigation of a question by the application
			<lb />
			of objective standards to facts found in the
			<lb />
			light of pre-existing legal rules;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			2)
			<lb />
			It declares rights or imposes upon parties
			<lb />
			obligations affecting their civil rights; and
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			3)
			<lb />
			that the investigation is subject to
			<lb />
			certain procedural attributes contemplating an
			<lb />
			opportunity of presenting its case to a party,
			<lb />
			ascertainment of facts by means of evidence if
			<lb />
			a dispute be on questions of fact, and if the
			<lb />
			dispute be on question of law on the
			<lb />
			presentation of legal argument, and a decision
			<lb />
			resulting in the disposal of the matter on
			<lb />
			findings based upon those questions of law
			<lb />
			and fact.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			23.
			<lb />
			The Court also stated that in deciding whether the
			<lb />
			authority required to act judicially when dealing with the matters
			<lb />
			affecting the rights of citizens may be regarded as a Tribunal, though
			<lb />
			not a court, the principal incident is the investiture of the &quot;trappings
			<lb />
			of a court&quot;, -such as authority to determine matters in cases initiated
			<lb />
			by parties, sitting in public, power to compel attendance of witnesses
			<lb />
			and to examine them on oath, duty to follow fundamental rules of
			<lb />
			evidence, power to pass orders mandatory to enforce obedience to
			<lb />
			their commands. Some though not necessarily all such trappings will
			<lb />
			ordinarily, make the authority which is under a duty to act judicially,
			<lb />
			a `tribunal&apos;.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			24.
			<lb />
			Further in the case of Associated Cement Companies Ltd. vs
			<lb />
			P.N. Sharma &amp; Anr., reported in AIR 1965 SC 1595, it was stated by
			<lb />
			the Supreme Court that the presence of some of the trappings may
			<lb />
			assist the determination of the question as to whether the power
			<lb />
			exercised by the authority which possesses the said trapping, is the
			<lb />
			judicial power of the State or not, and the main and the basic test,
			<lb />
			however, is whether the adjudicating power which is the particular
			<lb />
			authority is empowered to exercise, has been conferred on it by a
			<lb />
			statute and can be described as a part of the State&apos;s inherent power
			<lb />
			exercised in discharging its judicial function. Applying this principle,
			<lb />
			it was held by the Supreme Court that the Tribunal constituted under
			<lb />
			the Punjab Welfare Officers Recruitment and Conditions of Service
			<lb />
			Rules, 1952 was a Tribunal having the trappings of a court.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			25.
			<lb />
			More so, in the case of State of Haryana vs Smt. Darshana
			<lb />
			Devi &amp; Ors., reported in (1979)2 SCC 236, the Supreme Court, while
			<lb />
			dealing with a case under the provisions of Motor Vehicles Act, 1939,
			<lb />
			stated that as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;The reasoning of the High Court in holding that Order
			<lb />
			XXXIII will apply to the Tribunals which have the
			<lb />
			trappings of the civil court finds our approval. We
			<lb />
			affirm the decision.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			26.
			<lb />
			It is said that all Tribunals are not courts, though all the
			<lb />
			courts are Tribunals. The word &quot;courts&quot; is used to designate those
			<lb />
			Tribunals which are set up in an organized State for the
			<lb />
			Administration of Justice. The Administration of Justice is meant to
			<lb />
			be the exercise of judicial power of the State to maintain and uphold
			<lb />
			rights and to punish &quot;wrongs&quot;. Whenever there is an infringement of a
			<lb />
			right or an injury, the courts are there to restore the vinculum juris,
			<lb />
			which is disturbed.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			27.
			<lb />
			In addition to the above general principles, some of the
			<lb />
			courts have taken a specific view stating the principle that the Tribunal
			<lb />
			constituted under the M.V. Act is a court subordinate to the High
			<lb />
			Court in terms of Section 24 of the Code of Civil Procedure, The
			<lb />
			Karnataka High Court in Mrs. Noreen R. Srikantaiah v. L. Dasarath
			<lb />
			Ramaiah, Gulbarga &amp; Anr., reported in AIR 1985 Karnataka 208, held
			<lb />
			as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;8. Then again, the proposition that when the
			<lb />
			&quot;District Judge&quot; is notified as constituting the Tribunal,
			<lb />
			the conferment of the special jurisdiction on the
			<lb />
			District Judge is by virtue of his presiding over the
			<lb />
			District Court and not as persona designata and that
			<lb />
			though the term &quot;District Judge&quot; is used in the
			<lb />
			notification, the investiture of jurisdiction is in reality
			<lb />
			in the court of District Judge is eminently arguable. In
			<lb />
			Balakrishna Udayar v. Vasudeva Ayyar, AIR 1917 PC
			<lb />
			71, the Judicial Committee observed:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;It appears to their Lordships to be clear that in
			<lb />
			all these matters the Civil Court exercises its powers as
			<lb />
			a Court of Law, not merely as a persona designata
			<lb />
			whose determinations are not to be treated as
			<lb />
			judgments of a legal Tribunal......&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			9.
			<lb />
			It is not necessary to refer to the differing views
			<lb />
			to the High Courts on the point. We have now the
			<lb />
			pronouncement of the Supreme Court in Bhagwati
			<lb />
			Devi v. I.S. Goel, 1983 Acc CJ 123 which imparts an
			<lb />
			altogether new complexion to the problem and puts
			<lb />
			the point beyond controversy.
			<lb />
			In this decision,
			<lb />
			Supreme Court referred to its earlier pronouncement
			<lb />
			in Darshan Devi&apos;s case, AIR 1979 SC 855 which arose
			<lb />
			out of the decision of the Punjab &amp; Haryana High
			<lb />
			Court in Smt. Darshana Devi v. Sher Singh, AIR 1978
			<lb />
			Punj &amp; Har 265. The question before the High Court in
			<lb />
			that case was whether a claimant before the Tribunal
			<lb />
			constituted under S. 110 of the `Act&apos; is entitled to the
			<lb />
			benefit of O.33 R.1 C.P. C. The Tribunal had, in that
			<lb />
			case, negatived this claim holding that O.33, C.P. C.
			<lb />
			was not one of those provisions which had expressly
			<lb />
			been made applicable by the Punjab Motor Accidents
			<lb />
			Claims Rules, 1964. In support of its view the Tribunal
			<lb />
			had relied upon an earlier opinion expressed by Dua, J.
			<lb />
			that S.110-C of the M.V. Act by no means clothed the
			<lb />
			Tribunal with all the characteristics of a Civil Court.
			<lb />
			But in Darshana Devi&apos;s case, (AIR 1978 Punj &amp; Har
			<lb />
			265), Koshal, C.J. did not subscribe to the earlier view
			<lb />
			of Dua, J. but referred, with approval, to a Full Bench
			<lb />
			judgment of that Court in Shanti Devi v. General
			<lb />
			Manager, haryana Roadways, Ambala, AIR 1972 Punj
			<lb />
			&amp; Har 65 (FB), in which, Jain, J. speaking for the Full
			<lb />
			Bench had said (at p.72):
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;The proceedings before the Claims Tribunal
			<lb />
			closely resemble the proceedings in a Civil Court and
			<lb />
			to use the language of their Lordships of the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court in Jugal Kishore&apos;s case AIR 1967 SC 1494, the
			<lb />
			Claims Tribunal for all intents and pruposes discharges
			<lb />
			the same functions and duties in the same manner as a
			<lb />
			Court of law is expected to do. In this view of the
			<lb />
			matter I hold that the proceedings before the Claims
			<lb />
			Tribunal are not in the nature of arbitration
			<lb />
			proceedings and that the Claims Tribunal while
			<lb />
			disposing of the claim acts as a Court.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis ours)
			<lb />
			Darshana Devi&apos;s case, in which the above view of Jain,
			<lb />
			J. was reiterated, went up to the Supreme Court.
			<lb />
			Supreme Court observed:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;2.
			<lb />
			The poor shall not be prised out of the
			<lb />
			justice market by insistence on court-fee and refusal to
			<lb />
			apply the exemptive provisions of O.XXXIII, C.P. C. So
			<lb />
			we are distressed that the State of Haryana, mindless
			<lb />
			of the mandate of equal justice to the indigent under
			<lb />
			the Magna Carta of our Republic, expressed in Art. 14
			<lb />
			and stressed in Art.39A of the constitution has sought
			<lb />
			leave to appeal against the order of the High Court
			<lb />
			which has rightly extended the `pauper&apos; provisions to
			<lb />
			auto-accident claims. The reasoning of the high Court
			<lb />
			in holding that Order XXXIII will apply to Tribunals
			<lb />
			which have the trappings of the Civil Court finds our
			<lb />
			approval. We affirm the decision.&quot; (Emphasis ours)
			<lb />
			But in Revanappa&apos;s case (AIR 1983 Kant 164),
			<lb />
			Swami, J. did not accept the contention that in
			<lb />
			Darshana Devi&apos;s case, Supreme Court must be
			<lb />
			understood to have affirmed the view of Jain, J. in
			<lb />
			Shanti Devi&apos;s case (AIR 1972 Pun &amp; Har 65) (FB) on
			<lb />
			which Koshal, C.J. Had, in turn, placed reliance.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			10. However, Bhagwati Devi&apos;s case (1983 Acc CJ
			<lb />
			123) (SC), now puts the points outside the pale of
			<lb />
			controversy. The matter arose in the context of the
			<lb />
			power of the Supreme Court under S.25 to transfer
			<lb />
			suits and other proceedings, inter alia, from one &quot;Civil
			<lb />
			Court&quot; in one State to the other &quot;Civil Court&quot; in any
			<lb />
			other State. There is no distinction in the concept of a
			<lb />
			Court between S.24 and S.25 C.P. C. However, the
			<lb />
			requirement of the element of subordination envisaged
			<lb />
			in S.24 so as to render the power under S.24
			<lb />
			exercisable, is, understandably, not in S.25. If, for
			<lb />
			purposes of S.25 a Motor Accidents Claims Tribunal is
			<lb />
			a &quot;Civil Court&quot;, if follows, a fortiori, that the Tribunal is
			<lb />
			a &quot;Court&quot;, for the purpose of S.24 as well. It is in this
			<lb />
			context that the pronouncement in Bhagwati Devi&apos;s
			<lb />
			case is instructive on the aspect now under
			<lb />
			consideration. Supreme Court said:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;In view of the observations of this Court in State
			<lb />
			of Haryana v. Dharshan Devi, we are of the view that
			<lb />
			the Motor Accidents Claims Tribunal constituted under
			<lb />
			the M.V. Act is a Civil Court for the purposes of S.25 of
			<lb />
			the Civil P.C. We are satisfied that the cases before us
			<lb />
			are fit cases for being transferred from the file of the
			<lb />
			Motor Accidents Claims Tribunal, Moradabad to the
			<lb />
			file of the Motor Accidents Claims Tribunal Delhi
			<lb />
			................&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			This pronouncement of the Supreme Court should now
			<lb />
			serve to put the controversy at rest. In view of this
			<lb />
			pronouncement, the view taken in State of Karnataka
			<lb />
			v. Subbanna (AIR 1974 Kant 109) and in Revanappa&apos;s
			<lb />
			case (AIR 1983 Kant 164) that such a Tribunal is not a
			<lb />
			`Court&apos; cannot continue to hold the field.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			28.
			<lb />
			A Bench of this Court in Gurucharansing Hardayalsing
			<lb />
			Sethi v. Narhari Laxman Shinde &amp; Ors., reported in 1996(4) Bom.C. R.
			<lb />
			298 observed that the Motor Accident Claims Tribunal is a persona
			<lb />
			designata and stated that it is a court subordinate to High Court under
			<lb />
			Section 115 of the Code of Civil Procedure.
			<lb />
			The Court observed
			<lb />
			thus:-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;Though amongst various High Courts there was
			<lb />
			difference of opinion as to whether the Motor
			<lb />
			Accident Claims Tribunal is persona designeta or the
			<lb />
			Court subordinate to the high Court within the
			<lb />
			meaning of section 115 C.P. C., but after the Apex
			<lb />
			Court in (State of Haryana v. Smt. Darshana Devi &amp;
			<lb />
			Others), A.I. R. 1979 S.C. 855, observed that the
			<lb />
			Motor Accident Claims Tribunal has the trappings of
			<lb />
			the Civil Court, the later decisions of various High
			<lb />
			Courts are consistent that the Motor Accident Claims
			<lb />
			Tribunal, for all intents and purposes, is Court
			<lb />
			subordinate to the High Court and has trappings of
			<lb />
			Civil Court and amenable to revisional jurisdiction of
			<lb />
			the High Court under section 115 C.P. C. I fully
			<lb />
			agree with the view that Motor Accident Claims
			<lb />
			Tribunal is not a persona-designeta but a Court
			<lb />
			subordinate to the High Court under section 115 C.P.
			<lb />
			C.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			29.
			<lb />
			The Supreme Court in a very recent judgment in the
			<lb />
			case of Kamal Kumar Dutta &amp; Anr. v. Ruby General Hospital Ltd.
			<lb />
			&amp; Ors., reported in 2006 AIR SCW 4594, while dealing with the
			<lb />
			case under Sections 397 and 398 of the Companies Act also took
			<lb />
			the view that the Company Law Board has adjudicatory power
			<lb />
			to decide all questions of law and facts, and held that :-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;There is no two opinion in the matter that when the
			<lb />
			CLB exercises its power under Ss.397 &amp; 398, it
			<lb />
			exercised a quasi-judicial power as the original
			<lb />
			authority. It may not be a Court but it has all trapping
			<lb />
			of a Court.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			30.
			<lb />
			A Bench of Rajasthan High Court in the case of R.S. R.T. C.
			<lb />
			&amp; etc. etc. vs Vaibhav Kumar &amp; Ors., reported in AIR 2007 Rajasthan
			<lb />
			147, held as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;23. The legal position exposited by the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court in Kamal Kumar Dutta, 2006 AIR SCW 4594,
			<lb />
			applies on all fours to the order /award passed by the
			<lb />
			Motor Accident claims Tribunal under Section 168 of
			<lb />
			the Motor Vehicles Act and where such order/award is
			<lb />
			carried in an appeal under Section 173 of that Act.
			<lb />
			Even if it be assumed that the Motor Accident Claims
			<lb />
			Tribunal is not a Court as is the term ordinarily
			<lb />
			understood, it is beyond doubt that such Tribunal has
			<lb />
			all the trapping of a Court. Though the Tribunals
			<lb />
			occupy a special position of their own under the
			<lb />
			scheme of the Courts and Tribunals and special matters
			<lb />
			and questions are entrusted to them for their decision
			<lb />
			yet they share with the Courts one common
			<lb />
			characteristic viz.; both the Courts as well as Tribunals
			<lb />
			are constituted by the State and are invested with
			<lb />
			judicial functions as distinguished from purely
			<lb />
			administrative or executive functions. It is the State&apos;s
			<lb />
			inherent judicial power which is discharged by the
			<lb />
			Courts and Tribunals. If the Company Law Board
			<lb />
			constituted under the Companies Act in its
			<lb />
			adjudicatory powers has the trappings of a Court and
			<lb />
			an appeal under Section 10F of the Companies Act
			<lb />
			from its order to the single Judge is not amenable to
			<lb />
			further appeal (Letters Patent) to the Division Bench of
			<lb />
			the same Court because of Section 100A of the Code of
			<lb />
			Civil Procedure, a fortiori, an order passed by the
			<lb />
			Single Judge in appeal under Section 173 of the Motor
			<lb />
			Vehicles Act from the order/award of the Motor
			<lb />
			Accident Claims Tribunal shall not be subject to intra-
			<lb />
			Court appeal in view of the bar created by Section
			<lb />
			100A of the Code of Civil Procedure effective from 1 st
			<lb />
			July, 2002.&quot;
			<lb />
			( Emphasis supplied )
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			31.
			<lb />
			In the light of the above judgment and consistent view
			<lb />
			taken by the courts there can hardly be any doubt that the Tribunal
			<lb />
			does have trappings of a court. It satisfies all the tests stated above.
			<lb />
			In any case, it has power to summon, record statements on oath,
			<lb />
			compel attendance of the witnesses, determine controversies by a
			<lb />
			public adjudicatory process and even has the power to punish the
			<lb />
			defaulters. It can get its award executed in accordance with the law.
			<lb />
			Besides all these, it is performing duties and functions of
			<lb />
			administration of justice under the power of the State and in fact
			<lb />
			under a statute. At this stage itself, we may notice that the Division
			<lb />
			Bench of this Court in the case of Asha d/o Bhalchandra Joshi vs.
			<lb />
			National Insurance Co. Ltd., reported in 2008 (1) Mh. L.J. 724 did
			<lb />
			not consider the judgment of the Supreme Court in Kamal Kumar
			<lb />
			Dutta&apos;s case (supra) and of this Court in Gurucharansing Hardayalsing
			<lb />
			Sethi vs Narhari Laxman Shinde and others, (1996) 4 Bom. C.R. 298,
			<lb />
			besides it has ignored the basic principles applicable for determination
			<lb />
			i.e. whether the Tribunal has a trappings of a Court or not. With
			<lb />
			respect, we are unable to follow the view taken by a Division Bench in
			<lb />
			that case in this regard.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			32.
			<lb />
			As far as the appeals under the Motor Vehicle Act are
			<lb />
			concerned, it specifically provides that the award of the Tribunal made
			<lb />
			under Section 165 of the Act would be appeallable to the High Court
			<lb />
			under Section 173 of the Act. Section 173 of the Act thus reads as
			<lb />
			under: -
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;173. Appeals : (1) Subject to the provisions of sub-
			<lb />
			section (2), any person aggrieved by an award of a
			<lb />
			Claims Tribunal may, within ninety days from the date
			<lb />
			of the award, prefer an appeal to the High Court :
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Provided that no appeal by the person who is
			<lb />
			required to pay any amount in terms of such award
			<lb />
			shall be entertained by the High Court unless he has
			<lb />
			deposited with it twenty-five thousand rupees or fifty
			<lb />
			per cent of the amount so awarded, whichever is less,
			<lb />
			in the manner directed by the High Court;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			I
			Provided further that the High Court may
			<lb />
			entertain the appeal after the expiry of the said period
			<lb />
			of ninety days. If it is satisfied that the appellant was
			<lb />
			prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the
			<lb />
			appeal in time.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(2) No appeal shall lie against any award of a
			<lb />
			Claims Tribunal, if the amount in dispute in the appeal
			<lb />
			is less than ten thousand rupees.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			33.
			<lb />
			The bare reading of Section 173 of the Act shows that the
			<lb />
			provisions are self-contained in all respects. It provides for filing an
			<lb />
			appeal by any person aggrieved by an award of the Claim Tribunal
			<lb />
			provided the amount in appeal is not less than Rs.10,000/-. Such
			<lb />
			appeals are to be filed within 90 days and the appeal would be
			<lb />
			entertained by the High Court subject to satisfaction of the conditions
			<lb />
			stipulated under the proviso 1 of Section 173(1) of the Act. In terms
			<lb />
			of proviso 2 of Section 173(1) of the Act, the High Court can entertain
			<lb />
			an appeal even after the expiry of 90 days if it has shown sufficient
			<lb />
			cause for preferring an appeal beyond time. In other words, this
			<lb />
			provision indicates the scope of powers of the High Court while
			<lb />
			entertaining an appeal under the said provision. The ambit, scope and
			<lb />
			the powers thus have been outlined by the Legislature itself and may
			<lb />
			not be dependent on the provisions of other laws.
			<lb />
			There is no
			<lb />
			provision in the entire M.V. Act which provides for further appeal from
			<lb />
			the judgment passed by the High Court in exercise of its appellate
			<lb />
			jurisdiction under Section 173 of the M.V. Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			34.
			<lb />
			Once the M.V. Act provides for a remedy of First Appeal
			<lb />
			and does not specify availability of any further right of appeal, it is
			<lb />
			obvious that the Legislature does not intend to give any further right
			<lb />
			of appeal within the provisions of the Act particularly in relation to
			<lb />
			intra-Court appeal. The right to appeal and in fact all remedial
			<lb />
			provisions do not emerge from any fundamental or vested right. It is a
			<lb />
			grant or a statute under which such right of appeal is available. In
			<lb />
			view of this settled principle, the absence of any provision providing a
			<lb />
			further appeal in terms of Section 173 of the Act would obviously lead
			<lb />
			to one inevitable conclusion that the special law (i.e. Motor Vehicle
			<lb />
			Act) in comparison to general laws (i.e. Code of Civil Procedure) does
			<lb />
			not contemplate maintainability of a second appeal against the
			<lb />
			judgment of the learned Single Judge.
			<lb />
			It may also be noticed that
			<lb />
			remedy of appeal being a statutory right, cannot be introduced by
			<lb />
			judicial interpretative process. The Court would be very reluctant to
			<lb />
			read into the statute, a right of appeal in absence of any such specific
			<lb />
			provision.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			I
			NATURE OF RIGHT OF APPEAL:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			35.
			<lb />
			According to Salmond, (Salmond on Jurisprudence,
			<lb />
			Twelfth Edition), the right in the strict sense is duty which is
			<lb />
			something owed by one to another. Correspondingly, the latter has a
			<lb />
			right against the former. The expression `right&apos; is capable of being
			<lb />
			used in wider sense. Thus the rights are concerned with interest, yet
			<lb />
			right and interest are not identical. Bentham introduced the concept
			<lb />
			of natural law and natural rights which, according to him, are two
			<lb />
			kinds of fictions or metaphors which play a greater part in books of
			<lb />
			legislation that they deserve to be examined by themselves. Of
			<lb />
			course, this concept has not found much acceptance so far in
			<lb />
			legislative or judicial analysis. A legal right is commonly accompanied
			<lb />
			by the power of instituting legal proceedings for enforcement of it.
			<lb />
			Legal rights are normally enforceable by process of law. There could
			<lb />
			be a situation where a legal right itself is imperfect and, therefore,
			<lb />
			becomes unenforceable in law. Every legal right has distinguishable
			<lb />
			characteristics, like it is vested in a person, it is available against a
			<lb />
			person and such right is enforceable in accordance with the provisions
			<lb />
			of law. A legal right could also be a vested right as it gives right to a
			<lb />
			person aggrieved to prefer an appeal in accordance with the principles
			<lb />
			of that statute. In simple language, a right to appeal is a statutory
			<lb />
			right, it is neither a natural nor a fundamental right.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			36.
			<lb />
			An appeal is an application to a superior Court or Tribunal
			<lb />
			praying for reversal or varying or setting aside a judgment under
			<lb />
			appeal. A right which is conferred by statute or equivalent legislative
			<lb />
			authority is not a matter of practice or procedure and neither the
			<lb />
			superior nor the inferior Court or Tribunal nor both combined can
			<lb />
			create or take away such a right. Even the Civil Division of the Court
			<lb />
			of Appeal in England is bound by its own decisions. No appeal lies
			<lb />
			from a decision of the Court of Appeal as to whether a judgment or
			<lb />
			order is, for any purpose connected with an appeal to that Court, final
			<lb />
			or interlocutory. Right to appeal thus should be created by vested
			<lb />
			specific jurisdiction. (Halsbury Law of England, Fourth Edition).
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			37.
			<lb />
			In the case of Garikapati Veeraya (supra), the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court in unambiguous terms stated the principle that right of appeal is
			<lb />
			a vested right which is created by a statute alone. This was reiterated
			<lb />
			by the Supreme Court in a more recent judgment and was followed
			<lb />
			with approval in Kamal Kumar Dutta (supra), where the Court held
			<lb />
			that right to prefer appeal is a statutory right and it could be exercised
			<lb />
			only in case of adverse decision and will be governed by the law
			<lb />
			prevailing at the time of commencement of the suit and comprise of
			<lb />
			successive rights of appeal from Court to Court which rarely constitute
			<lb />
			one proceeding. This legal right was also capable of being taken away
			<lb />
			either expressly or by necessary intendment by a subsequent
			<lb />
			Legislature.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			38.
			<lb />
			In the case of Maria Cristina De Souza Sodder and others vs
			<lb />
			Amria Zurana Pereira Pinto and others, (1979) 1 SCC 92, the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court held as under :-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;It is no doubt well-settled that the right of appeal is a
			<lb />
			substantive right and it gets vested in a litigant no
			<lb />
			sooner the lis is commenced and such right or remedy
			<lb />
			will not be affected by any repeal of the enactment
			<lb />
			conferring such right unless the repealing enactment
			<lb />
			either expressly or by necessary application takes away
			<lb />
			such right or remedy.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			39.
			<lb />
			The principle of `appeal being a statutory right and no
			<lb />
			party has a right to file appeal except in accordance with the
			<lb />
			prescribed procedure&apos; is followed in the case of M/s M Ramnarain
			<lb />
			Private Limited and another vs State Trading Corporation of India
			<lb />
			Limited, (1983) 3 SCC 75, where the Supreme Court held as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;16.
			<lb />
			The right to prefer an appeal is a right
			<lb />
			created by statute. No party can file an appeal against
			<lb />
			any judgment, decree or order as a matter of course in
			<lb />
			the absence of a suitable provision of some law
			<lb />
			conferring on the party concerned the right to file an
			<lb />
			appeal against any judgment, decree or order. The
			<lb />
			right of appeal so conferred on any party may be lost to
			<lb />
			the party in appropriate cases by the provisions of some
			<lb />
			law such as the law of limitation and also by the
			<lb />
			conduct of the party and in appropriate cases a party
			<lb />
			may be held to have become disentitled from enforcing
			<lb />
			the right of appeal which he may otherwise have.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			40.
			<lb />
			This view was reiterated with approval by the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court in the case of Gujarat Agro Industries Co. Ltd. Vs
			<lb />
			Municipal Corporation of the City of Ahmedabad and others,
			<lb />
			(1999) 4 SCC 468, where the Court stated that even right of
			<lb />
			appeal can be made conditional or qualified and it is a creation
			<lb />
			of a statute alone. The Court held as under :-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;Right of appeal is the creature of a statute and it is for
			<lb />
			the legislature to decide whether the right of appeal
			<lb />
			should be unconditionally given to an aggrieved party
			<lb />
			or it should be conditionally given. Right of appeal
			<lb />
			which is a statutory right can be conditional or
			<lb />
			qualified. It cannot be said that such a law would be
			<lb />
			violative of Article 14 of the Constitution. If the statute
			<lb />
			does not create any right of appeal, no appeal can be
			<lb />
			filed. There is a clear distinction between a suit and an
			<lb />
			appeal. While every person has an inherent right to
			<lb />
			bring a suit of a civil nature unless the suit is barred by
			<lb />
			statute, however, in regard to an appeal, the position is
			<lb />
			quite opposite. The right to appeal inheres in no one
			<lb />
			and, therefore, for maintainability of an appeal there
			<lb />
			must be authority of law. When such a law authorises
			<lb />
			filing of appeal, it can impose conditions as well.&quot; (Para
			<lb />
			8).
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			41.
			<lb />
			Right of appeal is neither a natural nor inherent right
			<lb />
			vested in a party. It is substantive statutory right regulated by the
			<lb />
			statute creating it. (Kondiba Dagadu Kadam vs Savitribai Sopan Gujar
			<lb />
			and others, (1999) 3 SCC 722, and Kashmir Singh vs Harnam Singh
			<lb />
			and another, 2008 AIR SCW 2417).
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			42.
			<lb />
			Thus, it is evident that the right to appeal is not a right
			<lb />
			which can be assumed by logical analysis much less by exercise of
			<lb />
			inherent jurisdiction. It essentially should be provided by the law in
			<lb />
			force. In absence of any specific provision creating a right in a party to
			<lb />
			file an appeal, such right can neither be assumed nor inferred in
			<lb />
			favour of the party. On the bare reading of provisions of Section 173
			<lb />
			and in absence of any other specific provision providing further
			<lb />
			appeal, it is difficult to accept the view that with the aid of any of the
			<lb />
			provisions or by general practice the appellate order passed under
			<lb />
			Section 173 by a Single Judge of this Court would be further
			<lb />
			appealable by intra-Court appeal.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			RIGHT OF APPEAL UNDER LETTERS PATENT :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			43.
			<lb />
			It has been held that Letters Patent is a word of definite
			<lb />
			legal meaning. It is derived from the latin words literae patents. The
			<lb />
			Letters Patent are so called because they are open letters, they are not
			<lb />
			sealed up, but exposed to view, with the great seal pendant at the
			<lb />
			bottom and are usually directed or addressed by the King to all his
			<lb />
			subjects at large. Different Letters Patent have been handed down by
			<lb />
			the Sovereign in British India to Chartered High Courts which included
			<lb />
			only judicature of Bengal, Madras, Bombay, North-West Provinces,
			<lb />
			Patna, Lahore and Rangoon. (See Blackstone&apos;s Commentaries on
			<lb />
			the Laws of England, Vol. II. pp. 284-85).
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			44.
			<lb />
			Now, we may examine the impact of Clause 15 of the
			<lb />
			Letters Patent which provides for intra-Court appeal. Clause 15 of the
			<lb />
			Letters Patent does not create a substantive right of appeal from the
			<lb />
			decision of the Single Judge, but such right is obviously subject to the
			<lb />
			application of the stipulated condition. Right of appeal can be
			<lb />
			exercised only in accordance with the limitations specified in the
			<lb />
			provision granting right of appeal. Clause 15 of the Letters Patent
			<lb />
			reads as under :-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;15. Appeal to the High Court from Judges of the
			<lb />
			Court:-And We do further ordain that an appeal shall
			<lb />
			lie to the said High Court of Judicature at Bombay from
			<lb />
			the judgment (not being a judgment passed in the
			<lb />
			exercise of appellate jurisdiction by a Court subject to
			<lb />
			the superintendence of the said High Court, and not
			<lb />
			being an order made in the exercise of revisional
			<lb />
			jurisdiction and not being a sentence or order passed or
			<lb />
			made in the exercise of the power of superintendence
			<lb />
			under the provisions of section 107 of the Government
			<lb />
			of India Act, or in the exercise of criminal jurisdiction)
			<lb />
			of one Judge of, the said High Court or one Judge of
			<lb />
			any Divisional Court, pursuant to section 108 of the
			<lb />
			Government of India Act, and that notwithstanding
			<lb />
			anything herein before provided an appeal shall lie to
			<lb />
			the said High Court from a Judgement of one Judge of
			<lb />
			the said High Court from a Judge of any Division
			<lb />
			Court, pursuant to section 108 of the Government of
			<lb />
			India Act, made on or after the first day of February
			<lb />
			one thousand nine hundred and twenty-nine in the
			<lb />
			exercise of appellate jurisdiction; in respect of a decree
			<lb />
			or order made in the exercise of appellate jurisdiction
			<lb />
			by a Court subject to the superintendence of the said
			<lb />
			High Court, where the Judge who passed the judgment
			<lb />
			declares that the case is fit one for appeal; but that the
			<lb />
			right of appeal from other judgments of Judge of the
			<lb />
			High Court or of such Division Court shall be to Us,
			<lb />
			Our heirs of successors in Our or Their Privy Council,
			<lb />
			as hereinafter provided.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			45.
			<lb />
			Clause 15 of the Letters Patent is the provision which
			<lb />
			grants right of appeal to the aggrieved party against the judgment of
			<lb />
			the learned Single Judge of the Court to Letters Patent Bench. The
			<lb />
			exception carved out to this right of appeal is that the judgment not
			<lb />
			being a judgment passed in the exercise of appellate jurisdiction in
			<lb />
			respect of a decree or order made in the exercise of appellate
			<lb />
			jurisdiction by a Court subject to the superintendence of the said High
			<lb />
			Court, and not being an order made in the exercise of revisional
			<lb />
			jurisdiction and not being a sentence or order passed or made in the
			<lb />
			exercise of the power of superintendence under the provisions of
			<lb />
			section 107 of the Government of India Act, or in the exercise of
			<lb />
			criminal jurisdiction. In other words, where the clause grants right of
			<lb />
			appeal, it has inbuilt exception and limitation applicable to said right
			<lb />
			of appeal. It is also a settled proposition of law that a right to appeal
			<lb />
			can be regulated and/or restricted by the provisions of Section
			<lb />
			providing such right. The legal right that is available to a party to
			<lb />
			prefer an appeal from the judgment of the learned Single Judge thus is
			<lb />
			not a unrestricted or unfettered right. Besides the requirement that
			<lb />
			the order of the learned Single Judge as understood in common
			<lb />
			parlance has to be a judgment within the meaning of the said
			<lb />
			expression of clause 15 of the Letters Patent to perfect a right of
			<lb />
			appeal to litigant. Once it clears the parameter of a judgment and is
			<lb />
			not hit by any of the exceptions stated in the clause itself, an appeal
			<lb />
			may lie to a letters patent bench. Various aspects of Letters Patent
			<lb />
			Appeal and especially what is a judgment within Clause 15 of the
			<lb />
			Letters Patent has been dealt with by a Division Bench of this Court in
			<lb />
			a recent judgment delivered on 19 th June, 2008 ( The Bombay
			<lb />
			Diocesan Trust Association Pvt. Ltd. v. The Pastorate Committee of the
			<lb />
			Saint Andrews Church &amp; Ors.). A relevant observations of the said
			<lb />
			judgment are as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;10. While relying upon the case of
			<lb />
			Vinita M.
			<lb />
			Khanolkar v. Pragna M. Pai and others, 1998(1) SCC
			<lb />
			500, it is argued that provision of appeal in clause 15
			<lb />
			of the Letters Patent, which is a charter under which
			<lb />
			the High Court of Bombay functions, is not whittled
			<lb />
			down by the statutory provisions of section 6(3) of the
			<lb />
			Specific Relief Act. In that case, the Supreme Court
			<lb />
			stated that any statutory provision barring an appeal or
			<lb />
			revision cannot cut across the constitutional power of a
			<lb />
			High Court.
			<lb />
			Even the power flowing from the
			<lb />
			paramount charter under which the High Court
			<lb />
			functions could not get excluded unless the statutory
			<lb />
			enactment concerned expressly excludes
			<lb />
			appeals
			<lb />
			under under letters patent. It was also noticed that no
			<lb />
			such bar is discernible from language of section 6(3) of
			<lb />
			the Specific Relief Act holding that appeal under clause
			<lb />
			15 would lie to the Letters Patent Bench. It needs to be
			<lb />
			noticed that in this case, the Supreme Court was
			<lb />
			primarily concerned with the provisions of the Specific
			<lb />
			Relief Act which in comparison to the Contempt of
			<lb />
			Courts act is a statute of general impact. Furthermore,
			<lb />
			the provisions of section 6(3) contemplates that no
			<lb />
			appeal shall lie from any order or decree passed in any
			<lb />
			suit instituted under that section nor shall any review
			<lb />
			of such order or decree be allowed. It was on the
			<lb />
			language of the section that the Supreme Court was of
			<lb />
			the view that jurisdiction of the court under section 15
			<lb />
			of the Letters Patent was not ousted and the appeal
			<lb />
			was consequently, restored to the file of the High
			<lb />
			Court.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			11. Similarly, in the case of State of West Bengal and
			<lb />
			others v. Kartick Chandra Das and others, (1996) 5 SCC
			<lb />
			342,
			<lb />
			the Supreme Court again emphasised the
			<lb />
			principle that in absence of specific exclusion, the
			<lb />
			provisions of sections 4 to 24 and section 5 of the
			<lb />
			Limitation Act were applicable to the appeals filed
			<lb />
			under clause 15 including those under the Contempt of
			<lb />
			Courts Act. In that case, it was not an issue whether an
			<lb />
			appeal would lie to the Division Bench or not as
			<lb />
			recorded in para 4 of the judgment that maintainability
			<lb />
			of the appeal was not disputed. It is also useful to
			<lb />
			notice that in that case, the appeal had been preferred
			<lb />
			against issuance of contempt notice by the Division
			<lb />
			Bench. The Supreme Court held that the Appellate
			<lb />
			Side procedure of the Calcutta High Court was
			<lb />
			applicable.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			12. Lastly, reliance was also placed on the judgment
			<lb />
			of the Supreme Court in the case of P.S. Sathapan
			<lb />
			(Dead) by Lrs. v. Andhra Bank Ltd. and others, (2004)
			<lb />
			11 SCC 672. In that case, the Court was primarily
			<lb />
			concerned with bar under section 104(2) of the Civil
			<lb />
			Procedure Code and clause 15 of Letters Patent of
			<lb />
			Madras High Court. The Apex Court again affirmed
			<lb />
			the principle of harmonious construction of section 104
			<lb />
			which leads to the conclusion that Section 104(1)
			<lb />
			saves Letters Patent Appeal and bar of section 104(2)
			<lb />
			of the Civil Procedure Code does not apply. The only
			<lb />
			conclusion that can be arrived at is that unless there is
			<lb />
			specific exclusion by expression mention in the section
			<lb />
			then alone, the appeal would not lie.
			<lb />
			It will be
			<lb />
			appropriate to notice paragraphs 21 and 22 of this
			<lb />
			judgment on which the learned counsel placed heavy
			<lb />
			reliance.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;21. We are of the opinion that in reaching
			<lb />
			this conclusion the Court missed the relevant
			<lb />
			portion of clause 15 of the Letters Patent of
			<lb />
			the Bombay High Court. Reliance cannot,
			<lb />
			therefore, be placed on this judgment for the
			<lb />
			proposition that under clause 15 of the Letters
			<lb />
			Patent of the Bombay High Court no appeal to
			<lb />
			a Division Bench from the order of the Single
			<lb />
			Judge in exercise of appellate jurisdiction is
			<lb />
			maintainable.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			22. Thus the unanimous view of all courts
			<lb />
			till 1996 was that Section 104(1) CPC
			<lb />
			specifically saved letters patent appeals and
			<lb />
			the bar under Section 104(2) did not apply to
			<lb />
			letters patent appeals. The view has been
			<lb />
			that a letters patent appeal cannot be ousted
			<lb />
			by implication but the right of an appeal
			<lb />
			under the Letters Patent can be taken away by
			<lb />
			an express provision in an appropriate
			<lb />
			legislation. The express provision need not
			<lb />
			refer to or use the words &quot;letters patent&quot; but if
			<lb />
			on a reading of the provision it is clear that all
			<lb />
			further appeals are barred then even a letters
			<lb />
			patent appeal would be barred.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			13. These judgments referred by appellant are
			<lb />
			different on facts and the judicial dictum does not have
			<lb />
			a direct bearing to the matters in issue before us in the
			<lb />
			present appeal. In fact, in the case of Kartick Chandra
			<lb />
			Das (supra), it was specifically conceded that appeals
			<lb />
			against notice of contempt lies and there was no
			<lb />
			determination on the question of maintainability of
			<lb />
			appeal even with reference to the provisions of
			<lb />
			Limitation Act. Moreover, these were primarily
			<lb />
			determination of lis between the parties in regard to
			<lb />
			certain personal reliefs and were not the cases of
			<lb />
			discharge of power within special jurisdiction as to
			<lb />
			contempt.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			14. As is evident from the discussion of the
			<lb />
			judgments relied upon by the appellant, right of
			<lb />
			Letters Patent Appeal can be taken away by an express
			<lb />
			provision in an appropriate Legislation. It is not
			<lb />
			necessary that the section should expressly use the
			<lb />
			word &quot;Letters Patent&quot; but if on plain reading of the
			<lb />
			provision, it is clear that all further appeals are barred
			<lb />
			then even a Letters Patent Appeal would be barred.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The judgments cited by appellant do not have any
			<lb />
			direct bearing on issue in hand. In the controversy
			<lb />
			before us in as much as the provisions of the Specific
			<lb />
			Relief Act, section 104 of the CPC and the Limitation
			<lb />
			Act are not pari materia to the provisions of section 19
			<lb />
			of the Contempt of Courts Act. Section 19 of the Act
			<lb />
			reads as under:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;19. Appeals.-(1) An appeal shall lie as of
			<lb />
			right from any order or decision of High
			<lb />
			Court in the exercise of its jurisdiction to
			<lb />
			punish for contempt-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a) where the order or decision is that of a
			<lb />
			single Judge, to a Bench of not less than two
			<lb />
			Judges of the Court;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b) where the order or decision is that of a
			<lb />
			Bench, to the Supreme Court:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Provided that where the order or decision is
			<lb />
			that of the Court of the Judicial Commissioner
			<lb />
			in any Union territory, such appeal shall lie to
			<lb />
			the Supreme Court.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(2) Pending any appeal, the appellate Court
			<lb />
			may order that-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a) the execution of the punishment or
			<lb />
			order appealed against the suspended;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b) if the appellant is in confinement, he be
			<lb />
			released on bail; and
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(c) the appeal be heard notwithstanding
			<lb />
			that the appellant has not purged his
			<lb />
			contempt.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(3) Where any person aggrieved by any
			<lb />
			order against which an appeal may be filed
			<lb />
			satisfies the High Court that he intents to
			<lb />
			prefer an appeal, the High Court may also
			<lb />
			exercise all or any of the powers conferred by
			<lb />
			sub-section (2).
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(4) an appeal under sub-section (1) shall be
			<lb />
			filed-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a) in the case of an appeal to a Bench of
			<lb />
			the High Court, within thirty days;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b) in the case of an appeal to the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court, within sixty days, from the date of the
			<lb />
			order appealed against.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			15. The language of section 19 where gives a
			<lb />
			statutory right to a party to maintain an appeal, there
			<lb />
			it restricts such right by using specific language in
			<lb />
			regard to punishing a person for contempt. The
			<lb />
			expression used is &quot;An appeal shall lie as of right from
			<lb />
			any order or decision of High Court in the exercise of
			<lb />
			its jurisdiction to punish for contempt&quot;. Thus, the
			<lb />
			statute itself provides the class of cases in which an
			<lb />
			appeal shall lie. Once a special legislation restricts the
			<lb />
			right of appeal by specific language, it obviously
			<lb />
			excludes what is not specifically included.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			intention of the Legislature is certainly not to permit or
			<lb />
			grant statutory right of appeal unless the order passed
			<lb />
			was for grant of punishment for contempt. The section
			<lb />
			is self-contained provision and even provides that the
			<lb />
			appeal shall lie to two Judges bench of the High Court
			<lb />
			where the decision is of a Single Judge of that court
			<lb />
			and to the Supreme Court where the order is by a
			<lb />
			Bench of the High Court. The complete mechanism of
			<lb />
			right to appeal and forum to which the appeal would
			<lb />
			lie has been spelt out by the Legislature and, thus,
			<lb />
			there is no reason for the court to expand its scope to
			<lb />
			hold that appeal would lie by adding that even the
			<lb />
			order of discharge shall be included in the expression
			<lb />
			`punish for contempt&apos;.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			.....
			<lb />
			......
			<lb />
			.......
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			18. The appeals are filed against a decree or an
			<lb />
			order which is determination of a lis in accordance
			<lb />
			with law. The appeal would lie against such order or
			<lb />
			decree with the exception that such order or decree
			<lb />
			was not made in exercise of appellate jurisdiction. A
			<lb />
			decree as even contemplated under the provisions of
			<lb />
			Civil Procedure Code would be a finding on matters in
			<lb />
			issue between the parties and would decide such
			<lb />
			issues. Thus, the matter referred would be the one
			<lb />
			which decide the rights of the parties and in fact, is a
			<lb />
			substantial determination of rights of the parties to the
			<lb />
			lis before the Court of competent jurisdiction. As
			<lb />
			against this, a matter of contempt is primarily a
			<lb />
			matter between the Court and the contemnor and is
			<lb />
			not determination of any lis pending before the court
			<lb />
			on which parties are litigating. An order of discharge
			<lb />
			in a contempt, thus, would not be a judgment and
			<lb />
			order within the meaning of clause 15 of Letters Patent
			<lb />
			and an appeal against such an order is excluded under
			<lb />
			the language of section 19 of the Contempt of Courts
			<lb />
			Act which unambiguously states that only orders of
			<lb />
			punishment for contempt are appealable.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			19. As far as this court is concerned, as back as in
			<lb />
			Narendrabhai Sarabhai Hatheesing and others v.
			<lb />
			Chinubhai Manibhai Seth, AIR 1936 Bombay 314, the
			<lb />
			Division Bench took the view that order of court for
			<lb />
			breach of undertaking to court is not a judgment. An
			<lb />
			Order of the court refusing to commit a person for
			<lb />
			breach of an undertaking given to the court and
			<lb />
			embodied in the order of the Court cannot be said to
			<lb />
			be a judgment within the meaning of Clause 15, as it
			<lb />
			does not affect the merits of any question between the
			<lb />
			parties and hence is not appealable. The Bench also
			<lb />
			noticed a judgment of Full Bench of Calcutta High
			<lb />
			Court in Mohendra Lall Mitter v. Anundo Coomar
			<lb />
			Mitter, (1897) 25 Cal. 236 (F.B.) and declined to
			<lb />
			accept the view firstly as it was not binding and
			<lb />
			specifically for the reason that decision of the Calcutta
			<lb />
			High Court was in absence of any reason for the
			<lb />
			conclusion arrived at and ultimately rejected the
			<lb />
			contention that an order refusing the application to
			<lb />
			commit a person for contempt was appealable. The
			<lb />
			same principle was approved and distinguished by the
			<lb />
			Full Bench of this court in the case of Collector of
			<lb />
			Bombay v. Issac Penhas, AIR (35) 1948 Bombay 103,
			<lb />
			where the court held as under:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;17. On the preliminary point as to whether
			<lb />
			an appeal lies, there has been a long and
			<lb />
			continuous controversy in the different High
			<lb />
			Courts as to the true meaning to be given to
			<lb />
			the expression &quot;judgment&quot; in Cl. 15 of the
			<lb />
			Letters Patent. I should have thought that,
			<lb />
			apart from authority, an order of committal
			<lb />
			for contempt was a judgment within that
			<lb />
			definition. The order undoubtedly constitutes
			<lb />
			final adjudication. It affects the merits of the
			<lb />
			case and it also determines the right and
			<lb />
			liability of the appellant. Let us therefore
			<lb />
			consider whether there is anything in the
			<lb />
			reported decisions which are contrary to the
			<lb />
			view I am suggesting. The definition given by
			<lb />
			Sir Richard Couch, Chief Justice, in the two
			<lb />
			Calcutta decisions is considered to be a locus
			<lb />
			classicus as far as the definition of the
			<lb />
			expression &quot;judgment&quot; is concerned in Cl. 15,
			<lb />
			Letters Patent. The first of these decisions is
			<lb />
			reported in 8 Beng. L.R. 433. That was a case
			<lb />
			where an order was made directing the issue
			<lb />
			of a writ of mandamus to the Justices of the
			<lb />
			Peace for Calcutta to compel them to refer to
			<lb />
			arbitration question of compensation, and the
			<lb />
			question arose whether an appeal lay from
			<lb />
			that order, and Sir Richard Couch said in his
			<lb />
			judgment (p. 452):
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;We think that `judgment&apos; in Cl.15
			<lb />
			means a decision which affects the merits of
			<lb />
			the question between the parties by
			<lb />
			determining some right or liability.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			18. In the subsequent decision reported in
			<lb />
			13 Beng. L.R. 91 the interpretation was
			<lb />
			slightly extended and the learned Chief
			<lb />
			Justice said (page 101):
			<lb />
			A judgment &quot;is not a mere formal order,
			<lb />
			or an order merely regulating the procedure
			<lb />
			in the suit, but one that has the effect of
			<lb />
			giving a jurisdiction to the Court which it
			<lb />
			otherwise would not have.&quot;
			<lb />
			In that case the learned Chief Justice was
			<lb />
			considering an order refusing to set aside an
			<lb />
			order granting leave to sue to the plaintiff
			<lb />
			under Cl.12, Letters Patent.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			19. The Madras High Court has always
			<lb />
			given a more liberal interpretation to the
			<lb />
			expression &quot;judgment&quot;, and the leading case is
			<lb />
			the one reported in 35 Mad. 1, where we have
			<lb />
			the judgment of Sir Arnold White, and the
			<lb />
			opinion of that learned Chief Justice as to the
			<lb />
			true meaning of the expression &quot;judgment&quot; is
			<lb />
			(p.7):
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;If its effect, whatever its form may be,
			<lb />
			and whatever may be the nature of the
			<lb />
			application on which it is made, is to put an
			<lb />
			end to the suit or proceeding so far as the
			<lb />
			Court before which the suit or proceeding is
			<lb />
			pending is concerned, or if its effect, if it is
			<lb />
			not complied with, is to put an end to the suit
			<lb />
			or proceeding, I think the adjudication is a
			<lb />
			judgment within the meaning of the clause.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			20. This High Court has always preferred to
			<lb />
			follow the Calcutta High Court rather than the
			<lb />
			Madras High Court: or, in other words, it has
			<lb />
			undoubtedly given a more restricted meaning
			<lb />
			to the expression &quot;judgment&quot; than the Madras
			<lb />
			High Court has done-see the observations of
			<lb />
			Sir Basil Scott C.J. In 11 Bom. L.R. 241.
			<lb />
			....................................
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			23. Then we come to the decision which has
			<lb />
			created some difficulty, and that is the
			<lb />
			decision reported in 38 Bom. L.R. 571. The
			<lb />
			order with which the Divisional Bench of Sir
			<lb />
			John Beaumount C.J., and Rangnekar J. was
			<lb />
			concerned was refusing to commit a person
			<lb />
			for breach of an undertaking given to a Court,
			<lb />
			and the Court held that no appeal lay from
			<lb />
			such an order. It is difficult to see how such
			<lb />
			an order could possibly be a `judgment&apos;
			<lb />
			within the meaning of Cl. 15, Letters Patent
			<lb />
			and give the right of appeal to a person who
			<lb />
			had moved the Court for contempt and had
			<lb />
			failed to get an order for committal. It is
			<lb />
			impossible to say that any right or liability of
			<lb />
			the appellant was determined by the order of
			<lb />
			committal. The appellant had no right to get
			<lb />
			such an order from the Court. It was the
			<lb />
			discretion of the Court, and the Court having
			<lb />
			refused to exercise its discretion, the appellant
			<lb />
			could not say that any right of his was
			<lb />
			affected or any liability imposed upon him.
			<lb />
			Therefore on the facts of the case that
			<lb />
			decision is clearly distinguishable from the
			<lb />
			facts before us where the appellant has been
			<lb />
			ordered to pay a fine and has been held to be
			<lb />
			guilty of contempt. It cannot be disputed that
			<lb />
			in this case the appellant&apos;s rights are
			<lb />
			undoubtedly affected and that a liability has
			<lb />
			been imposed on him on a final adjudication
			<lb />
			by the learned Judge. But it is contended by
			<lb />
			Mr. Taraporewalla that the decision in 38
			<lb />
			Bom. L.R. 571 is of wider import than the
			<lb />
			facts on which it was decided. It is suggested
			<lb />
			that that decision lays down that there is no
			<lb />
			appeal from any order made by a Judge in
			<lb />
			contempt proceedings whether he refuses to
			<lb />
			commit or whether he makes a committal
			<lb />
			order. I refuse to read that judgment of the
			<lb />
			Court of Appeal in that light.
			<lb />
			What is
			<lb />
			contended is that that judgment relies on the
			<lb />
			definition given by Sir Richard Couch C.J. and
			<lb />
			it is argued that the decision of Bhagwati J. is
			<lb />
			not a decision between parties and, therefore,
			<lb />
			it cannot constitute a judgment. Now it is to
			<lb />
			be remembered that most of the decisions
			<lb />
			reported in the books dealing with the
			<lb />
			definition of `judgment&apos; were cases between
			<lb />
			parties and usually the question that fell to be
			<lb />
			determined was whether a certain order was
			<lb />
			final or interlocutory; and if interlocutory,
			<lb />
			whether it was `judgment&apos; within the
			<lb />
			meaning of Cl.15, Letters Patent. What we
			<lb />
			are concerned with here is not the case of a
			<lb />
			`judgment&apos; given between parties in a
			<lb />
			litigation between parties but a `judgment&apos;
			<lb />
			given against a party which affects his rights.
			<lb />
			It would be clearly wrong to apply a definition
			<lb />
			given in its own context applicable to its own
			<lb />
			facts and circumstances to an entirely
			<lb />
			different set of facts and circumstances. The
			<lb />
			expression &quot;between the parties&quot; in the
			<lb />
			definition of Sir Richard Couch J. is not an
			<lb />
			integral part of that definition. Therefore, in
			<lb />
			my opinion, in deciding that an appeal lies
			<lb />
			from an order of committal, we are in no way
			<lb />
			deviating from the accepted definition of Sir
			<lb />
			Richard Couch to the extent that that
			<lb />
			definition deals with the essentials and
			<lb />
			fundamentals of the expression `judgment&apos;
			<lb />
			occurring in Cl. 15, Letters Patent. As I have
			<lb />
			already pointed out, the order of Bhagwati J.
			<lb />
			affects
			<lb />
			the merits of the question by
			<lb />
			determining a right or liability. It is not
			<lb />
			between parties, but that it could not be
			<lb />
			because the contempt proceedings were
			<lb />
			between the Court and the appellant and not
			<lb />
			between the appellant and the respondent.
			<lb />
			Sir Richard Couch did not intend and could
			<lb />
			not have intended that any decision affecting
			<lb />
			the rights of a party against which the Court
			<lb />
			has made an order could not be a `judgment&apos;
			<lb />
			merely because there was no other party to
			<lb />
			those particular proceedings.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			.....
			<lb />
			.....
			<lb />
			.....
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			23. The expression &quot;judgment&quot; was examined by the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court in the case of Hanskumar Kishan Chand
			<lb />
			v. The Union of India, AIR 1958 SC 947. The Supreme
			<lb />
			Court while dealing with the powers of Federal Court
			<lb />
			specifically held that the word `judgment&apos; used in
			<lb />
			section 2(b) would be a judgment, decree or order of a
			<lb />
			High Court in civil case and an order under Defence of
			<lb />
			India Act would not be a judgment, decree or order
			<lb />
			and, thus, leave to appeal could not be granted.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			24. In the case of Shah Babulal Khimji v. Jayaben D.
			<lb />
			Kania and another, (1981) 4 SCC 8, the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court spelt out the guidelines and illustrations in
			<lb />
			regard to the Letters Patent clause 15 of the Bombay
			<lb />
			High Court and appeals which could be maintained
			<lb />
			before the Division Bench against the judgment. The
			<lb />
			court also explained the phrase `judgment&apos;. While
			<lb />
			including some of the interlocutory orders within the
			<lb />
			ambit of the judgment, the Court stated that it should
			<lb />
			receive a much wider and liberal interpretation than
			<lb />
			the word `judgment&apos; used in Civil Procedure Code.
			<lb />
			The court clearly stated the dictum that it cannot be
			<lb />
			said that every order passed by the trial Judge would
			<lb />
			amount to judgment.
			<lb />
			It seems that the word
			<lb />
			&quot;judgment&quot; has undoubtedly a concept of finality in a
			<lb />
			broader and not a narrower sense. The court held that
			<lb />
			an order even though it keeps the suit alive but still
			<lb />
			decides an important aspect of the trial and which
			<lb />
			affects the vital right of the defendants would be liable
			<lb />
			to be construed as judgment.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			25. The Supreme Court in its earlier judgments and
			<lb />
			reference can be made to the case of Nachiappa
			<lb />
			Chettiar and others v. Subramaniam Chettiar, AIR 1960
			<lb />
			SC 307, wherein the Apex court held that the word
			<lb />
			&quot;judgment&quot; cannot refer to the various interlocutory
			<lb />
			orders and judgments that may be passed during the
			<lb />
			hearing of the suit and so the word &quot;judgment&quot; cannot
			<lb />
			be given the meaning assigned to it by Section 2(9) of
			<lb />
			the Civil Procedure Code. It cannot mean in the
			<lb />
			context the statement given by the Judge of the
			<lb />
			grounds of a decree or order. It must mean a
			<lb />
			judgment which finally decides all matters in
			<lb />
			controversy in the suit. Similar view has been
			<lb />
			expressed by the Supreme Court in Shri Radhey Shyam
			<lb />
			v. Shyam Behari Singh, 1970(2) SCC 405.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			.....
			<lb />
			.....
			<lb />
			.....
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			28.
			<lb />
			Judgment by the court is an affirmation of a
			<lb />
			relation between the particular predicate and a
			<lb />
			particular subject. It is always a declaration that a
			<lb />
			liability, recognised as within the jural sphere, does or
			<lb />
			does not exist. A judgment, as the culmination of the
			<lb />
			action, declares the existence of the right, recognises
			<lb />
			the commission of the injury, or negatives the
			<lb />
			allegation of one or the other. [(Gurdit Singh and
			<lb />
			others v. State of Punjab and others, (1974) 2 SCC 260]
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			29.
			<lb />
			The principles which emerge from the
			<lb />
			consistent view taken by the Courts including the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court is, there has to be a conscious
			<lb />
			determination of rights and liabilities between the
			<lb />
			parties to a lis before the court of competent
			<lb />
			jurisdiction.
			<lb />
			Undisputedly, contempt is a matter
			<lb />
			primarily between the Court and the contemnor. The
			<lb />
			proceedings of Contempt of Court would be initiated
			<lb />
			against the contemnor through any of the specified
			<lb />
			modes with or without consent of the specified
			<lb />
			authorities depending on the facts and circumstances
			<lb />
			of each case. The contempt jurisdiction vested in the
			<lb />
			Court by development of law as well as under the
			<lb />
			statutory provision is very wide and is of pervasive
			<lb />
			magnitude. A party to the proceedings before the
			<lb />
			court may bring to the notice of the Court any matter
			<lb />
			which invites the attention of the Court for taking any
			<lb />
			action under the provisions of the Contempt of Courts
			<lb />
			Act. Once such act is done, the matter squarely falls in
			<lb />
			the exclusive domain of the Court of competent
			<lb />
			jurisdiction, as the purpose of contempt jurisdiction is
			<lb />
			primarily to ensure enforcement of the order of the
			<lb />
			court and to maintain the dignity of the judicial
			<lb />
			administrative system. The contempt proceedings per
			<lb />
			se are not taken or declined for the benefit or interest
			<lb />
			of the individual party. When the court passes an
			<lb />
			order of discharge or holds that no case for contempt
			<lb />
			of Court is made out and declines to take action, no
			<lb />
			right or interest of the parties to the lis are determined
			<lb />
			by the court much less finally. Such an order besides
			<lb />
			being not appealable on the bare reading of the
			<lb />
			provisions of section 19 of the Contempt of Courts Act,
			<lb />
			would also not be a judgment within the meaning of
			<lb />
			clause 15 of the Letters Patent and as such, not
			<lb />
			appealable. The provisions of section 19 of the Act are
			<lb />
			not ambiguous and do not leave any scope for addition
			<lb />
			or substitution of a word. Definite legislative intent is
			<lb />
			clear that right to appeal shall only be available in the
			<lb />
			cases where there is an order of punishment. The
			<lb />
			matter primarily and substantially being between the
			<lb />
			court and the contemnor , parties to the lis cannot be
			<lb />
			permitted to raise issues or litigate on the view of the
			<lb />
			court that a case of contempt is made out or not.
			<lb />
			Where the court in exercise of its judicial discretion
			<lb />
			and keeping in mind the well settled principles of
			<lb />
			contempt jurisdiction finds that contempt proceedings
			<lb />
			need not be initiated, or no contempt is made out or
			<lb />
			discharges the contemnor on merits of the case, the
			<lb />
			appeal before the Division Bench even with the aid of
			<lb />
			clause 15 of the Letters Patent would not be
			<lb />
			maintainable. In the present case, the learned Single
			<lb />
			Judge has concluded, as already noticed, that the
			<lb />
			petitioners themselves are not sure as to which of the
			<lb />
			contemnors are allowed to use the Welfare Centre and
			<lb />
			while taking an overall view of the matter held that
			<lb />
			this was not a fit case where action under the
			<lb />
			Contempt of Courts Act can be taken. This order of the
			<lb />
			learned Single Judge, in our opinion, is not appealable
			<lb />
			in view of the unambiguous language of section 19 of
			<lb />
			the Contempt of Courts Act and an appeal is not
			<lb />
			maintainable even under clause 15 of the Letters
			<lb />
			Patent. Although we have no hesitation in rejecting
			<lb />
			this appeal as being not maintainable, in the facts and
			<lb />
			circumstances of this case, Parties are left to bear their
			<lb />
			own cost.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			46.
			<lb />
			Another facet of right of appeal under this clause is that
			<lb />
			the provisions of clause 15 are subject to legislative powers of the
			<lb />
			Governor-General in Legislative Council and also of the Governor-
			<lb />
			General in Council under Section 71 of the Government of India Act,
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			1915. Clause 44 of the Letters Patent specifically contemplates that
			<lb />
			the provisions of Letters Patent are subject to the exercise of legislative
			<lb />
			powers by the competent legislature. In other words, Clause 15 of the
			<lb />
			Letters Patent does not confer an absolute or unqualified right to
			<lb />
			appeal. This remedy is subject to the other laws enacted by competent
			<lb />
			Legislature. Viewed from that angle, the restrictions contemplated
			<lb />
			under Section 100-A of the Code of Civil Procedure would be a
			<lb />
			relevant consideration which would control right of appeal as
			<lb />
			envisaged under Clause 15 of the Letters Patent.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			47.
			<lb />
			Clause 12 of Letters Patent is an independent clause which
			<lb />
			relates to the exercise of ordinary original jurisdiction in suits by this
			<lb />
			Courts. The orders which are passed by the High Court in exercise of
			<lb />
			its original jurisdiction would be apparently covered under clause 12
			<lb />
			of the Letters Patent but of course to the limitation stated in the
			<lb />
			provision itself. But, in the present case, jurisdiction under Clause 12
			<lb />
			is not a relevant consideration to answer the questions of law posed
			<lb />
			before us.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			48.
			<lb />
			In Shah Babulal Khimji&apos;s case (supra), the Supreme Court ,
			<lb />
			while explaining the ingredients of a judgment, held that Section 104
			<lb />
			with Order XLIII Rule 1 of the Code of Civil Procedure is neither
			<lb />
			inconsistent, nor override, nor controls clause 15 of the Letters Patent.
			<lb />
			The judgment was in relation to the orders passed by the learned
			<lb />
			Single Judge of this Court in exercise of its original jurisdiction.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			49.
			<lb />
			Similar view was also expressed by the Supreme Court in
			<lb />
			Vinita M. Khanolkar&apos;s case (supra) where the Court held that the order
			<lb />
			passed by the learned Single Judge in the proceedings under Section 6
			<lb />
			of the Specific Reliefs Act would be appealable under Clause 15 of the
			<lb />
			Letters patent. The Courts stated the principle that the powers of the
			<lb />
			appellate court and right provided under the provision to appeal can
			<lb />
			be excluded by a statute expressly and it cannot be excluded by
			<lb />
			juridical provision barring the appeal.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			50.
			<lb />
			We will shortly proceed to discuss the effect of provision of
			<lb />
			Section 100-A of the Code of Civil Procedure where the Legislature has
			<lb />
			specifically used non obstante language with particular reference to
			<lb />
			letters patent.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			INTERPRETATION OF STATUTES : * *
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			51.
			<lb />
			A statute is stated to be a will of the Legislature.
			<lb />
			It
			<lb />
			expresses a will of the Legislature, and function of the Court is to
			<lb />
			interpret the document, according to the intent of them that made it.
			<lb />
			It is a settled rule of construction of statute that the provisions should
			<lb />
			be interpreted with application of plain rule of construction. The
			<lb />
			courts normally would not imply anything in them which is
			<lb />
			inconsistent with the words expressly used by the statute. In other
			<lb />
			words, the Court would keep in mind that its function is jus dicere, not
			<lb />
			jus dare. The right of appeal being creation of a statute and being a
			<lb />
			statutory right does not invite unnecessary liberal or strict
			<lb />
			construction. The best norm would be to give literal construction
			<lb />
			keeping the legislative intent in mind.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			52.
			<lb />
			The Supreme Court in the case of Shiv Shakti Co-op.
			<lb />
			Housing Society, Nagpur vs Swaraj Developers and Others, reported in
			<lb />
			(2003) 6 SCC 659, while referring to the principles for interpretation of
			<lb />
			statutory provisions, held as under: -
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;19. It is a well-settled principle in law that the court
			<lb />
			cannot read anything into a statutory provision which
			<lb />
			is plain and unambiguous. A statute is an edict of the
			<lb />
			legislature. The language employed in a statute is the
			<lb />
			determinative factor of legislative intent. Words and
			<lb />
			phrases are symbols that stimulate mental references to
			<lb />
			referents. The object of interpreting a statute is to
			<lb />
			ascertain the intention of the legislature enacting it.
			<lb />
			(See Institute of Chartered Accountants of India v. Price
			<lb />
			Waterhouse.)
			<lb />
			The intention of the legislature is
			<lb />
			primarily to be gathered from the language used,
			<lb />
			which means that attention should be paid to what has
			<lb />
			been said as also to what has not been said. As a
			<lb />
			consequence, a construction which requires for its
			<lb />
			support, addition or substitution of words or which
			<lb />
			results in rejection of words as meaningless has to be
			<lb />
			avoided. As observed in Crawford v. Spooner courts
			<lb />
			cannot aid the legislatures&apos; defective phrasing of an
			<lb />
			Act, we cannot add or mend, and by construction make
			<lb />
			up deficiencies which are left there. (See State of
			<lb />
			Gujarat v. Dilipbhai Nathjibhai Patel ). It is contrary to
			<lb />
			all rules of construction to read words into an Act
			<lb />
			unless it is absolutely necessary to do so. [ See Stock v.
			<lb />
			Frank Jones (Tipton) Ltd. ] Rules of interpretation do
			<lb />
			not permit courts to do so, unless the provision as it
			<lb />
			stands is meaningless or of a doubtful meaning. Courts
			<lb />
			are not entitled to read words into an Act of Parliament
			<lb />
			unless clear reason for it is to be found within the four
			<lb />
			corners of the Act itself. ( Per Lord Loreburn, L.C. In
			<lb />
			Vickers Sons and Maxim Ltd. v. Evans, quoted in Jumma
			<lb />
			Masjid v. Kodimaniandra Deviah.)&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			53.
			<lb />
			The Law Commission of India, in its 183 rd Report, while
			<lb />
			dealing with the need for providing principles of interpretation of
			<lb />
			statute as regards the extrinsic aids of interpretation in General
			<lb />
			Clauses Act, 1897 expressed the view that a statute is a will of
			<lb />
			legislature conveyed in the form of text. Noticing that process of
			<lb />
			interpretation is as old as language, it says that the rules of
			<lb />
			interpretation were evolved even at a very early stage of Hindu
			<lb />
			civilization and culture and the same were given by `Jaimini&apos;, the
			<lb />
			author of Mimamsat Sutras, originally meant for srutis were employed
			<lb />
			for the interpretation of Smrities also. While referring to the said
			<lb />
			historical background, the Commission said thus: -
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;It is well settled principle of law that as the statute is
			<lb />
			an edict of the Legislature, the conventional way of
			<lb />
			interpreting or construing a statute is to seek the
			<lb />
			intention of legislature. The intention of legislature
			<lb />
			assimilates two aspects; one aspect carries the concept
			<lb />
			of `meaning&apos;, i.e., what the word means and another
			<lb />
			aspect conveys the concept of `purpose&apos; and `object&apos; or
			<lb />
			the `reason&apos; or `spirit&apos; pervading through the statute.
			<lb />
			The process of construction, therefore, combines both
			<lb />
			the literal and purposive approaches.
			<lb />
			However,
			<lb />
			necessity of interpretation would arise only where the
			<lb />
			language of a statutory provision is ambiguous, not
			<lb />
			clear or where two views are possible or where the
			<lb />
			provision gives a different meaning defeating the
			<lb />
			object of the statute. If the language is clear and
			<lb />
			unambiguous, no need of interpretation would arise.
			<lb />
			In this regard, a Constitution Bench of five Judges of
			<lb />
			the Supreme Court in R.S. Nayak v. A.R. Antulay, AIR
			<lb />
			1984 SC 684 has held:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;.....If the words of the Statute are clear and
			<lb />
			unambiguous, it is the plainest duty of the
			<lb />
			Court to give effect to the natural meaning of
			<lb />
			the words used in the provision.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			question of construction arises only in the
			<lb />
			event of an ambiguity or the plain meaning of
			<lb />
			the words used in the Statute would be self
			<lb />
			defeating.&quot;
			<lb />
			Recently, again Supreme Court in Grasim Industries
			<lb />
			Ltd. v. Collector of Customs, Bombay, (2002)4 SCC
			<lb />
			297 has followed the same principle and observed:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;Where the words are clear and there is no
			<lb />
			obscurity, and there is no ambiguity and the
			<lb />
			intention of the legislature is clearly conveyed,
			<lb />
			there is no scope for court to take upon itself
			<lb />
			the task of amending or altering the statutory
			<lb />
			provisions.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			54.
			<lb />
			Above stated principles clearly show that the Court can
			<lb />
			safely apply rudiments of plain construction to legislative intent and
			<lb />
			object sought to be achieved by the enactment while interpreting the
			<lb />
			provision of an Act. It is not necessary for the Court to implant or
			<lb />
			exclude words or over emphasize the language of a provision where it
			<lb />
			is plain and simple. We have already noticed that Section 100-A
			<lb />
			opens with a non obstante clause and clause 44 of the Letters Patent
			<lb />
			refers to the aspect that the letters patent would be read in community
			<lb />
			with the legislative enactment.
			<lb />
			A clause beginning with
			<lb />
			`notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time
			<lb />
			being in force including the Letters Patent&apos; normally would show the
			<lb />
			intent and the view of the Legislature enacting part of the section to
			<lb />
			give overriding effect over the provision of that Act or other laws in
			<lb />
			case of conflict.
			<lb />
			The enactment following it will have its full
			<lb />
			operation or that the provisions embraced in the non obstante clause
			<lb />
			will not be an impediment for the operation of the enactment. In the
			<lb />
			case of Union of India &amp; Anr. v. G.M. Kokil &amp; Ors., reported in
			<lb />
			1984(Supp) SCC 196, the Supreme Court observed thus:-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;A non obstante clause is a legislative device which is
			<lb />
			usually employed to give overriding effect to certain
			<lb />
			provisions over some contrary provisions that may be
			<lb />
			found either in the same enactment or some other
			<lb />
			enactment, that is to say, to avoid the operation and
			<lb />
			effect of all contrary provisions.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			55.
			<lb />
			The above observations have also been reiterated by the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court in the case of Pannalal Bansilal Patil v. State of Andhra
			<lb />
			Pradesh, reported in AIR 1996 SC 1023 and in the case of T.R.
			<lb />
			Thandur v. Union of India, reported in AIR 1996 SC 1643. Of course,
			<lb />
			a non obstante clause has to be distinguished from the phrase &quot;without
			<lb />
			prejudice&quot;. A provision enacted &quot;without prejudice&quot; to another
			<lb />
			provision does not have the effect of affecting the operation of the
			<lb />
			other provision and any action taken under it must not be inconsistent
			<lb />
			with other provision. It is also to be kept in mind that the wide
			<lb />
			meaning of non obstante clause and the enacting words following it
			<lb />
			cannot be curtailed when the use of wide language accords with the
			<lb />
			object by the Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			56.
			<lb />
			While dealing with interpretation of statutes regulating
			<lb />
			appeals the treatise of principles of statutory interpretation by Justice
			<lb />
			G.P. Singh ( 11 th Edition 2008) explains:-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;An appeal is the &quot;right of entering a superior court
			<lb />
			and invoking its aid and interposition to redress an
			<lb />
			error of the court below&quot; and &quot;though procedure does
			<lb />
			surround an appeal the central idea is a right&quot;. The
			<lb />
			right of appeal has been recognised by judicial
			<lb />
			decisions as a right which vests in a suitor at the time
			<lb />
			of institution of original proceedings. Any change in
			<lb />
			the law relating to appeals, after institution of original
			<lb />
			proceedings, which adversely touches this vested right
			<lb />
			is presumed not to be retrospective.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			57.
			<lb />
			In the case of A.G. Varadarajulu &amp; Anr. vs State of T.N. &amp;
			<lb />
			Ors., reported in (1998) 4 SCC 231, the Supreme Court held as
			<lb />
			under: -
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;16. It is well settled that while dealing with a non
			<lb />
			obstante clause under which the legislature wants to
			<lb />
			give overriding effect to a section, the court must try to
			<lb />
			find out the extent to which the legislature had
			<lb />
			intended to give one provision overriding effect over
			<lb />
			another provision. Such intention of the legislature in
			<lb />
			this behalf is to be gathered from the enacting part of
			<lb />
			the section. In Aswini Kumar Ghose v. Arabinda Bose,
			<lb />
			reported in AIR 1952 SC 369, Patanjali Sastri, J
			<lb />
			observed:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;The enacting part of a statute must, where it
			<lb />
			is clear, be taken to control the non obstante
			<lb />
			clause where both cannot be read
			<lb />
			harmoniously.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			58.
			<lb />
			In the case of Iridium India Telecom Ltd. vs Motorola Inc.,
			<lb />
			reported in (2005) 2 SCC 145, the Supreme Court, while relying
			<lb />
			upon the judgment of the of the Constitution Bench in the case of P.S.
			<lb />
			Sathappan vs Andhra Bank Ltd., reported in (2004) 11 SCC 672 did
			<lb />
			not accept the contention that the provision of superior legislation viz.
			<lb />
			Code of Civil Procedure would override the provision of the Letters
			<lb />
			Patent but clearly noticed firstly that there was no conflict between
			<lb />
			Section 104 of the Code of Civil Procedure and the Letters Patent and
			<lb />
			they could be harmoniously interpreted and permitted to operate in
			<lb />
			their field but specifically approved earlier view that once there was
			<lb />
			specific exclusion the provisions of Letters Patent would be overridden
			<lb />
			by the provisions of the Code. This was with reference to the
			<lb />
			language of Section 4 of the Code. Once there was specific provision
			<lb />
			to the contrary applicability of the special law could be excluded. It
			<lb />
			categorically specified and referred view of constitution bench in P.S.
			<lb />
			Sattapan&apos;s (supra) that the specific provisions of this kind would
			<lb />
			be a provision like Section 100-A of the Code.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			59.
			<lb />
			On the clear analysis and application of judicial
			<lb />
			interpretative process, it is clear that Section 100-A of the Code of
			<lb />
			Civil Procedure and the Clause 15 of the Letters Patent would have to
			<lb />
			be construed on their plain reading and without any conflict.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			DISCUSSION ON MERITS :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			60.
			<lb />
			The factual matrix of the case has already been stated by
			<lb />
			us above. Suffice it to note that the present appeals have been filed
			<lb />
			after coming into force a provision of Section 100-A of the Code of
			<lb />
			Civil Procedure (i.e. 1 st July, 2002). All these appeals have been
			<lb />
			preferred against the judgment of the learned Single Judge passed in
			<lb />
			exercise of its appellate jurisdiction. The appeals before the learned
			<lb />
			Single Judge were preferred in terms of Section 173 of the Motor
			<lb />
			Vehicles Act and were accordingly decided by the learned Single
			<lb />
			Judge vide judgments dated 12 th February, 2004 and 25 th January,
			<lb />
			2005. There is undoubtedly no provision contained in the M.V. Act
			<lb />
			which gives right to appeal to any dissatisfied litigant to prefer an
			<lb />
			appeal against the appellate judgment of the learned Single Judge. In
			<lb />
			other words, special statute does not provide any right of second
			<lb />
			appeal against the judgment of the appellate court. The Tribunal
			<lb />
			certainly has trappings of a civil court, may be, it is not a civil court in
			<lb />
			stricto senso. Once the special law and even the M.V. Act which is
			<lb />
			treated to be a self-contained Code, and which do not provide for a
			<lb />
			grant of specific right of second appeal, the same cannot be made
			<lb />
			available by a recourse to any general provision.
			<lb />
			It is an
			<lb />
			unquestionable proposition of law that right of appeal is a statutory
			<lb />
			right and not a general, natural, or a fundamental right. In the
			<lb />
			absence of any provision granting such statutory right to prefer second
			<lb />
			appeal, the litigant cannot be permitted to rely upon the general
			<lb />
			provisions, if at all there is any, to prefer a second appeal. The award
			<lb />
			made by the Motor Accident Claims Tribunal under Section 168 of the
			<lb />
			Act even if it is treated as a decree and so is the judgment of the
			<lb />
			learned Single Judge passed in appeal, still the Court would not be
			<lb />
			able to take recourse to general provision of the Code and for that
			<lb />
			matter, it will hardly be of any consequence as to whether the
			<lb />
			proceedings before the Tribunal are at parity with the civil court or
			<lb />
			actual proceedings are before the civil court. Non availability of right
			<lb />
			of appeal under the statute would be a complete answer to non-
			<lb />
			maintainable of such an appeal.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			61.
			<lb />
			Section 173 of the Motor Vehicles Act provides only for a
			<lb />
			restricted right of appeal and the same cannot be stretched by
			<lb />
			interpretative process to hold that even a second appeal or an appeal
			<lb />
			against the appellate jurisdiction of the Single Judge would be
			<lb />
			maintainable. This would obviously be an interpretation which would
			<lb />
			neither further the cause of the Legislation nor it will be true on the
			<lb />
			plain reading of the Section.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			62.
			<lb />
			We have already noticed that the Tribunal has the
			<lb />
			trapping of a Civil Court and various procedural and effective
			<lb />
			provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure have been made applicable
			<lb />
			substantially to the proceeding before the Tribunal. After the Award is
			<lb />
			passed by the Tribunal, an Appeal under Section 173 is maintainable
			<lb />
			before the High Court and the High Court would exercise its appellate
			<lb />
			jurisdiction arising from a statute with the help of the provisions of the
			<lb />
			Code of Civil Procedure. Section 100A was introduced by the
			<lb />
			Legislature with a specific object. The object being to curtail the right
			<lb />
			of Second Appeal and attach finality to the judgment of the first
			<lb />
			appellate Court in normal course of law. That is the reason why the
			<lb />
			Legislature has specifically worded Section 100A while opening the
			<lb />
			Section with a non-obstante clause and provided over-riding effect
			<lb />
			over the provisions of Letters Patent, other law and even other
			<lb />
			instrument having the force of law. The intent of the Legislature to
			<lb />
			provide precedence to enforcement of Section 100A is patently clear
			<lb />
			from the unambiguous and definite language of Section 100A. We
			<lb />
			must notice here that both the Motor Vehicles Act and the Code of
			<lb />
			Civil Procedure are Central enactments. No State amendment has
			<lb />
			been carried by the State of Maharashtra to dilute or alter the effect of
			<lb />
			the language of either Section 173 of the Motor Vehicles Act or
			<lb />
			Section 100A of the CPC. The Legislature was fully aware of the
			<lb />
			provisions of Section 173 as well as of the Letters Patent when it
			<lb />
			introduced Section 100A which came into force on 1 st July 2002. Once
			<lb />
			the Legislature , being aware of the existing law, has worded Section
			<lb />
			100A in specific terms, then it has to be given its natural and effective
			<lb />
			meaning. The Court while construing these provisions by applying the
			<lb />
			principles of harmonious construction or otherwise, cannot frustrate
			<lb />
			the object of provisions of Section 100A which has been given over-
			<lb />
			riding effect by use of non-obstante clause and with specific exclusion
			<lb />
			of other laws. Clause 15 of the Letters Patent thus would have to be
			<lb />
			read in conjunction with Clause 44 of the said Letters Patent and
			<lb />
			Section 100A of the CPC that too in light of the language of Section
			<lb />
			173 of the Motor Vehicles Act. The cumulative reading and analysis of
			<lb />
			these provisions in consonance with the Rules of interpretation stated
			<lb />
			above, would lead to simple and one conclusion that the Letters Patent
			<lb />
			appeal or an appeal against the judgment of the learned Single Judge
			<lb />
			passed in exercise of its appellate jurisdiction against the appellate
			<lb />
			judgment passed by the Court subordinate to the High Court, would
			<lb />
			not be appealable. Where Section 100A constitutes a complete bar
			<lb />
			against right to prefer an appeal against an appellate decision, there
			<lb />
			appeal cannot be preferred with the aid of Clause 15 of the Letters
			<lb />
			Patent against such judgment.
			<lb />
			Thus, either way, the obvious
			<lb />
			conclusion would be that no intra-Court appeal is maintainable in the
			<lb />
			High Court against the judgment passed by the learned Single Judge
			<lb />
			in exercise of its appellate powers in terms of Section 173 of the Motor
			<lb />
			Vehicles Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			63.
			<lb />
			Another aspect which would support the view which we
			<lb />
			are taking is that the whole object of introducing Section 100A was to
			<lb />
			curtail litigation by regulating the right of appeal. Attempt obviously
			<lb />
			is to attach finality to the judgment of the learned Single Judge of the
			<lb />
			High Court particularly where he has passed the judgment while
			<lb />
			exercising appellate jurisdiction of the High Court. Where the
			<lb />
			judgment of the Tribunal and the learned Single Judge is treated as a
			<lb />
			judgment within the meaning of Clause 15 of the Letters Patent or not
			<lb />
			or under the of the Code of Civil Procedure, would hardly
			<lb />
			make any difference on the conclusion inasmuch as even against an
			<lb />
			order of the Single Judge in exercise of appellate jurisdiction, a further
			<lb />
			appeal is prohibited in terms of Section 100A. The Legislative object
			<lb />
			of regulating the right of appeal and rendering Second Appeal from
			<lb />
			appellate order or judgment impermissible would stand defeated by
			<lb />
			any other interpretation. The rule of mischief contemplates that what
			<lb />
			remedy the Parliament resolved and attempted to cure the disease
			<lb />
			should be permitted to operate rather than the same be defeated by
			<lb />
			process of interpretation. The Court while performing its function of
			<lb />
			interpretation of law would make such construction as shall suppress
			<lb />
			the mischief and advance the remedy and to suppress subtle
			<lb />
			inventions and evasions for continuance of the mischief and pro
			<lb />
			privato commodo. The mischief which is sought to be controlled and
			<lb />
			avoided by the Legislature is not to grant repeated right of appeal and
			<lb />
			to introduce the concept of finality to the appellate judgment, decree
			<lb />
			or order. The provisions of the Motor Vehicles Act do not recognise
			<lb />
			an appeal from an appellate jurisdiction of the High Court passed
			<lb />
			under Section 173 of the Motor Vehicles Act. On the contrary, Section
			<lb />
			100A specifically bars filing of an appeal against such judgment. The
			<lb />
			provisions of Section 100-A have a precedence and take limited
			<lb />
			exception to the provisions of Clause 15 of the Letters Patent. On
			<lb />
			plain reading of Clause 15 of the Letters Patent, an appeal to a
			<lb />
			Division Bench of the High Court from the judgment of the learned
			<lb />
			Single Judge passed while deciding an appeal against the appellate
			<lb />
			judgment, and decree or order passed by the Court of competent
			<lb />
			jurisdiction subordinate to the High Court would not be maintainable.
			<lb />
			The only exception to this general rule is that where the learned Single
			<lb />
			Judge grants a certificate of fitness as contemplated under the
			<lb />
			language of Clause 15 of the Letters Patent. This we have noticed only
			<lb />
			to elucidate the point that Clause 15 will have to be read with Clause
			<lb />
			the Code of Civil Procedure. The cumulative reading of all these
			<lb />
			provisions would thus show that Clause 15 of the Letters Patent
			<lb />
			cannot be treated as a provision granting independent right of appeal
			<lb />
			de hors the other relevant provisions noticed by us in this judgment.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			64.
			<lb />
			The Supreme Court in the case of P S Sathappan (supra)
			<lb />
			clearly stated while referring to Clause 44 of the Letters Patent that
			<lb />
			provisions of Letters Patent were subject to legislative powers of the
			<lb />
			Governor-General-in-Legislative Council and, therefore, in the present-
			<lb />
			day context, subject to legislative power of the appropriate legislature.
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied).
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			65.
			<lb />
			Now we would refer to the judgments, some of which
			<lb />
			were relied upon by either party before us in support and against the
			<lb />
			proposition formulated at the beginning of this judgment.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			66.
			<lb />
			In the case of Kamal Kumar Dutta (supra), the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court was dealing with Sections 397 and 398 of the Companies Act
			<lb />
			and while holding that an appeal against an order made by the
			<lb />
			Company Law Board under Section 10E was maintainable before the
			<lb />
			High Court under Section 10F and after referring to the pre-
			<lb />
			amendment provisions held that no appeal was maintainable against
			<lb />
			the order of the learned Single Judge passed in appeal in face of
			<lb />
			Section 100A and despite the language of Clause 15 of the Letters
			<lb />
			Patent of the Calcutta High Court and held as under :-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;16. Appeal lies under Letters Patent from the
			<lb />
			judgment of the learned Single Judge of the High Court
			<lb />
			to the Division bench. In this connection, learned
			<lb />
			counsel placed reliance on a decision of this Court in
			<lb />
			the case of Garikapatti Veeraya vs N Subbiah
			<lb />
			Choudhury reported in 1957 SCR 488 and submitted
			<lb />
			that the appeal is vested right and it cannot be taken
			<lb />
			away. Alternative submission was if clause 15 does not
			<lb />
			apply, appeal lies under Section 483 of the Act. In this
			<lb />
			connection reliance was placed on decisions of this
			<lb />
			Court in the case of Arati Dutta vs M/s Eastern Tea
			<lb />
			Estate (P) Ltd reported in (1988) 1 SCC 523 and the in
			<lb />
			the case of Maharashtra Power Development
			<lb />
			Corporation Limited vs DabholPower Company &amp; Ors.,
			<lb />
			reported in (2003) 117 Company Cases 651. As against
			<lb />
			this, learned senior counsel for the appellants
			<lb />
			submitted that Section 10F of the Act came into being
			<lb />
			with effect from 31.5.1991. Prior to that application
			<lb />
			under Sections 397 and 398 of the Act was being filed
			<lb />
			with the Company Judge in the High Court. But after
			<lb />
			the amendment of the Act by Act 31 of 1988, this
			<lb />
			power under Sections 397 &amp; 398 of the Act has been
			<lb />
			given to the CLB. Under Section 10E of the Act, the
			<lb />
			Company Law Board was created. It deals with
			<lb />
			applications under Sections 397 and 398 of the Act.
			<lb />
			Therefore, learned Single Judge has not exercised
			<lb />
			original jurisdiction and as such the appeal
			<lb />
			contemplated under clause 15 of the Letters Patent is
			<lb />
			not maintainable. Learned senior counsel invited our
			<lb />
			attention to Section 100A of the Code of Civil
			<lb />
			Procedure which came into being with effect from
			<lb />
			1.7.2002. This section starts with non-obstante clause
			<lb />
			that notwithstanding anything contained in any Letters
			<lb />
			Patent for any High Court or in any other instrument
			<lb />
			having the force of law or in any other law for the time
			<lb />
			being in force, where any appeal from an original or
			<lb />
			appellate decree or order is heard and decided by a
			<lb />
			single Judge of a High Court, no further appeal shall lie
			<lb />
			from the judgment and decree of such single Judge.
			<lb />
			Therefore, it was pointed out that in view of the latest
			<lb />
			amendment in the Code of Civil Procedure, Letters
			<lb />
			Patent or intra court appeal will not lie when the
			<lb />
			learned Single Judge has exercised appellate
			<lb />
			jurisdiction. In fact, this amendment seems to have
			<lb />
			been brought about on the recommendations of the
			<lb />
			Malimath Committee report that right to appeal should
			<lb />
			be curtained and only one appellate forum should be
			<lb />
			available. Therefore, in view of this recommendations,
			<lb />
			this amendment was brought about. In support of this
			<lb />
			contention learned senior counsel invited our attention
			<lb />
			to the following decisions.
			<lb />
			(i) (2004) 11 SCC 672 ( P.S. Sathappan (dead) by
			<lb />
			Lrs Vs. Andhra Bank Ltd. &amp; Ors.)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii) (2003) 10 SCC 361 (Subal Paul vs Malina Paul &amp;
			<lb />
			Anr.)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) AIR 2003 AP 458 (Gandla Pannala Bhulaxmi vs.
			<lb />
			Managing Director, APSRTC &amp; Anr.)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iv) (1987) 62 Company Cases 504 (Rev. C.S. Joseph
			<lb />
			&amp; Ors. vs. T.J. Thomas &amp; Ors.)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(v) AIR 2004 Ker. 111 (Kesava Pillai Sreedharan
			<lb />
			Pillai &amp; etc. vs. State of Kerala &amp; Ors.)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			17. We have considered the rival submissions of the
			<lb />
			parties. The first question that we have to examine is
			<lb />
			whether the appeal against the order of the learned
			<lb />
			Single Judge lies before the Division Bench under
			<lb />
			Letters Patent or not. It may be relevant to mention
			<lb />
			here that prior to the amendment of the Act, the power
			<lb />
			under Sections 397 &amp; 398 used to be exercised by the
			<lb />
			Company Judge of the High Court. Appeal against that
			<lb />
			order of the learned Single Judge lies under Section
			<lb />
			483 of the Act before the Division Bench of the High
			<lb />
			Court. Section 483 of the Act reads as under :
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;483. Appeals from orders -Appeals from any
			<lb />
			order made or decision given before the
			<lb />
			commencement
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Companies
			<lb />
			(Second
			<lb />
			Amendment) Act, 2002, in the matter of the winding
			<lb />
			up of a company by the Court shall lie to the same
			<lb />
			Court to which, in the same manner in which, and
			<lb />
			subject to the same conditions under which, appeals
			<lb />
			lie from any order or decision of the Court in cases
			<lb />
			within its ordinary jurisdiction.
			<lb />
			But after the amendment the power which was being
			<lb />
			exercised under Sections 397 &amp; 398 of the Act by
			<lb />
			learned Single Judge of the High Court is being
			<lb />
			exercised by the CLB under Section 10E of the Act.
			<lb />
			Appeal against the order passed by the CLB, lies to the
			<lb />
			High Court under Section 10F of the Act. Therefore,
			<lb />
			the position which was obtaining prior to the
			<lb />
			amendment in 1991 was that any order passed by the
			<lb />
			Single Judge exercising the power under Sections 397
			<lb />
			&amp; 398 of the Act, the appeal used to lie before the
			<lb />
			Division Bench of the High Court. But after the
			<lb />
			amendment the power has been given to the CLB and
			<lb />
			the appeal has been provided under Section 10F of the
			<lb />
			Act. Thus Part 1A was inserted by the amendment with
			<lb />
			effect from 1.1.1964. But the constitution of the
			<lb />
			Company Law Board and the power to decide
			<lb />
			application under Sections 397 &amp; 398 of the Act was
			<lb />
			given to the CLB with effect from 31.5.1991. Therefore,
			<lb />
			on reading of Sections 10E, 10F, 397 &amp; 398 of the Act,
			<lb />
			it becomes clear that it is a complete code that
			<lb />
			applications under sections 397 &amp; 398 of the Act shall
			<lb />
			be dealt with by the CLB and the order of the CLB is
			<lb />
			appealable under Section 10F of the Act before the
			<lb />
			High Court. No further appeal has been provided
			<lb />
			against the order of the learned Single Judge. Mr.
			<lb />
			Nariman, learned senior counsel for the respondents
			<lb />
			submitted that an appeal is a vested right and
			<lb />
			therefore, under clause 15 of the Letters Patent of the
			<lb />
			Calcutta High Court, the appellants have a statutory
			<lb />
			right to prefer appeal irrespective of the fact that no
			<lb />
			appeal has been provided against the order of the
			<lb />
			learned Single Judge under the Act. In this connection,
			<lb />
			learned counsel invited our attention to a decision of
			<lb />
			this Court in the case of Garikapatti Veeraya vs. N
			<lb />
			Subbiah Choudhury reported in (1957) SCR SCR 488
			<lb />
			and in that it has been pointed out that the appeal is a
			<lb />
			vested right. The majority took the view that the
			<lb />
			appeal is a vested right. It was held as follows :
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;... that the contention of the appellant was well-
			<lb />
			founded, that he had a vested right of appeal to the
			<lb />
			Federal Court on and from the date of the suit and the
			<lb />
			application for special leave should be allowed.
			<lb />
			The vested right of appeal was a substantive right
			<lb />
			and, although it could be exercised only in case of an
			<lb />
			adverse decision, it was governed by the law prevailing
			<lb />
			at the time of commencement of the suit and
			<lb />
			comprised all successive rights of appeal from court to
			<lb />
			court, which really constituted one proceeding. Such a
			<lb />
			right could be taken away only by a subsequent
			<lb />
			enactment either expressly or by necessary
			<lb />
			intendment.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			So far as the general proposition of law is concerned
			<lb />
			that the appeal is a vested right there is no quarrel with
			<lb />
			the proposition but it is clarified that such right can be
			<lb />
			taken away by a subsequent enactment either expressly
			<lb />
			or by necessary intendment. The Parliament while
			<lb />
			amending Section 100A of the Code of Civil Procedure,
			<lb />
			by amending Act 22 of 2002 with effect from 1.7.2002,
			<lb />
			took away the Letters Patent power of the High Court
			<lb />
			in the matter of appeal against an order of learned
			<lb />
			single Judge to the Division Bench.
			<lb />
			Section 100A of the Code of Civil Procedure
			<lb />
			reads as .........................................................................
			<lb />
			Therefore, where appeal has been decided from an
			<lb />
			original order by a single Judge, no further appeal has
			<lb />
			been provided and that power which used to be there
			<lb />
			under the Letters Patent of the High Court has been
			<lb />
			subsequently withdrawn. The present order which has
			<lb />
			been passed by the CLB and against that appeal has
			<lb />
			been provided before the High Court under Section 10F
			<lb />
			of the Act, that is an appeal from the original order.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Then in that case no further Letters Patent Appeal shall
			<lb />
			lie to the Division Bench of the same High Court. This
			<lb />
			amendment has taken away the power of the Letters
			<lb />
			Patent in the manner where learned single Judge hears
			<lb />
			an appeal from the original order. Original order in
			<lb />
			the present case was passed by the CLB exercising the
			<lb />
			power under Sections 397 and 398 of the Act and
			<lb />
			appeal has been preferred under Section 10F of the Act
			<lb />
			before the High Court. Learned single Judge having
			<lb />
			passed an order, no further appeal will lie as the
			<lb />
			Parliament in its wisdom has taken away its power.
			<lb />
			Learned counsel for the respondents invited our
			<lb />
			attention to a letter from the then Law Minister. That
			<lb />
			letter cannot override the statutory provision. When
			<lb />
			the statute is very clear, whatever statement by the Law
			<lb />
			Minister made in the floor of the House, cannot change
			<lb />
			the words and intendment which is borne out from the
			<lb />
			words. The letter of the Law Minister cannot be read to
			<lb />
			interpret the provisions of Section 100A.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			intendment of the Legislature is more than clear in the
			<lb />
			words and the same has to be given its natural
			<lb />
			meaning and cannot be subject to any statement made
			<lb />
			by the Law Minister in any communication. The words
			<lb />
			speak for itself. It does not require any further
			<lb />
			interpretation by any statement made in any manner.
			<lb />
			Therefore, the power of the high Court in exercising
			<lb />
			Letters Patent in a matter where a single Judge has
			<lb />
			decided the appeal from original order, has been taken
			<lb />
			away and it cannot be invoked in the present context.
			<lb />
			There is no two opinion in the matter that when the
			<lb />
			CLB exercises its powers under Sections 397 &amp; 398 of
			<lb />
			the Act, it exercised its quasi-judicial power as original
			<lb />
			authority. It may not be a court but it has all the
			<lb />
			trapping of a court.
			<lb />
			Therefore, the CLB while
			<lb />
			exercising its original jurisdiction under Sections 397 &amp;
			<lb />
			398 of the Act passed the order and against that order
			<lb />
			appeal lie to the learned single Judge of the High Court
			<lb />
			and thereafter no further appeal could be filed.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			18. In this connection, our attention was invited to a
			<lb />
			decision in the case of Arati Dutta vs M/s Eastern Tea
			<lb />
			Estate (P) Ltd. reported in (1988) 1 SCC 523. This was
			<lb />
			a case in which the power was exercised by learned
			<lb />
			single Judge under Sections 397 &amp; 398 of the Act and
			<lb />
			against that order appeal lay to the Division Bench of
			<lb />
			the High Court under Section 483 of the Act. In that
			<lb />
			context, their Lordships observed that mere absence of
			<lb />
			procedural rules would not deprive the litigant&apos;s of
			<lb />
			substantive right conferred by the statute. We have
			<lb />
			already explained above that earlier the power under
			<lb />
			Sections 397 &amp; 398 of the Act was being exercised by
			<lb />
			learned Company Judge in the High Court and
			<lb />
			therefore, appeal lay to the Division Bench under
			<lb />
			Section 483 of the Act. If the power has been exercised
			<lb />
			by the Company Judge in the High Court, then one
			<lb />
			appeal shall lie before the Division Bench of the High
			<lb />
			Court under Section 483 of the Act. But that is not the
			<lb />
			situation in the present case. Therefore, this decision
			<lb />
			cannot be of any help to respondents.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			67.
			<lb />
			This judgment in fact is a complete answer to the
			<lb />
			arguments raised on behalf of the Appellants. In that case, the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court even took the view that a body like Company Law
			<lb />
			Board has the trapping of a Civil Court and it exercises original
			<lb />
			jurisdiction under Sections 397/398 of the Companies Act against
			<lb />
			which an appeal lies to the Single Judge. It also rejected the
			<lb />
			contention that Section 100A does not create a specific bar. While
			<lb />
			referring to the judgment of the Supreme Court in Subal Paul vs
			<lb />
			Malina Paul and another, (2003) 10 SCC 361, the Court referred with
			<lb />
			approval the dictum of the Court which reads as follows :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;Whenever the statute provides such a bar, it is so
			<lb />
			expressly stated, as would appear from Section 100-A
			<lb />
			of the Code of Civil Procedure.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			Motor Accident Claims Tribunal which has all the trapping of a Civil
			<lb />
			Court, discharges its judicial functions subject to the superintendence
			<lb />
			and control of the High Court. In fact, the High Court being its
			<lb />
			appellate Court, would exercise all the control over the Motor
			<lb />
			Accident Claims Tribunal.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			68.
			<lb />
			It can be useful to notice at this stage itself that in Kamal
			<lb />
			Kumar Dutta (supra), the view taken by a Division Bench of this Court
			<lb />
			in the case of Maharashtra Power Development Corporation Limited vs
			<lb />
			Dabhol Power Company and others, (2003) 117 Company Cases 651
			<lb />
			= AIR 2004 BOM 38, that appeal shall lie against the judgment of the
			<lb />
			Single Judge passed in Appeal against the order of Company Law
			<lb />
			Board as the Letters Patent Appeal or a statutory appeal under special
			<lb />
			enactment and will not be affected by the provisions of Section 100-A,
			<lb />
			was specifically rejected and the view taken by this Court was held to
			<lb />
			be incorrect proposition of law.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			69.
			<lb />
			In the case of Municipal Corporation of Brihanmumbai and
			<lb />
			another vs State Bank of India, (1999) 1 SCC 123, the Court was
			<lb />
			concerned with maintainability of a Letters Patent Appeal under
			<lb />
			Clause 15 from the judgment and order of the Single Judge passed on
			<lb />
			an Appeal under Section 218-D of Bombay Municipal Corporation Act.
			<lb />
			The Bombay Municipal Corporation Act, 1888 is a complete code and
			<lb />
			contains provisions of filing of appeals, etc., against the order made
			<lb />
			under the Act. In terms of Section 127(1) of the Act, the jurisdiction is
			<lb />
			exercised by the Chief Judge of Small Causes Court and the appeal
			<lb />
			against that order was preferred before the High Court under Section
			<lb />
			218-D of the Act and the Court held that no Second Appeal could lie
			<lb />
			from that order observing as under :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;9. Thus, according to Section 218-D, an appeal shall
			<lb />
			also lie to the High Court from any decision of the
			<lb />
			Chief Judge of the Small Cause Court in an appeal
			<lb />
			under Section 217, &quot;upon a question of law or usage
			<lb />
			having the force of law or the construction of a
			<lb />
			document&quot;. That the respondent had taken recourse to
			<lb />
			Section 218-D(1) in filing an appeal against the
			<lb />
			appellate order of the learned Additional Chief Judge
			<lb />
			of the Small Cause Court is not in dispute.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			appellant has not questioned the maintainability of the
			<lb />
			appeal filed by the respondent under Section 218-D of
			<lb />
			the Act before the learned Single Judge of the High
			<lb />
			Court before us. Thus, it is obvious that the appeal
			<lb />
			filed by the respondent under Section 218-D of the Act
			<lb />
			was a second appeal against the appellate order made
			<lb />
			by the Additional Chief Judge, Small Cause Court.
			<lb />
			Under the Bombay Municipal Corporation Act, no
			<lb />
			further appeal has been provided against the judgment
			<lb />
			of a learned Single Judge of the High Court deciding
			<lb />
			the second appeal under Section 218-D of the Act
			<lb />
			against an appellate order of the Chief Judge of the
			<lb />
			Small Cause Court passed under Section 217(1) of the
			<lb />
			Act. Section 100-A of the Code of Civil Procedure,
			<lb />
			which was introduced by the Amendment Act, 1976,
			<lb />
			specifically bars any further appeal in such cases. ....
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			10. This section has been introduced to minimise the
			<lb />
			delay in the finality of a decision. Prior to the
			<lb />
			enactment of the above provision, under the letters
			<lb />
			patent, an appeal against the decision of a Single Judge
			<lb />
			in a second appeal was, in certain cases, held
			<lb />
			competent, though under Section 100 of the Code of
			<lb />
			Civil Procedure, there was some inhibition against
			<lb />
			interference with the findings of fact. The right of
			<lb />
			taking recourse to such an appeal has now been taken
			<lb />
			away by Section 100-A of the Code of Civil Procedure
			<lb />
			(supra). Since an appeal under Section 217(1) of the
			<lb />
			Act is a first appeal in a second forum/court and an
			<lb />
			appeal under Section 218-D of the Act is the second
			<lb />
			appeal in the third forum/court, no further appeal
			<lb />
			would be competent before the fourth forum/court in
			<lb />
			view of Section 100-A of the Code of Civil Proeedure
			<lb />
			(supra).&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			70.
			<lb />
			At this stage, even at the cost of repetition, we may notice
			<lb />
			that the provisions of Section 173 of the Motor Vehicles Act provide
			<lb />
			for an appeal against the Award of the Tribunal specifically and do not
			<lb />
			contemplate any further appeal. Thus, the statute does not specifically
			<lb />
			provide for any further right of appeal.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			71.
			<lb />
			A Division Bench of Rajasthan High Court in the case of
			<lb />
			HYPERLINK &quot;http://R.S.R.T.C/&quot; HYPERLINK &quot;http://R.S.R.T.C/&quot;R.S.R.T.C. &amp; etc.
			<lb />
			etc. vs Vaibhav Kumar and others, etc., AIR 2007 RAJASTHAN 147,
			<lb />
			while dealing with identical questions relating to maintainability of a
			<lb />
			Letters Patent Appeal against the appellate order passed by the Single
			<lb />
			Judge of the High Court under Section 173 of the Motor Vehicles Act,
			<lb />
			held that the further intra-Court appeal is barred by Section 100-A of
			<lb />
			the Code of Civil Procedure. It mainly relied upon the judgment of
			<lb />
			the Kamal Kumar Dutta&apos;s case (supra), while also referring to other
			<lb />
			provisions including a view of Full Bench of the Andhra Pradesh High
			<lb />
			Court in the case of M/s United India Insurance Co. Ltd. vs. S. Surya
			<lb />
			Prakash Reddy and another, 2006 (4) Andh L T 448, The Court held
			<lb />
			as under :-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;16. A Full Bench of the Andhra Pradesh High Court in
			<lb />
			the case of Gandla Pannala Bhulaxmi v APRTC and
			<lb />
			another, AIR 2003 AP 458, was seized with the
			<lb />
			question whether the right of appeal available under
			<lb />
			the Letters Patent is taken away by Section 100A of the
			<lb />
			Civil Procedure Code in respect of the matter arising
			<lb />
			under special enactments or other instruments having
			<lb />
			the force of law. That was a case where Letters Patents
			<lb />
			Appeal was preferred from the order of a Single Judge
			<lb />
			passed in an appeal under Section 173 of the Motor
			<lb />
			Vehicles Act. The Full Bench of the Andhra Pradesh
			<lb />
			High Court upon consideration of the amended
			<lb />
			provision of Section 100A and the judgment of the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court in the case of Vinita M Khanolkar v
			<lb />
			Pragna M Pal, AIR 1998 SC 424 and another decision of
			<lb />
			the Supreme Court in Sharda Devi v State of Bihar, AIR
			<lb />
			2002 SC 1357, held that Section 100A of the Code of
			<lb />
			Civil Procedure in clear and specific terms prohibits
			<lb />
			further appeal against the judgment and decree of a
			<lb />
			Single Judge to a Division Bench notwithstanding
			<lb />
			anything contained in the Letters Patents. It was held
			<lb />
			that the Letter Patents which provides for further
			<lb />
			appeal to a Division bench remains intact but the right
			<lb />
			to prefer a further appeal is taken away even in respect
			<lb />
			of the matters arising under a special enactment or
			<lb />
			other instruments having the force of law.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			17. The view of the Kerala High Court is on the same
			<lb />
			lines. A Full Bench of Kerala High Court in the case of
			<lb />
			Kesava Pillai Sreedharan Pillai and etc. v State of Kerala
			<lb />
			and others, AIR 2004 Kerala 111, was concerned with
			<lb />
			the question whether an appeal from a judgment,
			<lb />
			decree or order passed by the Single Judge on an
			<lb />
			appeal against the order of a Court or tribunal is
			<lb />
			maintainable despite Section 100A of the Code of Civil
			<lb />
			Procedure effective from 1 st July, 2002.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			18. The Full Bench of the Kerala High Court noticed
			<lb />
			that the intention of the Legislature by enacting Section
			<lb />
			100A was to abolish an intra-Court appeal to the Bench
			<lb />
			of two Judges of the same High Court from a decision
			<lb />
			rendered by a Single Judge. It held that Section 100A
			<lb />
			of the Code of Civil Procedure would prevail over the
			<lb />
			provisions contained in Section 5(ii) of the Kerala High
			<lb />
			Court Act. We may observe here that the said provision
			<lb />
			is similar to erstwhile Section 18 of the Rajasthan High
			<lb />
			Court Ordinance, 1949 regarding further appeal to the
			<lb />
			Bench of two Judges from the decision of the Single
			<lb />
			Judge. The Full Bench of Kerala High Court has thus
			<lb />
			held that the right of further appeal as provided under
			<lb />
			Section 5 (ii) of the Kerala High Court Act stands
			<lb />
			abrogated by Section 100A of the Civil Procedure Code
			<lb />
			w. e. f. 1 st July, 2002.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			19. The Supreme Court in Subal Paul v Malina Paul
			<lb />
			and another, (2003) 10 SCC 3611 : AIR 2003 SC 1928,
			<lb />
			was concerned with the question whether the Letters
			<lb />
			Patent Appeal would lie from the judgment of a Single
			<lb />
			Judge of the High Court filed under Section 299 of the
			<lb />
			Indian Succession Act. Pertinently in Subal Paul&apos;s case
			<lb />
			the Supreme Court observed that whenever a statute
			<lb />
			provided such a bar it did so expressly as would appear
			<lb />
			from Section 100A of the Code of Civil Procedure. It is
			<lb />
			also important to notice that in Subal Paul an appeal
			<lb />
			was preferred before the Division Bench from the order
			<lb />
			of the Single Judge prior to 1 st July, 2002.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			20. The Constitution Bench of the Supreme Court in
			<lb />
			P.S. Sathappan (dead) by L.Rs. V Andhra Bank Ltd. &amp;
			<lb />
			Ors., (2004) 11 SCC 672 : AIR 2004 SC 5152,
			<lb />
			extensively dealt with the provisions contained in
			<lb />
			Section 100A and the other provisions of the Code of
			<lb />
			Civil Procedure, more particularly, Sections 4 and 104
			<lb />
			and had held that when the Legislature wanted to
			<lb />
			exclude the Letters Patent Appeal, it specifically did so
			<lb />
			and the words used in Section 100a were not by way of
			<lb />
			abundant caution. That is what the Supreme Court
			<lb />
			said in P.S. Sathappan (supra) (Para 30 of AIR ) :-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;It is thus to be seen that when the legislature
			<lb />
			wanted to exclude a letters patent appeal it specifically
			<lb />
			did so. The words used in Section 100A are not by way
			<lb />
			of abundant caution. By the Amendment Acts of 1976
			<lb />
			and 2002 a specific exclusion is provided as the
			<lb />
			legislature knew that in the absence of such words a
			<lb />
			Letters Patent Appeal would not be barred. The
			<lb />
			legislature was aware that it had incorporated the
			<lb />
			saving clause in Section 104(1) and incorporated
			<lb />
			Section 4, CPC. Thus, now a specific exclusion was
			<lb />
			provided.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>&quot;</item>

		<p>
			100-A : .............................................................
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			To be noted that here again the legislature has
			<lb />
			provided for a specific exclusion. It must be stated that
			<lb />
			now by virtue of Section 100A no letters patent appeal
			<lb />
			would be maintainable. However, it is an admitted
			<lb />
			position that the law which would prevail would be the
			<lb />
			law at the relevant time. At the relevant time neither
			<lb />
			Section 100A nor Section 104(2) barred a letters patent
			<lb />
			appeal.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			21. The recent decision that squarely concludes the
			<lb />
			controversy is the decision of the Supreme Court in the
			<lb />
			case of Kamal Kumar Dutta, 2006 AIR SCW 4594. That
			<lb />
			was a case where the Company Law Board passed order
			<lb />
			under Sections 397 and 398 of the Companies Act. An
			<lb />
			appeal was filed before the High Court under
			<lb />
			10F of the Companies Act. The said appeal was heard
			<lb />
			and disposed of by the Single Judge. From the order of
			<lb />
			the Single Judge under Section 10F of the Companies
			<lb />
			Act, the matter was carried to the Apex Court. Before
			<lb />
			the Apex Court, an objection was raised regarding
			<lb />
			maintainability of the appeal on the ground that the
			<lb />
			appellants have alternative remedy of approaching the
			<lb />
			Division Bench under Clause 15 of the Letters Patent
			<lb />
			and that the appellants ought to have availed the said
			<lb />
			remedy. Dealing with this aspect, the Supreme Court
			<lb />
			held that Letters Patent appeal against the order passed
			<lb />
			by a Single Judge in an appeal under Section 10F of the
			<lb />
			Companies Act would not be maintainable.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			22. It would be seen that the Supreme Court held
			<lb />
			that the power exercised by the Company Law Board
			<lb />
			under Sections 397 and 398 of the Companies Act is a
			<lb />
			quasi-judicial power as original authority. It may not
			<lb />
			be a Court but it has all the trappings of a Court and,
			<lb />
			therefore, the Company Law Board while exercising its
			<lb />
			original jurisdiction under Section 397 and 398 of the
			<lb />
			Companies Act passed the order and against that order
			<lb />
			appeal would lay to the learned Single Judge of the
			<lb />
			High Court and thereafter no further appeal could be
			<lb />
			filed.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			23. The legal position exposited by the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court in Kamal Kumar Dutta, 2006 AIR SCW 4694,
			<lb />
			applies on all fours to the order/award passed by the
			<lb />
			Motor Accident Claims Tribunal under Section 168 of
			<lb />
			the Motor Vehicles Act and where such order/award is
			<lb />
			carried in an appeal under Section 173 of that Act.
			<lb />
			Even if it be assumed that the Motor Accident Claims
			<lb />
			Tribunal is not a Court as is the term ordinarily
			<lb />
			understood, it is beyond doubt that such Tribunal has
			<lb />
			all the trapping of a Court. Though the Tribunals
			<lb />
			occupy a special position of their own under the
			<lb />
			scheme of the Courts and Tribunals and special matters
			<lb />
			and questions are entrusted to them for their decision
			<lb />
			yet they share with the Courts one common
			<lb />
			characteristic viz. : both the Courts as well as Tribunals
			<lb />
			are constituted by the State and are invested with
			<lb />
			judicial functions as distinguished from purely
			<lb />
			administrative or executive functions. It is the State&apos;s
			<lb />
			inherent judicial power which is discharged by the
			<lb />
			Courts and Tribunals, if the Company Law Board
			<lb />
			constituted under the Companies Act in its adjudicatory
			<lb />
			powers has the trappings of a Court and an appeal
			<lb />
			under Section 10F of the Companies Act from its order
			<lb />
			to the Single Judge is not amenable to further appeal
			<lb />
			(Letters Patent) to the Division Bench of the same
			<lb />
			Court because of Section 100A of the Code of Civil
			<lb />
			Procedure, a fortiori, an order passed by the Single
			<lb />
			Judge in appeal under Section 173 of the Motor
			<lb />
			Vehicles Act from the order/award of the Motor
			<lb />
			Accident Claims Tribunal shall not be subject to intra-
			<lb />
			Court appeal in view of the bar created by Section 100A
			<lb />
			of the Code of Civil Procedure effective from 1 st July,
			<lb />
			2002.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			72.
			<lb />
			The Bench also noticed the distinction between the decree,
			<lb />
			order and the award. It held that decision of the Single Judge in
			<lb />
			Appeal under Section 173 of the Motor Vehicles Act is nothing but a
			<lb />
			judgment. We adopt the reasoning and have no hesitation in coming
			<lb />
			to the conclusion that the Award of the Tribunal and in any case the
			<lb />
			judgment of the learned Single Judge passed under Section 173 of the
			<lb />
			Motor Vehicles Act in appeal has all the ingredients of a judgment
			<lb />
			within the meaning of Section 15 of the Letters Patent and/or under
			<lb />
			the Code of Civil Procedure.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			73.
			<lb />
			The provisions of Letters Patent, being a special law, as
			<lb />
			opposed to Civil Procedure Code which would be generally applicable
			<lb />
			to all Courts, would have normally taken precedence and regulated
			<lb />
			the right to file an appeal, but for the non-obstante clause and specific
			<lb />
			exclusion of its application in terms of Section 100A of the Code of
			<lb />
			Civil Procedure. In the case of P.S. Sathappan (supra) as well as in the
			<lb />
			case of Iridium India Telecom Ltd. (supra), it was held that the
			<lb />
			provision of Section 100A is the provision which specifically excludes
			<lb />
			application of other laws.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			74.
			<lb />
			We have discussed in some elaboration, the reasons for
			<lb />
			arriving at a conclusion that the Letters Patent Appeal against the
			<lb />
			appellate judgment passed in exercise of powers conferred on the
			<lb />
			court under Section 173 of the Motor Vehicles Act is not maintainable.
			<lb />
			Similar view was taken by a Five Judge Bench of the Andhra Pradesh
			<lb />
			High Court in the case of M/s United India Insurance Co. Ltd. vs. S.
			<lb />
			Surya Prakash Reddy and another, 2006 (4) Andh L T 448, and a Full
			<lb />
			Bench of the Madhya Pradesh High Court in the case of Laxminarayan
			<lb />
			vs Shivlal Gujar, 2003 91) MPLJ (FB) 10 = AIR 2003 MP 49 (FB).
			<lb />
			With respect, we also adopt the reasoning given by the two High
			<lb />
			Courts in support of our view. We also add and follow the view of
			<lb />
			these Courts which is in consonance with the judgment of the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court afore-referred. This principle would not apply to the
			<lb />
			Appeals which were preferred prior to 1 st July 2002 as the provisions
			<lb />
			of Section 100A are prospective in their operation and limitations.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			75.
			<lb />
			It is a settled principle of law that appeal is continuation of
			<lb />
			original proceedings and the procedural law regulating the right of
			<lb />
			appeal would be prospective unless and until it is clearly spelt out to
			<lb />
			the contrary. Equally well settled is the principle that right of appeal
			<lb />
			being a statutory right can be regulated and/or even taken away by a
			<lb />
			subsequent Legislation. There being no fundamental right or a
			<lb />
			general right to prefer appeals, the appeals instituted prior to 1 st July
			<lb />
			2002, before introduction of Section 100-A on the statute of Code of
			<lb />
			Civil Procedure would be controlled by earlier law and the appeals
			<lb />
			filed thereafter would be regulated by the present provisions of
			<lb />
			Section 100-A of the Code.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			76.
			<lb />
			In the case of Kamla Devi vs Kushal Kanwar and another,
			<lb />
			(2006) 13 SCC 295, the Supreme Court, where the Appeal before the
			<lb />
			learned Single Judge under the provisions of the Indian Succession Act
			<lb />
			was filed in the year 1992 against the order passed by the learned
			<lb />
			Single Judge dated 13 th February 1992, held that the Letters Patent
			<lb />
			Appeal would be maintainable as it was filed prior to coming into
			<lb />
			force of the Amending Act of 2002 Act. The Supreme Court also
			<lb />
			noticed the judgments in the case of Kamal Kumar Dutta (supra) and
			<lb />
			Subal Paul (supra). The main contention in these cases was with
			<lb />
			regard to retrospective or prospective operation of Section 100-A and
			<lb />
			also that for appeals filed prior to Amendment Act, it had not taken
			<lb />
			away the right of appeal provided the ingredients of Clause 15 of the
			<lb />
			Letters Patent were satisfied.
			<lb />
			Obviously, one of the relevant
			<lb />
			considerations would be as to when the right to file an appeal arose.
			<lb />
			As noticed in the case of Kamla Devi (supra), the judgment was passed
			<lb />
			on 13 th February 2002 and appeal itself was filed at that time and,
			<lb />
			therefore, was controlled by the law prior to the amendment of 1 st July
			<lb />
			2002.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			77.
			<lb />
			Having noticed the relevant principles of law and the
			<lb />
			interpretation that the relevant provisions of law need to be
			<lb />
			interpreted on settled canons of interpretative jurisprudence, now we
			<lb />
			may analyse the view taken by a Division Bench of this Court in the
			<lb />
			case of Asha Joshi (supra) which is the very basis for the present
			<lb />
			Reference. In paragraph 40 of the said judgment, the Bench
			<lb />
			concluded as under :-
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;40. To sum up, we hold that :
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a) Section 100-A of the Code of Civil Procedure
			<lb />
			would apply on to the proceedings governed by
			<lb />
			the Code;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b) Proceedings under section 140, 163-A or 166 of
			<lb />
			the Motor Vehicles Act are not governed by the
			<lb />
			Code and Claims Tribunal is not a Civil Court;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(c) Award by Tribunal is not a decree or order of a
			<lb />
			Civil Court;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(d) Such award is not a decree or order made in
			<lb />
			exercise of appellate jurisdiction by a Court subject
			<lb />
			to superintendence of the High Court;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(e) A single judge of this Court hearing appeals under
			<lb />
			section 173 of the Motor Vehicles Act from awards
			<lb />
			of Claims Tribunal consequently does not deliver a
			<lb />
			judgment in exercise of appellate jurisdiction in
			<lb />
			respect of a decree or order made in exercise of
			<lb />
			appellate jurisdiction;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(f) It would, therefore, follow that such judgment of
			<lb />
			Single Judge would be subject to an appeal under
			<lb />
			Clause 15 of the Letters Patent.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			78.
			<lb />
			With greatest respect, we are unable to contribute to the
			<lb />
			conclusions arrived at by the Bench as, in our opinion, it is not a
			<lb />
			correct exposition of law. Inter alia, we may notice the patent reasons
			<lb />
			for which we are unable to accept the law in Asha Joshi&apos;s case (supra).
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			(a) Despite the fact that the judgment was pronounced
			<lb />
			on 12 th December 2007, the judgment of the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court in Kamal Kumar Dutta (supra)
			<lb />
			decided on 11 th August 2006, which has a direct
			<lb />
			bearing and to a large extent answers the
			<lb />
			controversies in issue was not brought to the notice
			<lb />
			of the Bench. The ratio decidendi stated in Kamal
			<lb />
			Kumar Dutta (supra) case being squarely applicable
			<lb />
			to the facts of the present case, would have been
			<lb />
			the correct precept for answering the questions of
			<lb />
			law.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b) The Division Bench did not notice and interprete
			<lb />
			the language of Section 100-A of the Code of Civil
			<lb />
			Procedure in relation to the cases where the
			<lb />
			appeals were filed subsequent to 1 st July 2002.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(c) Clause 44 of the Letters Patent was not brought to
			<lb />
			the notice of the Bench so as to grant precedence to
			<lb />
			the provisions of Section 100-A even after the
			<lb />
			provisions of Clause 15 of the Letters Patent were
			<lb />
			attracted in the present case.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(d) The Bench treated the Motor Vehicles Act as a
			<lb />
			special law, however, no material was placed
			<lb />
			before the Bench to the effect that under the
			<lb />
			special statute the order passed by the Single Judge
			<lb />
			in exercise of its appellate jurisdiction under
			<lb />
			Section 173 was made appealable. In other words,
			<lb />
			no Second Appeal was provided under the Motor
			<lb />
			Vehicles Act.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(e) The Full Bench of the Madhya Pradesh High Court
			<lb />
			in the case of Laxminarayan (supra) and this Court
			<lb />
			in the case of Rahul Sharad (supra) were primarily
			<lb />
			concerned
			<lb />
			with
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			retrospectivity
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			prospectivity of the provisions of Section 100-A
			<lb />
			which in fact already stand settled by the judgment
			<lb />
			of the Supreme Court in Bento De Souza Egipsy vs
			<lb />
			Yvette Alvares Colaco, (2004) 13 SCC 438, and
			<lb />
			Kamla Devi (supra) and the said provisions being
			<lb />
			prospective and appeals in the case before the
			<lb />
			Bench having been filed subsequent o 1 st July 2002
			<lb />
			and as such they will be covered by the provisions
			<lb />
			of Section 100-A of the Code.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(f) The view of the Division Bench that the Tribunal
			<lb />
			was neither a Civil Court nor had the trapping
			<lb />
			thereof, in our humble opinion, is not correct
			<lb />
			position of law in view of the well settled position
			<lb />
			of law as afore-noticed. The Tribunal has all the
			<lb />
			trapping of a Civil Court and its orders are
			<lb />
			judgments or orders as even known in the common
			<lb />
			parlance. The learned Single Judge exercises
			<lb />
			powers of an appellate Court in terms of the Code
			<lb />
			of Civil Procedure while hearing an appeal
			<lb />
			preferred to that Court in terms of Section 173 of
			<lb />
			the Motor Vehicles Act.
			<lb />
			The Tribunal and
			<lb />
			particularly the appellate Court does not lose the
			<lb />
			trapping of a Civil Court while exercising such
			<lb />
			jurisdiction.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(g) The Division Bench placed heavy reliance upon the
			<lb />
			observations of the Supreme Court in the case of
			<lb />
			Sharda Devi (supra) stating that the provisions of
			<lb />
			Letters Patent were akin to the constitutional
			<lb />
			powers of the Court, but it was clarified and in fact
			<lb />
			not accepted by the Constitution Bench in P.S.
			<lb />
			Satthapan&apos;s case (supra) where the Court held as
			<lb />
			under :
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;.... At this stage it must be clarified that during
			<lb />
			arguments, relying on the sentence &quot;the powers
			<lb />
			given to a High Court under the Letters Patent are
			<lb />
			akin to the constitutional powers of a High Court&quot;
			<lb />
			in para 9 of this judgment it had been suggested
			<lb />
			that a Letters Patent had the same status as the
			<lb />
			Constitution.
			<lb />
			In our view these observations
			<lb />
			merely lay down that the powers given to a High
			<lb />
			Court are the powers with which that High Court is
			<lb />
			constituted. These observations do not put Letters
			<lb />
			Patent on a par with the Constitution.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(h) In our considered view, the Division Bench while
			<lb />
			determining the controversy before it could have
			<lb />
			hardly relied upon the judgment of the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court in the case of Jindal Vijaynagar Steel vs
			<lb />
			Jindal Praxair Oxygen Co. Ltd., (2006) 11 SCC
			<lb />
			521, where the Supreme Court was primarily
			<lb />
			concerned with interpretation of Clause 12 of the
			<lb />
			Letters Patent of the Bombay High Court and
			<lb />
			Section 20 of the Civil Procedure code in relation
			<lb />
			to determination of jurisdiction. The question in
			<lb />
			that case related to the determination of Ordinary
			<lb />
			Original Civil Jurisdiction under the Letters Patent
			<lb />
			Act in relation to a cause of action arising within
			<lb />
			the jurisdiction of the Court and on construction of
			<lb />
			Sections 20 and 120 of the Code read with
			<lb />
			Arbitration Act, 1940, it was held that the Court
			<lb />
			would exercise jurisdiction in terms of Clause 12 of
			<lb />
			the Letters Patent.
			<lb />
		</item>


		<p>
			79.
			<lb />
			Another aspect, which needs to be examined by us, is that
			<lb />
			the Division Bench in Asha&apos;s case (supra) in paragraph 33 noticed
			<lb />
			another judgment of a Division Bench of this Court in the case of
			<lb />
			Bhenoy G. Dembla &amp; Anr. vs M/s. Prem Kutir P. Ltd., reported in
			<lb />
			2003(4) Mh.L.J. 883, where the Division Bench had taken the view
			<lb />
			that keeping in view the provisions of Section 100-A of the Code of
			<lb />
			Civil Procedure and Section 10F of the Companies Act, 1956, an
			<lb />
			appeal from the judgment of the learned Single Judge in exercise of its
			<lb />
			appellate jurisdiction under Section 10-F of the Companies Act would
			<lb />
			not lie after 1 st July, 2002. The Bench held that :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;.......... There is no express conferment of a right of
			<lb />
			a further appeal to the Division Bench against the
			<lb />
			decision of a learned Single Judge. That being the
			<lb />
			position, an appeal to the Division Bench is clearly
			<lb />
			not maintainable against the decision of the Single
			<lb />
			Judge rendered after 1 st July, 2002.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			80.
			<lb />
			In our view, the most appropriate course of action in
			<lb />
			consonance with the judicial propriety and discipline would have been
			<lb />
			that the Division Bench dealing with Asha&apos;s case (supra) should have
			<lb />
			referred the matter to a larger Bench rather than expressing the
			<lb />
			contrary view to that of equi bench judgment in Bhenoy G. Dembla&apos;s
			<lb />
			case (supra) which had been pronounced much earlier. Be that as it
			<lb />
			may, we would leave the matter at that stage and proceed to discuss
			<lb />
			paragraph 33 of the judgment in Asha&apos;s case (supra) where the Bench
			<lb />
			distinguished the judgment in Bhenoy G. Dembla&apos;s case (supra) that the
			<lb />
			proceedings in that case had arisen from the provisions of Section 10-F
			<lb />
			of the Companies Act. The Division Bench in Asha&apos;s case (supra) had
			<lb />
			referred to earlier Division Bench Judgment of this Court in the case of
			<lb />
			Maharashtra Power Development Corporation Limited&apos;s case (supra) which
			<lb />
			had taken the contrary view and held that the judgment of Company
			<lb />
			Court pronounced in the appeal under Section 10-F of the Companies
			<lb />
			Act would not be a judgment and decree within the meaning of the
			<lb />
			provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure, and therefore, the appeal
			<lb />
			was not barred in terms of Section 100-A of the Code of Civil
			<lb />
			Procedure. The Division Bench in Asha&apos;s case (supra) ignored the fact
			<lb />
			that the view of the Division Bench of Bombay High Court in
			<lb />
			Maharashtra Power Development Corporation Limited&apos;s case (supra) was
			<lb />
			not approved by the Supreme Court in Kamal Kumar Dutta&apos;s case
			<lb />
			(supra), and in fact, diametrically opposite view has been expressed by
			<lb />
			the Supreme Court which we have already discussed in some detail.
			<lb />
			It was expected from the learned counsel appearing for the respective
			<lb />
			parties to bring these judgments to the notice of the Division Bench,
			<lb />
			which, if brought, we have no doubt in our mind that the Bench would
			<lb />
			have come to a different conclusion and preferably to the one
			<lb />
			indicated above.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			81.
			<lb />
			It is a settled norm of interpretation of statute that the
			<lb />
			enactment should be examined in its entirety and the Court essentially
			<lb />
			are considering the legislative scheme and object and intent of the
			<lb />
			Legislature even while applying the rule of plain interpretation.
			<lb />
			Reference to one or two odd provisions of the Act, Code or Rules
			<lb />
			framed under that Act may not thus sufficiently satisfy the
			<lb />
			requirements of law. We have discussed in some elaboration the
			<lb />
			various provisions of the Civil Procedure Code that have been made
			<lb />
			specifically applicable to the Motor Vehicles Act. The functions and
			<lb />
			powers of the Tribunal in the process of determination are controlled
			<lb />
			by the specific provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure as indicated in
			<lb />
			Section 169 of the Motor Vehicles Act and Rules 257 and 276 of the
			<lb />
			Maharashtra Motor Vehicles Rules framed under the Motor Vehicles
			<lb />
			Act. It has to entertain an application filed under Section 165 of the
			<lb />
			Act and has to exercise its adjudicatory powers required for the
			<lb />
			purpose permitting to file reply, give hearing and adequate
			<lb />
			opportunity to prove its case, then hear the arguments and decide the
			<lb />
			claim petition in accordance with law. The entire adjudicatory process
			<lb />
			is thus primarily and substantially controlled by the provisions of the
			<lb />
			Code. It is difficult for us to come to the conclusion that the Tribunal
			<lb />
			is not having the trapping of Civil Court. Technically or grammatically
			<lb />
			speaking, the Tribunal may not be a Civil Court, but it has all the
			<lb />
			trapping of the Court and it pronounces an Award which is
			<lb />
			determination of rights of parties and which has all the ingredients of
			<lb />
			a judgment and an order as known under civil jurisprudence.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			82.
			<lb />
			Now, we will proceed to deal with the judgment of the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court relied upon by the appellants. Heavy reliance was
			<lb />
			placed on the judgment in Subal Paul&apos;s case (supra) where the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court, while dealing with the provisions of Section 299 of
			<lb />
			the Succession Act, observed that this was not governed by Section
			<lb />
			104 of the Code of Civil Procedure and against the order passed by the
			<lb />
			learned Single Judge in exercise of that jurisdiction, letters patent
			<lb />
			appeal would lie. Firstly, the provisions of Section 100-A of the Code
			<lb />
			of Civil Procedure are not the subject matter of discussion in this case.
			<lb />
			Secondly, the appeal before the learned Single Judge had been filed
			<lb />
			prior to coming into force the provisions of Section 100-A of the Code
			<lb />
			i.e. 1 st July, 2002. The Supreme Court was primarily concerned with
			<lb />
			the interpretation of sub-section (2) of Section 104 and held that, that
			<lb />
			provision will not bar a remedy which otherwise is provided under any
			<lb />
			other law. We may find it necessary to refer to at this stage itself that
			<lb />
			the provision of Section 104 unlike the provision of Section 100-A of
			<lb />
			the Code of Civil Procedure does not contain any non obstante clause
			<lb />
			or legislative exception. In paragraph 20 of the judgment, the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court has specifically noticed that the provisions of Section 104 does
			<lb />
			not contemplate order or decree passed under a special statute and
			<lb />
			thus the restrictions carved out under Section 104 would not prohibit
			<lb />
			an appeal in terms of Section 299 of the Succession Act. The real
			<lb />
			catchword of the judgment of the Supreme Court in this case is: -
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;20.
			<lb />
			By reason of Section 104 of the Code of civil
			<lb />
			Procedure the bar of appeal under a special statute is
			<lb />
			saved. A plain reading of Section 104 of the Code of
			<lb />
			Civil Procedure would show that an appeal shall lie from
			<lb />
			an appealable order and no other order save as otherwise
			<lb />
			expressly provided in the body of this Code of or by any
			<lb />
			law for the time being in force. Section 104 of the Code
			<lb />
			merely recognises appeals provided under special statute.
			<lb />
			It does not create a right of appeal as such. It does not,
			<lb />
			therefore, bar any further appeal also, if the same is
			<lb />
			provided for under any other Act, for the time being in
			<lb />
			force. Whenever the statute provides such a bar, it is so
			<lb />
			expressly stated, as would appear from Section 100A of
			<lb />
			the Code of Civil Procedure.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			83.
			<lb />
			This judgment, in our opinion, does not support the case
			<lb />
			of the Appellants but the very pertinent feature of this judgment is that
			<lb />
			the Supreme Court has clearly held that an order passed by the High
			<lb />
			Court under Section 299 of the Succession Act is a judgment, if not a
			<lb />
			decree, observing that -
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;.....Whenever the statute provides such a bar, it is so
			<lb />
			expressly stated, as would appear from S. 100 A of
			<lb />
			the Code of Civil Procedure. If a right of appeal is
			<lb />
			provided for under the Act, the limitation thereof
			<lb />
			must also be provided therein. A right of appeal
			<lb />
			which is provided under the Letters Patent cannot be
			<lb />
			said to be restricted. Limitation of a right of appeal,
			<lb />
			in absence of any provision in a statute cannot be
			<lb />
			readily inferred.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			84.
			<lb />
			These dicta of the Supreme Court have not been noticed
			<lb />
			by the Division Bench in Asha&apos;s case (supra). Reliance was also placed
			<lb />
			upon a judgment of the Supreme Court in Sharada Devi&apos;s case (supra).
			<lb />
			In that case, the Supreme Court was concerned with an appeal to a
			<lb />
			Division Bench against the judgment of a learned Single Judge of the
			<lb />
			High Court as in terms of Section 54 of the Land Acquisition Act. The
			<lb />
			Court noticed that the expression &quot;only&quot; occurring in Section 54 after
			<lb />
			non obstante clause refers to forum of appeal i.e. an appeal would lie
			<lb />
			to the High Court, and not to any other Court and appeal would take
			<lb />
			within its sweep Letters Patent Appeal, while noticing that Section 54
			<lb />
			does not specifically excludes the provisions of the Letters Patent. The
			<lb />
			Court specifically noticed that the right to entertain appeal would not
			<lb />
			get excluded unless the concerned statutory enactment excludes an
			<lb />
			appeal under the Letters Patent. The language of Section 100-A of
			<lb />
			the Code of Civil Procedure specifically excludes the application of the
			<lb />
			Letters Patent. As already held by the Constitution Bench of the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court, the Letters Patent is not akin to constitutional powers.
			<lb />
			We may also notice here that the judgment of the Supreme Court in
			<lb />
			Sharada Devi&apos;s case (supra) was pronounced on 13 th March, 2002 i.e.
			<lb />
			prior to 1 st July, 2002 when the provision of Section 100-A of the Code
			<lb />
			of Civil Procedure was added and none of the contentions which we
			<lb />
			have considered above were raised before the Supreme Court. In
			<lb />
			these circumstances, again this judgment is of no help to the
			<lb />
			appellants.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			85.
			<lb />
			It is always not possible to state the legal proposition and
			<lb />
			answers to them with absolute precision. Still the Court makes
			<lb />
			attempt to answer the proposition of law accurately and adequately,
			<lb />
			with reference to the material facts as well as the points to be decided.
			<lb />
			The Courts are guided by the written laws, which they interpret and
			<lb />
			develop a meaningful set of rules by the process of case by case
			<lb />
			adjudication. The reasons for deciding the earlier case have been
			<lb />
			provided as the guidelines for future decision. We have attempted to
			<lb />
			cull out the reasons for taking the view that we have taken above.
			<lb />
			&quot;Experientia docet&quot; and &quot;Expedit rei publicae ut sit finis litium&quot; are the
			<lb />
			two accepted maxims which are equally applicable to the
			<lb />
			interpretation of statutes. We have to keep in mind the intent of the
			<lb />
			Legislature that in no uncertain terms, it decided to put an end to
			<lb />
			intra-Court appeal by debarring entertainment of the second appeal
			<lb />
			where the learned Single Judge of the High Court has pronounced an
			<lb />
			order or judgment in exercise of its appellate jurisdiction. In terms of
			<lb />
			Section 100-A of the Code of Civil Procedure, the unambiguous and
			<lb />
			definite expressions in Section 100-A of the Code of Civil Procedure
			<lb />
			clearly demonstrate this legislative intent.
			<lb />
			Clause 15 read with
			<lb />
			Clause 44 of the Letters Patent would squarely fall within the sweep of
			<lb />
			provisions of Section 100-A of the Code, which specifically by definite
			<lb />
			language excludes the provisions of the Letters Patent. There is no
			<lb />
			provision in the special i.e. M.V. Act providing further appeal against
			<lb />
			the appellate judgment passed by the learned Single Judge under
			<lb />
			Section 173 of the M.V. Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			86.
			<lb />
			Thus, we proceed to record and answer propositions of
			<lb />
			law formulated by us in paragraph 5 of the judgment as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>


		<item>
			(a)
			<lb />
			Upon amendment of Section 100-A of the
			<lb />
			Code of Civil Procedure by Amending Act of
			<lb />
			2002 with effect from 1 st July, 2002, no Letters
			<lb />
			Patent Appeal would be maintainable against
			<lb />
			the judgment rendered by the learned Single
			<lb />
			Judge of the High Court under the provision of
			<lb />
			Section 173 of the Motor Vehicles Act, 1988.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b)
			<lb />
			Appeal
			<lb />
			against the judgment of the learned
			<lb />
			Single Judge in exercise of its appellate
			<lb />
			jurisdiction
			Vehicles Act,
			under Section 173 of the Motor
			<lb />
			1988
			even with the aid of
			<lb />
			Clause 15 of the Letters Patent is not
			<lb />
			maintainable, and in fact, in both these
			<lb />
			situations, the appellate court would have no
			<lb />
			jurisdiction to entertain and decide such an
			<lb />
			appeal.
		</item>

		<p>
			Having answered the above questions of law, and in view
			<lb />
			of the fact that the Appeals themselves have been placed for decision
			<lb />
			before this Bench, we have no hesitation in holding that these appeals
			<lb />
			are not maintainable.
			<lb />
			Consequently, both these Appeals are
			<lb />
			dismissed. However, in the facts and circumstances of the cases, the
			<lb />
			parties are left to bear their own costs.
			<lb />
			CHIEF JUSTICE
			<lb />
			P.V. HARDAS, J.
			<lb />
			N.D. DESHPANDE, J
			<lb />
			ashwin/res.jts/lpa35-05.sxw
		</p>


	</text>
</tei>